<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Battle of Stillman's Run</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>3380939</id>
    <revision>
      <id>746677128</id>
      <parentid>571441681</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-28T21:15:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Notification of altered sources needing review #IABot (v1.2.6)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10141">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=23 August, 2007
|action1link=Talk:Battle of Stillman's Run#GA review
|action1result=Listed
|action1oldid=152819526

|action2=GAR
|action2date=November 3, 2007
|action2link=Talk:Battle_of_Stillman%27s_Run#GA_Sweeps_Review:_Pass
|action2result=Kept
|action2oldid=169108626

|currentstatus=GA
|topic=War}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Indigenous peoples of North America|class=GA}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=GA|US=yes}}
{{WikiProject Illinois|class=GA|importance=High}}
}}

==Old comment==
This is a great article, but it contains a few inexact statements that I'll take the liberty of correcting as soon as I find the time. Nevertheless, I think it is important to hear the feedback of anyone interested in the subject.

It is stated here that Black Hawk had the compromise of other tribes and the British to help him in his endeavor. Yet, every source I've consulted concur to say that both promises were either exaggerated or plain lies of his advisors, Neapope and the Winnebago prophet White Cloud. If I (and thus the sources I've been able to access) are wrong, please, let me know. Thanks, [[User:Phaedriel|Phaedriel]] 22:34, 10 December 2005 (UTC)

== Historic details are disputed ==

The exact details of the encounter between Black Hawk's envoy and Stillman's militia is not historically clear. There are several reputable versions of the encounter, and this article only provides one point of view.

Some don't include the present of a second Sauk group, some say Stillman's militia had an interpreter, some believe the militia men were drunk. etc.

Consider adding a section mentioning the conflicting history.   &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/24.148.10.122|24.148.10.122]] ([[User talk:24.148.10.122|talk]]) 04:04, 3 March 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Corrected statements ==

I reread the source in which I based this article on. I have corrected the mistatement. 

The Battle of Horseshoe Bend is linked to the Black Hawk War. Can some one please remove it.

==casualties==
These were copied directly from the west face of monument and grave markers
[[User:Rattis irrittis|Rattis irrittis]] 18:05, 30 December 2006 (UTC)

==Still needs citation==
The following are the only statements that still need citations in the article.

*The two statements following:
:*&lt;s&gt;The military expedition was turned over to U.S. General Henry Atkinson, who Black Hawk would address as &quot;White Beaver.&quot;{{Fact|date=March 2008}} Atkinson did not attempt to attack the band, noting that Black Hawk had not committed any act of violence, and that his forces were not numerous to lead an attack&lt;/s&gt;.{{Fact|date=March 2008}}
::*Reworded, removed, clarified and cited. [[User:IvoShandor|IvoShandor]] 08:17, 12 August 2007 (UTC)
*&lt;s&gt;Illinois Governor John Reynolds viewed the return of Black Hawk as an invasion, and immediately called up the Militia, and requested Federal support.&lt;/s&gt;{{Fact|date=March 2008}}
:Cited. [[User:IvoShandor|IvoShandor]] 08:17, 12 August 2007 (UTC)
*The following needs the section about Whiteside referenced.
:*&lt;s&gt;On 14 May 1832, a detachment of 275 militia under the command of Majors Isaiah Stillman and David Bailey, from the main force commanded by General Samuel Whiteside,{{Fact|date=March 2008}} were resting after a long march in the summer heat&lt;/s&gt;.
::*Noted vague orders, clarified, reworded, and cited. [[User:IvoShandor|IvoShandor]] 08:17, 12 August 2007 (UTC)
*&lt;s&gt;The miltia camp was located about three miles east of the Rock River in present day Stillman Valley, Illinois&lt;/s&gt;.{{Fact|date=March 2008}}
:*Basic location, cited. [[User:IvoShandor|IvoShandor]] 08:17, 12 August 2007 (UTC)
*&lt;s&gt;The remains of the slain soldiers were later located and buried near the site of the battlefield on a small bluff overlooking what would later be named Stillman Creek&lt;/s&gt;.{{Fact|date=March 2008}}
:*Removed and better sentence with cites added. [[User:IvoShandor|IvoShandor]] 09:19, 12 August 2007 (UTC)

[[User:IvoShandor|IvoShandor]] 06:24, 12 August 2007 (UTC)

Referencing completed. [[User:IvoShandor|IvoShandor]] 09:19, 12 August 2007 (UTC)

==GA review==
Hi there, nice article, I have a couple of points for you to address before I pass this piece, but it shouldn't be a problem for you. Nice work.
*'''General points'''
*The article suffers from over use of commas which break up the text and make it harder to read. Consider reading through and removing a few. If you want help with this then let me know.
:*I am working on this, however, some of the changes in wording that would be necessary to remove some commas would affect the accuracy of the article. If you see any that can be reworked please do so, I have went through the lead and prelude sections (divided the prelude into background and prelude per [[WP:MILHIST]]. Many of the commas I saw were serial commas which can stay or go either way, it doesn't matter to me. [[User:IvoShandor|IvoShandor]] 20:04, 21 August 2007 (UTC)
*'''Particular points'''
*In the lead link [[Isaiah Stillman]] and remove the word &quot;aptly&quot;: it may be correct, but it doesn't sound neutral. Make it &quot;had ignited&quot;, link [[Mississippi River]], put the phrase &quot;British Band&quot; in inverted commas, it is an unfamiliar term and a little confusing until explained. &quot;. . . the battle erupted when&quot; rather than after. Link [[John Giles Adams]].
:*These points have been addressed, though I would note that the battle did not begin until after the militia pursued the Sauk back to their camp. Black Hawk was attempting to negotiate a truce.[[User:IvoShandor|IvoShandor]] 19:36, 21 August 2007 (UTC)
*In lead it isn't clear whether Lincoln was present, not present, or whether his presence was still under investigation. Some clarification is needed.
:*This, in general, isn't clear. There is little more I can do to clarify other than say it is unclear. [[User:IvoShandor|IvoShandor]] 19:27, 21 August 2007 (UTC)
::*I tried to clarify this a bit in the lead. Reliable sources are hard to come by on this contentious point. Obviously, many of the parties involved in investigating such a claim have a vested interest in the outcome. [[User:IvoShandor|IvoShandor]] 19:38, 21 August 2007 (UTC)
*Say a little something about how the Sauk were removed: forcibly, by the army, by settlers etc.
:*This should be clear now that it was via a treaty. [[User:IvoShandor|IvoShandor]] 19:36, 21 August 2007 (UTC)
*How can Atkinson have written something and not been informed of it. It is not clear where Stillman's orders originated from (if it is historically unclear then this needs some explination).
:*Should have read Reynold's hand and not Atkinson's. Too many names to keep clear, hopefully this makes sense now. [[User:IvoShandor|IvoShandor]] 19:45, 21 August 2007 (UTC)
*Since &quot;Cass&quot; is linked in Lincoln's speech, then &quot;Hull&quot; should be too.--[[User:Jackyd101|Jackyd101]] 19:10, 21 August 2007 (UTC)
:*I will unlink Cass as I don't know who Hull is, and reading over the MOS it appears links are undesirable in quotations. [[User:IvoShandor|IvoShandor]] 19:27, 21 August 2007 (UTC)
::*All wikilinks in quotations removed. [[User:IvoShandor|IvoShandor]] 19:46, 21 August 2007 (UTC)
The other points I will address soon. [[User:IvoShandor|IvoShandor]] 19:27, 21 August 2007 (UTC)
:::I like what you've done with the article and well done on addressing my comments, I'll be happy to pass this when you are done (drop me a line).--[[User:Jackyd101|Jackyd101]] 01:15, 22 August 2007 (UTC)
::::I reckon this article is GA quality and I'll pass it. If there is anything from above not yet done (I can't see anything but just in case) then you can finish it afterwards, theres nothing important enough to hold this back. --[[User:Jackyd101|Jackyd101]] 00:00, 23 August 2007 (UTC)

==GA Sweeps Review: Pass==
As part of the [[WP:WGA|WikiProject Good Articles]], we're doing [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Good articles/Project quality task force/Sweeps|sweeps]] to go over all of the current GAs and see if they still meet the requirements of the [[WP:WIAGA|GA criteria]]. I'm specifically going over all of the &quot;Conflicts, battles and military exercises&quot; articles. I made several corrections myself throughout the article. I believe the article currently meets the criteria and should remain listed as a [[WP:GA|Good article]]. If you have any questions, let me know on my talk page and I'll get back to you as soon as I can. I have edited the article history to reflect this review. Happy editing! --[[User:Nehrams2020|Nehrams2020]] 06:36, 4 November 2007 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:4|one external link|4 external links}} on [[Battle of Stillman's Run]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=746677119 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20090815021319/http://lincoln.lib.niu.edu/blackhawk/page2c.html to http://lincoln.lib.niu.edu/blackhawk/page2c.html
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://geocities.com/old_lead/bhwchron.htm
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20070806094552/http://lincoln.lib.niu.edu:80/blackhawk/page2a.html to http://lincoln.lib.niu.edu/blackhawk/page2a.html
*Corrected formatting/usage for http://geocities.com/old_lead/abe.htm

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 21:15, 28 October 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>fhlxoyeb5ih2cmtz5lspe1urbp793ov</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
