<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:John Hancock</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>46515</id>
    <revision>
      <id>741615806</id>
      <parentid>741615757</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-28T16:37:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SineBot</username>
        <id>4936590</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Signing comment by [[User:Utv82803|Utv82803]] - &quot;/* Fake facts */ new section&quot;</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="26429">{{ArticleHistory|action1=GAN
|action1date=22:19, 15 November 2010
|action1link=Talk:John Hancock/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=396988508
|currentstatus=GA
|topic=History
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject United States|class=GA|importance=High|MA=yes|MA-importance=high|USgovernors=yes|USgovernors-importance=high|USPE=Yes|USPE-importance=Low|listas=Hancock, John|Boston=yes|Boston-importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Biography|living=no|class=GA|politician-priority=High|listas=Hancock, John|politician-work-group=yes}}
{{WikiProject Military History|class=GA|B-Class-1=yes|B-Class-2=yes|B-Class-3=yes|B-Class-4=yes|B-Class-5=yes|US=yes|ARW=yes}}
}}
{{Archive box|auto=yes}}
{{Wikipedia:Featured article tools}}

== Smuggling issue ==
I have added for balance that joe Hancock had smuggled an estimated $15,000,000 worth of Molasses.  It is good to put alternative points of view in the article in order to be balanced.  The phrasing in the article tends to be defensive when it comes to suggesting Hancock smuggled goods.  One sentence says that there are no records of Hancock smuggling.  Why would Hancock keep records of smuggling in the first place?  The British had repealed all of the imposed taxes, except for tea and offered high quality East India tea at lower prices then the Dutch tea, apparently that is what Hancock smuggled into the colonies.  In essence the British were competing with Hancock's business, legitimate or illegitimate. [[User:Cmguy777|Cmguy777]] ([[User talk:Cmguy777|talk]]) 17:57, 6 September 2010 (UTC)

:You've unwittingly demonstrated the perils of not using [[WP:RS|reliable sources]]. Your source ([http://www.capitalismmagazine.com/politics/taxation/3646-John-Hancock-and-Cigarette-Smuggling.html this article] by economist Walter Williams) is an unreferenced opinion piece by a non-historian who, in a passing mention of Hancock, claims that he &quot;smuggled an estimated 1.5 million gallons [of molasses] a year.&quot; You've misreported what he wrote as 1.5 million dollars, but it doesn't matter, since both figures are bogus.

:What is Williams's source? Wikipedia! Everything that Williams wrote about Hancock comes from the [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=John_Hancock&amp;oldid=209159138 version of this article] that was current when his piece was published. The article was a bit of a mess back then. Among the many misstatements in that version of the article was the claim that &quot;Hancock smuggled an estimated 1.5 million gallons of molasses per year.&quot; Williams repeated the claim nearly verbatim without checking the source. Alas, the Wikipedia editor had made a mistake: in the book cited, the 1.5 million gallons of molasses referred to the amount smuggled by the ''entire'' smuggling industry. How much of that was smuggled by Hancock, if indeed he smuggled any, is unknown. If we stick to the reliable sources, we can avoid perpetuating these kinds of errors. See [[WP:Identifying reliable sources]] for guidance.

:P.S. I suspect that the &quot;Hancock was a smuggler&quot; story is a myth popularized by 19th century advocates of free trade. The moral of the story is that trade barriers and high taxes are bad if they drove even a great patriot like Hancock to smuggling. The Williams article is another polemic in this tradition. In reality, Hancock may have done some smuggling, but he may have been wealthy enough to not have to bother with it on a large scale. Although his fortune was based in part on smuggling done by his uncle, John Hancock did not, as far as I can tell, have the reputation of a smuggler in his own lifetime. —[[User:Kevin Myers|Kevin]] [[User talk:Kevin Myers|Myers]] 04:17, 8 September 2010 (UTC)

:::I apoligize on the source or the mix up between &quot;gallons&quot; and &quot;dollars&quot;.  If Hancock was a smuggler, then it should be stated in the article without any POV.  Growing up in the U.S. education system I have had a life time of learning that the Founding Father's were above reproach, without sin, or monetary contradictions.  I am not out to destroy Hancock's or any other Founding Fathers reputation, however, I believe it is imperitive not to gloss over any issues that could be embarrasing or cause scandal.  Mentioning that he could have smuggled is good though.  Thanks for your input and concern. [[User:Cmguy777|Cmguy777]] ([[User talk:Cmguy777|talk]]) 00:26, 10 September 2010 (UTC)

Theres some pretty blatant POV here: the comment &quot;I suspect that the Hancock was a smuggler story is a myth popularized by 19th century advocates of free trade&quot; says it all, really. I agree entirly with with Cmguy777, although the post is now 4 years old. The article is extremely defensive - just because he signed the declaration does not make him a 'great' man. you say he was not known as a smuggler in his own lifetime, but he was obviously considered so by the British. This is a very biased aricle.--[[User:Godwhale|Godwhale]] ([[User talk:Godwhale|talk]]) 06:15, 19 September 2014 (UTC)

== Harvard University controversy ==
Historian James H. Stark contends the Hancock defaulted on money, 15,400 pounds, he owed to Harvard University while serving as its treasurer.  Harvard &quot;begged and entreated&quot; Hancock to pay the money back to no avail.  The matter was settled by his family in 1795 after his death in 1793.  Should this be in the article?

:Perhaps, although it may be much ado about nothing and therefore too minor for an encyclopedia article. Many decades after Stark, historian Donald Proctor argued that previous historians had misunderstood the situation. According to Proctor, Hancock, who as treasurer kept Harvard's cash, returned the money (plus interest) to Harvard in 1777. The real dispute, says Proctor, was a personal squabble between Hancock and [[Samuel Langdon]], the unpopular president of Harvard. Langdon wanted the money while Hancock was in Philadelphia serving in Congress, and became irritated that he didn't get the money until Hancock's return to Boston in 1777. Hancock's dispute was with Langdon, not Harvard; everything was okay after Langdon left Harvard in 1780. I thought about putting this into the article, but I figured people would read it and think &quot;So what?&quot; —[[User:Kevin Myers|Kevin]] [[User talk:Kevin Myers|Myers]] 20:52, 12 September 2010 (UTC)

::It is interesting how two different sources say different things on Hancock returning money to Harvard.  I believe the issue is signifigant.  Why did Hancock take the money in the first place? [[User:Cmguy777|Cmguy777]] ([[User talk:Cmguy777|talk]]) 05:48, 16 September 2010 (UTC)

:::I don't exactly remember, but perhaps he kept the money with him while British troops were occupying Boston—rich men like Hancock served as private bankers in the days before modern commercial banking—and took it with him when he fled to Philadelphia. I'll look into it again. —[[User:Kevin Myers|Kevin]] [[User talk:Kevin Myers|Myers]] 01:08, 21 September 2010 (UTC)

::::I haven't forgot about this, by the way. I'm still waiting for a book to come in from the library. It's more than a month overdue; hopefully the other person will return it soon. —[[User:Kevin Myers|Kevin]] [[User talk:Kevin Myers|Myers]] 14:40, 16 November 2010 (UTC)

:This controversy was also part of Hancock's long-running feuds with James Bowdoin ([http://books.google.com/books?id=vZaY5Vxx0qIC&amp;lpg=PA143&amp;pg=PA142#v=onepage&amp;f=false link]), something that is not mentioned here.  The battles between the two men were a major item in Massachusetts, and were not just political. ''[[User:Magicpiano|&lt;span style=&quot;background-color:khaki;color:firebrick;&quot;&gt;Magic&lt;/span&gt;]]''[[User_talk:Magicpiano|♪piano]] 20:12, 3 March 2012 (UTC)

::That's a good source. I used it in a paragraph about the Harvard controversy. —[[User:Kevin Myers|Kevin]] [[User talk:Kevin Myers|Myers]] 05:33, 9 January 2013 (UTC)

{{Talk:John Hancock/GA1}}

== Memorial stone image ==

The engraving on the memorial stone (Final years section) reads &quot;...erected AD MDCCCXCV...&quot; This Roman Numeral is 1895. The caption for the image, however, says &quot;erected in 1896.&quot; Is this a small oversight?

[[User:Mls1984|Mls1984]] ([[User talk:Mls1984|talk]]) 17:42, 13 January 2011 (UTC)

:You're very observant. The old biographies say that the money was appropriated for the memorial in 1894 and that the dedication service was held on September 10, 1896. Perhaps, when the stone was inscribed, they anticipated that the dedication service would be held in 1895. Maybe it was &quot;erected&quot; in 1895 and &quot;dedicated&quot; in 1896. I'll change the caption to &quot;dedicated in 1896&quot;, which appears to be true and less directly contradicts the inscription. —[[User:Kevin Myers|Kevin]] [[User talk:Kevin Myers|Myers]] 01:04, 14 January 2011 (UTC)

== Birth date == 
The birth dates are January 1737 (and a different day in January 1736 O.S.).  I have found sources stating 1736 and 1737 and thought it would be a good idea to cite something, or add a clarification why the years are different.  I am not very well schooled in the old style birth date conventions, so I am writing on the talk page instead of the article. -[[User:Ich|Ich]] ([[User_talk:Ich|talk]]) 17:37, 8 March 2011 (UTC)
:Editing the article, I see an html comment stating that the year started in March, not January.  I am taking the initiative to make a short comment in the footnote to the mention in the body text. -[[User:Ich|Ich]] ([[User_talk:Ich|talk]]) 17:45, 8 March 2011 (UTC)

== eponym ==

He is remembered for his large and stylish signature on the United States Declaration of Independence, so much so that the term &quot;John Hancock&quot; has become, in the United States, a synonym for signature.

Should substitute eponym for synonym.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/74.97.51.118|74.97.51.118]] ([[User talk:74.97.51.118|talk]]) 05:25, 27 July 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Ancestry ==

Hancock's ancestry is nowhere to be found on this page.  I am just wondering as that of all the other founding fathers is given mention, why is his not?  Is it not available or has it just yet to be added by some sort of coincidence?  I believe he was of English descent but I'd like the specifics.  Does anybody know or care to add it?[[User:Thesouthernhistorian45|Thesouthernhistorian45]] ([[User talk:Thesouthernhistorian45|talk]]) 05:29, 8 November 2011 (UTC)

:There is a generally accepted genealogy of the Governor that takes him back to the immigrant Nathaniel Hancock, who died in Cambridge, MA in 1652 and was presumably born in Padiham, Lancashire, England.  Earlier generations in England are more sketchy and disputed.  It would be a challenge to dig out primary sources for all of this.

:It would also be risky to introduce much of this detail into a &quot;Good Article&quot;, particularly given its strong political emphasis, without jeopardizing the flow and organization.  But it would probably look something like this:
&lt;pre&gt;
1. John HANCOCK (*1506? Chesterfield, Derbyshire, England; †?)
   sp: UNKNOWN
  2. Richard HANCOCK (*1527 Chesterfield, Derbyshire, England; †?)
     sp: Isabell *1536;  (∞1555)
    3. Richard HANCOCK (*19 Dec 1564 Chesterfield, Derbyshire, England; †?)
       sp: UNKNOWN
      4. Nathaniel HANCOCK (*3 Oct 1596 Padiham, Lancashire, England; 
        †1652 Cambridge, MA)
         sp: Joanna WRIGHT (*1609?; †1664?)
        5. Nathaniel HANCOCK (*18 Dec 1638 Cambridge, MA; 
          †12 Apr 1719 Cambridge, MA)
           sp: Mary PRENTICE (*25 Sep 1644; ∞8 Mar 1662/3; †20 Sep 1699)
          6. John HANCOCK (*1671; †1752)
             sp: Elizabeth CLARK (*1674; ∞1700; †1760)
            7. John HANCOCK (*1702; †1744)
               sp: Mary HAWKE (*1711; ∞1733; †aft.1783)
              8. (Gov.) John HANCOCK (*12 Jan 1736/7; †8 Oct 1793)
                 sp: Dorothy QUINCY (*1747; ∞1775; †1830)
&lt;/pre&gt;
::—[[User:Ziusudra|Ziusudra]] ([[User talk:Ziusudra|talk]]) 03:32, 7 December 2011 (UTC)

== Edit request on 11 January 2012 ==

{{edit semi-protected|answered=yes}}
&lt;!-- Begin request --&gt;

This article has the wrong birthday listed for John Hancock. According to biography.com (http://www.biography.com/people/john-hancock-9327271) as well as several other sites John Hancock's date of birth is January 12th 1737.

&lt;!-- End request --&gt;
[[Special:Contributions/170.135.112.12|170.135.112.12]] ([[User talk:170.135.112.12|talk]]) 21:16, 11 January 2012 (UTC)
:You didn't read carefully enough.  Both the old-style (Jan 12) and new-style (Jan 23) birth dates are right there at the top of the article.  -- [[User:DanielPenfield|DanielPenfield]] ([[User talk:DanielPenfield|talk]]) 21:54, 11 January 2012 (UTC)
:[[File:Pictogram voting wait.svg|20px|link=|alt=]] '''Already done'''&lt;!-- Template:ESp --&gt; - current information appears to be correct. [[User:Mato|Mato]] ([[User talk:Mato|talk]]) 22:38, 11 January 2012 (UTC)

== Edit request on 23 January 2012 ==

{{edit semi-protected|answered=yes}}
&lt;!-- Begin request --&gt;

his b-day is January 12, 1737
&lt;!-- End request --&gt;
[[Special:Contributions/69.161.126.89|69.161.126.89]] ([[User talk:69.161.126.89|talk]]) 22:48, 23 January 2012 (UTC)
:Yes, read the first line, &quot;John Hancock (January 23, 1737 [O.S. January 12, 1736] – October 8, 1793)&quot;, or the first line of the first section, &quot;John Hancock was born on January 23, 1737; according to the Old Style calendar then in use, the date was January 12, 1736.&quot;--[[User:Jac16888|&lt;font color=&quot;Blue&quot;&gt;Jac&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;Green&quot;&gt;16888&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Jac16888|&lt;sup&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;]] 23:02, 23 January 2012 (UTC)

== President of the United States in Congress Assembled ==

It is specious to label John Hancock just as a President of the Continental Congress.  Although you have changed my edits of John Hancock back to just a Continental Congress President, perhaps you can leave this post on the talk page to help your readers discern which listing - President of the Continental Congress OR President of the Continental Congress and President of the United States in Congress Assembled is correct.  A brief case that the Continental Congress expired with the ratification of the Articles of Confederation and the offices had significant differences is as follows: 

Although the Articles of Confederation was passed by the U.S. Continental Congress on November 15th, 1777, this Constitution of 1777 required the unanimous  ratification by all the 13 states.   Maryland was the last state to adopt the Articles of Confederation, completing its ratification on February 2, 1781. On February 22, 1781, it was unanimously resolved by Congress that:

The delegates of Maryland having taken their seats in Congress with powers to sign the Articles of Confederation: &quot;Ordered, That Thursday next [March 1, 1781] be assigned for compleating the Confederation; and that a committee of three be appointed, to consider and report a mode for announcing the same to the public: the members, [Mr. George] Walton, Mr. [James] Madison, Mr. [John] Mathews.&quot;

The March 1st, 1781, enacted Constitution of 1777 provided for a unicameral governing body called the United States in Congress Assembled (USCA) to govern the United States of America.  The USCA was charged &quot; .. to appoint one of their members to preside, provided that no person be allowed to serve in the office of president more than one year in any term of three years.&quot; 

On March 2nd, 1781, the Delegates, who were duly elected after each State had ratified the Articles of Confederation, convened in Philadelphia as the United States in Congress Assembled with Samuel Huntington presiding as the first USCA President.  Additionally, George Washington continued to serve as General and Commander-in-Chief of the United States Continental Army. 

The Constitution of 1777 Presidency, although similar to its predecessor, was a different and weaker office then that of the U.S. Continental Congress Presidency.

For instance, the Continental Congress Presidents, who served from September 5, 1774 to February 28, 1781, presided over a government that could enact legislation binding all 13 States with only a seven state quorum as opposed to the nine state minimum required by the Constitution of 1777. Additionally, Continental Congress Presidents, who decided what legislation came before Congress, often found themselves as the sole vote for their state,  giving them a 1/7th to 1/13th vote over crucial legislation, appointments, judicial decisions, and even military orders enacted during the Revolutionary War.  After March 1, 1781, the Constitution of 1777 mandated that two or more delegates must be present from each state for that delegation to be marked present and be eligible to vote in the new USCA government.   Therefore, on March 2nd, 1781, the first act of the USCA was to disqualify both New Hampshire and Rhode Island from voting in the new assembly because they each had only one delegate present.

On May 4, 1781, to further weaken presidential powers, Congress passed the &quot;Rules for conducting business in the United States in Congress assembled.&quot; that stripped the President of his power to control the congressional agenda which, was a tactic that the presiding officers (especially Henry Laurens) had expertly wielded as Continental Congress Presidents. These new USCA rules even went so far as to eliminate the President's prerogative to continue the debate, before a second to the motion was brought to the floor.

&quot;Rule 10. When a motion is made and seconded it shall be repeated by the President or If he or any other member desire being in writing it shall be delivered to the President in writing and read aloud at the table before it, shall be debated.&quot;

There are numerous other examples on the differences between the two offices that range from the USCA's Committee of the States experiment to govern the USA by a &quot;Board of Directors&quot; without the USCA President at its head to John Hanson's success in championing the congressional resolution that moved the bulk of his presidential correspondence duties to USCA Secretary Charles Thomson. Moreover, USCA Foreign Secretaries Robert R. Livingston and John Jay took over most of the U.S. Presidential duties of entertaining foreign diplomats and dignitaries under the Articles of Confederation government.

John Hancock was elected as both the President of the Continental Congress and the United states in Congress Assembled and not just as President of the Continental Congress.  To view the primary sources supporting this fact go to http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-c_Pu5PAiP_g/UOX0C4AiqhI/AAAAAAAADe0/tvVawnkqk5M/s1600/AA+AC.jpg and for documents issued by the USCA with John Hancock as President of the United States in Congress Assembled please go here -- www.johnhancock.org. --  [[User:Stas.klos|Stas.klos]] ([[User talk:Stas.klos|talk]]) 14:41, 24 January 2013 (UTC)

== Dealings with [[John Paul Jones]] ==

I have been reading this wonderful well researched text:  &lt;i&gt;John Paul Jones: A Sailor's Biography&lt;/i&gt;  by Samuel Eliot Morrison, (1964) [1959].  The book is listed as a reference on the [[John Paul Jones]] page.   The book mentions John Paul Jones's dealings in with John Hancock.  I looked up this Wiki article to see if it mentions the kind of unsavory behavior of Hancock mentioned in the book, which the article indeed does (Bravo!), but not this particular incident.  We could include some of it in the main text if desired to make an improvement to the article--it makes no difference to me, but it was surprising when I read it!  Here is direct quote from the book [items in square brackets are my commentary]:

: Congress on 25 March [1777] voted that their agents were to purchase and convert three ships, one of which to be given &quot;to Captain John Paul Jones, until better provisions be made for him.&quot;  John Hancock Hancock was lavish in his compliments, promised to rectify the rank list of 10 October 1776&lt;b&gt;†&lt;/b&gt;, and asked for Jones's captain's commission of 8 August to be returned in order to make out a new one dated 10 May (when ''[[Esek Hopkins|Hopkins]]'' [commander-in-chief of the [[Continental Navy]] ] appointed him to [[sloop]] ''[[USS Providence (1775)|Providence]]''); then pretended to have lost the 8 August document and issued him a new Captain's commission with the final date of 10 October, and with the Number 18 and the old sloop as ball-and-chain.  At least that is what Jones wrote three years later, and the story is so consistent with Hancock's way of doing business that it is probably true. (99)

&lt;b&gt;†&lt;/b&gt;The books explains that Jones lost seniority due to the ranking method used by the Congress on 10 October 1776 (on advice from the Marine Committee).  Because Jones had turned down a Captain position early on and took a 1st Lieutenant position instead, and because his appointment to sloop Providence was made on 10 May but not signed until 10 October, he was ranked lower than others who were less qualified and who had performed far more poorly in war to that point.  This unreasonably low seniority ranking, combined with his reassignment to [[sloop]] ''[[USS Providence (1775)|Providence]]'', one of the smaller combat ships of the Navy, &quot;drove Jones to fury, and continued to anger him as long as he lived.&quot; (87)  [[User:David Tornheim|David Tornheim]] ([[User talk:David Tornheim|talk]]) 12:28, 21 February 2015 (UTC)

== John Hancock was a Grand Master Mason ==

I added '''John Hancock was a member of the ''St. Andrews Lodge of Freemasonry'' in Boston that owned and met in the first floor of the [[Green Dragon Tavern]]. He eventually became the [[Grand Master]] of the Lodge&lt;ref&gt;citation needed&lt;/ref&gt;.''' [[Special:Contributions/69.180.104.60|69.180.104.60]] ([[User talk:69.180.104.60|talk]]) 21:26, 21 November 2015 (UTC)

{{reflist}}

== In Popular Culture -- Fallout 4 video game ==

[https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=John_Hancock&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=697347055&amp;oldid=695880555 This] material was recently added by {{u|50.194.79.161}}.  I support the revert by {{u|CatcherStorm}}.  I was about to revert it as well.  I would be okay with a single sentence about this video game *if* [[WP:RS]] can be provided for it showing this use of John Hancock was significant or notable. --[[User:David Tornheim|David Tornheim]] ([[User talk:David Tornheim|talk]]) 23:04, 29 December 2015 (UTC)

Seeing how Fallout 4 is one of the few significant mentions of John Hancock in recent memory (especially considering that the character is wearing Hancock's extant clothing from the Old State House museum in Boston), I'd wholly recommend including it.  I don't think there's any need to call out the character's achievements (the militia, mayor of Goodneighbor, etc), but it's worth mentioning that the character is named after/inspired by John Hancock. [[User:Shoom&amp;#39;lah|Shoom&amp;#39;lah]] ([[User talk:Shoom&amp;#39;lah|talk]]) 09:14, 10 February 2016 (UTC)

:Purely non-notable cruft with no clear connection. I wholeheartedly support its removal, and have done so in the past. '''[[User:ScrapIronIV|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#306b1e&quot;&gt;Scr&lt;span style=&quot;background:#0404B4;border-radius:7px;color:#FFFFFF&quot;&gt;★&lt;/span&gt;pIron&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:ScrapIronIV|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#6E6E6E&quot;&gt;IV&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;''' 11:45, 10 February 2016 (UTC)

== Only John Hancock and Charles Thomson signed the Declaration on 7/4/1776 ==

A strong argument can be made that John Hancock was the only representative of Congress that signed the fair copy of the Declaration on 7/4 with Secretary of Congress [[Charles Thomson]] attesting it, thus explaining why these two names appear on the bottom of the 200 Dunlap broadsides. [[Special:Contributions/2601:589:4705:C7C0:1C96:2508:525A:2F69|2601:589:4705:C7C0:1C96:2508:525A:2F69]] ([[User talk:2601:589:4705:C7C0:1C96:2508:525A:2F69|talk]]) 17:12, 31 December 2015 (UTC)
:{{ping|Slightsmile}} I notice you [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=John_Hancock&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=697612472&amp;oldid=697612363 reverted] the edits by {{u|2601:589:4705:C7C0:1C96:2508:525A:2F69}}. Regarding each of the changes:
# &quot;July 4&quot; -&gt; &quot;7/4&quot;.   This was not a good edit.
#  &quot;a copy&quot; -&gt; &quot;the ''fair copy''&quot;.  I have not reviewed the RS and do not know if this is correct or not. 
# &quot;the printer&quot; -&gt; &quot;the printer [[John Dunlap]]&quot;.  This looks like a good edit and provides more information to the reader by linking in another of our articles.
# &quot;The printer&quot; -&gt; &quot;Dunlap&quot;.  This also looks good.
# added &quot;as 'Attested by' implying that Hancock had signed the fair copy.&quot; I have not reviewed the RS and do not know if this is correct or not. 
:Can you please comment on each of the changes, and why you reverted all of them, and specifically if any of them can or should not be restored. --[[User:David Tornheim|David Tornheim]] ([[User talk:David Tornheim|talk]]) 19:37, 31 December 2015 (UTC)
::I found this edit in Recent Changes. Changing July 4 to 7/4 looked funny. I didn't know &quot;John Dunlap&quot; was a make of printer in the 1700's and so reasonably assumed it was a joke. Based on those points and that there was no explanation of the edit I assumed it was a vandalism. &quot;Each of the changes&quot;, there was only one revert. Thanks for showing me my mistake. I am obviously not familiar with the topic and [[User:David Tornheim|David Tornheim]], I would appreciate it if you could put the article back the way it's supposed to be. All the best. [[User:Slightsmile|&lt;font color=&quot;navy&quot;&gt;Slight&lt;/font&gt;]][[User talk:Slightsmile|&lt;font color=&quot;teal&quot;&gt;''Smile''&lt;/font&gt;]] 20:16, 31 December 2015 (UTC)
:::Thanks for your explanation.  I am not expert on Hancock either.  I will restore all but the July 4 part, noting that I am not sure about edits regarding the attestation and &quot;fair copy&quot;. --[[User:David Tornheim|David Tornheim]] ([[User talk:David Tornheim|talk]]) 20:23, 31 December 2015 (UTC)

== Fake facts ==

Stop editing over and over again mine says last edited 21 hours ago. Tyler Shaver 16:37, 28 September 2016 (UTC)  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Utv82803|Utv82803]] ([[User talk:Utv82803#top|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Utv82803|contribs]]) &lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;</text>
      <sha1>j55f9lsj81isb0pdgn4jofc7i19ysjr</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
