<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Gallipoli Campaign</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>407744</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749184570</id>
      <parentid>749183636</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-12T23:03:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Anotherclown</username>
        <id>8567476</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* CE */ resp</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="29625">{{Talk header}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=WAR
|action1date=08:50, 15 September 2006
|action1link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/Battle of Gallipoli
|action1result=failed
|action1oldid=75660769

|action2=GAN
|action2date=10 January 2008
|action2result=not listed
|action2oldid=183389889

|action3=FAC
|action3date=10:09, 14 April 2008
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Battle of Gallipoli/archive1
|action3result=not promoted
|action3oldid=205497664

|action4=PR
|action4date=10:30, 16 June 2013
|action4link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Gallipoli Campaign/archive1
|action4result=reviewed
|action4oldid=559180103

|action5=GAN
|action5date=19:04, 29 July 2013 (UTC)
|action5link=Talk:Gallipoli Campaign/GA1
|action5result=listed
|action5oldid=566322768
|topic=Warfare
|currentstatus=FFAC
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{MILHIST|class=GA|b1=y|b2=y|b3=y|b4=y|b5=y|A-Class=fail|portal1-name=World War I|portal1-link=Selected event/10|Australian=yes|British=yes|Canadian=yes|New-Zealand=yes|French=yes|Ottoman=yes|WWI=yes}}
{{WP Australia|class=GA|importance=Top|history=yes|history-importance=Top|military=yes|military-importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject New Zealand|class=GA|importance=top}}
{{WikiProject Ottoman Empire|class=GA|importance=high}}
{{WPTR|class=GA|importance=Top}}
{{WPUK|class=GA|importance=mid}}
}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2005-01-09|oldid1=10009045|date2=2006-01-09|oldid2=34428617|date3=2007-01-09|oldid3=99435783|date4=2008-01-09|oldid4=183077730|date5=2009-01-09|oldid5=262894705|date6=2009-04-25|oldid6=285990622|date7=2010-01-09|oldid7=336754423|date8=2010-04-25|oldid8=348518522|date9=2012-04-25|oldid9=489208220|date10=2014-04-25|oldid10=605767132|date11=2015-04-25|oldid11=658803096}}

== Ottoman entry into World War I ==

Gallipoli Campaign is not the article for arguing on &quot;Ottoman entry into World War I.&quot; That argument may have a position in [[Battle of Odessa (1914)]], but too many things happened before Gallipoli Campaign. A small reference to [[Ottoman entry into World War I]] is quite explanatory. The section in this article is quite big in content. Includes many non-factual claims (arguments); statements like &quot;the Ottoman Empire's geographic position meant that Russia and her allies France and Britain had a significant interest in Turkish neutrality in the event of war in Europe.&quot; is not factually-correct, but I guess there is a reference for that, surely there is a reference for everything on the internet! Arguing on these issues beyond the scope of the Gallipoli Campaign. If there is a need for fully developed section, this section needs to be factual, correctly supported, not a collection of POV statements, even if it is cited. [[:User:Anotherclown]]  Either let the Gallipoli Campaign link to Ottoman entry into World War I page https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Gallipoli_Campaign&amp;diff=654423093&amp;oldid=654422409 or let the correct information be included https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Gallipoli_Campaign&amp;diff=654420494&amp;oldid=654337465 --[[User:SelimAnkara1993|SelimAnkara1993]] ([[User talk:SelimAnkara1993|talk]]) 01:21, 1 April 2015 (UTC)
: Gday - thanks for starting the conversation about this, much appreciated. Given the close links b/n the issue of Turkey's entry into the war and the Gallipoli Campaign I think there is a need to cover the issue in some detail in this article, but using [[WP:SUMMARY|summary style]] so as not to provide it [[WP:UNDUE|undue weight]] (hence the reason for the state of this section as it currently is). Indeed most works on the topic (i.e. the Gallipoli Campaign) cited here seem to cover the background to the Turkish entry into the war and that is probably the reason why it was included in the first place (otherwise the article would not adequately summarise the campaign). You proposal seems to be either removing the section altogether and replacing with a very short paragraph - per your edit here [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Gallipoli_Campaign&amp;diff=654337465&amp;oldid=654320628], or covering in detail per your alternative edit here [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Gallipoli_Campaign&amp;diff=654422409&amp;oldid=654420494]. As I said in my edit summaries though there are issues with both, firstly the short summary you replaced the existing text with wasn't referenced, whilst the second edit was too detailed. Consequently I don't think either of your proposals are workable in their current form, although obviously other editors may disagree with me. IRT the other aspect of your comment, you obviously have concerns about the factual content currently included (although only mention one example above). As you state though all the information here is referenced to reliable sources so I don't think calling them POV statements is really accurate. Perhaps more might be gained by listing the concerns you have with the current content and providing a source for an alternative interpretation and then discussing on that basis rather than wholesale deletion of content, or replacing it with text that meets your interpretation / understanding of the events? [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 01:52, 1 April 2015 (UTC)

:: I do not think it is one or two problems of the current summary. These are from the first paragraph. Using two references: &quot;Young Turks seized power in [[Constantinople]] and installed [[Mehmed V]] as a figurehead Sultan.&quot; It was [[31 March Incident]] not [[Young Turk Revolution]] (seized power!) replaced the sultan. Who ever typed that misrepresented the source, or source is... Without a reference &quot;the French, British and Germans had offered financial aid&quot; is totally non-true. They were the debt collectors, not providers. That is nonsense. There are three sources behind the claim &quot;A pro-German faction influenced by Enver Pasha&quot; It is well known that Enver Pasha resented the German military mission. The fact that Ottoman government outreach got response only from Germany linked Enver to Germany. That is not being influenced, but cornered. Cornered argument brings the &quot;Great Game&quot; into this article. That is a paragraph by itself. With a reference: &quot;Russia and her allies France and Britain had a significant interest in Turkish neutrality&quot; In 1912, Russia &quot;kind of&quot; declared war. The note said change the governors or I will occupy you. They replaced the governors. But Russian military began planning for occupation in 1913. You can read these under [[Defeat and dissolution of the Ottoman Empire (1908–1922)]]. Just to follow your position; the clarification of the first paragraph, as you stated to adding other positions, I'm going to add 3-4 paragraphs just for the first paragraph. I believe there are other missing points. I just want to remind that you also have a position of &quot;too long.&quot; I sincerely believe a short summary to articles would be a better solution. You did not like my summary. So, write a &quot;three line summary&quot; and replace these three paragraphs to the links [[Ottoman entry into World War I]], [[Middle Eastern theatre of World War I]] and for political events to [[Defeat and dissolution of the Ottoman Empire (1908–1922)]]. If you want to argue when the Sultan changed, how much dedt the Empire had, or if Russia really wanted to be neutral, the articles already established. It is not like we would be deleting content. [[User:SelimAnkara1993|SelimAnkara1993]] ([[User talk:SelimAnkara1993|talk]]) 03:12, 1 April 2015 (UTC)
::: Unfortunately I'm struggling to understand a lot of the issues that you are attempting to raise, as I'm assuming English is a second language for you. I'll try but you may need to break your concerns down into smaller, more concise statements. So far you have mentioned some concerns with the first paragraph. Whilst I don't have access to all the sources used there (Haythornthwaite, Aspinall-Oglander, or Fewster, Basarin &amp; Basarin), I was able to spot check Howard (2002) ''The First World War'', p. 51 which states: &quot;...''power had been seized in 1908 by a group of young officers (the original 'Young Turks') set on modernizing the archaic political and economic system and restoring national prestige'''.&quot; That would seem to be faithfully used here in this article in my opinion, although again others might disagree. Perhaps either {{ping|Keith-264}} or {{ping|AustralianRupert}} might be able to check the other references used here if they have access to them? The pending spot check aside though I get the feeling that your objection isn't so much a case of the sources used being interpreted incorrectly but that you have a different understanding of the events being discussed than those in the sources used. &lt;u&gt;I'll ask again do you have any references that you can point to for these interpretations that you can present here? So far you haven't provided any.&lt;/u&gt; Given the language issues we seem to be having I'll try to state my position as clearly as possible: I remain unconvinced by your proposal to reduce this section to a &quot;three line summary&quot;, and I do not agree with adding &quot;3-4 paragraphs&quot; to it either. Certainly what is here can be corrected where / if there are found to be errors in it; however, I support doing this only if you can back up your concerns with [[WP:VERIFY|verifiable]] references to [[WP:RS|reliable sources]], not statements like &quot;''It is well known''...&quot;. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 07:05, 1 April 2015 (UTC)
I'm working today so I'll have a look later. I have the OH (Aspinall-Oglander) and Erikson ''Ordered'' and ''Defeat'' but I'm surprised that it's been questioned considering that the passage is descriptive.[[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 07:32, 1 April 2015 (UTC)
::: '''Young Turks seized power...''' -&gt; That is [[Young Turks]] and they sized the power with [[Young Turk Revolution]] (July 1908). '''...and installed Mehmed V''' [[Mehmed V]] (Reign: 27 April 1909 – 3 July 1918) Young Turk Revolution did not remove Abdul Hamid II, just opposite &quot;On 24 July 1908, Sultan Abdul Hamid II capitulated and announced the restoration.&quot;  The removal of [[Abdul_Hamid_II#Countercoup.2C_1909]] was in 1909 and nothing to do with Young Turk Revolution. I do not even see why this article is the place of all this jazz. [[User:SelimAnkara1993|SelimAnkara1993]] ([[User talk:SelimAnkara1993|talk]]) 12:28, 1 April 2015 (UTC)
::::Sorry, I can't help much with the sources as I am interstate for a while. Definately agree, though, that these changes should be discussed first. Regards, [[User:AustralianRupert|AustralianRupert]] ([[User talk:AustralianRupert|talk]]) 05:17, 2 April 2015 (UTC) 
:::At a glance I'd certainly support the view that the section could be pruned and the details left to the linked main article. I'll have a look in Strachan later.[[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 07:06, 2 April 2015 (UTC)
:::: On spot checking Haythornthwaite p. 6 mentions this did indeed occur in 1909 and states: &quot;The new Sultan then installed was Mohammed V, Abdul the Damned's younger brother, but he was merely a figurehead: all power was concentrated in the hands of the instigators of Abdul's overthrow, the 'Young Turks'. Google Book preview here [https://books.google.com.au/books?id=TAI13u0zQIMC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Gallipoli+1915:+Frontal+Assault+on+Turkey&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=O9wdVeKjBaLamAWSp4CYAw&amp;ved=0CDAQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=Gallipoli%201915%3A%20Frontal%20Assault%20on%20Turkey&amp;f=false]. I've tweaked the current text to reflect this - pls see my change here [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Gallipoli_Campaign&amp;diff=654704818&amp;oldid=654625464]. I will discuss the proposal below separately for continuity. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 00:28, 3 April 2015 (UTC)

== Ottoman entry into the war ''suggested edit'' ==

===Ottoman entry into the war===
{{Main|Ottoman entry into World War I}}
&lt;nowiki&gt;On 2 August 1914, the British requisitioned two modern battleships—{{ship|Ottoman battleship|Sultân Osmân-ı Evvel||2}} and {{ship|Ottoman battleship|Reşadiye||2}}—which were being built in British shipyards for the Ottoman navy, alienating pro-British elements in Constantinople, despite an offer of compensation if the Ottomans remained neutral.{{sfn|Howard|2002|p=52}} The German government offered two cruisers—{{SMS|Goeben}} and {{SMS|Breslau}}—to the Ottoman navy as replacements. The Entente [[Pursuit of Goeben and Breslau]] failed and the Ottoman government opened the [[Dardanelles]], to allow them entry to Constantinople, despite being neutral and required under international law, to block military shipping.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=18}} In September, the British naval mission of 1912 under Admiral [[Arthur Limpus]], was recalled due to increasing concern that the Ottoman Empire would enter the war. Rear Admiral [[Wilhelm Souchon]] of the Imperial German Navy, took over command of the Ottoman navy.{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|pp=9 &amp; 18}}{{sfn|Haythornthwaite|2004|p=7}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;

&lt;nowiki&gt;On 27 September, acting on initiative, the German commander of the Dardanelles forts, ordered the passage to be closed, adding to the impression that the Ottomans had sided with Germany.{{sfn|Haythornthwaite|2004|p=7}} The German naval presence and the success of German armies in Europe, gave the pro-German faction in the Ottoman government enough influence to declare war on Russia.{{sfn|Howard|2002|p=53}} On 27 October, ''Goeben'' and ''Breslau''—having been renamed {{ship|Ottoman battlecruiser|Yavûz Sultân Selîm||2}} and {{ship|Ottoman cruiser|Midilli||2}}—sortied into the Black Sea, bombarded the Russian port of [[Odessa]] and sank several Russian ships.{{sfn|Fewster|Basarin|Basarin|2003|p=44}} The Ottomans refused an Entente demand to expel the German missions and on 31 October 1914, entered the war on the side of the [[Central Powers]].{{sfn|Broadbent|2005|p=19}}{{sfn|Fewster|Basarin|Basarin|2003|p=44}}&lt;/nowiki&gt; 

&lt;nowiki&gt;Russia declared war on the Ottoman Empire on 2 November and the next day, a British naval squadron off the Dardanelles, bombarded the outer forts at Kum Kale and Seddulbahir and killed {{nowrap|86 soldiers.}}{{sfn|Carlyon|2001|p=47}} Britain and France declared war on the Ottoman Empire on 5 November and the Ottomans declared ''jihad'' (holy war) later that month and began the [[Caucasus Campaign]] against the Russians, to regain former Turkish provinces.{{sfn|Carlyon|2001|p=48}} The [[Mesopotamian Campaign]] began after a British landing, to occupy oil facilities in the [[Persian Gulf]].{{sfn|Holmes|2001|p=577}} The Ottomans prepared to attack Egypt in early 1915, aiming to occupy the [[Suez Canal]] and cut the Mediterranean route to [[British India|India]] and the Far East.{{sfn|Keegan|1998|p=238}} Strachan wrote that in hindsight, Ottoman belligerence was inevitable once {{lang|de|''Goeben''}} and {{lang|de|''Breslau''}} were allowed into the Dardanelles and that delays were caused by Ottoman unreadiness for war and Bulgarian neutrality, rather than uncertainty about policy.{{sfn|Strachan|2001|pp=678–679}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;[[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 12:27, 2 April 2015 (UTC)
:&quot;'''later that month and began the [[Caucasus Campaign]] when the Russians began the [[Bergmann Offensive]], to regain former Turkish provinces.'''&quot; The first conflict of Caucasus Campaign is [[Bergmann Offensive]] which is opened by Russia. [[User:SelimAnkara1993|SelimAnkara1993]] ([[User talk:SelimAnkara1993|talk]]) 12:58, 2 April 2015 (UTC)
:&quot;'''the pro-German faction in the Ottoman government enough influence to declare war on Russia.'''&quot; this is an interpretation by that author. The Sultan has the sole power to declare war. The declaration of war to Russia was on 11 November 1914.[[User:SelimAnkara1993|SelimAnkara1993]] ([[User talk:SelimAnkara1993|talk]]) 12:58, 2 April 2015 (UTC)
:An author's interpretation accurately summarised is reliable as the author's interpretation. If there are other authors with different interpretations, put them in. If you want to reword the Caucasus Campaign section with citations I'd be delighted, it's not my field.

&quot;'''later that month the [[Caucasus Campaign]] began when the Russians started the [[Bergmann Offensive]] and the Ottomans had the war aim of regaining former Turkish provinces.'''&quot; Will something like this be OK?[[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 13:17, 2 April 2015 (UTC)
: G'day, I'd suggest probably tweaking it slightly (mainly for narrative flow): &quot;...later that month the [[Caucasus Campaign]] began when the Russians started the [[Bergmann Offensive]] and the Ottomans sought to regain former Turkish provinces in the region.&quot; Regards, [[User:AustralianRupert|AustralianRupert]] ([[User talk:AustralianRupert|talk]]) 22:42, 2 April 2015 (UTC)
:: Gday again. [[User:Keith-264]] thanks very much for your efforts so far. I acknowledge that you have only taken this on following the suggestion / criticism of the article by another editor and that this is not your initiative so I appreciate your attempts to find a middle ground. Firstly, I'm not opposed to this draft (and support [[User:AustralianRupert]]'s suggested tweak) if there is consensus for it as it is a more concise, well-worded and descriptive summary of the topic. However, I am concerned that in this search for brevity we may be missing important details, which is why my position so far has been to keep the background section at its current approximate size and breadth of coverage, whilst correcting any inaccuracies / anything that is unclear (presuming of cse reliable sources support these changes). For instance: 
::# the state of the Ottoman Empire prior to the campaign is important to provide context to our readers (and indeed is mentioned in numerous works on the campaign) but is not mentioned in the proposed draft; and
::# in the current draft we don't mention the German military mission and von Sanders (who would later of cse play a major role in the campaign). 
:: These are just two examples, but there may be others. The effect of such a short summary in my opinion is that any reader that doesn't already have an understanding of the campaign is introduced to the subject rather abruptly, and without the necessary context to understand how it unfolds or who the key players are (and I don't believe this is adequately summarized at the main topic article yet either, which is still being worked on and is mostly unreferenced). 
:: At only three paragraphs this section (as it currently is, not the draft) doesn't really seem that big to me (although any overall expansion would probably create a [[WP:SIZE]] issue). As such I don't really see why there is a need to reduce it; however, if others are supportive of doing this then a section with the level detail of Keith's suggested draft would be a minimum in my opinion, and I still do not support its reduction to a single short paragraph per the original proposal. You will note above I have now tweaked the sentence regarding Mehmet V so I wonder if perhaps [[User:SelimAnkara1993]] might comment on that and if there are any other issues which they feel need to be amended. If the references support changes then I am more than happy to consider those of cse. Perhaps that may be an alternative way forward. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 01:21, 3 April 2015 (UTC)
:::I cut the preamble since it seemed to be the place for bones of contention but if you want a version of it back I'd support that too, although since it contains explanation as well as description consensus will be harder. I'm critically ill with manflu at the moment (;O)) hence my reluctance to look at sources. It was nice to see Selim's suggestions of detailed changes but we need citations before bigger ones.[[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 07:07, 3 April 2015 (UTC)
::::Skinner &amp; Stacke have 
* 29 October: Turkey commences hostilities against Russia (see July 31st. and November 2nd and 5th) . Turkish warships bombard Odessa, Sevastopol, and Theodosia.
* 30 October: Allied Governments present ultimatum to Turkey (see 29th). Great Britain and France sever diplomatic relations with Turkey. British and French Ambassadors demand passports (see 31st, and November 5th).
* 31 October: British Government issue orders for hostilities to commence against Turkey (see 30th, and November 1st and 5th).
* 1 November: Great Britain and Turkey commence hostilities (see 5th, and October 30th and 31st).
* 2 November: Russia declares war on Turkey (see October 29th)
* 5 November: Great Britain and France formally declare war on Turkey (see 1st and 11th, and October 31st).
* 6 November: Keupri-Keui (Armenia) taken by Russian forces (see 14th).[[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 07:24, 3 April 2015 (UTC)

== The German &quot;cruisers&quot; Goeben and Breslau ==

The article mentions that Germany &quot;offered two cruisers, SMS Goeben and SMS Breslau to the Ottoman Navy&quot;. While the Breslau was indeed a Magdeburg-class light (4,500 ton) cruiser armed with 10.5 cm (4.1&quot;) guns, the Goeben was a 23,000 ton Moltke-class battlecruiser armed with 280 cm (11&quot;) guns that threw a 302 kg (666 lb.) shell, heavy enough to sink the British battlecruiser HMS Indefagitable at Jutland. Cruisers and battlecruisers are not the same thing; the latter -- originally a brainchild of Admiral Jackie Fisher -- were vessels built for cruiser speed but with battleship armament --[[User:Death Bredon|Death Bredon]] ([[User talk:Death Bredon|talk]]) 12:04, 26 October 2015 (UTC)
:G'day, I've tweaked the wording to remove the word &quot;cruisers&quot;. Does this work? Regards, [[User:AustralianRupert|AustralianRupert]] ([[User talk:AustralianRupert|talk]]) 12:19, 26 October 2015 (UTC)

== NZ Troop Numbers ==

On 22 March 2016 there was much media attention in New Zealand regarding a revision of the recognised number of NZ troops involved in the Gallipoli Campaign.  ( &lt;ref&gt;http://www.mch.govt.nz/new-research-dramatically-increases-numbers-new-zealand-soldiers-gallipoli&lt;/ref&gt; and &lt;ref&gt;http://www.mch.govt.nz/sites/default/files/ENUMERATING%20NEW%20ZEALAND%20EXPEDITIONARY%20FORCE%20SERVICE%20INTERIM%20REPORT%20MARCH%202016%20%28D-0651931%29.PDF#overlay-context=new-research-dramatically-increases-numbers-new-zealand-soldiers-gallipoli&lt;/ref&gt; )
I accept that this is unproven, and potentially subject to debate, (it's history!) so I shouldn't have changed this page.  Sorry for that and thanks for the 'undo'.
So let's debate.  Should we change the infobox?
The source seems authoritative - NZ Defence Force and NZ Ministry of Culture and Heritage.  Surely unlikely to have a bias and ultra cautious against any risk of losing face through undertaking substandard research or unsafe conclusions.   The research was undertaken by the Chief Historian of MCH, and included relevant folk from NZDF, Archives NZ and Statistics NZ.  The findings are plausible and in fact address some problems with other numbers, often quoted, if not here.  The assumptions seem reasonable.
I propose that the Infobox 'Strength' number for New Zealanders be changed to 17,048.  This is the best number available at this date.[[User:Toothpickdog|Toothpickdog]] ([[User talk:Toothpickdog|talk]]) 05:43, 22 March 2016 (UTC)
{{reflist-talk}}
: Gday Toothpickdog, thanks for starting this discussion. I agree that the source you have provided is a reliable one so I have included this information in the body of the article now with this edit [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Gallipoli_Campaign&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=711290152&amp;oldid=711288583] (although I haven't amended the infobox). As far as I can tell the figures in the infobox are probably &quot;peak strength&quot; not the total number of personal that served over the entire campaign (or at least I'm assuming this is the case). Please note for instance that the infobox currently lists 20,000 Australians; however, a total of 50,000 + Australians actually served during the entire campaign - many being reinforcements or replacements for casualties etc. The figure of 20,000 refers to the initial commitment. I'm unsure about the rest of the figures for other nationalities however (e.g. Britain etc). The MCH source seems to be referring to total personnel (i.e. including reinforcements and replacements etc) and not peak strength so it would probably be out of place with the rest of the figures in the infobox if it were changed in isolation. {{ping|Keith-264}} - do you recall if the figures in the infobox are all meant to be &quot;peak strength&quot; or total figures? [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 23:08, 22 March 2016 (UTC)
::I think they're totals but I'm not sure.[[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 23:51, 22 March 2016 (UTC)
:::Yes they are, there wouldn't have been 460,000 British ashore at once. [[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 23:53, 22 March 2016 (UTC)
:::: Ok thanks Keith, yes that is a fair point. Given then that most of the figures in the infobox are totals (not &quot;peak strength&quot; like I suspected) both the New Zealand and Australian figures need to be changed to be consistent with them. As such with this cleared up I support Toothpickdog's proposal to do this. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 00:00, 23 March 2016 (UTC)
::::: I've made this change now [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Gallipoli_Campaign&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=711455215&amp;oldid=711418229]. Given the difference b/n Green (14,000) and MCH (17,000) for NZ figures I thought we should include both. I am open to other suggestions of how to acknowledge this difference though of cse. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 00:11, 23 March 2016 (UTC)
::::::Seems a good solution to me. Thanks, all. Regards, [[User:AustralianRupert|AustralianRupert]] ([[User talk:AustralianRupert|talk]]) 12:14, 23 March 2016 (UTC)
:::::: Me too.  Thanks!  [[User:Toothpickdog|Toothpickdog]] ([[User talk:Toothpickdog|talk]]) 02:30, 24 March 2016 (UTC)
{{od}} This change looks good, but should it be noted that this new (and extremely credible) figure is essentially a statistical estimate? - see page 8 of the source in particular where the authors repeatedly use the word &quot;approximately&quot; and discuss the statistical error factors. Other text probably needs to be revised - eg &quot;Among the dead were 2,721 New Zealanders, about a quarter of those who had landed on the peninsula&quot; (I've read today, but can't remember where) that this revision results in the NZ force having a similar casualty rate to the Australian force, which makes sense. [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 10:09, 24 March 2016 (UTC)
: Gday Nick. Good points - the bit from McGibbon re &quot;a quarter of those who had landed on the peninsula&quot; seems to be explained by the MCH source as the initial NZ strength so I have slightly reworded it to (hopefully) be consistent with the previous change - pls see my edit here [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Gallipoli_Campaign&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=711710815&amp;oldid=711455215]. Also I have now identified both the AS and NZ figures in the infobox as approximates. I am of cse open to further rewording in the text though if you feel the possible statistical issues with the revised NZ figures needs to be more explicitly acknowledged (or a note if you think that would be a better solution). [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 10:26, 24 March 2016 (UTC)

== What's happened to the lead? ==

It used to be succinct reportage of events and their significance, now it reads like journalism. 13:27, 15 July 2016 (UTC)[[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 13:29, 15 July 2016 (UTC)
:G'day, I also have concerns about the changes and have reverted them. Dbachmann: could you please outline your rationale here so that the proposed changes can be discussed? Regards, [[User:AustralianRupert|AustralianRupert]] ([[User talk:AustralianRupert|talk]]) 13:36, 15 July 2016 (UTC)
::I think a nod towards Oz, NZ and Turkish creation myths is right but not treating them as if they were what the campaign was for. I'll try to step back a bit though, because I'm in enough trouble already. Regards ;O))  [[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 13:41, 15 July 2016 (UTC)

== CE ==

Tidied references and changed &lt;nowiki&gt;; to '''&lt;/nowiki&gt; as apparently readers for people who can't see, can't deal with a semi-colon. [[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 12:15, 12 November 2016 (UTC)
: G'day. Unless there is objection to it I'd like to keep Bean's 2nd volume in the further reading as we only use his 1st volume as a reference and its still considered a fairly important work on the topic in this part of the world (even if dated). Thoughts? [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 21:52, 12 November 2016 (UTC)
::Apols Another', I thought it was a duplicate, which is why I got rid, quite happy for rv[[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 22:54, 12 November 2016 (UTC)
:PS I abbr US states but didn't notice I'd only abbr NSW in Oz locations....[[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 22:56, 12 November 2016 (UTC)
:: No worries, all the best. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 23:03, 12 November 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>qdb58brzg5rg87zte164pkaqcy4f4c7</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
