<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Führerbunker</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>433354</id>
    <revision>
      <id>719162495</id>
      <parentid>719136122</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-05-08T00:43:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lowercase sigmabot III</username>
        <id>17518500</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Archiving 13 discussion(s) to [[Talk:Führerbunker/Archive 1]]) (bot</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15834">{{GA|01:15, 28 June 2014 (UTC)|page=1|topic=Warfare|oldid=614708240}}
{{WPMILHIST|class=GA|WWII-task-force=yes|German=yes|Fortifications=yes
&lt;!-- 1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points are appropriately cited. --&gt;
|B-Class-1= yes
&lt;!-- 2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain major omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|B-Class-2= yes
&lt;!-- 3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;
|B-Class-3= yes
&lt;!-- 4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;
|B-Class-4= yes
&lt;!-- 5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;
|B-Class-5= yes}}
{{WikiProject Germany|class=GA|importance=High
| b1 &lt;!--Referencing &amp; citations--&gt; = yes
| b2 &lt;!--Coverage &amp; accuracy    --&gt; = yes
| b3 &lt;!--Structure              --&gt; = yes
| b4 &lt;!--Grammar &amp; style        --&gt; = yes
| b5 &lt;!--Supporting materials   --&gt; = yes
}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2011-01-16|oldid1=408160335|date2=2013-01-16|oldid2=533162291|date3=2015-01-16|oldid3=642426936}}
[[Category:GA-Class Nazi Germany articles]]
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 1
|minthreadsleft = 5
|minthreadstoarchive = 1
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:Führerbunker/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{Archives |bot=Lowercase sigmabot III|search=yes }}

==Hitler's remains==
What happened to Hitler's remains after burning?
jck 16-Jan-2004

:See [[Hitler's death]] which goes into quite a bit of detail about all this. It seems they may well have (eventually) ended up in the Elbe in 1970. &amp;mdash; [[User:Trilobite|Trilobite]] [[User_talk:Trilobite|(Talk)]] 22:12, 7 Mar 2005 (UTC)

== Fuhrerbunder: Discovered Its Mysteries ==

I have removed this from the &quot;Further Reading&quot; section. The book is self-published ([http://www.isem-editions.com/home_eng.html here] is the publisher website). The author is an amateur historian. A PDF copy of the book is available online [http://www.vho.org/aaargh/fran/livres8/GUIDOHbunker.pdf here]. It's not the scholarly type of work that should be added to our reading list in my opinion. Comments welcome -- [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 14:25, 25 May 2014 (UTC)
:It should be excluded. Not shown to be [[WP:RS]]. 22:07, 25 May 2014 (UTC)[[User:Kierzek|Kierzek]] ([[User talk:Kierzek|talk]])
::when i see Jesus Christ vs Adolf Hitler as a title to a section, I tend to stop reading. It is not appropriate in terms of being a reliable SS. There is far superior material out there. Concur with [[User:Diannaa]]. [[User:Irondome|Irondome]] ([[User talk:Irondome|talk]]) 23:06, 25 May 2014 (UTC)

I am Pietro GUIDO, the author of the book FUHRERBUNKER-DISCOVERED ITS MYSTERIES, published by the society of capital ISEM SRL, of which I was president. In fact the isbn number 88-87077-03-7 is indicative of the publisher ISEM. Is this a valid motive to be excluded by the list of the books in &quot;Further Reading&quot;? 
Coming to the contents of the book, it is worth to quote that it has reached the sixth edition and from over 10 years it is purchased all over the world. 
Who is interested can go on the page &quot;Readers' Reviews&quot; of the site www.hitlerbunker.com where are published over thirty letters of readers (among which the builder of the bunker and Rochus Misch) that judge my book  as the best and the more detailed book ever written on the Fuhrerbunker. 
Even the prestigious book of Kelleroff on the bunker has reproduced images taken from my book.
At this point, do you think my book unworthy to appear in the Further Reading page?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/2.32.250.129|2.32.250.129]] ([[User talk:2.32.250.129|talk]]) 19:39, 26 May 2014 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Thank you for coming to the talk page to discuss this matter. I have several reasons for wanting to exclude the book. It is self-published; the prose is low quality; the book is not written by a historian or academic but rather by an amateur; although there's a bibliography, there's no footnotes; and the book will be impossible for most readers to obtain and hence useless to the general reader. -- [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 23:17, 26 May 2014 (UTC)

:Thank you for your reply to the talk page. Despite your exclusion of the book, it has sold in ten years so many thousands of copies that you cannot imagine: I beg you to go and read the letters received from all over the world, published in the &quot;Readers' Reviews&quot; page of the website, written by more competent personalities (among them Hochtief,the company that built the bunker, the Berlin Senatskanzlei, the Hitler's bodyguard Rochus Mish, etc..) ,with their enthusiastic opinion on the value of the book. I am not a historian or academic or an amateur,I am simply a researcher. If parts of my book are reproduced, without my permission, in other books (Sven Felix Kelleroff) or websites for online reading, this testifies the significance of this source.
By the way, the book is easy to be purchased: it is enough to enter the website www.hitlerbunker.com and go to the page &quot;Order the book&quot;.
Pietro GUIDO
::Sorry but the consensus is to not include the book in Further Reading. The three experienced Wikipedians who have commented have said no, which is a pretty clear [[WP:consensus|consensus]] to exclude. Consensus is how we make decisions on this wiki. Sorry, -- [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 22:31, 28 May 2014 (UTC)

Dear Consensus, congratulations for your &quot;objective&quot; taking of position. God enlightes you! Pietro GUIDO, 30 May 2014

== Semi-protected edit request on 30 May 2014 ==

{{edit semi-protected|Führerbunker|answered=yes}}
&lt;!-- Begin request --&gt;
&quot;Construction&quot; chapter, 4th line:
Please change &quot;located 2,5 metres (8ft 2 in) lower&quot; to &quot;located 2,25 metres (7 ft 5 in) lower&quot; because the unique, reliable source &quot;Stasi - Archiv der Zentralstelle MfS-HA IX/11 UTA n°5 Kopie BStU-AR8&quot; shows that the difference of level between the Fuhrerbunker and the Vorbunker is 2,25 metres (8,50 - 6,25 metres).
&lt;!-- End request --&gt;
[[User:IDROSTICCHIO|IDROSTICCHIO]] ([[User talk:IDROSTICCHIO|talk]]) 16:37, 30 May 2014 (UTC)

:[[File:Red information icon with gradient background.svg|20px|link=]] '''Not done:'''&lt;!-- Template:ESp --&gt; The current source for that claim, ''The Reich Chancellery and Führerbunker Complex: An Illustrated History of the Seat of the Nazi Regime'', actually has [[The Reich Chancellery and Führerbunker Complex|its own article]]. That gives it the edge in [[WP:V|verifiability]], even if it were mistaken. Regardless of that, there is no way for us to make a change like this through the {{tl|edit semi-protected}} template because it inherently lacks consensus. The best way for you to move forward would be to start a discussion with your fellow editors here on the talk page and try to reach a new consensus or compromise. Thanks, [[User:Older and ... well older|Older and ... well older]] ([[User talk:Older and ... well older|talk]]) 00:05, 31 May 2014 (UTC)
::Te map with the vertical section of the two bunkers drawn by the Stasi experts in 1974, is visible at page 107 of the Pietro Guido Book &quot;FührerbunkerDiscovered Mysteries&quot; published by Isem Srl. I would like to ask the Consensus if it is the case to make the change. &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:2.32.221.43|2.32.221.43]] ([[User talk:2.32.221.43|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/2.32.221.43|contribs]]) 15:58, May 31, 2014&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;
:::I don't agree with making this change, as I am unable to access the Stasi report to confirm that that is what it says, and besides, secondary sources are preferred over primary sources. The Peitro Guido book (of which you are the author) is self-published and cannot be considered a reliable source. -- [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 16:43, 31 May 2014 (UTC)
:::Mr Guido, please read the message I have posted '''[[User talk:2.32.221.43|here]]''' regarding [[WP:conflict of interest|conflict of interest]]. -- [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 16:53, 31 May 2014 (UTC)
::::I checked my sources: Kellerhoff states, page 56: the Führerbunker was 2.5 meters beneath the floor of the Vorbunker. &quot;10 steps went down a staicase that made 90-degree turns&quot;. He matches with Lehrer 2006, with info. as to both bunkers, pp. 117, 119, (and mainly for this point) on page 123 who states, of the two separate shelters, the Führerbunker was located 2.5 metres (8 ft 2 in) lower than the Vorbunker. [[User:Kierzek|Kierzek]] ([[User talk:Kierzek|talk]]) 17:20, 31 May 2014 (UTC)

Dear “Older and…well older” first of all I would like to know why a secondary source has to be thought more reliable than a primary one (unless this is established by the Wikipedia Bible).   If you have a minimum knowledge of the principles of statistics  you should know that the primary sources are more reliable because they come from official bodies, while the secondary sources are background  that explain, interpret and analyze. Normally the secondary are a good way to start research and often have the  scope to arrive to the primary ones. A primary source is  more reliable since it shows or gives exact happenings without bias unlike a secondary source, which might interpret the information differently and with  various perceptions.  Let me make an example: primary sources are from a person who has witnessed the event firsthand, a secondary sources are  the first person he told. As a consequence your sentence that  the secondary source “The Reich Chancellery….” gives it the edge in verifiability is a logic swearword. 
Going to my proposal to change the object of the claim (and cancelled from our mind that “secondary sources”  are preferred over primary sources) what does it mean that my book is not a reliable book? Forget  my book! I have indicated the  unique primary source to change the statement (2,25 metres instead of 2,5), the Stasi document,  to amend an error. If you are not able to find it, this is your guilt. I can publish it in the talk page or  send to you by post.
Please stop  to hide you behind the leaf of fig tree  of the  “self-published book” and the” conflict of interest” (!).With my proposal I do not ask you to mention my book, I am only communicating to the Consensus a primary source, more reliable than all your secondary sources  (Kellerhoff e Lehrer included), with the aim to improve the Wikipedia information. 
With reference to the Kellerhoff  book I would like to know what foresees the ethical code of Wikipedia with reference to the inclusion in the list of “Sources” of a book that contains pages copied from other books, (as my book), without the permission of the author/editor. IDROSTICCHIO (talk) 19:30, 1 June 2014.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/2.32.208.30|2.32.208.30]] ([[User talk:2.32.208.30|talk]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:The relevant Wikipedia policy page is [[WP:PRIMARY]], which states that secondary sources are preferred over primary and tertiary sources. It's not just a question of the editors here present being able to access the document, it's also for the future, as content must be [[WP:V|verifiable]]. Since using secondary sources is preferable to primary sources, it's unlikely that you will get consensus to change the content based on a primary source that is difficult/impossible to access. I personally am opposed to making the change for that reason. -- [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 18:22, 1 June 2014 (UTC)

Dear Diannaa, this is an extract of the Wikipedia policy about sources:
&quot;Primary sources are original materials that are close to an event, and are often accounts written by people who are directly involved. They offer an insider's view of an event, a period of history, a work of art, a political decision, and so on. Primary sources may or may not be independent or third-party sources. An account of a traffic accident written by a witness is a primary source of information about the accident; similarly, a scientific paper documenting a new experiment conducted by the author is a primary source on the outcome of that experiment. Historical documents such as diaries are primary sources.[3]
Policy: Unless restricted by another policy, primary sources that have been reliably published may be used in Wikipedia; but only with care, because it is easy to misuse them.[4] Any interpretation of primary source material requires a reliable secondary source for that interpretation. A primary source may only be used on Wikipedia to make straightforward, descriptive statements of facts that can be verified by any educated person with access to the primary source but without further, specialized knowledge...&quot;
At this point, even a child, understands that the most reliable source is the primary one. In this case you can have directly or through me (forwarding to you the original source) the original source which does not require a great intelligence to read two numbers (8,5 metres and 6,25 metres)! You are putting your hands on your eyes to defend obtusely a foolish thesis contrary to the common sense and the Wikipedia policy. Frankling speaking, I have not understood what is the true reason of such behaviour.
Going to another topic: why don't you express, in this talk page, your opinion about the case of the Kellerhoff book above quoted in my talk of 1 June 2014? -- [[User talk Idrosticchio]]11.30, 3 June 2014  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/2.32.208.30|2.32.208.30]] ([[User talk:2.32.208.30|talk]]) 09:28, 3 June 2014 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:The Wikipedia guideline clearly states that secondary sources are preferred over primary sources. Regarding the Kellerhoff book possibly being in violation of your copyright, I am not going to express an opinion about that. -- [[User:Diannaa|Diannaa]] ([[User talk:Diannaa|talk]]) 18:47, 3 June 2014 (UTC)

== Semi-protected edit request on 8 June 2014 ==

{{edit semi-protected|Führerbunker|answered=yes}}
&lt;!-- Begin request --&gt;
Please change &quot;2,5 mt&quot; in &quot;2,25 mt /7,4 Ft&quot; . The primary source is the Stasi investigation published on the P. Guido book &quot;Fuhrerbunker-Discovered its Mysteries&quot;, published by Isem srl, 2009.
&lt;!-- End request --&gt;
[[Special:Contributions/93.148.81.50|93.148.81.50]] ([[User talk:93.148.81.50|talk]]) 16:07, 8 June 2014 (UTC)

In &quot;construction&quot;, line 4, please change 2,5 mt in 2,25 mt/7,4 Ft
[[User:IDROSTICCHIO|IDROSTICCHIO]] ([[User talk:IDROSTICCHIO|talk]]) 16:20, 8 June 2014 (UTC)
:[[File:Red information icon with gradient background.svg|20px|link=]] '''Not done:''' please provide [[WP:RS|reliable sources]] that support the change you want to be made.&lt;!-- Template:ESp --&gt; As indicated in the section directly above this one. — &lt;span class=&quot;nowrap&quot;&gt;&amp;#123;&amp;#123;U&amp;#124;[[User:Technical 13|Technical 13]]&amp;#125;&amp;#125;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;sup&gt;([[Special:EmailUser/Technical 13|e]] • [[User talk:Technical 13|t]] • [[Special:Contribs/Technical 13|c]])&lt;/sup&gt; 16:38, 8 June 2014 (UTC)

{{Talk:Führerbunker/GA1}}

== Photo caption ==

&quot;the cone-shaped structure in the centre served as the exhaust,&quot; Surely that should read &quot;served as the chimney&quot;? --[[User:Dweller|Dweller]] ([[User talk:Dweller|talk]]) 16:53, 15 December 2015 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>fcprzhhqu2j3tizxfrz5f1vy8iup7kq</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
