<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Lawrence Sullivan Ross</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>4512228</id>
    <revision>
      <id>655289975</id>
      <parentid>653611996</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-04-07T03:15:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SporkBot</username>
        <id>12406635</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Remove template per [[Wikipedia:Templates for discussion/Log/2015 March 16|TFD outcome]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11476">{{Talk header}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=FAC
|action1date=16:20, 5 November 2007
|action1link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Lawrence Sullivan Ross
|action1result=promoted
|action1oldid=167914966
|action2=FTC
|action2date=17:11, 11 January 2009
|action2link=Wikipedia:Featured topic candidates/Texas A&amp;M University/archive1
|action2result=failed
|action2oldid=259182690
|currentstatus=FA
|maindate=May 22, 2009
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Military History|class=FA
|B-Class-1=yes
|B-Class-2=yes
|B-Class-3=yes
|B-Class-4=yes
|B-Class-5=yes|ACW-task-force=yes|US-task-force=yes}}
{{WikiProject United States|class=FA|importance=High|TX=yes|TX-importance=High|A&amp;M=yes|A&amp;M-importance=mid|USgovernors=yes|USgovernors-importance=low|listas=Ross, Lawrence Sullivan}}
{{WikiProject Biography|living=no
|class=FA
|military-priority=low
|military-work-group=yes
|politician-priority=mid
|politician-work-group=yes
|listas=Ross, Lawrence Sullivan
}}
{{WikiProject Politics|class=FA|importance=low}}
}}

== Ku Klux Klan ==

I attend Texas A&amp;M (where we have a large statue of &quot;Sully&quot; as he is called in front of the Academic Building) and there has been talk of him being a member of, and even a leader of, the KKK while in Texas. Can anyone substantiate this? [[User:JRDarby|JRDarby]] 05:58, 14 May 2007 (UTC)

I've been reading Judith Benner's biography of Sully, and it doesn't mention any KKK leanings.  She quotes a lot from Ross's private letters, which means she should have had access to all the facts that are still recordable.  Overall, the tone of the book is very favorable to Sully though.   [[User:Karanacs|Karanacs]] 15:19, 18 September 2007 (UTC)
:I checked other books and found no mention that he was a member of the KKK.  [[User:Karanacs|Karanacs]] 15:02, 20 September 2007 (UTC)

==Fair use rationale for Image:Sealtexas.jpg==
[[Image:Nuvola apps important.svg|70px|left]]
'''[[:Image:Sealtexas.jpg]]''' is being used on this article. I notice the image page specifies that the image is being used under [[Wikipedia:Fair use|fair use]] but there is no [[Wikipedia:Fair use rationale guideline|explanation or rationale]] as to why its use in '''this''' Wikipedia article constitutes fair use. In addition to the [[Wikipedia:Image copyright tags/Fair use|boilerplate fair use template]], you must also write out on the image description page a specific explanation or rationale for why using this image in each article is consistent with [[WP:FU|fair use]].

Please go to [[:Image:Sealtexas.jpg|the image description page]] and edit it to include a [[Wikipedia:Fair use rationale guideline |fair use rationale]]. Using one of the templates at [[Wikipedia:Fair use rationale guideline]] is an easy way to insure that your image is in compliance with Wikipedia policy, but remember that you must complete the template. Do not simply insert a blank template on an image page.

If there is  other fair use media, consider checking that you have specified the fair use rationale on the other images used on this page.  Note that any fair use images uploaded after 4 May, 2006, and lacking such an explanation will be deleted one week after they have been uploaded, as described on [[Wikipedia:Criteria for speedy deletion#Images.2FMedia|criteria for speedy deletion]]. If you have any questions please ask them at the [[Wikipedia:Media copyright questions|Media copyright questions page]]. Thank you.&lt;!-- Template:Missing rationale2 --&gt;

[[User:BetacommandBot|BetacommandBot]] 01:12, 2 July 2007 (UTC)

==Quick review==
The following suggestions were generated by a semi-automatic [[User:AndyZ/peerreviewer|javascript program]], and might not be applicable for the article in question.
*If this article is about a person, please add &lt;code&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;{{persondata|PLEASE SEE [[WP:PDATA]]!}}&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/code&gt; along with the required parameters to the article - see [[Wikipedia:Persondata]] for more information.&lt;sup&gt;[[User:AndyZ/G#persondata|[?]]]&lt;/sup&gt;
*Per [[WP:WIAFA]], this article's table of contents (ToC) may be too long- consider shrinking it down by merging short sections or using a proper system of daughter pages as per [[Wikipedia:Summary style]].&lt;sup&gt;[[User:AndyZ/G#toc|[?]]]&lt;/sup&gt;
*This article may need to undergo [[WP:SS|summary style]], where a series of appropriate subpages are used. For example, if the article is [[United States]], then an appropriate subpage would be [[History of the United States]], such that a summary of the subpage exists on the mother article, while the subpage goes into more detail.&lt;sup&gt;[[User:AndyZ/G#SS|[?]]]&lt;/sup&gt;
*There are a few occurrences of [[weasel word]]s in this article- please observe [[WP:AWT]]. Certain phrases should specify exactly who supports, considers, believes, etc., such a view.
**''it has been''
**''allege''
**might be weasel words, and should be provided with proper [[WP:FOOTNOTE|citations]] (if they already do, or are not weasel terms, please &lt;strike&gt;strike&lt;/strike&gt; this comment).&lt;sup&gt;[[User:AndyZ/G#awt|[?]]]&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;!--This javascript cannot determine if a citation is provided; if all weasel terms are covered by citations, please strike this--&gt;
*Watch for [[User:Tony1/How_to_satisfy_Criterion_2a#Redundancy|redundancies]] that make the article too wordy instead of being crisp and concise. (You may wish to try Tony1's [[User:Tony1/How to satisfy Criterion 1a: redundancy exercises|redundancy exercises]].)
**Vague terms of size often are unnecessary and redundant -  “some”, “a variety/number/majority of”, “several”, “a few”, “many”, “any”, and “all”. For example, “&lt;font color='red'&gt;&lt;s&gt;All&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/font&gt; pigs are pink, so we thought of &lt;font color='red'&gt;&lt;s&gt;a number of&lt;/s&gt;&lt;/font&gt; ways to turn them green.”
**Avoid misplaced formality: “in order to/for” (-&gt; to/for), “thereupon”, “notwithstanding”, [[User:Tony1/How to satisfy Criterion 1a#Saying good-bye to misplaced formality|etc]].
More to follow later. &lt;span style=&quot;background-color: maroon; color: white&quot;&gt;[[User:BQZip01|&lt;font color=&quot;white&quot;&gt;'''—&amp;nbsp;''BQZip01''&amp;nbsp;—'''&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:BQZip01|talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 06:49, 25 September 2007 (UTC)

:Thanks.  I added the persondata and combined some of the sections to make for a slightly nicer TOC.  The weasel words are cited.  [[User:Karanacs|Karanacs]] 15:07, 26 September 2007 (UTC)

==rescue of cynthia parker==
I have read (sorry, can't find the ref) that contrary to &quot;our&quot; eurocentric view, many women were happier in indian communities then in white communities, at least for pre revolutionary New england. Perhaps this is 1960s mythology; perhaps not. In any event, the &quot;rescue&quot; sounds a little suspicious - based on those stereotypes of hte bad savages and the enlightened whiteman.[[Special:Contributions/65.220.64.105|65.220.64.105]] ([[User talk:65.220.64.105|talk]]) 13:29, 22 May 2009 (UTC)

:In response to the above comments, I have also read and re-read the paragraphs pertaining to the rescue of Cynthia Ann Parker (not &quot;Cynthia Parker,&quot; as the above unidentified writer names her). At no point in the article can I find where it states or implies that she was &quot;happier&quot; living with the Parkers after her rescue, so I don't know what he is contradicting. In fact, the article specifically states that Parker &quot;was not happy to have been rescued by Ross,&quot; although this poorly written phrase inadvertently implies that she may have been happy if she had been rescued by someone else. But, that is what you get with an internet encyclopedia with no professional editor. 

:This previous writer refers to &quot;our eurocentric (sic) view.&quot; American readers in the early part of this twenty-first century don't have a &quot;Euro-centric view.&quot; In any case, the attitudes of female captives of North-Eastern tribes in &quot;pre-Revolutionary New England&quot; has absolutely nothing to do with the attitudes of female captives of the Comanche in the middle of the nineteenth century. Anyone who has read the many first person accounts given by rescued captives of the Comanche is familiar with their treatment of white captives. Further, it is well-documented that kidnapping victims of any culture learn to assimilate and identify with their captors, in spite of their poor treatment. This is often referred to as &quot;Stockholm syndrome.&quot; Nevertheless, it doesn't mean that the captive is better off with the captor.

:Like this writer's disjointed comments, what it is that, in his mind, makes the rescue of Cynthia Ann Parker &quot;sound a little suspicious,&quot; is left unclear. Either Parker was rescued or she was not. The fact that she was rescued is a well-established piece of history. The Parker family and others had been searching for her ever since her capture by the Comanche twenty-five years before. The fact that her rescue was delayed by twenty-five years makes it no less a rescue. [[User:PGNormand|PGNormand]] ([[User talk:PGNormand|talk]]) 17:52, 28 December 2009 (UTC)

==Statue of Sully==

In the section titled &quot;Legacy,&quot; one paragraph is devoted to the statue of Ross on the Texas A&amp;M campus. The first half of that paragraph is about the statue itself. However, the second half of the paragraph is a tangent relating to the recent &quot;tradition&quot; of students placing pennies at the foot of the statue to ensure good luck during final exams. (I place the word &quot;tradition&quot; in quotes, because it is so recent that it was not observed when I was a student in the late 1960s and early 1970s.) This tangent contains three sentences. The first of these simply states what this tradition is. The second sentence attributes the tradition to a campus legend, which states that Ross, during his presidency at the college, often tutored students, &quot;and as payment would accept only a penny for their thoughts.&quot; This makes no sense for several reasons. First, the term &quot;a penny for your thoughts,&quot; means that the person speaking will pay &quot;a penny for your thoughts.&quot; It does not mean that the person speaking will take &quot;a penny for your thoughts.&quot; Second, the payment that is referenced in the campus legend is payment for tutoring, not for anyone's thoughts. This reference in the article would make more sense if it stated that Ross accepted &quot;only a penny for tutoring.&quot; Third, if this legend were true, then the tradition would have started as soon after the statue's erection, and it would have been started by students who remembered paying Ross a penny for tutoring. But we know that the tradition did not start until sometime in the mid-1970s at the earliest, and probably after that, by students who were born sixty-plus years after Ross died. The third sentence in this tangent states that &quot;at exam time, his statue ... is often covered in pennies.&quot; This statement is untrue on the face of it. It is a greatly exaggerated figure of speech. Finally, the source of this tangent, listed in the endnote, is an article that appeared in the campus newspaper in 2004. The source quoted in the 2004 newspaper article is a member of the Class of 2006 who does not give a source for his/her statement, but says that the tradition started during the life of Ross. For that to have been true, the statue would have to been completed before Ross died. My recommendation is that this entire three-sentence tangent, which is not about Ross, but about about a statue of him, be removed from this article on &quot;Lawrence Sullivan Ross.&quot; [[User:PGNormand|PGNormand]] ([[User talk:PGNormand|talk]]) 19:05, 28 December 2009 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>jm5zqsn0vxwqlcxjy4lln08rswfaf3a</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
