<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Ming dynasty</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>163176</id>
    <revision>
      <id>729653402</id>
      <parentid>729653349</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-07-13T17:42:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>LlywelynII</username>
        <id>7764849</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Southern Ming and Tungning */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="83616">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=FAC
|action1date=04:36, 22 January 2008
|action1link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Ming Dynasty
|action1result=promoted
|action1oldid=186041430
|currentstatus=FA
|maindate=November 16, 2011
}}
{{Vital article|level=4|topic=History|class=FA}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WPCHINA|class=FA|importance=Top|history=yes}}
{{WPEASTASIA|class=FA|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Former countries|class=FA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Military History|class=FA|Chinese=y}}
}}
{{WPCD|class=FA}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2008-01-23|oldid1=186315135|date2=2009-01-23|oldid2=265908085|date3=2010-01-23|oldid3=339530804|date4=2011-04-25|oldid4=425752536|date5=2013-04-25|oldid5=552193375|date6=2015-04-25|oldid6=658803096|date7=2016-04-25|oldid7=717074001}}

{{Very long|May 2011}} 

{{Archive box|search=yes|
* [[Talk:Ming Dynasty/Archive 1|Archive 1]] &lt;small&gt;(Dec 2002–May 2009)&lt;/small&gt;
}}
{{Copied|from=Ming Dynasty|to=Clan of Zhu|from_oldid=http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Hongwu_Emperor&amp;oldid=416691812|diff=http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Clan_of_Zhu&amp;oldid=416970552}}
__TOC__
{{Clear}}

==Coinage==
&lt;nowiki&gt;[[File:Ming coinage 14th 17th century.jpg|thumb|Ming coinage, 14-17th century.]]&lt;/nowiki&gt; - Ming coinage 14-17th century.[[User:Per Honor et Gloria|''&lt;b&gt;&lt;Font color=&quot;#FF0000&quot;&gt;Per&amp;nbsp;&lt;/Font&gt;&lt;Font color=&quot;#FF8000&quot;&gt;Honor&amp;nbsp;&lt;/Font&gt;&lt;Font color=&quot;Orange&quot;&gt;et&amp;nbsp;&lt;/Font&gt;&lt;Font color=&quot;#FFC000&quot;&gt;Gloria&lt;/Font&gt;&lt;/b&gt;'']]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Per Honor et Gloria|&lt;big&gt;✍&lt;/big&gt;]] 15:51, 6 March 2010 (UTC)
:As with [[Talk:Tang Dynasty]], once again I realize that this article has no pictures of currency and coinage! Thanks for posting this here, because, once again, I know just where to put it! Cheers.--&lt;strong&gt;[[User:PericlesofAthens|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;Pericles of Athens&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:PericlesofAthens|&lt;font color=&quot;#0000CD&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 16:06, 6 March 2010 (UTC)
:Image is in article now. --[[User:Funandtrvl|Funandtrvl]] ([[User talk:Funandtrvl|talk]]) 16:27, 12 August 2010 (UTC)

== Flag ==
&lt;nowiki&gt;[[File:日月旗.svg|thumb|日月旗]]&lt;/nowiki&gt; -- I read on [http://baike.baidu.com/view/1172187.htm Baidu Baike] that Ming had a flag called 日月旗, and following instructions [http://hi.baidu.com/chingyuenciv/blog/item/65388d031d41e78bd43f7ca9.html here], I constructed the image I post here. However, I don't know much about this flag. I think it would be good if someone could find out more about it and incorporate it into the article. [[User:Asoer|Asoer]] ([[User talk:Asoer|talk]]) 08:36, 11 May 2010 (UTC)

Also the Senior Grand Secretary  	Xie Jin redirects to the wrong page.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/92.233.64.99|92.233.64.99]] ([[User talk:92.233.64.99|talk]]) 17:02, 9 March 2014 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

::I have done a bit of research, unfortunately, it is a hoax.&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid black;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Arilang1234|&lt;font style=&quot;color:white;background:#fe0000;&quot;&gt; Arilang  &lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt; &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Arilang1234|''talk'']]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt; 06:31, 5 March 2011 (UTC)

==Reference to Kolmas' book==
I've marked the references to Kolmas as needing which book title and year, as it is missing entirely from the article. --[[User:Funandtrvl|Funandtrvl]] ([[User talk:Funandtrvl|talk]]) 16:24, 12 August 2010 (UTC)

== christianity ==

I believe the &quot;since the Tang dynasty&quot; part about Christianity is rather misleading, as by the beginning of the Ming dynasty, those ealier Chinese Nestorian communities were all long gone.

Also I think one could argue that the Jesuit missionaries would be better treated under 'foreign relations', or at least it should be explained how the topic is relevant to religion within the Ming dynasty - i.e. how much influence Christian religion - rather than European science - had on China. If the situation was the same as in [[History of Roman Catholicism in Japan|Japan]], mentioning the Jesuits under 'religion' would be a no-brainer, but my humble impression is that the religious influence of the Jesuits in China was much less considerable.

Same about the Kaifeng Jews. How much of China's population did they represent? Did any of them do something significant, a la Zheng He?

[[User:Yaan|Yaan]] ([[User talk:Yaan|talk]]) 17:28, 6 January 2011 (UTC)

== What is this supposed to mean ? ==
:&quot;The Ming Dynasty, or anachronistically referred to as Empire of the Great Ming, &quot;
what is this sentence supposed to mean ?   What is &quot;anachronistic&quot; about it ?  All this 
chinese people I know call it that &quot;Da Ming&quot; period.[[User:Eregli bob|Eregli bob]] ([[User talk:Eregli bob|talk]]) 05:29, 25 April 2011 (UTC)
:Sure, it's anachronistic to talk about it as &quot;Great Ming&quot; in English. Of course, at the time, people just called it &quot;Cathay&quot; and &quot;China&quot;; plus, it's worse to refer to the geographic entity and political system as a &quot;Dynasty&quot; rather than an &quot;Empire&quot; anyway; so the editor's kinda of correct while totally missing the point and adding needless snark and POV to the article. Just fix it. —&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:LlywelynII|&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:#BBBBBB 0.1em 0.1em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;LlywelynII&lt;/span&gt;]] 15:46, 14 October 2012 (UTC)

== I want help and collaboration fixing violation of Wikipedia's [[WP:Summary_style|summary]] and [[WP:Article_size|article size]] policies ==

Anyone looking over [[History of the Ming Dynasty]] and [[Ming Dynasty]] to improve and add citations (as I was today) should be disturbed; often sections are ''identical''.  Instead of the [[Ming Dynasty|Ming article]] containing a briefer summary of [[History of the Ming Dynasty]], it is copied verbatim in direct contradiction of Wikipedia's policies (please see [[WP:Summary_style]] and [[WP:Article_size]]}.  I have a ton of secondary sources on the Ming, and want to add facts and citations but feel I can't until this fundamental, underlying problem is addressed.  Can any of you collaborate and help me improve Ming content and rectify this problem that is a stain on Wikipedia's usually excellent coverage of China's important history? 
--[[User:NickDupree|NickDupree]] ([[User talk:NickDupree|talk]]) 03:45, 17 May 2011 (UTC)
:I'll be improving summarizing the [[Ming Dynasty]] history section so that it's not identical to [[History of the Ming Dynasty]].  This is a huge undertaking.  For details, see the discussion at [[Wikipedia:Editor_assistance/Requests#I_want_help_and_collaboration_fixing_violation_of_Wikipedia.27s_summary_and_article_size_policies]] --[[User:NickDupree|NickDupree]] ([[User talk:NickDupree|talk]]) 21:44, 19 May 2011 (UTC)
::I've finished trimming back and summarizing the content duplicated at [[History of the Ming Dynasty]] because I think it is crucial in order for further improvements to even be possible. Some of the most duplicative and detailed content was deleted so people can view it over at [[History of the Ming Dynasty]] and one section moved to [[History of the Ming Dynasty]].  History of the Ming Dynasty will be the in-depth treatment of the subject, and [[Ming Dynasty]] will be a better-summarized overview (though my overhaul will only touch the history heading). Both articles will be better for it. 04:51, 1 June 2011 (UTC)~  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:NickDupree|NickDupree]] ([[User talk:NickDupree|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/NickDupree|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== largest naval battle in history??? ==

yet it doesn't appear in the largest naval battles page at all.
unless there is an agreement that this battle of lake poyang was one of the largest, this should be changed to just give an idea of how many combatants there were (sorry forgot to login again user: teknotiss)  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/188.220.151.59|188.220.151.59]] ([[User talk:188.220.151.59|talk]]) 15:50, 16 November 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Sorry, i can't sign in at the moment, but I would like to question this also. In the linked page on largest naval battles in history there are examples of larger numbers of ships, higher tonnages, and larger numbers of participants. Surely this needs to be changed or referenced to say who argues this and why.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/88.150.237.2|88.150.237.2]] ([[User talk:88.150.237.2|talk]]) 10:53, 27 April 2014 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Map ==
Who made this map? It's complete nonsense. Tibet and far northeast Manchuria were part of the Ming Empire? Really? It looks like something ginned up by Chinese nationalists to justify modern day control over those areas. [[Special:Contributions/174.21.85.72|174.21.85.72]] ([[User talk:174.21.85.72|talk]]) 17:41, 24 May 2012 (UTC)
:I have restored the [[:File:Ming-Empire2.jpg|map used]] when the article passed FAC because as well as the issues above (which I do not know enough about to comment on) the [[:File:永乐年间的明朝（简）.png|newer map]] used Chinese symbols; as most of the English Wikipedia's readers speak English it is more useful to have the map with English labels. [[User:Nev1|Nev1]] ([[User talk:Nev1|talk]]) 17:53, 24 May 2012 (UTC)

:Beyond which, there is a ''huuuuge'' discussion in the talk archive about those maps. They're quite indefensible &amp; would need strong well-argued support here before they should be included. —&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:LlywelynII|&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:#BBBBBB 0.1em 0.1em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;LlywelynII&lt;/span&gt;]] 16:19, 14 October 2012 (UTC)
It is extremely important to remember to be as neutral and nonaggressive as possible. Please do not attempt to instigate Chinese Nationalism into this topic, as this is both insulting to the Chinese government and unnecessary content on Wikipedia. If you continue to feel the senseless urge to condemn the Chinese Government, please by all means do so in front of a well-educated Chinese ambassador, and see what the result will be. If Wikipedia is the only place that you can muster up your punitive courage to protest the Chinese government, then your out of luck.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Aslanofnarnia7|Aslanofnarnia7]] ([[User talk:Aslanofnarnia7|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Aslanofnarnia7|contribs]]) 05:24, 23 March 2014 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt; 

Also, did you actually take the time to read the article itself I the first place, I wonder! You claim that Chinese conquests in Tibet were unrealistic and a means of the Chinese government to defense their present day administration of that region. It clearly states in their article of Chinese conquests on Tibet. If you are still skeptical about the article itself, you are more than welcome to bring this issue to the author of this article. Just as some helpful advice in the future, if you want other people to accept your opinions, especially on Wikipedia, you need to procure actual evidence to defend your claim, which, in this case, would be that Tibet was independent from Ming rule. Without any evidence, we will always resort to status quo, in other words, resorting to the original content. More importantly, please use a respectful attitude when addressing sensitive issues such as the Chinese government. Stirring up trouble and resentment and unnecessary political conflicts is never a number one priority for Wikipedian users. If you abide by these suggestions, you will be appreciated by your fellow users. On the other hand, should you choose not to see sense, then you will have to take the consequences of creating a hostile work environment and possibly face being blocked from editing for quite a period of time. If following these simple expectations to function in a  safe and informative online environment is asking too much, consider politely removing your presence from this website and creating your own, where, by your own self centered and ignorant and insolent attitude, you will learn the appropriate protocol of the modern day commonly accepted form of online social, verbal, and communicative language. If you wish to go down that road, the all I can say is... Good luck???

== &quot;...smaller loyalist movements continued until the proclamation of the Republic of China&quot;??? ==
The text says: &quot;Despite the Ming defeat, smaller loyalist movements continued until the proclamation of the Republic of China.&quot; What does it mean? There were actual pretenders? There were descendants of the ming dyansty fighting to become Emperors? Who were they? What happened? --[[User:Lecen|Lecen]] ([[User talk:Lecen|talk]]) 02:20, 15 June 2012 (UTC)


I agree this is a very confounding ending to the section,  does it actually mean there were pretenders for several hundred years until the 20th century?
The Republic of China was proclaimed by Mao in 1912 afaik.  There should either be a citation here or clarification.
[[User:Metaldev|Metaldev]] ([[User talk:Metaldev|talk]]) 03:36, 30 June 2013 (UTC)

==Those names aren't names, they're adjectives: it's &quot;the Hongwu Emperor&quot; every time, not &quot;Hongwu&quot; or &quot;Emperor Hong Wu&quot;==
I know it takes some time to wrap your head around, but the [[Chinese names]] during this period were pretty complicated and by the time you were emperor the [[naming taboo]] meant anyone who could say your name was already dead. Names like the &quot;Hongwu Emperor&quot; and the &quot;Yongle Emperor&quot; reference ''times'' and not ''people''. The closest equivalent in English would be something like the &quot;Elizabethan Queen&quot; or the &quot;'90s President&quot; {{ndash}} she's not &quot;Queen Elizabethan&quot; and he's not &quot;Nineties&quot;.

It's a mite nitpicky but given the importance of the article to people coming in to learn about the culture, it's worth keeping the idea clear. —&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:LlywelynII|&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:#BBBBBB 0.1em 0.1em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;LlywelynII&lt;/span&gt;]] 16:19, 14 October 2012 (UTC)

== Banner ==

http://books.google.com/books?id=i6gfSl7PHE4C&amp;pg=PA218&amp;lpg=PA218&amp;dq=sacrifice+to+the+banner+ming&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=Y-OlNQjhUO&amp;sig=2FBuYeYDlU3PpaB6UR86jIaDgL8&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=jJt7UKCvIYHN0AGs4YH4Ag&amp;ved=0CDAQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=sacrifice%20to%20the%20banner%20ming&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=dCUhSRR7yP4C&amp;pg=PA67&amp;lpg=PA67&amp;dq=sacrifice+to+the+banner+ming&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=wO-WPBc2Ht&amp;sig=IEPxHbMoOBLiBuGbCwczSYIMgtw&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=jJt7UKCvIYHN0AGs4YH4Ag&amp;ved=0CDYQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=sacrifice%20to%20the%20banner%20ming&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=TCIjZ7l6TX8C&amp;pg=PA124&amp;lpg=PA124&amp;dq=sacrifice+to+the+banner+ming&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=l2Qiuhr23I&amp;sig=xcitudjRGd7FcYNo5Sv-YYoEdE4&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=jJt7UKCvIYHN0AGs4YH4Ag&amp;ved=0CDwQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q=sacrifice%20to%20the%20banner%20ming&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=hi2THl2FUZ4C&amp;pg=PA341&amp;lpg=PA341&amp;dq=sacrifice+to+the+banner+ming&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=1NxcdIFIhu&amp;sig=PumqLrxIPpdP2ZC_6-7kO19nL1g&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=jJt7UKCvIYHN0AGs4YH4Ag&amp;ved=0CEIQ6AEwAw#v=onepage&amp;q=sacrifice%20to%20the%20banner%20ming&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=067On0JgItAC&amp;pg=PA588&amp;lpg=PA588&amp;dq=sacrifice+to+the+banner+ming&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=5PxkoOvYFa&amp;sig=mIwSpVXRO0bK0NMldMEoleyvbLg&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=jJt7UKCvIYHN0AGs4YH4Ag&amp;ved=0CEcQ6AEwBA#v=onepage&amp;q=sacrifice%20to%20the%20banner%20ming&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=Idhyr1hqS0kC&amp;pg=PA800&amp;lpg=PA800&amp;dq=sacrifice+to+the+banner+ming&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=a8zHtuDGRq&amp;sig=PKnDtzxu1EBVjsB4GNWZi5HkKHk&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=jJt7UKCvIYHN0AGs4YH4Ag&amp;ved=0CE4Q6AEwBQ#v=onepage&amp;q=sacrifice%20to%20the%20banner%20ming&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=i6pIMVGPkuUC&amp;pg=PA31&amp;lpg=PA31&amp;dq=sacrifice+to+the+banner+ming&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=jn78S7f7Nq&amp;sig=_81duwIDxo9O06YRMn28yQdF9CI&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=jJt7UKCvIYHN0AGs4YH4Ag&amp;ved=0CFIQ6AEwBg#v=onepage&amp;q=sacrifice%20to%20the%20banner%20ming&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=_6H1TvEpETMC&amp;pg=PA90&amp;lpg=PA90&amp;dq=sacrifice+to+the+banner+ming&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=nbESsnMiDe&amp;sig=nBVFf20T00nJl-f0la73GL8G9G0&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=jJt7UKCvIYHN0AGs4YH4Ag&amp;ved=0CFgQ6AEwBw#v=onepage&amp;q=sacrifice%20to%20the%20banner%20ming&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=UVceic7Z4moC&amp;pg=PA47&amp;lpg=PA47&amp;dq=sacrifice+to+the+banner+ming&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=k9r4YQHilW&amp;sig=H-AcQhxS-TbuxMNG0Juq9VDYYhU&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=jJt7UKCvIYHN0AGs4YH4Ag&amp;ved=0CGAQ6AEwCA#v=onepage&amp;q=sacrifice%20to%20the%20banner%20ming&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=l6ab-z8tps0C&amp;pg=PA270&amp;lpg=PA270&amp;dq=sacrifice+to+the+banner+ming&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=ie2GPwt5ks&amp;sig=NF7ah5gQ9jMLUa0oLxEFuc_Kmos&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=jJt7UKCvIYHN0AGs4YH4Ag&amp;ved=0CGUQ6AEwCQ#v=onepage&amp;q=sacrifice%20to%20the%20banner%20ming&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=MKfXAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=sacrifice+to+the+banner+ming&amp;dq=sacrifice+to+the+banner+ming&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=hFrH0hhHmx&amp;sig=4OWa1QWM7Aq5RBkScq45dz2rBKM&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=-Jx7UJ6yD_C80QHKlYCgAQ&amp;ved=0CC8Q6AEwADgK


http://books.google.com/books?id=MTXxqqXw59kC&amp;pg=PA121&amp;lpg=PA121&amp;dq=sacrifice+to+the+banner+ming&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=Vr1v_KYWub&amp;sig=B7EzKulKJG6VltlKKbvSMoen-0s&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=-Jx7UJ6yD_C80QHKlYCgAQ&amp;ved=0CDMQ6AEwATgK#v=onepage&amp;q=sacrifice%20to%20the%20banner%20ming&amp;f=false


http://books.google.com/books?id=YQOhVb5Fbt4C&amp;pg=PA209&amp;lpg=PA209&amp;dq=sacrifice+to+the+banner+ming&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=ug35jPg-bq&amp;sig=PNdCx4aPMb6PHeOlX5FR-lZq3G0&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=-Jx7UJ6yD_C80QHKlYCgAQ&amp;ved=0CDgQ6AEwAjgK#v=onepage&amp;q=sacrifice%20to%20the%20banner%20ming&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=YfKOGTcHvncC&amp;pg=PT334&amp;lpg=PT334&amp;dq=sacrifice+to+the+banner+ming&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=C98OVEET5A&amp;sig=rmcxGFNwQoM1nGWK_0O_OcOo5b0&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=-Jx7UJ6yD_C80QHKlYCgAQ&amp;ved=0CD8Q6AEwAzgK

http://books.google.com/books?id=8hOgAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA235&amp;lpg=PA235&amp;dq=sacrifice+to+the+banner+ming&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=e_g40Rp6YX&amp;sig=mAw6Zm5jV98b51ahHImm5LTpGi8&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=-Jx7UJ6yD_C80QHKlYCgAQ&amp;ved=0CEUQ6AEwBDgK#v=onepage&amp;q=sacrifice%20to%20the%20banner%20ming&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=SQWW7QgUH4gC&amp;pg=PA1086&amp;lpg=PA1086&amp;dq=sacrifice+to+the+banner+ming&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=j6DpnA4eBf&amp;sig=ww_UDSjS3i_A03KRl-gOUTEsA44&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=-Jx7UJ6yD_C80QHKlYCgAQ&amp;ved=0CEsQ6AEwBTgK#v=onepage&amp;q=sacrifice%20to%20the%20banner%20ming&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=1h9zzSH-NmwC&amp;pg=PA62&amp;lpg=PA62&amp;dq=sacrifice+to+the+banner+ming&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=SJ4diRdGu6&amp;sig=hzAwWzkim3_ZCpO_DACTS3GgSKA&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=-Jx7UJ6yD_C80QHKlYCgAQ&amp;ved=0CFEQ6AEwBjgK#v=onepage&amp;q=sacrifice%20to%20the%20banner%20ming&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=5iN5J9G76h0C&amp;pg=PA462&amp;lpg=PA462&amp;dq=sacrifice+to+the+banner+ming&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=8qPmJUPuGf&amp;sig=n8lVKbNZnc3h5Tiytg4S5v28_IQ&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=-Jx7UJ6yD_C80QHKlYCgAQ&amp;ved=0CFcQ6AEwBzgK#v=onepage&amp;q=sacrifice%20to%20the%20banner%20ming&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=cRXAcZGcpa8C&amp;pg=PA109&amp;lpg=PA109&amp;dq=sacrifice+to+the+banner+ming&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=dPhPA7a5es&amp;sig=xZd63W-9zSGwaRJcmVk1WSEcMWk&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=-Jx7UJ6yD_C80QHKlYCgAQ&amp;ved=0CF0Q6AEwCDgK#v=onepage&amp;q=sacrifice%20to%20the%20banner%20ming&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=UQAMAAAAYAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=sacrifice+to+the+banner+ming&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=h0ahtxDTzh&amp;sig=rjiT3oVlkCuxeUAyb1It17lMq5s&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=-Jx7UJ6yD_C80QHKlYCgAQ&amp;ved=0CGMQ6AEwCTgK#v=onepage&amp;q=sacrifice%20to%20the%20banner%20ming&amp;f=false

05:27, 15 October 2012 (UTC)  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Ghressho|Ghressho]] ([[User talk:Ghressho|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Ghressho|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Foreign relations and the bureau of translation in the ming dynasty ==

The bureau used to manage foreign relations was the Siyiguan

Later during the Qing the [[Lifanyuan]] took over relations with the Mongols, Central Asia, Russians, and Tibet, while the Board of Rites took over relations with the south and eastern countries.

The [[Tongwen Guan]] replaced the Huitong Siyiguan

http://www.iolaw.org.cn/pdf/paper/2008/四夷馆与同文馆名称考.pdf

A seperate article on the Ming dynasty bureau of translation ([[Huitong Siyiguan]]) should be created, I have secondary and primary sources here. The primary sources will go into wikisource, which will be linked to the wikipedia article.

The Chinese article on Siyiguan

https://zh.wikipedia.org/wiki/会同四译馆

Chinese–Barbarian Dictionary

https://zh.wikipedia.org/wiki/华夷译语

http://zh.wikisource.org/wiki/華夷譯語

Author: (明)火原潔撰

Book contributor: 北京大學圖書館

Looks like Thai or Shan

華夷譯語(一)

https://archive.org/details/02076757.cn

No idea what language this is

華夷譯語(二)

https://archive.org/details/02076758.cn

No idea

華夷譯語(三)

https://archive.org/details/02076759.cn

No idea

華夷譯語(四)

https://archive.org/details/02076760.cn

Persian

華夷譯語(五)

https://archive.org/details/02076761.cn

Persian

華夷譯語(六)

https://archive.org/details/02076762.cn

[[Old Uyghur language]] 

高昌館來文

https://archive.org/details/02076763.cn

I assume this is Tibetan

譯文備覽

https://archive.org/details/02076764.cn

http://books.google.com/books?id=0MMVAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=RA1-PA383&amp;dq=Hoa+i+i+yu+hirth&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=NLBnU_XZLuresATbnICQCg&amp;ved=0CDQQ6wEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=Hoa%20i%20i%20yu%20hirth&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=dw07AQAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA383&amp;dq=Hoa+i+i+yu+hirth&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=NLBnU_XZLuresATbnICQCg&amp;ved=0CDsQ6wEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Hoa%20i%20i%20yu%20hirth&amp;f=false



http://books.google.com/books?id=-bsuAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA99&amp;dq=Hoa+i+i+yu+hirth&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=NLBnU_XZLuresATbnICQCg&amp;ved=0CGcQ6wEwCQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Hoa%20i%20i%20yu%20hirth&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=bbVRKmLxU00C&amp;pg=PA99&amp;dq=Hoa+i+i+yu+hirth&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=NLBnU_XZLuresATbnICQCg&amp;ved=0CEAQ6wEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q=Hoa%20i%20i%20yu%20hirth&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=cQcMAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=RA1-PA334&amp;dq=Hoa+i+i+yu+hirth&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=NLBnU_XZLuresATbnICQCg&amp;ved=0CFAQ6wEwBQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Hoa%20i%20i%20yu%20hirth&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=i34LAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA345&amp;dq=Hoa+i+i+yu+hirth&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=n7BnU5qZHJSmsAS_3oDgCg&amp;ved=0CGEQ6AEwCTgK#v=onepage&amp;q=Hoa%20i%20i%20yu%20hirth&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=jxE_AQAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA114&amp;dq=Hoa+i+i+yu+hirth&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=tLBnU_CADMPjsASfkIKwBQ&amp;ved=0CDIQ6AEwADgU#v=onepage&amp;q=Hoa%20i%20i%20yu%20hirth&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=Iy4PAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA114&amp;dq=Hoa+i+i+yu+hirth&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=tLBnU_CADMPjsASfkIKwBQ&amp;ved=0CDoQ6wEwATgU#v=onepage&amp;q=Hoa%20i%20i%20yu%20hirth&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=mSQ7AQAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA114&amp;dq=Hoa+i+i+yu+hirth&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=tLBnU_CADMPjsASfkIKwBQ&amp;ved=0CEAQ6wEwAjgU#v=onepage&amp;q=Hoa%20i%20i%20yu%20hirth&amp;f=false

[[Jurchen_language#Ming_Dynasty_Jurchen_dictionaries]]

[[Jurchen_script#History]]

Page xix

http://books.google.com/books?id=fdAOAAAAQAAJ&amp;pg=PR19&amp;dq=The+use+of+these+alphabets+seem+to+have+outlived+the+dynasty,+for+a+college+was+established+the+special+study+of+the+in+1407,+during+the+Ming&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=AaxWU7OTM9PEsATz84GoBQ&amp;ved=0CCkQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=The%20use%20of%20these%20alphabets%20seem%20to%20have%20outlived%20the%20dynasty%2C%20for%20a%20college%20was%20established%20the%20special%20study%20of%20the%20in%201407%2C%20during%20the%20Ming&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=v6k-AAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PR19&amp;dq=The+use+of+these+alphabets+seem+to+have+outlived+the+dynasty,+for+a+college+was+established+the+special+study+of+the+in+1407,+during+the+Ming&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=AaxWU7OTM9PEsATz84GoBQ&amp;ved=0CC8Q6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=The%20use%20of%20these%20alphabets%20seem%20to%20have%20outlived%20the%20dynasty%2C%20for%20a%20college%20was%20established%20the%20special%20study%20of%20the%20in%201407%2C%20during%20the%20Ming&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=Smk_AAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA168#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=jCxPAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA168#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=jCxPAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA168&amp;dq=Ming+dynasty+Government+schools+taught+Siamese,+Burmese,+Persian,+Turki,+Tibetan,+and+two+dialects+of+the+south-western+tribes.&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=70BSU_yxKva2sATdEw&amp;ved=0CCsQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=Ming%20dynasty%20Government%20schools%20taught%20Siamese%2C%20Burmese%2C%20Persian%2C%20Turki%2C%20Tibetan%2C%20and%20two%20dialects%20of%20the%20south-western%20tribes.&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=Smk_AAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA168&amp;dq=Ming+dynasty+Government+schools+taught+Siamese,+Burmese,+Persian,+Turki,+Tibetan,+and+two+dialects+of+the+south-western+tribes.&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=70BSU_yxKva2sATdEw&amp;ved=0CDEQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Ming%20dynasty%20Government%20schools%20taught%20Siamese%2C%20Burmese%2C%20Persian%2C%20Turki%2C%20Tibetan%2C%20and%20two%20dialects%20of%20the%20south-western%20tribes.&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=AS4BAAAAQAAJ&amp;pg=PA168&amp;dq=Ming+dynasty+Government+schools+taught+Siamese,+Burmese,+Persian,+Turki,+Tibetan,+and+two+dialects+of+the+south-western+tribes.&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=70BSU_yxKva2sATdEw&amp;ved=0CDcQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q=Ming%20dynasty%20Government%20schools%20taught%20Siamese%2C%20Burmese%2C%20Persian%2C%20Turki%2C%20Tibetan%2C%20and%20two%20dialects%20of%20the%20south-western%20tribes.&amp;f=false

Page 168

http://books.google.com/books?id=w0kMAAAAIAAJ&amp;q=Ming+dynasty+Government+schools+taught+Siamese,+Burmese,+Persian,+Turki,+Tibetan,+and+two+dialects+of+the+south-western+tribes.&amp;dq=Ming+dynasty+Government+schools+taught+Siamese,+Burmese,+Persian,+Turki,+Tibetan,+and+two+dialects+of+the+south-western+tribes.&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=70BSU_yxKva2sATdEw&amp;ved=0CD0Q6AEwAw

http://books.google.com/books?id=cqc8VqybPI0C&amp;pg=PA83#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false

http://www.ritsumei.ac.jp/acd/cg/lt/rb/601/601PDF/aisin.pdf

http://books.google.com/books?id=dJd_uwAACAAJ

http://www.omniglot.com/writing/jurchen.htm

http://www.iranicaonline.org/articles/chinese-iranian-ix

http://www.iranicaonline.org/articles/chinese-iranian-viii

http://books.google.com/books?id=WbgRAQAAMAAJ

http://books.google.com/books?id=7WpJAQAAIAAJ

http://books.google.com/books?id=pZbiZwEACAAJ

http://books.google.com/books?id=NYFBtTUZFxEC&amp;pg=PA395#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?ei=oH33UMK8N4KR0QGP7IHQAg&amp;id=Fqc2AQAAIAAJ&amp;dq=回回+語&amp;q=回回館譯語#search_anchor

http://books.google.com/books?id=-9_coC0dptgC&amp;pg=PT91#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=bYhj_2Yo2OUC&amp;pg=PA100&amp;dq=Mongolian+persian+burmese+thai+jurchen&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=-ElIU7HfA4LfsAS2yICQDQ&amp;ved=0CDUQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=Mongolian%20persian%20burmese%20thai%20jurchen&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=9MouAQAAIAAJ&amp;q=were+offered+the+opportunity+to+learn+many+languages+(Tartar,+Jurchen,+Mongolian,+Turkish,+Tangut,+Persian,+Burmese+or+Thai).&amp;dq=were+offered+the+opportunity+to+learn+many+languages+(Tartar,+Jurchen,+Mongolian,+Turkish,+Tangut,+Persian,+Burmese+or+Thai).&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=FUtIU9WfIPLLsQSEmIKYDQ&amp;ved=0CDAQ6AEwAQ

http://books.google.com/books?id=rdotAAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA260&amp;dq=Mongolian+persian+burmese+thai+jurchen&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=-ElIU7HfA4LfsAS2yICQDQ&amp;ved=0CDoQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Mongolian%20persian%20burmese%20thai%20jurchen&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=JWpF-dObxW8C&amp;pg=PA1441&amp;dq=Mongolian+persian+burmese+thai+jurchen&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=-ElIU7HfA4LfsAS2yICQDQ&amp;ved=0CEYQ6AEwAw#v=onepage&amp;q=Mongolian%20persian%20burmese%20thai%20jurchen&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=rQsOAQAAMAAJ&amp;q=Mongolian+persian+burmese+thai+jurchen&amp;dq=Mongolian+persian+burmese+thai+jurchen&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=nUpIU_PnI9DnsAT7iYH4Bg&amp;ved=0CC4Q6AEwADgK

http://books.google.com/books?id=iYluAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=Mongolian+persian+burmese+thai+jurchen&amp;dq=Mongolian+persian+burmese+thai+jurchen&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=nUpIU_PnI9DnsAT7iYH4Bg&amp;ved=0CDIQ6AEwATgK

http://books.google.com/books?id=xtARAQAAMAAJ&amp;q=The+Asian+Institute+was+founded+in+1407,+and+included+in+it+were+eight+schools+for+eight+languages,+namely,+Da+Da(Mongolian),+Nu+Zhi+(Jurchen),+Hui+Hui+(Persian)+,+Xi+Fan+(Tibetan),+Xi+Tian+(Hindi),+Bai+Yi+(Thai),+Gao-+chang+(Qocho,+Uighur)+...&amp;dq=The+Asian+Institute+was+founded+in+1407,+and+included+in+it+were+eight+schools+for+eight+languages,+namely,+Da+Da(Mongolian),+Nu+Zhi+(Jurchen),+Hui+Hui+(Persian)+,+Xi+Fan+(Tibetan),+Xi+Tian+(Hindi),+Bai+Yi+(Thai),+Gao-+chang+(Qocho,+Uighur)+...&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=n0tIU-nGEpW0sATQioDgCQ&amp;ved=0CCsQ6AEwAA

Siyi guan College of Translators and Thai language

http://books.google.com/books?id=Ka6jNJcX_ygC&amp;pg=PA149#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=aU5hBMxNgWQC&amp;pg=PA198#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false

Chinese and salar language primers of persian and arabic.

http://books.google.com/books?id=ciShtCrJijIC&amp;pg=PA18#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false

http://93.17.52.30/crlao/recherche.php?terme=522&amp;kwrefs=oui

http://books.google.com/books?id=J28qAAAACAAJ&amp;source=gbs_similarbooks

http://doktori.btk.elte.hu/lingv/apatoczky/diss.pdf

http://www.worldcat.org/title/yiyu-yi-yu-beilu-yiyu-bei-lu-yi-yu-an-indexed-critical-edition-of-a-sixteenth-century-sino-mongolian-glossary/oclc/149482741

http://www.for.aichi-pu.ac.jp/museum/pdf/takekoshi43.pdf

http://las.sinica.edu.tw/search~S0*cht?/a%7B21542b%7D%7B214943%7D%7B21615c%7D%7B214f7a%7D%7B21472a%7D%7B215e7a%7D/a%7B21542b%7D%7B214943%7D%7B21615c%7D%7B214f7a%7D%7B21472a%7D%7B215e7a%7D%7B214561%7D%7B213b33%7D%7B21522f%7D+%7B21515b%7D/-3%2C-1%2C0%2CB/frameset&amp;FF=a%7B21542b%7D%7B215277%7D%7B21376f%7D%7B21605b%7D%7B21334b%7D%7B214a48%7D%7B214e61%7D+%7B215b4d%7D&amp;1%2C1%2C

http://w3.uniroma1.it/santangelo/sao_file/ming_qing_yanjiu.pdf

http://books.google.com/books?id=BwuSpFiOFfYC&amp;pg=PA156#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=xrGAXH_ne4IC&amp;pg=PA1042#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false

[[User:Rajmaan|Rajmaan]] ([[User talk:Rajmaan|talk]]) 07:08, 14 May 2014 (UTC)

==Islamic astronomy in ming china==

http://books.google.com/books?id=iA1ZAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA107&amp;dq=Hui+hui+astronomy&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=LYvDULHULKXV0gH8lIDwCQ&amp;ved=0CDgQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q=Hui%20hui%20astronomy&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=-UhVAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA107&amp;dq=Hui+hui+astronomy&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=LYvDULHULKXV0gH8lIDwCQ&amp;ved=0CDsQ6AEwAw#v=onepage&amp;q=Hui%20hui%20astronomy&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=BwuSpFiOFfYC&amp;pg=PA36&amp;dq=Hui+hui+astronomy&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=LYvDULHULKXV0gH8lIDwCQ&amp;ved=0CEQQ6AEwBg#v=onepage&amp;q=Hui%20hui%20astronomy&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=jqb7L-pKCV8C&amp;pg=PA382&amp;dq=Hui+hui+astronomy&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=LYvDULHULKXV0gH8lIDwCQ&amp;ved=0CEcQ6AEwBw#v=onepage&amp;q=Hui%20hui%20astronomy&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=pXLO2k1oaPsC&amp;pg=PA160&amp;dq=Hui+hui+astronomy&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=LYvDULHULKXV0gH8lIDwCQ&amp;ved=0CE0Q6AEwCQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Hui%20hui%20astronomy&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=cEfiZlUpI5oC&amp;pg=PA27&amp;dq=Hui+hui+astronomy&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=LYvDULHULKXV0gH8lIDwCQ&amp;ved=0CDIQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=Hui%20hui%20astronomy&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=wV0NHaVG0-sC&amp;pg=PA223&amp;dq=Hui+hui+astronomy&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=MozDULKuLKjE0AGR9IHgBQ&amp;ved=0CC8Q6AEwADgK#v=onepage&amp;q=Hui%20hui%20astronomy&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=BxrVIMubOikC&amp;pg=PA24&amp;dq=Hui+hui+astronomy&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=MozDULKuLKjE0AGR9IHgBQ&amp;ved=0CDUQ6AEwAjgK#v=onepage&amp;q=Hui%20hui%20astronomy&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=RrPJVT-FunMC&amp;pg=PA284&amp;dq=Hui+hui+astronomy&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=MozDULKuLKjE0AGR9IHgBQ&amp;ved=0CEQQ6AEwBzgK#v=onepage&amp;q=Hui%20hui%20astronomy&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=8hOgAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA457&amp;dq=Hui+hui+astronomy&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=MozDULKuLKjE0AGR9IHgBQ&amp;ved=0CDsQ6AEwBDgK#v=onepage&amp;q=Hui%20hui%20astronomy&amp;f=false

Page 33 and 34

http://books.google.com/books?id=gu5VAAAAYAAJ&amp;q=Hui+hui+astronomy&amp;dq=Hui+hui+astronomy&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=MozDULKuLKjE0AGR9IHgBQ&amp;ved=0CEEQ6AEwBjgK


http://books.google.com/books?id=SQWW7QgUH4gC&amp;pg=PA510&amp;dq=Hui+hui+astronomy&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=MozDULKuLKjE0AGR9IHgBQ&amp;ved=0CDgQ6AEwAzgK#v=onepage&amp;q=Hui%20hui%20astronomy&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=1emXJemW-jgC&amp;pg=PT990&amp;dq=Hui+hui+astronomy&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=MozDULKuLKjE0AGR9IHgBQ&amp;ved=0CDIQ6AEwATgK

http://books.google.com/books?id=XULERYYEJo0C&amp;pg=PA22&amp;dq=Hui+hui+astronomy&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=LYvDULHULKXV0gH8lIDwCQ&amp;ved=0CEEQ6AEwBQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Hui%20hui%20astronomy&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=GNpdcKMZyg0C&amp;pg=PA148&amp;dq=Hui+hui+astronomy&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=LYvDULHULKXV0gH8lIDwCQ&amp;ved=0CD4Q6AEwBA#v=onepage&amp;q=Hui%20hui%20astronomy&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=gQYscrT0fgQC&amp;pg=PA697&amp;dq=Hui+hui+astronomy&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=LYvDULHULKXV0gH8lIDwCQ&amp;ved=0CDUQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Hui%20hui%20astronomy&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=raKRY3KQspsC&amp;pg=PA454&amp;dq=Hui+hui+astronomy&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=LYvDULHULKXV0gH8lIDwCQ&amp;ved=0CEoQ6AEwCA#v=onepage&amp;q=Hui%20hui%20astronomy&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=iFxGpHGMAZQC&amp;pg=PA125&amp;dq=Hui+hui+astronomy&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=MozDULKuLKjE0AGR9IHgBQ&amp;ved=0CEcQ6AEwCDgK#v=onepage&amp;q=Hui%20hui%20astronomy&amp;f=false

http://books.google.com/books?id=iN9Tdfdap5MC&amp;pg=PA451&amp;dq=Hui+hui+astronomy&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=MozDULKuLKjE0AGR9IHgBQ&amp;ved=0CEoQ6AEwCTgK#v=onepage&amp;q=Hui%20hui%20astronomy&amp;f=false

Zheng He voyages

http://www.ari.nus.edu.sg/docs/wps/wps04_031.pdf

Ryukyu in the Ming Reign Annals 1380s-1580s 

Geoff Wade

http://poseidon01.ssrn.com/delivery.php?ID=687101067008100018024029007076087090096055058047023043031089013109086107029088030121061053000000033097052119077127031016096065009094010045014112119009115125078014001067043087096029020112083122095081110125&amp;EXT=pdf

[[User:Rajmaan|Rajmaan]] ([[User talk:Rajmaan|talk]]) 21:49, 5 May 2014 (UTC)

== Da Ming Lü (Great Ming Code) ==

http://books.google.com/books?id=RV6WqcAY3zwC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_ge_summary_r&amp;cad=0#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false

17:35, 3 September 2013 (UTC)

== Edit request on 30 September 2013 ==

{{edit semi-protected|&lt;!-- Page to be edited --&gt;|answered=yes}}
&lt;!-- Begin request --&gt;
The wikipage referred for Wen Zhen is wrong as it refers to a Communist Party leader.
Check the disambiguation  page for 
Wang Zhen (eunuch).
&lt;!-- End request --&gt;
[[Special:Contributions/173.176.120.156|173.176.120.156]] ([[User talk:173.176.120.156|talk]]) 22:48, 30 September 2013 (UTC)

:[[File:Red question icon with gradient background.svg|20px|link=|alt=]] '''Not done:''' please be more specific about what needs to be changed.&lt;!-- Template:ESp --&gt; I don't see that link in the article. (The closest I can find is a link to [[Wen Zhengming]].) Could you please be more specific about the location of the problem? [[User:Rivertorch|Rivertorch]] ([[User talk:Rivertorch|talk]]) 04:25, 3 October 2013 (UTC)

== Ming capitals? ==

&quot;Nanjing (Yingtian prefecture)
(1368–'''1644''')[1]
Beijing (Shuntian prefecture)
(1403–1644)&quot;

Shouldn't it be
&quot;Nanjing (Yingtian prefecture)
(1368–'''1403''')[1]
Beijing (Shuntian prefecture)
(1403–1644)&quot;?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/209.29.23.129|209.29.23.129]] ([[User talk:209.29.23.129|talk]]) 00:18, 19 December 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Mongol Chinese relations during the Ming ==

Mongols in the nobility and military of Ming dynasty China

http://www.jstor.org/stable/2718543

CHINESE IN SOUTHERN MONGOLIA DURING THE SIXTEENTH CENTURY

http://www.jstor.org/stable/40726017

A MONGOL SETTLEMENT IN NORTH CHINA AT THE END OF THE 16TH CENTURY

http://www.jstor.org/stable/41926456

THE MONGOLS IN CHINA : 1400-1450

http://www.jstor.org/stable/40725869

The Ming used Mongols in its military to fight in most of its wars, including crushing rebellions by southern ethnic minorities such as the Li in Hainan

Politics, Force and Ethnicity in Ming China: Mongols and the Abortive Coup of 1461

http://www.jstor.org/stable/2652684?seq=5

Images of Subject Mongols Under the Ming Dynasty

http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/late/summary/v025/25.1robinson.html

[[User:Rajmaan|Rajmaan]] ([[User talk:Rajmaan|talk]]) 17:06, 3 May 2014 (UTC)

==Move discussion in progress==
There is a move discussion in progress on [[Talk:Han Dynasty#Han Dynasty to Han dynasty |Talk:Han Dynasty]] which affects this page. Please participate on that page and not in this talk page section. Thank you. &lt;!-- Talk:Han Dynasty crosspost --&gt; —[[User:RMCD bot|RMCD bot]] 13:28, 14 March 2014 (UTC)

== List of present day countries that were part of the Ming Empire ==

The article clearly states quite a few successful Ming military campaigns in present day Mongolia. Why is Mongolia not included on the above said list? It needs to be included! Also, Taiwan is not a country, it is not officially recognized by the United Nations. As far as official may be concerned, Taiwan is a part of China, so it is absolutely ludicrous to place it on the list. It is redundant, because the official KMT government of the self proclaimed &quot;legitamate country of Republic of China&quot; actually claims mainland China as well, so either way, whether or not Taiwan is a country actually doesn't even matter. By both governments claims, Taiwan is a province of China. So don't put Taiwan on the list, its the same as putting two Chinas. [[User:Aslanofnarnia7|Aslanofnarnia7]] ([[User talk:Aslanofnarnia7|talk]]) 05:33, 23 March 2014 (UTC)

:@{{u|Aslanofnarnia7}} – There's a simpler reason why Taiwan should be removed: the Ming never controlled it! And just to confirm: by &quot;the above said list&quot;, do you mean the &quot;Today part of&quot; section of the infobox? [[User:Madalibi|Madalibi]] ([[User talk:Madalibi|talk]]) 06:03, 23 March 2014 (UTC)
::The Ming never controlled the island of Taiwan, but it indeed controlled [[Penghu]] (Pescadores), at least for many decades. [http://books.google.com/books?id=A8Yv6B0q-hkC&amp;pg=PA221 This book] mentions that &quot;Li sent Zheng, who probably had been a leader in one of the Chinese settlements on Taiwan, to persuade the Duth to withdraw from the Pescadores, '''which were part of the Ming Empire''', to Taiwan, which was not&quot;. Today Penghu is part of ROC or Taiwan, so &quot;Ming controlled territory that are part of Taiwan&quot; may be true as well. --[[User:Cartstyle|Cartstyle]] ([[User talk:Cartstyle|talk]]) 15:57, 25 March 2014 (UTC)

Yes, Madalibi, I am referring to the &quot;Today part of&quot; section of the infobox. So what is your opinion on the Mongolia issue? I still am quite convinced that at some point or other in time the Ming Empire controlled it. [[User:Aslanofnarnia7|Aslanofnarnia7]] ([[User talk:Aslanofnarnia7|talk]]) 04:30, 25 March 2014 (UTC)

:@{{u|Aslanofnarnia7}} – Hmmm, it's true that the [[Yongle Emperor]] led [[Yongle Emperor's campaigns against the Mongols|five large-scale campaigns into Mongol territory]], and made the Mongols fear China's military might, but each campaign lasted only a few months, and none produced lasting results. After Yongle died in 1424, his successors never tried to attack the Mongols again. This means that the territory that is now modern [[Mongolia]] was never under secure Ming control for more than a few weeks, perhaps a few months. [[Tan Qixiang]]'s ''[[Historical Atlas of China (1982)|Historical Atlas of China]]'' 中国历史地图集 (1982), which usually gives a rather &quot;optimistic&quot; view of China's territory, also doesn't include Mongolia into the Ming realm (see volume 7). For these two reasons – known historical events and a [[WP:RS|reliable source]] that is sympathetic to modern Chinese territorial claims yet doesn't include Mongolia in Ming territory – I would say we shouldn't include Mongolia in the &quot;Today part of&quot; section of the infobox. [[User:Madalibi|Madalibi]] ([[User talk:Madalibi|talk]]) 07:10, 25 March 2014 (UTC)

== Semi-protected edit request on 14 April 2014 ==

{{edit semi-protected|answered=yes}}
&lt;!-- Begin request --&gt;
I propose moving a line about the 1556 Shaanxi Earthquake to earlier in its subsection (&quot;Decline and Fall of the Ming Dynasty&quot;), and adding a few lines as to why that event was significant.  Probably better would be framing it with a new subsection I propose below.

Line To Move:  &quot;The deadliest earthquake of all time, the Shaanxi earthquake of 1556, occurred during the Jiajing Emperor's reign, killing approximately 830,000 people.[64]&quot;

Reasons:
1)  At its current location, it is misplaced with events from a century later.  This is probably the results of previous edits of the article.
2)  Logically, the earthquake can be seen as related to the fall of the dynasty, but it is more like part of the &quot;beginning of the end&quot;; an early event in what was a long decline.  An examination of the article &quot;Jiajing Emperor&quot; (http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jiajing_Emperor) supports this notion, as his 1507-1567 rule seems to set the pattern for the end of the Ming.  The earthquake comes near the end of that period as that emperor became increasingly disengaged from rule.
3)  The article &quot;Fall of the Ming Dynasty&quot; (https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fall_of_the_Ming_dynasty), referenced right after the section heading &quot;Decline and Fall of the Ming Dynasty&quot;, appears to be a stub article and makes a much less compelling argument than &quot;Jiajing Emperor&quot; that the decline began around 1600.  This claim seems contradicted by the sentence I am proposing to move, the information in &quot;Jiajing Emperor&quot; and the information immediately following the reference in the subsections &quot;Reign of the Wanli Emperor&quot; and &quot;Role of the Eunuchs.&quot;
4)  The sentence I propose moving needs a bit of context, all of which is found in &quot;Jiajing Emperor.&quot;  Otherwise it is just a meaningless factoid hanging out there.

Proposed New Subsection with Moved Line:

[Inserted after &quot;Decline and fall of the Ming dynasty
                    Main article: Fall of the Ming dynasty&quot;]

The Era of Tranquility and the Seeds of Decline
   Main articles:  &quot;Jiajing Emperor&quot; (http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jiajing_Emperor)
                   &quot;1556 Shaanxi Earthquake&quot; (https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1556_Shaanxi_earthquake)
The Jiajing Emperor presided over China for forty-five years (1521-1567), successfully enough that the period was era-named &quot;Admirable Tranquility.&quot;  However, his increasing inattention to governmental affairs as time went on is cited as setting patterns that would be disastrously followed by his successors.  While he was focused on religious issues and personal pursuits, he cut himself off to access by his ministers and people.  Control of governmental affairs devolved to less capable persons of influence and court eunuchs even as the state was faced with serious challenges.  The last twenty-five years of his reign saw harassment and invasions by Mongols from the north, country-wide dissent over spending on Taoist temples, and serious piracy along the southeastern coastlines.  Compounding these were the long-term economic effects of natural disaster.  The deadliest earthquake of all time, the Shaanxi earthquake of 1556, occurred during the Jiajing Emperor's reign, killing approximately 830,000 people.

&lt;!-- End request --&gt;
[[User:MikePaulC|MikePaulC]] ([[User talk:MikePaulC|talk]]) 19:19, 14 April 2014 (UTC)

:Hi {{u|MikePaulC|Mike}}, and thanks for this well thought-out proposal! Even if [[Ming dynasty]] is already a &quot;[[WP:FA|featured article]]&quot; (that is, one of the best on Wikipedia), it can still be improved, and I think your proposal does just that. Among other things, it makes me notice that Ming history from the 1460s to the 1570s is not discussed at all! So I like your new text. All we are missing are references to [[WP:RS|reliable sources]] to support all the claims it makes. Do you have access (including online) to such sources? Would you like to add the references yourself or do you need assistance? If you're not sure how to add footnotes, just click &quot;Edit&quot; anywhere in the text and see how it's done. (The semi-protection will be lifted once you've performed a total of ten edits.) Two details: common names in subtitles shouldn't be capitalized (see [[WP:SECTIONCAPS]]); and the [[Chinese era name|reign title]] &quot;Jiajing&quot; was chosen when that emperor ascended the throne, so it can't be seen as a comment on his ruling style. Cheers! [[User:Madalibi|Madalibi]] ([[User talk:Madalibi|talk]]) 08:16, 16 April 2014 (UTC)
:[[File:Red information icon with gradient background.svg|20px|link=]] '''Not done:''' please provide [[WP:RS|reliable sources]] that support the change you want to be made.&lt;!-- Template:ESp --&gt; — &lt;span class=&quot;nowrap&quot;&gt;&amp;#123;&amp;#123;U&amp;#124;[[User:Technical 13|Technical 13]]&amp;#125;&amp;#125;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:Technical 13|t]] • [[Special:EmailUser/Technical 13|e]] • [[Special:Contribs/Technical 13|c]])&lt;/sup&gt; 13:42, 27 April 2014 (UTC)

== Semi-protected edit request on 16 April 2014 ==

{{edit semi-protected|&lt;!-- Page to be edited --&gt;|answered=yes}}
&lt;!-- Begin request --&gt;
Under &quot;Society and culture,&quot; the first word of the first sentence (&quot;literature&quot;) should be capitalized.
&lt;!-- End request --&gt;
[[User:Asadron|Asadron]] ([[User talk:Asadron|talk]]) 07:17, 16 April 2014 (UTC)

:Done! Thanks for pointing this out, {{u|Asadron}}. [[User:Madalibi|Madalibi]] ([[User talk:Madalibi|talk]]) 08:42, 16 April 2014 (UTC)

== Maps ==
Империя Мин
[[File:Ming Empire cca 1580 (en).svg|thumb|map of 1580]]
[[File:Ming Dynasty 1415.png|thumb|map of 1415]]
[[File:Ming foreign relations 1580.jpg|thumb|map of 1580]]

[[File:Ming-Empire2.jpg|thumb|Harvard University Press Atlas published this map in ''History and Commercial Atlas of China'']]

[[File:Nouvelle-France_map-en.svg|thumb|[[Louisiana (New France)]]- '''only 200 French troops were stationed in the entire area several times, with tens of thousands of Native Americans surrounding them''']]

[[File:Mississippi River basin.jpg|thumb|Entire Mississippi River basin claimed by France]]

[[File:New Spain.svg|thumb|[[New Spain]] - a few missions and priests in California counts as control]]

[[File:NorthAmerica1762-83.png|thumb|Britain shown as controlling everything east of the Missisipi]]

[[File:Frank_bond_1912_louisiana_and_the_louisiana_purchase.jpg|thumb|[[American Indian Wars|America had to fight for over 100 years to actually subdue the natives and rule over all the land they &quot;claimed&quot; to own]].]]

I recently added the 1580 map (on the right) to this article. As my addition of the 1580 map was twice reverted by [[User:Bloodyducklips]] I like the give my reasoning here before I do another revert. 

In my opinion the 1580 map, made by capable Czech editors, is vastly superior to the old 1415 map. It has a lot of details (Great Wall, provincial capitals, main roads, names of surrounding nations) and is esthetically more appealing. 

The 1415 map has issues in my opinion. The extension of the Ming empire in the northeast all the way to the [[Sea of Okhotsk]] is misleading. According to Dardess, John W. (2011) ''Ming China, 1368-1644 A Concise History of a Resilient Empire'', page 18, the Yongle emperor in 1411 send some troops, measuring around 1,000 men, to this region. They built some forts and a Buddhist temple (which was destroyed by locals a few years later) and gave local chiefs a Ming title. Ming influence was limited and only for a couple of years. This was never a integrated part of the Ming empire. 

Regards, [[User:Joplin|Joplin]] ([[User talk:Joplin|talk]]) 19:55, 3 October 2014 (UTC)

: I don't think using a map of an Empire which is near her doom is suitable. This is similar as using a map showing the Eastern Roman Empire which is under the Turkics' attack. The misleading part is that you just use a small map instead of a map showing the greatest extent of an empire. I suggest you use the map in early 15th century.--'''[[User:Alvin Lee|Alvin]]'''  ''[[User talk:Alvin Lee|Lee]]'' 13:51, 11 January 2015 (UTC)
: Moreover, the 1415 map was similar to the map made by [[Harvard–Yenching Institute]], &quot;Historical and commercial atlas of China&quot; (1935). I believe it is a reliable source.--'''[[User:Alvin Lee|Alvin]]'''  ''[[User talk:Alvin Lee|Lee]]'' 13:44, 13 January 2015 (UTC)

::Extent of the Ming ended in the 15th century but the Ming state existed in 1368-1644. [[User:Andequer|Andequer]] ([[User talk:Andequer|talk]]) 04:48, 14 January 2015 (UTC)
:::That is the point. The map used should show the greatest extent of the Ming, in order to let readers to know the influence of the Empire.--'''[[User:Alvin Lee|Alvin]]'''  ''[[User talk:Alvin Lee|Lee]]'' 06:51, 14 January 2015 (UTC)
:::: I would not say that 1580 was Ming near its doom. A map of that time would be effectively the maximum extent of the Ming. It wasn't until towards the end of the Wanli Emperor's rule that a decline could be noted. I suspect the 1415 map date was chosen so as to include Yongle's north east expedition but i agree with Jopin that that expedition doesn't count as bringing the far north east into Ming control. If we went down that route then we would have to include the places that Zhenghe's treasure ships landed too. [[User:Rincewind42|Rincewind42]] ([[User talk:Rincewind42|talk]]) 16:10, 14 January 2015 (UTC)
:::::I agree with Joplin &amp; Rincewind that the 1580 map is both more handsome and more useful in its clear presentation of important features. The map also shows gradual shading of the borderlands, which is more faithful to the historical reality that there were no sharply defined borders. 1580 is probably the height of Ming in terms of culture and economy, so it is as good a date as any and better than most.
:::::Could we find an appropriate place later in the article for the 1415 map?[[User:CWH|ch]] ([[User talk:CWH|talk]]) 18:03, 14 January 2015 (UTC)

::::::{{u|Rincewind42}} {{u|Joplin}}'s claim that the 1415 map is misleading is incorrect. The map was not made by a random user's imagination [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Ming-Empire2.jpg but based exactly off this map in a book by Harvard University Press]. '''The building of a few forts and stationing a couple of troops in areas with tribal natives is in most cases taken as an acceptable basis for claims of sovereignty by most historians. The same thing is shown for the Russian Empire during the expansion into [[Siberia]]. Just a few hundred Russian Cossacks put up a few forts like [[Albazin]] and suddenly claimed the entire area for the Russian Empire, while vast stretches of the land were empty or controlled by native tribes. The same thing is portrayed on maps of America during the early 19th century- when America made the [[Louisiana Purchase]] from France and claimed the [[Oregon Territory]], for many years when it officially &quot;owned&quot; the territories, in fact there were just a few forts and a few American army troops stationed with the government signing treaties with the local Native American tribes, who wielded actual control over the area. Same thing when France owned [[Louisiana (New France)]]- essentially France claimed a massive gigantic piece of land, but actually what they had were only a few forts and a couple of troops and recognized the local Native American chiefs titles. At times only 200 French troops were stationed in the entire area with tens of thousands of Native Americans. I've seen western history books and they all show the entire piece of Louisiana all the way from Montana down to the Mississippi as blue colored and under French control. To think that it was actually under their rule is a massive joke. Same thing with [[New Spain]]. Spain only had a few forts and missions in California, basically some missions only had a couple of Spanish Priests and nothing else, yet historians color the entire area as under Spanish rule despite Native Americans being in actual control. Same thing with British colonial America. They only had a few forts in the Ohio River Valley and other areas, with Natives controlling most of the land, yet everything east of the Mississippi is colored red for British on colonial maps''' Why is there a different standard for China and for European nations? The Yongle Emperor sent [[Yishiha]] to set up the '''[[Nurgan Regional Military Commission]] 奴兒干都指揮使司''' in the area which is essentially the same as what Europeans did when they established colonies in America. The destroyed temple was rebuilt, see [[Yongning Temple Stele]]. It says [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Ming-Empire2.jpg Nurkan (Nurgan) right in that area next to the Sea of Okhotsk where it is part of the Ming on the Harvard University Press map]. Nurgan was the administrative name of the area when it was under Ming rule. '''Zheng He never set up an administrative seat like the Nurgan Regional Military Commission in any areas he went to. Your logic comparing Yishiha and Zheng He's voyages is a [[straw man]] argument, this is like comparing [[Henry Hudson]] to [[Humphrey Gilbert]], and saying since Henry Hudson went exploring but didn't establish any colonies for Britain, that Gilbert didn't establish any colonies either and [[St. John's, Newfoundland and Labrador]] was never part of the British Empire.''' If you insist on the 1415 map as illegitimate, we must delete all the maps of New Spain, New France, and colonial America on the grounds that they are all misleading and were never an &quot;integrated part&quot; of those nations.[[User:Rajmaan|Rajmaan]] ([[User talk:Rajmaan|talk]]) 19:31, 14 January 2015 (UTC)

::::::'''And the Qing control of the region was essentially the same as the Ming- the Qing Emperors only maintained a tiny amount of tribal Evenk, Daur, Oroqen and other Bannermen to guard the area from Russian incursions, leaving the Evenks, Daurs, Oroqen and others under the control of their native chiefs, and left it largely to themselves and mostly empty, with few administrative structures. So in 1858 Russia was able to walk in with its Cossacks and settlers and openly seize the area during the [[Treaty of Aigun]].'''[[User:Rajmaan|Rajmaan]] ([[User talk:Rajmaan|talk]]) 19:39, 14 January 2015 (UTC)

&lt;blockquote&gt;'''&quot;At times, fewer than two hundred [French] soldiers were assigned to all of the colony, on both sides of the Mississippi. In the mid-1720s, Louisiana had some 2,500 French, plus 1,500 slaves. In contrast, Louisiana Indians numbered well over 35,000.&quot;'''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uga.edu/colonialseminar/DuVal.pdf Kathleen DuVall, &quot;Interconnectedness and Diversity in 'French Louisiana'&quot;, in ''Powhatan's Mantle: Indians in the Colonial Southeast'', ed. Gregory A. Waselkov, Peter H. Wood, and M. Thomas Hatley, Lincoln, NE: University of Nebraska Press, 2nd edition, 2006, accessed 28 May 2010]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

::Finally, someone do agree that Nurgan Regional Military Commission was the territory of Ming. And there are several expansions in early 15th century which no longer under Ming's control in late 16th century, such as Annam and territories to the north of the Ming Great Wall.--'''[[User:Alvin Lee|Alvin]]'''  ''[[User talk:Alvin Lee|Lee]]'' 01:39, 15 January 2015 (UTC)
:::Moreover, the map used should show the greatest extent of an Empire, in order to reflect her influence and military strength. Both &quot;economy&quot; and &quot;culture&quot; cannot be reflected from that map, thus this is NOT a valid point.--'''[[User:Alvin Lee|Alvin]]'''  ''[[User talk:Alvin Lee|Lee]]'' 01:42, 15 January 2015 (UTC)

:::Also [[Hami Prefecture]] and the [[Ordos Loop]] were both ruled by the Yongle Emperor along with Annam and much of Inner Mongolia and &quot;Manchuria&quot;, and were lost by the 16th century.[[User:Rajmaan|Rajmaan]] ([[User talk:Rajmaan|talk]]) 04:22, 15 January 2015 (UTC)
::::Indeed. So please use the greatest extent map to show the power of the Empire.--'''[[User:Alvin Lee|Alvin]]'''  ''[[User talk:Alvin Lee|Lee]]'' 04:30, 15 January 2015 (UTC)

:::The discussion of North America is off-topic – we should follow reliable historians of China.  The ''History and Commercial Atlas of China'' (1935), published by the Harvard-Yenching Institute but written by [[Albert Herrmann]], is considered dated nowadays.  In particular modern authors would not include the expanse to the north, because Yongle's campaigns failed to establish control of the area.
:::I disagree with the dictum that the infobox map must show the empire at its greatest extent.  The objective of the map in the infobox is to give readers an impression of the extent of the empire.  A map that depicts borders that were stable for three quarters of the period of the dynasty does this better than one based on short-lived, unsustainable and partial control, such as Yongle's disastrous 20-year occupation of Annam.
:::Regarding the shading of the borders, I agree that it depicts an important reality in many areas, but it makes no sense at the coast, and there were well-defined parts of the boundary along the Great Wall and for much of the border with Annam.  [[User talk:Kanguole|Kanguole]] 09:59, 15 January 2015 (UTC)
The Ming state began to lose their invaded territories since mid-15th century. See [[Tumu Crisis]]. We need to clarify about border history of the Ming state. [[User:Andequer|Andequer]] ([[User talk:Andequer|talk]]) 13:33, 15 January 2015 (UTC)

:::If you claim its considered dated, then show us a modern map depicting the extent of Yongle's rule by an alternate historian instead of comparing it to the 1580 map. Yongle's occupation of Annam was not partial or unstable from 1407-1418, the Lam Son uprising only started after a decade of Yongle's rule. [[Hami Prefecture]] was under Ming sovereignty for decades in the 15th century and the Ming made a conscious decision to later to abandon the Ordos Loop when building the Great Wall in the 16th century. Most of eastern Qinghai was also under Ming rule before it was lost in the 16th century. And instead of citing unspecified &quot;modern authors&quot;, show us the actual sources. The Temple was rebult by Yishiha on his second expedition. The Cambridge History of China has an alternate map which shows a big piece of [https://books.google.com/books?id=tyhT9SZRLS8C&amp;pg=PR25#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Inner Mongolia north of Hebei as within the &quot;Early Ming frontier&quot;].[[User:Rajmaan|Rajmaan]] ([[User talk:Rajmaan|talk]]) 17:57, 15 January 2015 (UTC)

This book wrote by the Chinese writer: Yuan-Kang Wang, Harmony and War: Confucian Culture and Chinese Power Politics (Columbia University Press, 2013)

...This Tumu debacle marked a  turning point in Ming strategy toward the Mongols. It was the end of the era of offensive grand strategy and the last time the Chinese army went beyond the northern border ten masse to pursue the nomads. Instead, China withdrew from the steppe transition zone...the Mongols gradually moved in and used it as forward base to raid Chinese territory. In the second period (1450-1548), Ming power continued to decline. The number of soldiers required on the borders became insufficient, problems of desertion and low morale plagued the Ming military, domestic rebellions were on the rise, and factional conflicts crippled the Ming court. In contrast, the Mongols, aside from brief periods of internecine conflicts, were united under a series of able leaders and became increasingly powerful. They occupied the strategically vital Ordos and projected power from there...[[Dayan Khan]] settled in the [[Ordos]] in 1500 and used this fertile land as forward base to raid China. The next year, he led 100,000 cavaltymen and launched a major attack on Guyan and [[Ningxia]]. The Ming military was incapable of warding off Mongol attacks. [[User:Andequer|Andequer]] ([[User talk:Andequer|talk]]) 16:39, 17 January 2015 (UTC)

::::The map you've linked is a good example of what I mean.  You'll note that northeastern limit of the &quot;Early Ming frontier&quot; in that map is in the area of modern Shenyang, rather than near the mouth of the Amur.  [[User talk:Kanguole|Kanguole]] 01:00, 16 January 2015 (UTC)
:::::It is still missing both Hami, northeastern Qinghai and Annam, and the first two were part of the Ming for decades.[[User:Rajmaan|Rajmaan]] ([[User talk:Rajmaan|talk]]) 03:30, 16 January 2015 (UTC)
:::::'''The infobox map must show the empire at its greatest extent'''. Why Western empires uses maps showing their greatest extent, and this is not applicable for Chinese empires? Shouldn't all articles be unified? Allow me to use the example of Byzantine Empire:
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Justinian555AD.png|
File:ByzantineEmpire867AD4lightpurple.PNG|

&lt;/gallery&gt;
The territory of Byzantine Empire in AD 555 is in its greatest extent, but that does not last long. So why not use the map showing the territory held by the empire which was not controlled briefly? The AD 867 map should be more appropriate instead. --'''[[User:Alvin Lee|Alvin]]'''  ''[[User talk:Alvin Lee|Lee]]'' 03:15, 16 January 2015 (UTC)

::Despite your bold type, there is no such rule.  Focussing on a border around the greatest extent, including briefly-held and unsustainable possessions, gives a misleading impression of an ancient state.  Reliable sources tend to use maps of the typical territory when giving an overview (which is what the infobox is for).  There's no reason to follow the example of [[Byzantine Empire]].  [[User talk:Kanguole|Kanguole]] 00:55, 18 January 2015 (UTC)

:::So could you kindly explain why Byzantine Empire article uses a map that shows the greatest extent with many briefly-held and unsustainable possessions? Do not avoid my questions.--'''[[User:Alvin Lee|Alvin]]'''  ''[[User talk:Alvin Lee|Lee]]'' 08:20, 19 January 2015 (UTC)

:And could anyone explain why Annan and Nurgan should not be considered as territory? And for the boarders, why Western empires uses clear and specific boarders instead of the blur ones, and yet no one talked about it? --'''[[User:Alvin Lee|Alvin]]'''  ''[[User talk:Alvin Lee|Lee]]'' 01:17, 17 January 2015 (UTC)

::Kanguole needs to respond and prove that Nurgan was not a territory of the Ming if he wants to maintain the current map.[[User:Rajmaan|Rajmaan]] ([[User talk:Rajmaan|talk]]) 01:38, 17 January 2015 (UTC)

:::The ''Cambridge History'' that you pointed to shows that they don't consider Nurgan to have been Ming territory.  In the text, you'll find them saying that Yongle's campaigns didn't establish control over the regions they went through (and indeed the diversion of resources to them led to the abandonment of the &quot;Early Ming frontier&quot; marked on that map).  [[User talk:Kanguole|Kanguole]] 02:07, 17 January 2015 (UTC)
::::I already noted that the map is incorrect, it doesn't show Hami prefecture, a massive piece of northeastern Qinghai, nor Annam as part of the Ming in any point in time. I pointed to it as an &quot;alternate map&quot;, not a correct one.[[User:Rajmaan|Rajmaan]] ([[User talk:Rajmaan|talk]]) 04:45, 17 January 2015 (UTC)
:::::Still the ''Cambridge History'' is a particularly well-respected source.  There is a discussion of Hami and its relations with the early Ming on pages 247–249 and 215–254 of Volume 8, where Hami is described as a tributary state, but not governed by the Ming.  While the Ming did occupy Annam for 20 years, their hold was limited by a series of uprisings throughout that period (not just in the last 10 years).  It is hardly representatative of Ming territory.  [[User talk:Kanguole|Kanguole]] 00:55, 18 January 2015 (UTC)
::::::A source at [[Qara Del]] says Hami was turned into a Ming prefecture.[[User:Rajmaan|Rajmaan]] ([[User talk:Rajmaan|talk]]) 05:22, 18 January 2015 (UTC)
:::::::Temporarily. [[User:Andequer|Andequer]] ([[User talk:Andequer|talk]]) 09:17, 18 January 2015 (UTC)
:::::::I don't have access to that book at the moment, but I notice that the reference was originally attached to &quot;The Qara Del accepted the Ming supremacy to save its existence in 1404.&quot;[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Kara_Del&amp;oldid=459653641]  The addition &quot;and came under Ming control as [[Hami Prefecture]]&quot; came later from a different editor,[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Kara_Del&amp;diff=460195658&amp;oldid=460195067][http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Kara_Del&amp;diff=next&amp;oldid=460204310][http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Kara_Del&amp;diff=next&amp;oldid=460244868] who also added the claim (without a reference) to [[Hami Prefecture]].[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Hami_Prefecture&amp;diff=460247935&amp;oldid=447613135]  I'll check the book when I get a chance.  [[User talk:Kanguole|Kanguole]] 11:09, 18 January 2015 (UTC)
::::::Annan again. When a country controlled a territory which upising happens, you just don't consider that as its territory? Fabulous deduction! Many countries' greatest extent will not be considered as territory in your logic. So please, do not use such reasons to exclude territories of the empire. Also, you can't just ignore the 130 North East military posts. It seems that you are having a '''[[Double Standard]]''' on Eastern and Western countries. Please look at both of them fairly, not just saying &quot;We should not use greatest extent map for this article,&quot; while using greatest extent maps for Western countries.--'''[[User:Alvin Lee|Alvin]]'''  ''[[User talk:Alvin Lee|Lee]]'' 06:07, 18 January 2015 (UTC)

::::So please explain, how would Ming establish a Military Commission and about 130 military posts &quot;Wei-so&quot; 衛所 in North East, and yet has no power over them? Also, you still have yet respond to my doubts on Annan.--'''[[User:Alvin Lee|Alvin]]'''  ''[[User talk:Alvin Lee|Lee]]'' 04:39, 17 January 2015 (UTC)
According to Yuan-Kang Wang's book the Ming dynasty lost Inner Mongolia in the mid 15th century. [[User:Andequer|Andequer]] ([[User talk:Andequer|talk]]) 09:13, 18 January 2015 (UTC)

::::Didn't the Ming consciously decide to abandon the [[Ordos Loop]] to the Mongols and build the Great Wall at its southern end?[[User:Rajmaan|Rajmaan]] ([[User talk:Rajmaan|talk]]) 05:10, 3 May 2015 (UTC)

:::::{{u|Kanguole}} [https://books.google.com/books?id=DpeQhJ3hcwsC&amp;pg=PA70#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Alternative map].[[User:Rajmaan|Rajmaan]] ([[User talk:Rajmaan|talk]]) 03:34, 26 August 2015 (UTC)

:I would just like to add the map of 1424 from Chinese Wikipedia [[File:明成祖時期疆域.png|100px]], including the [[Jimi system]] areas, to this discussion. --&lt;span style=&quot;background: #003153; font-family: 'Helvetica Neue', Helvetica, FreeSans, 'Liberation Sans'; font-weight: 500; padding: 3px; border-radius: 2px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Emphrase|&lt;span style=&quot;color: white;&quot;&gt;Emphrase&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt; 03:02, 13 June 2016 (UTC)
{{reflist-talk}}

== Flag ==

I have a suggestion for use of a flag in the article.  As we all know, we will never know at the moment 100% of the flag accuracy for Ming dynasty China.  However, there is evidence of a certain flag that has been proposed to be authentic [http://accel21.mettre-put-idata.over-blog.com/0/00/57/47/voyages/nanjing-10-05/nanjing-039-zhonghuamen.jpg seen here] above this [http://accel92.mettre-put-idata.over-blog.com/0/00/57/47/voyages/nanjing-10-05/nanjing-028-zhonghuamen.jpg pass] at Nanjing.

Nanjing was the first capital of the Ming and considering it is only common sense that the Chinese would leave the flag above the gate if it had validity.  Who in this case would just leave a random flag up there? It's also quite popular in Ming dynasty portrayal in modern culture.

The flag has been modified for Wikimedia Commons in [https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Flag_of_Ming_Dynasty.svg this form] and in [https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Ming_Dynasty_Flag_(1368~1644).png this form] although the second version's border should be black.

I suggest this but I also suggest noting directly below it as I attempted to do in the recent history of the [[Yuan dynasty]] with the popular blue flag (with the white design in the middle) shown in modern day depictions of the Khan's Yuan Dynasty flag.  As long as we note DIRECTLY BELOW the flag, I don't see the problem with showing the depicted flag as they will know it isn't official but it is a popular depiction, etc.

Thoughts? Can we come to a conclusion? [[User talk:Kamek98|Eric - Contact me please. I prefer conversations started on my talk page if the subject is changed]] 02:01, 15 December 2014 (UTC)

::'''Update''' there is also a flag [https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:%E6%97%A5%E6%9C%88%E6%97%97.svg that was apparently used] to distinguish from the Portuguese. There is information found [http://baike.baidu.com/view/1172187.htm#1 here]. [[User talk:Kamek98|Eric - Contact me please. I prefer conversations started on my talk page if the subject is changed]] 02:19, 15 December 2014 (UTC)
:::All of those images have messages claiming something to the effect of &quot;this flag is fictitious&quot;. If you really want to use them then you need to provide reliable sources (which Baidu and personal observations aren't) [[User:Underbar dk|_dk]] ([[User talk:Underbar dk|talk]]) 06:15, 15 December 2014 (UTC)
::::You need to read closer. It does not say it is fictitious but may be because it is not official.  Sure, Baidu isn't the best source but a personal observation and common sense can prove the best source.  And consider the note under the banner like I proposed. [[User talk:Kamek98|Eric - Contact me please. I prefer conversations started on my talk page if the subject is changed]] 22:47, 15 December 2014 (UTC)
:::::The flag looks cool, but it cannot be used without [[Wikipedia:Identifying reliable sources|the explicit support from a reliable source]]. Baidu is not a reliable source, as it is much the same thing as Wikipedia, only the Chinese version. You need to find an academic paper, thesis, article, or book that shows this flag and insists that it was used as a national flag. To be honest, I don't think China had an official national flag until the late Qing dynasty, in emulation of the European tradition of having a single national flag for each country. And by that I don't mean battle standards and flags symbolizing aristocratic clans or ruling houses. I am talking about flags that were deliberately chosen by the government to represent the modern nation-state in the global arena. I would be very surprised if the Ming, even the late Ming emperors, upheld this sort of view or policy in or even before 17th century. Your ideas about flags strike me as very anachronistic for late medieval and early modern societies that did not yet have the notion that there should be representative symbols for nation-states. These ideas began in Europe after the creation of flags like the [[Union Jack]], or [[Flag of Great Britain]], but were used only for maritime purposes to distinguish British ships from others during the 17th and 18th centuries (following the personal union of England and Scotland under the rule of King [[James VI and I]], r. 1603 - 1625). The creation of the national [[flag of the United States]] in 1777 was rather exceptional for its time, considering that it wasn't until about the mid 19th century that most countries in Europe adopted a national flag.--&lt;strong&gt;[[User:PericlesofAthens|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;Pericles of Athens&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:PericlesofAthens|&lt;font color=&quot;#0000CD&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 00:06, 16 December 2014 (UTC)
::Maybe am I thinking of banners? [[User talk:Kamek98|Eric - Contact me please. I prefer conversations started on my talk page if the subject is changed]]
:::I appreciate {{u|Kamek98}}'s move to add something colorful, and the work in finding sources, but in the end I second the view of {{u|PericlesofAthens}} that there is no Reliable Source for this &quot;flag,&quot; &quot;banner&quot; or whatever and that the idea of an official flag is [[anachronistic]]. [[User:CWH|ch]] ([[User talk:CWH|talk]]) 02:36, 16 December 2014 (UTC)

== About the population entry in infobox ==
The datum 66,598,337 seems correct, but it's not mentioned in the source, which only gives an estimate of 65000000.--[[User:578985s|578985s]] ([[User talk:578985s|talk]]) 06:14, 5 September 2015 (UTC)

== Southern Ming and Tungning ==
Most historians date the end of the Southern Ming to the death of the [[Yongli Emperor]] in 1662.  Recent edits to this article and [[Kingdom of Tungning]] have extended this date to the fall of the Tungning (on Taiwan) in 1683.  The cited source, ''Statecraft and Political Economy on the Taiwan Frontier, 1600–1800'', by John Robert Shepherd, n.32, pp. 469–470 says:
:The Chengs styled their government in Taiwan a regional government (''mu fu'') of the deposed Ming dynasty and not a center of imperial government. The Chengs continued to use Yung-li reign dates, although that heir to the Ming throne had been executed in 1662 (Hung Chien-chao 1981: 125, 177, 252, 284).  Cheng Ching headed a Ming government that had only a spiritual emperor: &quot;Cheng Ching never failed to perform the rituals of his paying tribute to the non-present emperor on the first and fifteenth day of each month. Similar rituals were followed when he had to make important personnel appointments. On such occasions, he would wear his court apparel, face north, make a report to an empty throne with Chu Shu-kuei [a Ming prince] standing on the left side of it, and then burn the report&quot; (ibid.: 296). Burning memorials is a standard Chinese means of communicating with gods.
It is clear that [[Zhu Shugui]]'s role was merely to be present at this ceremony, not to perform rituals.  There is no justification of presenting him as a ruler of Tungning, as recently done at that article.  All accounts (including the above) are clear that it was the Zhengs who ruled.  To cast this as a continuation on the Southern Ming, in contrast to the sources, is original research.  [[User talk:Kanguole|Kanguole]] 00:39, 11 July 2016 (UTC)

:The Kingdom of Tungning was considered part of the Ming by the Zheng family and not an independent Kingdom. Ming Prince [[Zhu Shugui]] was the appointed representative and stand in for the [[Yongli Emperor]] who appointed him as the official Ming Imperial family representative to the Zheng family forces. The Zheng used Yongli calendar dates and used Zhu Shugui as his stand in at ceremonies to Yongli. All accounts are also clear that Queen [[Elizabeth II]] has no power and that power in Britain is in the hands of [[Prime Minister]] [[David Cameron]]. Does this mean we delete the Queen from lists of heads of state? The [[Governor General of Canada]] and [[Governor-General of Australia]] are Queen Elizabeth's representatives to those countries while the Prime Ministers there hold the real power. The sources show Yongli as the acknowledged head of state and or Zhu Shugui as his representative.

:''Conflict and Commerce in Maritime East Asia: The Zheng Family and the Shaping of the Modern World, c.1620–1720'', by Xing Hang p. 233. says:
::[https://books.google.com/books?id=tQ10CwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA233#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false &quot;'''Under the watchful eyes of the Qing envoys, Zheng Keshuang handed over his seals and other symbols of authority that had tied the family's destiny to the defunct Ming and Yongli court.'''&quot;]
:There are sources for the following at the Kingdom of Tungning article itself:
::'''[[Kingdom_of_Tungning#Capture_of_Taiwan_and_establishment_of_Zheng_Kingdom|Realizing that developing his forces in Taiwan into a large enough threat to unseat the Qing would not be achieved in the short term, Koxinga began transforming Taiwan into a practically proper, albeit preferably temporary, seat of power for the southern Ming loyalist movement. Replacing the Dutch system of government previously used in Taiwan, Koxinga instituted a Ming-style administration, the first Chinese governance in Taiwan. This system of government was divided into six departments: civil service, revenue, rites, war, punishment, and public works.[3] Great care was taken to symbolise support for the Ming legitimacy, an example being the use of the term guan instead of bu to name departments, since the latter is reserved for central government, whereas Taiwan was to be a regional office of the rightful Ming rule of China.[8] Formosa (Taiwan) was also renamed by Koxinga as Tungtu, though this name was later changed by his son, Zheng Jing, to Tungning.[3]]]'''

:This is from Chinese Wikipedia article on Zhu Shugui and its sourced:
::'''[[w:zh:朱術桂#.E7.94.9F.E5.B9.B3|1655年（永曆九年），因為永曆帝和明鄭王朝勢力相隔遙遠，永曆帝特准鄭成功設置六官方便施政，同時允許他委任官職，武官可達一品，文職可達六部主事。鄭成功每次拜封官員，都請朱術桂和明朝宗室在旁觀禮，以示尊重體制]]&lt;ref&gt;2004，[[許雪姬]]總策劃，《臺灣歷史辭典》，「朱術桂」條目，頁303。台北：文建會&lt;/ref&gt;'''

:Zhu Shugui was the Yongli Emperor's appointed representative and stand in of the Ming Imperial family for the Zhengs.[[User:Rajmaan|Rajmaan]] ([[User talk:Rajmaan|talk]]) 00:58, 11 July 2016 (UTC)

::It is pointless to quote Wikipedia (en or zh) – what matters are the sources.  And while we have plenty of sources saying that the Zhengs sought to bolster their legitimacy by presenting themselves as agents of the then-defunct Ming, they do not consider the Zheng regime as part of the Southern Ming.
::You have misread Shepherd's note above (which you cited in the article): Zhu Shugui did not stand in for the Yongli emperor at those ceremonies – the empty throne did, and the reports were passed to the dead emperor by burning them.  Zhu Shugui was there to stand by the throne, as he might have done when the emperor was alive.  [[User talk:Kanguole|Kanguole]] 14:42, 11 July 2016 (UTC)
{{reflist-talk}}

:::I specifically said, &quot;This is from Chinese Wikipedia article on Zhu Shugui and its '''sourced''':&quot;, &quot;There are '''sources''' for the following at the Kingdom of Tungning article itself:&quot;

:::The sources made clear that Tungning viewed itself as part of the Ming dynasty and that Zhu Shugui as appointed by the Yongli Emperor to represent him and the Ming Imperial family to the Zhengs.

:::[https://books.google.com/books?id=qywlAQAAMAAJ&amp;q=the+Ming+government+had+to+establish+a+temporary+capital+at+Nanking.+...+The+Cheng+family+ruled+Taiwan+for+three+generations+covering+23+years+(1661-+1683)+.+...+In+1683,+his+grandson+Cheng+K%27e-shuang+(f%5E;%C2%A33%5E)+surrendered+to+the+Manchu+forces+under+the+command+of+General+Shih+Lang+(%5EIJO,+and+this+ended+the+Southern+Ming+Dynasty.&amp;dq=the+Ming+government+had+to+establish+a+temporary+capital+at+Nanking.+...+The+Cheng+family+ruled+Taiwan+for+three+generations+covering+23+years+(1661-+1683)+.+...+In+1683,+his+grandson+Cheng+K%27e-shuang+(f%5E;%C2%A33%5E)+surrendered+to+the+Manchu+forces+under+the+command+of+General+Shih+Lang+(%5EIJO,+and+this+ended+the+Southern+Ming+Dynasty.&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjMsY645evNAhXDaT4KHfLuATYQ6AEIIDAA '''the Ming government had to establish a temporary capital at Nanking. ... The Cheng family ruled Taiwan for three generations covering 23 years (1661- 1683) . ... In 1683, his grandson Cheng K'e-shuang (f^;£3^) surrendered to the Manchu forces under the command of General Shih Lang (^IJO, and this ended the Southern Ming Dynasty. in this book''']
:::[https://books.google.com/books?id=UuXmRrr6F0MC&amp;pg=PA351#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false '''They continued to refer to the various short-lived remnant regimes in South China of the Ming princes of the Chu family as the continuing line of the Ming dynasty and followed their reign- titles — Hung-kuang (1645), Lung-wu (1645-46), Shao-wu (1646-47), and Yung- li (1647-61), which continued in Taiwan until 1683 — in their political, calendar, and literary references.''']
:::[https://books.google.com/books?id=QQdWAAAAYAAJ&amp;q=the+Ming+government+had+to+establish+a+temporary+capital+at+Nanking.+...+The+Cheng+family+ruled+Taiwan+for+three+generations+covering+23+years+(1661-+1683)+.+...+In+1683,+his+grandson+Cheng+K%27e-shuang+(i3l$j%5EL$0+surrendered+to+the+Manchu+forces+under+the+command+of+General+Shih+Lang+(56i3%26),+and+this+ended+the+Southern+Ming+Dynasty.&amp;dq=the+Ming+government+had+to+establish+a+temporary+capital+at+Nanking.+...+The+Cheng+family+ruled+Taiwan+for+three+generations+covering+23+years+(1661-+1683)+.+...+In+1683,+his+grandson+Cheng+K%27e-shuang+(i3l$j%5EL$0+surrendered+to+the+Manchu+forces+under+the+command+of+General+Shih+Lang+(56i3%26),+and+this+ended+the+Southern+Ming+Dynasty.&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjnmZmk5uvNAhUIID4KHSLmAywQ6AEIIDAA ''' the Ming government had to establish a temporary capital at Nanking. ... The Cheng family ruled Taiwan for three generations covering 23 years (1661- 1683) . ... In 1683, his grandson Cheng K'e-shuang (i3l$j^L$0 surrendered to the Manchu forces under the command of General Shih Lang (56i3&amp;), and this ended the Southern Ming Dynasty.''']

:::[https://books.google.com/books?id=XikMAAAAIAAJ&amp;q=The+death+of+Koxinga+weakened+the+strength+of+the+Southern+Ming.+In+1683+(the+37th+year+of+Yung-li)+his+grandson+Chen+K%27e-shuang+surrendered+to+Shih+Lang,+and+thus+ended+the+Southern+Ming+dynasty.+The+people+who+followed+Koxinga+...&amp;dq=The+death+of+Koxinga+weakened+the+strength+of+the+Southern+Ming.+In+1683+(the+37th+year+of+Yung-li)+his+grandson+Chen+K%27e-shuang+surrendered+to+Shih+Lang,+and+thus+ended+the+Southern+Ming+dynasty.+The+people+who+followed+Koxinga+...&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwi2luz25uvNAhWBOj4KHb38AkwQ6AEIHjAA '''The death of Koxinga weakened the strength of the Southern Ming. In 1683 (the 37th year of Yung-li) his grandson Chen K'e-shuang surrendered to Shih Lang, and thus ended the Southern Ming dynasty. The people who followed Koxinga ...''']
:::[https://books.google.com/books?id=iepJAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT1311#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false '''The so-called Southern Ming court continued to rule Taiwan until the Qing dynasty took control of the island in 1683.''']

:::[https://hub.hku.hk/handle/10722/65389 '''The role of Prince Tang in the Southern Ming dynasty (1644-1683)'''] [https://www.researchgate.net/publication/44241897_The_role_of_Prince_Tang_in_the_Southern_Ming_dynasty_1644-1683_a_study_of_the_man_and_histime_tangwangzhuyujianzhishengpingjiqizainanmingshishangzhidewei]
::::[http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1179/014703780788765027 '''Interest in the history of the Southern Ming (1644–1683) has existed in China for a very long period of time, but comprehensive and systematic ...''']

:::[http://chinesecoins.lyq.dk/mingrebels.html '''Prince Gui (or Yong Li as were his reign title) issued two types of Yong Li coins, but this coin was not issued by Prince Gui. It was issued by a vassal of the Ming called Zheng Chenggong. The coins were minted in Nagasaki, and circulated in Taiwan between 1661-1683. The reason that he used Yong Li's reign title was that he shared the Southern Ming regime's resistance against foreign aggression.'''][[User:Rajmaan|Rajmaan]] ([[User talk:Rajmaan|talk]]) 16:26, 11 July 2016 (UTC)
:It's obviously going to be standard procedure to date the dynasty to the death of the last ruling member of the family. That said, if the Tungning themselves considered themselves to be Ming partisans and if the guy finds sources that treat them as such, there's nothing wrong with mentioning it in the articles in a secondary fashion.&amp;nbsp;—&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:LlywelynII|&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:#BBBBBB 0.1em 0.1em 0.1em; class=texhtml&quot;&gt;Llywelyn&lt;font color=&quot;Gold&quot;&gt;II&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 17:42, 13 July 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>o70yltsk8pyjd1b5wpuu4pokowm8vdi</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
