<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:HMS New Zealand (1911)</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>5990117</id>
    <revision>
      <id>659427729</id>
      <parentid>641050328</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-04-27T07:27:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Yobot</username>
        <id>7328338</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Tagging for WPNZ prelimary stage: Banner normalisation using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (10903)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11892">{{Article history
|action1=WAR
|action1date=15:14, 15 August 2011 
|action1link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/HMS New Zealand (1911)
|action1result=approved
|action1oldid=337128777

|action2=GAN
|action2date=13:53, 18 July 2010
|action2link=Talk:HMS New Zealand (1911)/GA1
|action2result=listed
|action2oldid=374016084

|action3=GTC
|action3date=02:43, 17 August 2010
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured topic candidates/Indefatigable class battlecruisers/archive1
|action3result=promoted
|action3oldid=377330524

|action4=GTC
|action4date=03:25, 17 December 2010
|action4link=Wikipedia:Featured topic candidates/Battlecruisers of the Royal Navy/archive1
|action4result=promoted
|action4oldid=396862588

|action5=FAC
|action5date=23:15, 6 January 2012
|action5link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/HMS New Zealand (1911)/archive1
|action5result=promoted
|action5oldid=469866091

|action6=FTC
|action6date=22:33, 31 October 2013 (UTC)
|action6link=Wikipedia:Featured topic candidates/Battlecruisers of the World/archive1
|action6result=promoted

|ftname=Battlecruisers of the world
|ft2name=Battlecruisers of the Royal Navy
|dykdate=14 December 2009
|dykentry=... that during the [[Battle of Jutland]], the captain of '''{{HMS|New Zealand
|1911
|6}}''' ''(pictured)'' wore a [[Māori]] [[Māori traditional textiles#Piupiu|piupiu]] (grass skirt) and carried a greenstone [[tiki]] to ward off evil?
|topic=history
|currentstatus=FA
|four=no
|maindate=November 19, 2012
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Military history|A-Class=pass|class=FA|old-peer-review=yes|ANZSP=y|British=y|Maritime=y|WWI=y|Majestic-Titan=1}}
{{WikiProject United Kingdom|class=FA|importance=}}
{{WikiProject New Zealand|class=FA|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Ships|class=FA}}
}}

== Disambiguating hatnote on unambiguous article ==
Since there are no other ships named &quot;HMS New Zealand (1911)&quot;, the hatnote here is unneeded. See [[WP:NAMB]]. -- [[User:JHunterJ|JHunterJ]] ([[User talk:JHunterJ|talk]]) 13:56, 17 November 2012 (UTC)
:But there are other ships named HMS New Zealand and the reader needs guidance in case this is not the one that he wanted. There's a reason why ships have their own style of hatnote and why virtually every British warship has a hatnote just like this one.--[[User:Sturmvogel 66|Sturmvogel 66]] ([[User talk:Sturmvogel 66|talk]]) 14:26, 17 November 2012 (UTC)
::The reason may be simple inertia and [[WP:LOCALCONSENSUS]]. How does this hypothetical reader reach an article titled [[HMS New Zealand (1911)]] if this is not the one he wanted? Not by wikilink (which intend this ship) or by the search box (which will give him the set index). -- [[User:JHunterJ|JHunterJ]] ([[User talk:JHunterJ|talk]]) 14:28, 17 November 2012 (UTC)
:::More than likely, the disambiguator (year) means nothing to the reader, so he may want the pre-dreadnought battleship or some other ship listed on the ship index page.--[[User:Sturmvogel 66|Sturmvogel 66]] ([[User talk:Sturmvogel 66|talk]]) 15:58, 17 November 2012 (UTC)
::::That doesn't explain how he might have reached this page instead of the set index. If the year doesn't mean anything to him, he'll land on the set index. -- [[User:JHunterJ|JHunterJ]] ([[User talk:JHunterJ|talk]]) 17:34, 17 November 2012 (UTC)
:::::Could have been from a link, I suppose. [[WP:Ships]] does things in its own way, even to article titles, and I'm OK with that.--[[User:Sturmvogel 66|Sturmvogel 66]] ([[User talk:Sturmvogel 66|talk]]) 17:42, 17 November 2012 (UTC)
::::::Please see [[WP:LOCALCONSENSUS]]. -- [[User:JHunterJ|JHunterJ]] ([[User talk:JHunterJ|talk]]) 18:02, 17 November 2012 (UTC)
:::::::Don't really care. I believe that WP:Ships rules make more sense in this case.--[[User:Sturmvogel 66|Sturmvogel 66]] ([[User talk:Sturmvogel 66|talk]]) 19:18, 17 November 2012 (UTC)
::::::::&quot;Don't really care.&quot; is unhelpful. ''Why'' does the [[WP:LOCALCONSENSUS]] make &quot;more sense&quot; here, since the broader consensus of [[WP:NAMB]] makes the same sense for actually describable reasons (the title isn't ambiguous, readers are unlikely to land here in need of a navigational hatnote), and the only reason you've given for ignoring it is &quot;because WP:Ships says so&quot;. -- [[User:JHunterJ|JHunterJ]] ([[User talk:JHunterJ|talk]]) 19:25, 17 November 2012 (UTC)
:::::::::Speaking as a person with an interest in maritime history and ships, I often &quot;land&quot; in articles like this one, when looking for another ship of the same name. It's quite easy to reach the wrong ship when searching, it happens to me all the time. Removing hatnotes like the one here would be ''really'' unfortunate. [[User:Manxruler|Manxruler]] ([[User talk:Manxruler|talk]]) 20:04, 17 November 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::JHunterJ: how does one get on this page? As manxrukler says. Maybe it is time to demonstrate the opposite: &quot;someone who does not look for this page, will not end up here&quot;. Meanwhile the answer could be: links from outside of WP can misdirect. For example Google does not use the same DAB logic as WP does. Then, once on this page, the reader cannot get to the right page (but through a hatnote). Even worse, the reader will not know that this is the wrong page. -[[User:DePiep|DePiep]] ([[User talk:DePiep|talk]]) 00:35, 18 November 2012 (UTC)
:::::::::::Adding: Another situation where a reader can arrive at this page while looking for another HMS New Zealand. That is when a reader ''browses'' the set list (or dab page) [[HMS New Zealand]], looking for a specific ship (Say, the ship from shipyard X). That reader can click each name from the list to check, ''and go back to the list throug the hatnote'' when not found. -[[User:DePiep|DePiep]] ([[User talk:DePiep|talk]]) 01:13, 18 November 2012 (UTC)
::::::::::::While the potential for confusing one title for another is a good reason, I don't think providing round-trip navigation is a valid reason. There should be no expectation for hatnotes to provide functionality readily available through the browser's back button. [[User:Bkonrad|older]] ≠ [[User talk:Bkonrad|wiser]] 21:50, 18 November 2012 (UTC)

[[WP:NAMB]] is a frequently criticized guideline, and arguably does not enjoy a broad consensus. While the disambiguating phrase &quot;(1911)&quot; is sufficient to produce a unique article title, IMO the titles can be confused easily enough that a hatnote is helpful in this case. [[User:Bkonrad|older]] ≠ [[User talk:Bkonrad|wiser]] 23:19, 17 November 2012 (UTC)

:I agree - the hatnote is useful to readers. [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 01:04, 18 November 2012 (UTC)

The relevant part of the NAMB guideline is: ''However, a hatnote may still be appropriate when even a more specific name is still ambiguous.'' It recognizes that sometimes the parenthesis disambiguation is not enough for the user to arrive to the right article and thus the hatnote is needed. The majority of editors above feel that this is the case here; I'd say the reason for this is that both article titles are distinguished only by year, so both disambiguation terms belong to the same class. This is enough for having unique titles, but not for useful navigation. [[User:Diego Moya|Diego]] ([[User talk:Diego Moya|talk]]) 12:53, 18 November 2012 (UTC)
:The Google example Diego Moya provided on the hatnote talk page was very useful in demonstrating a reason to keep the hatnote here. Much more than &quot;because all ships ignore the broader consensus&quot; or &quot;I don't care&quot;. Thanks. -- [[User:JHunterJ|JHunterJ]] ([[User talk:JHunterJ|talk]]) 20:47, 18 November 2012 (UTC)

I think the problem is that this article title isn't ambiguous with ''all'' of the entries on the disambiguation page, only with the one HMS Zealandia entry that also mentions 1911. So a wordier {{tl|about}} hatnote should be used here to elaborate that. --[[User:Joy|Joy &amp;#91;shallot&amp;#93;]] ([[User talk:Joy|talk]]) 08:15, 27 November 2012 (UTC)
:First of all this thread leads to a need for redefinition of WP:NAMB. Currently it only mentions WP internal searching and linking, not the external search engines. Second, the suggestion by Joy [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=HMS_New_Zealand_%281911%29&amp;diff=525097607&amp;oldid=523995274] is a sort of compromise that does not solve either side. To me, it does not reflect the outcome of this talk (which is until now: there is a good reason in the google-remark to keep the hatnote coutering NAMB), and still it is not conform NAMB. (The other HMS has a disambiguated title, by the year, too, so NAMB still says no need for a hatnote).  Apart from these two the result as a hatnote is cryptic and missing its primary goal. For now I revert to the earlier version we are talking about, by WP:IAR and reasonable sense I think. -[[User:DePiep|DePiep]] ([[User talk:DePiep|talk]]) 09:12, 27 November 2012 (UTC)

:: First of all, no, this thread doesn't lead to that need - you simply can't change an established guideline at a single article's talk page. The appropriate place for that discussion is at [[Wikipedia talk:Hatnote]].
:: Fixing the &quot;Google leads people to random places&quot; problem is not a problem specific to one article, at least I don't see anyone claiming that it disproportionally affects one article, so it should not be worked around at one single place.
:: The primary goal of hatnotes is to tell you &quot;You've arrived at an ambiguous title&quot;, and what to do. This article's title ''is'' ambiguous with [[HMS New Zealand (1904)]] because of a common date. The date is not obvious from that other title, but the fact is that the latter ship was called the same name up to some point in 1911. Hence, [[WP:NAMB]] does ''not'' apply in that case. But, this article's title is ''not'' ambiguous with a 1946 Malta-class aircraft carrier that ''doesn't even have an article'' and is instead just a line on the disambiguation page.
:: The suggestion that a ''featured article'' should violate an established guideline is, well, preposterous in and of itself. It's even more silly to violate it with the goal of linking a single unreferenced sentence about a vessel whose potential article name would not be ambiguous with this article's name.
:: --[[User:Joy|Joy &amp;#91;shallot&amp;#93;]] ([[User talk:Joy|talk]]) 14:02, 29 November 2012 (UTC)
:::Don't put too much weight on the small number of ships using this name as that is not necessarily typical. The hatnote needs to deal with a dozen or more ships for some of the more popular RN ship names and I think that it works well enough as is.--[[User:Sturmvogel 66|Sturmvogel 66]] ([[User talk:Sturmvogel 66|talk]]) 17:01, 29 November 2012 (UTC)
::::It now occurs to me to mention that ship articles do not follow the general WP naming guidelines as they are far too general to be useful when there are dozens of ships with the same name. So we preemptively disambiguate to minimize any confusion and rely on the ship index pages to guide readers to the exact ship that they're interested in if all they've got is a name. Hence the hatnotes, the utility of which [[WP:NAMB]] doesn't even recognize.--[[User:Sturmvogel 66|Sturmvogel 66]] ([[User talk:Sturmvogel 66|talk]]) 19:58, 29 November 2012 (UTC)

==s' or 's?==
This truly isn't actually the thing that is exercising me most today, (and I don't do LOLs), however.... The article says captains Halsey and Green both wore the lucky piupiu, and also says &quot;The captain's piupiu was returned to New Zealand&quot;.
Shouldn't that be &quot;captains' piupiu&quot; because more than one captan wore it?
Or is it be &quot;captain's piupiu&quot; beause only one captain could wear it at a time?
I'll go back to work now.[[User:Moriori|Moriori]] ([[User talk:Moriori|talk]]) 18:56, 18 November 2012 (UTC)
:The latter, I think - the piupiu was assigned to whoever the captain of the ship was and only he was meant to wear it. [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 11:22, 19 November 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>fxs4hs625xlqczg5dzlvxsbokxtiphk</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
