<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Empire of Brazil</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>303123</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749690205</id>
      <parentid>749310394</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-15T18:12:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Astynax</username>
        <id>1484699</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Recent edits */ read the entire article</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17055">{{Skip to talk}}
{{Talk header|noarchive=}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 3
|minthreadsleft = 4
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:Empire of Brazil/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=PR
|action1date=05:25, 27 Jun 2005
|action1link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Empire of Brazil/archive1
|action1result=reviewed
|action1oldid=16143547

|action2=GAN
|action2date=14 November 2006
|action2result=not listed
|action2oldid=87764960

|action3=FAC
|action3date=01:37, 23 February 2011
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Empire of Brazil/archive1
|action3result=promoted
|action3oldid=415427070

|currentstatus=FA
|maindate=27 April 2011
}}
{{Vital article|level=4|topic=History|class=FA}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Brazil |class=FA|importance=Top|history=yes|gov=yes}}
{{WikiProject Former countries|class=FA
| b1 &lt;!--Referencing &amp; citations--&gt; = yes
| b2 &lt;!--Coverage &amp; accuracy    --&gt; = yes
| b3 &lt;!--Structure              --&gt; = yes
| b4 &lt;!--Grammar &amp; style        --&gt; = yes
| b5 &lt;!--Supporting materials   --&gt; = yes
| b6 &lt;!--Accessibility          --&gt; = yes
| EB-taskforce = yes
}}
{{MILHIST|class=FA|South-American=y}}
{{WikiProject History|importance=high|class=FA}}
{{WikiProject Uruguay|topic=hist|importance=high|class=FA}}
{{GOCE|user=Chaosdruid|date=1 July 2010}}
}}
{{Archives |bot=MiszaBot I |age=3 |units=months |index=/Archive index |auto=no |search=yes|
*[[Talk:Empire of Brazil/Archive 1|Archive 1]]
*[[Talk:Empire of Brazil/Archive 2|Archive 2]]
*[[Talk:Empire of Brazil/Archive 3|Archive 3]]
}}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn 
|target=/Archive index |mask=/Archive &lt;#&gt; |leading_zeros=0 |indexhere=yes 
}}
{{American English}}

== White Slaves ==

In the part about slavery, white slaves are mentioned. It is said they were &quot;the product of generations of inter-ethnic sexual relations between male slave owners and their female mulatto slaves&quot;, it is then said: &quot;although this was very rare and was not approved of socially&quot;, It is unclear if this sentence refers to white slaves, which were very rare and probably not approved, or about &quot;the inter-ethnic sexual relations between male slave owners and their female mulatto slaves&quot; which was really common, and informally accepted (many were indeed rapings, but there were countless cases of slave owners who fell in love with their slaves and freed them, (sometimes marrying)  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Knoterification|Knoterification]] ([[User talk:Knoterification|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Knoterification|contribs]]) 03:01, 15 January 2015 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:White slaves were not tolerared. Sexual relations between masters and slaves were common. --[[User:Lecen|Lecen]] ([[User talk:Lecen|talk]]) 03:23, 15 January 2015 (UTC)
:Lecen is correct. White Christian Europeans were not slaves (though European immigrants could be subject to indentured service, as they could be in the North American colonies). It is probably best to reword the confusing term &quot;white slaves&quot;, although I'm unsure of another term. Perhaps something like &quot;slaves who appeared to be European&quot; might be better. I'll insert that for now, but if anyone has a better term, feel free to change it to something more accurate. [[User:Astynax| &amp;bull; Astynax]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Astynax|&lt;span style='color:#3399CC'&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 04:17, 15 January 2015 (UTC)

no artigo do ce em portugues diz que quase 2 em 3 escravos eram alogenos mas não especifica o resto de que origem seriam?  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/2804:14C:DA94:730:40BC:37A5:D830:7AD|2804:14C:DA94:730:40BC:37A5:D830:7AD]] ([[User talk:2804:14C:DA94:730:40BC:37A5:D830:7AD|talk]]) 05:58, 13 February 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Initial sentence '''was''' misleading ==
I'm not denying the accuracy of the primary facts in the article – only that they support the initial sentence.

The article itself leaves no doubt that the Brazilian Empire lasted from 12 October 1822 to 15 October 1889.  The Provincia Cisplatina lasted from 1821 to 1828 only (and even that was not uniformly Brazilian), but let's be generous and call it 7 years.   

It follows that the sentence '''The Empire of Brazil was a 19th-century state that broadly comprised the territories which form modern Brazil and Uruguay''' does not give a correct impression.  

To see why, try the following, pedantically accurate version:  &quot;The Empire of Brazil was a 19th-century state that broadly comprised the territory of the modern United States of Brazil and – for 7 out of 67 years or only 10.4% of the time – the Oriental Republic of Uruguay&quot;.  So we ought to rewrite the initial sentence accordingly, but without the pedantry, of course.  This gives:

'''The Empire of Brazil was a 19th-century state that broadly comprised the territory that forms modern Brazil and, for a short tome, Uruguay.''' Ttocserp 18:56, 27 August 2015 (UTC)  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Prkprescott|Prkprescott]] ([[User talk:Prkprescott|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Prkprescott|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

os mapas estão cheios de erros vou falar só de alguns geopoliticos outros nem se falam oeste de sc ainda era missions orientais contestado pré 1905 a regionalização do ibge do xx-ii total non sense era inimaginavel no xix mesmo para os paulistas de 1887 que viam só 3 regiões no grosso só se viam 2 o norte ou seja tudo a norte do rj e o sul ou seja tudo a sul do rj antes da divisão que aparece houveram 300 tentativas de regionalização sob todos os aspectos  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/2804:14C:DA94:730:40BC:37A5:D830:7AD|2804:14C:DA94:730:40BC:37A5:D830:7AD]] ([[User talk:2804:14C:DA94:730:40BC:37A5:D830:7AD|talk]]) 06:01, 13 February 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Agassiz e as fotos evidenciam um recife interessante as fotos selecionadas tendem a mostrar um recife menor a foto de Salvador é fantástica  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/2804:14C:DA94:730:40BC:37A5:D830:7AD|2804:14C:DA94:730:40BC:37A5:D830:7AD]] ([[User talk:2804:14C:DA94:730:40BC:37A5:D830:7AD|talk]]) 06:03, 13 February 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Images ==

The copyrights for the images used in the article have been verified as usable in Wikipedia. The images and their associated texts have undergone vetting during the Featured Article process. If you have additional or better images, please make certain that they have meet the licensing and other criteria for [[Wikipedia:Featured article criteria|FA]] articles and Wikipedia's [[Image use policy]]. If in doubt, please discuss before attempting to add other images. [[User:Astynax| &amp;bull; Astynax]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Astynax|&lt;span style='color:#3399CC'&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 18:00, 26 June 2016 (UTC)
:[[User:Astynax| &amp;bull; Astynax]], I've left another notice on the user's talkpage, urging them to engage here. [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 10:23, 27 June 2016 (UTC)

== Recent edits ==

There are two Brazilian editors who have been pushing their edits in the past months, coming back here and there trying to succeed. I got an odd message in Portugueseby one of them accusing me of having something against the Brazilian state of Pernambuco. The other editor is an 18-year old boy who is a self declared monarchist. As can be seen in the article there is a photo of Pernambuco in &quot;Consolidation&quot; and another in the next section, &quot;Growth.&quot; There are several Brazilian provinces which, unfortunately, are not depicted in pictures. The article has a basic and clear structure: smaller sections (that it, with less paragraphs) have one photo, to prevent overcrowding. The article is well written, certainly one of the best in the entire Wikipedia, and it works because it's solidly based on the best historiography in the topic. Which is why it's so stable and has suffered no major or minor changes (just minimal) since it became a Featured Article. The two aforementioned editors are unwilling to debate, instead opting to edit war. They should have come here, not me, but I can't expect a reasonable behavior from all. I urge them to start working on other articles, that are in desperate need for improvements. There are countless important articles about wars, statesmen and general topics on Brazil's imperial period that need work. Go there. --[[User:Lecen|Lecen]] ([[User talk:Lecen|talk]]) 17:20, 3 November 2016 (UTC)

:{{ping|Lecen}}, You act like an [[Wikipedia:Ownership of content|owner of the article]]. My contributions are of the best quality. The [[Brazilian Institute of Geography and Statistics]] (IBGE) is the highest organ of Brazil when it comes to population statistics, and can not be ignored in favor of an irrelevant historian.--[[User:Juniorpetjua|Juniorpetjua]] ([[User talk:Juniorpetjua|talk]]) 14:25, 5 November 2016 (UTC)
::I don't speak Portuguese or Spanish so for me going through your changes is difficult. However, from your linked source at the IBGE I believe I can glean what the numbers and names mean. For example, the total slave population in 1864 appears to me to be 1,715,000, in the Nordeste (North-East?) Bahia in 1864 had a slave population of 300,000 (17.49%), in Sudeste (South-East?) Rio de Janeiro in 1864 also had a slave population of 300,000 (17.49%). Yet in your edit [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Empire_of_Brazil&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=747574240&amp;oldid=747573641 here] you claim that Rio de Janeiro had a slave population of 23% and Bahia had 18% - they appear to me to both have had 17.49% so rounding error as well. That does assume that I am reading these numbers correctly. So I decide to go to 1874 as well, total slave population; 1,540,829, Bahia's slave population has dropped off drastically to 165,403 (10.7%) while Rio de Janeiro's slave population has actually increased to 301,352 (19.2%) but still no where near the claimed 23%. From what I can see you've given an accurate representation of Bahia but not so for Rio de Janerio - only in 1887 where Rio de Janeiro's slave population is 162,421 out of 723,419 (22.45%) does the mathematics line up. For the others; Pernambuco 15% cited in article and 15% is what I worked out, Minas Gerais 14% cited in article and 14.5% is what I worked out, Sao Paulo 5% cited in article and 4.66% is what I worked out. Finally, in 1864 Corte would have had 5.8% of Brazil's slave population, more than both Sao Paulo and Rio Grande do Sul for 1864, but it isn't mentioned anywhere. Even without challenging your source I am not getting anywhere near one of the figures you're claiming in your edit - the one for Rio de Janeiro. [[User:Mr rnddude|Mr rnddude]] ([[User talk:Mr rnddude|talk]]) 15:01, 5 November 2016 (UTC)
:::Additional comment; {{u|Juniorpetjua}} there is nothing stopping you from contributing to any article you would like to, but, when editor's question your changes you must go to the talk page and discuss your proposed changes. You cannot force your edits into an article. WP:BRD - bold edit (which you've done), revert (which other editor's have done), discuss (go to the talk page, put your sources up and debate with other editors till you reach a solution that all parties find acceptable). This article is an FA, this does not preclude contributions, but, it does suggest that ''more'' will be expected than it might otherwise be. I don't have a problem with your source, but, I do have a problem with your outcome. I'd like to be able to access Lidia Besouchet's work as well, unfortunately that doesn't seem possible as google books has no preview of the book for me to browse. [[User:Mr rnddude|Mr rnddude]] ([[User talk:Mr rnddude|talk]]) 15:17, 5 November 2016 (UTC)

::::{{u|Mr rnddude}}, the numbers are correct. The Court of the Empire of Brazil (''Corte'' in Portuguese), which was in Rio de Janeiro, had 100,000 slaves. That is, Rio de Janeiro had a total of 400,000 slaves (23%) in 1864.--[[User:Juniorpetjua|Juniorpetjua]] ([[User talk:Juniorpetjua|talk]]) 17:07, 5 November 2016 (UTC)
:::::Mhmm, alright that makes sense. My only other comments for the time being is that 17.49% is rounded down to 17% not up to 18% (see Bahia), similarly 14.5% is rounded up to 15% not down to 14% (see Minas Gerais). The other values match up with what you put into the article. The question now lies solely down to one thing, which source is better/more accurate; the IBGE or Lidia Besouchet? [[User:Mr rnddude|Mr rnddude]] ([[User talk:Mr rnddude|talk]]) 03:09, 6 November 2016 (UTC)
:::::::Check the page. The IBGE is using as source a secondary source. The information provided was not created by the IBGE. The first national census was done in 1872. Anything before that is speculative. --[[User:Lecen|Lecen]] ([[User talk:Lecen|talk]]) 03:47, 6 November 2016 (UTC)
::::::::{{tq|The IBGE is using as source a secondary source.}} Yes I am aware of this, that doesn't change the question; &quot;[W]hich is better/more accurate? I'm more concerned that this article present ''accurate'' information than anything else. {{tq|Anything before that is speculative}}, that also applies to Besouchet and any other source that discusses the question. [[User:Mr rnddude|Mr rnddude]] ([[User talk:Mr rnddude|talk]]) 03:57, 6 November 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::Besouchet and Vainfas (read the article, there are two secondaries sources mentioned) rely on the 1872 census, which is why it says &quot;around 1870.&quot; As I said, anything before that is speculative. About being accurate or not, only the 1872 census is. --[[User:Lecen|Lecen]] ([[User talk:Lecen|talk]]) 04:28, 6 November 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::::{{u|Mr rnddude}} &quot;Around 1870&quot; and &quot;1872 census&quot; are very different things. João José Reis (J. J. REIS), the source used by the IBGE, is the highest Brazilian authority and a world reference in the history of slavery in the nineteenth century. PhD in History from the [[University of Minnesota]], J. J. Reis was [http://drclas.harvard.edu/people/jo%C3%A3o-jos%C3%A9-reis Visiting Professor at the Harvard University, Princeton University, University of London, University of Michigan and Brandeis University].--[[User:Juniorpetjua|Juniorpetjua]] ([[User talk:Juniorpetjua|talk]]) 05:03, 6 November 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::::If the 1864 statistics by the IBGE are speculative - which explains the unusually round figures for that period - the next valid figures would be the 1874 statistics? These would be; Rio de Janeiro 22.6%, Bahia 10.7%, Minas Gerais 20.2%, Sao Paulo 11.3% and Rio Grande do Sul 6.39% making up ~71% of the total slave population. Add Pernambuco at 6.9% and Maranhao at 4.8% and that's ~83% of the slave population across those regions. If nobody minds I'll try to find a source in English that discusses this and go through it for myself. [[User:Mr rnddude|Mr rnddude]] ([[User talk:Mr rnddude|talk]]) 05:33, 6 November 2016 (UTC)
{{outdent|::::::::::::}}{{u|Mr rnddude}} It is the IBGE that carries out the population census in Brazil, and the 1872 census was marked by poor accuracy and poor information quality. I would also like to talk about another very serious flaw in the article, which is the absence of an important episode that occurred during the Empire of Brazil: The [[Confederation of the Equator]]. It was a separatist movement in the province of Pernambuco, which was at that time the richest province in Brazil. [http://escola.britannica.com.br/article/483190/Confederacao-do-Equador Pernambuco ended up losing more than half of its territory as punishment for the rebellion]. Why isn't there anything on the subject on the page?--[[User:Juniorpetjua|Juniorpetjua]] ([[User talk:Juniorpetjua|talk]]) 06:31, 13 November 2016 (UTC)
:{{u|Mr rnddude}} ^^^ --[[User:Juniorpetjua|Juniorpetjua]] ([[User talk:Juniorpetjua|talk]]) 17:39, 13 November 2016 (UTC)
::Patience, I am not available everyday and have other Wiki projects of my own. Thanks for the message and I'll get back to you as soon as I can, hopefully tomorrow. [[User:Mr rnddude|Mr rnddude]] ([[User talk:Mr rnddude|talk]]) 18:01, 13 November 2016 (UTC)
:The Confederation of the Equator rebellion is already mentioned on the page, with a link to the full article, as is the appropriate emphasis in an already long and broadly themed article such as this. [[User:Astynax| &amp;bull; Astynax]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Astynax|&lt;span style='color:#3399CC'&gt;talk&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 18:12, 15 November 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>h2agwrop7ok6o9p3dkw9c66q2hw5hg8</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
