<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Stede Bonnet</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>7973171</id>
    <revision>
      <id>635729536</id>
      <parentid>635345886</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-11-28T04:08:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Vycl1994</username>
        <id>19014806</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>param</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20321">{{talkheader}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Biography|living=n|class=FA|listas=Bonnet, Stede|military-work-group=y|military-priority=Low}}
{{WikiProject Piracy|class=FA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Military History|class=FA|Biography=y|Maritime=y|Early-Modern=y}}
}}
{{ArticleHistory|action1=GAN
|action1date=12 July, 2007
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=144294291

|action2=FAC
|action2date=04:25, 4 November 2007
|action2link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Stede Bonnet
|action2result=promoted
|action2oldid=168082628

|topic=History
|currentstatus=FA
|maindate=January 23, 2008 
}}

== Captain Codd? ==
This line I'm not sure on: &quot;Captain Codd, whose merchant ship was taken on 12 October, described Bonnet as walking the deck in his nightshirt, lacking any command and still unwell from his wounds.&quot;

Captain Codd, I'm probably wrong but is that not the Fish finger's Captain? Confused so I'll leave it I guess. &lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[User:GothmogII|GothmogII]] ([[User talk:GothmogII|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/GothmogII|contribs]]) 20:24, 1 May 2007 (UTC).&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- HagermanBot Auto-Unsigned --&gt;

Believe it or not, that really is the correct name according to period sources. [[User:Vincent pearse|Vincent pearse]] ([[User talk:Vincent pearse|talk]]) 15:37, 18 January 2009 (UTC)

==The Shudders==
Link: http://www.amazon.com/Unfortunate-Career-Stede-Bonnet-1688-1718/dp/B002X33UPO/ref=sr_1_2?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1288045065&amp;sr=8-2
This band have named an album after Stede.[[Special:Contributions/86.141.225.55|86.141.225.55]] ([[User talk:86.141.225.55|talk]]) 22:19, 25 October 2010 (UTC)

== Article introduction ==
I've fixed the factual errors in the introduction, but I'm still not satisfied with the introduction as a whole.  It is much too long, and reads like the entire article was put into a car crusher and squeezed into three paragraphs.  In my view, an introduction should not try to recapitulate the entire article, but state only the most pertinent facts, in one paragraph if possible.

Still, I am undoubtedly biased, as I created a large portion of this article back in March 2007, and doubtless have a preference for my own work.  Therefore, I would like to have some other opinions before I go about changing the introduction wholesale.  [[User:Piratedan|Pirate Dan]] 15:08, 16 July 2007 (UTC)
:Essentially, leads are supposed to act as outlines for the entire article. I found the article lead to be a bit in excess, so I tried to trim it down a bit. It's still pretty big, so I'll check out what can still be removed. &lt;span style=&quot;background:#E0FFFF;color:#007FFF;font-family:Georgia;&quot;&gt;[[User:Nishkid64|Nishkid64]] ([[User talk:Nishkid64|talk]])&lt;/span&gt; 17:21, 18 August 2007 (UTC)

:: I propose the following new introduction, focusing on what was really important about Bonnet, his piratical career, and leaving the minor details for the main article: 

::''Stede Bonnet (c. 1688 – December 10, 1718) was an early 18th century Barbadian pirate, sometimes called the &quot;the gentleman pirate&quot; because he owned moderate wealth in land before turning to a life of crime. In the summer of 1717, with no prior sailing experience, he bought a ship and turned to piracy, ravaging vessels off America's eastern seaboard.

::''Bonnet met the infamous pirate Blackbeard in [[Nassau, Bahamas|Nassau]] and temporarily ceded his ship's command to Blackbeard. Before separating in [[December]], [[1717]], Blackbeard and Bonnet plundered and captured merchant ships along the East Coast. After Bonnet failed to capture the Protestant Caesar, his crew abandoned him to rejoin Blackbeard. Bonnet stayed as a guest on Blackbeard's ship until Blackbeard abandoned him off North Carolina.  Bonnet then rescued some pirates marooned by Blackbeard and returned to piracy in [[July]], [[1718]].''

::''In [[September]], [[1718]], while anchored in the estuary of the Cape Fear River, Bonnet was defeated and captured by a naval expedition under Colonel William Rhett. Taken to Charleston, Bonnet escaped, but was recaptured on Sullivan's Island. Convicted of two acts of piracy, Bonnet was sentenced to death.  He was hanged in Charleston on [[December 10, 1718]].''

::[[User:Piratedan|Pirate Dan]] 13:42, 25 October 2007 (UTC)
:::To be honest PD (having given my support at FAC), I think the wording before your last edit (summary &quot;tightening&quot;) was better.  Can you ''own'' wealth?  I suppose you can, but it looks strange to me.  My tuppence, anyway. [[User:Carre|Carre]] 13:46, 25 October 2007 (UTC)

::::Well, I wanted to get rid of &quot;lived as a moderately wealthy landowner,&quot; since &quot;lived as&quot; was clearly surplus verbiage.  My first thought was just to say he &quot;was a moderately wealthy landowner,&quot;  but many stylists say to avoid the verb &quot;was&quot; for a more active verb like &quot;owned&quot; whenever possible.  But if you find the phrase &quot;owned moderate wealth in land&quot; awkward, I'd be happy to change it to &quot;was a moderately wealthy landowner.&quot;  [[User:Piratedan|Pirate Dan]] 19:35, 25 October 2007 (UTC)
[←]''was a moderately...'' seems good to me, although I'd need to see it in full context to be sure.  I think it'll be ok though.  Stylists, to my mind, over-concentrate on the active versus the passive:  there is room for both in good prose, and you shouldn't ignore one in favour of the other where it results in clumsy writing (which I think the current version is). [[User:Carre|Carre]] 20:15, 25 October 2007 (UTC)

: OK, I've changed it.  It does look a little more natural. [[User:Piratedan|Pirate Dan]] 20:36, 25 October 2007 (UTC)
::Yes, that looks lovely;  I can't even see why there would be an argument about it!  What do stylists know?!  Nice one.  [[User:Carre|Carre]] 20:53, 25 October 2007 (UTC)
:::The lead is supposed to be comprehensive outline of the entire article. I don't think your version does the trick. I agree the lead I wrote is long and can be shortened, but it can't be this short. &lt;span style=&quot;background:#E0FFFF;color:#007FFF;font-family:Georgia;&quot;&gt;[[User:Nishkid64|Nishkid64]] ([[User talk:Nishkid64|talk]])&lt;/span&gt; 22:03, 25 October 2007 (UTC)
::::I'm sorry;  my comments to this version of the lead have been about just one phrase, and nothing else.  I just glanced at the whole result, and it looks fine to me from a length perspective, but I haven't checked its content vs the article.  That will have to wait til tomorrow for me, since it's late here (PS a lead should only ever be 3-4 paragraphs). [[User:Carre|Carre]] 22:26, 25 October 2007 (UTC)
[←] Grr, it was definitely late last night!  Nishkid's right, the current lead is fine as is;  the proposed new one would be too short.  I've just done a minor copyedit on the article's lead, just to make it flow a little better (IMO, of course).  Hopefully the changes are acceptable. [[User:Carre|Carre]] 10:07, 26 October 2007 (UTC)

==Map?==
I really enjoyed reading this article. It is very well written and it held my attention. (A rarity for the featured articles) I do have one request. Would it be possible to add a map showing the mouth of the Cape Fear, Charleston, and other points of interest? [[User:Dincher|Dincher]] ([[User talk:Dincher|talk]]) 02:18, 23 January 2008 (UTC)
:Yarrrrr, glad to see you liked the article, laddy. Perhaps you were intrigued by the fact that Bonnet was a pirate! In that case, I might as well churn out more pirate FAs. This [[:Image:Wpdms nasa topo cape fear river.jpg|image]] highlights the Cape Fear River and its tributaries. &lt;span style=&quot;background:#E0FFFF;color:#007FFF;font-family:Georgia;&quot;&gt;[[User:Nishkid64|Nishkid64]] ([[User talk:Nishkid64|talk]])&lt;/span&gt; 03:11, 23 January 2008 (UTC)
::Argh, I be talkin' about a more specific map. One that might lead to some traysure! Or show which estuary the fight was fought on. [[User:Dincher|Dincher]] ([[User talk:Dincher|talk]]) 04:51, 23 January 2008 (UTC)

== &quot;Because of marital problems&quot; ==

Sounds like an excuse to me.  What sort of marital problems are causative of piracy, and are there any other cases recorded?  Perhaps it may have been &quot;after his wife told him to ... go away, he did, and ...&quot;.  [[Special:Contributions/82.46.46.98|82.46.46.98]] ([[User talk:82.46.46.98|talk]]) 14:42, 23 January 2008 (UTC)
:The specifics of the marital problems were never provided. &lt;span style=&quot;background:#E0FFFF;color:#007FFF;font-family:Georgia;&quot;&gt;[[User:Nishkid64|Nishkid64]] ([[User talk:Nishkid64|talk]])&lt;/span&gt; 17:06, 23 January 2008 (UTC)
::I, also, thought its mention in the intro was odd.  It's explained later in the story that this is a quote from a writer of a history of the pirates.  The intro should mention the source since the tidbit is so odd.  [[User:Tempshill|Tempshill]] ([[User talk:Tempshill|talk]]) 18:56, 23 January 2008 (UTC)

==Lead==
The lead is pretty shocking for a FA, perhaps someone with more knowledge should edit it? [[User:Mattyness|Mattyness]] ([[User talk:Mattyness|talk]]) 16:42, 23 January 2008 (UTC)
:Someone moved most of the contents of the lead to a separate section called &quot;Overview&quot;. I have reversed that change. &lt;span style=&quot;background:#E0FFFF;color:#007FFF;font-family:Georgia;&quot;&gt;[[User:Nishkid64|Nishkid64]] ([[User talk:Nishkid64|talk]])&lt;/span&gt; 17:03, 23 January 2008 (UTC)
::It certainly is far too detailed. Here's how I would shorten it:

'''Stede Bonnet''' (c. 1688&lt;ref name=&quot;p55&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Butler |first=Lindley S. |title= Pirates, Privateers, and Rebel Raiders of the Carolina Coast|year= 2000 |publisher= [[University of North Carolina Press]] |location=[[Chapel Hill, North Carolina]]|isbn=0-87169-240-6 | pages=p55}}&lt;/ref&gt; – [[December 10]] [[1718]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Snow |first=Edward R. |title= Pirates and Buccaneers of the Atlantic Coast|year= 1944 |publisher=Yankee Publishing Co. |location=[[Dublin, New Hampshire|Dublin]], [[New Hampshire]]|isbn= | pages=p272}}&lt;/ref&gt;)&lt;ref&gt;All dates in this article are in the [[Old Style and New Style dates|Old Style form]] used in Britain and her colonies during Bonnet's life, except that the new year is dated from [[January 1]].&lt;/ref&gt; was an early 18th-century [[Barbados|Barbadian]] [[piracy|pirate]], sometimes called &quot;the gentleman pirate&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Pringle|first=Patrick |title= Jolly Roger: The Story of the Great Age of Piracy|year= 2001 |publisher= [[Dover Publications]] |location=[[Mineola, New York]]|isbn=0-486-41823-5 | pages=p191}}&lt;/ref&gt; because he was a moderately wealthy landowner before turning to a life of crime. 

Because of marital problems, and despite his lack of sailing experience, Bonnet turned to piracy in the summer of 1717. He bought a sailing vessel, named it ''Revenge'', and sailed along the American eastern seaboard, capturing and burning several ships. Upon reaching [[Nassau, Bahamas|Nassau]], [[The Bahamas|Bahamas]], a notorious pirate den, Bonnet met and ceded command to the infamous [[Blackbeard]]. Before separating in December 1717, Blackbeard and Bonnet plundered more merchant ships along the east coast. 

In the summer of 1718, Bonnet was pardoned and received authorization to turn [[privateer]] against Spanish shipping. However, he soon returned to piracy. He was captured later that year, escaped, and was recaptured. He was found guilty of two counts of piracy and hanged at [[Charleston, South Carolina]] on [[December 10]] [[1718]].

[[User:Clarityfiend|Clarityfiend]] ([[User talk:Clarityfiend|talk]]) 01:03, 14 February 2008 (UTC)
:The current lead is acceptable per [[WP:LEAD|guidelines]]. I think your proposed lead cuts out a number of important details that should be mentioned in the lead. &lt;span style=&quot;background:#E0FFFF;color:#007FFF;font-family:Georgia;&quot;&gt;[[User:Nishkid64|Nishkid64]] ([[User talk:Nishkid64|talk]])&lt;/span&gt; 23:53, 15 February 2008 (UTC)

::Acceptable does not mean good. A lead section should be concise; the current version is far too detailed IMO. That's what the body of the article is for. How about a third opinion? I see that there are editors that specialize in intros. [[User:Clarityfiend|Clarityfiend]] ([[User talk:Clarityfiend|talk]]) 00:52, 16 February 2008 (UTC)
:::I agree that lead sections should be concise, but they need to serve as a standalone outline of the entire article. The proposed lead fails to do that. It goes from Bonnet and Blackbeard in December 1717 straight to his pardon in summer of 1718. Bonnet achieved his notability during this small period of time (recall that he had a short pirating career), so the details in between need to be covered. This is what the current lead does. I'll try to remove some unnecessary details, but I won't go as far as your version. Also, this issue was brought up previously, but another editor, Carre, who is quite familiar with FACs and such, said the current lead is fine. &lt;span style=&quot;background:#E0FFFF;color:#007FFF;font-family:Georgia;&quot;&gt;[[User:Nishkid64|Nishkid64]] ([[User talk:Nishkid64|talk]])&lt;/span&gt; 04:00, 16 February 2008 (UTC)
::::I don't agree that my version is an inadequate outline of the article. It explains who the subject is, why he is notable, and what his fate was. When three different editors question the quality of the lead, it is time to reconsider your stance. [[User:Clarityfiend|Clarityfiend]] ([[User talk:Clarityfiend|talk]]) 08:41, 18 February 2008 (UTC)
:::::And I have... I've trimmed the lead significantly since the lead issues were first brought up. Your proposed lead is insufficient because it leaves out details between December 1717 and the summer of 1718, a time period when Bonnet achieved most of his infamy, and notability. &lt;span style=&quot;background:#E0FFFF;color:#007FFF;font-family:Georgia;&quot;&gt;[[User:Nishkid64|Nishkid64]] ([[User talk:Nishkid64|talk]])&lt;/span&gt; 14:55, 20 February 2008 (UTC)

==&quot;Treacherous&quot;==
:''Bonnet set sail at once to hunt down his treacherous ex-confederate, but could not find him, and Bonnet never met Blackbeard again.[32] ''

I read the article up to this point and was surprised at the word &quot;treacherous&quot;.  I didn't read about any treachery in the article.  [[User:Tempshill|Tempshill]] ([[User talk:Tempshill|talk]]) 18:56, 23 January 2008 (UTC)
:Blackbeard did not allow Bonnet to command the ''Revenge''. Instead, he basically locked him up in the ''Queen's Anne Revenge'', which is why Bonnet confided to his crew that he would rather live a life of self-exile than be subjected to such treatment. The men had been on good terms before, and this sudden betrayal of sorts is why the word &quot;treacherous&quot; is used. &lt;span style=&quot;background:#E0FFFF;color:#007FFF;font-family:Georgia;&quot;&gt;[[User:Nishkid64|Nishkid64]] ([[User talk:Nishkid64|talk]])&lt;/span&gt; 19:15, 23 January 2008 (UTC)

== Women ==
&lt;s&gt;&quot;Because of marital problems...Bonnet decided to turn to piracy in the summer of 1717.&quot; See the problems women cause? Jk, jk &lt;/s&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;Times New Roman&quot;&gt; &lt;font color=&quot;#800000&quot;&gt;[[User:Bmrbarre|Benjamin]]&lt;/font&gt; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#000080&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Bmrbarre|Scrīptum est]] [[User:Bmrbarre/Me and Wikipedia|-]] [[Special:Contributions/Bmrbarre|Fecī]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 22:33, 23 January 2008 (UTC)
:Careful! You're asking for an unnecessary argument. [[User:Brutannica|Brutannica]] ([[User talk:Brutannica|talk]]) 05:23, 24 January 2008 (UTC)
::Yeah, that's probably not the best thing to be joking about. &lt;span style=&quot;background:#E0FFFF;color:#007FFF;font-family:Georgia;&quot;&gt;[[User:Nishkid64|Nishkid64]] ([[User talk:Nishkid64|talk]])&lt;/span&gt; 02:25, 25 January 2008 (UTC)
:::Apparently some people can't take a joke. For every woman I have offended, I'm sorry. &lt;font face=&quot;Times New Roman&quot;&gt; &lt;font color=&quot;#800000&quot;&gt;[[User:Bmrbarre|Benjamin]]&lt;/font&gt; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#000080&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Bmrbarre|Scrīptum est]] [[User:Bmrbarre/Me and Wikipedia|-]] [[Special:Contributions/Bmrbarre|Fecī]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 00:53, 6 February 2008 (UTC)

== Proposal to remove date-autoformatting ==
Dear fellow contributors

[[Wikipedia:Manual_of_Style_%28dates_and_numbers%29#Date_autoformatting|MOSNUM]] no longer encourages date autoformatting, having evolved over the past year or so from the mandatory to the optional after much discussion there and elsewhere of the disadvantages of the system. Related to this, MOSNUM prescribes [[Wikipedia:Manual_of_Style_%28dates_and_numbers%29#Full_date_formatting|rules for the raw formatting]], irrespective of whether or not dates are autoformatted. [[Wikipedia:Manual_of_Style_%28links%29#Overlinking_and_underlinking|MOSLINK]] and [[Wikipedia:Context#What_generally_should_not_be_linked|CONTEXT]] are consistent with this. 

There are at least six disadvantages in using date-autoformatting, which I've capped here:
{{hidden|contentstyle=border:1px solid #C0C0C0; |headerstyle=color:black; background: #C0C0C0; |header= Disadvantages of date-autoformatting|content=&lt;/br&gt;

*'''(1) In-house only'''
:*(a) It works only for the WP &quot;elite&quot;. 
:*(b) To our readers out there, it displays all-too-common inconsistencies in raw formatting in bright-blue underlined text, yet conceals them from WPians who are logged in and have chosen preferences.  
:*(c) It causes visitors to query why dates are bright-blue and underlined.

*'''(2) Avoids what are merely trivial differences'''
:*(a) It is trivial whether the order is day–month or month–day. It is more trivial than color/colour and realise/realize, yet our consistency-within-article policy on spelling ([[WP:ENGVAR]]) has worked very well. English-speakers readily recognise both date formats; all dates after our signatures are international, and no one objects.

*'''(3) Colour-clutter: the bright-blue underlining of all dates'''
:*(a) It dilutes the impact of high-value links.
:*(b) It makes the text slightly harder to read.
:*(c) It doesn't improve the appearance of the page.

*'''(4) Typos and misunderstood coding'''
:*(a) There's a disappointing error-rate in keying in the auto-function; not bracketing the year, and enclosing the whole date in one set of brackets, are examples.
:*(b) Once autoformatting is removed, mixtures of US and international formats are revealed in display mode, where they are  much easier for WPians to pick up  than in edit mode; so is the use of the wrong format in country-related articles.
:*(c) Many WPians don't understand date-autoformatting—in particular, how if differs from ordinary linking; often it's applied simply because it's part of the furniture.

*'''(5) Edit-mode clutter'''
:*(a) It's more work to enter an autoformatted date, and it doesn't make the edit-mode text any easier to read for subsequent editors.

*'''(6) Limited application'''
:*(a) It's incompatible with date ranges (&quot;January 3–9, 1998&quot;, or &quot;3–9 January 1998&quot;, and &quot;February–April 2006&quot;) and slashed dates (&quot;the night of May 21/22&quot;, or &quot;... 21/22 May&quot;).
:*(b) By policy, we avoid date autoformatting in such places as quotations; the removal of autoformatting avoids this inconsistency.}}

Removal has generally been met with positive responses by editors. I'm seeking feedback about this proposal to remove it from the main text (using a script) in about a week's time on a trial basis. The original input formatting would be seen by all WPians, not just the huge number of visitors; it would be plain, unobtrusive text, which would give greater prominence to the high-value links. BTW, anyone has the right to object, and my aim is not to argue against people on the issue. [[User:Tony1|&lt;font color=&quot;darkgreen&quot;&gt;'''Tony'''&lt;/font &gt;]] [[User talk:Tony1|&lt;font color=&quot;darkgreen&quot;&gt;(talk)&lt;/font &gt;]] 12:35, 30 July 2008 (UTC)

== Method of surrender ==
For the second time I have removed a reference to Bonnet's crew raising a white flag in surrender.  There could have been a white flag used, but surrender at sea in those days could also be signified simply by lowering the battle flag or by striking the sails.  Without more evidence, the article should not speculate on how Bonnet's pirates surrendered. [[User:Piratedan|Pirate Dan]] ([[User talk:Piratedan|talk]]) 14:07, 3 October 2008 (UTC)

== Early piracy phase ==
The accounts in Butler regarding Bonnet's earliest piracy actions may need further scrutiny. Will try to do so in coming month. --[[User:Vincent pearse|Vincent pearse]] ([[User talk:Vincent pearse|talk]]) 15:42, 18 January 2009 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>89izwy3432t3eq2tw1gkm7xp849suwp</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
