<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Pennsylvania-class battleship</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>6391142</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750342144</id>
      <parentid>746361567</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-19T04:07:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Crisco 1492</username>
        <id>356335</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>schedule</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9944">{{Article history
|maindate=December 7, 2016
|action1=FAC
|action1date=10:02, 19 May 2013
|action1link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Pennsylvania-class battleship/archive1
|action1result=promoted
|action1oldid=555767389
|currentstatus=FA}}
{{WPMILHIST|class=FA|B1=yes|B2=yes|B3=yes|B4=yes|B5=yes|Maritime=yes|US=yes|WWII=yes|OMT=1}}
{{WikiProject Ships|class=FA|B1=yes|B2=yes|B3=yes|B4=yes|B5=yes}}


==Clarifications==
In several US battleship class articles, there is a standard paragraph at the end regarding &quot;'Standard type battleship' concept of the US Navy...&quot;
It states: &quot;a tight tactical radius (~700 yards)&quot;. This doesn't make any sense. A tactical radius of a battleship should be something along the lines of 700nm, not 700 yards. Is it perhaps denoting a TURNING radius of 700 yards, a DEFENSIVE radius of 700 yards (seems small), or is it just a unit error and should be Nautical miles instead of Yards? [[User:BBODO|BBODO]] 15:49, 17 November 2006 (UTC)

:The &quot;radius of action&quot; listed in &lt;ref&gt;Stefan Terzibaschitsch, ''Der Schlachtschiffe der US Navy im 2. Weltkreig'', J.F. Lehmanns Verlag, 1977.&lt;/ref&gt; is 8,000 nautical miles at cruising speed of 12 knots for the Pennsylania class. The tactical radius of 700 yards denotes turning radius giving all standard type battleships similar operating characteristics. [[User:Naaman Brown|Naaman Brown]] ([[User talk:Naaman Brown|talk]]) 17:07, 10 June 2009 (UTC)

==Improvements to this page==
This is supposed to be about the Pennsylvania Class Battleships and not about the indivual ships.  I would expect this to be about the design and influence of the class along with flaws and not a deployment record.  All in all a pretty poor page. I am about to begin upgrading it.  Any and all comments are highly desired please. [[User:Tirronan|Tirronan]] 22:33, 12 April 2007 (UTC)

== Underwater Protection ==
This section doesn't seem to make much sense. An Artillery shell in a torpedo? A 'Davis' Torpedo? It sounds as if someone's heard about Davis Ammunition&lt;ref&gt;http://www.big-ordnance.com/Davis/davis_ammunition.htm&lt;/ref&gt; and gotten confused; can anyone elucidate as to what this section's trying to say? [[User:Njan|njan]] 15:22, 5 May 2007 (UTC)

:Yes there actually was such an animal, it was called the Davis Torpedo and consisted of a short barrel and projectile housed in a torpedo.  It never made it to actual production but it seemed to hold U.S. Battleship underwater protection systems in some state of confusion.  Norman Friedman's book goes into this at some detail.  In point of fact regular torpedos turned out to be much more dangerous and so it goes.  Actually it also lead to greater understanding of why shells diving under water were actually a hazard later.  Interestingly Japanese shells were designed with this in mind so that if a shell landed short it would fly fairly straight under water for at least a short period and strike underneith the armor belt. [[User:Tirronan|Tirronan]] 16:10, 5 May 2007 (UTC)

:: Great! Any chance of documenting that on wikipedia and/or finding a reference to provide? [[User:Njan|njan]] 16:42, 5 May 2007 (UTC)

Actually I have a great reference for it and I'll put it in tonight.  I am at work right now so pulling out my reference book wouldn't look too good.  [[User:Tirronan|Tirronan]] 20:48, 5 May 2007 (UTC)

== plainlinks ==

The &quot;plainlinks&quot; span is a rarely used technique that makes external references look like interwiki links and is therefore surprising to the the reader when clicked on. It should be replaced by a normal external link per [[WP:CITEFOOT]] &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:NE Ent|NE Ent]]&lt;/small&gt; 12:13, 16 March 2014 (UTC)
: I'm not sure why we need a cite link at all, since that is normally provided on the photograph page. --[[User:Yaush|Yaush]] ([[User talk:Yaush|talk]]) 03:24, 17 March 2014 (UTC)
::{{ec}} Hi NE Ent and Yaush, while I appreciate that plainlinks are rarely used, the approach passed FAC without attracting comment, and it's a better solution than scattering the external link arrows throughout the article. Furthermore, they certainly aren't citations—it's a way of acknowledging credit for the photos (which is also very non-standard, but thankfully Wikipedia allows a wide leeway to article writers), many of which were specifically scanned and uploaded by the National Archives and Records Administration for this article and {{USS|Arizona|BB-39}}. Best regards, [[User:The ed17|Ed]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:The ed17|[talk]]] [[WP:OMT|[majestic titan]]]&lt;/sup&gt; 03:29, 17 March 2014 (UTC)
:::The fact that it passed FAC isn't particularly relevant -- it's such an obscure technique I doubt the reviewer(s) thought to look for it. Per Yaush, I've removed the link altogether. &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:NE Ent|NE Ent]]&lt;/small&gt; 09:26, 17 March 2014 (UTC)
::::And as I've stated, that's a personal choice of mine, and Wikipedia has traditionally given wide stylistic leeway to the people who are writing the article. [[User:The ed17|Ed]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:The ed17|[talk]]] [[WP:OMT|[majestic titan]]]&lt;/sup&gt; 02:28, 18 March 2014 (UTC)
:::::You chose to submit content under the conditions &quot;Work submitted to Wikipedia can be edited, used, and redistributed—by anyone—&quot;. Note per [[Template:Plain_link/doc]] {{tl|Plain link}} is intended for local and interwiki links, not external ones. See also [[Wikipedia_talk:External_links#plainlinks]] &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:NE Ent|NE Ent]]&lt;/small&gt; 13:48, 13 April 2014 (UTC)

On the one hand, [[WP:ELPOINTS|&quot;External links should not normally be used in the body of an article.]]&quot; and &quot;[[WP:OWN|No one, no matter how skilled, or of how high standing in the community, has the right to act as though he or she is the owner of a particular article.]]&quot; On the other, &quot;[[WP:IAR|If a rule prevents you from improving or maintaining Wikipedia, ignore it]]&quot; and &quot;[[WP:MOS|Style and formatting should be consistent within an article, though not necessarily throughout Wikipedia.]]&quot;

The [[WP:CITE|citation style]] used in this article is nonstandard (inasmuch as the general references are not bulleted, some ref tags combine two short citations instead of each short citation having its own tag, and the source links are missing their [[Help:External link icons|icons]]), but this is not an issue so long as the information is presented clearly and succinctly—so long as the reader can find what they need to find. I also note that this article at one time followed a more standard style, and it was probably unnecessary to change it, but that's not in itself a reason to change it back, two years later.

That said...
*The external link in the infobox caption is inconsistent with this article's now-established citation style. It is also a [[WP:DEADLINK|dead link]], which would be easier to repair if there were a full citation instead of a naked external link.
*The use of the &lt;code&gt;plainlinks&lt;/code&gt; css class is highly unusual. As far as I know, this class was created to correctly render internal wikilinks that, for technical reasons, have to be input as external links. The external link icon is a minimalistic way to tell the reader, at a glance, which links will take them away from Wikipedia and which will lead to other articles. If a [[WP:consensus|consensus]] of editors has concluded that hiding this information from the user is preferred, I'm curious to read that discussion.
There's little reason to make dramatic changes to this article simply for the sake of conforming to the Manual of Style. The MoS should support articles, not hinder their growth. If a future editor makes major contributions to this article and finds that the nonstandard citation style is hampering their efforts, it will be worth revisiting, but as it stands now this isn't a battle worth fighting. At the same time, it may be useful for the creator of the nonstandard style to reexamine that work and evaluate which elements are true improvements on the Wikipedia MoS and which are mere expressions of one editor's [[WP:JDL|personal taste]]. [[User:Ibadibam|Ibadibam]] ([[User talk:Ibadibam|talk]]) 07:49, 15 April 2014 (UTC)
:There are nine usages of &quot;plainlinks&quot;, including one which includes everything in the References section. That is wildly excessive, and while we are grateful to have use of the images, they are presumably suitably licensed so &quot;courtesy of&quot; should not be needed—such credits are highly unusual. However, I agree with Ibadibam—there are far worse problems on Wikipedia, and it is not worth pursuing the matter. If it is a real problem, it will eventually be resolved. [[User:Johnuniq|Johnuniq]] ([[User talk:Johnuniq|talk]]) 08:12, 15 April 2014 (UTC)
::It should not be necessary to put &quot;Photograph by ''x'', courtesy of ''y''&quot; in the image captions. That information should be on the file description pages, per [[WP:CREDITS]]. --[[User:Redrose64|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#a80000; background:#ffeeee; text-decoration:inherit&quot;&gt;Red&lt;/span&gt;rose64]] ([[User talk:Redrose64|talk]]) 09:11, 15 April 2014 (UTC)

== Pennsylvania-class battleship for TFA on December 7==
I added Pennsylvania-class battleship to [[Wikipedia:Today's featured article/requests]] for  December 7, the 75th anniversary of the Attack on Pearl Harbor.
:I think more should be added about ''Arizona'' in the &quot;Service histories&quot; section. All that is said is that she was sunk. ''Pennsylvania'' continues to be explained quite thoroughly. I will add something if its agreed upon. Also, why is there a picture in the &quot;Reference&quot; section? I don't recall a lot of other articles that do this.[[User:Pennsy22|Pennsy22]] ([[User talk:Pennsy22|talk]]) 06:08, 26 October 2016 (UTC)
::I agree that adding more to the &quot;Service histories” about the Arizona and the USS Arizona Memorial would be useful.  The references are for other sections of the talk page.  ([[User:Halgin|Halgin]] ([[User talk:Halgin|talk]]) 23:20, 26 October 2016 (UTC))

==References==

{{reflist}}</text>
      <sha1>drd90lza4l7dyxdhupwakcqthpa9iy5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
