<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Stanley Bruce</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>311941</id>
    <revision>
      <id>645075962</id>
      <parentid>574388729</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-02-01T01:21:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SporkBot</username>
        <id>12406635</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Repair [[:Category:Pages using duplicate arguments in template calls|duplicate template args]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23463">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=20:41, 26 July 2013
|action1link=/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=565936228


|action2=FAC
|action2date=10:04, 16 September 2013
|action2link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Stanley Bruce/archive1
|action2result=promoted
|action2oldid=573135375
|currentstatus=FA
|maindate=October 7, 2013
|topic=history
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Military history|British-task-force=yes
|WWI-task-force=yes
|class=FA
}}
{{WikiProject Biography|living=no
|class=FA
|politician-work-group=yes|politician-priority=Mid
|listas=Bruce, Stanley
|military-work-group=yes|military-priority=Low
}}
{{WikiProject Australia|class=FA
|importance=Top
&lt;!-- Wikiproject specific tags --&gt;
|politics=yes
|politics-importance=top
}}
}}


----

==Move back to Stanley Bruce==

[[Wikipedia: naming conventions (names and titles)]] says:

:''When individuals received hereditary peerages after retiring from the post of Prime Minister (unless they are better known for their later career under an additional/alternative title), or for any other reason are known exclusively by their personal names, do not include the peerage dignity. Examples: [[Anthony Eden]] (not &quot;[[Anthony Eden, 1st Earl of Avon]]&quot;), [[Bertrand Russell]] (not &quot;[[Bertrand Russell, 3rd Earl Russell]]&quot;) (but [[Henry Addington, 1st Viscount Sidmouth]] not &quot;[[Henry Addington]]&quot;).''

--This article therefore should live at Stanley Bruce, not 1st Viscount Bruce. [[User:Lacrimosus|Slac]] [[User talk:Lacrimosus|&lt;small&gt;speak up!&lt;/small&gt;]] 08:00, 21 Apr 2005 (UTC)

:I disagree. The naming convention refers to Prime Ministers ''of Great Britain'' who are ennobled, not those of Commonwealth countries. There is a very notable difference, especially given the fact that Australia was so much more closely-tied with Britain then that the post of Australian Prime Minister was not of the prestige and independence it carries today. Therefore, the page should be titled as would be any, for example, Governor-General or local Premier &amp;mdash; ''with'' the title. [[User:Wally|Wally]] 21:04, 25 Apr 2005 (UTC)

::But it seems hard to justify that there should be one rule for British Prime Ministers and another for Australian Prime Ministers especially since as you mention, they were so close.  Moreover, the policy doesn't specifically mention &quot;British&quot;.  The reason for the policy is to ensure that public figures are listed under the name by which they are most frequently known: Lord Houpeton was known as Lord Houpeton, so that's where the page is.  Anthony Eden, despite the fact that he was ennobled after his prime ministership is known as Anthony Eden, and similarly with Bruce.  It's simply a matter of listing the page under what he is most commonly known.  Forrest should simply be listed as Forrest, since histories of his Premiership refer to him as Forrest, not as Lord Forrest. [[User:Lacrimosus|Slac]] [[User talk:Lacrimosus|&lt;small&gt;speak up!&lt;/small&gt;]] 21:59, 25 Apr 2005 (UTC)

Since the title was Viscount Bruce of Melbourne, not Viscount Bruce, it should either be at [[Stanley Bruce]] or [[Stanley Bruce, 1st Viscount Bruce of Melbourne]]. The current location, at any rate, is wrong. [[User:Proteus|Proteus]] [[User_talk:Proteus|(Talk)]] 21:00, 26 Apr 2005 (UTC)

There seems to be a convention not to include the &quot;of&quot; part of British peers' titles. The conventions on this subject are extremely complicated. Only [[User:Emsworth]] seems to understand them, so perhaps you should ask him. [[User:Adam Carr|Adam]] 00:41, 27 Apr 2005 (UTC)

::Every modern peerage is created in two parts: the actual title, and a territorial designation, the latter normally in the form &quot;of X in the County of Y&quot;. [[Margaret Thatcher|Lady Thatcher]], for instance, was created &quot;Baroness Thatcher, of Kesteven in the County of Lincolnshire&quot;; her title is &quot;Baroness Thatcher&quot;, not &quot;Baroness Thatcher of Kesteven&quot;, as the &quot;of Kesteven&quot; is what's normally colloquially referred to as &quot;after the comma&quot;. Some peerages, however, have &quot;of X&quot; bits before as well as after the comma: [[Charlie Falconer, Baron Falconer of Thoroton|Lord Falconer of Thoroton]], for instance, was created &quot;Baron Falconer of Thoroton, of Thoroton in the County of Nottinghamshire&quot;; his title is &quot;Baron Falconer of Thoroton&quot;, not &quot;Baron Falconer&quot;, and he can never correctly be referred to as &quot;Lord Falconer&quot; (though he often is). Bruce's peerage was of the latter type: he was created &quot;Viscount Bruce of Melbourne, of Westminster Gardens in the City of Westminster&quot;; his title was therefore &quot;Viscount Bruce of Melbourne&quot;, not &quot;Viscount Bruce&quot; (there already being a plain &quot;Bruce&quot; title in &quot;Earl Bruce, of Whorlton in the County of York&quot;, an Earldom created as a subsidiary title of the [[Marquess of Ailesbury|Marquessate of Ailesbury]]). [[User:Proteus|Proteus]] [[User_talk:Proteus|(Talk)]] 08:26, 27 Apr 2005 (UTC)

:I've asked him; hopefully he can assist us here. [[User:Lacrimosus|Slac]] [[User talk:Lacrimosus|&lt;small&gt;speak up!&lt;/small&gt;]] 01:05, 27 Apr 2005 (UTC)

Firstly, I would like to note that I cannot claim to know more about the nobility than Proteus, who is truly an expert on the subject. His statement above on territorial designations above is absolutely correct. Thus, the article belongs at either [[Stanley Bruce, 1st Viscount Bruce of Melbourne]], or at [[Stanley Bruce]]. -- [[User:Lord Emsworth|Emsworth]] 10:51, 27 Apr 2005 (UTC)

It's true that he was plain Mr Bruce when he was Prime Minister, but he lived for 38 years after leaving that office, and held a variety of other posts, and for two-thirds of that time he was known as Lord Bruce. One could make a good case that was known to more people as Lord Bruce than he was as Mr Bruce. But I don't much care which title for the article is used: debates like this greatly increase my admiration for Robespierre. [[User:Adam Carr|Adam]] 13:55, 27 Apr 2005 (UTC)

:Don't they everyone...  The simple means of solving debates is that it is a purely [[WP:consensus|consensus]] individual judgment these days, even Debrett's which is probably something Robespierre would burn and I don't own does not stay still.  Every Lord is different we have 'Mellow Scotch Peers wallowing in the well-aged style of the &quot;Earl of Montrose&quot; never Lord Montrose mind, humble hard labouring life peers, subtly intoning in early life &quot;but I was born 1st Earl of Wedgwood-Benn&quot; and the odd courtesy (sons of Marquesses and Dukes) Lord... and subsidiary (son) Viscounts/Earls... who go on the world stage leaving all vestige of UK Royal Graces they have to one side unless invited to proper right royal London or Middle East event when it suits them.  Quite a variety but all adding to the choice available. - [[User:Adam37|&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;'''Adam37'''&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:Adam37|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 20:54, 26 July 2013 (UTC)

== Assessment scale ==

This shows as only of &quot;mid&quot; importance. I must respectfully disagree. He was a PM, and the only PM in Australia to lose his own seat. I'd say that he was very significant. - [[User:Ta bu shi da yu|Ta bu shi da yu]] 07:36, 26 February 2007 (UTC)
:OK but then Barton will have to be high (and maybe Watson)[[User:Grahamec|Grahamec]] 11:48, 14 August 2007 (UTC)
::IIRC Rebecca (or CJ?) and I discussed this a while ago - I set some of the PMs as some were medium some were high, one was reverted, I told them of the inconsistency, and they didn't realise. We were deciding whether to catagorise all Australian PMs as mid or high importance. But we never got around to doing anything :P Wikiproject politics talk page is the place for this. [[User:Timeshift9|Timeshift]] 16:12, 14 August 2007 (UTC)

==Redundant photos==

Timeshift has cluttered this and all the Australian PM articles with redundant, unframed and uncaptioned photos. When I removed them, I was subjected to a torrent of personal abuse. He has now restored them. I am not going to repeat that experience, but someone who knows how to handle obstinate and ill-mannered people like him better than I do should make an effort to persuade him that these photos are ugly and useless, and should be removed. The photos of the official prime ministerial portraits, by the way, are clearly breaches of copyright. [[User:Intelligent Mr Toad|Intelligent Mr Toad]] 11:43, 2 September 2007 (UTC)
: I'm not seeing any evidence of any discussion at all, having checked this page, his talk page and yours. Also, copyright on pictures taken in 1929 or previously would have expired the year after I was born, which was quite a while ago. With allegations of abusive conduct, I would be at least expecting to see some evidence somewhere of dialogue occurring, otherwise it could be viewed as a [[WP:NPA|personal attack]]. [[User talk:Orderinchaos|Orderinchaos]] 11:53, 2 September 2007 (UTC)
::a) You're the only one that takes issue with multiple PM images. b) I don't recall personal abuse (but hey, anything can be seen as abuse these days). c) See above re copyright. d) If you believe the photos are ugly, don't look at the man, or if it's the quality of the picture, find a better quality one. www.pictureaustralia.org is a good place to start. It seems you want to make a fuss for the point of making a fuss. [[User:Timeshift9|Timeshift]] 11:57, 2 September 2007 (UTC)

From Timeshift's talk page, 27 July (now deleted):
:I have deleted all the redundant and uncaptioned photos you added to the Australian Prime Minister articles. Wikipedia is not a photo gallery and is not improved by multiple virtually identical photos. Also, the official PM portraits are not in the public domain. Intelligent Mr Toad 09:17, 27 July 2007 (UTC)
:Bite me. You hear me? Bite me. I'm sick and tired of crap from people like you, I could be annoying like you too but I choose to be productive on wikipedia instead. Repeated again for the hearing impaired: BITE ME. Timeshift 10:38, 27 July 2007 (UTC)

I call that personal abuse, particularly when totally unprovoked - I had never dealt with Timeshift before.

I am not arguing that the old photos of PMs are copyright, only the portraits. The old photos are just ugly and redundant, especially when they are not formatted to Wikipedia style and have no captions. [[User:Intelligent Mr Toad|Intelligent Mr Toad]] 12:13, 2 September 2007 (UTC)
: It appears, now I look, to be at [[User talk:Timeshift9/Archive3#Redundant_photos]]. His reply six hours later with a presumably clearer head lays out his position reasonably clearly. I agree the photos could be better positioned, but I don't have any problem with their being there. On consideration, your original post may have been interpreted as patronising, given its recipient was a user with a reasonably solid history including an FA. [[User talk:Orderinchaos|Orderinchaos]] 12:18, 2 September 2007 (UTC)
::Ah yes, now I remember. For starters, don't accuse me of deleting it. It is still there for all and sundry to read. And how can you argue only the portraits are copyright if they've also been around for over 50 years? And why complain about style or captions? You're more than welcome to fix/add. But removing? Destructive, pointless, and not carried out by anyone except you. [[User:Timeshift9|Timeshift]] 12:20, 2 September 2007 (UTC)

* My original comment to Timeshift was perfectly straightforward and not at all patronising. Adding photos that serve no useful purpose but merely duplicate existing ones, particularly with no frames, no captions, and no regard to positioning, is not appropriate conduct. Nor is using the language directed at me in response to my original comment. I note he is continuing to use a very aggressive tone. This kind of adolescent behaviour is what drives many people away from Wikipedia.
* In most cases it is not a matter of &quot;fix and add.&quot; What is the point of three almost identical photos captioned &quot;Stanley Bruce&quot;? I don't object to multiple photos where they show different things, but these ones, and most of the others Timeshift has added to the PM articles, do not. I repeat my original point that Wikipedia is not a photo gallery.
* The copyright status of photos of the official portraits has been debated here before and they were ruled to be not in the public domain. I'm not a copyright lawyer but that was the consensus of experts. The 50-year rule applies not to the paintings themselves but to the photos of the paintings, which are clearly less than 50 years old and are someone's copyright, unless Timeshift took them himself, which I doubt since photography is not permitted in the Parliament House gallery where they hang. [[User:Intelligent Mr Toad|Intelligent Mr Toad]] 17:08, 2 September 2007 (UTC)
:And you're the only one to take issue with the photos, why? You're more than welcome to find a better looking photo if its the quality you're not happy with, and you're also welcome to fix formatting/layout/caption issues. Update: And i've just fixed them with better photos and captions. It's a nice feeling to contribute instead of taking away from wikipedia. [[User:Timeshift9|Timeshift]] 23:43, 2 September 2007 (UTC)

== Exploiting Fears ==

When you use the phrase &quot;exploited public fears of communism and militant trade unions&quot; it does tend to have a negative connotation even though technically it may be correct. It gives the impression that Bruce improperly or unjustifiably took advantage of the contemporary false fears of communism and militant trade unionism.
Australia in the 1920s was not the same as it is today. Totalitarianism, in one form manifested by Communism, was a very real threat. The western democracies Germany and Italy had either fallen to it or were threatened with it by attempted coups. (The Beer Hall Putsch) Russia had fallen into the horrors of the revolution and the subsequent civil war.
The 1926 British General Strike, [1926_United_Kingdom_general_strike] promoted by the militant unions was something that scared all in the UK, even those in the Labour Party.
The twenties and thirties were more turbulent times.

I would suggest &quot;...won favour by responding to public concerns about communism and militant trade unions..&quot; as a more neutral way to describe his role.

[[User:Edward Carson|Edward Carson]] 01:18, 5 November 2007 (UTC)

:I find that the opposite. Bruce exploited these fears just like Menzies did. [[User:Timeshift9|Timeshift]] 01:48, 5 November 2007 (UTC)

== John Howard - Bennelong Comparisons ==
I removed this:

:He is the only Australian Prime Minister to have suffered this fate ([[John Howard]] become the second, following the results in the [[Australian general election, 2007|2007 general election]] that he has lost his seat of [[Division of Bennelong|Bennelong]] to [[Maxine McKew]]).

because it is not official yet. Please abstain until the result is in. [[User:Doktor Waterhouse|Doktor Waterhouse]] ([[User talk:Doktor Waterhouse|talk]]) 07:43, 26 November 2007 (UTC)
:It is certainly likely that John Howard ''will'' lose his seat, but as I have said it is not yet official. When it does occur I favour the latest edit which states: For more than 70 years , he was the only Australian Prime Minister to have suffered this fate until [[John Howard]] in [[2007]].
But we need to be patient. [[User:Doktor Waterhouse|Doktor Waterhouse]] ([[User talk:Doktor Waterhouse|talk]]) 08:12, 26 November 2007 (UTC)

:Grammatically, I'd prefer: For more than 70 years, until [[John Howard]] lost his seat in the [[Australian general election, 2007|2007 election]], he was the only Australian Prime Minister to have suffered this fate.  --  [[User:JackofOz|JackofOz]] ([[User talk:JackofOz|talk]]) 09:13, 27 November 2007 (UTC)

Once the postal votes are in, perhaps we won't even need to change the page ;)  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/58.167.120.88|58.167.120.88]] ([[User talk:58.167.120.88|talk]]) 07:52, 28 November 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Haha, you don't recover two percent on postal votes mate. All the election analysts have called it for Labor, and McKew and Howard have unofficially declared. But have fun dreaming on :-) [[User:Timeshift9|Timeshift]] ([[User talk:Timeshift9|talk]]) 08:58, 28 November 2007 (UTC)

I'm in favour of waiting until the cabinet (and Parliamentary Secretaries) are sworn in on Monday by the GG before we edit this page. Just to make sure it is official (though I don't think it's in doubt)[[User:Doktor Waterhouse|Doktor Waterhouse]] ([[User talk:Doktor Waterhouse|talk]]) 07:14, 29 November 2007 (UTC)

==McKew and Holloway==
With all the talk about McKew beating Howard (assuming she has), I've been wondering what ever happened to Ted Holloway.  I mean, was he as well-known in his day as Maxine McKew has become in ours?  Was he some sort of cult hero for the Labor Party?  A large proportion of Australians could name Bruce as the only defeated PM in his own seat, but I'd bet less than 1 in 1000 could tell you who beat him.  So, why is that Bruce's defeat has gone down in the political annals, but the man who actually won the seat is even less than a political footnote these days?  --  [[User:JackofOz|JackofOz]] ([[User talk:JackofOz|talk]]) 09:22, 27 November 2007 (UTC)
:Well, it's trivia really isn't it? Only die-hard political historians (Kim Beasley anyone) really know his name. Who really knows what will happen with McKew in terms of her historical longevity?[[User:Doktor Waterhouse|Doktor Waterhouse]] ([[User talk:Doktor Waterhouse|talk]]) 07:12, 29 November 2007 (UTC)

::Maxine was already a well-known public figure, and I'd be very surprised if she ever slipped into the obscurity that seems to have befallen Ted Holloway.  But trivia or not, I'd really like to know more about him.  --  [[User:JackofOz|JackofOz]] ([[User talk:JackofOz|talk]]) 08:43, 29 November 2007 (UTC)

:::You mean like [[Ted Holloway]] and [http://www.adb.online.anu.edu.au/biogs/A140539b.htm his entry in the Australia Dictionary of Biography]? [[User:Timrollpickering|Timrollpickering]] ([[User talk:Timrollpickering|talk]]) 12:23, 29 November 2007 (UTC)

==Only Australian hereditary peer?==

See my query re Clive Baillieu @ [[Talk:Australian peers#Clive Baillieu]].  --  [[User:JackofOz|JackofOz]] ([[User talk:JackofOz|talk]]) 06:43, 20 January 2009 (UTC)

:I've now added this information to [[Australian peers]], with a note that it's unclear whether he was an Australian when he was elevated to the peerage.  Since this may affect the claim that Bruce was the only one, we need to say something about it so as not to mislead people.  But I don't want to end up with a mini-article on Australian peers in this article.  Thoughts on wording?  --  [[User:JackofOz|JackofOz]] ([[User talk:JackofOz|talk]]) 02:35, 29 January 2009 (UTC)

== Place of Birth ??? ==

This article quotes that he was born in Wombalano mansion in Toorak, yet most sources I've seen says he was born in a mansion in Grey Street, St Kilda.  I can only find one source which claims he was born in Toorak (the National Archives of Australia).  Certainly there is a plaque in [[Grey Street, Melbourne|Grey Street, St Kilda]] which is inscribed that this was the place of his birth.

While there is no doubt he grew up in Wombalano, I very much doubt he was born there, as it was apparently built in 1884, a year after Stanley was born .... [http://home.vicnet.net.au/~malvern/whos_who.htm]

So which is correct ???  I suggest the article be mended to reflect the correct place of birth.

--[[User:Biatch|Biatch]] ([[User talk:Biatch|talk]]) 05:42, 1 February 2009 (UTC)

== Support for the White Australia Policy ==

What is the point of including the two quotes in support of the White Australia Policy (WAP)?

The WAP was supported by every Australian Government regardless of ideological persuasion until the mid-1960's. There is no historical evidence to suggest that Bruce was any more committed to the WAP than any of his predecessors or successors or for that matter any of his contemporaries including the opposition ALP.  Indeed, it was the union movement who were the biggest supporters and beneficiaries of the WAP.  The quotes are therefore out of context and give too much weight to that aspect of his government.

These quotes when combined with the “exploited fears” comment cannot be regarded as NPOV.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/114.73.148.119|114.73.148.119]] ([[User talk:114.73.148.119|talk]]) 07:20, 29 June 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:The quotes are quite startling to read in 2010. As you say, there were probably many MPs of the era who had similar opinions. However, this was the Prime Minister of the country making those comments, so they are very historical and relevant. I'm not personally aware of similar quotes from other politicians in that era, but if you know of some, you should add them to the articles of those other politicians as well. Especially if a Prime Minister made speeches in support of White Australia.--'''[[User:Lester|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Lester&lt;/span&gt;]]''' 08:16, 29 June 2010 (UTC)

::Agreed. Removing tag. [[User:Timeshift9|Timeshift]] ([[User talk:Timeshift9|talk]]) 09:27, 29 June 2010 (UTC)

{{Talk:Stanley Bruce/GA1}}

== &quot;Men, Money and Markets&quot; or &quot;Men, Money, Markets&quot; ==
{{resolved}}
Did the official policy name include the word &quot;and&quot;? Sources, eg [http://www.nma.gov.au/primeministers/stanley_bruce][http://adb.anu.edu.au/biography/bruce-stanley-melbourne-5400], differ. (The article currently includes &quot;and&quot;, but the ref that it cites does not!) If we are treating the phrase as a title (capitalising) then we should try to get it right. In any case we should probably wrap it in quotation marks. [[User:Mitch Ames|Mitch Ames]] ([[User talk:Mitch Ames|talk]]) 09:22, 24 August 2013 (UTC)
:* This is a really good point, and thus far I have not found any consistency in the use of the term, except that the 'and' version seems to appear somewhat more. The term is actually not mentioned in legislation, as the policy was enshrined in a series of different acts. In parliament and in the newspapers, the use varies - Bruce himself in speeches says both. The Trove database records both phrasings in widespread use at the time: [http://trove.nla.gov.au/newspaper/result?q=%22men%2C+money%2C+and+markets%22 Men, Money and Markets] [http://trove.nla.gov.au/newspaper/result?q=%22men%2C+money%2C+markets%22 Men, Money, Markets]. Confusingly, Bruce also swaps the word order in some speeches to [http://trove.nla.gov.au/ndp/del/article/40678533?searchTerm=%22men,%20money,%20markets%22&amp;searchLimits= 'money, men and markets']. Thus I simply adopted the phrasing I found to be most commonly used in press and by Bruce himself, as I do not think there was, technically speaking, an official policy name. [[User:Unus Multorum|Unus Multorum]] ([[User talk:Unus Multorum|talk]]) 06:03, 25 August 2013 (UTC)

:::I suggest that the words ought not be capitalised then, because the phrase (in any of its variations) is not a proper noun. [[User:Mitch Ames|Mitch Ames]] ([[User talk:Mitch Ames|talk]]) 13:34, 26 August 2013 (UTC)
:::* Done! [[User:Unus Multorum|Unus Multorum]] ([[User talk:Unus Multorum|talk]]) 03:40, 2 September 2013 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>t8mai3h0g75jfy0jhbilf3ekq178zz6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
