<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Song dynasty</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>507601</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745992982</id>
      <parentid>719111435</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-24T17:01:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Kanguole</username>
        <id>5563803</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* top */ add oldid for FA</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="35321">{{Vital article|level=4|topic=History|class=FA}}
{{Article history
|action1=PR
|action1date=07:41, 17 April 2007
|action1link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Song Dynasty/archive1
|action1result=reviewed
|action1oldid=123405169

|action2=FAC
|action2date=21:24, 28 April 2007
|action2link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Song Dynasty/archive1
|action2result=not promoted
|action2oldid=126341275

|action3=GAN
|action3date=01:19, 1 May 2007
|action3result=listed
|action3oldid=127306646

|action4=FAC
|action4date=18:13, 25 August 2007
|action4link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Song Dynasty
|action4result=promoted
|action4oldid=153281099

|action5=FTC
|action5date=20:33, 24 September 2007
|action5link=Wikipedia:Featured topic candidates/Song Dynasty
|action5result=promoted
|action5oldid=159127766

|action6=FTR
|action6date=16:08, 11 October 2009
|action6link=Wikipedia:Featured topic removal candidates/Song Dynasty/archive1
|action6result=kept
|action6oldid=319251208

|action7=FTR
|action7date=17:19, 29 March 2010
|action7link=Wikipedia:Featured topic removal candidates/Song Dynasty/archive2
|action7result=demoted
|action7oldid=352199643

|action8=FTC
|action8date=04:00, 29 November 2011
|action8link=Wikipedia:Featured topic candidates/Song Dynasty/archive2
|action8result=promoted
|action8oldid=463131466

|ftname=Song Dynasty
|ftmain=yes
|topic=History
|currentstatus=FA
|maindate=August 13, 2009
}}
{{On this day|date1=2004-03-19|oldid1=6413881|date2=2005-03-19|oldid2=16334945|date3=2006-03-19|oldid3=44443576|date4=2007-03-19|oldid4=116146037|date5=2008-03-19|oldid5=199354568|date6=2009-02-04|oldid6=268412554|date7=2010-02-04|oldid7=341943287|date8=2011-01-09|oldid8=406936150|date9=2012-02-04|oldid9=474811389|date10=2015-02-04|oldid10=645579273|date11=2016-02-04|oldid11=703061974}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject China|class=FA|importance=Top|history=yes}}
{{WikiProject East Asia|class=FA|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Former countries|class=FA|B-Class-1=yes|B-Class-2=yes|B-Class-3=yes|B-Class-4=yes|B-Class-5=yes}}
{{WikiProject Archaeology|class=FA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=FA|Chinese=y}}
}}

==PICTURE==
The picture of the 'trebuchet' is actually the drum-odometer described beneath the trebuchet section.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/147.8.250.47|147.8.250.47]] ([[User talk:147.8.250.47|talk]]) 03:25, 26 November 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==MAP==
Please kindly be noted that Chinese never ruled Taiwan during the Song dynasty, so Taiwan should not be colored as part of it on map.  The first Chinese administrative body was installed on ths island only after Manchurians conquered the Zheng Clan in 1683.  
[[User:ashinakhan|ashinakhan]] 13:10, 24 May 2006 (UTC)
:And you don't think the Zheng clan was Chinese?  --[[User:Nlu|Nlu]] ([[User talk:Nlu|talk]]) 15:25, 24 May 2006 (UTC)
:: Don't deliberately conflate ethnicity and political rule. Mainlander, right?--[[User:203.70.89.231|203.70.89.231]] 15:59, 8 February 2007 (UTC)
:::The fact that you'd think so indicates how people who think like you view people who don't agree with you politically to all be enemies.  --[[User:Nlu|Nlu]] ([[User talk:Nlu|talk]])


-------
Did the Southern Song themselves admit to being tributaries of the Jurchen? [[User:John Kenney|john]] [[User_talk:John Kenney|k]] 05:51, 9 May 2005 (UTC)

:That line (&quot;Because Chinese diplomatic theory did not recognize relations between equal states, the Southern Song was technically a tributary state of the northern dynasty&quot;) doesn't seem to make sense to me either.  In other words, how does the conclusion follow from the first part?  It needs more support; until then, I'm going to delete it. [[User:TresÁrboles|TresÁrboles]] 04:14, 23 Jun 2005 (UTC)

==GDP==

:From a standard of living perspective, the GDP per capita Chinese under the Song Dynasty was about $600 in today's dollars. Western Europe had slowly declined from this level in 1 AD to $400 by 1000 AD. Western Europe started to become slightly wealthier than a stagnant China by 1300. ''By 1800, Western European GDP/capita reached three times that of a China entering a period of decline. And by 1900, the gap expanded to an eight-fold difference. During the height of Communism in the 1960s, GDP/capita in Europe was 16 times as great -- a trend that began to reverse sharply in the 1980s under China's open policy.''

Isn't the indicated section a bit off the subject?
--[[User:24.42.130.57|24.42.130.57]] 22:05, 8 October 2005 (UTC)

-------

Why are the shihao all refered to as &quot;too tedious&quot;?  That seems a trite excuse for laziness.  Or did the emperors themselves find their names thus, and then never allow their selection? --Baixue 9 December 2005

== White gap ==
Why is there a white gap next to the Song in the History of China table?--[[User:Countakeshi|Countakeshi]] 07:42, 17 December 2005 (UTC)
:I don't see one.  Can you try a different browser and see if same thing still happens?  (I use Safari.)  --[[User:Nlu|Nlu]] ([[User talk:Nlu|talk]]) 07:47, 17 December 2005 (UTC)
::I just got rid of it.--[[User:Countakeshi|Countakeshi]] 07:52, 17 December 2005 (UTC)

I've read through the whole thing and I'm quite disappointed that Yue Fei (岳飛) wasn't mentioned at all.  There should be at least one reference to this icon.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/99.244.249.39|99.244.249.39]] ([[User talk:99.244.249.39|talk]]) 05:02, 31 July 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
::Hah! Apparently you didn't read hard enough. He's mentioned in the &quot;Southern Song&quot; sub-section of History in this article, and he is discussed at some length in [[History of the Song Dynasty]]. Is Yue Fei all you care about? Put things into a bigger 319-year perspective here.--&lt;strong&gt;[[User:PericlesofAthens|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;Pericles of Athens&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:PericlesofAthens|&lt;font color=&quot;#0000CD&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 05:55, 31 July 2008 (UTC)

==Song Duzong==

I'm confused why an article is not created for this emperor. Surely we don't want gaps in the chain. --[[User:CharlieHuang|CharlieHuang]] 18:03, 12 February 2006 (UTC)
* Create it then. That's what Wikipedia's for. Jesus Christ, people.--[[User:203.70.89.231|203.70.89.231]] 15:56, 8 February 2007 (UTC)

== Founder? ==

was the founder really who is named in the article or was it Zhao Kuangyin?
:Zhao Kuangyin and Taizu of Song are the same person.  --[[User:Nlu|Nlu]] ([[User talk:Nlu|talk]]) 04:55, 4 December 2006 (UTC)

==where did this info come from?==
:&quot;Accompanying this was the beginnings of what one might term the Chinese industrial revolution. For example the historian Robert Hartwell has estimated that per capita iron output rose sixfold between 806 and 1078, such that, by 1078 China was producing 125,000 &quot;

i can not find this anywere else, where did it come from? &lt;small&gt; — The preceding [[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[User:Trekkie711|Trekkie711]] ([[User talk:Trekkie711|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Trekkie711|contribs]]) 03:43, 7 December 2006 (UTC).&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- HagermanBot Auto-Unsigned --&gt;

:Try [http://donwagner.dk/SongAdmin/SongAdmin.pdf www.staff.hum.ku.dk/dbwagner/SongAdmin/SongAdmin.pdf]. --[[User talk:Gwern |Gwern]] [[Special:Contributions/Gwern | (contribs)]] 05:48 [[7 December]] [[2006]] (GMT)

==population comparison==

The article states: &quot;For example it has been estimated that Hangzhou had more than 400,000 inhabitants by 1200: far larger than any European city;&quot; But [[Constantinople#The_Komnenoi_1081-1185]] states that estimates of Constantinople's population range from 100,000 to 500,000.

== Accidential deletion ==

I accidently deleted information as I was trying add more.  Can anyone who knows how please restore the information I accidently deleted without deleting my additions?  [[User:Ludahai|ludahai 魯大海]] 02:14, 24 February 2007 (UTC)

==Featured Article Status?==

After editing the section for &quot;China's First Standing Navy&quot; and adding tons of art pics, this article is looking very, very good. In fact, I think so highly of it now that I think I'll request to have it as a featured article. Anyone object?

--[[User:PericlesofAthens|PericlesofAthens]] 09:03, 26 March 2007 (UTC)

==Population question==
As an editor who knows very little about this topic, I have trouble following this bit from the opening: 

''Between the 10th and 11th centuries, the population of China doubled in size. This growth came about through expanded rice cultivation in central and southern China, along with the production of abundant food surpluses. Within its borders, the Northern Song Dynasty had a population of some 100 million people.''

The Northern Song is defined just below as lasting from 960–1127.. so I can't quite tell if the population figure of 100 million is before or after the population doubling. I reordered the sentences for some hoped for clarity, but it is still not quite clear, I think. [[User:Pfly|Pfly]] 08:36, 21 April 2007 (UTC)
:Thanks for the edits Pfly! And yes, during the Northern Song (actually starting from the early 10th century), the population did rise from 50 million to 100 million.--[[User:PericlesofAthens|PericlesofAthens]] 14:07, 21 April 2007 (UTC)

==GA Review==

'''High quality prose, including proper spelling, grammar, and clear language. Also look for proper formatting and organization of the article, with appropriate use of wikilinks, sections, table of contents, and general organization as spelled out in the Manual of Style.''' 
There are some issues here.
**Like in the past articles, Needham's volumes need to have titles.
**This sentance from the lead ''During the Song Dynasty, China's northern borders were threatened by the Khitans of the Liao Dynasty, the Tanguts of the Western Xia Dynasty, and the Jurchens of the Jin dynasty.'' must be moved or rewritten. It feels out of place in the context of the paragraph. Perhaps mentions that the Song dynasty as whole was constantly threatened from outside its borders to add some context which is sorely lacking in the lead
*'''Adequate referencing, preferably with the use of either inline or Harvard citations '''
Good references, but they can be improved. I am a believer that each paragraph must have at least one reference (with the exception of the lead). There are some paragraphs that do not have any references.
**1st in founding of the song
**1st in partisans, and factions...
**1st and 3rd in 'From Northern Song...
**1st, 4th and 5th (the 4th and 5th paragraphs are too short as it stands, and should probably me merged) in Mongol invasion...
*'''There is appropriate broadness of coverage of the topic '''
I have some issues here, they are disccused below.
**The history section is too long. I would suggest cutting it down by a significant amount and spinning off a seperate article called [[History of the Song Dynasty]]
**Normally length would not always be an issue here, but this article is already long as it is, and doesn't adequatly dedicate enough to the Society, culture, economy, and technology section. Ideally, the history section and the 'Society, culture... sections' should be roughly the same size. This can't always be achived but as it stands now, the history section comprises about 75% of the article, compared the 25% for the second part. The percentage should be no less than 60/40, in my opinion. The article is about the dynasty after all, and not just the history. Here are some suggestions on how to remdy this:
***Printing should be expanded beyond one sentance, and perhaps even made into a section of its own. Consider discussing [[Bi Sheng]] and movable type printing (you can probably incorporate some of the text from the technology article), multi-colour printing (which began in 1107), as well as the social effects of printing on China. Printing contributed to the popularaziation of the examination system, as well as the rise of neo-confucianism.
***I would also suggest spinning off gunpowder into its own section, as it was an extremely important innovation of the Song dynasty. You could probably just incorporate much of what has already been written in the Song technology article.
***The architecture section merits a bit of expansion that can use text from the architecture article
*** Expand the economy section beyond just one paragraph. I would dedicate one paragraph to each of the following (all of which are written in the economy article), paper money, the Needham question, and trade
***Neo-Confucianism should have its own section due to its prominence in this period, and its important during subsequent Chinese dynasties.
***Finally, expand the culture section to incorporate more from the culture article
*'''It is written from a neutral point of view.''' 
It is.
*'''It has not been the subject of recent editwars (check the history) '''
No edit wars
*'''If images are used, that they are free images, or if they are copyright, that their use is covered by Wikipedia's fair use guidelines'''
&lt;s&gt;There is a problem with the licensing of the Liao Dynasty Guanyin. This image should probably be replaced. The rest of the images are good.&lt;/s&gt;
:I looked at the image's talk page and it appears as though this issue has been resolved.[[User:Zeus1234|Zeus1234]] 18:05, 29 April 2007 (UTC)

Overall, it is a good article, but it still needs some work to achieve GA status. I will put it on hold for the time being to see if any work can be done to fix the deficits I have mentioned. If you have any questions, please do not hesitate to ask. [[User:Zeus1234|Zeus1234]] 05:33, 29 April 2007 (UTC)

After reading the spinoff articles about the Song dynasty, I am confident these changes can be easily applied, and would strongly recommend you also spin off a history article to make the history section here not as long.[[User:Zeus1234|Zeus1234]] 15:31, 29 April 2007 (UTC)

:One more thing that I should add. As there is now more emphasis on Song social history, the lead should also reflect this and incorporate more information about social history.[[User:Zeus1234|Zeus1234]] 03:32, 30 April 2007 (UTC)

::I just noticed something else in the current revision that should be addressed. The new history section should be subdivided into two sections, Northern Song and Southern Song, as these were two distinct periods in the history of the dynasty.[[User:Zeus1234|Zeus1234]] 03:49, 30 April 2007 (UTC)

: I'd like to point out that there are further image-related problems.  --[[User talk:Iamunknown|Iamunknown]] 03:50, 30 April 2007 (UTC)
::Such as?[[User:Zeus1234|Zeus1234]] 04:25, 30 April 2007 (UTC)


==Alive Date==

Is it really necessary to list the date when they are alive? 
for example:
Tong Guan (1054-1126 AD)
Su Shi (1037-1101 AD)
Wang Anshi (1021-1086 AD)

Would it be better off if the date was deleted? &lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[Special:Contributions/65.24.135.38|65.24.135.38]] ([[User talk:65.24.135.38|talk]]) 06:14, 1 May 2007 (UTC).&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- HagermanBot Auto-Unsigned --&gt;
:Yes, it is very important, especially since the Song Dynasty encompassed several different generations over more than 300 years. For example, you can see that the Neo-Confucian philosopher Cheng Yi (1033-1107) clearly lived before and influenced the philosopher Zhu Xi (1130-1200), and were not contemporaries in any sense. If the Song Dynasty was only 10 years long, yeah, I could see what you're saying. But the Song Dynasty encompassed 4 different centuries (of the Christian era).--[[User:PericlesofAthens|PericlesofAthens]] 08:05, 1 May 2007 (UTC)

::While I agreed it is useful in some cases to list the date, such as the reign of the emperor. However, I felt adding date to every single important official considerably decreased the readability of the article, making it more difficult for the reader enjoy the article.  If the reader really want to find out when the person in question is alive couldn't they accomplish same thing by clicking on the link and read their biography? For example, in the article for Roman Empire (http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_Empire) there is no date appended to every single individual mentioned in the article. Forsake for readability, the dates should be deleted unless it is absolutely needed for the discussion. &lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[Special:Contributions/65.24.135.38|65.24.135.38]] ([[User talk:65.24.135.38|talk]]) 04:08, 2 May 2007 (UTC).&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- HagermanBot Auto-Unsigned --&gt;

== Lead ==

This article is currently around 20,000 characters, so the lead should be 2 to 3 paragraphs per [[WP:LEAD]]. [[User:Cliff smith|Cliff smith]] 23:03, 2 May 2007 (UTC)


==The conventional long name of the infobox==
唐朝正式國號為「唐」，而非「大唐」。元朝是中國史上第一個把「大」字加入正式國號的朝代。參見明朝人朱國禎《涌幢小品》卷二「國號」條：「國號上加大字，始於胡元，我朝因之。……其言大漢、大唐、大宋者，乃臣子及外夷尊稱之詞。」 [http://zh.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E5%94%90%E6%9C%9D]. Same as Tang Dynasty, it explained that Song Dynasty's native name is &quot;Song&quot; but not &quot;Great Song&quot; or &quot;The Song Dynasty&quot; --[[User:Lmmnhn|Lmmnhn]] 08:49, 4 August 2007 (UTC)

== Image overlapping text ==

When I made the images default size, one of them now overlaps the text and I can't seem to fix it. [&lt;nowiki&gt;[Image:Wood Bodhisattva 2.jpg|thumb|right|A seated wooden [[Bodhisattva]] statue, [[Jin Dynasty, 1115-1234|Jin Dynasty]] (1115&amp;ndash;1234).]]&lt;/nowiki&gt;. Very sorry to do that and sorry I cannot figure out how to fix it. Sincerely, [[User:Mattisse|Mattisse]] 01:58, 11 August 2007 (UTC)
::That's ok, it looks like [[user:Balthazarduju]] fixed that.--[[User:PericlesofAthens|PericlesofAthens]] 08:14, 11 August 2007 (UTC)

== Lead ==

It bothers me that you have great detail about the social life (festival, clubs, games etc.) in the lead, but none of it is mentioned in the article. Could some the the last paragraph in the lead be wittled down and put under Society?  Sincerely,  [[User:Mattisse|Mattisse]] 01:58, 12 August 2007 (UTC)
::Good point, I will put that down there now.--&lt;strong&gt;[[User:PericlesofAthens|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;Pericles of Athens&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:PericlesofAthens|&lt;font color=&quot;#0000CD&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 15:34, 12 August 2007 (UTC)

== disambig ==

The following need disambig:&lt;br /&gt;clepsydra&lt;br /&gt;date&lt;br /&gt;grid&lt;br /&gt;Luohan&lt;br /&gt;pavilion&lt;br /&gt;postal service&lt;br /&gt;transparent&lt;br /&gt;[[User:Randomblue|Randomblue]] ([[User talk:Randomblue|talk]]) 19:05, 21 February 2008 (UTC)
::Fixed every one.--&lt;strong&gt;[[User:PericlesofAthens|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;Pericles of Athens&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:PericlesofAthens|&lt;font color=&quot;#0000CD&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 19:42, 23 February 2008 (UTC)

Another occurrence of [[Luohan]] and [[pavilion]] still need disambig. Also, [[pharmaceutical]] links to 'pharmaceutical company', which should maybe be corrected. [[User:Randomblue|Randomblue]] ([[User talk:Randomblue|talk]]) 22:17, 27 February 2008 (UTC)
::Done and done. Anything else?--&lt;strong&gt;[[User:PericlesofAthens|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;Pericles of Athens&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:PericlesofAthens|&lt;font color=&quot;#0000CD&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 04:49, 28 February 2008 (UTC)

Things I'm not sure about/suggestions:&lt;br /&gt;The Jurchen -&gt; the Jurchens&lt;br /&gt;Xian -&gt; Xi'an&lt;br /&gt;gunpowder is linked 4 times, maybe a bit too much for such a basic notion&lt;br /&gt;Shen Kuo is linked 6 times&lt;br /&gt;pagoda tower -&gt; pagoda&lt;br /&gt;
[[User:Randomblue|Randomblue]] ([[User talk:Randomblue|talk]]) 16:35, 28 February 2008 (UTC)

Ah yes, one other thing, the picture descriptions which aren't proper sentences (i.e. no verb) should not have a dot at the end. [[User:Randomblue|Randomblue]] ([[User talk:Randomblue|talk]]) 16:37, 28 February 2008 (UTC)


Population
the article states that the population doubled between the 10th and 11th centuries.  no time passed between these two centuries: one ended and another began. is the meaning that DURING these two centuries, ie, over two hundred years, the population doubled then the article should be changed.
[[User:Daiyounger|Daiyounger]] ([[User talk:Daiyounger|talk]]) 18:59, 19 March 2008 (UTC)



== Turk Bayan ==

I think M.Rossabi thinks the baarin was turkic clan. For me, I don't believe it , however, most nomads had common features. But scholars usually claim that they are one of Mongol clans of Alanghuo.--[[User:Enerelt|Enerelt]] ([[User talk:Enerelt|talk]]) 09:41, 3 October 2008 (UTC)

== Salt Monopoly? ==

This is an important topic. I thought the paragraph was useful, though perhaps too long for this article. Maybe there should be a full version of the paragraph moved to [[Economy of the Song Dynasty]] even though the significance is as much political, as shown in the references to [[Wang Anshi]]'s reforms in the [[Society of the Song Dynasty]] article.

So should we ask to [[BZsupershot5]]to pare down the paragraph rather than delete it completely? There are references to the Salt Monopoly in the [[Tang Dynasty]] article and an article on the [[salt commission]]. A Wikipedia search &quot;Salt Monopoly&quot; got me a number of hits. &lt;ref&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:Search?search=Salt+Monopoly&amp;sourceid=Mozilla-search&lt;/ref&gt;

Time is not hanging heavy on my hands, but if nobody else starts one in a couple weeks, I might just establish a [[Salt Monopoly (China)]] stub in order to get the ball rolling. [[User:CWH|ch]] ([[User talk:CWH|talk]]) 16:29, 16 March 2009 (UTC)
::The first chief concern here should not be adding content or creating new articles, but gathering a list of credible sources that someone (maybe me) will gather, read, and research in order to take notes and then write a comprehensive paragraph or two in [[Economy of the Song Dynasty]] which summarizes all the material. This is the most scholarly and professional approach, while at the same time takes into consideration the article's existing size and size constraints (see [[WP:SIZE]]). I checked my university library catalogue and found nothing useful in regards to Song-era monopolized industries, let alone salt. I checked journal articles at JSTOR, and although that database seems to have some decent sources on Ming and Qing era salt production and administration, there are no articles which specifically tackle the Song-era salt industry. If my university library and JSTOR don't have any valuable information to offer, good luck to anyone else.--&lt;strong&gt;[[User:PericlesofAthens|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;Pericles of Athens&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:PericlesofAthens|&lt;font color=&quot;#0000CD&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 18:20, 16 March 2009 (UTC)

* I think is impprtnt topic too.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/68.78.32.186|68.78.32.186]] ([[User talk:68.78.32.186|talk]]) 03:59, 22 March 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Northern Song likely typo, please confirm==

I made [[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Song_Dynasty&amp;diff=280147714&amp;oldid=279481604|this edit]] because &quot;martial status&quot; was very likely a typo for &quot;marital status.&quot; Can you confirm if this is historically correct? If [[wikt:martial]] was in fact intended, perhaps it would be clearer to say something like &quot;military position.&quot;  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Mrevan|Mrevan]] ([[User talk:Mrevan|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Mrevan|contribs]]) 19:24, 29 March 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
::It's fixed.--&lt;strong&gt;[[User:PericlesofAthens|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;Pericles of Athens&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:PericlesofAthens|&lt;font color=&quot;#0000CD&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 19:29, 29 March 2009 (UTC)

== [[Only a Northern Song]] ==

George Harrison's song was about the Song Dynasty, I believe.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/68.226.20.192|68.226.20.192]] ([[User talk:68.226.20.192|talk]]) 06:47, 1 April 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Nice try. Still, since [[Northern Song]] redirects to a section of this page, I wonder whether there should be a disambiguation link at the top of the section, to dab [[Only a Northern Song]] and [[Northern Songs]]:
::''For other uses, see [[Northern Song (disambiguation)]].''
:Or is this overkill? — [[User:Sjorford|sjorford]][[User talk:Sjorford|++]] 12:47, 11 June 2009 (UTC)

== Congratulations ==

Well done to all the editors who worked on this excellent article. [[User:Eusebeus|Eusebeus]] ([[User talk:Eusebeus|talk]]) 03:52, 13 August 2009 (UTC)
:Thanks. It was mostly little ole me. Lol. This is one of my older ones, actually. My newer featured articles are perhaps written to a higher standard. Anyways, thanks for taking an interest in this one. Cheers.--&lt;strong&gt;[[User:PericlesofAthens|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;Pericles of Athens&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:PericlesofAthens|&lt;font color=&quot;#0000CD&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 04:07, 13 August 2009 (UTC)
::I love Chinese History, so I owe a debt of interest to your work on this article. Any plans to do the [[Three Kingdoms]]? I wouldn't mind giving it a go myself. [[User:MasterOfHisOwnDomain|MasterOfHisOwnDomain]] ([[User talk:MasterOfHisOwnDomain|talk]]) 09:06, 13 August 2009 (UTC)
:Echoed, a good article. [[User:SGGH|SGGH]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User_talk:SGGH|ping!]]&lt;/sup&gt; 11:39, 13 August 2009 (UTC)

==Coinage==
[[File:Chinese Seisou Genbou coin.jpg|thumb|[[Northern Song]] coin (聖宋元寶).]]
[[Northern Song]] Chinese coin (聖宋元寶). [[User:Per Honor et Gloria|''&lt;b&gt;&lt;Font color=&quot;#FF0000&quot;&gt;Per&amp;nbsp;&lt;/Font&gt;&lt;Font color=&quot;#FF8000&quot;&gt;Honor&amp;nbsp;&lt;/Font&gt;&lt;Font color=&quot;Orange&quot;&gt;et&amp;nbsp;&lt;/Font&gt;&lt;Font color=&quot;#FFC000&quot;&gt;Gloria&lt;/Font&gt;&lt;/b&gt;'']]&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Per Honor et Gloria|&lt;big&gt;✍&lt;/big&gt;]] 20:12, 6 March 2010 (UTC)

==Digital Gazetteer of the Song Dynasty==
This database tracking demographic and political geographic change during the Song era is (finally) being publicly released (please take a look over at http://songgis.ucmercedlibrary.info for release notes and details), and I'd be happy to license any of the visualizations created, or create new visualizations based on the underlying data, for this or other Song-related wikipedia articles.  You can get ahold of me on my user page or by looking up my contact information.  [[User:Elijahmeeks|Elijahmeeks]] ([[User talk:Elijahmeeks|talk]]) 03:31, 24 March 2010 (UTC)

== Removal // Royal House infobox ==

The infobox shown over on the right in this section was removed by [[User:Lonelydarksky|Lonelydarksky]]:

{{Royal house|
|surname =House of Sòng
|estate =China
|coat of arms =
|country =[[Mid-Imperial China|China]]
|parent house =—
|titles =[[List of emperors of the Song Dynasty|Emperor of China]]
|founder =[[Emperor Taizu of Song|Emperor Tàizǔ]]
|final ruler =[[Emperor Bing of Song|Emperor Bǐng]]
|current head =
|founding year =960
|deposition =1279: [[Yuan Dynasty|Mongol conquest]]
|nationality =[[Han Chinese|Han]]
|cadet branches =
}}

The justification provided in the edit summary being that the edit was made by a suspected sockpuppet.  Now, I don't know if this editor is a sock or not, or, in fact, anything about the situation, but this seems to be a genuinely constructive edit.  Has there been some discussion elsewhere about the use of this infobox in articles on the dynasties of Imperial China that has rejected the use of this infobox?  If not, I would advocate restoring this (though probably not in the same exact same place) to the article; the information it contains is accurate (though the link for deposition should be to [[Mongol conquest of the Song Dynasty]] and not straight to [[Yuan Dynasty]]). [[User:Variable|siafu]] ([[User talk:Variable|talk]]) 17:54, 9 March 2011 (UTC)

:The sockpuppet has been confirmed (see [[Wikipedia:Sockpuppet investigations/Yongle the Great/Archive#09 March 2011|here]]). The banned user, [[User:Yongle the Great|Yongle the Great]], has been repeatedly attempting to evade the ban by [[WP:SOCK|sockpuppetry]]. All his edits, regardless of whether they're constructive or not, should be reverted per [[WP:BAN#Bans apply to all editing, good or bad]]. I've no objections to restoring the removed information, provided that it's not done by a sockpuppet of the banned user. &lt;span style= &quot;font-family: Fangsong; font-size: 10pt&quot;&gt;[[User:Lonelydarksky|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#000&quot;&gt;'''Lonelydarksky (暗無天日)'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;sub&gt; [[User_talk:Lonelydarksky|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#333&quot;&gt;contact me (聯絡)&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; 13:09, 11 March 2011 (UTC)

== Area significant digits ==

I cannot figure out how to edit the box titled &quot;Song&quot; at the right of the page, but the areas (especially the last one, where 2,000,000 sq km is converted to 772,204 sq mi) have a ridiculously high number of significant digits.
[[Special:Contributions/140.247.12.169|140.247.12.169]] ([[User talk:140.247.12.169|talk]]) 23:08, 8 October 2011 (UTC)

== Kaifeng/Beijing ==

The second paragraph of the article states, &quot;the Song capital was in the northern city of Beijing(now Kaifeng).&quot;  The page for Kaifeng lists several names that the city has been known as, but none of those is Beijing.  This needs clarification or correction.  [[User:Laszlo Panaflex|Laszlo Panaflex]] ([[User talk:Laszlo Panaflex|talk]]) 14:30, 9 May 2013 (UTC)

  I believe Xijin on this map is the modern-day Beijing.  It seems, however, to be depicted as built on top of a river island.  Beijing is not to my knowledge on one of those.  Is it?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/208.70.120.26|208.70.120.26]] ([[User talk:208.70.120.26|talk]]) 17:51, 30 October 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Asking for All Dating to be fitted with BC and AD... such as (Anno Domini) or (Before Christ)   ==

Each date should have BC or AD, its very confusing when the writers leave this out of Wikipedia pages.[[Special:Contributions/82.38.160.13|82.38.160.13]] ([[User talk:82.38.160.13|talk]]) 23:49, 8 February 2014 (UTC)ved

:Make it BCE and CE. [[User:Joshua Jonathan|&lt;font size=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Forte;color:black&quot;&gt;Joshua Jonathan&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] -[[User talk:Joshua Jonathan|&lt;font size=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-family:Monotype Corsiva;color:black&quot;&gt;Let's talk!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] 08:04, 9 February 2014 (UTC)

::See [[WP:ERA]] for why we should do neither of these. Quote: 'BC and AD are the traditional ways of referring to this era. BCE and CE are common in some scholarly texts and religious writings. Either convention may be appropriate.' and, 'Do not change the established era style in an article unless there are reasons specific to its content.' and, 'Do not use CE or AD unless the date or century would be ambiguous without it (e.g. &quot;The Norman Conquest took place in 1066&quot; not 1066 CE nor AD 1066). On the other hand, &quot;Plotinus was a philosopher living at the end of the 3rd century AD&quot; will avoid unnecessary confusion. Also, in &quot;He did not become king until 55 CE&quot; the era marker makes it clear that &quot;55&quot; does not refer to his age. Alternatively, &quot;He did not become king until the year 55.&quot;' [[User:Rincewind42|Rincewind42]] ([[User talk:Rincewind42|talk]]) 13:50, 9 February 2014 (UTC)

==Move discussion in progress==
There is a move discussion in progress on [[Talk:Han Dynasty#Han Dynasty to Han dynasty |Talk:Han Dynasty]] which affects this page. Please participate on that page and not in this talk page section. Thank you. &lt;!-- Talk:Han Dynasty crosspost --&gt; —[[User:RMCD bot|RMCD bot]] 13:28, 14 March 2014 (UTC)

==About the map==
I doubt that using a population map or whatever is suitable for an article about ancient countries...--'''[[User:Alvin Lee|Alvin]]'''  ''[[User talk:Alvin Lee|Lee]]'' 13:47, 11 January 2015 (UTC)
:If the data come from reliable sources, of course it is. [[User:HammerFilmFan|HammerFilmFan]] ([[User talk:HammerFilmFan|talk]]) 01:43, 4 February 2015 (UTC)

== Origin of the name &quot;Song&quot; ==

To add to article: what &quot;Song&quot; means (for example, &quot;Ming,&quot; the name of the following dynasty, means &quot;shining&quot;). [[Special:Contributions/173.89.236.187|173.89.236.187]] ([[User talk:173.89.236.187|talk]]) 18:29, 21 July 2015 (UTC)
:[[wikt:宋|宋]] is defined in most dictionaries as &quot;a dynasty&quot; and also &quot;a surname&quot;. It's not clear what Song means. The Ming was deliberately named by its leadership; not all names have that kind of meaning. [[User:Ogress|'''Ogress''']] [[User_Talk:Ogress|&lt;sub style=&quot;color:#BA55D3;&quot;&gt;''smash!''&lt;/sub&gt;]] 18:49, 21 July 2015 (UTC)
::It doesn't have a meaning other than as the name of the dynasty and as a (still current) surname, although it is used as a homophone for [[phon]], which has nothing whatsoever to do with the dynasty. [[User:Philg88|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#3a23e2; font-weight:bold; text-shadow:grey 0.1em 0.1em 0.1em;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;Philg88&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;♦[[User_talk:Philg88|talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 19:19, 21 July 2015 (UTC)
:::Like many dynasties before the Yuan, &quot;Song&quot; is geographical, named after [[Songzhou]] where the founding emperor served as [[jiedushi]]. [[User:Underbar dk|_dk]] ([[User talk:Underbar dk|talk]]) 22:25, 21 July 2015 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Song dynasty]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=713179352 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Corrected formatting/usage for //www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/islam/history/china_print.html

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner&lt;/span&gt;]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 12:58, 2 April 2016 (UTC)

== Really 959? ==

Why does the heading for Northern Song say it began in 959 when most reference works say it began in 960, and nowhere in this article does it state what happened in 959? [[Special:Contributions/173.89.236.187|173.89.236.187]] ([[User talk:173.89.236.187|talk]]) 17:27, 7 May 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>iflvmh4js3f6fdm725vwhvzrdewr210</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
