<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Battle of Hastings</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>333707</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745313678</id>
      <parentid>745311416</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-20T12:27:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ealdgyth</username>
        <id>4497767</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Reasons for Outcome: */ reply</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="43636">{{Article history
|action1=GAN
|action1date=18:54, 5 June 2013
|action1link=/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=558487219

|action2=FAC
|action2date=10:02, 15 August 2013
|action2link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Battle of Hastings/archive1
|action2result=promoted
|action2oldid=568634004
|currentstatus=FA
|topic=warfare}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Middle Ages |class=FA|importance=High }}
{{WikiProject Anglo-Saxon Kingdoms |importance =Top | class =FA }}
{{WikiProject Military history |class=FA|British-task-force=yes |Middle-Ages-task-force=yes }}
{{WikiProject England |class=FA|importance=low }}
{{WikiProject Norse history and culture|class=FA|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Sussex|class=FA|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Normandy|class=FA|importance=mid}}
{{Vital article |topic=History |level=4 |class=FA}}
}}
{{Talk header}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{talk archive navigation}}
|maxarchivesize = 70K
|counter = 2
|minthreadsleft = 4
|minthreadstoarchive = 1
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:Battle of Hastings/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{Auto archiving notice |bot=MiszaBot I |age=3 |units=months }}
{{On this day |date1=2004-10-14|oldid1=6790477|date2=2005-10-14|oldid2=25469260|date3=2006-10-14|oldid3=81452582|date4=2014-10-14|oldid4=629416089}}

== William II of Normandy (was Semi-protected edit request on 22 April 2015) ==
{{edit semi-protected|Battle of Hastings|answered=y}}
&lt;!-- Begin request --&gt;
From the first line, please change &quot;Duke William II of Normandy&quot; to &quot;Duke William I of Normandy&quot; because the William of Normandy that fought at the battle of Hastings was the first William of Normandy thus styled as William I of Normandy. William II was his son.
&lt;!-- End request --&gt;
[[User:Jebbens|Jebbens]] ([[User talk:Jebbens|talk]]) 21:33, 22 April 2015 (UTC)
: No. William the Conqueror is the second William who was Duke of Normandy, so he's correctly styled &quot;Duke William II of Normandy&quot;. See [[William I of Normandy|William Longsword]]. William Longsword was William the Conqueror's great-great-grandfather. [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 21:43, 22 April 2015 (UTC)

::It doesn't appear so simple.  Our article [[William the Conqueror]] currently lists him as William I in bold, and William II only secondarily.  In the infobox, it lists his successor as [[William II]] (of England).  --[[User:A D Monroe III|A D Monroe III]] ([[User talk:A D Monroe III|talk]]) 22:24, 22 April 2015 (UTC)
::That is, while the &quot;of England&quot; or &quot;of Normandy&quot; can make the I vs. II &quot;correct&quot;, it's confusing to a casual reader, and may deserve some clarification.  --[[User:A D Monroe III|A D Monroe III]] ([[User talk:A D Monroe III|talk]]) 22:29, 22 April 2015 (UTC)

:::What are you suggesting? that it is phrased &quot;Duke William II of Normandy (later to become King William 1 of England)&quot;&lt;br /&gt;This seems rather cumbersome in an article about a battle, rather than the individual, especially as, if you click the link [[William II of Normandy]] it takes you direct to [[William the Conqueror]] which explains he &quot;had been Duke of Normandy since 1035 under the style William II&quot;&lt;br /&gt;We either need a proposed re-wording, or to accept the status quo. - [[User:Arjayay|Arjayay]] ([[User talk:Arjayay|talk]]) 17:29, 23 April 2015 (UTC)

::::I appreciate that this is an old discussion, but it's worth noting that this one is slightly more complex than it appears.  If the relevant Wikipedia articles are correct, during his lifetime, [[William Longsword, Count of Rouen|William Longsword]] and his predecessor [[Rollo]] were referred to as the Counts of Rouen, not Dukes of Normandy..  William Longsword's son [[Richard I of Normandy]] was the first person recorded as a &quot;Duke&quot;.  Some non-contemporary sources have referred to all the counts and dukes as &quot;dukes&quot;, and it may well be that there was no real change in status, just a change in the terminology used.
::::I would agree that referring to [[William the Conqueror]] as &quot;Duke William II of Normandy'&quot; is confusing.  However, there is another option: he was also known (unambigously) as &quot;William the Bastard&quot;. I propose changing the opening sentence:
:::::::The '''Battle of Hastings''' was fought on 14 October 1066 between the Norman-French army of Duke [[William the Conqueror|William II of Normandy]] and an English army under the [[Anglo-Saxons|Anglo-Saxon]] King [[Harold Godwinson]], beginning the [[Norman conquest of England]]. 
::::to
:::::::The '''Battle of Hastings''' was fought on 14 October 1066 between the Norman-French army of [[William the Conqueror|William the Bastard, Duke of of Normandy]], and an English army under the [[Anglo-Saxons|Anglo-Saxon]] king [[Harold Godwinson]], beginning the [[Norman conquest of England]].
::::Any objections?
::::[[User:Parsonscat|The Parson's Cat]] ([[User_talk:Parsonscat|talk]]) 18:04, 5 October 2016 (UTC)

::::: Yes, I object. There really isn't much evidence that William was really known as William the Bastard by any Norman source during his lifetime. I'd be fine with &quot;William, the Duke of Normandy&quot; which avoids the whole numbering issue. But William the Bastard was clearly a name used as a pejorative by his enemies and not one he'd embrace. [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 18:28, 5 October 2016 (UTC)

:::::: Done.  Now says &quot;William, Duke of Normandy&quot;. [[User:Parsonscat|The Parson's Cat]] ([[User_talk:Parsonscat|talk]]) 20:14, 5 October 2016 (UTC)

:::::: Reinstated as &quot;William, the Duke of Normandy&quot; - I think there's consensus here, judging by the lack of further comments.
:::::: [[User:Parsonscat|The Parson's Cat]] ([[User_talk:Parsonscat|talk]]) 10:09, 8 October 2016 (UTC)

== The repeated editing in of information on &quot;new site&quot; ==
=== March 2016 ===
This information: &quot;The field south of the [[Battle Abbey]] has been historically considered the actual location where the Anglo-Saxon army formed its defense shield to stop the Norman advance. At the end of 2013 [[Time Team|British Channel 4's Time Team]] performed archeological survey and excavated the field. No human remains or any remnants of an axe, sword, arrow or armour from the conflict have ever been found in the area, even though some 10,000 men are believed to have died there. Channel 4 suggested that possibly the actual location of the battle is not south of the Abbey, but about 200 meters east.&quot; is being edit-warred in. A &quot;Time Team&quot; TV investigation is not needing this much undue weight placed on it in an article on the whole battle. I note that English Heritage has not changed their opinion, nor have any historians changed theirs. This information really doesn't belong in the article and has been repeatedly added ... while being reverted by other editors. There are a number of problems with this content besides the [[WP:UNDUE]] problem of a fringe theory.  At least the sentence &quot;No human remains or any remnants of an axe, sword, arrow or armour from the conflict have ever been found in the area, even though some 10,000 men are believed to have died there&quot; is almost an exact word-for-word copy from  [http://www.telegraph.co.uk/history/10486441/Battle-of-Hastings-fought-at-site-of-mini-roundabout.html &quot;However, no human remains or artefacts from the conflict have ever been found in the area, even though some 10,000 men are believed to have died there.&quot; which is in this article]. And that article basically goes on to point out that this &quot;theory&quot; is not supported by anyone else, including English Heritage. See [http://www.english-heritage.org.uk/learn/story-of-england/medieval-part-1/battle-of-hastings-location/ this from English Heritage]. Basically, this is a fringe theory and has no place in the article .. or in Wikipedia. [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 00:38, 29 March 2016 (UTC)
:Ealdgyth, thank you for clarifications, good objectivity. [[User:Wiley Sage|Wiley Sage]] ([[User talk:Wiley Sage|talk]]) 01:10, 29 March 2016 (UTC)

=== {{anchor|Dispute30Sep2016}}September/October 2016 ===
{{anchor|Dispute30Nov2016}}::{{ping|Ealdgyth}} This page does need to conform to [[WP:NPOV]]. While Lawson may believe that he &quot;and other modern historians&quot; agree on the site of Caldbec Hill, this is not uncontentious.  You can't prove a contentious point from a single citation.  English Heritage - which is a reputable authority - would disagree and point us at many conflicting sources that support the traditional Senlac site.  Wikipedia should document both.  While I agree that Time Team isn't &quot;a historian&quot;, English Heritage's Roy Porter, who wrote the article I referenced, most certainly is: he views the LiDAR investigation and landscape analysis as being strongly supportive of the &quot;traditional&quot; battlefield location.
::You can't go about claiming things are 'fringe theories' simply because your favourite historians disagree.
::[[User:Parsonscat|The Parson's Cat]] ([[User_talk:Parsonscat|talk]]) 16:56, 30 September 2016 (UTC)

::: This statement (which was just editwarred back in) &quot;The traditional site of the Battle of Hastings is Senlac Hill, the of the present-day remains of Battle Abbey... &quot;makes no sense. Also - see above - the information is way undue. And breaks the whole flow of the article - you're inserting information about a 2014 investigation (by a TV show, not an archaelogist or historian, no less) into the description of the actual preparations for the battle. Also - the reference being used is stated as having a date of 2 December 2016 - that's patently not possible (as it's 30 September 2016). There have been many investigations of the battlefield, and I'm sure some archaelogical investigations - but none of those merit mention in the article on the battle itself. There have been many possible sitings of the battlefield but most historians (which ... Lawson says in the source given for the statement &quot;most historians&quot; which keeps getting tagged without actually having the source being consulted, near as I can tell) concur with location. It's a fringe theory when no other historians take it up. [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 17:05, 30 September 2016 (UTC)
::: Further ... the statement &quot;The traditional site of the Battle of Hastings is Senlac Hill, the of the present-day remains of Battle Abbey, and William the Conqueror is said to have directed that the abbey's high altar be placed on the exact spot where Harold died; the battle is said to have been fought on the land to the south and west of the abbey.&quot; is sourced to [http://www.english-heritage.org.uk/visit/places/1066-battle-of-hastings-abbey-and-battlefield/history/description/ this page from English Heritage] but no where on that page is any mention made of Senlac Hill. Nor does the source say anything about the battle being fought to the south and west of the abbey. The information fails to be verified by the source given. [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 17:11, 30 September 2016 (UTC)

::::{{ping|Ealdgyth}} Apologies for the missing word 'site', now added.  Can I suggest you read the sources again, please?  You'll see a map of the battlefield which shows the space to the south and west of the abbey.  The source I indicated very definitely contains the essential claims that I re-stated. 
::::The only part that isn't in the article is the naming of the site as Senlac Hill.  Senlac Hill exists today in Battle, and if you look on any map, Google identifies its two halves: Lower Lake and Upper Lake.  Lawson would agree with this terminology: he believes (or believed?) that the Saxon army assembled on Caldbec Hill and the Norman Army assembled on Senlac Hill.
::::Could you name the modern historians that Lawson cites, please?
::::It's certainly not true to say that no modern historians disagree with Lawson: I quoted English Heritage's Roy Porter who takes a measured and sceptical view of Time Team's contribution.  Note that I inserted information from English Heritage and Roy Porter, not from Time Team.  I am very sure that we could find other historians who take this view.  I would suggest that rather than books, articles in peer-reviewed academic journals would be the gold standard here.  Perhaps you have expertise to identify these?
::::I'm sure that the flow of the article could be better - please do improve.  But the traditional site of the Battle of Hastings does need to be mentioned and given due weight.  That's not to say that Lawson's wrong: it's just that Wikipedia needs to give all credible positions due weight, not make judgements.
::::[[User:Parsonscat|The Parson's Cat]] ([[User_talk:Parsonscat|talk]]) 17:49, 30 September 2016 (UTC)
:::::: Senlac is mentioned. And we don't need to go into great details about which hill is which - this is an overview article. If someone wants all the indepth details - the place for them to go is to the various books that are used as sources. We locate the battle site as between Caldbec Hill to the north and Telham Hill - (in the background and location section) and then describe the naming of it as Senlac in that section. That's where the due weight is. The fact of the abbey's high altar being located on the site of Harold's death is dealt with later in the article - repeating it is not needed elsewhere. Lawson doesn't cite other historians - he says what the traditional view is ... and then goes on to refute with his own view. When a historian says &quot;The usual view&quot; or &quot;The mainstream view&quot; ... that is enough to state that &quot;most historians&quot; (this is also borne out by the fact that none of the sources I just went back and checked differ on the location of the battle being at the site of the Abbey. As for there being no bodies or other artifacts found at the site - we mention in this article that the site had some extensive work done on it to build the abbey - the top of at least one hill was leveled off. (There is also mention of a possible skeleton related to the battlefield later in the article in the explanatory footnotes.) [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 18:05, 30 September 2016 (UTC)
:::::::{{ping|Ealdgyth}} Exactly what does Lawson say, please?  I can easily access peer-reviewed journals, I don't have ready access to Lawson's book.  &quot;Historians&quot; is not a well-defined term: it can mean highly-respected academics who publish in peer-reviewed papers, or it can mean populist history authors who sometimes have a strong academic pedigree but not always.  Lawson may be referring to them.  Could you clarify this, please?  Lawson must himself have given some references?
:::::::I would disagree with your analysis of the article as it stands: reading the original you would not realise that the site Lawson's modern historians are claiming differs significantly from the traditional battlefield site.  Calddec Hill and Senlac Hill are a mile apart. This is something important, and the readers do need to know this.  They shouldn't be told that there is a consensus that the Saxon army formed up and fought on Caldbec Hill, when there is an I porta t - and dare I say more orthodox - view that the Saxon army formed up on the traditional site.  Do you understand where I am coming from here, please?
:::::::Other than this, are you now happy that my edits stands?  I believe I've responded adequately, but what do you think 
:::::::[[User:Parsonscat|The Parson's Cat]] ([[User_talk:Parsonscat|talk]]) 18:35, 30 September 2016 (UTC)
:::::::: No, I'm not happy with your additions. Your text still duplicates texts elsewhere to little need. I'm not about to type out what Lawson says because it covers two pages - it's properly summarized here. If I typed all that in here, it'd be a copyright violation. But it's not just Lawson - Peter Rex in ''1066'' says &quot;Duke William, early on the morning of Saturday 14 October, had moved up to the crest of Telham Hill, some 200 feet above sea level, from which he was able to observe English movements on Calbec...&quot; (p. 61). Frank McLynn in ''1066'' says &quot;At first light the Norman advance guard on Telham Hill saw the Anglo-Saxon standards on Caldbec Hill&quot; (and he never once mentions Senlac in the book, as it's not in the index). Peter Merren in ''1066'' says &quot;The Battle of Hastings was fought on a saddle of land formed by Caldbec Hill in the north and Telham Hill in the south&quot; (p. 101). David Howarth in ''1066'' says &quot;The apple tree where Harold's army met was on Caldboc Hill&quot; (p 169) and describes the place of the battle as between Caldboc Hill and Telham hill. Howarth describes the valley between the two hills as &quot;Santlache&quot; and says that's the basis for the corruption by the NOrmans in to Senlac.  Matthew Bennett in ''Campaigns of the Norman Conquest'' says that the English formed up on Caldebec Hill (p. 39). Gravett in ''Hastings 1066'' has the English forming up on Caldebec Hill and the Normans arriving at Telham about 6am on the 14th. (p. 59) He does mention Senlac - but as the marshy area between the two hills, not as a hill itself. It's clear that the battle was fought between the two hills, given all of these sources. Even English Heritage avoids mentioning Senlac in their pages. We go by what the sources state - and your source doesn't mention Senlac itself (nor on the map) so it can't be used for what you're trying to make it say. [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 19:14, 30 September 2016 (UTC)
:{{ping|Ealdgyth}} Again, can you respond to what I've actually asked, please?  Who does Lawson say claim the battle took place on Caldbec Hill rather than the site of Battle Abbey?  Are these academic historians or are they popular history writers?  That should not require you to reproduce two pages.  If you can't do this, you need to back down. 
:There is a difference between the place an army met - which was traditionally Caldbec Hill - and the place it formed up to fight.  The sources you have may well make that distinction: from what you have written, it is not clear.
: [[User:Parsonscat|The Parson's Cat]] ([[User_talk:Parsonscat|talk]]) 19:33, 30 September 2016 (UTC)
:: One - you don't need to ping me each and every time. Since I did the majority of the work on this article, I have it watchlisted. Again - Lawson says &quot;The traditional view&quot; is that the battle took place between Caldebec and Telham with the English line on Caldebec. He disagrees to some degree. One reason for simply stating that the battle took place between the two hills is that this is what the sources agree on. Then you get into many different ideas about what happened when - all of which are subjects for scholarly monographs but are too much detail for an encyclopedia article. Scholarly monographs go into great detail - this isn't a monograph. We need to cover the information, based on sources such as the above, so that the average reader can understand what's going on. The article currently states &quot;The battle took place 7 miles (11 km) north of Hastings at the present-day town of Battle,[78] between two hills – Caldbec Hill to the north and Telham Hill to the south.&quot; - does that disagree with anything you're saying? Again - overview. We don't need to wade into the scholarly debate about whether or not this tiny detail is correct. Your information about Harold's death site being the high altar site is already in the article. The information about Time Team is undue weight as no other such survey is discussed in the article - those sorts of surveys are the basis for the secondary historians we are basing the article on. Most of the above writers are historians - Howarth and Rex are the closest to &quot;popular&quot; historians. Several of them are military historians, and two of the works are from Osprey, quite a well respected military history publisher. And again - your source does not say anything about Senlac, so until I see a source that does say something you're trying to insert - I can't see inserting it. [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 19:53, 30 September 2016 (UTC)
:::You shouldn't be deleting other editors' referenced work just because you feel a sense of ownership of the article.  It's not up to you what gets inserted.  Please see [[WP:OWNERSHIP]]. 
:::You're very fixated on the lack of a reference to Senlac Hill, and haven't seemed to grasp that the point I am making is that many historians - and as yet, you've not identified  someone you regard as an academic historian - would disagree with the article's current claim, which is that the Saxon line was on Caldbec Hill.  Traditionally, the Saxon line was believed to have been formed at the site of Battle Abbey which is very definitely not at Caldbec Hill.  This is not a minor issue: it's significant.
:::The naming of the Battle Abbey site as Senlac Hill is a minor point, and would not normally be contentious: the [[Senlac Hill]] article on Wikipedia does discuss this, though perhaps needs merging into here.  However, if your after a strong reference, you can easily find one at
:::*{{cite web | url=https://www.english-heritage.org.uk/content/properties/1066-battle-of-hastings-abbey-and-battlefield/2235361/Battle-Abbey-GNVQ-Tourism.pdf | title=Battle Abbey and Battlefield: information for tutors and students of tourism studies | author=English Heritage | access-date=30 September 2016 | date=2002 | publisher=English Heritage | type=educational resource}}
:::[[User:Parsonscat|The Parson's Cat]] ([[User_talk:Parsonscat|talk]]) 20:18, 30 September 2016 (UTC)
:::: The references did not back up the information cited to them. It's perfectly acceptable to delete information that is not referenced in the reference given. That's not referenced information. And the edit being discussed didn't just mention Senlac Hill - it added information that is elsewhere in the article and information about a survey. If you want to propose specific information about Senlac Hill backed by a reference or so - that's one thing. But an edit has to be taken as a whole - not just one piece of the information.  The new reference is not really ideal - it is not exactly high quality. I did check biographies of William and Harold - neither Douglas nor Bates discuss the location of the actual fighting in their biographies of William. Walker does a bit but his biography isn't what you'd call academic. Rex also has a biography of Harold, where he puts Harold on Caldebec Hill. Several of the authors above mention that Harold moved down into the valley and then moved back... Huscroft in ''The Norman Conquest'' names no names but says that Harold drew up his battle lines on a hill. [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 20:41, 30 September 2016 (UTC)
:::::The references do back up the information I inserted in the article.  I suggest you read them again.  
:::::I disagree with your view of the article, and I think you're treating the article in contravention of [[WP:OWNERSHIP]].
:::::I feel that the source I've given is strong enough to show that Battle Abbey's site is known as Senlac Hill.  This shouldn't be contentious.  It's just the present-day name of a hill in Battle.
:::::It's not for individual users like yourself to decide how Wikipedia works: you need to refer to Wikipedia policies and guidelines.  Can you do this here?
:::::[[User:Parsonscat|The Parson's Cat]] ([[User_talk:Parsonscat|talk]]) 20:54, 30 September 2016 (UTC)

::::::It is not just Ealdgyth who disagrees with your approach, but other editors such as hchc2009 and myself. Discussion of a TV programme has no place in this article. Time Team was conducted by first rate archaeologists who boasted that they followed up their programmes with peer reviewed articles. If they thought on reflection that their investigation produced significant discoveries, then there will be an article, but judging by Roy Porter's comments, it does not seem likely that their discoveries were important enough to require amendment of the Wiki article. [[User:Dudley Miles|Dudley Miles]] ([[User talk:Dudley Miles|talk]]) 21:49, 30 September 2016 (UTC)

:::::::Can you please look at the edit made: the key point - supported by a reference - which was that the traditional site of the Saxon line was not Caldbec Hill but Battle Abbey.  This was not referenced to Time Team: it was referenced to English Heritage, in an article that did not mention Time Team.
:::::::What do you think of this?  The current article makes a clear claim suggestion that there is a full consensus that the Saxon army formed up on Caldbec Hill.  I feel that the article needs to reflect the fact that there is a significant body of thought that disagrees.
:::::::I have referred this discussion to [[Wikipedia:Dispute resolution noticeboard#Talk:Battle of Hastings#Dispute30Sep2016|Wikipedia's Dispute Resolution process]].  I plan to take a back seat now and see what the wider community thinks.
:::::::[[User:Parsonscat|The Parson's Cat]] ([[User_talk:Parsonscat|talk]]) 22:32, 30 September 2016 (UTC)
:{{ping group||ealdgyth|Dudley Miles}} can I draw your attention to [[WP:CANVAS]] please.  I see that you've discussed this on your talk pages.  Wikipedia has a suggested way of asking other editors to get involved in a more neutral way. [[User:Parsonscat|The Parson's Cat]] ([[User_talk:Parsonscat|talk]]) 22:40, 30 September 2016 (UTC)

== Site: Battle Abbey versus Caldbec Hill (October 2016) ==
* The current article seems to state that there is agreement among modern historians that the Battle of Hastings took place on '''Caldbec Hill''', with a (referenced) assertion from an author.  

* The traditional academic consensus is that the Battle of Hastings was fought '''on the site of [[Battle Abbey]]''', which is not Caldbec Hill.  This is sourced to numerous near-contemporary documents including the ''Anglo-Saxon Chronicle''. The following sources support this:
::: {{cite book|url=http://archaeologydataservice.ac.uk/archives/view/eh_monographs_2014/contents.cfm?mono=1089016 |author-last=Hare |author-first=J. N. |title=Battle Abbey: The Eastern Range and the Excavations of 1978-80 |publisher=English Heritage|location=London|date=1984 | access-date=1 October 2016 | isbn=9781848021341 |via=Archaeology Data Service | pages=11}}
::: {{cite web | url=http://www.english-heritage.org.uk/visit/places/1066-battle-of-hastings-abbey-and-battlefield/history/research/ | title=Research on Battle Abbey and Battlefield | publisher=English Heritage | access-date=5 October 2016}}
:::{{cite web | url=http://www.english-heritage.org.uk/learn/story-of-england/medieval-part-1/battle-of-hastings-location/ | title=Where Did the Battle of Hastings Happen? | publisher=English Heritage | access-date=5 October 2016}}
::: {{cite web | url=http://www.battlefieldstrust.com/resource-centre/viking/battleview.asp?BattleFieldId=17 | title=Battle of Hastings: 14 October 1066 | website=UK Battlefields Resource Centre | publisher=Battlefields Trust | access-date=5 October 2016}}

* Many writers seem to agree that the likely place Harold's army met and camped overnight was Caldbec Hill.  Recently, Grehan, Mace and Lawson (possibly others?) have conjectured that Harold's army took up its defensive position at Caldbec Hill too, rather than at the traditional site.  There are already references in the article in support of this hypothesis.  

* There seems to be little modern easy-to-find academic literature on the topic: apart from popular history books, the only thing I can find is a Ph.D. thesis from Canada.  This is an interesting read, and says that from a geographic perspective, both the Battle Abbey site and the Caldbec Hill site are geographic possibilities.  (Two other proposed sites - including Crowhurst - are dismissed outright.)

::: {{cite thesis | degree=Ph.D. | author-last=Hewitt | author-first=C. E. M. | title=The Battle of Hastings: A Geographic Perspective | publisher=University of Western Ontario | date=2016 | access-date=5 October 2016 | url=http://ir.lib.uwo.ca/etd/3628/}}

* There are two incidental details that may well not need to appear in the article: the site of Battle Abbey is today called [[Senlac Hill]], but if its [[Senlac Hill|Wikipedia article]] is correct, that name may not be contemporary.  Also, a widely-reported &quot;new site&quot; from a popular archaelogical TV programme was actually part of the traditional site, not a new site at all.  However, neither of these points is at all key to the argument.

* In light of all this, I would suggest amending the article from:

:::Most recent historians&lt;ref name=Lawson190&gt;Lawson ''Battle of Hastings'' pp. 190–191&lt;/ref&gt; conclude that Harold's forces deployed in a small, dense formation around the top of Caldbec Hill,&lt;ref name=Gravett59&gt;Gravett ''Hastings'' p. 59&lt;/ref&gt; with their flanks protected by woods and a stream and marshy ground in front of them.&lt;ref name=Bennett40&gt;Bennett ''Campaigns of the Norman Conquest'' p. 40&lt;/ref&gt; Lawson points out the possibility that the English line was a bit longer and extended enough to anchor on one of the streams nearby.&lt;ref name=Lawson190/&gt; The English formed a shield wall, with the front ranks holding their shields close together or even overlapping to provide protection from attack.&lt;ref name=Gravett64&gt;Gravett ''Hastings'' p. 64&lt;/ref&gt;

:to

:::There is a consensus that Harold's forces deployed in a small, dense formation at the top of a steep slope.&lt;ref name=Lawson190&gt;Lawson ''Battle of Hastings'' pp. 190–191&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Gravett59/&gt;   Traditionally, historians have identified this as the present-day site of [[Battle Abbey]],&lt;ref name=Hare84&gt;Hare ''Battle Abbey'' p.11&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=EngHer05Oct2016&gt;English Heritage ''Research on Battle Abbey and Battlefield''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=BattlefieldsTrust05Oct2016&gt;Battlefields Trust ''Battle of Hastings: 14 October 2016''&lt;/ref&gt; but some recent writers have suggested that it was Caldbec Hill,&lt;ref name=Lawson190/&gt;&lt;ref name=Gravett59/&gt; with the English flanks protected by woods and a stream and marshy ground in front of them.&lt;ref name=Bennett40/&gt;  The English formed a shield wall, with the front ranks holding their shields close together or even overlapping to provide protection from attack.&lt;ref name=Gravett64/&gt;

* What do people feel about this?  At the moment, we seem to be giving [[WP:UNDUE]] weight to the Caldbec Hill hypothesis at the expense of the traditional Battle Abbey site.

[[User:Parsonscat|The Parson's Cat]] ([[User_talk:Parsonscat|talk]]) 17:39, 5 October 2016 (UTC)

: Perhaps &quot;Harold's forces deployed in a small, dense formation at the top of steep slope,&lt;ref name=Gravett59&gt;Gravett ''Hastings'' p. 59&lt;/ref&gt; with their flanks protected by woods and marshy ground in front of them.&lt;ref name=Bennett40/&gt; The line may have extended far enough to be anchored on a nearby stream.&lt;ref name=Lawson190&gt;Lawson ''Battle of Hastings'' pp. 190–191&lt;/ref&gt; The English formed a shield wall, with the front ranks holding their shields close together or even overlapping to provide protection from attack.&lt;ref name=Gravett64/&gt; The exact hill that the English fought on is unclear with older sources stating the site of the abbey,&lt;ref name=Hare84&gt;Hare ''Battle Abbey'' p.11&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=EngHer05Oct2016&gt;English Heritage ''Research on Battle Abbey and Battlefield''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=BattlefieldsTrust05Oct2016&gt;Battlefields Trust ''Battle of Hastings''&lt;/ref&gt; but some newer sources suggesting it was Caldbec Hill.&lt;ref name=Lawson190/&gt;&lt;ref name=Gravett59/&gt;&quot;

:[[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 18:24, 5 October 2016 (UTC)

:: I prefer a slight variation: &quot;Harold's forces deployed in a small, dense formation at the top of steep slope,&lt;ref name=Gravett59&gt;Gravett ''Hastings'' p. 59&lt;/ref&gt; with their flanks protected by woods and marshy ground in front of them.&lt;ref name=Bennett40/&gt; The line may have extended far enough to be anchored on a nearby stream.&lt;ref name=Lawson190&gt;Lawson ''Battle of Hastings'' pp. 190–191&lt;/ref&gt; The English formed a shield wall, with the front ranks holding their shields close together or even overlapping to provide protection from attack.&lt;ref name=Gravett64/&gt; The exact hill that the English fought on is disputed with traditional sources stating the site of the later abbey,&lt;ref name=Hare84&gt;Hare ''Battle Abbey'' p.11&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=EngHer05Oct2016&gt;English Heritage ''Research on Battle Abbey and Battlefield''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=BattlefieldsTrust05Oct2016&gt;Battlefields Trust ''Battle of Hastings''&lt;/ref&gt; but some newer sources suggesting it was Caldbec Hill.&lt;ref name=Lawson190/&gt;&lt;ref name=Gravett59/&gt;&quot;  It's very close, so I'll start making this changes do we can continue discussion if needed.
::[[User:Parsonscat|The Parson's Cat]] ([[User_talk:Parsonscat|talk]]) 20:18, 5 October 2016 (UTC)
::: Let others weigh in. There isn't any great hurry... you can allow others to have time to see things.  And I dislike the &quot;traditional&quot; wording - it implies too much. Older/newer is much less tinged with other meanings - that's a clear dichotomy without weighing in on which might be correct. [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 20:31, 5 October 2016 (UTC)
::: Please let others weigh in before adding information. Not even three hours after your first edit and you're already putting it in. I prefer to see others views on this, given the discussions before. As a gesture of good faith towards others, it would be nice if the edit was self-reverted. [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 20:33, 5 October 2016 (UTC)
::::[[User:Parsonscat|The Parson's Cat]], any reason to prefer &quot;disputed&quot; over &quot;unclear&quot; in your choice of wording?  That seems to be the only difference. [[User:Mike Christie|Mike Christie]] ([[User_talk:Mike Christie|talk]] - [[Special:Contributions/Mike_Christie|contribs]] -  [[User:Mike Christie/Reference library|library]]) 09:03, 6 October 2016 (UTC)
:::::I agree with Ealdgyth that &quot;traditional&quot; is not right, and &quot;older&quot; is better as more neutral. I think the choice between &quot;unclear&quot; and &quot;disputed&quot; is marginal, and I would prefer &quot;uncertain&quot; to either. [[User:Dudley Miles|Dudley Miles]] ([[User talk:Dudley Miles|talk]]) 10:03, 6 October 2016 (UTC)
::::::I missed that part; read it too fast.  I agree &quot;older&quot; is more neutral.  I like &quot;uncertain&quot;. [[User:Mike Christie|Mike Christie]] ([[User_talk:Mike Christie|talk]] - [[Special:Contributions/Mike_Christie|contribs]] -  [[User:Mike Christie/Reference library|library]]) 11:52, 6 October 2016 (UTC)
:Apologies for the delay: I'm travelling at the moment, and don't have regular internet access. 
:The reason I prefer &quot;traditional&quot; is that &quot;older versus newer&quot; creates a sense that there was an old way of thinking about things, but we now know better.  It's actually the case that many (nearly all?) present-day academic historians still regard Battle Abbey as the battlefield site, so it's not really and &quot;old versus new&quot; thing.  (We want to avoid editorial bias, obviously!)  I don't think that holders of either viewpoint would object to the label &quot;traditional&quot;.
:Similarly, the reason I prefer &quot;disputed&quot; is that I don't think there is any evidence that there is a consensus that the site is &quot;unclear&quot;.  A good example of this is Marc Morris's review of John Grehan and Martin Mace's ''The Battle of Hastings 1066: The Uncomfortable Truth'', which you can find [http://www.historytoday.com/blog/2013/05/battle-hastings-uncomfortable-truth here], and it's easy to find other examples - English Heritage also seems pretty confident [http://www.english-heritage.org.uk/learn/story-of-england/medieval-part-1/battle-of-hastings-location/ here].  This doesn't look to me like &quot;uncertainty&quot;, but rather a disagreement or dispute.  Can anyone think of a better way of capturing this?
:Hope that helps.  It might be a few days before I can check in again, but I'd rather people went ahead than hung around waiting for me.  
:I wonder whether there might be a consensus that [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]]'s new text is at least a reasonable starting point?  We could keep discussing the precise wording here?  
:[[User:Parsonscat|The Parson's Cat]] ([[User_talk:Parsonscat|talk]]) 18:05, 7 October 2016 (UTC)

::As the comments here have dried up, I'm going to implement a change which I think reflects a consensus:
:::Harold's forces deployed in a small, dense formation at the top of steep slope,&lt;ref name=Gravett59&gt;Gravett ''Hastings'' p. 59&lt;/ref&gt; with their flanks protected by woods and marshy ground in front of them.&lt;ref name=Bennett40/&gt; The line may have extended far enough to be anchored on a nearby stream.&lt;ref name=Lawson190&gt;Lawson ''Battle of Hastings'' pp. 190–191&lt;/ref&gt; The English formed a shield wall, with the front ranks holding their shields close together or even overlapping to provide protection from attack.&lt;ref name=Gravett64/&gt; Sources differ on the exact site that the English fought on: some sources state the site of the abbey,&lt;ref name=Hare84&gt;Hare ''Battle Abbey'' p.11&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=EngHer05Oct2016&gt;English Heritage ''Research on Battle Abbey and Battlefield''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=BattlefieldsTrust05Oct2016&gt;Battlefields Trust ''Battle of Hastings''&lt;/ref&gt; but some newer sources suggest it was Caldbec Hill.&lt;ref name=Lawson190/&gt;&lt;ref name=Gravett59/&gt;
::I hope this is a reasonable reflection of consensus.
::[[User:Parsonscat|The Parson's Cat]] ([[User_talk:Parsonscat|talk]]) 17:19, 12 October 2016 (UTC)

== Reasons for Outcome: ==

These are suitably speculative but deserve further comment:

1) The notion that because the battle lasted all day, the English army couldn't have been exhausted by its earlier travails is simplistic. All accounts agree that Stamford Bridge was an exceptionally brutal affair, and there can be little doubt that any army would have been degraded by such an experience; the extensive marching would only have served to wear it out further. In reality, the duration of the battle infers that it probably contained long periods of relative inactivity; doubtless because both sides were wary of conceding any advantage to their opponents. Many studies have demonstrated that armoured men can only sustain close combat for several minutes at a stretch before becoming exhausted; Hastings wouldn't have been any different.

2) The claim that William was a more experienced commander than Harold is probably true, but is nonetheless overstated. In reality, Harold had extensive experience of campaigning, and not a little military success to his record. He would certainly have been considered an &quot;experienced commander&quot;.  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/94.199.236.87|94.199.236.87]] ([[User talk:94.199.236.87#top|talk]]) 12:07, 20 October 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
: Without sources to back this up, this is pure original research. [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 12:27, 20 October 2016 (UTC)

== Stamford or Stamford Bridge? ==
At present, the article has a couple of references to Harold leaving &quot;Stamford&quot;.   I'm about to amend this to &quot;Stamford Bridge&quot; as this is the name of the village.  (There is a Stamford in England, but it's nowhere near Stamford Bridge.)

In support of this, please see::
* [[Stamford]]
* [[Stamford Bridge]]

I hope this won't be contentious, but if so, please discuss below.

[[User:Parsonscat|The Parson's Cat]] ([[User_talk:Parsonscat|talk]]) 16:53, 13 October 2016 (UTC)

: We could probably go with just &quot;leave the battlefield&quot; or &quot;leave the north&quot; as a variation. As an aside - the article on the village is totally unsourced ... so it's not much use in determining if there was an actual village there at the time of the battle. [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 18:41, 13 October 2016 (UTC)

::  I misread the surrounding text before I made my edit, so that might not quite work - apologies.  It was actually &quot;The deaths of ... at Stamford Bridge&quot;.  This could be re-worded as &quot;the battle&quot;. I have no objections - please all edit until perfect. [[User:Parsonscat|The Parson's Cat]] ([[User_talk:Parsonscat|talk]]) 20:15, 13 October 2016 (UTC)

== Location map for Infobox ==
{{Location map many | United Kingdom East Sussex
| width = 308
| float = right
| caption = Site of Battle of Hastings in East Sussex
| label1 = Battle
| label1_size = 100
| mark1 = Battle icon active (crossed swords).svg
| mark1size = 20
| lat1_deg = 50.914507
| lon1_deg = 0.487790
&lt;!-- Hastings --&gt;
| label2 = Hastings
| label2_size = 75
| position2 = right
| lat2_deg = 50.8563015
| lon2_deg = 0.5728745 
&lt;!-- Eastbourne --&gt;
| label3 = Eastbourne
| label3_size = 75
| position3 = bottom
| mark3 = Black pog.svg
| lat3_deg = 50.77
| lon3_deg = 0.28
&lt;!-- Rye --&gt;
| label4 = Rye
| label4_size = 75
| position4 = right
| mark4 = Black pog.svg
| lat4_deg = 50.95
| lon4_deg = 0.73
&lt;!-- Newhaven --&gt;
| label5 = Newhaven
| label5_size = 75
| position5 = top
| mark5 = Black pog.svg
| lat5_deg = 50.80
| lon5_deg = 0.06
&lt;!-- Lewes --&gt;
| label6 = Lewes
| label6_size = 75
| position6 = left
| mark6 = Black pog.svg
| lat6_deg = 50.875627
| lon6_deg = 0.017855
&lt;!-- Crowborough --&gt;
| label7 = Crowborough
| label7_size = 75
| position7 = right
| mark7 = Black pog.svg
| lat7_deg = 51.06
| lon7_deg = 0.16
&lt;!-- Hailsham --&gt;
| label8 = Hailsham
| label8_size = 75
| position8 = bottom
| mark8 = Black pog.svg
| lat8_deg = 50.86
| lon8_deg = 0.26
&lt;!-- Bexhill-on-Sea --&gt;
| label9 = Bexhill-on-Sea
| label9_size = 75
| position9 = bottom
| mark9 = Black pog.svg
| lat9_deg = 50.85
| lon9_deg = 0.47
&lt;!-- Heathfield --&gt;
| label10 = Heathfield
| label10_size = 75
| position10 = bottom
| mark10 = Black pog.svg
| lat10_deg = 50.97
| lon10_deg = 0.26
&lt;!-- Uckfield --&gt;
| label11 = Uckfield
| label11_size = 75
| position11 = left
| mark11 = Black pog.svg
| lat11_deg = 50.97
| lon11_deg = 0.
&lt;!-- Seaford --&gt;
| label12 = Seaford
| label12_size = 75
| position12 = bottom
| mark12 = Black pog.svg
| lat12_deg = 50.77
| lon12_deg = 0.10
&lt;!-- Peacehaven --&gt;
| label13 = Peacehaven
| label13_size = 75
| position13 = left
| mark13 = Black pog.svg
| lat13_deg = 50.80
| lon13_deg = 0.00
}}
I'm about to add a map showing the location of the battle within East Sussex to the infobox.  Please feel to improve and/or discuss below.

[[User:Parsonscat|The Parson's Cat]] ([[User_talk:Parsonscat|talk]]) 20:15, 13 October 2016 (UTC)

== References: talk page only ==
{{reflist}}

== Lead image ... ==

I greatly prefer [[:File:Harold dead bayeux tapestry.png]] as the lead image - it's shows up the details much better in the infobox, rather than the image that has been twice placed in the infobox. Rather than just doing the edit again, let's discuss per the [[WP:BRD]] cycle. Given the small size imposed on images that are in the infobox, it's usually better to use images that show details better. The image of the Norman knights is very very small and loses all detail. Also, showing the climax of the battle (Harold's death) strikes me as a much better idea than generic knights. [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 14:39, 14 October 2016 (UTC)
:Fully agree, the previous image should be restored. Cheers, [[User:Ian Rose|Ian Rose]] ([[User talk:Ian Rose|talk]]) 15:01, 14 October 2016 (UTC)
:: Anyone else (such as the person who changed the picture twice) want to weigh in? [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 12:10, 15 October 2016 (UTC)
::: Agree - should be changed back. [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 13:19, 15 October 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>ppsxzaieprmixmqaqcvnpwtesn2snfx</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
