<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:We Can Do It!</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>34479284</id>
    <revision>
      <id>712857801</id>
      <parentid>706570387</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-03-31T14:12:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cyberbot II</username>
        <id>16283967</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Notification of altered sources needing review #IABot</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12895">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=22:14, 8 February 2012
|action1link=Talk:We Can Do It!/GA1
|action1result=passed
|action1oldid=475833371

|action2=PR
|action2date=18:10, 3 June 2012
|action2link=Wikipedia:Peer review/We Can Do It!/archive1
|action2result=reviewed
|action2oldid=495805640

|action3=FAC
|action3date=17:43, 10 October 2012
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/We Can Do It!/archive1
|action3result=passed
|action3oldid=516486808

|dykdate=8 March 2012
|dykentry=that the wartime poster &quot;'''[[We Can Do It!]]'''&quot; ''(pictured)'' was parodied using [[Marge Simpson]]?

|four=yes
|topic=Art and architecture
|currentstatus=FA
|maindate=February 15, 2013
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Politics|class=FA|importance=low}}
{{WPMILHIST|class=FA|B-Class-1=|B-Class-2=|B-Class-3=|B-Class-4=|B-Class-5=|US=yes|WWII=yes}}
{{WikiProject Feminism|class=FA|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Gender Studies|class=FA}}
{{WikiProject Visual arts|class=FA}}
{{WikiProject Women's History|class=FA|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Popular culture|class=FA|importance=low}}
{{WPUSA|class=FA|importance=low}}
}}

== Links for several words removed ==

While I don't like to see over-linking, I strongly feel that it was not proper to remove links as has recently been done.  Perhaps most intelligent adults would understand the correct meaning of propaganda, but I'd be willing to bet that a fair number do not.  The other links are proper and reasonable for the young Wikipedia readers.  I will leave it up to the person that wrote the article and/or other editors for now, but if I get no response to this note I'm going to return some of them. [[User:Gandydancer|Gandydancer]] ([[User talk:Gandydancer|talk]]) 12:35, 9 February 2012 (UTC)

== Infobox ==

I added an infobox to this article. It's been removed twice, the first time with the edit summary &quot;''Infobox not needed''&quot;, the second &quot;''I prefer [the other] version''&quot;.  The first of these is false, as it makes metadata about the subject available to parsers and to services like [[[DBpedia]], and the second seems to put personal aesthetic feelings above utility and service to our readers. The infobox should be restored.&lt;span class=&quot;vcard&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fn&quot;&gt;[[User:Pigsonthewing|Andy Mabbett]]&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span class=&quot;nickname&quot;&gt;Pigsonthewing&lt;/span&gt;); [[User talk:Pigsonthewing|Talk to Andy]]; [[Special:Contributions/Pigsonthewing|Andy's edits]]&lt;/span&gt; 22:11, 10 March 2012 (UTC)

:Please don't add an infobox. It's not needed for this article. The editors who wrote this page don't want it because it adds nothing to the article. If you can get enough editors to agree with you that it's needed here, then you'll have [[WP:CONSENSUS|consensus]] to add it. Thanks, [[User:MathewTownsend|MathewTownsend]] ([[User talk:MathewTownsend|talk]]) 22:37, 10 March 2012 (UTC)
::Infoboxes are certainly helpful but they are not required. There are even FA-level articles without them, such as [[Emily Dickinson]], where the editors decided against the big box. In this case I thought that the aesthetic trumped the practical, because the image has its own text already, and it looks very striking standing alone at 300 pixels wide. Finally, I don't think the image name should be italicized (it is just a poster) but the infobox you used [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=We_Can_Do_It!&amp;oldid=480975246 puts italics on the article title]. Those were my reasons for reverting. [[User:Binksternet|Binksternet]] ([[User talk:Binksternet|talk]]) 02:26, 11 March 2012 (UTC)
:::The italics in the infobox can be overridden. Not everyone sees images at the resolution you choose to use. &lt;span class=&quot;vcard&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fn&quot;&gt;[[User:Pigsonthewing|Andy Mabbett]]&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span class=&quot;nickname&quot;&gt;Pigsonthewing&lt;/span&gt;); [[User talk:Pigsonthewing|Talk to Andy]]; [[Special:Contributions/Pigsonthewing|Andy's edits]]&lt;/span&gt; 07:58, 11 March 2012 (UTC) 
::&quot;''The editors who wrote this page''&quot; have no special claim to it, per [[WP:OWN]]. Besides, I am now one of the editors who wrote this page. And consensus is not voting. You don't address my point about metadata, which demonstrates that your claim that the infobox &quot;''adds nothing to the article''&quot; is false. &lt;span class=&quot;vcard&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fn&quot;&gt;[[User:Pigsonthewing|Andy Mabbett]]&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span class=&quot;nickname&quot;&gt;Pigsonthewing&lt;/span&gt;); [[User talk:Pigsonthewing|Talk to Andy]]; [[Special:Contributions/Pigsonthewing|Andy's edits]]&lt;/span&gt; 07:58, 11 March 2012 (UTC)

== Rediscovery of Westinghouse poster ==

The re-discovery of the Westinghouse poster remains something of a mystery. It was almost certainly after 1980 since the documentary ''[[The Life and Times of Rosie the Riveter]]'', which shows numerous posters from the WWII era, doesn't show or mention the Westinghouse poster at all. The earliest known reference to the poster is apparently a 1982 or 1984 issue of ''[[Modern Maturity]]'' (sources conflict). A 1985 issue of ''U.S. News and World Report'' also prominently features the poster. [[User:Kaldari|Kaldari]] ([[User talk:Kaldari|talk]]) 19:12, 23 May 2012 (UTC)

:I would ''so'' love to know exactly which media source was first in bringing the image out of obscurity. There's an untold story there. [[User:Binksternet|Binksternet]] ([[User talk:Binksternet|talk]]) 19:27, 23 May 2012 (UTC)

::The scholarly Kimble and Olson source says that the earliest media they located was a 1982 issue of the ''Washington Post Magazine'', a Sunday supplement to the newspaper. I don't know the date. [[User:Binksternet|Binksternet]] ([[User talk:Binksternet|talk]]) 20:13, 23 May 2012 (UTC)

:::Ah, the full cite is in Kimble and Olson. The cite is this: Patricia Brennan, &quot;Poster Art for Patriotism's Sake&quot;, ''Washington Post Magazine'', May 23, 1982, p. 35. Another article mentioned in Kimble and Olson is 1985's &quot;The Legacies of World War II&quot; by ''U.S. News &amp; World Report''{{'}}s Senior Editor Stewart &quot;Stew&quot; Powell. [[User:Binksternet|Binksternet]] ([[User talk:Binksternet|talk]]) 01:03, 24 May 2012 (UTC)

==Geraldine Hoff photograph==
I just reorganized the article some so that all the material about the Geraldine Hoff photograph is grouped in one place. I also added the photo under fair use. Hope that's OK. [[User:Kaldari|Kaldari]] ([[User talk:Kaldari|talk]]) 19:49, 26 May 2012 (UTC)

:Incorporating the photo in the best manner required exactly the actions you took. Thank you! [[User:Binksternet|Binksternet]] ([[User talk:Binksternet|talk]]) 04:28, 27 May 2012 (UTC)

==Contacting experts for advice==
I sent an email to Lester C. Olson and James J. Kimble, authors of &quot;Visual Rhetoric Representing Rosie the Riveter&quot;, one of the best sources in the article. I asked for some pointers for moving forward. Kimble responded, generally praising the Wikipedia article, and offering the following comments:
*Only two original examples of the poster are known to exist, one at NAMH and one in the US National Archives (both in Washington DC).
*Kimble agrees with Penny Coleman that Hoff/Doyle was likely not the model. 
*Kimble recalls joining Olson to interview a co-worker of artist J. Howard Miller, and the co-worker showed a large collection of published drawings and photographs, indexed by subject, that Miller worked from to make his images. This recollection by Kimble conflicts with Westinghouse historian Charles A. Ruch who said that Miller was not in the habit of working from photos. Kimble says that he doubts the connection between the Hoff UPI photo and the &quot;We Can Do It!&quot; poster but that Miller might have worked from an existing image. He concludes that it is impossible to know exactly what inspired Miller.
*Kimble says the poster was probably brought out of storage by the National Archives in 1981–82 and reproduced to make souvenirs to commemorate the 40th anniversary of US involvement in the war.

I sent another email to Patricia Brennan, reporter for the ''Washington Post'' who in 1982 wrote the earliest known article about the poster. I sent the email to Brennan's WaPo email address which was shown in cached webpages but it bounced back undeliverable—no such addressee. Perhaps Brennan is retired or otherwise unavailable for comment. I have not seen a Brennan-authored newspaper article more recent than 2006. [[User:Binksternet|Binksternet]] ([[User talk:Binksternet|talk]]) 04:28, 27 May 2012 (UTC)

:Lester C. Olson responded on 31 May to say that his colleague Kimble was &quot;on target&quot; with his comments.
:In late May I emailed NAMH curators William L. Bird and Harry R. Rubenstein, authors of ''Design for Victory: World War II posters on the American home front'' which includes the &quot;We Can Do It!&quot; poster. I wanted to know the provenance of the poster: when it arrived at NAMH and how, when it was rediscovered and how, what they first did with it (which was probably to reproduce it in various forms for sale.) I have not heard back. [[User:Binksternet|Binksternet]] ([[User talk:Binksternet|talk]]) 15:23, 10 July 2012 (UTC)

== Proposed date for Main Page appearance ==

FAs shown on the Main page often appear on a date that is/was important to the topic. For this topic, important dates are:
*February 15, 1943 – first shown at Westinghouse factories
*May 23, 1982 – First public appearance outside of Westinghouse
*March – Women's History Month (U.S.)
*1918 – artist's year of birth (no known month or day)

I think it would be great to feature the article on February 15, 2013, on the 70th anniversary. [[User:Binksternet|Binksternet]] ([[User talk:Binksternet|talk]]) 18:38, 10 October 2012 (UTC)

:I've added the request [[Wikipedia:Today's_featured_article/requests#We_Can_Do_It.21|here]].--[[User:Chimino|Chimino]] ([[User talk:Chimino|talk]]) 16:21, 9 January 2013 (UTC)

::Excellent! Thank you for your well-composed blurb. [[User:Binksternet|Binksternet]] ([[User talk:Binksternet|talk]]) 18:28, 9 January 2013 (UTC)

== Adjustment of the Article ==

After reading “We Can Do It!”, I think this article has a very well organization and introduction. I am able to learn the knowledge of the poster clearly. However, I think this article can improve further. When I read the article, I found there are some paragraphs from different sections all talking about the Michigan factory worker, Geraldine Hoff. They doubted whether Geraldine Hoff was the prototype women in the poster or not. These separated discussions made me think the logic of this article was a little bit disorderly. In my opinion, to make readers more easily understand the content fluently, this article can add a new and specific section particularly to place all the discussions about the prototype women in the poster. Here is a referential article “[[Criticism_of_Apple_Inc.|Criticism of Apple Inc]]” which shows many specific aspects of the criticism.  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/2605:E000:5B00:1200:3192:91CB:F5C3:CE1B|2605:E000:5B00:1200:3192:91CB:F5C3:CE1B]] ([[User talk:2605:E000:5B00:1200:3192:91CB:F5C3:CE1B|talk]]) 01:30, 24 February 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:4|one external link|4 external links}} on [[We Can Do It!]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=712857797 my edit]. You may add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it, if I keep adding bad data, but formatting bugs should be reported instead. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether, but should be used as a last resort. I made the following changes:
*Attempted to fix sourcing for http://fieldnotes.msnbc.msn.com/_news/2010/12/30/5738254-geraldine-doyle-inspiration-for-rosie-the-riveter-dies-at-86
*Attempted to fix sourcing for http://fieldnotes.msnbc.msn.com/_news/2010/12/30/5738254-geraldine-doyle-inspiration-for-rosie-the-riveter-dies-at-86
*Attempted to fix sourcing for http://fieldnotes.msnbc.msn.com/_news/2010/12/30/5738254-geraldine-doyle-inspiration-for-rosie-the-riveter-dies-at-86
*Attempted to fix sourcing for http://fieldnotes.msnbc.msn.com/_news/2010/12/30/5738254-geraldine-doyle-inspiration-for-rosie-the-riveter-dies-at-86

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II&lt;/sup&gt;]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner&lt;/span&gt;]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 14:12, 31 March 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>lcgp9xxxi5sk3janey7i5yuar9dih5w</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
