<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:HMS Hood</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>686176</id>
    <revision>
      <id>712910502</id>
      <parentid>689334420</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-03-31T20:13:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>212.159.44.170</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Modern theories on the sinking */  needs rewrite subsection plus various spelling/typos</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="27193">{{talkheader}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=WAR
|action1date=12 September 2006
|action1link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/HMS Hood (51)/archive1
|action1result=failed
|action1oldid=75135994

|action2=GAN
|action2date=22:37, 21 September 2010
|action2link=Talk:HMS Hood (51)/GA1
|action2result=listed
|action2oldid=386187790

|action3=GTC
|action3date=03:25, 17 December 2010
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured topic candidates/Battlecruisers of the Royal Navy/archive1
|action3result=promoted
|action3oldid=401151799

|action4=WAR
|action4date=03:13, 28 May 2011 (UTC)
|action4link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/HMS Hood (51)
|action4result=approved
|action4oldid=431246379

|action5=FAC
|action5date=14:18, 16 September 2011
|action5link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/HMS Hood (51)/archive1
|action5result=promoted
|action5oldid=450803033

|action6=FTC
|action6date=22:33, 31 October 2013 (UTC)
|action6link=Wikipedia:Featured topic candidates/Battlecruisers of the World/archive1
|action6result=promoted

|ftname=Battlecruisers of the world
|ft2name=Battlecruisers of the Royal Navy
|topic=history
|currentstatus=FA
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Ships|class=FA}}
{{WPMILHIST|class=FA|A-Class=pass|British=yes|Maritime=yes|WWI=yes|WWII=yes|OMT=1}}
{{ShipwrecksWikiProject|importance=high|class=FA}}
{{WP Scotland|class=FA|importance=Mid}}
}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2004-05-24|oldid1=3767962|date2=2005-05-24|oldid2=14219886|date3=2006-05-24|oldid3=54912952|date4=2007-05-24|oldid4=133149054|date5=2012-05-24|oldid5=493946985}}
__TOC__
{{archive box|[[/Archive 1|September 2004 - May 2008]]}}

==Infobox==
Can someone tidy up the displacement? What are &quot;long tons&quot;: have never heard of them? Surely this should be sth like:
&quot;xxxxx tons (xxxxx metric tons)&quot;. Thanks, [[User:Bigpad|bigpad]] ([[User talk:Bigpad|talk]]) 08:12, 19 June 2008 (UTC)

While I have no objection whatsoever to changing the article to refer to tons instead of long tons, [[displacement (ship)]] is typically measured in [[Long ton|long tons]]. For a long time I wondered why the displacement in metric tons is a larger number than its displacement in tons, as I assumed [[Short ton|short tons]] were being used. [[User:WeeWillieWiki|WeeWillieWiki]] ([[User talk:WeeWillieWiki|talk]]) 21:15, 19 June 2008 (UTC)

Royal Navy ships aren't measured in &quot;long tons&quot;, they are measured in tons. Americans may think that they are the same thing, but what on earth were you thinking? This is like saying Jane Sixsmith plays field hockey. Sheesh! --[[User:Skyring|Pete]] ([[User talk:Skyring|talk]]) 21:27, 5 July 2010 (UTC)
:Oh, and what kind of tons are your &quot;tons&quot;? Long, short and metric are the three types that I'm familiar with.--[[User:Sturmvogel 66|Sturmvogel 66]] ([[User talk:Sturmvogel 66|talk]]) 21:59, 5 July 2010 (UTC)
::The same tons that have been used to describe warship displacements for centuries. If you can find an English-language contemporary reference that describes HMS Hood's displacement in anything other than tons, let me know, will you? --[[User:Skyring|Pete]] ([[User talk:Skyring|talk]]) 06:52, 10 July 2010 (UTC)
:::Not real interested in what was used contemporaneously, I need to describe them for the current audience. Beside I can't convert these tons to the other types without knowing how many pounds are in these tons of yours.--[[User:Sturmvogel 66|Sturmvogel 66]] ([[User talk:Sturmvogel 66|talk]]) 06:57, 10 July 2010 (UTC)
::::My tons? LOL! As I said, the same tons that have always been used. Do have any reference that shows anything else being used? Surely you aren't just making stuff up? --[[User:Skyring|Pete]] ([[User talk:Skyring|talk]]) 07:43, 10 July 2010 (UTC)

This cropped up in a very annoying thread on the convert template talk page, so let me sum things up for everyone.
* Unbeknowst to many people, there are a number of different types of &quot;ton&quot; in use in the world. 
* The 2240 pound ton was standard in the U.K and is known as the &quot;imperial ton&quot;, or &quot;long ton&quot;. 
* The 2000 pound ton is standard in the U.S. and is commonly known as the &quot;short ton&quot;. 
* The 1000 kilogram ton is standard in the rest of the world, and is known as the &quot;tonne&quot; in the Commonwealth and the &quot;metric ton&quot; in the U.S. 
* While the short ton is the most common one used in the U.S., Americans also commonly use the long ton in shipping and for measuring some commodities, 
* Historically the Royal Navy used the &quot;imperial ton&quot; or &quot;long ton&quot; to measure the displacement of its ships, it called them &quot;tons&quot; because that is the size most commonly used in the U.K. 
* The U.K. is at least nominally converted to metric after joining the EU, so the Royal Navy now measures the displacement of its ships in &quot;tonnes&quot;. 
* The difference is somewhat academic because the tonne is only 1.6% smaller than the long ton. 
* The Hood increased substantially in displacement during its lifetime, so the difference is even  less consequential.
Now Pete seems to think the use of the world &quot;ton&quot; is important, but I tend to believe that the real issue is accuracy and clarity. Hence, if you want to use the imperial ton, you should call it either &quot;imperial ton&quot; or &quot;long ton&quot;, or Americans will confuse it with the short ton they are familiar with. Alternatively you can use &quot;tonne&quot; for everything and be done with it.[[User:RockyMtnGuy|RockyMtnGuy]] ([[User talk:RockyMtnGuy|talk]]) 17:11, 10 July 2010 (UTC)

== Cronological error , summer 1940 ==
It says that Hood participated in the destructione of the french fleet in '''july 1940n only a week after the french surrender to germany''', but France surrendered (at Foch's old railway wagon ´from november 1918, at the exact same place, the Compiegne-wood) on '''june 14th'''. So eighter the french fleet was destructed 4-5 weeks after the surrender or , the sinking of the french fleet happended in '''june'''. I'm no sure wich, but both &quot;sinking of the french fleet&quot; happened in june or it happened more like a month after the surrender. /Malinka70 forgot my password    &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/83.249.32.226|83.249.32.226]] ([[User talk:83.249.32.226|talk]]) 04:10, 6 September 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:There is no error: France surrendered officially on 25 June (armistice was signed on 22nd at Compiegne and came into effect three days later). [[User:Bigpad|bigpad]] ([[User talk:Bigpad|talk]]) 23:32, 29 October 2009 (UTC)

== Image ==

There is a [http://www.fremantleports.com.au/About/PhotoGallery/19001929.asp photograph available] of HMS Hood taken when she arrived in Fremantle in 1924, it would be a PD image as it was taken and published in 1924. [[User:Gnangarra|Gnan]][[User_talk:Gnangarra|garra]] 13:08, 22 September 2008 (UTC)

==Modern theories on the sinking==

Smoke and fire from the explosion of a battleship's magazine may be vented somewhere else than the origin of the explosion as the magazines ended to be heavily armored. Photographs of the explosion of the USS Arizona at Pearl Harbor show a huge cloud of black smoke from the smoke stack when the explosion was actually in the forward magazine. [[User:Naaman Brown|Naaman Brown]] ([[User talk:Naaman Brown|talk]]) 17:03, 4 December 2008 (UTC)

hi im zoe 
My grandads brother and cousin was on that ship when it was hit and sunk by the bismark and both died  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/86.130.199.80|86.130.199.80]] ([[User talk:86.130.199.80|talk]]) 18:37, 1 March 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

When Bismarck was sunk a few days later even more sailors died. But those lives where of course german...  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/83.249.35.216|83.249.35.216]] ([[User talk:83.249.35.216|talk]]) 22:05, 8 September 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

'''Facts'''
Bismarck was brand new, Hoods basic construction from 1916. Although heavier and larger artillery
Hood was a)less protected  b)Bismarck had better targeting  c)Holland underestimated their enemy
or overestimated Hood. It took only 22 seconds to reload the artillery of Bismarck, and it would not explode by a single hit from Hood.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/83.249.35.216|83.249.35.216]] ([[User talk:83.249.35.216|talk]]) 22:03, 8 September 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

*Sigh* this isn't the place for that kind of discussion. As to the point of this: I've added an edit to the modern theroies section. I don't know how to add a referance however, if somone could oblige me by adding it i;d much appreciate it.. My source is the book: Hood and BIsmark, P206. It was written by David Mearns and Rob White who where both involved in the discovery of the wreak.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/80.225.48.48|80.225.48.48]] ([[User talk:80.225.48.48|talk]]) 23:13, 13 March 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

===Section badly needs rewrite===
The Modern theories section is enormously confusing because it lists theories that have been discounted by the evidence gained from looking at the wreck. It means that the reader has to spend effort working out which ones are valid and which not, which is crazy. Not going to get in a reversion war (see page history), but the whole section needs revising and the stuff that is years out of date removed or at least clearly distinguished. [[Special:Contributions/212.159.44.170|212.159.44.170]] ([[User talk:212.159.44.170|talk]]) 20:13, 31 March 2016 (UTC)

==Loch Eriboll==
Just wondered if there should be a mention of the memorial on the side of [[Loch Eriboll]]?  --[[User:Jmb|jmb]] ([[User talk:Jmb|talk]]) 20:26, 23 June 2009 (UTC)

== Armor belt angled outward? ==

I have always been confused by this section of the article.

Outward like the walls of a pyramid, or outward like the sides of a shot glass?

Please see my detailed diagrams below.

[Bullet! Yay :) ]&gt; \ &lt;- armor (&quot;shot glass&quot; armor)

[Bullet! Yay :) ]&gt; / &lt;- armor (&quot;pyramid&quot; armor)

I ask because the latter would seem to present the armor at a better angle for penetration as range increases, while the former would seem to leave stuff below it exposed since the bottom is farther from the enemy. Which way was ''Hood's'' belt designed?

[[User:Archer884|J.M. Archer]] ([[User talk:Archer884|talk]]) 17:11, 27 January 2010 (UTC) (aka ignorant battleship buff)

&gt;&gt;&gt;The belt was angled so that the top was further outboard then the bottom (shot glass). Which is the opposite of tank design. Bottom of the belt is below the waterline. The deck armour has a slope from deck level which is level to the top of the belt to the bottom. Cross section at http://www.navweaps.com/index_inro/no21987-Midship.jpg  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/92.233.101.80|92.233.101.80]] ([[User talk:92.233.101.80|talk]]) 19:16, 13 June 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
The risk of shells skimming the angle of the belt when striking at long range and ending up inside the torpedo defence lead to a return to vertical armour in the KGV, Lion and Vanguard designs

== Sunset ==

The article claims that &quot;Hood would have met the German squadron just after sunset (roughly 02:00 so far north in May)&quot;. I don't care how far North you go, you won't get sunset after Midnight. Indeed, running it through a spectral calculator for that date gives a sunset hours earlier.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/130.88.171.211|130.88.171.211]] ([[User talk:130.88.171.211|talk]]) 00:41, 24 May 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Good question - that also arises on the Battle of Denmark Strait page; here is my comment copied from there.  Kennedy, 1974, states in Chapter 6 that - for the British fleet - 'ship's clocks were four hours ahead of local time' at the point when Victorious was preparing to launch the first Swordfish attack on Bismark. As these events take place in the longitude range 30-37 degrees West (corresponding to 2 hours behind Greenwich), the implication is that the British fleet was indeed operating on Double Summer Time. Clearly operational coherence requires all units in a given command work to the same clock; immense confusion would result if each ship adjusted to its own longitude! Later in this chapter Kennedy remarks that the USCG cutter Modoc had its clock set one hour behind local time, therefore 5 hours behind the British fleet. I have added Kennedy's statement to the article, but not my OR about double summer time. Changes of course brought the engagement later than first envisaged, to dawn, in fact; early in Chapter 4 Kennedy states: '..in that cold, pale dawn, with the eastern sky pink and violet on the low cirrus and a hazy blue above..'   [[User:John M Brear|John M Brear]] ([[User talk:John M Brear|talk]]) 14:45, 28 November 2011 (UTC)
:To add a little...time zones at high latitude are always problematic. Far enough north and ships 100 miles east-west of each other might theoretically be several hours apart in time. With a dispersed fleet, the answer to &quot;What time is it?&quot; is basically &quot;It is whatever time the fleet commander says it is.&quot; [[User:Rumiton|Rumiton]] ([[User talk:Rumiton|talk]]) 15:00, 28 November 2011 (UTC)

::Britain operated on permanent [[British Summer Time|Double British Summer Time]] throughout the Second World War, that is, 2 hours ahead of GMT. The latter (GMT) however would be used for navigation.  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/95.148.220.13|95.148.220.13]] ([[User talk:95.148.220.13|talk]]) &lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Copyediting ==

*Most Americans don't know that the British &quot;purpose-built&quot; is roughly &quot;special-purpose&quot; in American, so I'd prefer we reword it.  Which battlecruisers were completed after ''Hood''? - Dank ([[User talk:Dank|push to talk]]) 01:49, 4 September 2010 (UTC)
**She was the last one completed so I've deleted the phrase. Good catch.--[[User:Sturmvogel 66|Sturmvogel 66]] ([[User talk:Sturmvogel 66|talk]]) 02:36, 4 September 2010 (UTC)
*I don't like the &quot;For this reason&quot; sentence, but I don't have a quick fix.  I'll come back to it after the article passes GAN. - Dank ([[User talk:Dank|push to talk]]) 14:30, 4 September 2010 (UTC) Also the &quot;At this point in her service&quot; sentence. - Dank ([[User talk:Dank|push to talk]]) 14:54, 4 September 2010 (UTC)
*Ugh.  It's an important article, but I'm going to put this one aside for a couple of months and come back later; there are a lot of judgment calls to make and I'd really like to bring in more editors and copyeditors on this one. - Dank ([[User talk:Dank|push to talk]]) 15:07, 4 September 2010 (UTC)
*In the first section, does &quot;as completed&quot; mean as opposed to the design specs or as opposed to later, after refits? - Dank ([[User talk:Dank|push to talk]]) 18:52, 4 September 2010 (UTC)
**Mostly the former, but some of the latter.--[[User:Sturmvogel 66|Sturmvogel 66]] ([[User talk:Sturmvogel 66|talk]]) 19:37, 4 September 2010 (UTC)

== Outbreak of war ==


Currently, the article states:

&quot;When war with Germany was declared in September 1939, Hood was operating in the area around Iceland, protecting convoys from German attack.&quot;

Does this mean Hood was operating around Iceland when war was declared and then started defending convoys in that area? Or was war declared and Hood sent out to patrol?

Presumably she wasn't defending convoys at the declaration of war. [[User:JJJJS|JJJJS]] ([[User talk:JJJJS|talk]]) 18:45, 19 April 2011 (UTC)
:Hood was already at sea when war was declared, but I've reworded things.--[[User:Sturmvogel 66|Sturmvogel 66]] ([[User talk:Sturmvogel 66|talk]]) 20:55, 19 April 2011 (UTC)

::Cheers, it makes more sense now. I wasn't familiar enough with the history to feel comfortable changing it. [[User:JJJJS|JJJJS]] ([[User talk:JJJJS|talk]]) 13:37, 20 April 2011 (UTC)

==Photo of explosion==
It appears that the photo of ''Hood'' exploding was taken from the ''Bismark''.  If this is true, it might be helpful to say so in the photo caption.  Also, in the photo, is that the ''Prince of Wales'' in the background? [[User:Cla68|Cla68]] ([[User talk:Cla68|talk]]) 10:02, 14 May 2011 (UTC)

I have no knowledge of the origin of that picture, yet it seems very improbable that any pictures taken from ''Bismark'' survived her sinking and that one of the handful of survivors would think to take a roll of film with him. Even if that had happened, the British would have surely taken the film from the man and it would have gone into a British archive.

It's more likely the picture was taken from the ''Prince Euigen'' and handed over to the German naval authorities on her return for use in intelligence, propaganda or documentation. This would account for a copy being in the ''Bundesarchiv''. [[User:Catsmeat|Catsmeat]] ([[User talk:Catsmeat|talk]]) 07:30, 28 May 2011 (UTC)
:That makes sense. [[User:Cla68|Cla68]] ([[User talk:Cla68|talk]]) 06:12, 15 August 2011 (UTC)

== The &quot;last photo&quot; probably shows A turret, not X turret of Prince of Wales ==

The photo image showing three guns on the POW has been “corrected” to say that it was taken near X turret. Previously the caption implied that it showed a forward turret trained as far aft as possible. I didn’t make the original statement or the correction, but I do think this is the A turret. I think everyone will agree that it can’t be B turret, because that one would only have two guns. Untrimmed versions of this same photo show the fourth gun, elevated to a position out of view in this cropped image, so we can be sure that this shows either A turret or X turret. The editor who changed the caption (stating in his edit summary that if this were A turret then the ship must be steaming away from the Hood) is wrong. While I agree that we can rule out the possibility that POW would be steaming away from Hood, the statement overlooks the possibility that the A turret is simply turned to point as far aft as possible, which it would be in heavy seas prior to actually engaging the enemy. Under such circumstances the X turret would probably be trained dead aft, and these guns seem to be pointing somewhat to port. Also, the very same untrimmed versions of the photo that reveal the fourth gun also reveal a major superstructure object (possibly the base of B turret) that would be in the way of these guns if they were to try to point dead aft. I hope that someone else will look at the untrimmed photo, it is easily available on sites about HMS Hood, and carefully consider the possibility that this is A turret with guns trained as far aft as possible on the port side of the ship.
[[Special:Contributions/207.30.62.198|207.30.62.198]] ([[User talk:207.30.62.198|talk]]) 23:25, 27 October 2011 (UTC)
:It could be A turret, but only comparing a detailed photo or drawing of the area around either turret to match the ventilators(?) visible beneath the barrels will decide the question.--[[User:Sturmvogel 66|Sturmvogel 66]] ([[User talk:Sturmvogel 66|talk]]) 03:01, 28 October 2011 (UTC)
::It's A turret. Check the discussion at [[Battle of the Denmark Strait]]. [[User:Rumiton|Rumiton]] ([[User talk:Rumiton|talk]]) 14:57, 28 October 2011 (UTC)

:::Alternatively, in the absence of &lt;u&gt;sources&lt;u&gt; declaring where the picture was taken from, just edit the caption to remove reference as to which turret. Average reader is probably satisifed with knowing from which ship it was taken. [[User:GraemeLeggett|GraemeLeggett]] ([[User talk:GraemeLeggett|talk]]) 18:15, 28 October 2011 (UTC)
::::We don't need sources to tell us the sun rises in the east, and this situation is just as clear. We can and should be precise. Did you read the discussion at [[Battle of the Denmark Strait]]? [[User:Rumiton|Rumiton]] ([[User talk:Rumiton|talk]]) 14:41, 29 October 2011 (UTC)
:::::[[Talk:Battle_of_the_Denmark_Strait#The_photo_probably_shows_A_turret.2C_not_X_turret|the discussion]] you refer to makes no mention of sources. Policy says anything &quot; likely to be challenged &quot; should be supported by referencing and that the &quot;burden of evidence lies with the editor who adds or restores material&quot; the purpose being to &quot;improv[e] the credibility of Wikipedia and show[] that the material is not original research.&quot; An assertion that it is A turret based on personal observation is OR. [[User:GraemeLeggett|GraemeLeggett]] ([[User talk:GraemeLeggett|talk]]) 15:03, 29 October 2011 (UTC)
::::::If describing something as obvious when it is obvious is called original research, what shall we call demanding a source to tell us that the obvious is obvious? How about obstructionism and pedantry? [[User:Rumiton|Rumiton]] ([[User talk:Rumiton|talk]]) 15:35, 30 October 2011 (UTC)
:::::::This is a featured article for which &quot;Claims are verifiable against high-quality reliable sources&quot;. If this picture has been used in a book (or other work) then presumably it's been discussed or captioned and therefore can be sourced. I'm not suggesting it's not Hood or not the last picture or not from any specific part of PoW - I'm asking that editors don't make their own interpretations. [[User:GraemeLeggett|GraemeLeggett]] ([[User talk:GraemeLeggett|talk]]) 18:08, 30 October 2011 (UTC)

One reason why there should be at least some explanation for the objects seen in the foreground is that even a casual viewer is likely wonder why he is seeing what appear to be guns from a triple turret when POW had only quads and a twin. That point, at least, needs to be addressed. I am also wondering why there was no demand for citation during all of the very long time that the caption stated that the view was from “X” turret.
[[Special:Contributions/207.30.62.198|207.30.62.198]] ([[User talk:207.30.62.198|talk]]) 01:56, 31 October 2011 (UTC)

There is a site about Loss of HMS Hood that has the same photo, untrimmed, and it has as the caption these words:
&quot;Probably one of the last photographs ever taken of H.M.S. Hood.  A photogrammetric analysis of this photo shows Hood is bearing about 341 degrees from Prince of Wales, range 975 meters (1,070 yards).  &quot;A&quot; turret guns of the Prince of Wales are trained on the port quarter.&quot;

I hope this can count as a citation
[[Special:Contributions/207.30.62.198|207.30.62.198]] ([[User talk:207.30.62.198|talk]]) 22:44, 1 November 2011 (UTC)

And, by the way, the aft most quad turret on PoW was the &quot;Y&quot; turret, not the &quot;X&quot; turret
[[Special:Contributions/207.30.62.198|207.30.62.198]] ([[User talk:207.30.62.198|talk]]) 23:21, 1 November 2011 (UTC)

== It may just be the technical author in me ==

But the article really could use a reference diagram. The wreck section would be so much easier to read with a simple schematic included.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/69.157.174.189|69.157.174.189]] ([[User talk:69.157.174.189|talk]]) 20:33, 25 May 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Recovery of bell ==

Something to note: there is going to be a recovery operation to try and retrieve the bell soon. Should probably keep an eye out to see if it needs inclusion in here at some point. [http://www.telegraph.co.uk/history/world-war-two/9436069/Microsoft-founder-to-recover-bell-from-HMS-Hood.html Telegraph article]. Regards, [[User:Woody|Woody]] ([[User talk:Woody|talk]]) 21:43, 29 July 2012 (UTC)
:Took them a few years, but they [http://news.usni.org/2015/08/10/bell-of-sunken-wwii-battlecruiser-hms-hood-recovered-from-ocean-floor recovered the bell]. [[User:BB-PB|Parsecboy]] ([[User_talk:BB-PB|talk]]) 11:27, 11 August 2015 (UTC)

== Wreck-final salvo vs flame ==

Many have heard the &quot;final salvo&quot; story, but it doesn't appear in the article prior to Wreck para 4 &quot;Other researchers have...time.&quot; Without some setup, this doesn't make much sense, does it? Should the final salvo be mentioned in Denmark Strait, or be explained more in Wreck?[[User:Sammy D III|Sammy D III]] ([[User talk:Sammy D III|talk]]) 20:23, 8 December 2012 (UTC)
:I think that it gets as much coverage as it deserves. Its unprovable either way and thus a non-issue, IMO.--[[User:Sturmvogel 66|Sturmvogel 66]] ([[User talk:Sturmvogel 66|talk]]) 21:31, 8 December 2012 (UTC)
::Why? No references here now, but wasn’t the “last salvo” story reported at the time? It became part of the Hood myth, didn’t it? And an explosion makes far more sense than the almost certainly emotional last salvo story, doesn’t it?
::Modern theories and Wreck both speculate on unprovable theories, as do articles on Bismarck, Yamato, Titanic, and other sunken ships. Sort of a cottage industry. And this one uses reason to possibly explain what has often seemed like a fantastic fabrication to many of us. They were not making it up, they just were wrong.[[User:Sammy D III|Sammy D III]] ([[User talk:Sammy D III|talk]]) 23:27, 8 December 2012 (UTC)
:::I don't think that it's worth mentioning, but feel free to add it yourself. Just be sure to cite it properly.--[[User:Sturmvogel 66|Sturmvogel 66]] ([[User talk:Sturmvogel 66|talk]]) 00:54, 9 December 2012 (UTC)
::::From [http://hmshood.com/history/denmarkstrait/bismarck2.htm HMS Hood association] &quot;According to the Germans, as the bow rose into the air, Hood’s forward turrets were seen to fire one last salvo. If this is true, it is likely due to a short or a mechanical failure.&quot;  &lt;br /&gt;
::::I have read elsewhere that mercury switches triggered by the list -could cause the turret to fire. [[User:JRPG|JRPG]] ([[User talk:JRPG|talk]]) 15:30, 5 September 2013 (UTC)

== [[:File:HMS Hood (51) - March 17, 1924.jpg]]==
Hello! This is a note to let the editors of this article know that [[:File:HMS Hood (51) - March 17, 1924.jpg]] will be appearing as [[Wikipedia:picture of the day|picture of the day]] on May 24, 2014. You can view and edit the POTD blurb at [[Template:POTD/2014-05-24]]. If this article needs any attention or maintenance, it would be preferable if that could be done before its appearance on the [[Main Page]]. Thanks!&amp;nbsp;—&amp;nbsp;[[User:Crisco 1492|Crisco 1492]] ([[User talk:Crisco 1492|talk]]) 08:54, 25 April 2014 (UTC)
{{POTD/2014-05-24}}</text>
      <sha1>7b3jtm05aa0k8fuzjkltyxudkp7yzka</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
