<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Nelson's Pillar</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>14756877</id>
    <revision>
      <id>717973167</id>
      <parentid>717961769</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-04-30T20:18:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ssilvers</username>
        <id>1329099</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rv disruptive edit. Talk pages are for the discussion of article improvement.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="31001">{{ArticleHistory
|currentstatus=FA
|maindate= 24 April 2016

|action1=PR
|action1date=2016-03-23
|action1link=Wikipedia:Peer_review/Nelson's Pillar/archive1
|action1result=reviewed 
|action1oldid=711492185

|action2=FAC
|action2date=2016-03-30
|action2link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Nelson's Pillar/archive1
|action2result=promoted
|action2oldid=712647363
}}

{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Ireland|class=FA|importance= low}}
{{WikiProject Wikipedia Saves Public Art|class=FA}}
{{WPMILHIST|class=FA|Napoleonic=yes|Memorials=yes}}
}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2004-03-08|oldid1=2758721|date2=2005-03-08|oldid2=16334933|date3=2006-03-08|oldid3=42846917|date4=2007-03-08|oldid4=113499273|date5=2008-03-08|oldid5=196659237|date6=2009-03-08|oldid6=275745981|date7=2010-03-08|oldid7=348457975|date8=2011-03-08|oldid8=417802485}}

-------
{{Archives |auto=yes}}

==24 April 2016==
I've been leaving notes around asking whether anyone would be interested in getting an appropriate article ready as a possible [[WP:TFA]] for the above date, the centenary of the start of the Easter Rising. I've not had much response, so I'm looking myself at likely articles. Now, this is not the most obvious candidate; but I think there would be grave difficulties in getting any of the main Rising articles through the various review hurdles in time for the anniversary. This  is shorter, less contentious, and developed enough to be doable as a featured article in the time available. It's also an interesting, even poignant story. I'm willing to give it a go, and have plenty of good sources (including Kennedy's book) but if possible I like first to hear from any other interested editors. [[User:Brianboulton|Brianboulton]] ([[User talk:Brianboulton|talk]]) 00:21, 8 February 2016 (UTC)
:I'd be happy to help out where I can (though that won't be much). I did add links to [[Nelson's Column]] and [[Monuments and memorials to Horatio Nelson, 1st Viscount Nelson]] in the 'see also' section. That is really a suggestion that links be incorporated into the body of the text somehow. What I'm trying to suggest is that the context of other memorials erected at the same time be included, i.e. to expand a bit on the sentence in the lead: &quot;among the first and grandest monuments&quot;. Where did it stand in terms of size and expense and fame when compared to the other major memorials? [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 13:43, 9 March 2016 (UTC)

A rather esoteric source here: ''[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=J7lLgV6WC7MC Monumental Space in the Post-Imperial Novel: An Interdisciplinary Study]'' (2011) by Rita Sakr. Chapter 2 is the relevant one: '&quot;broken pillars&quot;: Counter-Monumental Tactics in James Joyce's Ulysses'. The pillar appears a couple of times in [[Ulysses (novel)]]. [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 14:34, 9 March 2016 (UTC)

:I haven't tackled the lead at all at this point, and the wording as it appears now will likely be wholly replaced. The point about other equivalent monuments is a good one; the obvious comparison is with the [[Wellington Monument, Dublin|Wellington Monument]], which ought to get a mention somewhere. I will devise an appropriate sentence. As to ''Ulysses'', this is one of several mentions that will be covered in a properly-organised section yet to be drafted. [[User:Brianboulton|Brianboulton]] ([[User talk:Brianboulton|talk]]) 17:59, 12 March 2016 (UTC)

::Thank you. I was just reading through [http://www.historyireland.com/20th-century-contemporary-history/nelsons-pillar/ this] (looks a good source) which says: ''&quot;One proposal was to move it to the Phoenix Park as a companion piece to the Wellington monument. But that idea was dismissed: the Pillar would be dwarfed by the obelisk; 134 feet to the tip of the statue compared to 205 feet to the tip of the much bulkier obelisk.&quot;''. I suspect the Fallon book probably covers this already, but maybe that 1998 article was one of the earlier sources. I hear the Fallon book has lots and lots of pictures. :-) (I was slightly puzzled by the [unexplained] references to 'Gogarty' along with Yeats and Joyce as being among those for whom the monument was 'much loved', presumably [[Oliver St. John Gogarty]]?).  [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 18:23, 12 March 2016 (UTC)

== Images of Nelson's Pillar and related subjects ==

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Between the 1860s and 1911, Nelson was joined by monuments to Daniel O'Connell, William Smith O'Brien and Charles Stuart Parnell, as well as Sir John Gray and the temperance campaigner Father Matthew.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
I went and looked up pictures of these statues to maybe use as additional images in this article (though that is a bit of a stretch - a artwork of the Blakeney statue would have been ideal, but that may not exist). I am not sure where they exist in relation to where the Pillar was, but I found one artwork of the O'Connell statue with the Pillar in the background and added that to the gallery below with a modern photo with the Spire in the background - a nice contrast. Two other galleries as well, with images for consideration (though not as a gallery, as images in the article if appropriate - I am presenting them as galleries here for ease of viewing).
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:FRENCH(1891) p332 STATUE OF DANIEL O'CONNELL.jpg|1891 artwork of O'Connell statue, with Pillar in background
File:OConnellMonument.JPG|2005 photo of O'Connell statue, with Spire in background
&lt;/gallery&gt;
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:William Smith O’Brien Statue Dublin 2009 09 27.JPG|O'Brien statue
File:Memorial to Charles Parnell.jpg|Parnell statue
File:Father Mathew Statue O'Connell Street.JPG|Mathew statue
File:Millennium spire (8197403318).jpg|Gray statue
&lt;/gallery&gt;
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:O'Connell Street from Nelson's Pillar in 1964.jpg|View in 1964 from the Pillar looking south along O'Connell Street to the O'Connell monument
File:View from top of Nelson's Pillar, Sackville Street (O'Connell Street), Dublin.jpg|1921 view looking down from the Pillar to people at its base
&lt;/gallery&gt;
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Pillar2.jpg|Entrance - no date and provenance
File:NelsonP2.jpg|Children on viewing platform - no date and provenance
File:Nelson14.jpg|Viewing platform - poor quality and - no date and provenance
&lt;/gallery&gt;
Would be nice to have images of the entrance and viewing platform, but see [[commons:User talk:Foxhunter22]] (the uploader of those three images) and [[Wikipedia:Media copyright questions#File:No18.jpg]]. Might be worth contacting that user to see what the source of these photos is. [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 13:06, 12 March 2016 (UTC)

:None of the Foxhunter images is safe to use, including those presently in the article gallery which will be removed. While it would be nice to use the entrance and viewing platform images, they are not so essential, in my view, as to warrant the time required to hunt down their sources, particularly as neither is old enough (1950s, probably) to establish PD with certainty. Note: there are excellent images of the entrance in the external link &quot;Old Dublin Town&quot;. On the other monument images listed above, they are mostly not within this article's scope. If someobody wishes to create [[O'Connell Street monuments]], then they will be useful and pertinent; here they are tangential at best. [[User:Brianboulton|Brianboulton]] ([[User talk:Brianboulton|talk]]) 18:44, 12 March 2016 (UTC)
::Understood. This was why I didn't put them in the article without discussing first. The only one that I did put in the article, was removed (as discussed elsewhere). I have now finished a more thorough sweep through Commons to pick up on pictures that include the Pillar, mostly only incidental. I am hopeful I may have found a couple more that are directly of the pillar, which haven't been proposed here before. I will make a gallery of those here and at Commons. That will enable those who follow the link to Commons to see a proper gallery over there. [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 19:14, 12 March 2016 (UTC)
*The gallery at Commons is at [[:commons:Nelson's Pillar, Dublin|Nelson's Pillar, Dublin]]. That page doesn't include [[:File:Sackville St Dublin 1842.jpg]] because some bot hasn't moved it yet (it has been tagged for being moved for more than three years). That 1842 artwork looks a bit strange, because the GPO should be this side of the column. I guess artworks weren't always completely accurate. I will remove the gallery of images of unknown provenance and sort out the deletion requests on Commons. [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 22:09, 12 March 2016 (UTC)

Some additional (old postcard) images spotted [http://joyceimages.com/episode/7/?page=11 here]. Maybe worth following up. I did notice this factoid: ''&quot;In 1900, it was the 4th highest monument in the world.&quot;'' Can that be reliably sourced? Am currently trying to work out how G. P. Baxter (the designer of the 1894 entrance) was... [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 00:55, 13 March 2016 (UTC)
:One puzzle solved - it was [http://www.dia.ie/architects/view/379/BEATER,+GEORGE+PALMER George Palmer Beater] (not Baxter). Many sources out there are repeating this error. Hopefully this correction will start the slow process of reversing that spread of misinformation (where-ever it originated from). [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 01:06, 13 March 2016 (UTC)
::For the record, the text referring to 'G. P. Baxter' was added [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Nelson%27s_Pillar&amp;diff=next&amp;oldid=4146205 18 June 2004] and persisted until being removed on [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Nelson%27s_Pillar&amp;diff=678199360&amp;oldid=678198771 27 August 2015]. The correct G. P. Beater was added on [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Nelson%27s_Pillar&amp;diff=709782917&amp;oldid=709782646 13 March 2016]. This is only one example of many errors and corrections made over the course of the history of most articles in Wikipedia. It is unfortunate that this error also exists outside Wikipedia. Whether the online sources that currently refer to G.P. Baxter were misled by Wikipedia is not clear, but that may have happened as printed sources don't as far as I can tell make this error. [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 14:14, 13 March 2016 (UTC)

===Fair use images===
Among the images I recently removed, there was one fair use image ([[:File:Nelsons Pillar Dublin2.jpg]]). The source information is not good enough there, IMO, and as we have the National Library of Ireland image of the bombed column, there probably isn't enough justification to have any fair use images in this article, but adding this section in case it is worth discussing. [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 13:13, 13 March 2016 (UTC)

===National Library of Ireland images===
The [http://catalogue.nli.ie/ National Library of Ireland catalogue] can be searched for images. Some examples I found (others may want to look for more) are:
*[http://catalogue.nli.ie/Record/vtls000534531 Order of the procession, on laying the first stone] (1808)
*[http://catalogue.nli.ie/Record/vtls000182715 Sackville Street, Dublin] (1860-1880)
*[http://catalogue.nli.ie/Record/vtls000148773 Nelson's Pillar] (this one is already uploaded from the British Library [[:File:DUBLIN(1811) p202 NELSON'S PILLAR.jpg|here]])
*[http://catalogue.nli.ie/Record/vtls000036248 View of the Post Office &amp; Nelson's Pillar] (Brocas engraving)
*[http://catalogue.nli.ie/Record/vtls000182851 George IV visit to Dublin in 1821] (flag on Pillar)
*[http://catalogue.nli.ie/Record/vtls000046680 The G.P.O. and Nelson's Pillar, O'Connell Street, Dublin], a nice inter-war image, but unlikely to be freely licensed
Some of these may be better than existing images. Depends on whether there is the time to work on this aspect of the article or not, or whether the existing images suffice. [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 22:26, 14 March 2016 (UTC)

==Cultural references==
As well as the mention in [[Ulysses (novel)]] by James Joyce, the Pillar is mentioned in a poem (''Dublin'') by [[Louis MacNeice]]. Both quoted [http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-35787116 here]. [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 16:03, 12 March 2016 (UTC)
:There was an earlier sentence in [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Nelson%27s_Pillar&amp;oldid=701329384 this version] of the article before the recent changes: ''&quot;[[Oliver St. John Gogarty|Oliver St John Gogarty]] described it as &quot;the grandest thing we have in Dublin&quot; in [[As I Was Going Down Sackville Street]].&quot;'' Leaving this note here as a reminder for when this section gets re-worked. [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 18:26, 12 March 2016 (UTC)
:And from the Dublin City Public Libraries photostream on Flickr: [https://www.flickr.com/photos/dublincitypubliclibraries/9023104727 O'Connell Monument, Nelson's Pillar, O'Connell Street, June 1962], with a quotation from ''[[Strumpet City]]'' (1969) by [[James Plunkett]]. There will be many such throwaway references, but collecting them here in case they are of use. [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 19:10, 12 March 2016 (UTC)
::I have the cultural refs you mention, and a few others... In redrafting this section, selection is important; &quot;throwaway&quot; references in books such as Plunkett's are ten a penny, and the section could easily become a dumping ground for each and every time the Pillar is mentioned in any novel with an Irish background.  Acknowleged literature (e.g. Yeats, Gogarty, Joyce, Austin Clarke and MacNeice} is a different matter. [[User:Brianboulton|Brianboulton]] ([[User talk:Brianboulton|talk]]) 16:39, 14 March 2016 (UTC)
:::Definitely avoid the section becoming a dumping ground for throwaway references. Any quotes or mentions in cultural works need to be backed up by serious discussion in secondary literature. Having said that, I have a small collection I put together today, which I'll put here for consideration. [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 22:01, 14 March 2016 (UTC)
Some examples of this monument in poetry and other cultural works:
*Good discussion of some cultural themes [http://mulliken.okstate.edu/nelsons-pillar/ here].
*Yeats wrote a poem called '[http://www.poemhunter.com/best-poems/william-butler-yeats/the-three-monuments/ The Three Monuments]' (written 1925, published 1927 - [https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=MZWwCwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA86#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false]). This is a reference to Nelson's Pillar and two other monuments either side (Parnell and O'Connell) - see [https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=glhvNnjjNagC&amp;pg=PA76#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false here]. (This makes Plunkett's contrasting of the three monuments in ''Strumpet City'' positively Yeatsian!)
*[[Austin Clarke (poet)]] wrote 'Nelson's Pillar, Dublin' (1960)
*[[Richard Murphy (poet)]] in the 1980s wrote 'Nelson's Pillar' in ''The Price of Stone &amp; Earlier Poems'' (it appeared in Part 6: The Price of Stone 1981-1984), the opening stanza being: &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;My duty done, I rose as a Doric column&lt;br/&gt;Far from at home, planted to reach the sky;&lt;br/&gt; A huge stake in the crossed heart of a glum&lt;br/&gt; Garrison city overlooked by my blind eye.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
*[[Mairéad Byrne]] wrote 'The Pillar' (published in a 2003 collection). See [http://www.wildhoneypress.com/BOOKS/NELSON.HTM here], [http://www.wildhoneypress.com/BOOKS/PILLAR.html here], [http://www.wildhoneypress.com/BOOKS/The%20Pillar_fulltext.htm here] and [http://www.wildhoneypress.com/Reviews/Alan%20Sondheim%20on%20Mairead.htm here]. Not sure if there is much more to say there (i.e. I am not sure if there is commentary on that work in secondary literature). 
*Not relevant for this article, but I might see if it is worth using in a more relevant article, the poet [[George Croly]] published a collection of poems in 1820 called ''The Angel of the World'', one of which was a poem called 'Nelson's Pillar'. It can be read [http://www.forgottenbooks.com/readbook_text/The_Angel_of_the_World_An_Arabian_Tale_Sebastian_A_Spanish_Tale_1000177586/169 here] and [http://www.forgottenbooks.com/readbook_text/The_Angel_of_the_World_An_Arabian_Tale_Sebastian_A_Spanish_Tale_1000177586/171 here] (split over two pages). Nice poem. Not this Pillar, but about the [[Britannia Monument]], which was also [http://www.mustrad.org.uk/articles/nelson.htm mentioned in a song]. Seems that writing poetry and singing about Nelson monuments doesn't just happen in Dublin.
That's probably enough examples. [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 22:01, 14 March 2016 (UTC)
*I've not used all of these, or the section would be disproportionate, but a fair sample are there. [[User:Brianboulton|Brianboulton]] ([[User talk:Brianboulton|talk]]) 21:32, 16 March 2016 (UTC)

== Architectural sources ==

These entries [http://www.dia.ie/works/view/37333/building here] may be of use (from the Irish Architectural Archive's ''Dictionary of Irish Architects''). [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 01:53, 13 March 2016 (UTC)
:A footnote [https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=rL7XbB3l7nUC&amp;pg=PA68 here] states that there was a stone sarcophagus placed over the Trafalgar panel and that the sarcophagus had been removed by 1866. This sarcophagus is visible in [[:File:DUBLIN(1837) p089 NELSON'S PILLAR, SACKVILLE STREET.jpg|this artwork]]. A crop of this artwork would show both the sarcophagus and an example of the inscriptions. There were renovations and repairs that took place in 1868 (the architect was Sandham Symes), so maybe that is related in some way. [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 02:25, 13 March 2016 (UTC)

This looks to be a useful source with much on Nelson's Pillar (they call it the Nelson Monument) and also comparing it with the Wellington Monument: [http://yalebooks.co.uk/pdf/9780300159097.pdf 'Deification in the early century'], which is chapter 1 of ''[http://yalebooks.co.uk/display.asp?k=9780300159097 Nineteenth-century Irish Sculpture]'' (2010) by Paula Murphy. Has an artwork of the laying of the foundation stone. [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 02:52, 13 March 2016 (UTC)

I took the time to look up the other architects who submitted designs to the competition, according to the ''Dictionary of Irish Architects'' (though some care should be taken when using this source). The ones we have articles on are: [[Henry A. Baker]], [[Sir Richard Morrison]] and the rather more famous [[Joseph Gwilt]] (though this was early on in his career). [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 20:33, 14 March 2016 (UTC)

== Art history ==

[[George Petrie (artist)]] should probably get a mention because: (a) [[:File:DUBLIN(1837) p089 NELSON'S PILLAR, SACKVILLE STREET.jpg|this artwork]] is one of his; and (b) because other people have highlighted his work, such as [https://www.ria.ie/ga/node/93150 here] and [http://www.tcd.ie/Library/about/exhibitions/drawn-to-the-page/printing.php here]. [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 03:01, 13 March 2016 (UTC)

== Sarcophagus and original entrance location ==

I found a source that said where the original entrance location was - it was on the west side of the monument according to Whelan in ''Reinventing Modern Dublin: Streetscape, Iconography and the Politics of Identity'' (2003): ''&quot;The entrance was positioned to the west side of the monument, approached by a flight of steps which brought the visitor beneath the street level under the pillar to where the spiral stairs of 168 steps commenced.&quot;''

I also found an additional source, a 72-page work called ''[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=f-dOAAAAMAAJ A Monument in the City: Nelson's Pillar and Its Aftermath]'' (1998) by John O'Regan. I presume later sources used this, but it might have more details to add. It was where I found more details of the sarcophagus (not a real sarcophagus of course, just an architectural/sculptural feature): ''&quot;In the collection of architectural drawings in the National Library there are four Francis Johnston drawings of Nelson's Pillar. [...] The second sheet is a sketch of the Pillar as it was executed [...] This is an important drawing as it shows the sarcophagus which has since been removed.&quot;'' I think O'Regan is quoting from Henchy's 1948 article in the ''Dublin Historical Record'', so maybe those with full access to that could add a sentence about this?
:Henchy's article mentions that the sarcophagus was on the south side and was removed before 1866. He also gives details of the old entrance on the west side. I have added a sentence to the article confirming the location of the original entrance. [[User:Brianboulton|Brianboulton]] ([[User talk:Brianboulton|talk]]) 17:45, 14 March 2016 (UTC) 

Possibly of interest is [http://archive.irishartsreview.com/gpairisartsrevi/pdf/1988/20492060.pdf.bannered.pdf SACKVILLE STREET/O'CONNELL STREET] by Maura Shaffrey and published in the ''Irish Arts Review'' in 1988. It opens with a nice artwork of Sackville Street from the 1760s before the Pillar was erected (plus a nice view of the Pillar on page 146). [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 18:09, 13 March 2016 (UTC)

== Irish and British parliamentary debates ==

A couple of points about the British and Irish legislatures and the bills relating to the Pillar:
*[https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Nelson%27s_Pillar&amp;diff=709932349&amp;oldid=709931882 This edit] replaced the 'Nelson Pillar Act, 1969' source I had created a citation template for. It would be good to see this brought back, IMO, because: (a) the [http://www.irishstatutebook.ie/eli/1969/act/9/enacted/en/html page itself] actually shows the full text of the bill (the link can be changed to the full text if needed) and could be of interest to readers of the article. It is also a better source for factual details of the bill, as opposed to the source to a debate in the Irish Senate.
:*OK, I've restored the Bill source (I think it was removed in error when I revised the section. [[User:Brianboulton|Brianboulton]] ([[User talk:Brianboulton|talk]]) 21:43, 16 March 2016 (UTC)
*I read that debate in the Irish Senate in full [http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/DebatesWebPack.nsf/takes/seanad1969042300013?opendocument]. Some rather funny (in one sort of way) moments there. I was reminded of this when I came across another parliamentary debate that took place in London in 1891. [http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/commons/1891/feb/13/second-reading Second Reading of the Nelson's Pillar (Dublin) Bill] (Like the other debate, this is worth reading in full). Might it be worth working that into the article somehow?
:*On balance I believe this would be excesssive detail. Sheehy-Skeffington's point is a useful one, but in the main it's the cosequences of these acts, not the detailed debates, which are our concern. [[User:Brianboulton|Brianboulton]] ([[User talk:Brianboulton|talk]]) 21:43, 16 March 2016 (UTC)
I haven't found any other parliamentary debates specifically relating to the Pillar, but it would be good to find them if they exist. [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 21:01, 14 March 2016 (UTC)

== Comparison with other monuments ==

Starting a section to discuss the potential material relating to other monuments. The ones that should be mentioned, IMO, are:
*[[Nelson's Column]] - seems obvious to compare cost, height and timing. I did read somewhere that some criticised the Pillar in Dublin because of a lack of proper carvings. That might have been expanded on somewhere in the histories and commentaries. But maybe not - have struggled to find much here.
*[[Wellington Monument, Dublin]] - several sources compare the Pillar and this monument, raised in Dublin to another British hero of the Napoleonic Wars, but which didn't suffer the fate of the Pillar.
*[[Britannia Monument]] - very similar in design (same panels), and by [[William Wilkins (architect)|William Wilkins]], so the connection is obvious there.
Are there any other monuments that this one has been compared and contrasted with? Maybe [[Nelson's Column, Montreal]] as an example of another early column? [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 21:16, 14 March 2016 (UTC)
:*Definitely the Trafalgar Square column needs a mention - some of the comparative details might be footnoted. Wellington's obelisk in Phoenix Park is also worthy of comment. If you've seen it you'll realise why it couldn't be disposed of à la Nelson: it's absolutely massive at the base and would take several tons of dynamite to shift. See [[:File:Ireland - Dublin - Phoenix Park - Wellington Monument 2.jpg|here]] Also it doesn't involve a statue or a likeness so it's less personal. And Wellington, unlike Nelson, was an Irishman (albeit of the Ascendancy) which probably counted in his favour. I'll incorporate some text on these two, but I don't think the Britannia and the Montreal warrrant inclusion. [[User:Brianboulton|Brianboulton]] ([[User talk:Brianboulton|talk]]) 16:25, 16 March 2016 (UTC)
::*Noting here that a comment at the featured article candidate discussion led to [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Nelson%27s_Pillar&amp;diff=712072532&amp;oldid=712068998 a footnote being added] regarding the Montreal column. [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 00:02, 30 March 2016 (UTC)

== &quot;located&quot; and &quot;until 1924 Sackville Street&quot; ==

This is a great article and it is good to see it as our featured article of the day! However, there are a couple of issues in the lede that I think should be discussed. At present, the opening sentence reads &quot;Nelson's Pillar (also known as the Nelson Pillar or simply The Pillar) was a large granite column capped by a statue of Horatio Nelson, in the centre of O'Connell Street (until 1924 Sackville Street) in Dublin, Ireland.&quot; Personally I think that there are two prose issues here that we could do something about. First, I would recommend adding &quot;located&quot; at the juncture between &quot;Horatio Nelson,&quot; and &quot;in the centre&quot;; I made that change myself but it was then reverted. I nevertheless think it to be a good addition and would like to see if I can get some support for its reintroduction. The second issue lies with &quot;(until 1924 Sackville Street)&quot; which I think has the capacity to confuse some readers, particularly those in the United States. For instance, the sentence could be misread as referring to a location that was in the juxtaposition of two separate roads, O'Connell Street and Sackville Street. In such a scenario, &quot;1924&quot; might be mistaken for an address rather than a year, which is something I think that we should be trying to avoid; we could perhaps go with something more precise like &quot;&quot;known as Sackville Street prior to 1924)&quot; instead. [[User:Midnightblueowl|Midnightblueowl]] ([[User talk:Midnightblueowl|talk]]) 18:23, 24 April 2016 (UTC)

Ya know us yanks don't really get confused as much as you folk think. [[User:JuanRiley|Juan Riley ]] ([[User talk:JuanRiley|talk]]) 19:35, 24 April 2016 (UTC)
:Ah, I should probably have qualified why I made reference to our American readers! It's because in U.S. urban centres like New York City one can find locations with names like &quot;1235 West Street&quot; and such; very high numbers appended to street names. These are far less common in Europe, or at least the British Isles. My original comment was most certainly not meant as a slur on the intelligence of Americans! [[User:Midnightblueowl|Midnightblueowl]] ([[User talk:Midnightblueowl|talk]]) 21:01, 24 April 2016 (UTC)
::Sorry I misinterpreted you. Got it now. Have a good day. [[User:JuanRiley|Juan Riley ]] ([[User talk:JuanRiley|talk]]) 21:10, 24 April 2016 (UTC)

*Midnightblueowl, thank you for doing the decent thing and coming to the talk page to discuss. It's a shame that juanriley doesn't seem to have the good manners or grace to follow your example, and has decided to edit war the point, despite being asked to follow both [[WP:BRD]] and [[WP:STATUSQUO]]. Some people are so tiresome in their efforts to get their own way. It's especially sad to see that, despite edit warring to insert the word once again, they can't remain honest in what they are doing, claiming &quot;no edit war&quot;, even though they are... edit warring. - [[User:SchroCat|SchroCat]] ([[User talk:SchroCat|talk]]) 19:50, 24 April 2016 (UTC)

Having followed this article through peer review and FAC, I know a little bit about how the phrasing here changed. The lead as it currently stands was first drafted [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Nelson%27s_Pillar&amp;diff=710445344&amp;oldid=710437301 here]: ''&quot;situated in the middle of [[O'Connell Street]] (originally Sackville Street)&quot;''. The word 'originally' was then changed to [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Nelson%27s_Pillar&amp;diff=712068998&amp;oldid=712067483 previously] as the street was once a lane called Drogheda Street (as the article itself states). This is one reason why the current wording of 'known as Sackville Street prior to 1924' is not ideal. The wording changed again with [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Nelson%27s_Pillar&amp;diff=712106402&amp;oldid=712105361 this edit] to ''&quot;in the center of [[O'Connell Street]] (then Sackville Street)&quot;'' (with 'centre' later changed to 'centre'). The wording that appeared on the main page was established in its final form [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Nelson%27s_Pillar&amp;diff=712218082&amp;oldid=712212248 here], with 'then' becoming 'until'. Then the word 'located' was [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Nelson%27s_Pillar&amp;diff=716871048&amp;oldid=716858706 added], edit warred over, and finally the current version of the text was formulated [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Nelson%27s_Pillar&amp;diff=next&amp;oldid=716961249 here]: ''&quot;located in the centre of [[O'Connell Street]] (known as Sackville Street prior to 1924)&quot;''. I have [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Nelson%27s_Pillar&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=717064923&amp;oldid=717051353 tried a different phrasing], turning things round a bit, emphasising the location name when it was ''built'' and immediately referring the reader to the modern name to avoid confusion (''&quot;built in the centre of what was then Sackville Street (later O'Connell Street)&quot;''). I left out the date when the street name changed, as that is too detailed for the lead section. [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 14:38, 25 April 2016 (UTC)
:That looks good, Carcharoth. Cheers - [[User:SchroCat|SchroCat]] ([[User talk:SchroCat|talk]]) 14:54, 25 April 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>f6h7w4g87yylsd08cel0vhimqgzi29p</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
