<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:1940 Brocklesby mid-air collision</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>31078408</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738265844</id>
      <parentid>738237072</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-07T22:40:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ian Rose</username>
        <id>502570</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Clarify &quot;pancake landing&quot; */ ++</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18291">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=16:26, 6 March 2011
|action1link=Talk:1940 Brocklesby mid-air collision/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=417380748

|action2=WAR
|action2date=04:35, 22 May 2014 (UTC)
|action2link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/1940 Brocklesby mid-air collision
|action2result=approved
|action2oldid=608918404
|four=yes

|action3=FAC
|action3date=14:34, 8 August 2014
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/1940 Brocklesby mid-air collision/archive1
|action3result=promoted
|action3oldid=620396363

|dykdate=13 March 2011
|dykentry=... that on 29 September 1940, two [[Avro Anson]]s '''[[1940 Brocklesby mid-air collision|collided in mid-air]]''' over [[Brocklesby, New South Wales|Brocklesby]], Australia, became locked together in &quot;piggyback&quot; fashion, and then successfully landed in a field?
|currentstatus=FA
|topic=History
|maindate=29 September 2014
}}
{{talkheader}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Aviation|class=FA|Accident=y}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=FA|A-Class=pass|Aviation=y|ANZSP=y|WWII=y}}
{{WikiProject Australia|class=FA|importance=Low|military=y|military-importance=Low}}
}}

{{Talk:1940 Brocklesby mid-air collision/GA1}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2015-09-29|oldid1=683267097}}

==Title==
Should this have the &quot;1940&quot;? It is not necessary for disambiguation.--[[User:Grahamec|Grahame]] ([[User talk:Grahamec|talk]]) 01:10, 7 March 2011 (UTC)
:Heh, I agree it isn't required for dab purposes -- it's my first air accident article from scratch and it looked like including the year might be a standard but, if not, I have no problem with losing it. Cheers, [[User:Ian Rose|Ian Rose]] ([[User talk:Ian Rose|talk]]) 01:49, 7 March 2011 (UTC)
::I'm not particularly worried.--[[User:Grahamec|Grahame]] ([[User talk:Grahamec|talk]]) 07:44, 7 March 2011 (UTC)

== Telekinetic pilot? ==
How could the pilot of the upper Anson have controlled the engines of the lower Anson from the upper Anson?  Sounds like a hoax to me. --[[User:Whoop whoop pull up|Whoop whoop pull up]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Whoop whoop pull up|Bitching Betty]] | [[Special:Contributions/Whoop whoop pull up|Averted crashes]]&lt;/sup&gt; 21:43, 23 June 2011 (UTC)
:I don't believe it says he controlled the engines of the lower aircraft; it says that with the engines of the lower aircraft still running, couple with the control surfaces of his own (upper) aircraft, he was able to fly the interlocked planes. Cheers, [[User:Ian Rose|Ian Rose]] ([[User talk:Ian Rose|talk]]) 21:52, 23 June 2011 (UTC)

Yes, but once the pair of planes is on the ground, and the engines of the lower plane roaring at cruise speed (or higher, probably), how would they be throttled down or turned off?  Also, what's a &quot;tailplane&quot;? [[User:Terry Thorgaard|Terry Thorgaard]] ([[User talk:Terry Thorgaard|talk]]) 16:59, 29 September 2014 (UTC)
: {{u|Terry Thorgaard}}, It appears from the photo that the landing gear of the lower aircraft was crushed on landing. The propellers would have hit the ground. From [[:Image:WhenAnsonLandsOnAnson1940.jpg]] it appears the tips of the propellers snapped off and it's likely the engine was still running. In that case, the pilot of the upper aircraft likely climbed into the lower aircraft and shut down the engines.

: I too wondered what a &quot;tailplane&quot; was. The term is not listed an 1942 aviation dictionary that I have which also includes slang used by the American and British flying forces.  That dictionary's definition for &quot;tail&quot; uses the wording &quot;.. a group of stabilizing planes, or fins, to which are attached certain controlling surfaces such as [[Elevator (aeronautics)|elevator]]s and [[rudder]]s&quot;.  I usually call them the [[horizontal stabilizer]]s and [[vertical stabilizer]]s and had to laugh when I saw that &quot;horizontal stabilizer&quot; redirects to [[tailplane]].  FWIW, neither horizontal stabilizer nor vertical stabilizer are listed in the dictionary. I've started a [[Talk:Tailplane#US versus UK English|talk discussion]] on the tailplane page as it's a UK term. --[[User:Marc Kupper|Marc Kupper]]&amp;#124;[[User talk:Marc Kupper|talk]] 17:52, 29 September 2014 (UTC)
::“Tailplane” distinguishes the little wings at the back from the “mainplane”, the big wings.  That said, don’t know how I failed to link it when I linked flaps and ailerons – tks for taking care of it. Cheers, [[User:Ian Rose|Ian Rose]] ([[User talk:Ian Rose|talk]]) 23:55, 29 September 2014 (UTC)

== a/an historic marker ==
Is it because &quot;a historic marker&quot; tends to imply &quot;a marker indicating an historically notable place or event&quot; while &quot;an historic marker&quot; tends to imply &quot;a marker which is, itself, historically notable&quot;? But if it's the latter, doesn't any application of &quot;historic&quot; to a marker, without further elucidation, imply that the maker itself is notable, history-wise? Some other word or phrase might be called for. On the other hand, &quot;historic marker&quot; is idiomatic and most everyone understands what is meant. [[User:Herostratus|Herostratus]] ([[User talk:Herostratus|talk]]) 20:48, 25 April 2014 (UTC)
:Hi Hero, you're replying to my edit summary? No, they mean the same thing. I'm currently working on copyediting software, and the advice on word usage falls into two piles: things that pretty much everyone agrees on (after they read up a bit), and things that some writers really want to know and others don't care about. This one is in the second batch; so far, I've only seen one South African writer and Ian use &quot;an historical&quot; on Wikipedia, and commenters on usage for the last 200 years have almost universally recommended against it (because it suggests that you're dropping the &quot;h&quot; sound, which ... sadly ... makes some readers assume things about your class or education). But ''[[Garner's]]'' admits that this usage is &quot;widespread&quot; in the journalistic corpus he uses, so I would never put this in a list of &quot;mistakes&quot; (such as the list at [[WP:RETF]]) ... but if writers are interested in knowing the opinions of copyeditors, we generally recommend against it (in all flavors of English). - Dank ([[User talk:Dank|push to talk]]) 21:44, 25 April 2014 (UTC)
::Oh, OK. Well, you should stop doing that I guess, since &quot;an historical...&quot; is both common and correct. Certainly in America; you may be from one of the more minor English-speaking countries, and I can't speak for them. It's not a class or education issue, at all, and has nothing do with dropping aitches but rather the way sounds are formed in the mouth. In America at least &quot;a&quot; is generally pronounced more or less &quot;ah&quot; rather than &quot;ay&quot; as may be found elsewhere, thus making &quot;a historical...&quot; (&quot;ah hi..&quot;) physically awkward (the technical terms for this -- unvoiced subglottal fricatives or whatever it is -- are above my pay grade, but you can look it up). Since that's how people talk, that's how it's written -- commonly.

::''Commonly'', I say; not universally, or even (as far as I know) most often; but often enough to be common. Since it's common, it's not &quot;wrong&quot; but just a matter of personal preference. Since it's personal preference, it's not recommended to substitute yours for a previous editors, since that's sterile roiling of the text to no objective gain, and let's not do that, and I've restored the previous version on that basis. [[User:Herostratus|Herostratus]] ([[User talk:Herostratus|talk]]) 02:37, 26 April 2014 (UTC)

== FAC blurb is longer than article lead ==
I noticed that the FAC blurb is longer than the article lead itself (181 words versus 120 words). Normally the FAC blurb is shorter than the lead; what do you think about replacing the current introduction with the more descriptive FAC blurb? [[User:AmericanLemming|AmericanLemming]] ([[User talk:AmericanLemming|talk]]) 00:46, 29 September 2014 (UTC)

{{quote box
|quote = On 29 September 1940, a mid-air collision occurred over Brocklesby, New South Wales, Australia. Two Avro Ansons of No. 2 Service Flying Training School RAAF were on a cross-country navigational exercise and made a banking turn at an altitude of 1,000 feet (300 metres). Leading Aircraftman Leonard Fuller lost sight of the aircraft below him, and the pair collided, locking together and knocking out the upper Anson's engines. The lower Anson's turret wedged into the other's port wing root, its fin and rudder balancing the upper aircraft's port tailplane. Both navigators and the pilot of the lower Anson bailed out. Fuller found that he was able to control the interlocked aircraft using his ailerons and flaps, together with the still-functioning engines on the machine underneath. After flying for five miles (eight kilometres), he made an emergency landing in a paddock. All four crewmen survived the incident, and the upper Anson was repaired and returned to flight service. The freak accident garnered news coverage around the world and, according to the Greater Hume Shire Council, it remains Brocklesby's &quot;main claim to fame&quot;.
|source = FAC blurb}}

{{quote box
|quote = On 29 September 1940, a mid-air collision occurred over Brocklesby, New South Wales, Australia. The accident was unusual in that the aircraft involved, two Avro Ansons of No. 2 Service Flying Training School RAAF, remained locked together after colliding, and then landed safely. Both navigators and the pilot of the lower Anson bailed out after the collision. The pilot of the upper Anson found that he was able to control the interlocked aircraft with his ailerons and flaps, together with the still-functioning engines on the machine underneath. He elected to stay with the aircraft, and made an emergency landing in a nearby paddock. All four crewmen survived the incident, and the upper Anson was repaired and returned to flight service.
|source = Article introduction}}


:'''Oppose.''' The FAC blurb does well as a standalone summary of the article. Really, either quote works well to summarize the article. But the FAC blurb seems too detailed for the article's lead section. [[MOS:BEGIN]] says &quot;The first paragraph should define the topic with a neutral point of view, but without being overly specific.&quot; The article lead should not give all the details that are in the FAC blurb, not with the more detailed coverage of the collision in the main text. [[User:NealCruco|NealCruco]] ([[User talk:NealCruco|talk]]) 02:57, 29 September 2014 (UTC)
::I agree with Neal. FAC blurbs need to be of a certain length to occupy the space allocated for them on the main page, and so sometimes end up longer than the lead of the article. In general it's best to keep the length of the lead of articles to a short summary, and not go into more detail than is needed to provide readers with an overview of the topic. [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 11:36, 29 September 2014 (UTC)
:(edit conflict with Nick-D) Perhaps a word from the person who writes most of the TFA blurbs would be helpful. The TFA blurb is always a [[Procrustian]] solution since it works to a target of 1,200 characters to ensure regularity of size of blurb to help with balance between the left- and right-hand sides of the main page every day. Leads that are longer than this get chopped down, leads that are shorter get expanded.  The arbitrary character count requirements of the TFA blurb should not dictate the contents of the lead of an article. [[User:Bencherlite|Bencherlite]][[User talk:Bencherlite|&lt;i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Talk&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/i&gt;]] 11:39, 29 September 2014 (UTC)

== Control with second aircraft's engines ==
{{Tq|&quot;The pilot of the upper Anson found that he was able to control the interlocked aircraft with... the still-functioning engines on the machine underneath.&quot;}}

Having been raised on this page ''[[#Telekinetic pilot?|in 2011]]'', it's remarkable that this nonsensical claim is on the main page today. &lt;span class=&quot;vcard&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fn&quot;&gt;[[User:Pigsonthewing|Andy Mabbett]]&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;span class=&quot;nickname&quot;&gt;Pigsonthewing&lt;/span&gt;); [[User talk:Pigsonthewing|Talk to Andy]]; [[Special:Contributions/Pigsonthewing|Andy's edits]]&lt;/span&gt; 11:13, 29 September 2014 (UTC)
:I'm not sure why you omitted the part of the sentence which connects these facts? &quot;The pilot of the upper Anson found that he was able to control the interlocked aircraft with his ailerons and flaps, together with the still-functioning engines on the machine underneath&quot; seems sensible to me - the pilot used the controls of his aircraft to steer, and the engines of the other aircraft powered the two aircraft along. There's scope to clarify the wording (perhaps &quot;The pilot of the upper Anson found that he was able to control the interlocked aircraft with his ailerons and flaps, with the still-functioning engines on the machine underneath providing propulsion&quot; or similar?), but it's not &quot;nonsensical&quot; IMO. {{ping|Ian Rose}} what do you think? [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 11:25, 29 September 2014 (UTC)
::Hmm, I think that two people in the space of two years have forgotten that in English, &quot;aircraft&quot; is plural as well as singular. I mean we could say the &quot;pair of aircraft&quot;, or &quot;the combination&quot; was being controlled, but we've already established the two were locked together so it seems superfluous to me. Cheers, [[User:Ian Rose|Ian Rose]] ([[User talk:Ian Rose|talk]]) 11:33, 29 September 2014 (UTC)
:It's true that the original wording was comprehensible once you thought about it and understood what it meant, but it still sounded odd, and it threw me off at first. So I took the trouble to reword it to remove the ambiguity. In so doing I realized that the original statement never explained that the upper aircraft's engines had stopped, so I pointed that out. --[[User:Colin Douglas Howell|Colin Douglas Howell]] ([[User talk:Colin Douglas Howell|talk]]) 13:32, 29 September 2014 (UTC)
::Fair point about clarifying that one Anson's engines stopped, I just re-tweaked a bit. Cheers, [[User:Ian Rose|Ian Rose]] ([[User talk:Ian Rose|talk]]) 13:54, 29 September 2014 (UTC)
:::Definitely an improvement. Thanks. :) --[[User:Colin Douglas Howell|Colin Douglas Howell]] ([[User talk:Colin Douglas Howell|talk]]) 15:35, 29 September 2014 (UTC)

== Well done ==
Rather brilliant FA, well done involved editors! Best wishes [[Special:Contributions/77.96.249.228|77.96.249.228]] ([[User talk:77.96.249.228|talk]]) 21:25, 29 September 2014 (UTC)

== Collision and emergency landing question ==
Shouldn't the last sentence of the paragraph, &quot;Well, sir, I did everything we've been told to do in a forced landing—land as close as possible to habitation or a farmhouse and, if possible, land into the wind. I did all that. There's the farmhouse, and I did a couple of circuits and landed into the wind. She was pretty heavy on the controls, though!&quot; be in quotation marks? [[User:Ward20|Ward20]] ([[User talk:Ward20|talk]]) 21:57, 29 September 2014 (UTC)
:From memory the quote marks are discouraged these days. Cheers, [[User:Ian Rose|Ian Rose]] ([[User talk:Ian Rose|talk]]) 23:12, 29 September 2014 (UTC)
::Thanks. [[User:Ward20|Ward20]] ([[User talk:Ward20|talk]]) 23:18, 29 September 2014 (UTC)

== External links modified ==
Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[1940 Brocklesby mid-air collision]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=711976060 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Attempted to fix sourcing for http://www.awm.gov.au/catalogue/research_centre/pdf/rc09125z007_1.pdf

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=true}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 02:50, 26 March 2016 (UTC)

== Clarify &quot;pancake landing&quot; ==

As above. [[Special:Contributions/178.16.15.40|178.16.15.40]] ([[User talk:178.16.15.40|talk]]) 14:10, 7 September 2016 (UTC)
:No need to. It is already linked in mainspace to [[Belly landing]] which is simply another term for it. [[User:Irondome|Irondome]] ([[User talk:Irondome|talk]]) 14:40, 7 September 2016 (UTC)
::Tks Irondome, I was about to respond that I don't think &quot;[[pancake landing]]&quot; is a particularly obscure or hard-to-understand term, and that it's linked anyway.  Cheers, [[User:Ian Rose|Ian Rose]] ([[User talk:Ian Rose|talk]]) 14:42, 7 September 2016 (UTC)
::: That's not an argument against changing it to something else that could be clearer, though, is it? It's just you asserting that, subjectively, you yourself don't see a problem. [[Special:Contributions/178.16.15.40|178.16.15.40]] ([[User talk:178.16.15.40|talk]]) 16:44, 7 September 2016 (UTC)
::: In fact, if you would, would you mind specifying any reasons you see ''pancake landing'' as better. [[Special:Contributions/178.16.15.40|178.16.15.40]] ([[User talk:178.16.15.40|talk]]) 16:47, 7 September 2016 (UTC)
::::See below. Cheers, [[User:Ian Rose|Ian Rose]] ([[User talk:Ian Rose|talk]]) 22:40, 7 September 2016 (UTC)
:: Presumably then it could simply be changed to use the term ''belly landing'' with absolutely no other change in as far as you you can see then? [[Special:Contributions/178.16.15.40|178.16.15.40]] ([[User talk:178.16.15.40|talk]]) 16:43, 7 September 2016 (UTC)
:::[[WP:ENGVAR]] comes into it. Pancake landing was a widely used term in the R.A.F, R.A.A.F and other Commonwealth air forces. Belly landing was the U.S.A.A.F preferred term. I think Pancake landing in this subject context would be the preferred term here. [[User:Irondome|Irondome]] ([[User talk:Irondome|talk]]) 17:36, 7 September 2016 (UTC)
::::Fully agree, I mentioned &quot;pancake&quot; being the preferred Commonwealth term in my edit summary when the term was first changed in the article prior to this discussion. Cheers, [[User:Ian Rose|Ian Rose]] ([[User talk:Ian Rose|talk]]) 22:40, 7 September 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>tb1vsmle1agexktmyuu86blphgbpca6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
