<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Stephen, King of England</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>70259</id>
    <revision>
      <id>747368351</id>
      <parentid>744956680</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-02T00:05:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Adding/updating {{OnThisDay}} for 2016-11-01.  Errors? [[User:AnomieBOT/shutoff/OnThisDayTagger]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="27900">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=20:25, 2 July 2011
|action1link=Talk:Stephen, King of England/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=437439318

|action2=WAR
|action2date=15:18, 18 August 2011 
|action2link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/Stephen, King of England
|action2result=approved
|action2oldid=445299597

|action3=FAC
|action3date=14:52, 15 October 2011
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Stephen, King of England/archive1
|action3result=promoted
|action3oldid=455392933

|topic=Royalty, nobility and heraldry
|currentstatus=FA
}}
{{talk header}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Biography|living=no|class=FA|military-work-group=yes|military-priority=mid|royalty-work-group=yes|listas=Stephen Of England}}
{{WikiProject Middle Ages|class=FA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject English Royalty|class=FA|importance=high}}
{{WPMILHIST|class=FA|b1=y|b2=y|b3=y|b4=y|b5=y|Biography=y |British=y |Medieval-task-force=y|A-Class=pass}}
}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2013-11-01|oldid1=579575589|date2=2015-11-01|oldid2=688461768|date3=2016-11-01|oldid3=747210486}}

==Anarchy==
The section on the Anarchy states the Henry II entered the fray with few soldiers and was latter defeated, it then states that Stephen assisted him. This makes littles sense as it sounds as though Henry would be fighting against Stephen (and in turn support his mother) and yet Stephen assits him. Some clarification is needed. 
[[User:Sovereignlance|Sovereignlance]] ([[User talk:Sovereignlance|talk]]) 02:26, 17 August 2010 (UTC)


==Untitled==
Why is this page &quot;Stephen I&quot;?  There was only one. -- [[User:Zoe|Zoe]]

&quot;The majority of the barons of England swore to support Matilda,&quot; but in the next sentence, &quot;Stephen's claim was supported by the majority of the barons.&quot;  What gives?  Did people change allegiance or were the barons giving 110%? [[User:JHCC|JHCC]] 18:43, 24 Aug 2004 (UTC)

It wasn't that the barons were giving 110%, the fact was that Henry I had forced them into swearing an oath to be faithful in seeing Matilda to the throne upon his death. However, upon Henry's death, Stephen moved for the throne with great speed, and managed to win the support of many of the barons due to the fact that he had more to offer them than Matilda. He was a strong male baron in Europe at the time, held extensive lands in England, and had the support of the Church. Matilda's husband was Geoffrey of Anjou, who was an Angevin and not liked by many of the lords who held lands in both Normandy and England, and who would be opposed to an Angevin king, so when Stephen was crowned, they instantly lent their support, hoping that they may benefit from his reign more so than Matilda's. However, the issue as a whole of the anarchy that ensued following his succession is much more complex than this, but I hope what I can give helps! a lot of this is subject to debate, and are covered in 'King Stephen' by RHC Davis and 'The Reign of Stephen' by K Stringer
==image==

[[Image:Aftnn King Stephen, who we reckon was responsible for Christianity in eastern Europe.jpg|right|100px]]
is the statue pictured a statue of the kind in this article or is it a statue of some other king with the same of name (and if so king of where when). (when information is found the image should be placed in an approprote place on the commons and removed from [[commons:Commons:Really unused]]

That looks like a statue of King [[Stephen I of Hungary]] [[User:Mississippienne|Missi]]

==Claims==

&lt;s&gt;In the article it states, &quot;'' Empress Maud, Henry's daughter, and her claim to the throne. However, Stephen of Blois, who was a grandson of William the Conqueror through his mother, Adela...''&quot;&lt;/s&gt;

&lt;s&gt;Matilda (Maud) was also The Conqueror's grandchild through her father, so had at least an equal claim to the throne. Should her relationship to William not also be cited? One of the reasons why neither Matilda's nor Stephen's claim to the throne was ironclad was that the application of [[Salic Law]] had not been resolved in England, and wasn't until [[Mary I of England|Mary]]. Both Matilda and Stephen were descended from William in the female line.&lt;/s&gt; [[User:Duckecho|Duckecho]] ([[User talk:Duckecho|Talk)]] 4 July 2005 16:47 (UTC)

:I edited to accommodate the above concerns. [[User:Duckecho|Duckecho]] ([[User talk:Duckecho|Talk)]] 6 July 2005 17:53 (UTC)

==Pronounciation==
Is it pronouced Steven or Stefan? I always wonder when I see &quot;King Stephen&quot;. [[User:Sotakeit|Sotakeit]] 19:21, 10 February 2006 (UTC)

It's pronounced Étienne since he was French, but Steven for the english pronunciation. [[User:Ciriii|Ciriii]] 00:22, 3 April 2006 (UTC)
and people also say that he is looking reem  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/90.216.55.128|90.216.55.128]] ([[User talk:90.216.55.128|talk]]) 19:49, 25 March 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== last Norman King of England? ==

How on earth was Stephen any more a Norman king of England than Henry II?  Both of them had a mother from the House of Normandy and a father from another northern French dynasty.  I'm going to change this. [[User:John Kenney|john k]] 22:42, 9 September 2006 (UTC)

Actually, Stephen is considered to be the last king of the Norman dynasty. Henry is considered the first king of the House of Plantagenet. [[User:RockStarSheister|RockStarSheister]] ([[User talk:RockStarSheister|talk]]) 06:39, 10 March 2008 (UTC)

:I also do not understand why Stephen is considered a Norman King of England. If Henry II is considered the first Plantagenet King of England because his paternal descent was from the House of Plantagenet, why would Stephen be any different as a paternal descendant of the House of Blois? [[User:Chell484|Chell484]] ([[User talk:Chell484|talk]]) 23:29, 30 September 2010 (UTC)

:: It's a historian's convention. Stephen was pretty much raised at his uncle's court, and no one denies that his mother was definitely the dominant influence between his parents. Don't forget that Stephen's father was ... henpecked... and sent back to the Crusades in disgrace by his wife where he died. Stephen didn't control Blois or Chartres, he held a Norman county before seizing the throne, so rather than have a &quot;house of blois&quot; of one member, most historians lump Stephen in with the Normans. If Eustace had lived, things might have turned out differently with this, but Stephen was not successful in founding a dynasty. [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 23:40, 30 September 2010 (UTC)
:::I'd like to see some sources for this supposed historian's convention. [[User:John K|john k]] ([[User talk:John K|talk]]) 04:56, 1 October 2010 (UTC)
::::I would also have to add that Stephen's lack of success was due to the support Matilda received from her half-brother [[Robert of Gloucester]], not to mention his own laxity in dealing with his unruly barons. Stephen fathered several children besides Eustace; in fact his granddaughter Matilda, one of the daughters of [[Marie of Blois]], married into the House of Brabant.--[[User:Jeanne boleyn|Jeanne Boleyn]] ([[User talk:Jeanne boleyn|talk]]) 05:31, 1 October 2010 (UTC)
:::: Well, the best source for being considered &quot;Norman&quot; would have to be the British Monarchy themselves, as Stephen (and Matilda) are listed under the &quot;Norman Dynasty&quot; on their website: [http://www.royal.gov.uk/HistoryoftheMonarchy/KingsandQueensofEngland/TheNormans/TheNormans.aspx The Normans]. [[Frank Barlow (historian)]] lists Stephen in his genealogical chart of the Norman Dynasty (Barlow ''Feudal Kingdom of England'' pp. 452-453). Robert Bartlett wrote ''England Under the Norman and Angevin Kings'' covering the period 1075 to 1225. Note he didn't write on the Norman, Blois, and Angevin kings. Richard Huscroft, in ''Ruling England 1042-1217'' lumps Stephen's reign into the &quot;Anglo-Norman&quot; period, which goes until 1154. Note that I didn't write the section on him being the &quot;last Norman king&quot;, I'm just pointing out that many consider him such, and trying to explain why. [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 10:28, 1 October 2010 (UTC)
:::::The British Monarchy website ''is not'' as reliable as people think it is. If we considered it the best source, we could say that the United Kingdom suddenly came to exist in 1603. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 12:49, 1 October 2010 (UTC)
::::::The British Monarchy website is awful.  It should be used sparingly, at best. [[User:John K|john k]] ([[User talk:John K|talk]]) 05:23, 2 October 2010 (UTC)
:::::::I've found : S. Morillo, ''Warfare under the Anglo-Norman kings, 1066–1135'' (1994). I've searched through David Crouch's ''King Stephen'', and found nothing to support either claims. Regards. [[User:PurpleHz|PurpleHz]] ([[User talk:PurpleHz|talk]]) 16:19, 2 October 2010 (UTC)
::::::::It seems pointless to have a historical convention that is historically inaccurate. It should be of note that the box at the bottom of the article lists Stephen as a member of the House of Blois, while the &quot;English Royalty&quot; sidebox in the article lists him and his issue as members of the House of Normandy. Why not simply change the sentence in the article's introduction to: &quot;He was King of England from 1135 to his death, and also the Count of Boulogne jure uxoris.&quot; [[User:Chell484|Chell484]] ([[User talk:Chell484|talk]]) 18:33, 2 October 2010 (UTC)
:If Henry II is not &quot;Norman dynasty&quot;, then Stephen isn't either. He's of the Blois dynasty. I'm tired of the argument that we must accept historical nonsense regarding dynasties just because the high visibility of a lot of websites give it the appearance of &quot;being established&quot;. This means getting rid of &quot;dynasties&quot; themselves ... these are things that developed in this form only later, but have been imposed on this period from that period. [[User:Deacon of Pndapetzim|Deacon of Pndapetzim]] (&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Deacon of Pndapetzim|Talk]]&lt;/small&gt;) 18:43, 2 October 2010 (UTC)

The division of monarchs into dynasties can be somewhat schematic, but this is the normal division.  It might be worth saying this in the article. [[User:PatGallacher|PatGallacher]] ([[User talk:PatGallacher|talk]]) 23:52, 2 October 2010 (UTC)

:His grandfather was William the Conqueror. You can't get any more Norman than that! His claim to the throne was obviously based on his mother's ancestry so it doesn't seem unreasonable to class him as a Norman king. [[User:TheMathemagician|TheMathemagician]] ([[User talk:TheMathemagician|talk]]) 13:09, 18 October 2016 (UTC)

== personal heraldry ==

[http://furry.wikia.com/wiki/Wemic] ha an image that is supposedly his personal coat of arms, a liontaur passant on a red field. Does anyone have a reliable cite to conform this? [[User:Rhialto|Rhialto]] 23:00, 2 January 2007 (UTC)

==Description by Walter Map==
I gave a precise reference for this and had a go at translating it accurately. But I'm not sure what Walter meant by ''idiota''. Perhaps someone who has a better idea will correct my version. &lt;font face=&quot;Gill Sans&quot;&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;[[User:Andrew Dalby|And]]&lt;/font&gt;'''[[User Talk:Andrew Dalby|rew D]]'''&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;[[User:Andrew Dalby/Bibliography|alby]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/font&gt; 15:59, 18 February 2007 (UTC)

==Recent??==

Is it true that Stephen has only recently been accepted as a King in English history? I'm sure I read that somewhere... If true, should this be mentioned in the article? --[[User:El Pollo Diablo|El Pollo Diablo]] ([[User talk:El Pollo Diablo|Talk]]) 10:07, 7 December 2007 (UTC)

:I've never heard of anything to suggest he wasn't always considered a King of England.  A quick search on google books will find books from 200 years ago or more that mention him as king. [[Special:Contributions/86.21.225.156|86.21.225.156]] ([[User talk:86.21.225.156|talk]]) 17:40, 28 March 2009 (UTC)

==Foggy history==
Was King Stephen's reign 1135-54 or 1135-41, 1141-54. Was Matilda ''Queen regnant of England'' in 1141? [[User:GoodDay|GoodDay]] ([[User talk:GoodDay|talk]]) 20:36, 16 December 2007 (UTC)

==English Royal descent==
This section, included by [[User:Andrei Iosifovich|Andrei Iosifovich]], has been proven incorrect in that there is a traceable line from Stephen to [[Elizabeth II of the United Kingdom|Elizabeth]]. Still, it's some nice info, so I'll include it here. [[User:Andrei Iosifovich|Andrei Iosifovich]] ([[User talk:Andrei Iosifovich|talk]]) 14:51, 30 April 2008 (UTC)

===English Royal descendents===
Through his granddaughter Maud of Boulogne, who married [[Henry I, Duke of Brabant]], Stephen is the ancestor of English royals, but no line leads directly to [[Elizabeth II of the United Kingdom|the current monarch]]. Through a marriage of [[Louis d'Évreux]], a descendent of the Brabant line, to the Queen of Navarre, Stephen is an ancestor of some monarchs of [[France]] and [[Navarre]], including [[Marguerite of France (born 1282)|Marguerite of France]], second wife of King [[Edward I of England]]; however, [[Edward II of England|Edward's heir]] was already born to a previous wife. Edward and Marguerite's descendents include [[Joan of Kent]], first [[Princess of Wales]] and mother of King [[Richard II of England]]; but Richard had no children and the throne passed to his cousin [[Henry IV of England|Henry IV]]. Henry married [[Joanna of Navarre]], another descendent of King Stephen's, but they had no children together.

The Navarrese monarchs also became [[King of France|Kings of France]] when Henri III of Navarre became King [[Henry IV of France]]. His daughter [[Henrietta Maria of France|Henrietta Marie]] married King [[Charles I of England]] and Scotland, and thus became ancestor to the rulers of England and Scotland from 1660 to 1714; but following the [[Act of Settlement 1701]] the throne passed to descendents of Charles I's sister [[Elizabeth Stuart|Elizabeth]], and no further British monarchs can claim descent from Stephen. However, Stephen is an ancestor to the [[Jacobite succession|Jacobite pretenders and their successors]] to the present day.

This is the descent of the [[House of Stuart]] and subsequent Jacobite claimants from Stephen:

# '''Stephen'''
# [[Marie of Boulogne]]
# Maud of Boulogne
# [[Henry II, Duke of Brabant]]
# [[Henry III, Duke of Brabant]]
# [[Maria of Brabant]]
# [[Louis d'Évreux]]
# [[Philip III of Navarre]]
# [[Charles II of Navarre]]
# [[Charles III of Navarre]]
# [[Blanche I of Navarre]]
# [[Eleanor of Navarre]]
# [[Gaston of Foix, Prince of Viana]]
# [[Catherine of Navarre]]
# [[Henry II of Navarre]]
# [[Jeanne III of Navarre]]
# [[Henry IV of France]]
# [[Henrietta Maria of France]]
# [[Henrietta Anne Stuart]]
# [[Anne Marie of Orléans]]
# [[Charles Emmanuel III of Sardinia]]
# [[Victor Amadeus III of Sardinia]]
# ''[[Victor Emmanuel I of Sardinia]]''
# ''[[Maria Beatrice of Savoy]]''
# [[Archduke Ferdinand Karl Viktor of Austria-Este]]
# ''[[Maria Theresia of Austria-Este]]''
# ''[[Rupprecht, Crown Prince of Bavaria]]''
# ''[[Albrecht, Duke of Bavaria]]''
# ''[[Franz, Duke of Bavaria]]''

== Stephen helping Henry???? ==

The following confuses me:

&quot;Desperately, and in secret, the boy then asked Stephen for help. According to the Gesta Stephani, &quot;On receiving the message, the king...hearkened to the young man...&quot; and bestowed upon him money and other support.&quot;

&quot;The boy&quot; being Maud's son Henry, the future Henry II, who was fighting AGAINST Stephen.  Why on earth would Stephen help him?

: Stephen did indeed assist the future [[Henry II]].  It was this sort of behaviour that drove his supporters to despair and allowed Matilda to be as strong as she was.  [[User:Paul75|Paul75]] ([[User talk:Paul75|talk]]) 05:32, 24 January 2009 (UTC)

:: In 1147, Stephen bought the young Henry out since he couldn't pay his mercenaries. The ODNB says : 'It was Stephen, ‘always full of pity and compassion’ (''Gesta Stephani'', 206–7), who sent Henry the money to pay off his troops and return home. ' For Baldwin de Reviers, he didn't pardon him, but exiled him. Baldwin soon joined the angevin court. Regards, [[User:PurpleHz|PurpleHz]] ([[User talk:PurpleHz|talk]]) 18:32, 18 June 2009 (UTC)

If I recall, he did the same with Baldwin de Redvers - after defeating and capturing him, Stephen promptly forgave him and released him, only for Baldwin to immediately take up arms against him once again.  My understanding is that Stephen was chivalrous to a fault, and lacked the ruthlessness required of a king in that age. [[Special:Contributions/86.21.225.156|86.21.225.156]] ([[User talk:86.21.225.156|talk]]) 21:28, 28 March 2009 (UTC)

==Duke of Normandy?==

I have read that Matilda was able to take Normandy fairly early, and was the &quot;Duke of Normandy&quot;. Why is she not listed as the duke?[[Special:Contributions/173.137.205.77|173.137.205.77]] ([[User talk:173.137.205.77|talk]]) 16:38, 18 June 2009 (UTC)
:Mathilda didn't took over the Normandy, but her husband did. So she was the duchess, but not the ruler of the duchy. Geoffrey did hommage for the duchy to the King of France in 1144, but he had his control since 1141/1142. Regards, [[User:PurpleHz|PurpleHz]] ([[User talk:PurpleHz|talk]]) 18:26, 18 June 2009 (UTC)

==Heirs General==
#[[William I, Count of Boulogne]], only son outlived Stephen as ''William III''
#[[Marie I, Countess of Boulogne]], elder-sister of William as ''Mary I''
#[[Ida, Countess of Boulogne]], eldest daughter of Marie
#[[Matilda II, Countess of Boulogne]], daughter of Ida
#[[Albert, Count of Clermont]], only son of Matilda
#[[Henry III, Duke of Brabant]], eldest paternal grandson of [[Mathilde of Flanders]] younger sister of [[Ida, Countess of Boulogne]] as ''Henry II''
#[[Henry IV, Duke of Brabant]], eldest son of ''Henry II'' as ''Henry III''
#[[John I, Duke of Brabant]], younger brother of ''Henry III'' as ''John I''
#[[John II, Duke of Brabant]], only son of ''John I'' as ''John II''
#[[John III, Duke of Brabant]], only son of ''John II'' as ''John III''
#[[Joanna, Duchess of Brabant]], eldest daughter of John III
#[[John the Fearless]], eldest maternal grandson of [[Margaret of Brabant, Countess of Flanders]] younger sister of Joanna as ''John IV''
#[[Philip the Good]], only son of ''John IV'' as ''Philip I''
#[[Charles the Bold]], only son of Philip as ''Charles I''
#[[Mary of Burgundy]], only daughter of Charles as ''Mary II''
#[[Philip I of Castile]], only son of ''Mary II'' as ''Philip II''
#[[Charles V, Holy Roman Emperor]], eldest son of ''Philip II'' as ''Charles II''
#[[Philip II of Spain]], eldest son of ''Charles II'' as ''Philip III''
#[[Philip III of Spain]], only son outlived ''Philip III'' as ''Philip IV''
#[[Philip IV of Spain]], eldest son of ''Philip IV'' as ''Philip V''
#[[Charles II of Spain]], only legitimate son of ''Philip V'' as ''Charles III''
#[[Louis, Grand Dauphin]], only son of [[Maria Theresa of Spain]] eldest sister of ''Charles III'' as ''Louis I''
#[[Louis, Duke of Burgundy (1682–1712)]], eldest son of ''Louis I'' as ''Louis II''
#[[Louis, Duke of Brittany (1707–1712)]], eldest son of ''Louis II'' as ''Louis III''
#[[Louis XV of France]], younger brother of ''Louis III'' as ''Louis IV''
#[[Louis XVI of France]], eldest paternal grandson of ''Louis IV'' as ''Louis V''
#[[Louis XVII of France]], only son outlived ''Louis V'' as ''Louis VI''
#[[Marie Thérèse of France]], eldest sister of ''Louis VI'' as ''Mary III''
#[[Henry, Count of Chambord]], grandson of [[Charles X of France]] youngest brother of ''Louis V'' as ''Henry IV''
#[[Robert I, Duke of Parma]], eldest son of [[Louise Marie Thérèse d'Artois]] only sister of ''Henry IV'' as ''Robert I''
#[[Henry, Duke of Parma]], eldest son of ''Robert I'' as ''Henry V''
#[[Joseph, Duke of Parma]], younger brother of ''Henry V''
#[[Elias, Duke of Parma]], younger brother of Joseph
#[[Robert II, Duke of Parma]], son of Elias as ''Robert II''
#[[Infanta Alicia, Dowager Duchess of Calabria]], younger sister of ''Robert II'' as ''Mary IV''
[[User:HenryXVII|Heinrich ⅩⅦ von Bayern]] ([[User talk:HenryXVII|talk]]) 15:42, 3 August 2010 (UTC)

== Current picture same as that of Henry II ==

This current picture is the same as that of the page about Henry II.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Plinythemodern|Plinythemodern]] ([[User talk:Plinythemodern|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Plinythemodern|contribs]]) 21:55, 7 August 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Similar, but not the same at all. [[User:PurpleHz|PurpleHz]] ([[User talk:PurpleHz|talk]]) 13:00, 12 August 2010 (UTC)

== Expansion... ==

I've gone through and given the article a proper scrub over and general expansion; in doing so, I'll guarantee various typos and errors etc. will have crept in, and it will no doubt benefit from both copy-editing and a once-over from experts in the period. [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 17:28, 31 May 2011 (UTC)

{{Talk:Stephen, King of England/GA1}}


I have once more altered the entry relating to Henry's death, so that the correct location is depicted. Would whoever altered the original correction, please leave the present link...he did not die at Lyon! [[User:Train guard|Train guard]] ([[User talk:Train guard|talk]]) 09:12, 1 April 2012 (UTC)

== Image in infobox ==

Does anyone know for certain the names of the documents in which [[Mathew Paris]]' illustrations of Stephen appear (like maybe [[Chronica Majora]] or something else)? Maybe the names could be added to some of the image captions throughout the article. The image in the infobox doesn't have a caption, and I was about to add one, and it made me wonder if anyone knew. I wonder now though if the infobox is getting too long to add a caption; is that the reason why it doesn't currently have one?--[[User:Brianann MacAmhlaidh|Brianann MacAmhlaidh]] ([[User talk:Brianann MacAmhlaidh|talk]]) 08:23, 25 September 2011 (UTC)
:I'm not personally in favour of adding the names of painters etc to the captions throughout the article (in this instance, I don't think they're particularly relevant to what the images are being used for, and someone could always click on the image if they wanted more). I like the idea of adding it to the infobox: the picture is from Historia Anglorum.[[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 18:21, 25 September 2011 (UTC)

== Heraldry ==

[[File:King-Stephen-I-England-Blois-Arms.svg|100px|right]]
This image is supposedly Stephen's coat of arms, and it appears in a couple of articles. Does anyone know if these arms were historically borne by Stephen, or are they just an example of [[attributed arms]]?--[[User:Brianann MacAmhlaidh|Brianann MacAmhlaidh]] ([[User talk:Brianann MacAmhlaidh|talk]]) 12:43, 6 March 2013 (UTC)
: The period of Stephen's reign is a bit early for formal heraldry - I've never seen a set of arms attributed to Stephen in any scholarly history of his reign. Matthew says of the growth of heraldry in Stephen's reign that &quot;The impetus for personal heraldry came form noble families themselves, not from the king.&quot; [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 14:11, 6 March 2013 (UTC)
:: As far as I'm aware, it's just a much later invention. Like Ealdgyth says, it would be the wrong period for something like this, and I haven't seen anything in the histories of Stephen. [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 20:57, 6 March 2013 (UTC)

== Henry II first of the Angevin kings? ==

The intro refers to Henry II as &quot;the first of the Angevin kings.&quot; This is confusing to those of us who learned of him as &quot;the first of the Plantagenet kings.&quot; (Even the link on &quot;[[Angevin]]&quot; redirects to &quot;[[House of Plantagenet]]&quot;.) Does not &quot;Angevin&quot; refer to the empire and &quot;Plantagenet&quot; to Henry's lineage? The article &quot;House of Plantagenet&quot; states that &quot;Henry accumulated a vast and complex feudal holding that was '''''later''''' called the Angevin Empire.&quot; (Emphasis added.)

It seems to me that the intro should clarify this: Henry II was the first of the Plantagenet kings; &quot;Angevin&quot; refers to the empire he built.

Cheers, [[User:Rico402|Rico402]] ([[User talk:Rico402|talk]]) 15:17, 17 July 2013 (UTC)

:It's a fair point to raise, but it's a bit more complex than that. There are two different ways to describe the Plantagenet dynasty; one starts with Henry II, the other with Henry III. There's a fuller discussion of this in our wiki Plantagenet article's good article review, but both are legitimate perspectives. The British monarchy - for example - considers Henry II, Richard and John to be the Angevin kings, followed by Henry III as the first Plantagenet, as do many good historians; plenty of other equally good historians start that Plantagenet list with Henry II. I've seen some that argue in favour of Henry III being an Angevin too, but that's rarer. Contemporaries didn't use either phrase quite as we do; Plantagenet is not really a term they used at all, and they wrote about &quot;the Angevins&quot; rather than a dynasty. The &quot;Angevin empire&quot;, as you say, is a much later, 19th century term, that has had its fashionable and less fashionable moments over the last century. Historians focusing on Stephen, and the 12th-13th centuries in England more generally, typically use the &quot;Angevin kings&quot; phrase rather than &quot;Plantagenet&quot; (see Robert Bartlett's &quot;England Under the Norman and Angevin Kings: 1075 - 1225&quot; as an accessible example of this trend, but Church, Everard or Warren would be equally good examples of historians who use the term), and so I went for this in the article. I'm happy to add a footnote explaining it further with a few references if you'd like. In the longer term, I'd like to get round to writing a proper Angevin article, as the current redirect isn't perfect! (NB: and let's not open the can of worms as to whether Stephen was a member of the Norman Kings! :) ) [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 16:44, 17 July 2013 (UTC)

== Illegitimate formatting ==
There is a serious issue in Wikipedia's designation in the sidebar of illegitimate children!  We must clear up the appearance because the illegitimate title flows to legitimates. This problem appears here and on King Henry II and I’m sure other pages. [[User:Markbeaulieu|Markbeaulieu]] ([[User talk:Markbeaulieu|talk]]) 17:33, 10 October 2014 (UTC)
:Sorry, I'm not sure I quite follow you Mark - could you explain what the &quot;flows to&quot; bit meant? [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 17:36, 10 October 2014 (UTC)
::I think I see what Mark means. There is an italic heading &quot;illegitimate children&quot; in the infobox next to the list of legitimate children. As all the children are legitimate so far as I can see, presumably the solution is just to delete the 'illegitimate' heading. [[User:Dudley Miles|Dudley Miles]] ([[User talk:Dudley Miles|talk]]) 17:48, 10 October 2014 (UTC)
:::Ah, see what you mean. Yep, sounds sensible. [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 17:51, 10 October 2014 (UTC)

== Coronation ==

All the sources agree that it was the 22nd, not the 26th. Not sure when/where 26th crept in. Besides King p. 47 and Crouch p. 37, Davis ''King Stephen'' (3rd ed) p. 16 says &quot;Consequently the archbishop anointed Stephen king on 22 December 1135...&quot;. Chibnall ''The Empress Matilda'' p. 65 says of Stephen &quot;ON 22 December he was anointed king.&quot;. Green ''Henry I'' p. 222 says of Stephen &quot;On 22 December he was crowned by the archbishop of Canterbury.&quot; [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 23:25, 26 December 2014 (UTC)
:Absolutely.  [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 23:28, 26 December 2014 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>37x8b500kzkkfuvbu80ksvr8iiqbgl3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
