<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Diocletian</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1487242</id>
    <revision>
      <id>740737810</id>
      <parentid>738480624</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-23T00:01:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Oatley2112</username>
        <id>9329905</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Noted changes in article</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17868">{{talkheader}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=FAC
|action1date=15:31, 31 March 2008
|action1link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Diocletian
|action1result=promoted
|action1oldid=202179013

|maindate=25 September 2010
|currentstatus=FA
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Greece|class=FA|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Biography|living=n|class=FA|listas=Diocletian|military-work-group=y|military-priority=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Classical Greece and Rome|class=FA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Politics|class=FA|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Croatia|class=FA|importance=Low}}
{{WikiProject Dacia|class=FA|importance=Mid}}
{{MILHIST|class=FA|Classical=y|Biography=y}}
{{WikiProject Rome|class=FA|importance=mid}}
}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2005-11-20|oldid1=28772413|date2=2006-11-20|oldid2=88705217|date3=2007-11-20|oldid3=172755258|date4=2008-11-20|oldid4=252867419|date5=2009-11-20|oldid5=326830550|date6=2010-11-20|oldid6=397686436|date7=2011-11-20|oldid7=461655513|date8=2014-11-20|oldid8=634600785|date9=2015-11-20|oldid9=691560860}}
{{archivebox|
* [[/Archive 1|2005–March 2008]]
}}

==Persecution of 303==
On one hand, some Christians clearly escaped, otherwise the religion would have ceased to exist! But to allow as the only comment that only apostates survived is clearly wrong and biased. See for example, http://www.althusius.net/node/54. Some were blinded, had their noses slit, their ears cut off.

Another reference which I cannot verify says 3000-3,500, not much in the greater scheme of things '''but''' the people executed were the leadership, bishops, etc. While this might not be satisfactory for sheer bloody numbers, it can sure demoralize a movement. And 3,000 (if true) is no great fun either if your group is the target. [[User:Student7|Student7]] ([[User talk:Student7|talk]]) 01:11, 31 May 2008 (UTC)
:The genius of [[WP:SS]] is that it allows detailed descriptions of almost anything the benefit of a proper home. The details of the Great Persecution belong at [[Diocletianic Persecution]] and [[Persecution of early Christians in the Roman Empire]]. Obviously, the affair was bloody; that much is conveyed by the choice descriptions of the persecutions effected in Nicomedia alone. &quot;Before the end of February, a fire destroyed part of the imperial palace.[158] Galerius convinced Diocletian that the culprits were Christians, conspirators who had plotted with the eunuchs of the palace. An investigation was commissioned, but no responsible party was found. Executions followed anyway, and the palace eunuchs Dorotheus and Gorgonius were executed. One individual, Peter, was stripped, raised high, and scourged. Salt and vinegar were poured in his wounds, and he was slowly boiled over an open flame. The executions continued until at least April 24, 303, when six individuals, including the bishop Anthimus, were decapitated.[159]&quot; Surely that conveys a sense of the events, without going off into tangential detail on persecutions that happened far from Diocletian.
:A good line or two about martyrdom and the Christian movement would be good, and a descriptive &quot;it was bloody and evil&quot; thrown in to characterize the persecutions in the East, but I've lost most of my sources (the interlibrary loans came due a few months back) and can't supply anything to fit those purposes. I'm wary of any sort of numerical estimate here, given the weakness of the source material. If you can attach a good scholarly name or press to the estimate, I'd consider it. Actually, if you have any specific (and brief: we're running up against page size recommendations here) suggestions on how to amend the text to better describe the persecution, you should air them here. I'm willing to listen. [[User:Geuiwogbil|Geuiwogbil]] ([[User talk:Geuiwogbil|Talk]]) 03:11, 1 June 2008 (UTC)
:RE: [[User:192.175.84.19|192.175.84.19]]. &quot;This section is grossly misleading, it implies that the &quot;great persecution&quot; was largely in the minds of the christians. Only a handful really lost their lives it seems to say.&quot; I'm sorry that you got that impression. I hope there are remedies beyond eliminating the line sourced to Treadgold. Personally, I think the Treadgold line is quite important: it's important to note for the reader that most Christians live on, either through weak enforcement of the edicts' provisions or through the superficial compliance of Christian laity. (The superficial compliance, of course, became a difficult issue for the Church in Constantinian times; it's what spawns the [[Donatist]] controversy and the [[Meletius of Lycopolis|Melitian schism]].) Martyrs shouldn't be written out of the narrative, but they're less important than the great mass of Christians who survived. If you can suggest an emendations to correct the seeming implications that &quot;the &quot;great persecution&quot; was largely in the minds of the christians&quot; or that &quot;Only a handful really lost their lives&quot; (perhaps a well-sourced fatality line, as per the above, would be helpful here), I would be much obliged. Thanks for contributing! [[User:Geuiwogbil|Geuiwogbil]] ([[User talk:Geuiwogbil|Talk]]) 03:11, 1 June 2008 (UTC)

::I appreciate the remark on summaries. Higher level articles tend to get reinflated all over again, exactly what the forking was supposed to relieve.

::I agree that Diocletian may have had good reason in his mind to stop what may have looked to him to be a palace coup or an internal coup of some sort.

::Nevertheless, saying that Christians escaped only through perfidy and apostasy is truly gratuitous. The persecution was aimed at bishops, apparently. They sure didn't escape! The people with their noses slit, and other mutilations didn't escape! 

::To me, it's like coming in after the Holocaust or Rawandan massacre and saying that the survivors must have lied about their faith, race, or whatever. It's a nasty observation and unfair IMO without a bit more detail.

::For the average Christian at the time, it was a scary several years. Like the Jews in Germany during the 30s, you either surived by your wits or were beaten. Not a fun way to live IMO.[[User:Student7|Student7]] ([[User talk:Student7|talk]]) 12:18, 1 June 2008 (UTC)

:::Alright, so how do we emphasize that the persecution essentially failed in its aims without maligning the Christians or downplaying the severity of the persecutions? Does the most recent revision satisfy? [[User:Geuiwogbil|Geuiwogbil]] ([[User talk:Geuiwogbil|Talk]]) 23:51, 1 June 2008 (UTC)

::::Yes. Good. Thanks.

::::To satisfy other editors, was the &quot;apostasy&quot; statement taken from an otherwise scholarly source? My point was that Burckhardt figured out (as probably did other scholars) that there well may have been an attempted coup. But it is one thing to deduce a possible coup from the record, quite another to deduce apostasy since those phrases probably didn't slide through repeated Christian scroll copying. 

::::Having said that, is it important to put (maybe in the subordinate article) that &quot;one source thought that.....?&quot; While it is clear where my sympathies lie, I'm not trying to force a pov article against true scholarship, as much as it's hard for me to swallow. 

::::Thanks again for your consideration. [[User:Student7|Student7]] ([[User talk:Student7|talk]]) 02:07, 2 June 2008 (UTC)
:::::Ah, no, actually none of the sources I've read give much emphasis to apostasy IIRC. The &quot;laying low&quot; part gets the greater emphasis. Treadgold's actual words de-emphasize apostasy: &quot;The persecution failed to force many Christians to apostasize...&quot; Thus, I don't think it's too much of a loss to drop it. Details of alleged apostasy by the Meliteans and Donatists are better placed in the [[Diocletianic Persecution]] subarticle, where they can receive due emphasis. [[User:Geuiwogbil|Geuiwogbil]] ([[User talk:Geuiwogbil|Talk]]) 03:29, 2 June 2008 (UTC)

He ordered that the deacon Romanus of Caesarea have his tongue removed for defying the order of the courts and interrupting official sacrifices. Romanus was then sent to prison, where he was executed on November 17, 303. - See Eusebius' Ecclesiastical History, &quot;The Book of Martyrs,&quot; Chapter 2, for the full story on Romanus.  I just want to take a hammer and break the bust of Diocletian everytime I go to the Getty Museum and see his evil face.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Easeltine|Easeltine]] ([[User talk:Easeltine|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Easeltine|contribs]]) 14:57, 1 June 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Diocletian's ethnicity ==
Do we know anything about Diocletian's ethnicity? Nothing is said about this in the article. If there is information regarding his ethnicity then it should be presented in the article. For my own part, I have absolutely no knowledge of Diocletian's ethnicity, but going by his name, it would seem possible that he was at least partially of Greek origin - of course, I am just speculating, and possible content in the article regarding his ethnicity would need to be sourced. --[[User:Kurt Leyman|Kurt Leyman]] ([[User talk:Kurt Leyman|talk]]) 18:40, 10 June 2009 (UTC)

Can we speak about a &quot;ethnicity&quot; in this Time? His Father was a Illyrian  &quot;freebuying Fighter&quot; gr.--[[Special:Contributions/84.75.20.66|84.75.20.66]] ([[User talk:84.75.20.66|talk]]) 13:22, 18 May 2010 (UTC)

== Who is Aper? ==
Aper seems key to the death of Numerian and ascension of Dioicletian, but I see no explanation of who he is. [[User:Spark240|Spark240]] ([[User talk:Spark240|talk]]) 12:22, 17 March 2010 (UTC)
:[[Lucius Flavius Aper]].  I've added a link to the article at the first mention of his name.  [[User:Richard-of-Earth|Richard-of-Earth]] ([[User talk:Richard-of-Earth|talk]]) 21:32, 25 September 2010 (UTC)

== today's article ==
what Diocletian is today's article right on!!! I have been learning about him in my late antiquity class, cool  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Kpasby|Kpasby]] ([[User talk:Kpasby|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Kpasby|contribs]]) 10:20, 25 September 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== doesn't make sense ==
In introduction: &quot;Of course this was purely a political favor done by a Senator after a blistering affair.&quot;

== Regarding military capitals ==
Something else that doesn't make sense: The statement that &quot;Trier sat on the Rhine.&quot; Trier does not, and never has, sat on the Rhine. It is, instead, on the Mosel. Is the author using &quot;the Rhein&quot; in a larger sense here? [[User:Moonbiter|Moonbiter]] ([[User talk:Moonbiter|talk]]) 18:45, 15 December 2010 (UTC)

== Date of Diocletian's death ==
The date of his death does not appear to be as cut-&amp;-dried as this article makes it. Byron J. Nakamura discusses the evidence -- &amp; it appears the authorities have argued over the correct answer for quite a while -- &amp; himseld argues that 3 December 312 may be the correct date. See [http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1086/420722 &quot;When Did Diocletian Die? New Evidence for an Old Problem,&quot; ''Classical Philology''], '''98''', (2003), pp. 283-289. -- [[User:Llywrch|llywrch]] ([[User talk:Llywrch|talk]]) 23:42, 3 September 2011 (UTC)
: Interesting, and remaining to be addressed. [[User:William Avery|William Avery]] ([[User talk:William Avery|talk]]) 20:16, 10 February 2016 (UTC)
:: Updated article with relevant details. [[User:Oatley2112|Oatley2112]] ([[User talk:Oatley2112|talk]]) 00:01, 23 September 2016 (UTC)

== Abdication, Vitellius before Diocletian ==
I believe Emperor Vitellius abdicated on December 18, 69. He was not allowed to and was not successful in abdicating, but he did voluntarily and publicly  abdicate. His rule was very brief and he was in fact murdered while still being forced to be the emperor. Source Morgan, Gwyn, 69 A.D., Oxford University Press 2006  pages 240-242. He sites Tacitus and Suetonius as his sources I am new to this so I wanted to let someone else perhaps do any editing deemed necessary, perhaps you could add successfully voluntarily abdicated, you could include Vitellius, or you could just delete that the part about &quot;only...&quot; I'll let you decide if and what changes to make. [[User:Eaglebeach|Eaglebeach]] ([[User talk:Eaglebeach|talk]]) 18:32, 9 March 2012 (UTC)

== Foundation of the Tetrarchy ==
In the &quot;Foundation of the Tetrarchy&quot; it states that &quot;Galerius was assigned Syria, Palestine, Egypt, and responsibility for the eastern borderlands.&quot;  Barnes is given as a reference.  I haven't read Barnes, but the map in the section indicates that Galerius was in charge of the Danube.  Edward Gibbon says &quot;While the Cæsars exercised their valour on the banks of the Rhine and Danube, the presence of the emperors was required on the southern confines of the Roman world.&quot; &lt;ref&gt;Edward Gibbon, The History of the Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire, ed. J.B. Bury with an Introduction by W.E.H. Lecky (New York: Fred de Fau and Co., 1906), in 12 vols. Vol. 2. 7/21/2014. [chapter 13, page 160] http://oll.libertyfund.org/titles/1366#lf0214-02_footnote_nt_467_ref &lt;/ref&gt; [[User:James Pelletier|Jim P.]] ([[User talk:James Pelletier|talk]]) 04:02, 22 July 2014 (UTC)
: I have the same problem with the map (and two years after your post it hasn't been addressed). Either the article has Diocletian and Galerius campaigning in the wrong places, or the map is wrong regarding their two rulerships. The text has Diocletian staying and fighting in the Balkans and Galerius fighting in Syria and Egypt. The reversals are so substantial and repeated that it's impossible to know which of them was where. I tend to think of maps as being prepared with great care and fact-checking - but could there be a massive typo in the Diocletian and Galerius rulerships? That would be the only mistake - though a big one - on the map. Meanwhile, the descriptions of where each of them was fighting are repeated and emphasized, so it's hard to believe someone could have made such a mistake consistently over so many words and paragraphs. Just to confuse matters more, the article on Galerius has him campaigning in the Balkans ''and'' the Middle East https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Galerius. Finally, the article on the Tetrarchy has Diocletian responsible for the eastern borderlands and Galerius in the Balkans. https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tetrarchy Bottom line - I think the map is right and the text is wrong.[[User:Wlegro|Wlegro]] ([[User talk:Wlegro|talk]]) 17:55, 6 September 2016 (UTC)
:: I disagree. The text as it stands is fundamentally correct when it comes to detailing Diocletian's and Galerius's activities from 293 through to 305; the problem is that the map is based upon an old understanding of the apparent fixed nature of the Tetrarchy's rule over specific provinces, which is based upon later primary sources looking at the then current stable subdivisions of the empire and retrospectively applying that to the period of the Tetrarchy. Pat Southern, in &quot;''The Roman Empire from Severus to Constantine''&quot; states the following (pgs 147-148):

::&quot;''The appearance of four Emperors did not necessarily involve a fourfold division of the Roman world, though it seems from their attachment to certain groups of provinces as if each Caesar and each Augustus controlled an allocated portion of the Empire; indeed Aurelius Victor specifically states that this was the case, but in fact there were no strict boundaries between the four quarters of the Roman world where each man operated, even though there were four cities which became their headquarters, or capitals. Lactantius complained that everything had been multiplied by four as each of the Tetrarchs tried to outdo each other, increasing their armies, bodyguards, Imperial staffs and so on, but he exaggerated in order to condemn the regime that persecuted Christians, as opposed to his hero Constantine who founded the Christian Empire. A division of the Empire into four distinct units would seem perfectly reasonable to those authors who compiled their histories during the fifth century and later, when officially established territorial boundaries were the norm. It would seem logical to them that this had also been the case during the Tetrarchy, but at the turn of the third and fourth centuries the four Emperors were assigned to regions as and when they were needed, and not to specific areas as part of a fixed geographical plan. It is not known how far each of the Tetrarchs could act, take decisions or legislate in the areas where the others were operating, but it is fairly certain that Diocletian could override protocols and take decisions in any part of the Empire, commensurate with his seniority.''&quot;

::This means that Diocletian and Galerius's oversight of certain zones shifted across the years, depending upon where Diocletian believed he and Galerius needed to be, and that Diocletian had direct oversight of the Danubian provinces while he was there, and over the Eastern provinces when he was there. So the provinces requiring imperial oversight may have been grouped together and had discrete boundaries, but not the Tetrarch assigned to it. Analysis is also clouded by the apparent stability of the situation in the West, where after the raising of Constantius, Maximian largely confined himself to Italy, and left the fighting on the Rhine to his ''Caesar''. Nevertheless I think that the section that that states the assignment of fixed areas of imperium for each Tetrarch is the one that needs to be reworked, with the map possibly removed. [[User:Oatley2112|Oatley2112]] ([[User talk:Oatley2112|talk]]) 05:46, 9 September 2016 (UTC)
::: Updated article with relevant details. [[User:Oatley2112|Oatley2112]] ([[User talk:Oatley2112|talk]]) 00:01, 23 September 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>qnvs1zuczgowp149q0m0a1tmhb86uau</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
