<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:June 1941 uprising in eastern Herzegovina</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>42672752</id>
    <revision>
      <id>673445313</id>
      <parentid>655289327</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-07-28T09:47:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Peacemaker67</username>
        <id>15690513</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>talk page format and archiving</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25740">{{Talk header}}
{{Australian English}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=09:55, 10 June 2014 (UTC)
|action1link=Talk:June 1941 uprising in eastern Herzegovina/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=612305642
|topic=Warfare
|currentstatus=FA

|action2=WAR
|action2date=08:18, 23 September 2014 (UTC)
|action2link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/June 1941 uprising in eastern Herzegovina
|action2result=approved
|action2oldid=625893445

|action3=FAC
|action3date=2015-01-05
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/June 1941 uprising in eastern Herzegovina/archive1
|action3result=promoted
|action3oldid=639534026
}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
| algo=old(30d)
| archive=Talk:June 1941 uprising in eastern Herzegovina/Archive %(counter)d
| counter=1
| maxarchivesize=100K
| archiveheader={{Automatic archive navigator}}
| minthreadsleft=4
| minthreadstoarchive=1
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Bosnia and Herzegovina|class = FA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Croatia|class = FA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Serbia|class = FA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Yugoslavia|class = FA|importance=low}}
{{MILHIST|class = FA|A-Class=pass|b1=y|b2=y|b3=y|b4=y|b5=y|Balkan=y|WWII=y}}
}}
{{Old peer review|archive = 1}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
| algo                = old(30d)
| archive             = Talk:June 1941 uprising in eastern Herzegovina/Archive %(counter)d
| counter             = 1
| maxarchivesize      = 150K
| archiveheader       = {{Aan}}
| minthreadstoarchive = 1
| minthreadsleft      = 3
}}{{Auto archiving notice|age=30|small=no|bot=Lowercase sigmabot III}}

== Requested move ==
&lt;div class=&quot;boilerplate&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #efe; margin: 2em 0 0 0; padding: 0 10px 0 10px; border: 1px dotted #aaa;&quot;&gt;&lt;!-- Template:RM top --&gt;
:''The following discussion is an archived discussion of a [[WP:requested moves|requested move]]. &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/span&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on the talk page. Editors desiring to contest the closing decision should consider a [[Wikipedia:move review|move review]]. No further edits should be made to this section. ''

The result of the move request was: '''Moved''' to [[June 1941 uprising in eastern Herzegovina]], per apparent consensus. [[User:No such user|No such user]] ([[User talk:No such user|talk]]) 08:24, 16 May 2014 (UTC)

----


[[:June Uprising in Eastern Herzegovina]] → {{no redirect|June uprising in eastern Herzegovina}} – [[WP:LOWERCASE]] and the only English source located that uses the phrase renders it with uprising and eastern, per [https://www.google.com.au/search?tbm=bks&amp;hl=en&amp;q=http%3A%2F%2Fbooks.google.com.au%2Fbooks%3Fid%3DpVCx3jerQmYC%26pg%3DPA123%26redir_esc%3Dy%23v%3Donepage%26q%3DJune%2520Uprising%2520in%2520Eastern%2520Herzegovina%26f%3Dfalse#hl=en&amp;q=%22June+Uprising+in+Eastern+Herzegovina%22&amp;tbm=bks this] [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 22:00, 5 May 2014 (UTC)
* '''Comment''': I think I found a couple of sources which use capitalized letters in the name of this event:
** {{cite book|last=Tomasevich|first=Jozo|authorlink=Jozo Tomasevich|title=War and Revolution in Yugoslavia: 1941 - 1945|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=fqUSGevFe5MC&amp;pg=PA406|publisher=Stanford University Press|isbn=978-0-8047-7924-1|page=406|quote= For Juretid's statement, see Mlinaric, Tito: der rote Rebell,p. 24. &quot;Cited in Kovacevic and Skoko, &quot;The June 1941 '''U'''prising in Herzegovina,&quot; p. 102. }}
** {{cite book|last=Tomasevich|first=Jozo|authorlink=Jozo Tomasevich|title=The Chetniks|url=http://books.google.com/books?id=yoCaAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA477|date=1 January 1975|publisher=Stanford University Press|isbn=978-0-8047-0857-9|page=477|quote=Bajic, Nevenka. &quot;The June 1941 '''U'''prising in Herzegovina.&quot; In Godiinjak Istoriskog druitva Bosne i Hercegovine, VIII, 225-44. Sarajevo, 1956. }}--[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 22:44, 5 May 2014 (UTC)
:*You do realise you are trying to use the translated titles of two articles written in Serbo-Croat, don't you? They aren't English sources, Antidiskriminator. I don't know how many times I am expected to try to explain this to you before you will comprehend it. They are both in the bibliographies of the Tomasevich books. There is only one English source, apply [[WP:LOWERCASE]] consistent with Redzic. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 23:12, 5 May 2014 (UTC)
::In Tomasevich books two articles written in Serbo-Croat appear in translated form with capitalized proper name. --[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 06:38, 6 May 2014 (UTC)
:::Sorry, but that does not constitute real English usage. Tomasevich has translated them in his Bibliographies for the benefit of readers. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 06:52, 6 May 2014 (UTC)
:::: Your position here directly contradicts to your position at [[Talk:Pavle Đurišić]] where you insist on exact terminology used by Tomašević ([[Talk:Pavle_Đurišić#RfC:_Should_this_article_contain_wikilink_to_article_about_Moslem_militia.3F|link]]). --[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 08:02, 6 May 2014 (UTC)
:::::Your accusation is completely unfounded. I'll let the community decide whether your wafer-thin argument flies or not, thanks. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 08:13, 6 May 2014 (UTC)
::::::This is a discussion. I pointed to two sources you extensively use on wikipedia that use capitalized letters in the name of this event to help to reach consensus. ''&quot;Your wafer-thin argument flies&quot;'' is another unnecessary harsh comment you write to me. --[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 08:34, 6 May 2014 (UTC)
:::::::Look, Antidiskriminator. It is not a discussion, you are just defending your title, as usual. Your position here is completely untenable. You have asked for independent advice about the capitalisation and appear to have rejected it, in favour of defending the indefensible. That really is your problem, and it is not &quot;harsh&quot; to point out the truth. You are not trying to reach consensus, you are blatantly attempting to manipulate non-English sources to make them appear to be English sources so you can retain the title you gave the article. It is transparent. Please be straight with the community and stop trying to use &quot;work-arounds&quot; when you are pulled up on legitimate issues. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 08:47, 6 May 2014 (UTC)
::::::::No. You again contradict yourself. [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk%3AMoslem_militia&amp;diff=607198340&amp;oldid=607197568 It is not about positions, and attacking and defending them.] I can't see any other reason for your behavior except creation of a false narrative to discredit me and to discourage me and others from participation in discussion and editing. Please be so kind to stop with this kind of behavior. --[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 10:06, 6 May 2014 (UTC)
:::::::::Unfortunately, you just don't get it. It is you that are defending your title with no basis. I merely pointed out how it was contrary to policy, moved it, and you promptly moved it back without a shred of basis in sources. You have misrepresented the source of title (that only appears in Redzic in English), as appearing in Tomasevich, when in fact the examples you gave were translations of article titles published in Serbo-Croat, that Tomasevich merely translated in the Bibliography of his books. Nice of him, but it doesn't show English usage. That fact that this is &quot;die in a ditch&quot; stuff for you is hard to fathom. I think if it was anyone else you would read the policy and accept you got it wrong, and just move it. But you get so entrenched you won't budge. It really is a waste of time, time better spent creating and expanding articles, which you have recently started to do in my area of interest. I'd like to encourage you to do more of it, but your article titles leave much to be desired. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 10:20, 6 May 2014 (UTC)
::::::::::Incorrect. I am not &quot;defending my title with no basis&quot; as you try to assert here. I explained that the topic of this article is historical event which usually have capitalized names. I also pointed to two works of Tomasevich who used capitalized names for this event. It is more than a &quot;shred of basis&quot;. [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk%3AMoslem_militia&amp;diff=607198340&amp;oldid=607197568 It is not about positions, and attacking and defending them.] It is about discussion. I'd like to encourage you to discuss i.e. your pragmatic contradictory approach to Tomasevich, instead to misuse talkpage of this article also to disseminate a false narrative aimed to discredit me and to discourage me and others from participation in discussion and editing. --[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 10:37, 6 May 2014 (UTC)
:::::::::::It is a complete waste of my time discussing this with you. I have explained what you have done with the article titles. I will await other uninvolved members of the community to discuss the matter further. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 10:54, 6 May 2014 (UTC)
:::::::::::* Why uninvolved? Here is how scholars who are involved in the matter capitalize the title of this event: 
:::::::::::** [http://www.ceeol.com/aspx/issuedetails.aspx?issueid=1dd451d7-2c89-420f-aa6d-42e6c169d161&amp;articleId=5510704b-e617-4273-a8d0-6744e1243187 &quot;The '''J'''une '''U'''prising in '''E'''astern '''H'''erzegovina in 1941&quot;, Journal of Contemporary History (2/2003)]
:::::::::::* It is also consistent with other articles on [[June uprising|June Uprisings]]--[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 19:58, 6 May 2014 (UTC)
{{od}}you mean ''Časopis za suvremenu povijest'' 2/2003. Why didn't you mention that this is (another) translated title of a Croatian language journal article? Another attempt to &quot;work-around&quot; the fact we are talking about titles in English. This is getting very, very tiresome. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 21:59, 6 May 2014 (UTC)
* '''Support''' – I would have thought that caps would be OK on Eastern, but checking book n-grams I see that lowercase is much more common for &quot;in eastern Herzegovina&quot;.  And uprising is clearly not part of a proper name.  [[User:Dicklyon|Dicklyon]] ([[User talk:Dicklyon|talk]]) 02:13, 7 May 2014 (UTC)
*'''Comment''' - Perhaps it would be easier to go by the correct English grammar. I am slightly inclined towards the position that they should stay capitalised as both, &quot;June Uprising&quot; and &quot;Eastern Herzegovina&quot; are nouns, thus written capitalised. [[User:FkpCascais|FkpCascais]] ([[User talk:FkpCascais|talk]]) 02:22, 7 May 2014 (UTC)
:*Fkp, that is NOT the &quot;correct English grammar&quot;. You are confusing nouns, adjectives and proper nouns. &quot;June&quot; is a proper noun, spelled with an initial capital. &quot;Uprising&quot; is not a proper noun, it is just a noun. &quot;Eastern Herzegovina&quot; is not a noun, &quot;Eastern&quot; is an adjective denoting geographic situation, &quot;Herzegovina&quot; is a proper noun, spelled with an initial capital. Per Dicklyon, uprising is NOT part of a proper name. And in any case it would not be &quot;easier&quot; (whatever that is meant to mean), to ignore WP titling policy. It is used by only one source published in English, so we apply English usage per Redzic and [[WP:LOWERCASE]]. What would be &quot;easier&quot;, would be following WP titling policy. Regards, [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 02:39, 7 May 2014 (UTC)
::*&quot;Eastern Herzegovina&quot; if considered an actual name of the territory then it should be capitalised, just as &quot;Economy of South Korea&quot; would be. It depends if we consider &quot;Eastern Herzegovina&quot; as a territorial unit or not. If we do, then it should be capitalised, but if we only consider &quot;Herzegovina&quot; as territory, then &quot;eastern&quot; would be an adjective, thus not capitalised. Regarding &quot;June Uprising&quot;, I beleave that is actually a noun (both words) and as such they should both be capitalised, just as the &quot;Revolution&quot; in &quot;[[Russian Revolution]]&quot; is. You are missing the fact that we are not talking here about a month, June, but about an event called &quot;June Uprising&quot;. ;) [[User:FkpCascais|FkpCascais]] ([[User talk:FkpCascais|talk]]) 03:08, 7 May 2014 (UTC)
:::*That's just not right, and your example is inappropriate. South Korea is the common name for a country, eastern Herzegovina is a vaguely defined region in a vaguely defined region. How could it be a territorial unit? People don't even agree on the boundaries of Herzegovina, particularly between Bosnia (as a region) and Herzegovina. We have one English source here, Fkp. One. It is Redzic, who renders it as &quot;June uprising in eastern Herzegovina&quot;. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 03:23, 7 May 2014 (UTC)
::::*I agree with you about &quot;Eastern Herzegovina&quot;, it was only used as capitalised during the early 1990s period ([[Eastern Herzegovina]]) when a separate territorial unit was formed in it. However, regarding June uprising (I would say June Uprising), I am much more inclined to consider both words as a proper noun of the event. By now, I support [[June Uprising in eastern Herzegovina]]. [[User:FkpCascais|FkpCascais]] ([[User talk:FkpCascais|talk]]) 14:15, 7 May 2014 (UTC)
:::::*[[User:Sturmvogel_66]] (who assessed the article for MILHIST) suggested it needs 1941 in the title. Perhaps one way of dealing with that would be [[:Uprising in eastern Herzegovina (June 1941)]]. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 00:11, 8 May 2014 (UTC)
::::::*Augh... the brackets look so ugly... can´t we avoid them? [[User:FkpCascais|FkpCascais]] ([[User talk:FkpCascais|talk]]) 01:21, 8 May 2014 (UTC)
:::::::*Well, I'm open to suggestions, but studious avoidance of the only English sourced title, and stubborn insistence on grammatically dubious capitalisation also results in an &quot;ugly&quot; title in my view. BTW, the other Herzegovina Uprising article is parenthetically disambiguated by year. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 01:48, 8 May 2014 (UTC)
* '''Support proposed capitalization''': neither &quot;uprising&quot; nor &quot;eastern&quot; are used as proper nouns here. As to the disambiguation method, I'm uncertain: I too dislike parentheses, particularly in descriptive titles. Perhaps [[June 1941 uprising in eastern Herzegovina]], or [[Eastern Herzegovina uprising, June 1941]]? (this unsigned comment by [[User:No such user]])
:*I'd prefer the former, commas are almost as bad as parentheses in my view. Cheers, [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 07:12, 8 May 2014 (UTC)
*'''Support''' &quot;June 1941 uprising in eastern Herzegovina&quot;. [[User:23 editor|23 editor]] ([[User talk:23 editor|talk]]) 12:54, 8 May 2014 (UTC)
*'''Support''' move per nomination. Current capitalization is contrary to the MOS. [[User:Anotherclown|Anotherclown]] ([[User talk:Anotherclown|talk]]) 01:36, 10 May 2014 (UTC)
&lt;hr /&gt;
:''The above discussion is preserved as an archive of a [[WP:RM|requested move]].  &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/span&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on this talk page or in a [[WP:move review|move review]]. No further edits should be made to this section.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- Template:RM bottom --&gt;
Although I voted in the discussion (and proposed the title), I boldly moved this article, to cut the [[WP:BURO]]. Should anyone object, there is [[WP:MR]]. [[User:No such user|No such user]] ([[User talk:No such user|talk]]) 08:24, 16 May 2014 (UTC)

== Use of Serbo-Croat translation of Tomasevich 1975 ==

I believe the use of the translated 1979 Serbo-Croat version of Tomasevich's original 1975 work is in conflict with [[WP:NONENG]], in that &quot;Citations to non-English sources are allowed. However, because this is the English-language Wikipedia, English-language sources are preferred over non-English ones, whenever English sources of equal quality and relevance are available.&quot; In this case, the English source is not only of equal quality and relevance, the 1975 work in English is, in fact, the original work, and the 1979 is only a derivative of it. Given the English version is the original work, and this if English WP, it is inappropriate to use the translated version in preference to the English one, here or elsewhere. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 23:59, 5 May 2014 (UTC)
:Its Yugoslav edition, not derivative of English source. Its not inappropriate to use Yugoslav edition if wikipedia editor do not possess English language edition.--[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 06:35, 6 May 2014 (UTC)
::Where does it say that? [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 06:54, 6 May 2014 (UTC)
:::[[WP:COMMON SENSE]] --[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 07:51, 6 May 2014 (UTC)
::::I'm happy to take it to the community for a decision. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 08:14, 6 May 2014 (UTC)
:::::You certainly cannot ''force'' Antid to use English version, when he owns a SC translation and it is much more convenient for him; it is certainly not &quot;inappropriate&quot;. However, the original English work should take precedence in case of any disagreement. If quotations are provided, they should be from the English edition, not back-translated SC edition. Now, page numbers probably won't match, but that's often the case with multiple editions of same English works, isn't it? Some AGF usually works well, although I understand it is currently at shortage with respect to Antidiskriminator. [[User:No such user|No such user]] ([[User talk:No such user|talk]]) 07:33, 8 May 2014 (UTC)
::::::Pretty much what I am saying. He has access to the sh translation via znaci, and the pages don't always exactly match my paper copy of the original. He has already tried to use a difference in wording between the two in a bid to have words removed from the Djurisic article, and there are echoes of the same issue with the Selbstschutz article and the Moslem militia article. It is exactly because of such behaviour that I am running low on AGF when it comes to Ad. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 07:55, 8 May 2014 (UTC)

== Sources ==

I am surprised with such premature GA nomination taking in consideration that the only source for almost all assertions about the uprising is one work of Croatian historian Davor Marjan. In one of earlier assessments the editor who is a main contributor to this article and nominator for GA status stated that such articles do not meet B class status.

* ''&quot; needs more balanced coverage, almost all refs are Israeli or Jewish, needs supporting materials&quot;'' ([https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk%3AAzzam_Pasha_quotation&amp;oldid=568034556&amp;diff=prev diff])

I propose to add more supporting materials to this article.--[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 16:09, 15 May 2014 (UTC)
:that is a very generic comment. You are referring to me, of course. What refs would they be? [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 23:43, 15 May 2014 (UTC)
::Antidiskriminator. This is the first and only warning you are going to get about this. Your trawling through my quick assessments of thousands of new and unassessed MILHIST articles to find something that mentions Israel and Jewish sources in a transparent attempt to discredit my work is completely and utterly unacceptable on Wikipedia. If you '''ever''' make any further baseless allusions in any way that I might hold anti-Semitic views, I will take you straight to WP:AN and ask for an indefinite site ban based on your involvement in the Jews and Communism discussion at WP:AN, this comment and any further comments. Your involvement in the Jews and Communism discussion does not do you any credit at all. You blatantly tried to get the administrators there to investigate your conspiracy theory about a &quot;travelling circus&quot; for your own ends, and now that appears to have failed, you are trying to make allusions about my editing to link me to that matter. The specific case you are referring to was one where an infamous comment was made against Jews and Israel prior to the 1948 Arab-Israeli War , and the sources in the article at the time I quickly assessed it did not in my opinion include sufficient balance of non-Jewish and non-Israeli sources. There were two reasons why the article did not meet B-Class, and they were the issue of the range of coverage (sources) and the lack of any images or infobox etc, ie both criteria b2 and criteria b5. If the article had an infobox or image, it would have had no problem being MILHIST C-Class, and a couple more non-Israeli/non-Jewish sources would have made it MILHIST B-Class.
::Now, regarding this article. There are no similarities between that article and this one in terms of balanced sources. Yes, Marijan is used extensively, because Marijan is a high quality academic source that details the activities that occurred during the uprising on a day by day basis, unlike the other sources who do not provide that level of detail. However, of the citations used in this article, about 25% are from eight other sources, so to characterise Marijan as the only source for almost all assertions about the uprising, or that the article lacks a good range of sources, is completely baseless. Marijan does not contradict the other sources used in the article regarding the details they do provide, such as the preceding massacres, neither do they contradict him. He is a well-published Doctor of History whose Masters thesis was on the Ustase militia, and the paper in question was published in the ''Journal of Contemporary History''. If you want to be taken seriously here, please explain what your concerns are about using Marijan as a source, and provide reliable published sources of similar quality that contradict his account. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 02:14, 16 May 2014 (UTC)
::: I clearly referred to assertions about uprising, not prelude and background. Most of the first 18 references that include more of other sources cover background and prelude section. When it comes to text about uprising itself, almost all assertions are referenced with  one work of Croatian historian Davor Marjan. Like I explained above, that is something you yourself believe is insufficient even for B class status. No doubt you know this, but you still wrote another unnecessarily harsh comment to me threatening to report me. Almost every single comment you write to me is unnecessarily harsh and contains violation of AGF which made editing of many articles unpleasant for me and discouraged me from further editing. In order to avoid being subjected to this kind of treatment this will be my last comment in this article. This page is removed from my watchlist, like all other pages you chased me away from. All the best.--[[User:Antidiskriminator|Antidiskriminator]] ([[User talk:Antidiskriminator|talk]]) 06:56, 16 May 2014 (UTC)
::::You did not. &quot;Uprising&quot; is the whole article. You didn't specify the &quot;Uprising section&quot;, so how am I to know that is what you meant? Just one more example of your poor English communication causing unnecessary drama, again. After making a vague generalised complaint, your response to provide specifics is to withdraw. That is your usual response, and it has been repeated over and over for years. When you should be apologising for your completely unacceptable attempt to raise an issue related to anti-semitism, you complain that '''I''' am being too harsh. My complaint about your terrible behaviour was entirely justified, and you should be ashamed of yourself for even attempting to raise it. I am the only one that has the right to be offended here. Goodbye and good riddance. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|send... over]]) 07:13, 16 May 2014 (UTC)

:That sort of character assassination by insinuation and out-of-context quoting is disgusting. [[User:No such user|No such user]] ([[User talk:No such user|talk]]) 08:19, 16 May 2014 (UTC)

== &quot;Tonogal&quot;... ==

...might be a misspelling of '''Togonal'''. Not sure which is correct, Google search returns both. [[User:GregorB|GregorB]] ([[User talk:GregorB|talk]]) 20:29, 21 November 2014 (UTC)

Still better than [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=June_1941_uprising_in_eastern_Herzegovina&amp;action=historysubmit&amp;diff=632478756&amp;oldid=630656574 Hermana Tonogala ]. [[User:23 editor|23 editor]] ([[User talk:23 editor|talk]]) 20:52, 21 November 2014 (UTC)
:Thanks guys, my conjunctions are rarely on the ball. I'll see if I can find something definitive. [[User:Peacemaker67|Peacemaker67]]  ([[User_talk:Peacemaker67#top|crack... thump]]) 22:17, 21 November 2014 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>c52tt9dpnrkg14ol16e1fr1u95g9xs9</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
