<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Edward Low</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>12107482</id>
    <revision>
      <id>635345728</id>
      <parentid>634950893</parentid>
      <timestamp>2014-11-25T06:20:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adamdaley</username>
        <id>2669838</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Cleanup.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22570">{{talkheader}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Biography|living=n|class=FA|listas=Low, Edward|military-work-group=y|military-priority=Low}}
{{WikiProject Piracy|class=FA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Military History|class=FA|Biography=y|Maritime=y|Early-Modern=y}}
}}
{{ArticleHistory|action1=PR
|action1date=20:19, 1 October 2007
|action1link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Edward Low/archive1
|action1result=reviewed
|action1oldid=161635915

|action2=GAN
|action2date=21:48, 04 October 2007
|action2link=Talk:Edward Low#GA passed
|action2result=listed
|action2oldid=162317648

|action3=FAC
|action3date=16:20, 5 November 2007
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Edward Low
|action3result=promoted
|action3oldid=167873901

|topic=history
|currentstatus=FA
|maindate=May 22, 2008
}}
{{User:WildBot/m04|sect={{User:WildBot/m03|1|Privateer#Privateering on the Spanish Main}}|m04}}

== George Roberts ==
Seems to be some disagreement between the article and the pullquote as to whether George Roberts really existed or was a fictional construct?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/216.164.44.4|216.164.44.4]] ([[User talk:216.164.44.4|talk]]) 15:01, 8 November 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== GA passed ==
I think this is a good and interesting article that is very close to GA standard. I particularly like the layout in the body of the article, where there are relevant quotations down the right hand side. Very nice. I do have a few points to raise though, before I list the article as a GA.

*The last chapter of the ''Brutality'' section, starting &quot;A snow called the Unity was added to the fleet ...&quot; seems to have nothing to do with brutality.
*In the paragraph above that, there's a sentence that starts &quot;Leslie described Low as a psychopath ...&quot;. It would be nice to be given some idea of what Leslie's expertise is at that point. For instance, &quot;Historian Edward Leslie ...&quot;
*The ''Captain'' section starts off &quot;Low abandoned his plans off the coast of Brazil, and moved on to the Caribbean ...&quot; What plans did he abandon? I don't see anything preceding that to explain what his plans were in going to Brazil.
*The ''Captain'' section doesn't seem to sit well. It's very short, and it's a bit confusing, as George Roberts is variously described as Captain George Roberts, and a mate on the British ship King Sagamore. If this was a meeting after Low had captured the ''Pink'', wouldn't the meeting have taken place aboard the renamed ''Rose Pink''?
*I'm a little bit dubious about potential POV statements like &quot;... '''terrorised''' the Azores ..&quot;, and more particularly &quot;One of Low's most particularly noted episodes of '''sadism''' ...&quot;. Brutality certainly, but sadism? That implies some degree of sexual satisfaction for the act. Is there any evidence for that?
*I think there's some serious overlinking in the article. For instance, [[man of war]] is linked twice in the last chapter of the ''Brutality'' section; [[rum]] is linked in the last paragraph of the ''Life in Boston'' section; [[silk]] is linked in the ''Flags'' section; in the sentence &quot;Low was rescued by a [[French|France]] ship ...&quot; French is linked to France; [[rigger]] links to a disambiguation page, none of the entries on which seem to be relevant to Low's job.
*Low's brother was &quot;... was '''hung''' at Tyburn for thievery, but Low himself was &quot;... '''hanged''' ... in Martinique ...&quot; &quot;The men were '''hung''' for felony, piracy and robbery ...&quot; As a British English speaker, I prefer &quot;hanged&quot;, but whichever is chosen, it ought to be consistent.
*In the ''Piracy'' section for instance, in the paragraph beginning &quot;He sank the other ships of the fleet, and abandoned the Rebecca. The Boston News Letter of 9 July 1722 published a list of those captured by Low. A number of the fishermen were forced to join Low, including Philip Ashton who later escaped in May 1723 ...&quot; the dates aren't linked consistently. In one case the full date is only partially linked and a month/year (May 1723) isn't linked. I believe that there may be some debate over the value of wikilinking full dates, but whatever decision is made should be made consistently.

I don't see any other issues with this article in regard to the [[Wikipedia:What_is_a_good_article%3F|good article criteria]]; it appears to be stable, written from a neutral point of view, broad coverage with plenty of relevant references, and with appropriate copyright information for all images. So I'm putting the article on hold pending some agreement on the specific issues I've raised above. Well done to all the editors. --[[User:Malleus Fatuarum|Malleus Fatuarum]] 14:45, 4 October 2007 (UTC)

::Haha, that would pretty much be me.  Thanks. I'll fiddle with it. [[User:Neil|&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration:none; font-family: cursive ;color: #006600&quot;&gt;Neil&lt;/span&gt;]]&amp;nbsp;[[User_talk:Neil|&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration:none; color: #006600&quot;&gt;ム&lt;/span&gt;]] 17:27, 4 October 2007 (UTC)

:::As far as the suggestions go, all done except two;  the [[wikt:sadism|sadism]] one - sadism means &quot;experiencing pleasure at the pain of others&quot;, or &quot;enjoying the pain of others&quot;; this does not have to mean sexual pleasure.   [[wikt:Terrorise|Terrorise]] means to &quot;instil terror&quot; - do not get confused with &quot;[[terrorism]]&quot;, the use of which can have POV issues depending on context.  The dates are consistently linked - day/month linked (so we get 4 October or October 4), year never linked.  [[User:Neil|&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration:none; font-family: cursive ;color: #006600&quot;&gt;Neil&lt;/span&gt;]]&amp;nbsp;[[User_talk:Neil|&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration:none; color: #006600&quot;&gt;ム&lt;/span&gt;]] 17:50, 4 October 2007 (UTC)

*Stand-alone years ought not to be linked certainly, but years as part of a full date ought to be, especially where the day and month are linked as they are in this article, as per [[wp:date#Autoformatting and linking]].
*On the &quot;sadism&quot; issue, nobody can know what drove Low to his excesses of cruelty. Perhaps he derived no pleasure at all from it, but simply did it to instill fear in others. The text suggests that he carried out the act described as &quot;sadism&quot; in rage. That's very different from deriving pleasure from it.
*So far as the &quot;terrorised&quot; issue is concerned, I won't stick on that. I haven't confused it with terrorism, and it's certainly a plausible claim to make in any case. --[[User:Malleus Fatuarum|Malleus Fatuarum]] 18:21, 4 October 2007 (UTC)


A few issues (yes, I have issues!):
*Is 'Rhode Island sloop' intended to describe where the ship was from, or is it the name of a specific type of sloop?
*The list of Commands in the infobox doesn't seem right. From reading the article, I get:
:*Rebecca
:*Rose Pink
:*Ranger
:*Fancy
:*Merry Christmas
*Most links in the 'See also' section are already listed within the article.
*Is his '''death''' the subject of much speculation, or is it the manner, place, time, etc of his death? Picky I know, but I still don't like that sentence.
[[User:Maralia|Maralia]] 19:40, 4 October 2007 (UTC)

:To summarise where we are with this review, I will list this article as a GA if two outstanding issues are addressed:
:*the sadism claim is either substantiated or removed.
:*full dates are either consistently autoformatted, or not.
:--[[User:Malleus Fatuarum|Malleus Fatuarum]] 20:08, 4 October 2007 (UTC)

::Lots of points!

**Sadism - changed to cruelty (it's repeated earlier, but I've run out of synonyms).  The first rquote probably substantiates it (mirth, but it's really not a big deal.
**Years - hmm, I thought dates like this: &quot;[[4 October]] 2007&quot; were fine.  The MOS on that must have changed since I last looked at it about 18 months ago(!), I'll delink them.
**Rhode Island sloop - refers to sloops that were a part of the &quot;Rhode Island Navy&quot;.  Nothing to suggest they were different in any physical way to normal sloops. ([http://www.nuwc.navy.mil/hq/history/0002.html], [http://www.americanrevolution.org/nav3.html], [http://www.english.udel.edu/lemay/franklin/1737frame.html], [http://sloopprovidenceonline.org/history.htm]).
**List of commands - it's probably never going to be complete, because as best I can gather, Low changed ships a lot.  But the ''Ranger'' was definitely captained by Low at one point, I'll add it.
**See alsos - fixed.  I'd like to keep [[Piracy in the Caribbean]] there as it's piped in the article.
**Death - let's go with &quot;There are conflicting reports on the circumstances of Edward Low's death&quot; - okay to you?

::Phew! You guys are tough. [[User:Neil|&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration:none; font-family: cursive ;color: #006600&quot;&gt;Neil&lt;/span&gt;]]&amp;nbsp;[[User_talk:Neil|&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration:none; color: #006600&quot;&gt;ム&lt;/span&gt;]] 20:28, 4 October 2007 (UTC)

:::RE: Death - I'm happy with your rephrased statement above; however the sentence I really had issues with was 'His death, in around 1724, has been the subject of much speculation' which still remains in the lede. [[User:Maralia|Maralia]] 20:31, 4 October 2007 (UTC)

::::Baaaargh, missed that.  Changed to match. [[User:Neil|&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration:none; font-family: cursive ;color: #006600&quot;&gt;Neil&lt;/span&gt;]]&amp;nbsp;[[User_talk:Neil|&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration:none; color: #006600&quot;&gt;ム&lt;/span&gt;]] 20:33, 4 October 2007 (UTC)

Tough but fair I hope. I think this is a great article, and I'm going to promote it to GA. --[[User:Malleus Fatuarum|Malleus Fatuarum]] 20:38, 4 October 2007 (UTC)
:Qapla'! [[User:Neil|&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration:none; font-family: cursive ;color: #006600&quot;&gt;Neil&lt;/span&gt;]]&amp;nbsp;[[User_talk:Neil|&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration:none; color: #006600&quot;&gt;ム&lt;/span&gt;]] 21:15, 4 October 2007 (UTC)

A Star Trek fan as well as a pirate fan. Congratulations on what you've done with this article. --[[User:Malleus Fatuarum|Malleus Fatuarum]] 21:32, 4 October 2007 (UTC)


**The only pirates i know in my lifetime are Captain Hook and Captain Jack Sparrow. So, uh, nice meeting Ed Low. [[User:Fleurbutterfly|Fleurbutterfly]] 13:18, 22 May 2008 (UTC)

==Resources==
*[http://ftp.rootsweb.com/pub/usgenweb/pa/philadelphia/areahistory/watson0208.txt Area History: Chapters 4 - 5, Vol II - Watson's Annals of Philadelphia And Pennsylvania, 1857]
*[http://query.nytimes.com/mem/archive-free/pdf?_r=1&amp;res=9C0DE7DC1238E233A25757C1A96E9C94639ED7CF&amp;oref=slogin NYT article for quotes]
No stopping now! [[User:Neil|&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration:none; font-family: cursive ;color: #006600&quot;&gt;Neil&lt;/span&gt;]]&amp;nbsp;[[User_talk:Neil|&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration:none; color: #006600&quot;&gt;ム&lt;/span&gt;]] 21:15, 4 October 2007 (UTC)

== Suggestion pre FA nomination ==
You've probably been through an FA nomination before, in which case I'm teaching my granny to suck eggs. But just in case you haven't, I'll warn you that the reviewers can be very picky.

Breaches of the MOS like this – [[28 May]] 1722 – will have have them jumping up and down in excitement waving their &quot;Oppose 1a)&quot;s. As I understand the MOS, the rule is that full dates should be autoformatted, and so should day and month. So the example I quoted ought to be [[28 May]] [[1722]]; it's only years on their own that ought not to be wikilinked, not years as part of a full date. --[[User:Malleus Fatuarum|Malleus Fatuarum]] 22:54, 5 October 2007 (UTC)
:{{done}}  And yeah, but believe it or not, the last FA nomination I went through was almost 2 years ago(!), and for an [[shoe polish|entirely different topic]]. [[User:Neil|&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration:none; font-family: cursive ;color: #006600&quot;&gt;Neil&lt;/span&gt;]]&amp;nbsp;[[User_talk:Neil|&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration:none; color: #006600&quot;&gt;ム&lt;/span&gt;]] 09:30, 6 October 2007 (UTC)
You're obviously a man of very catholic tastes. Good luck with the FA review. --[[User:Malleus Fatuarum|Malleus Fatuarum]] 13:19, 6 October 2007 (UTC)

== &quot;Good Quarters to be given when Craved&quot; ==
Is &quot;quarters&quot; mercy or lodgings? [[User:Jnestorius|jnestorius]]&lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:Jnestorius|talk]])&lt;/sup&gt; 01:02, 22 May 2008 (UTC)

== Introduction  ==
The New York Times reference in the introduction should be accompanied by a source citation (in my opinion).  Not a biggie, but would add just that much more credibility to a good article--Thanks[[Special:Contributions/75.68.192.62|75.68.192.62]] ([[User talk:75.68.192.62|talk]]) 02:36, 22 May 2008 (UTC)
::Expanding on this, I caught myself wonder what year the NYT made this comment. I think many readers, like myself, may not be clear on just how long some papers have been around, and may wonder if it was an of-the-times comment, or something printed in retrospect. [[User:Dxco|Dxco]] ([[User talk:Dxco|talk]]) 05:29, 22 May 2008 (UTC)

Why is Arthur Conan Doyle description of Edward Low mentioned? he was not a contemporary and as far as I can see from the wiki article on Doyle. Was he an expert on pirates somehow?  [[Special:Contributions/77.1.109.219|77.1.109.219]] ([[User talk:77.1.109.219|talk]]) 11:09, 22 May 2008 (UTC)
:Low was fairly unheard of, and never received the kind of attention and &quot;media treatment&quot; that [[Edward Teach]] or [[Stede Bonnet]] have received, which is why I decided to write the article.  Very few people as notable as Conan Doyle have ever written about him. [[User:Neil|&lt;u style=&quot;text-decoration:none;font:100% cursive;color:#600&quot;&gt;Neıl&lt;/u&gt;]] [[User_talk:Neil|&lt;u style=&quot;text-decoration:none;color:#226&quot;&gt;&lt;B&gt;龱&lt;/B&gt;&lt;/u&gt;]] 23:08, 22 May 2008 (UTC)

== Kudos! ==
I came accross this article from the front page FA section, and really enjoyed it! It was concise and to the point, but as well had a nice flavor to it, where the authors allowed a touch of saltiness to it by relying on quotes that contain terminology of the time. A fun read. Good job![[User:Dxco|Dxco]] ([[User talk:Dxco|talk]]) 05:31, 22 May 2008 (UTC)
==Date of Death? ==
The opening sentence gives 1724 as the date of Low's death, yet in the Death section there is no conclusive proof of when he died? [[User:Markb|Markb]] ([[User talk:Markb|talk]]) 10:40, 22 May 2008 (UTC)

**they said it's &quot;disputed&quot;. [[User:Fleurbutterfly|Fleurbutterfly]] 13:13, 22 May 2008 (UTC)

==More ships than noted?==
About halfway through the page, in the &quot;Capsizing of the ''Rose Pink'' section, the text reads [edited]

&quot;and his fleet of '''two''' ships ('''the ''Rose Pink'' and the ''Fancy''''',...... and Low—now captaining the schooner '''''Squirrel'''''&quot;

Fine, he had two vessels, neither had that final name, so where did the ''Squirrel'' come from? --[[User:Dumarest|Dumarest]] ([[User talk:Dumarest|talk]]) 11:35, 22 May 2008 (UTC)
:I've expanded the sentence to clarify this. [[User:Neil|&lt;u style=&quot;text-decoration:none;font:100% cursive;color:#600&quot;&gt;Neıl&lt;/u&gt;]] [[User_talk:Neil|&lt;u style=&quot;text-decoration:none;color:#226&quot;&gt;&lt;B&gt;龱&lt;/B&gt;&lt;/u&gt;]] 17:49, 22 May 2008 (UTC)

== Rephrase? ==
&quot;Following the death of his wife during childbirth in late 1719, he became a pirate two years later, &quot; - this is badly phrased. Perhaps &quot;He became a pirate in 1921, two years after the death of his wife during childbirth&quot; or similar? [[Special:Contributions/217.34.222.220|217.34.222.220]] ([[User talk:217.34.222.220|talk]]) 14:06, 22 May 2008 (UTC)

It should be two separate sentences: one idea per sentence. We do not know if the death of his wife contributed to his decision to become a pirate or if it was unrelated. [[User:Monado|Monado]] ([[User talk:Monado|talk]]) 14:34, 22 May 2008 (UTC)

== &quot;Scoundrel&quot; is an opinion ==
Is there an agreed-on definition for &quot;scoundrel&quot; for which Edward Low qualified during his time as a thief? Can we find another word that conveys the idea of socially inappropriate conduct but which is not a value judgement? Do we have more information about his activities that we can use here? &quot;Thief&quot; indicates that he stole. Is there another action noun we can pair with it? Did he fight? Kidnap? Intimidate? [[User:Monado|Monado]] ([[User talk:Monado|talk]]) 14:39, 22 May 2008 (UTC)
:Definition of [http://www.answers.com/scoundrel&amp;r=67 scoundrel]: &quot;a villain, a rogue&quot;.  Based on the &quot;Early life&quot; section, yes, &quot;scoundrel&quot; is an appropriate term. [[User:Neil|&lt;u style=&quot;text-decoration:none;font:100% cursive;color:#600&quot;&gt;Neıl&lt;/u&gt;]] [[User_talk:Neil|&lt;u style=&quot;text-decoration:none;color:#226&quot;&gt;&lt;B&gt;龱&lt;/B&gt;&lt;/u&gt;]] 16:53, 22 May 2008 (UTC)

== Sexual Orientation ==
Edward Low was a Homosexual, correct? That's what I remember from school.[[Special:Contributions/66.142.195.205|66.142.195.205]] ([[User talk:66.142.195.205|talk]]) 16:26, 22 May 2008 (UTC)

#You need a [[WP:RS|reliable source]] for your assertion
#It doesn't belong in the &quot;See also&quot; section any more than &quot;heterosexuality&quot; belongs in the [[Bill Gates]] article.-[[User:Wafulz|Wafulz]] ([[User talk:Wafulz|talk]]) 16:44, 22 May 2008 (UTC)
::I agree that it doesn't belong in the 'see also' section; the article on [[homosexuality]] doesn't appear to say anything about Edward Low, and if he was indeed gay, that should be discussed and sourced within the body of the article rather than just linking to the term. -[[User:FisherQueen|FisherQueen]]&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot;&gt; ([[User talk:FisherQueen|talk]] · [[Special:Contributions/FisherQueen|contribs]])&lt;/span&gt; 21:03, 26 April 2009 (UTC)
:::You need a [[WP:RS|reliable source]] for your facts. I heard about this too and went to school on the east coast. It's going to be hard to find citations for that statement. I suppose if a celebrity said it in an interview or put it in a magazine it could be used. [[User:Lawtonlawdawg|Lawtonlawdawg]] ([[User talk:Lawtonlawdawg|talk]]) 16:19, 27 May 2009 (UTC)

== Time problem ==
In the second paragraph, the phrasing suggests that Sir Arthur Conan Doyle and the New York Times were contemporaneous with Low; but of course Low was long dead before either Doyle or the NYT came to be.  I'd suggest either replacing these quotes with contemporary sources; or at the very least, starting the sentence with something like &quot;Two centuries later, Doyle described Low as . . . .&quot;  Otherwise it's rather misleading to the casual reader.[[User:Textorus|Textorus]] ([[User talk:Textorus|talk]]) 18:29, 22 May 2008 (UTC)
:How does it suggest they were contemporaneous with Low?  I don't find it misleading.  I am probably biased as I wrote it, of course. [[User:Neil|&lt;u style=&quot;text-decoration:none;font:100% cursive;color:#600&quot;&gt;Neıl&lt;/u&gt;]] [[User_talk:Neil|&lt;u style=&quot;text-decoration:none;color:#226&quot;&gt;&lt;B&gt;龱&lt;/B&gt;&lt;/u&gt;]] 22:14, 22 May 2008 (UTC)

== Urgent - Vandalism? ==
My undo of vandalism was reverted by a very experienced &amp; reputable admin Epbr123 - but I can still see the 'vandalism' namely using table cells at the very bottom of the article to display very large (albeit pixellated) lewd images (after Guide to Edward Low in the external links).  Could someone please check - am I the only one seeing this &amp; if so how?  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:IvorE|IvorE]] ([[User talk:IvorE|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/IvorE|contribs]]) 19:18, 22 May 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

I am also seeing these extremely lewd images (as of 20:26 BST), But I am new to Wikipedia and do not know how to change it.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/80.192.9.70|80.192.9.70]] ([[User talk:80.192.9.70|talk]]) 19:27, 22 May 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Thanks, I'm glad I wan't seeing things. I must apologise though: in my desire to remove the images I think I deleted a valid part of the article (the Pirates and Privateers related links). The article seems OK now (20:55 BST) but I'm still curious how the &lt;s&gt;[[retard]]&lt;/s&gt; managed to create the 'images' on the page.[[User:IvorE|IE]] ([[User talk:IvorE|talk]]) 19:58, 22 May 2008 (UTC)

== Ed vs. Ned ==
Several users have changed the nickname mentioned from &quot;Ned&quot; to &quot;Ed&quot;. All of the sources that I have checked linked from this article mention either &quot;Ned Low&quot; or &quot;Edward Low&quot;. Can anyone provide references for the changes to &quot;Ed&quot;? &amp;mdash; [[User:Lambda|λ]] ([[User talk:Lambda|talk]]) 22:07, 22 May 2008 (UTC)
:There are none.  I hesitate to call it vandalism, but even if it's well-meaning, it is wholly incorrect. [[User:Neil|&lt;u style=&quot;text-decoration:none;font:100% cursive;color:#600&quot;&gt;Neıl&lt;/u&gt;]] [[User_talk:Neil|&lt;u style=&quot;text-decoration:none;color:#226&quot;&gt;&lt;B&gt;龱&lt;/B&gt;&lt;/u&gt;]] 22:12, 22 May 2008 (UTC)

==More ships than noted?==
About halfway through the page, in the &quot;Capsizing of the ''Rose Pink'' section, the text reads [edited]

&quot;and his fleet of '''two''' ships ('''the ''Rose Pink'' and the ''Fancy''''',...... and Low—now captaining the schooner '''''Squirrel'''''&quot;

Fine, he had two vessels, neither had that final name, so where did the ''Squirrel'' come from? --[[User:Dumarest|Dumarest]] ([[User talk:Dumarest|talk]]) 11:35, 22 May 2008 (UTC)
:I've expanded the sentence to clarify this. [[User:Neil|&lt;u style=&quot;text-decoration:none;font:100% cursive;color:#600&quot;&gt;Neıl&lt;/u&gt;]] [[User_talk:Neil|&lt;u style=&quot;text-decoration:none;color:#226&quot;&gt;&lt;B&gt;龱&lt;/B&gt;&lt;/u&gt;]] 17:49, 22 May 2008 (UTC)  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/164.58.104.33|164.58.104.33]] ([[User talk:164.58.104.33|talk]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== His brother ==
The article briefly refers to Ned's brother (&quot;The brother later took to other forms of criminal activity and ended up hanged at Tyburn for 'thievery'.&quot;). His crime would probably be called burglary or similar today. Richard Low was found guilty of &quot;breaking open the dwelling House of Captain John Guyon&quot; and of &quot;breaking open the dwelling-House of Jacob Curtis.&quot; His accomplices in these two cases were William Davis, Joseph Montisano, John Hall and Stephen Bunch. All ended up in the gallows at Tyburn, as per the Old Bailey proceedings of 10 December 1707. (Source: http://www.oldbaileyonline.org/browse.jsp?path=sessionsPapers%2F17071210.xml)  [[User:Idontcareanymore|Idontcareanymore]] ([[User talk:Idontcareanymore|talk]]) 17:13, 6 September 2011 (UTC)
:That's really good, thank you.  I've put it in the article. [[User:Fish and karate|&lt;u style=&quot;text-decoration:none;font:100% cursive;color:#28c&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;fish&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/u&gt;]]&amp;amp;[[User_talk:Fish and karate|&lt;u style=&quot;text-decoration:none;font:100% cursive;color:#D33&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;karate&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/u&gt;]] 10:14, 7 September 2011 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>nzl4dj2ikrauwmow33y9e3fbl716p29</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
