<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Empress Matilda</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>324403</id>
    <revision>
      <id>729672568</id>
      <parentid>729648066</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-07-13T20:03:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cassianto</username>
        <id>10612090</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* If Sagaciousphil has a &quot;dispute&quot;, can he please explain what it is? */ [[WP:TALKNO]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="57074">{{British English}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=11:16, 2 February 2014 (UTC)
|action1link=/GA1
|action1result=pass
|action1oldid=593568017
|topic=History

|action2=WAR
|action2date=17:55, 7 March 2014 (UTC)
|action2link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/Empress Matilda
|action2result=approved
|action2oldid=598576130

|action3=FAC
|action3date=13:29, 29 May 2014
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Empress Matilda/archive1
|action3result=promoted
|action3oldid=610087511

|currentstatus=FA
|maindate=July 2, 2014
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Biography
|living=no
|class=FA
|military-work-group=yes
|military-priority=mid
|royalty-work-group=yes
|listas=Matilda, Empress
|royalty-priority=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Middle Ages|class=FA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject England|class=FA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject English Royalty|class=FA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Women's History|class=FA|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Germany|class=FA|importance=low|HRE-taskforce=yes|HRE-taskforce-importance=}}
{{WikiProject Austria|class=FA|importance=low}}
{{WPMILHIST|class=FA|A-Class=pass|British=yes|French=yes|Medieval=yes}}
}}

{{OnThisDay|date1=2013-11-01|oldid1=579575589|date2=2016-04-07|oldid2=713649802}}

== [[Wikipedia:WikiProject_Biography/Assessment#Class_parameter|Biography assessment rating]] comment ==
[[Wikipedia:WikiProject Biography/Assessment|WikiProject Biography Assessment]]

The article may be improved by following the [[Wikipedia:WikiProject_Biography#WikiProject_Biography_11_easy_steps_to_producing_at_least_a_B_article|WikiProject Biography 11 easy steps]] to producing at least a B article. -- '''&lt;font color=&quot;#FF3300&quot;&gt;[[User:Yamara|Yamara]]&lt;/font&gt;''' 04:31, 16 June 2007 (UTC)

==Discussion==
In google it says that she is a king and it says it got it from wikipedia! is there a way to fix or did google just mahe that up?
[[User:Oliverrushton|Oliverrushton]] ([[User talk:Oliverrushton|talk]]) 16:11, 22 April 2015 (UTC)
What does this mean?
&lt;blockquote&gt;
brother William Adelin had perished several years before in the wreck of the White Ship, leaving Matilda the only legitimate heir to the English throne, a fact that King Henry II may have had contrary evidence to.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
This seems to imply Henry II had some evidence about his mother not being the only legitimate heir. I have not read anything elsewhere that would shed light on this. This seems confusing, and if it cannot be verified perhaps it should be deleted.
----
Why is she called a queen regnant and a monarch of England when she never was truly queen? Most lists of English monarchs include Stephen and Henry II but do not include her as an actual monarch. Shouldn't she be removed as a monarch? Even she never called herself queen, not even during the few months when she held advantage over Stephen.

''the circumstances of her escape were the stuff of fiction'' - could someone elaborate? [[User:RickK|RickK]] 02:07, 22 Sep 2003 (UTC) &amp;lt;ScoobyDoo&amp;gt;Yeh-yeh-yeh&amp;lt;/ScoobyDoo&amp;gt; [[User:Phil Boswell|Phil]] 18:13, Jan 21, 2004 (UTC)

I don't find any mention of tthis in Cross' history. The struggle between Stephen and Matilda was an on-going back-and-forth affair. Perhaps the wording could changed. It might be better to mention what the &quot;fiction&quot; is, before discrediting it. [[User:Decumanus|Decumanus]] 18:39, 21 Jan 2004 (UTC)

==

''Maud was besieged at Oxford; the circumstances of her escape were the stuff of fiction.''

changed to

''Maud was besieged at Oxford, but escaped''.


Also, it seems to me that the first paragraph is a bit of a mess

''Empress Maud (February 7, 1102 - September 10, 1169) is the title by which Matilda the daughter and dispossessed heir of King Henry I of England and his wife Maud of Scotland (herself daughter of Malcolm III Canmore and St. Margaret of Scotland), is known, in order to differentiate her from the many other Matildas of the period.''

Think that maybe this could be separate and restated?

''Empress Maud (February 7, 1102 - September 10, 1169) is the title by which Matilda, the daughter and dispossessed heir of King Henry I of England, is known, in order to differentiate her from the many other Matildas of the period. She was the daughter of Henry and his wife Maud of Scotland (who was herself daughter of Malcolm III Canmore and St. Margaret of Scotland),''

Or something like that?
-- St. Weasel



-- St. Weasel

Something is obviously wrong with the math here if she was 7 in 1111 and 23 in 1125...  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/67.40.108.244|67.40.108.244]] ([[User talk:67.40.108.244|talk]]) 19:15, 5 March 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Hello, I am new to the wikipedia thing and was doing research on female rulership in the early middle ages and had this question:

Is there a reference as to what inspired Henry I to recall his daughter Maud, the dowager Empress of Holy Roman Empire, and install her as his single legitimate heir over other male canidates? As far as I can see, with the exception of a few Spanish Visgothic kingdoms there was no precident for designnating a female heir to rule as Queen Regnant in her own right. Eleanor of Aquataine is the next closest example and her father willed her the succession with an independant duchy. But this would not be for a few years yet.


According to the wiki article on The Anarchy (as the period of civil war is known) &quot;On Henry's death in 1135, Stephen rushed to England,&quot; yet according to this article &quot;Stephen of Blois, a nephew of Henry I, usurped the throne ... An immediate reason for this was that Stephen was in England, whilst Matilda was in Anjou.&quot;
Which is correct? Or possibly it just needs expanding to show that he rushed to England whilst she was still in Anjou?  [[Special:Contributions/88.105.2.120|88.105.2.120]] ([[User talk:88.105.2.120|talk]]) 06:28, 14 November 2008 (UTC)TheDixieFlatline

== Maud/Matilda ==

Is there a particular reason why this article focuses on (and is titled for) the name Maud? I don't pretend to be a great authority on British history, but in all the reading I had done of the period, I never encountered the name Maud until this Wikipedia article. I did some searches (and I'm not the best internet searcher) and while I did occasionally find hits on Maud, it seemed like a lot of them just came back to this article&amp;mdash;there were far more to Empress Matilda. [[User:Duckecho|Duckecho]] ([[User talk:Duckecho|Talk)]] 4 July 2005 22:14 (UTC)

::This odd Maud/Matilda business has been around for a long time,  it was like that when I was a little kid and long time ago.  It certainly hasn't just been made up recently.[[User:Eregli bob|Eregli bob]] ([[User talk:Eregli bob|talk]]) 07:45, 25 November 2012 (UTC)

I understand the concern for ambiguity due to the proliferation of Matildas at the time; her grandmother, Stephen's wife, and a couple of others, but from her marriage to Emporer Henry V, she became styled as Empress Matilda, which would seem to erase any confusion (such as with her grandmother Queen Matilda, and her cousin Countess Matilda, Stephen's wife). [[User:Duckecho|Duckecho]] ([[User talk:Duckecho|Talk)]] 4 July 2005 22:14 (UTC)

Moreover, there at least a couple of Wiki articles I've seen that refer to her as Matilda in the text even though the wikifying text is forced to be to Empress Maud. [[User:Duckecho|Duckecho]] ([[User talk:Duckecho|Talk)]] 4 July 2005 22:14 (UTC)

Is there any evidence that Maud was a name commonly used for her in her time? Is there any interest in renaming the article Empress Matilda? Is there any strong sentiment for leaving it alone? [[User:Duckecho|Duckecho]] ([[User talk:Duckecho|Talk)]] 4 July 2005 22:14 (UTC)

== Manual move ==

[[User:Duckecho]] (since he has now left I guess I can point him out specifically) manually moved this back in July, so I deleted that and moved the article properly. There were some edits made in the past five months that have been lost, but nothing major I hope. (If so, too bad, blame Duckecho.) [[User:Adam Bishop|Adam Bishop]] 15:29, 5 December 2005 (UTC)

== Name info ==

There is more info available at [http://www.findagrave.com/cgi-bin/fg.cgi?page=gr&amp;GRid=8619917 Find-A-Grave]. [[User:Lincher|Lincher]] 16:00, 23 March 2006 (UTC)

== Foggy history ==
Was Mitilda ''Queen regnant of England'' in 1141? Isn't [[Mary I of England]] viewed as England's 'first female monarch'? [[User:GoodDay|GoodDay]] ([[User talk:GoodDay|talk]]) 20:38, 16 December 2007 (UTC)
:The title of this section says it all. However, I concluded from the text that we should treat Matilda as Queen regnant for the period she held actual power, and, thus, Stephen as not-King '''[[User:DBD|D]][[WP:BRoy|B]][[User talk:DBD|D]]''' 21:17, 16 December 2007 (UTC)
::The title of this section says it all. Mary I is the first woman to have been unquestionably Queen regnant of England. However, Jane Grey's claims are sometimes recognised, and Matilda is also sometimes recognised. [[User:Michaelsanders|Michael]]  [[User talk:Michaelsanders|Sanders]] 16:22, 17 December 2007 (UTC)

== Undisputed reign? ==
The article says her temporary reign in 1141, wihch is wrong, it was still disputed by Stephen (the true King) and his barons.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/67.124.149.222|67.124.149.222]] ([[User talk:67.124.149.222|talk]]) 19:06, 5 March 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Visit to Italy==
this sentence is unclear: 'in march 1116 Henry and matilda visited rome and tuscany, and she acted as regent in his abscence.' ?? were they together? how did she act as regent if she was in italy with him? clarification is in order.[[User:Toyokuni3|Toyokuni3]] ([[User talk:Toyokuni3|talk]]) 04:20, 21 May 2008 (UTC)
:Could not the Matilda who went to Rome be Matilda, the wife of Henry rather than Empress Matilda, daughter of Henry? I've no idea on the matter myself, but this seems a plauable explanation as to why a Matilda can both go to Rome and stay behind to be regent. [[User:Evil Eye|Evil Eye]] ([[User talk:Evil Eye|talk]]) 23:35, 27 July 2008 (UTC)

== Queen of England ==

There seems to be no consensus on whether or not Matilda is Queen of England. This is important as it effects the name and angle of the article. As the first line of the article is &quot;Matilda of England&quot; that does suggest that she was monarchs of England and so should be treated accordingly. [[User:The Quill|The Quill]] ([[User talk:The Quill|talk]]) 17:25, 27 November 2008 (UTC)
:No, it doesn't suggest that she was a monarh of England. Was Catherine of Aragon monarch of Aragon? It doesn't matter what you and me think. Consensus has to be reached among the historians. Anyway, I do not object to moving this article to Matilda of England. She is entitled to that name as an imperial and royal consort, if not as a monarch. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 17:39, 27 November 2008 (UTC)

::Thank You for agreeing to a page move it means alot to me! [[User:The Quill|The Quill]] ([[User talk:The Quill|talk]]) 17:50, 27 November 2008 (UTC)

=== Part II ===

Know that the first issue has been dealt with a consensus needs to be reached on whether or not we can calim Matilda as Queen of England. I know that lists don't usually show Matilda as being monarch however other monarchs such as [[Lady Jane Grey]] are often missed of lists however are considered a ''true'' monarch  by Wikipedia. Jane Grey held a bitterly disputed title for 9 days and is considered a Queen yet Matilda held the title for a number of months and is excluded. I don't want to make any edits of such a controversial nature until we have a consensus. [[User:The Quill|The Quill]] ([[User talk:The Quill|talk]]) 19:47, 30 November 2008 (UTC)

:We cannot decide to call her Queen of England because: 1. she never claimed that title (she preffered Lady of the English, since queen was the title of the king's wife) 2. historians haven't agreed whether she was a monarch. We should include both Matilda and Jane in the lists of English monarch with a note that their status is not quite certain. Have you noticed that English (after Mary I) and British monarchs rarely named their daughters Matilda or Jane? That's because they were not sure whether Empress Matilda and Lady Jane Grey should be included in the numbering of monarchs. It's not up to us to decide. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 18:22, 1 December 2008 (UTC)

::To counter your first point I was using the word queen as a matter of convinence. How she titled herself as monarch would of course be how she would be reffered to in the article (possibly with a sidenote explaining what Queen meant at that time. For your second point I agree with you about how we can't claim Matilda to be a monarch without an element of doubt however I do believe that more recognition of her title to be shown. [[User:The Quill|The Quill]] ([[User talk:The Quill|talk]]) 19:31, 1 December 2008 (UTC)


It seems to me that Maude/Matilda was a reigning Queen of England, in the sense that all the pre-qualificiations were in place: Her father's designation and sworn fealty of the nobility. Her cousin Stephen usurped the crown primarily with the aide of his brother... who was a leading prelate. What is interesting in the artical is the absence of her sucesses in Normandy and Anjou.... which were the central spears of power in the Norman world. England was very important, but secondary in many ways to Normandy and Anjou, as later Plantaganet rulers demonstrated. Additionally, following 1136, Matilda enjoyed wide suport and [[History of Gwynedd during the High Middle Ages#During England's Anarchy 1135-1157|popularity by the Marcher lords occupying Wales]] who viewed Matilda favorably (according to historian John Davies)[[User:Drachenfyre|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;'''''♦Drachenfyre♦'''''&lt;/font&gt;]]·&lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Drachenfyre|Talk]]&lt;/small&gt; 06:51, 13 December 2008 (UTC)

:To me this seems compelling enough evidence to say that she was indeed Queen of England. Unless anyone has any opposistion then I will begin to change the article to show this. [[User:The Quill|The Quill]] ([[User talk:The Quill|talk]]) 09:44, 13 December 2008 (UTC)

::It's already stated in the article that she was ''de jure'' heiress to the thrones, but she was never crowned (which was very important at that time, symbolizing the legitimacy of the new monarch). Stephen, on the other hand, was crowned and enjoyed the support of the majority of the barons. Even the Pope acknowledged Stephen as the rightful monarch of England. I am trying to maintain NPOV - I too believe that Matilda was the righful heiress, but that's my POV. Our POV does not belong to Wikipedia. I will strongly oppose claiming that she was undoubtly monarch of England. I will also oppose refering to her as Queen of England in any context because she herself believed that the title of queen belongs only to the wife of king and therefore believed that the title of queen would degrade her. We are entitled to our POV, but the article needs to retain NPOV. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 14:15, 13 December 2008 (UTC)

:::From know on we can refer to her as ''Lady'' if it makes you better. Stephen isn't recognised between April and November 1141. If you look carefully she can see that I always refer to her as disputed monarch. [[User:The Quill|The Quill]] ([[User talk:The Quill|talk]]) 19:25, 16 December 2008 (UTC)

::::I would also like to use Infobox German Royalty (at least until we combine all infoboxes into one), since Matilda gained her highest title and rank through her first marriage (that's why we use Infobox British Royalty for Aexandra of Denmark who was Danish by birth, but held a higher title through marriage). Matilda was known as Empress Matilda and styled herself that way even after remarriage (which was not uncommon: [[Katherine Parr]] also kept her royal title after remarriage, as did many dowager duchesses who married earls). We've almost reached a consensus. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 20:32, 16 December 2008 (UTC)

::As is have explained before if a person is of noble heritage of a country then that infobox shoudl be used that that of the title they held. Anyway Matilda was never actually Empress she was never crowned the highest title she actually ever held was Queen of the Romans. [[User:The Quill|The Quill]] ([[User talk:The Quill|talk]]) 20:42, 16 December 2008 (UTC)

:::Alright, I will not oppose using Infobox British Royalty if you successfully replace Infobox British Royalty with Infobox Danish Royalty in [[Alexandra of Denmark|this article]] (if nobody opposes the replacement). As for Matilda's highest title, even if you don't consider her imperial title (which she ''did'' use) to be valid, the title of German Queen is still her highest title. Anyway, her right to use the imperial title is disputed, but more historians recognize her as empress than as monarch of England. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 20:55, 16 December 2008 (UTC)

::::Thanky You for letting me use Infobox British Royalty. I do accept that German Queen is her highest title and that Lady of the English is diputed. However, she hever held the title Holy Roman Empress offically she asked historians to record her as being crowned but wasn't actauuly. [[User:The Quill|The Quill]] ([[User talk:The Quill|talk]]) 16:19, 17 December 2008 (UTC)

:::::I said: ''I will not oppose using Infobox British Royalty if you successfully replace Infobox British Royalty with Infobox Danish Royalty in [[Alexandra of Denmark|this article]] (if nobody opposes the replacement)''. But this is a pointless discussion anyway, so I don't care which infobox is used. There are bigger issues we should be discussing about. For example, you cannot assert that she wasn't Holy Roman Empress because she wasn't crowned (she wasn't crowned monarch of England either and you don't mind that). She was spouse of an Emperor who had been recognized and crowned by the Pope. [[Maria Theresa, Archduchess of Austria]] was crowned only Queen [regnant] of Hungary, but nobody disputes that she was also Queen [regnant] of Croatia and Bohemia, as well as Queen [consort] of the Romans and Holy Roman Empress. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 20:11, 17 December 2008 (UTC)

::::::::This isn't a negotiation page you can't bargin one infobox for another. I can assert that she was regent of England because 1. She was ''de jure'' monarch. 2. The Privy Council were on her side (originally). She wasn't Holy Roman Empress because she proclaimed herself as Empress, the only evidence that she was Empress she forced people to write or was written after she was dead and was sourced from the histories she forced people to write. [[User:The Quill|The Quill]] ([[User talk:The Quill|talk]]) 16:20, 18 December 2008 (UTC)

:::::::::I am not bargaining. You said that ''if a person is of noble heritage of a country then that infobox shoudl be used that that of the title they held''. I'm sure that all members of WikiProject British Royalty would disagree with you on this statement and your edit would be reverted very quickly. So, if Alexandra of Denmark article uses IBR, then this article should use IGR. But this is irrelevant because (hopefully) we'll get a universal infobox. Anyway, I don't care for your point of view, just like I don't care for my own point of view when it comes to writing and editing articles. First of all, a [[regent]] is a person who acts as head of state when the monarch is unable to perform his/her duties. Thus, Matilda was definitely never a regent. By the way, I have no idea what you meant to say about her imperial title. To counter your points: 1. she was ''de jure'' heiress, but not ''de jure'' monarch, although she was ''de facto'' head of state for few months; 2. the Privy Council supported her while she was the heiress presumptive, but not after her father's death. Another important fact is that she was never crowned and that the Pope never recognized her as a monarch. I will not oppose your edits as long as you don't break NPOV. The article is currently very neutral. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 19:35, 18 December 2008 (UTC)
:::::::::I'm not sure I understand the claim that Matilda was not empress.  One generally did not become Empress of the Holy Roman Empire by being crowned by the pope - I'm not sure if any of the empresses was ever crowned by the pope, although perhaps a couple were.  One became Empress by one's husband being crowned Emperor in Rome.  Which Matilda's husband was - Heinrich V was crowned twice, in 1111 and 1116.  Although he was not crowned by the pope, I don't think this makes a difference - several emperors were crowned by personages other than the pope, including both Heinrich V's own father and the later ruler Ludwig IV. [[User:John Kenney|john k]] ([[User talk:John Kenney|talk]]) 03:44, 2 June 2009 (UTC)
:Whether all members of WikiProject BRoy agree with me or not it is the current status quo. In the UK the term Queen Regent is used to for monarchs who are the actual head of state to distuinguish them from consorts who may (rather illogically) hold the title king or queen but don't hold any actualy power. The term heir(ess) is always ''de jure'' it is impossible not to be ''de jure'' a successor and a heir are completely different things. Matilda was ''de jure'' successor but not ''de facto'' successor. Also being ''de facto'' head of state actually makes her a monarch (as England was a monarchy). The fact that the pope didn't support her is irrelevant the pope had no actual legal authority to decide who was monarch of another country. The Pope recognising you is nice but not required. The articel is really that neutral at the moment is it? It hardly informative enoguh to be anything. [[User:The Quill|The Quill]] ([[User talk:The Quill|talk]]) 12:57, 19 December 2008 (UTC)

::Oh, dear. In the UK and elsewhere the term '''[[queen regnant]]''' is used to describe a female monarch of a kingdom. ''Regent'' and ''regnant'' are clearly not the same thing. You can understand this just by reading Wikipedia articles on [[regent]] and [[queen regnant]]. Thank you for explaining it to me, but I know that heir and successor are different terms. A successor is a person who has succeeded and we cannot claim that Matilda succeeded to the English crown because Stephen was proclaimed king immediately after Henry II's death (since succession to the Crown was not yet carved in stone in 12th century). Please stop saying nonsense, you are not going to convince anyone by saying that &quot;being de facto head of state makes her a monarch&quot;. Marie de' Medici was ''de facto'' head of state of France, yet nobody considers her to be a monarch of France. Margaret of Anjou was also ''de facto'' head of state of England, yet nobody considers her to be a monarch of England. Don't you realise that the English Reformation took place because of the Pope's vast authority over the King of England? The King couldn't even handle his own marriage without the Pope's consent. Papal approval was very, very important in 12th century and Stephen was the one whose accession the Pope approved. The article gives facts, not opinions, and that's what makes it neutral. You can't say that it's not informative enough just because it doesn't contain various theories. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 19:21, 19 December 2008 (UTC)

:::The Pope dealt with marriage in the name of God. Henry was the representative of God when it came to ruling the land. (As it is believed). The Popes approval was important but it wasn't actually neccessary. [[User:The Quill|The Quill]] ([[User talk:The Quill|talk]]) 13:51, 21 December 2008 (UTC)
:::: Perhaps a discussion of what actual historians studying the period and studying Matilda/Stephen might be in order, rather than theoretical arguments based on later time periods. [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 14:57, 21 December 2008 (UTC)

:::::Yes, we went off topic. My point is that we should maintain the neutral point of view (which user The Quill doesn't [want to] respect). Wikipedia must not ''[[Wikipedia:WikiProject English Royalty#Participants|fight for the rights of disputed monarchs]]''. [[Wikipedia:Point of view|A user's point of view]] and [[Wikipedia:Original research|original research]] do not belong to Wikipedia. If scholars cannot agree that she was a monarch, then Wikipedia should not claim that she was. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 15:11, 21 December 2008 (UTC)
::::: Well, a quick look at ''The Handbook of British Chronology'' shows that they don't list her as monarch. [http://www.royal.gov.uk/output/Page17.asp The Official British Monarchy Page on the Norman Monarchs] doesn't list her either (you need to do the pull down menu there). The [[Oxford Dictionary of National Biography]] doesn't list her as an English Monarch either, looking at [http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/theme/92701?backToResults=list=yes|group=yes|feature=yes|aor=7|orderField=alpha this list (need a subscription to see it)]. [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 15:16, 21 December 2008 (UTC)
::::::That's exactly my point, yet The Quill insists on treating her as a monarch. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 15:24, 21 December 2008 (UTC)

:::::::Getting Matilda recognised as a monarch is just one of my many goals. It isn't the most important and isn't the one that I am currently trying to achieve. If you look carefully at my arguments and edits you will see that I am trying to get her recognised as a legitiment heir(ess) who didn't get her crown. Many people at the time considered her to be the true moanrch, I know this doesn't make her a monarch but it does make her a calimant. [[User:The Quill|The Quill]] ([[User talk:The Quill|talk]]) 20:29, 21 December 2008 (UTC)

:::::::: We're, however, writing an encyclopedia, where we sumarize what reliable secondary sources (i.e. historians) write about the subject. If most of the historians don't call her the &quot;legitimate monarch&quot; then we can't say that in the infobox or the article. [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 20:37, 21 December 2008 (UTC)

:::::::::One again you have completely ignored what I have just said. I didn't said that she is  a &quot;''legitimate monarch''&quot; but a &quot;''claiment monarch''&quot; who had a strong claim to the throne and was recognised by many people at the time. [[User:The Quill|The Quill]] ([[User talk:The Quill|talk]]) 09:45, 22 December 2008 (UTC)
::I would go along with you, Quill on this one as I believe Matilda should be recognised as a monarch and the article needs to be moved to Queen Matilda of England. I know we disagreed on Jane Grey, but here I fully support your move.--[[User:Jeanne boleyn|jeanne]] ([[User talk:Jeanne boleyn|talk]]) 06:28, 23 December 2008 (UTC)
:::I suppose you mean ''Matilda of England''? ''Queen Matilda of England'' would make no sense for two reasons: 1) she herself never used that title; 2) it would create inconsistency with other monarchs of England (if she is to be put among them). I do not object moving this article to ''Matilda of England'', as she was (unlike Lady Jane Grey) daughter of an English monarch. We should not let our POV affect the article's neutrality. I would be thrilled if all the scholars agree that she was the rightful monarch, but until such thing happens, our opinion means nothing and we cannot claim that she was a monarch when scholars dispute her status. We have no right to fill the articles with our POV and we don't have right to do original research. Wikipedia is not supposed to publish original thought. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 10:02, 23 December 2008 (UTC)

Part of the problem here is that under the later-developed doctrine of the succession to the Crown of England, Matilda would clearly have qualified as the legitimate Monarch, unlike in France, where the so-called Salic Law excluded females from the line of succession.  But in the 12th century these doctrines were still fluid, so there was scope for genuine disagreement and uncertainty.  It is impossible to say that Matilda was or was not the de jure Monarch at a time when the law of succession had not been firmly settled.  When that law *was* settled in the 14th century, partly as a consequence of the English claim to the Crown of France, it was necessary to maintain the legal fiction that the law had always permitted a female succession, so that Matilda was the rightful Monarch and Stephen a usurper.[[Special:Contributions/86.135.4.52|86.135.4.52]] ([[User talk:86.135.4.52|talk]]) 22:50, 4 December 2014 (UTC)

==Second Marriage to ....==

Second Marriage to Geoffery reads like it is her second marriage to the same man. I recommend changing it simply to ''Marriage to Geoffery of Anjou.'' [[User:Drachenfyre|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;'''''♦Drachenfyre♦'''''&lt;/font&gt;]]·&lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Drachenfyre|Talk]]&lt;/small&gt; 07:00, 13 December 2008 (UTC)

==Page move==
I have restored this article to its title prior to the highly controversial move of 30 November.  I have protected it to allow for a debate to take place on the title.  If you wish to rename it, please follow the procedure described in paragraph 3 of [[Wikipedia:Requested moves]]. [[User:Deb|Deb]] ([[User talk:Deb|talk]]) 19:03, 22 December 2008 (UTC)
:Why have you done this knowone has disputed the name of the article. If you had an issue then you should have made your views known on the talk page first. You are abusing your positison as an admin to prevent anyone reverting the page back to how it was before you moved the page as would be standard procedure. [[User:The Quill|The Quill]] ([[User talk:The Quill|talk]]) 19:07, 22 December 2008 (UTC)
::I approve the move back to common usage:Empress Mathilda. The Quill's reocurse is [[WP:RM]]; but I shall oppose the request. [[User:Pmanderson|Septentrionalis]] &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Pmanderson|PMAnderson]]&lt;/small&gt; 19:38, 29 December 2008 (UTC)
:I tend to favor Matilda of England also, given that she was designated by her father and was ratified by the nobles as his successor, she was Queen by hereditary and civil right, though England itself was occupied by a usurper. Using the name of the artical as ''Empress Matilda'' is more akin to using ''Richard the Lionheart'' for that artical, rather then [[Richard I of England]]. [[User:Drachenfyre|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;'''''♦Drachenfyre♦'''''&lt;/font&gt;]]·&lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Drachenfyre|Talk]]&lt;/small&gt; 09:51, 15 January 2009 (UTC)
:: The thing is, that in the scholarly literature she's usually known as the Empress Matilda, to distinquish her from her mother and various other relatives who were also Matilda's. [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 14:20, 15 January 2009 (UTC)

:::She isn't known as Empress Matilda to distinguish her but because she threatened people if they didin't use the word Empress even though she wasn't actually am Empress she was never crowned! 19:33, 15 January 2009 (UTC)

::::She threatened people? Oh, please. She was a princess married to an emperor - therefore an empress. Coronation represents recognition of a person's right to rule. Matilda was merely an empress consort and couldn't rule as such, therefore coronation was neccessary. However, one of the factors that make her status as a monarch of England disputable is the lack of coronation. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 19:40, 15 January 2009 (UTC)

== Æðelic ==

The [[Anglo-Saxon Chronicle]] entry for 1127, the only time it gives a name to Matilda / Maud / The Empress, calls her '''Æðelic'''.  Æðelic was presumably her name amongst the English, and Matilda her name amongst the French, just as her mother had been Eadgyð in Scotland but suddenly had to be Matilda at the Norman court.

[[User:Howard Alexander|Howard Alexander]] ([[User talk:Howard Alexander|talk]]) 21:57, 12 June 2009 (UTC)
:That's interesting. Do you have a source? [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 22:05, 12 June 2009 (UTC)

::The actual text, from the [[Laud Chronicle]] is:
::&lt;Blockquote&gt;Ðis gear heald se kyng Heanri his hird æt Cristes mæsse on Windlesoure. Þær wæs se Scotte kyng Dauid. 7 eall ða heaued læred 7 læuued þæt wæs on Engleland. 7 þær he let sweren ercebiscopes 7 biscopes 7 abbotes 7 eorles 7 ealle þa ðeines ða þær wæron his dohter Æðelic Englaland 7 Normandi to hande æfter his dæi. þe ær wæs þes Caseres wif of Sexlande&lt;/Blockquote&gt;
::The latter section reads (quickly word for word translated) &quot;''and there he made swear archbishops and bishops and abbots and earls and all the thanes (barons) who were there, his daughter Æðelic England and Normandy to hand after his day, who before was the Emperor of Germany's wife''&quot;
::[[User:Howard Alexander|Howard Alexander]] ([[User talk:Howard Alexander|talk]]) 21:27, 13 June 2009 (UTC)
:::I suspect that the similarity of &quot;Æðelic&quot; to Aetheling/Adelin is too great to be coincidental. [[User:DrKiernan|DrKiernan]] ([[User talk:DrKiernan|talk]]) 12:49, 16 April 2014 (UTC)

== A queen regnant? A successor of Henry I? ==

I've reverted PatGallacher's edit so that we can discuss it. Matilda never took the title of queen of England. She planned to do so after coronation, as was customary at the time and meanwhile she used the title ''Lady of the English'' (her grandsons were styled ''Lord of England/the English'' until their coronations), so I am not sure that it is appropriate to put her into [[:Category:Queens regnant of England]] (she simply wasn't a queen of England). Matilda could be regarded as a monarch for several months in 1141, from the moment she deposed her crowned cousin until the moment she was deposed - thus, if she was a legitimate monarch, she succeeded Stephen (not Henry I) and was succeeded by Stephen. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 14:51, 18 September 2009 (UTC)
::If she had succeeded in her campaign,  she would have been regarded as having succeeded her father Henry I, not her cousin the usurper Stephen.  Just as Charles II regarded himself as having succeeded his father Charles I, not Cromwell.[[User:Eregli bob|Eregli bob]] ([[User talk:Eregli bob|talk]]) 07:51, 25 November 2012 (UTC)
:I havent read Maude's bio in a long while, but wasn't she able to assert her control in Normandy even after 1141? So while Stephan ruled in England Maude ruled in Normandy?[[User:Drachenfyre|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;'''''♦Drachenfyre♦'''''&lt;/font&gt;]]·&lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Drachenfyre|Talk]]&lt;/small&gt; 18:45, 18 September 2009 (UTC)
::Correction to myself, it seems after 1141 she stayed in England until 1148, when she returned to Anjou, and according to the current text of the artical, Geoffery of Anjou conqured Normandy in 1148 and gave it to their son Henry II to rule over. But I could swear that I had read she was administering Normandy by right herself. I'll have to research that point.[[User:Drachenfyre|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;'''''♦Drachenfyre♦'''''&lt;/font&gt;]]·&lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Drachenfyre|Talk]]&lt;/small&gt; 18:50, 18 September 2009 (UTC)
::: As I recall, Geoffrey always held that he'd conquered Normanday, not that it'd passed to her by sucession necessarily. But I'm on the road, and not where I can get to books. But I do agree with Surtsicna that calling her a queen of England is not correct, especially as she never claimed the title herself. [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 19:16, 18 September 2009 (UTC)

==Dynasty==

Currently Maude is tagged to the Plantagent dynasty, shouldn't she instead be tagged to the Norman dynasty?[[User:Drachenfyre|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;'''''♦Drachenfyre♦'''''&lt;/font&gt;]]·&lt;small&gt;[[User_talk:Drachenfyre|Talk]]&lt;/small&gt; 12:01, 15 November 2009 (UTC)

Hm. Yes, daughter of a Norman, but mother of a Plantegenet, so probably Norman.--[[User:Harkey Lodger|Harkey]] ([[User talk:Harkey Lodger|talk]]) 12:10, 15 November 2009 (UTC)

== Baptised as Adelaide? ==

I was browsing thepeerage.com when I noticed that it claims that Matilda was baptised as Adelaide. A quick Google Book Search shows that there are secondary sources which confirm this claim. For example, [http://books.google.com/books?ei=J0JnS_G2MZWqzgTildGODQ&amp;cd=1&amp;id=p5E4AAAAMAAJ&amp;dq=empress+Matilda+Henry+I+baptized+Adelaide&amp;q=%22baptised+as+Adelaide%22 The Angevin empire: or The three reigns of Henry II, Richard I, and John (A.D. 1154-1216)] claims that she was &quot;baptised as Adelaide&quot; and that she changed her name to Matilda when she married the Emperor. This is an important information, if true. Does anyone have anything against including this information? [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 21:10, 1 February 2010 (UTC)
: Well, Chibnall says &quot;Nothing is known of Matilda's childhood and early education...&quot; (p. 9) Nor does Chibnall in ''The Empress Matilda'' give a secure birth date. Ramsey's writing in 1903, and tracing his reasoning to [http://books.google.com/books?id=vSwLAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA267 Foundations Volume II p. 267] I see he's basing it on [[John of Hexham]], who is not considered a very reliable source. I'd go with Chibnall, personally, who does not mention any such &quot;fact&quot;. [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 22:21, 1 February 2010 (UTC)
::You are right, her biographer is certainly more reliable than a historian who merely mentions her. --[[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 22:28, 1 February 2010 (UTC)
::: Just to be doubly safe, I checked the account of Matilda's marriage to Henry in Hollister's ''Henry I'', and nothing is mentioned there about her changing her name. Hollister consistently calls her Maud, which is his way of distinquishing her from her mother Matilda, her grandmother Matilda... and all the OTHER Matlidas... [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 22:35, 1 February 2010 (UTC)
:::: Strikes me she is more likely to be called Adelaide after the death of Adelin rather than before. [[User:DrKiernan|DrKiernan]] ([[User talk:DrKiernan|talk]]) 12:49, 16 April 2014 (UTC)

== Empress ==
I have fact-tagged this :
&lt;blockquote&gt;Despite being popularly known as &quot;Empress&quot; from her first marriage, Matilda's right to the title was dubious. She was never crowned Holy Roman Empress by a legitimate Pope  — which ceremony was normally required to achieve the title; although, in later years she encouraged chroniclers to believe she had been crowned by the Pope.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br&gt;I'm skeptical that such a long string of claims can actually be supported.[[User:Wjhonson|Wjhonson]] ([[User talk:Wjhonson|talk]]) 13:42, 6 October 2010 (UTC)
:I am sure I read that somewhere so it's not OR. I'll try to find the reference. Anyway, [http://books.google.com/books?id=GreHiInDx24C&amp;pg=PA186&amp;dq=Matilda+Empress+crowned+queen+of+the+romans+chronicles&amp;hl=bs&amp;ei=bICsTKeEPOeP4ga7kr32Bw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCIQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=Matilda%20Empress%20crowned%20queen%20of%20the%20romans%20chronicles&amp;f=false rhis] might be interesting.  [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 14:28, 6 October 2010 (UTC)
:A wife takes her husband's titles, surely?  Her husband was emperor (crowned by the pope and everything), so she was empress.  Hell, even some actual emperors were not crowned by the Pope himself, and are still considered emperors.  Henry VII and Charles IV were both crowned by cardinals; Louis IV was crowned by Sciarra Colonna, the &quot;captain of the Roman People&quot;; Henry IV was crowned by an anti-pope.  [[User:John K|john k]] ([[User talk:John K|talk]]) 15:30, 6 October 2010 (UTC)
::If I recall correctly, the other book I was referring to claims that she was not crowned empress at all. Apparently, she was crowned Queen of the Romans ''before'' her marriage and used only that title on her seals though she preferred the imperial title in her charters. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 15:41, 6 October 2010 (UTC)

== Empress or Countess ==

wouldn't the fact that she married a count make her a countess, not empress?[[User:ZFT|ZFT]] ([[User talk:ZFT|talk]]) 03:49, 17 August 2011 (UTC)
:She claimed the title of Empress from her first marriage to the Holy Roman Emperor; she then married a count second time around. [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 06:38, 17 August 2011 (UTC)
::Empress is rather more grand; doubtless why she claimed it. -- cheers, [[User:Michael C Price|Michael C. Price]] &lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Michael C Price|talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 07:59, 17 August 2011 (UTC)

==Removal of grandparents==
I don't care much (either) for ancestors or descendants that couldn't have known the person about whom the biography is constructed, but wouldn't some of those removed been alive when she was born? [[User:Student7|Student7]] ([[User talk:Student7|talk]]) 16:13, 28 November 2012 (UTC)

== Reigning Duchess of Normandy ==

The current article seem to say, as far as I understand, that she was reigning duchess of the Duchy of Normandy jointly with her spouse from 1144 until 1149. Is this correct? If so, then should she not have an sucessionbox which states this, and should she not also be included in the List of rulers of the [[Duke of Normandy]]? It should also be stated exactly which years she ruled Normandy in the absence of her son. --[[User:Aciram|Aciram]] ([[User talk:Aciram|talk]]) 12:29, 27 February 2013 (UTC)
:I would like to see a source that says that. It is my understanding that Geoffrey became duke of Normandy by conquest and that Matilda was only duchess as his spouse. I doubt she was even the duchy's ''de iure'' ruler. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 15:42, 27 February 2013 (UTC)
::It's unclear. Looking back through Chibnall's biography of Matilda, there is definite uncertainty on what Henry decreed on his death - in particular, whether he declared that Matilda and Geoffrey should rule jointly in England and Normandy, or just Matilda, or if he preferred Stephen. Matilda titled herself &quot;empress&quot;, rather than countess or duchess, and occasionally &quot;daughter of the king of the English&quot; or, post-1141, &quot;Lady of the English&quot;. Geoffrey begins to call himself &quot;Duke of Normandy&quot; after Jan 1144. Later, Matilda issues joint charters in Normandy with Henry, entitling themselves &quot;the Empress Matilda, daughter of King Henry, and Henry, her son the Duke of Normandy&quot;. But I can't see anywhere where she calls herself the duchess - probably because as an Empress, she didn't feel she needed to. [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 20:32, 27 February 2013 (UTC)
:::Well, the issue is not so much the title so much as the position as such, that is to say: whether she was in fact formally and juridicially joint co-regent with her spouse in Normandy--[[User:Aciram|Aciram]] ([[User talk:Aciram|talk]]) 22:52, 28 February 2013 (UTC)
::::It's still not a question that's easy to answer. 12th century titles weren't as ordered and structured as in later centuries, and there wasn't a formal process for determining dukes and duchesses etc. Acts of homage, on occasion, gave an element of formality, as did the occasional Papal ruling, but I suspect the idea of someone being legally declared a joint co-regent would have quite alien. Geoffrey started to act as duke when he took over the capital, and then signed off charters etc. with that title; there aren't any primary records that I know of where anyone confirmed Matilda's status in the way one might a modern ruler. Modern historians don't typically talk about her as being a duchess of Normandy, if that helps at all. [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 20:48, 1 March 2013 (UTC)

== Expansion... ==

I've given the article a bit of an expansion, and I think everything should now be backed by current, high quality academic sources. I've reused some edited material from [[the Anarchy]] and [[Stephen of England]] articles. It will probably need a decent copyedit. [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 11:56, 24 December 2013 (UTC)

{{Talk:Empress Matilda/GA1}}

== Was William Adelin married to Matilda of Anjou? ==

In ''Marriage to Geoffrey of Anjou'', it is is said that [[William Adelin]] was due to marry [[Matilda of Anjou]]. The articles about the two of them state that they were betrothed in 1113 and that they did actually marry, each citing a different source but the same date and place - June 1119 in Lisieux. There is a slight inconsistency here. Wonderful article, by the way. I have been waiting to read up on Matilda for a long time. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 09:57, 22 January 2014 (UTC)
:My mistake - have checked back, and they had married shortly before his death. Will amend and reference in a moment... Thanks for the copyedit and the family tree, btw - looks good! [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 16:14, 22 January 2014 (UTC)

== Citation format... ==

Kiernan, I've reverted, as the webpage citation of the ODNB was cited differently as its an electronic source (in this a webpage) rather than a written book or article. There's only only webpage cited in the article, so it stands out, but its similar to the approach used on other monarch articles in this period.

Thanks for sorting the succession box, btw! [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 11:26, 8 April 2014 (UTC)
:NB - Kiernan, I'm just about to catch a flight, so if I don't reply to any comments until tomorrow, that's not me being rude! [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 12:02, 8 April 2014 (UTC)
::I never considered you rude! Quite the contrary in fact. [[User:DrKiernan|DrKiernan]] ([[User talk:DrKiernan|talk]]) 12:49, 16 April 2014 (UTC)

== Seal ==

[[File:Matilda.JPG|thumb|Engraving]][[File:MatyldaAnglie.jpg|thumb|Photograph]] There's an engraving of the seal that provides a clearer picture if you're interested in swapping out the photo of the original. [[User:DrKiernan|DrKiernan]] ([[User talk:DrKiernan|talk]]) 16:53, 8 April 2014 (UTC)
:Thanks Kiernan. It's certainly clearer, although I'm not sure how accurate the engraving is (and I will admit to a fondness for the original old seals!). Will give it a think - what do you reckon, though, any preference? [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 15:27, 9 April 2014 (UTC)
::No; I'm not advocating one or other, merely offering a choice! [[User:DrKiernan|DrKiernan]] ([[User talk:DrKiernan|talk]]) 12:49, 16 April 2014 (UTC)

== Picture ==

Is [[:File:Matylda.jpg|File:Matylda.jpg]] really depicting the subject of this article? Since it comes from the [[Gospels of Henry the Lion]], I feel it would make more sense if it were a depiction of his wife [[Matilda of England, Duchess of Saxony]] (a granddaughter of the Empress, actually). This picture was cropped from [[:File:Gospels1.jpg|this page of the Gospels]], which is not clearly described on Commons (a curse on people who do not label their pictures adequately!), but according to [[:fr:Évangéliaire d'Henri le Lion|the French Wikipedia]], it is indeed a portrayal of Henry the Lion and his wife being led to the Virgin Mary by SS. Blaise and Ægidius. [[User:Ælfgar|Ælfgar]] ([[User talk:Ælfgar|talk]]) 02:28, 29 June 2014 (UTC)

== She captured Stephen of Blois? ==

Noticed this article from the Featured Article of the Day.
Shouldn't the statement that &quot;She captured Stephen at the Battle of Lincoln&quot; instead say: &quot;Her forces captured Stephen at the Battle of Lincoln&quot;?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Acefox|Acefox]] ([[User talk:Acefox|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Acefox|contribs]]) 01:51, 2 July 2014 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Recent dispute ==

I have been trying to make some really inoffensive, indeed anodyne changes to this page, and I am being repeatedly thwarted by two users. One of them, SagaciousPhil, has just given me a &quot;warning&quot; threatening dire things if I dare to make any changes to the page. I think this is both excessive and mindless, and very far from sagacious. 

In particular, I have been told to seek 'consensus' on this page or else seek 'dispute resolution.' It is my contention that the changes I have sought to make do not give rise to any dispute or &quot;warring.&quot; Indeed my changes are most moderate and, in the real world, utterly non-controversial. If the sagacious guy named Phil has discerned a dispute, he should state what that dispute is, based on the content of what I have changed. If not, he should restore what I had written.  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/59.182.175.195|59.182.175.195]] ([[User talk:59.182.175.195|talk]]) 19:08, 9 July 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Hi 59.182.175.195. I am not in any way involved in this dispute, but I am sorry that you feel threatened for making your attempted improvements. I think the concern is that you are adding additional information in the middle of content that is cited to a particular source, and your information is not directly supported by those sources. As a result, unsourced content is being mixed with sourced content, and this is confusing for people who might try to read those sources for more information. This article is a [[WP:FA|featured article]]—FAs are the highest-quality articles on this website and go through a rigorous screening process. Therefore, to maintain FA quality, it is necessary that the clarity and verifiability of these articles be preserved. Do feel free to ask me any questions that you may have, and I appreciate your good-faith efforts to improve Wikipedia. [[User:Biblioworm|Biblio]] ([[User_talk:Biblioworm#top|talk]]) &lt;small&gt;[[Wikipedia:WikiProject Reforming Wikipedia|WikiProject Reforming Wikipedia.]]&lt;/small&gt; 19:52, 9 July 2016 (UTC)
{{collapse top|Hatting [[WP:TALK|off-topic opinion discussion]] which I started. Apologies for discussing this at an inappropriate venue. [[User:Biblioworm|Biblio]] ([[User_talk:Biblioworm#top|talk]]) &lt;small&gt;[[Wikipedia:WikiProject Reforming Wikipedia|WikiProject Reforming Wikipedia.]]&lt;/small&gt; 02:13, 13 July 2016 (UTC)}}
:To the experienced editors, please try not to discourage or frighten new editors who are simply trying to improve articles [[WP:AGF|in good faith]]. We cannot reasonably expect them to be familiar with our extensive web of content policies—is it not true that none of us were when we started here? It is better to inform them so that they can improve their editing. [[User:Biblioworm|Biblio]] ([[User_talk:Biblioworm#top|talk]]) &lt;small&gt;[[Wikipedia:WikiProject Reforming Wikipedia|WikiProject Reforming Wikipedia.]]&lt;/small&gt; 19:52, 9 July 2016 (UTC)
:: Biblio - did you actually read the edit sumaries? I don't see how they could possibly be considered frightening or threatening. An edit warring notice is standard procedure when someone continues to edit war something into an article. It was the standard template, that's all. No additional threats/statements/whatever were issued with it. And, frankly, source integrity is very very important everywhere on Wikipedia - adding information that is not in a supported citation is a big deal. It isn't something we should encourage at all, whether or not the article is an FA or not. [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 20:15, 9 July 2016 (UTC)
:::I realize that adding unsourced information is a big deal, and I support high sourcing standards for our recognized content and our articles in general. I have personally applied high standards as well, having been extremely careful to meticulously source all articles I have worked on (four of which are GAs). My comment about &quot;discourag[ing] or frigten[ing]&quot; new editors was in reference to the template on the IP's talk page. It is indeed the standard template. But if I were a new user, I would be terribly frightened by a red &quot;STOP!&quot; hand attached to a bolded notice that I am in danger of being blocked, especially when I was just trying to improve an article and didn't understand why I was being continually reverted. I'm not trying to blame anyone, because I would have used the same templates in the past. But when dealing with new editors who are just trying to improve an article in good faith, I eventually concluded that it is better to calmly explain our policies to them instead of just posting templates. To us they may not look frightening at all, because we are so used to them, but they must be very frightening to new users who were just trying to help. We should reduce our use of imposing boilerplate templates and instead try to help good-faith new users become better editors. [[User:Biblioworm|Biblio]] ([[User_talk:Biblioworm#top|talk]]) &lt;small&gt;[[Wikipedia:WikiProject Reforming Wikipedia|WikiProject Reforming Wikipedia.]]&lt;/small&gt; 22:49, 9 July 2016 (UTC)
::::Then take your complaint to the editors of these templates. You've written four GAs? Congratulations! I lost count some time ago. [[User:Eric Corbett| &lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;font-weight:900; color:green;&quot;&gt;Eric&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Eric Corbett|&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;font-weight:500;color: green;&quot;&gt;Corbett&lt;/span&gt;]] 19:35, 11 July 2016 (UTC)
::::... although I am able to check, and it appears to be thirty-two. Now stop taking the piss. [[User:Eric Corbett| &lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;font-weight:900; color:green;&quot;&gt;Eric&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Eric Corbett|&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;font-weight:500;color: green;&quot;&gt;Corbett&lt;/span&gt;]] 19:41, 11 July 2016 (UTC)
:::::Eric, my intention is not to start a dispute with you or anyone else. I was simply recommending that we give friendly advice to new editors rather than place blaring, pre-packaged templates on their talk page. And as I said, I would have used those templates myself until recently. Obviously, I cannot do anything if someone chooses to continue using the standard templates—I have no right to impose my will on others. But I do have a right to voice my concerns about them and try to have them improved, just as you have a right to support them.  And as for your many GAs and FAs, I congratulate you as well—I do not deny that you and many others can claim far more recognized content than I can. I have much respect for prolific content creation. My only point in citing my four GAs was to show that I personally take much care to source my writing. In any case, the IP has not returned, so there is no longer any need to continue this thread. [[User:Biblioworm|Biblio]] ([[User_talk:Biblioworm#top|talk]]) &lt;small&gt;[[Wikipedia:WikiProject Reforming Wikipedia|WikiProject Reforming Wikipedia.]]&lt;/small&gt; 20:02, 11 July 2016 (UTC)
::::::If you want to deal with new editors who wreck articles, in a more gentle way, then maybe the Village Pump is the place to have that discussion. [[User:Eric Corbett| &lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;font-weight:900; color:green;&quot;&gt;Eric&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Eric Corbett|&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;font-weight:500;color: green;&quot;&gt;Corbett&lt;/span&gt;]] 20:27, 11 July 2016 (UTC)
:::::::To make my position clear, I am proposing &quot;more gentle&quot; treatment for new editors (obviously not including blatant vandals) who are merely unaware of our policies, as all of us were when we started editing. Of course, that emphatically does not mean that we should permit poorly formatted or unsourced content to ''remain'' at the expense of readers. In fact, I fully support increased quality standards and safeguards, such as expanded PC protection for articles of high quality or importance. But I am simply suggesting that it is best to calmly inform such editors of our policies and quality expectations before making use of standard warnings, etc.—as in other contexts, it is possible that simply informing someone will make them more productive, which would be good for everyone. However, it is obviously a completely different matter if someone rejects the information and continues to disturb article quality even ''after'' being told of the applicable policies. [[User:Biblioworm|Biblio]] ([[User_talk:Biblioworm#top|talk]]) &lt;small&gt;[[Wikipedia:WikiProject Reforming Wikipedia|WikiProject Reforming Wikipedia.]]&lt;/small&gt; 20:58, 12 July 2016 (UTC)
{{collapse bottom}}</text>
      <sha1>6104f3l9wz56ee4bmf4y6gqs4qpt3qk</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
