<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Ian Fleming</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>432770</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745583594</id>
      <parentid>745526611</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-22T00:45:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lowercase sigmabot III</username>
        <id>17518500</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Archiving 1 discussion(s) to [[Talk:Ian Fleming/Archive 4]]) (bot</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22103">{{talkheader}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=01:10, 17 December 2011 (UTC)
|action1link=Talk:Ian Fleming/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=466197780

|action2=PR
|action2date=09:43, 17 May 2012
|action2link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Ian Fleming/archive1
|action2result=reviewed
|action2oldid=492991337

|action3=FAC
|action3date=12:44, 26 July 2012
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Ian Fleming/archive1
|action3result=not promoted
|action3oldid=504176301

|action4=WAR
|action4date=09:07, 14 September 2012 (UTC)
|action4link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/Ian Fleming
|action4result=approved
|action4oldid=512344373

|action5=FAC
|action5date=18:54, 20 September 2012
|action5link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Ian Fleming/archive2
|action5result=promoted
|action5oldid=513695345

|topic=literature
|currentstatus=FA
|maindate=October 23, 2012}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Biography|living=no|class=FA|a&amp;e-work-group=yes|a&amp;e-priority=high|military-work-group=yes|military-priority=low|listas=Fleming, Ian}}
{{WikiProject Caribbean|class=FA|importance=low|Jamaica=yes|Jamaica-importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Children's literature|class=FA|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject literature|class=FA|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject England|class=FA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject James Bond|class=FA|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=FA|A-Class=pass|Biography=y|British=y|WWII=Y}}
{{WP1.0|v0.7=pass|class=FA|category=Langlit|importance=ZZ}}}}
{{Outline of knowledge coverage|James Bond}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 4
|minthreadsleft = 4
|minthreadstoarchive = 1
|algo = old(30d)
|archive = Talk:Ian Fleming/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{WikiProject Guild of Copy Editors}}
{{Archives |search=yes |bot=MiszaBot I |age=1 |units=month |index=/Archive index }}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn 
|target=/Archive index |mask=/Archive &lt;#&gt; |leading_zeros=0 |indexhere=yes 
}}

== Knighthoods ==

Was Ian Fleming ever offered a knighthood, or other British honours? Did he turn them down?  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/118.211.63.27|118.211.63.27]] ([[User talk:118.211.63.27|talk]]) 13:51, 12 November 2015 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:No, he wasn't offered any. - [[User:SchroCat|SchroCat]] ([[User talk:SchroCat|talk]]) 13:56, 12 November 2015 (UTC)

== Sanitisation ==

For a featured article, which by definition represents the very pinnacle of thoroughness and exhaustive effort, there is literally nothing mentioned about Fleming's sexual predilections (though I note with great interest the epic battles being fought over the placing of full stops). Is this article being deliberately sanitised?

== Oh no - not the infobox debate again! ==

I was reading one of the hypothetical questions in editor [[User: Oshwah]]'s request for adminship and came across a not-so hypothetical Ian Fleming infobox scenario. Question 4 on [[https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Ian_Fleming&amp;oldid=561331674]] asked what the nominee would do in the event of an infobox battle.  Curious, I went to this article, and saw that just like the scenario described, there's no infobox.

The Ian Fleming article's talk archive_1 [[https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Ian_Fleming/Archive_1#Infobox]] shows a long and bitter discussion between two camps, about whether the long standing infobox should be removed or not.  The infobox existed, as it does in the vast majority of articles about people, and its removal by an anti-infobox editor generated the controversy.  You can save time and skip to the resolution at the bottom where it is decided that the infobox will stay, but as a compromise perhaps some parameters might be weeded out.  (How to do this is debatable - you can't change the template for one article.  You either include the info in the fields or you don't.)  The July 2012 request to archive the discussion summed it up.[[https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Ian_Fleming/Archive_2#Request_to_archive]]

The pro and anti-infobox camps face this issue quite a bit.  Another case Oshwah found in his answer [[https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Arbitration/Requests/Case/Infoboxes#Use_of_infoboxes]] ruled that &quot;The use of infoboxes is neither required nor prohibited for any article by site policies or guidelines. Whether to include an infobox, which infobox to include, and which parts of the infobox to use, is determined through discussion and consensus among the editors at each individual article.&quot;  This statement passed 10 to 0 at 00:12, 11 September 2013.

Going back to Ian Fleming, the Man With The No Infobox, it looks like the result of the discussion and consensus back in July 2012 was to keep the infobox, and so it stayed until July 1, 2013.  At that point, [[User:SchroCat]] changed the infobox to make it collapsible, and in an uncharacteristic move (for him) for a non-revert edit, left no edit summary.[[https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Ian_Fleming&amp;diff=next&amp;oldid=561331674]]  The first complaints and reverts of the collapsible infobox started shortly thereafter.[[https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Ian_Fleming&amp;diff=next&amp;oldid=569110655]], [[https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Ian_Fleming&amp;diff=next&amp;oldid=570893751]].  [[User: Cassianto]], one of the earlier supporters from the anti-infobox camp reverted the last one, changing the standard infobox back to a collapsible one.

On August 31, 2013, [[User:SchroCat]] posted on the talk page that he was going to ask for permission to remove the infobox.  Here's the post, and his follow up ten days later stating he was going to remove the infobox because nobody responding meant that there was consensus.[[https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Ian_Fleming/Archive_3#Is_the_collapsed_box_needed]]  On Sept. 10, 2013, with this edit [[https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Ian_Fleming&amp;diff=next&amp;oldid=571118390]], [[User:SchroCat]] removed the infobox.  He added a bold warning on top that says basically &quot;don't add the infobox because consensus was that it be removed.&quot;  The edit summary simply said &quot;per talk page&quot;, rather than &quot;removed infobox due to consensus&quot;, which might have raised a few more eyebrows and drawn the proper attention to this.   I'm in favor of the infobox myself - it's best for busy people.  Those who don't like it are wired differently, but it does have a very important use for quick fact checking.  Of greater concern is that the earlier discussion to keep the infobox was ignored.  I'm assuming good faith, but don't see how this process was in any way transparent.  How many people who like infoboxes are going to read the bottom of a really long talk page, especially a post calling the infobox a &quot;collapsed box&quot;.  Even calling it infobox in the edit summary might have gotten more interest.  This seems like a way to get around consensus, and is contrary to the principles of Wikipedia.  Since the issue will continue to come up when people see the infobox is missing, and there are very few people going to dig into this like I am, I'd like to see a permanent note of explanation on this talk page instead of just a bold warning in the article to not add an infobox.[[User:Timtempleton|Timtempleton]] ([[User talk:Timtempleton|talk]]) 01:00, 24 August 2016 (UTC)
:And? I asked if there were any objections to the removal and there were none, so it was removed. 
:In future, perhaps you could try to AGF (and you can start with any response you choose to make). Although you claim to have in the above, there is little evidence given some of the misleading and incorrect statements you've made. To come up with accusations that &quot;{{tq|This seems like a way to get around consensus}}&quot; is a shoddy and untruthful accusation, and if you had AGF in your error-strewn wall of text it would be less tedious for all concerned. Just to correct another untruth, I am not, and never have been &quot;{{tq|an anti-infobox editor}}&quot;: quite the contrary. Again, to claim that &quot;{{tq|the earlier discussion to keep the infobox was ignored}}&quot; is also untrue: if I had removed the box without posting the question you ''may'' have had a point. But I didn't. I used the talk page to,ask if anyone objected and no-one did; since then there has been no discussion on the talk page and there has been peace and quiet on the idiotbox front until now. I wonder how many of the flashmob of warriors will turn up now... – [[User:SchroCat|SchroCat]] ([[User talk:SchroCat|talk]]) 02:57, 24 August 2016 (UTC)
{{u|Timtempleton}} ← this is how you ping someone, just so you know; your little attempt failed.  As for your desire to put a Swan Vesta to yet another a can of Super Unleaded, I think it's pathetic really.  I have no desire to discuss this matter with you. '''&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:7px 7px 8px Black;&quot;&gt;[[User:Cassianto|&lt;font face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;Cassianto&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Cassianto#top|&lt;font face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;''' 07:40, 24 August 2016 (UTC)
:There seems to be a much wider debate here regarding infoboxes. Should they be allowed or not on all articles. It just seems inconsistent to allow them for some authors, like Ernest Hemingway or John Steinbeck, and then not allow them for others. Maybe they shouldn't be allowed for any. Or maybe they should only be allowed for articles on Movies, Novels, etc. It seems that there needs to be a set standard across Wikipedia regarding infoboxes, including what can and cannot be included in an infobox if they are allowed. [[User:SonOfThornhill|SonOfThornhill]] ([[User talk:SonOfThornhill|talk]]) 14:10, 24 August 2016 (UTC)
:I knew you'd see this immediately and felt no need to ping you, any more than you felt you needed to ping the dissenting editors when you removed the infobox.  Pinging {{u|Ritchie333}} since it was his post that brought this to my attention.  I posted the information and history, and came to my conclusion, but left it open for you respond.  You both did.  You disagree that you did anything without full transparency, and that I should assume good faith.  My core point still stands in need of a response.  Assuming good faith would be easier if 1) there had not already been a decisive decision on this which you agreed with and 2) you didn't wait until things died down before quietly (ie. without an edit summary) changing the infobox to collapsible, without requesting comment, in clear disregard of the long fought consensus.  I disagree with you that there is clear consensus with only a quick 10 day post with a vague title (didn't mention infobox) on the talk page, after the troubled history of this issue.  I would like to hear from anyone who reads the entire history as I did and doesn't also feel that this is not transparent.  The quick anger you show to my note and the tone will also make others think that I hit a nerve.  Nonetheless, you can restore the infobox, and post in the talk page and ask the other question - if anyone would like it to be removed. I can ping the others form the discussion and we can do this in the open.  That's a good faith act that would help me and others to assume good faith in the future.  You've done some great work on the article and we are fellow Fleming fans - let's not let this turn into a referendum on personal preferences.[[User:Timtempleton|Timtempleton]] ([[User talk:Timtempleton|talk]]) 16:25, 24 August 2016 (UTC)
::Of ''course'' there is quick anger: you have accused other editors of acting in an underhand manner. That's a lie. I have explained the steps I took, and the fact that I took an old discussion into account, which is why I posted the question about removing. Nothing in WP is set in stone, and you should read [[WP:CCC]]. You suggest that I should not have &quot;wait[ed] until things died down&quot; before posting the question: that shows an ignorance in how WP works. If I had posted sooner than a year I would have been accused of [[Wikipedia:Disruptive editing|Disruptive editing]]. The thread was appropriately named (again, if you think otherwise that's just ignorance of WP). Given the rather aggressive and insulting stance you have taken on this – on a topic you only came to through an AfC, and without knowledge or understanding, I have nothing else to say to you, except I consider you are acting in a tendentious and dishonourable manner. – [[User:SchroCat|SchroCat]] ([[User talk:SchroCat|talk]]) 17:17, 24 August 2016 (UTC)
::Related to [[User:SonOfThornhill]]'s question, whether or not to have an infobox is personal preference.  I think the busier a person is, the more they appreciate it, but I know there are two camps.  The only guideline is one that I mentioned above &quot;The use of infoboxes is neither required nor prohibited for any article by site policies or guidelines. Whether to include an infobox, which infobox to include, and which parts of the infobox to use, is determined through discussion and consensus among the editors at each individual article.&quot;  So let's discuss together to get consensus here for removing it, since the earlier decision was to keep it.[[User:Timtempleton|Timtempleton]] ([[User talk:Timtempleton|talk]]) 16:32, 24 August 2016 (UTC)
:::With millions of other articles about and in need of attention, why are you bothering this one? '''&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:7px 7px 8px Black;&quot;&gt;[[User:Cassianto|&lt;font face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;Cassianto&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Cassianto#top|&lt;font face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;''' 17:23, 24 August 2016 (UTC)
::::Also pinging {{u|Oshwah}} since he's familiar with this issue, having studied the history as part of one of the questions for his rfa proceedings.  I have not voted on his candidacy yet, and see this as an interesting opportunity to view how he would handle a real life contentious content dispute.  Note that my concerns was not addressed in the responses above, and I was essentially told to go away and edit other articles.  To answer the question as to why I'm interested - I'm in favor of an infobox on the Ian Fleming article, as I have never found a situation where an article isn't improved with one, but this goes beyond that.  The idea of Wikipedia being a democratic process where everyone can work together to build consensus has been corrupted.  A decision made with many participants was quietly overruled by a pair of editors who as it appears were unwilling to accept the ruling.  Please convince me that this is not how things also appear to others, and I will offer a public apology.  I worry that unless this is brought to light now, and resolved as a teaching moment, there's nothing to stop the editors (and indeed others down the road) from practicing the same behavior with other articles.  I'm also pinging earlier participant {{u|Jeffrw}}, who in the interest of full disclosure said he liked the infobox, to balance the discussion.  I don't think this is WP:CANVASSING because I also pinged [[User:Ritchie333]] whose opinion on this subject I don't know.[[User:Timtempleton|Timtempleton]] ([[User talk:Timtempleton|talk]]) 20:14, 24 August 2016 (UTC)
:::::If there's no infobox, and consensus is stable that there shouldn't be an infobox, don't have an infobox. I don't think the typical reader is bothered about it as much at finding any information they were looking for. [[User:Ritchie333|&lt;b style=&quot;color:#7F007F&quot;&gt;Ritchie333&lt;/b&gt;]] [[User talk:Ritchie333|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:#7F007F&quot;&gt;(talk)&lt;/sup&gt;]] [[Special:Contributions/Ritchie333|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:#7F007F&quot;&gt;(cont)&lt;/sup&gt;]] 20:18, 24 August 2016 (UTC)
::::::{{u|Timtempleton}}, your &quot;pinging&quot; of various editors, especially those who you know get excited about Infoboxes, is nothing short of [[WP:CANVASS|canvassing]]. You are coming across as a troll and your disruptive behaviour is certainly not welcome here. '''&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:7px 7px 8px Black;&quot;&gt;[[User:Cassianto|&lt;font face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;Cassianto&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Cassianto#top|&lt;font face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;''' 20:50, 24 August 2016 (UTC)
:::::&quot;{{tq|The idea of Wikipedia being a democratic process}}&quot;: again, a lack of awareness is evident here. You should read [[WP:DEM]]: &quot;Wikipedia is not a democracy&quot;. If you think pinging people who you know are going to vote a particular way, should I do it as well—just to ensure a level playing field? Any right-minded admin would take me to task for doing that. To correct what you have inaccurately summarised above: nothing was &quot;quietly overruled&quot;, despite your claims to the contrary. That would have entailed me deleting the IB without bothering to try any form of discussion. I made a valid attempt to raise the question the article talk page. No-one objected (although perhaps I should have taken a lead from your book and just pinged people I know would vote a particular way). I made the edit based on the fact that of the c.230 people who have this on their watchlist, not one of them objected to my suggestion. I can't force people to the page, or to make them comment (although if I ''had'' canvassed offline to swing the vote this conversation would never have been started). I am bemused by what &quot;behaviour&quot; you want me to stop on other articles... using the talk page to suggest changes? – [[User:SchroCat|SchroCat]] ([[User talk:SchroCat|talk]]) 21:03, 24 August 2016 (UTC)
*{{u|Timtempleton}}: I can only echo exactly what SchroCat, Cassianto and Ritchie have said and you really are not helping here. As SchroCat states, many people have this article and its talk page on their watch list so would have been fully aware of his talk page suggestion to remove the info box. No one chose to respond or object despite having ample opportunity to do so. To re-ignite this is bordering on disruptive. [[User:Sagaciousphil|&lt;span style=&quot;color: Navy&quot;&gt;SagaciousPhil&lt;/span&gt;]] - [[User Talk:Sagaciousphil|'''Chat''']] 21:16, 24 August 2016 (UTC)
::::::If I was canvassing I'd just ping people who I knew for sure agreed with me - that's only one of the three people I pinged, a minority.  I'm open to all opinions, especially if it helps me understand the other side's point. [[User:Ritchie333]] - if consensus was stable there'd be no need for a BIG BOLD WARNING at the top of the article, telling others to not add an infobox, claiming consensus.  Most people reading that note and halting mid-edit would just move on - not realizing that their instinct was right, and the original consensus was to have an infobox.  I stand behind my facts and know where you all stand as well, but it's important for this discussion to be here on the talk page.  Others curious about the lack of an infobox who go to add it and see the warning note sending them to the talk page can now understand the history and decide if there is an issue with the process or not.  Off to enjoy a martini - shaken, not stirred.[[User:Timtempleton|Timtempleton]] ([[User talk:Timtempleton|talk]]) 22:30, 24 August 2016 (UTC)
:::::::When people explain things to you, it's best to read them fully. When they provide links (like [[WP:CCC]], to explain that the &quot;consensus can change&quot;), it's worth taking the, on board and not keep going on about an &quot;original consensus&quot; that has subsequently been overtaken. See Ritchie's comment above. – [[User:SchroCat|SchroCat]] ([[User talk:SchroCat|talk]]) 23:32, 24 August 2016 (UTC)

Instead of all the snark and accusations can we discuss the issue of whether the article should have an infobox or not. I'm undecided. What are the pros and cons? [[User:SonOfThornhill|SonOfThornhill]] ([[User talk:SonOfThornhill|talk]]) 13:30, 25 August 2016 (UTC)
:Dear God, no!  Instead, [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Ian_Fleming/Archive_1#Infobox happy reading]. '''&lt;span style=&quot;text-shadow:7px 7px 8px Black;&quot;&gt;[[User:Cassianto|&lt;font face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;Cassianto&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Cassianto#top|&lt;font face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/span&gt;''' 14:51, 25 August 2016 (UTC)
::Cassianto's link sends people to a discussion which is summarized thusly &quot;All parties appear to agree that there is no consensus to remove the infobox and thus it should be retained&quot;.  SchroCat has also inadvertently weakened his own argument by focusing on how consensus can change, while he and the anti-infobox team does everything it can, including calling people trolls and asking them to leave and go edit elsewhere, in order to not have to entertain different viewpoints.  Unlike the others quoted above with public promises to not engage, I'm not going to comment any more, although I will monitor this page and read the comments in the hopes that the spirit of Wikipedia is maintained.  I think there are enough people who can figure out what's going on without my help, and this will hopefully allow the meanspiritedness to dissipate and be replaced by a discussion all editors can be proud of.[[User:Timtempleton|Timtempleton]] ([[User talk:Timtempleton|talk]]) 20:51, 25 August 2016 (UTC)
:::I have weakened nothing: I have outlined what most editors know – that nothing is ever truly set in stone and can change. A statement of our own guidelines weakens nothing. Can I also correct yet ''another'' untruth you have come out with: no-one here is &quot;anti-Infobox&quot;. I have added IBs to numerous pages, including ones I have created, as well as others. I have happily taken articles and lists through FAC and FLC and been in full agreement with the inclusion. Other articles have IBs that are disadvantageous to both article and reader, and the rather otiose box is something that isn't needed. Still, glad to hear you are taking a step back. – [[User:SchroCat|SchroCat]] ([[User talk:SchroCat|talk]]) 21:03, 25 August 2016 (UTC)

== Muriel Wright ==

On the night of the 14/15 March 1944, his girlfriend Muriel Wright was killed by a German bomb (during [[Operation Steinbock]]). Worthy of mention? It says he was devastated by her death. [[User:Dapi89|Dapi89]] ([[User talk:Dapi89|talk]]) 17:08, 21 October 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>hbptu57zh45getadwrd7vzap3an1jn3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
