<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Early life and military career of John McCain</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>16058470</id>
    <revision>
      <id>706557098</id>
      <parentid>706523434</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-02-23T23:45:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Wasted Time R</username>
        <id>269193</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Again, Wikipedia at its finest */ thanks</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="35651">{{Talk header|search=yes}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=FAC
|action1date=15:43, 5 April 2008
|action1link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Early life and military career of John McCain/archive1
|action1result=not promoted
|action1oldid=203526755
|maindate= 23 February 2016

|action2=FAC
|action2date=00:52, 12 July 2008
|action2link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Early life and military career of John McCain
|action2result=promoted
|action2oldid=225122490

|currentstatus=FA
}}

{{Subarticle|John McCain}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Aviation|class=FA|B-Class-1=yes|B-Class-2=yes|B-Class-3=yes|B-Class-4=yes|B-Class-5=yes|US=yes|Biography=yes}}
{{WikiProject Biography|living=yes|class=FA
|military-work-group=yes
|military-priority=low
|listas=McCain, John}}
{{WPMILHIST|class=FA|B-Class-1=yes|B-Class-2=yes|B-Class-3=yes|B-Class-4=yes|B-Class-5=yes|US=yes|Biography=yes}}
{{WikiProject Politics|class=FA|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Vietnam|class=FA|importance=low}}
| blp=yes
}}
{{auto archiving notice|bot=MiszaBot I|age=30|dounreplied=yes}}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn
|target=Talk:Early life and military career of John McCain/Archive index
|mask=Talk:Early life and military career of John McCain/Archive &lt;#&gt;
|leading_zeros=0
|indexhere=yes}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 140K
|counter = 2
|minthreadsleft = 10
|minthreadstoarchive = 1
|algo = old(30d)
|archive = Talk:Early life and military career of John McCain/Archive %(counter)d
}}

== Release video ==

A film of McCain being released from his captors were found in [[Sveriges Television|SVT]]'s archives. They believe that it is the only film clip existing of the release. Maybe it is notable enough to be included in the article? Here's the link [http://svt.se/svt/jsp/Crosslink.jsp?d=22584&amp;a=1243689&amp;lid=puff_1243756&amp;lpos=rubrik]. --[[User:Krm500|Krm500]] ([[User talk:Krm500|talk]]) 16:16, 11 September 2008 (UTC)

:Good find, thanks.  I've expanded the description of his actual release, since it's often recounted, and I've added the SVT article/video as an additional footnote.  [[User:Wasted Time R|Wasted Time R]] ([[User talk:Wasted Time R|talk]]) 21:21, 11 September 2008 (UTC)

== Did McCain study Latin? ==

A December 2007 editorial in the New York Times (http://www.nytimes.com/2007/12/03/opinion/03mount.html) mentioned that the majority of US Presidents have studied Latin and/or Greek, but that the frontrunners (then Guiliani, Hillary and Obama), all had not.  Does anyone know if McCain ever studied Latin?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/137.158.152.209|137.158.152.209]] ([[User talk:137.158.152.209|talk]]) 14:29, 18 September 2008 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Hmm, interesting question.  It's very likely that Latin was taught in the 1950s at [[Episcopal High School (Alexandria, Virginia)]], but whether it was required and whether McCain took it, I don't know.  I don't recall reading it in any of his biographies ...  [[User:Wasted Time R|Wasted Time R]] ([[User talk:Wasted Time R|talk]]) 21:09, 18 September 2008 (UTC)

== Jeopardy! category ==

[moved here from user talk page] &lt;br/&gt;
Hi Wasted Time R. I think you made the right decision by moving the Jeopardy! bit to the &quot;early life&quot; subarticle, but the category belongs on the BLP article. Don't you think that Category:Jeopardy! contestants should only only show articles with persons as their subjects? I mean, an &quot;early life&quot; can't be a contestant. And McCain wasn't a &quot;different person&quot; in his early life. Robert K S (talk) 04:05, 28 September 2008 (UTC)

:This is one of the unsolved difficulties of [[WP:Summary style]] with respect to biographical subjects -- where do the categories go?  I've placed this subarticle into many categories related to McCain's service in Vietnam, because this is the definitive article about that subject, and thus about McCain's belonging to those categories.  The same rationale would extend to being a ''Jeopardy!'' contestant (way cool that you found those old broadcast sheets, by the way).  Even moreso, in fact, because [[:Category:Jeopardy! contestants]] will be in constant danger of being removed from the main article, due to nothing in that article appearing to support its inclusion.  So that's my rationale for including it here.  [[User:Wasted Time R|Wasted Time R]] ([[User talk:Wasted Time R|talk]]) 13:27, 28 September 2008 (UTC)

::The above response doesn't address the issue, namely that the recategorization creates a category entry that is generically wrong (in the sense that it stashes a species into a genera in which it cannot belong).  An &quot;early life&quot; is not a &quot;contestant&quot;; going to [[:Category:Jeopardy! contestants]] one should only see articles named with the names of persons.  The hypothetical danger of category removal would seem to be easily fixable with a hidden markup tag explaining that the support can be found in the subarticle. [[User:Robert K S|Robert&amp;nbsp;K&amp;nbsp;S]] ([[User talk:Robert K S|talk]]) 15:42, 28 September 2008 (UTC)

:::Well, if you make the species/genera rigorousness the most important criteria, okay.  But of course readers who peruse [[:Category:Jeopardy! contestants]] and click on each entry to read about that person's appearance on the show and how well they did, will be stuck here.  They won't find anything at [[John McCain]].  Even if they think to look in subarticles, they won't know which one to look at.  But I won't pursue this further.  The ultimate solution for this kind of problem is adding an indexing capability to Wikipedia, so that it looks more like real books do.  Then you could look up 'Jeopardy! appearance' in the index, and it would direct you to the right place in the right (sub)article.   [[User:Wasted Time R|Wasted Time R]] ([[User talk:Wasted Time R|talk]]) 16:08, 28 September 2008 (UTC)

== Major ==

What was his major at the academy?[[Special:Contributions/69.111.73.245|69.111.73.245]] ([[User talk:69.111.73.245|talk]]) 07:05, 30 September 2008 (UTC)

:There were no majors at the Naval Academy at that time.  There was a fixed Bachelor of Science that all midshipmen took, that was heavily focused on math, science, and engineering, especially electrical engineering.  [[User:Wasted Time R|Wasted Time R]] ([[User talk:Wasted Time R|talk]]) 22:44, 1 October 2008 (UTC)

== verification wanted ==

According to John McCain, during the Cuban Missile Crisis he was [http://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/20081021/ap_on_el_pr/mccain &quot;in the cockpit, on the flight deck of the USS Enterprise, off of Cuba&quot;]. This article ('''Early life and military career of John McCain''') nor the [[John McCain]] article do not mention anything about this. Can we verify or refute what he is saying? [[User:Kingturtle|Kingturtle]] ([[User talk:Kingturtle|talk]]) 20:51, 21 October 2008 (UTC)

:This article already says &quot;McCain was made a lieutenant in June 1962,[53] and was on alert duty on Enterprise when it helped enforce the naval quarantine of Cuba during the October 1962 Cuban Missile Crisis.[59]&quot;  [[User:Wasted Time R|Wasted Time R]] ([[User talk:Wasted Time R|talk]]) 21:49, 22 October 2008 (UTC)

== Birth certificate image ==

So what exactly is the purpose of adding [[:Image:McCain Certificate of Birth.jpg]] to the article?  The caption says &quot;This is apparently McCain’s original long-form birth certificate&quot;; if it's only &quot;apparently&quot;, why are we using it?  If its inclusion is intended to cast doubt upon the statement that McCain was born in a Navy hospital in the Panama Canal Zone, but instead support the notion that he was born in a civilian hospital outside the PCZ, we need a [[WP:RS]] secondary source that says so; this image suffers from the usual [[WP:PRIMARY]] problem that we don't exactly know what it means.  If the image's inclusion is meant to support the PCZ statement, it again needs a reliable secondary source saying so.  [[User:Wasted Time R|Wasted Time R]] ([[User talk:Wasted Time R|talk]]) 02:09, 19 November 2008 (UTC)

::I came across the image and thought it would be appropriate here.  It is not intended to cast doubt on anything.  Please remove it if you like.  I don't see that it's any less appropriate than an image of his father or grandfather, but there's no problem whatsoever if you'd like to delete it.[[User:Ferrylodge|Ferrylodge]] ([[User talk:Ferrylodge|talk]]) 16:49, 19 November 2008 (UTC)

:::I've deleted it.  The problem is, you found the image from the lawsuit against McCain's presidential eligibility; as you can [http://moritzlaw.osu.edu/electionlaw/litigation/documents/McCain-Surreply-7-21-08.pdf see here], this was considered the &quot;smoking gun&quot; that proved McCain was born outside the PCZ.  As such it would conflict with our footnotes 2 and 3.  But, I haven't found any RS that confirms the image is legitimate; it might be some Rathergate-style concoction for all we know.  Even if we find out it's legitimate, we still don't know what it means; it may be that for administrative purposes, back then all naval base births were registered to Colon and Colon Hospital.  Finally, it's rare that we include birth certificate images in any of our BLPs; images of famous parents and grandparents are more common.  [[User:Wasted Time R|Wasted Time R]] ([[User talk:Wasted Time R|talk]]) 00:21, 20 November 2008 (UTC)

== Birthplace again ==

I've been hanging out at [[WP:BLPN]] lately, where there was recently a discussion again about McCain's birthplace.  It's unclear to me what the purpose of that discussion was, but I do want to point out something that was said there....

This article currently says: &quot;John Sidney McCain III was born on August 29, 1936,[1] at a United States Navy hospital[2][3][4] at Coco Solo Naval Air Station[5][6] in Panama Canal Zone, Panama....&quot; Notice that the city of &quot;Colon&quot; is not mentioned here in this article.

At [http://mccain.senate.gov/public/index.cfm?FuseAction=StudentsTeachers.FAQ McCain's official senate web site], there is this: &quot;'Where and when were you born?' 'I was born August 29, 1936 in Colon, Panama Canal Zone CoCo Solo Submarine Base'.&quot; So, it seems to me that this source should be footnoted in the present article, and I would also include the word &quot;Colon&quot; in the article text.  The purpose here is to be accurate.  It is not to suggest that McCain was born in Panamanian rather than US jurisdiction (even if he were, it is abundantly clear to me that he would have been eligible for the presidency due to the citizenship and age of his parents).  McCain says he was born in Colon so we ought to as well.  But this is no big deal as far as I'm concerned.  I just wanted to report here what I saw at BLPN.  Cheers.[[User:Anythingyouwant|Anythingyouwant]] ([[User talk:Anythingyouwant|talk]]) 10:28, 16 November 2010 (UTC) (semi-retired)

:Well, what McCain says casually in a routine Q-and-A with young students isn't necessarily definitive.  I think most people believe that the Coco Solo base was not actually within Colón but rather just near it.  That would mean McCain's statement was contradictory, although in he may have just been trying to give some idea of where Coco Solo was in general.  The sources that WP articles on McCain use, especially [http://blog.washingtonpost.com/fact-checker/2008/05/citizen_mccain.html this] and [http://voices.washingtonpost.com/fact-checker/2008/05/john_mccains_birthplace.html this] from WaPo 'Fact Checker', make a distinction between Coco Solo (true) and Colón (Internet rumor).  To say there's no distinction at all requires stronger evidence than just this one statement from McCain, and including this in the article will just further stir up the &quot;zonists&quot; (to distinguish them from the O. birthers).  Even in your semi-retired state, you should realize that would be asking for trouble ...  [[User:Wasted Time R|Wasted Time R]] ([[User talk:Wasted Time R|talk]]) 11:39, 16 November 2010 (UTC)

::I take the reference to &quot;Colon Panama&quot; to be an indication of where CoCo Solo is. Whether the base is actually within Colon city limits now or not, it's certainly ''near'' it, so a helpful reference point. However the article already refers to the Panama Canal Zone, and I can't see how to lever a reference to Colon into it without rewriting it entirely, which I'm not sure is worth the effort. [[User:Rd232|Rd232]] &lt;sup&gt;[[user talk:rd232|talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 12:06, 16 November 2010 (UTC)
:::Inserting an additional footnote would not require rewritng anything.  And WTR, maybe McCain was smoking dope, or his mother lied to him.  :-). But seriously, I think it's  &lt;s&gt;a very&lt;/s&gt; an extremely bad idea to let our editing decisions be affected by how nutcases might react, or be designed to make them seem nuttier than they really are.[[User:Anythingyouwant|Anythingyouwant]] ([[User talk:Anythingyouwant|talk]]) 16:25, 16 November 2010 (UTC)
::::The only relevance of the &quot;nutters&quot; (if we must call them that) is as a reminder that if we can't add something that's actually helpful (giving the reader more information) we're better off not complicating things. The McCain quote alone isn't really helpful - it would only be relevant in combination with a reliable source that explained the relationship between the base and the city then and now. By which time, it is however getting into &quot;who cares&quot; territory best left for the other article (natural born...) where it's discussed in some detail. If you want to actually propose something concrete, go ahead, but I just don't think it's very important. The only importance, in fact, comes in relation to the &quot;not eligible&quot; claim, for which there appears no basis in fact. If the controversy over it were prominent enough, it would justify covering it ''qua'' controversy (as part of the 08 election), but I'm not sure if it is. [[User:Rd232|Rd232]] &lt;sup&gt;[[user talk:rd232|talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 19:04, 16 November 2010 (UTC)
:::::Yes, my concrete proposal is simply to add a footnote, with no change to the text, so that readers can access McCain's statement about his birthplace at his official government website. That's all.
:::::&lt;nowiki&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://mccain.senate.gov/public/index.cfm?FuseAction=StudentsTeachers.FAQ FAQ for Students and Teachers], Official U. S. Senate Web Site of John McCain.  Accessed 2010-11-16.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/nowiki&gt;[[User:Anythingyouwant|Anythingyouwant]] ([[User talk:Anythingyouwant|talk]]) 19:23, 16 November 2010 (UTC)
::::::I just don't see adding this footnote as being helpful.  While this FAQ page is indeed part of &quot;McCain's Official U.S. Senate Web Site&quot;, that doesn't make it authoritative, and given that it isn't linked to from the McCain Senate main page, it may have gotten limited attention.  For all I know it was put together by some intern cutting and pasting from various other documents.  The statement in it that McCain played on the varsity football team in high school also contradicts this article, which uses the Alexander biography as a source to say that he played on the junior varsity football team.  The Timberg bio also has him playing on the jv team and being underweight even for that, and neither mentions him playing on the varsity football team.  Should we now add a footnote to this FAQ page for this, and let the reader ponder another contradiction?  I'd rather not.  One of the conditions of this article reaching FA status was to limit the use of ''Faith of My Fathers'' as a source to the extent possible, and to explain each use that remained in each footnote.  This FAQ page is in the same boat, only it has probably received less editorial attention.  [[User:Wasted Time R|Wasted Time R]] ([[User talk:Wasted Time R|talk]]) 12:06, 17 November 2010 (UTC)
::::::::I was a big advocate for using third-party sources wherever possible in the McCain articles, assuming they corroborate the text, but that doesn't mean that both can't be used when they each adequately support the same text, and they're consistent with each other, and the non-third-party source adds something intriguing.  But in this case you've ably questioned whether the non-third-party source is reliable.  McCain himself says that he played jv football even as a senior.[http://rncnyc2004.blogspot.com/2008/04/john-mccain-episcopal-high-school-video.html] So, I agree that we should not include the extra footnote.[[User:Anythingyouwant|Anythingyouwant]] ([[User talk:Anythingyouwant|talk]]) 14:39, 17 November 2010 (UTC)

== Again, Wikipedia at its finest ==

I congratulate [[User:Wasted Time R]] and all of the editors on this fine article.  It is clear that you have become experts on this man and I cannot think of a better or more thought out article other than [[John McCain]].  The referencing is impeccable in my view and I am proud and humbled to be a fellow Wikipedian when I read this type of article.[[User:Mugginsx|Mugginsx]] ([[User talk:Mugginsx|talk]]) 13:38, 5 April 2012 (UTC)

:Thanks again.  [[User:Wasted Time R|Wasted Time R]] ([[User talk:Wasted Time R|talk]]) 01:31, 6 April 2012 (UTC)

:: Yep, nice article. Congrats [[Special:Contributions/200.116.144.155|200.116.144.155]] ([[User talk:200.116.144.155|talk]]) 14:43, 23 February 2016 (UTC)

::: Thanks, this is one of those where I am still pleased with the result and have never regretted the time and effort put into it.  I had nothing to do with it becoming TFA but I'm glad it did.  [[User:Wasted Time R|Wasted Time R]] ([[User talk:Wasted Time R|talk]]) 23:45, 23 February 2016 (UTC)

== SURVIVORS' GUILT ==

I do not care WHO writes it or says it, including the POW THEMSELVES.  There is NO proof that one prisoner was tortured MORE than another. Unless a man was of special value to the enemy, such as cryptographer (who after Korean War were not allowed in combat) or someone who was otherwise perceived as a valuable person to exploit (such as a [[William F. Dean|General William Dean]] in Korean War) or ([[Lloyd M. Bucher|Commander Bucher]] in the Pueblo Incident) the prisoners were tortured randomly.  Conversely, you note that these men have never made statements to the effect that they were tortured '''more''' than others. See: General Dean's story, Publisher: New York : Viking Press, 1954. A psychological follow-up of former prisoners of war of the Chinese Communists : final report Author: Edgar H Schein; W E Cooley; Margaret T Singer Arlington, Va. : Reproduced by the Armed Services Technical Information Agency, [1960-62?  and many many more publications of this type.

Please do not repeat the stuff (took out unfortunate word) out in the media, or even the guilt ridden statement of prisoners who survived. It is beneath the standards of Wikipedia and everywhere else for that matter to do that.

It is not is the psychological history, it is not in the military de-briefings, it is nowhere except in the guilt stricken minds of the men who survived.  What you have is the perceptions of POWs which are not credible.
 
A person who is beated and tortured, whether it be an abused child or wife, or a prisoner of war BLOCK OUT that kind of detailed information.  If their mind did not block it out they would go mad.  It is a well known fact in the medical and psychological studies.   They have ''glimpes'' of memory and in the cases of prisoners of war virtually all have SURVIVORS GUILT, a  psychological affliction common to ALL prisoners of war and indeed many soldiers who survived when many of their friends did not.

Please do not take a featured article down with this unprovable and cruel statement.  It simply has no basis in fact in the scientific community or anywhere else for that matter even when it is said by the former prisoner of war himself and repeated by someone trying to make a buck with a sensational story.  As a relative of a former prisoner of war and a former National Librarian for American Ex-POW Organization, I appeal to your sense of honor to see this for what it is and keep it out of the article.

If nothing else it makes Wikipedia look foolish to reprint it.

If you refuse to take it out would you please clarify it with a companion statement citing the psychological studies.

Thank you. [[User:Mugginsx|Mugginsx]] ([[User talk:Mugginsx|talk]]) 10:17, 3 May 2012 (UTC)

:We had the same discussion on the John McCain main article.  You got so worked up there that I decided to let it slide, but I'm not going to do the same here, because this is the detailed article that has to be fully accurate in a military history sense.  I spent a huge amount of time here getting all the unit assignments right, the dates right, etc., and this has to be right too.  It's simply a matter of historical fact that the torture of U.S. POWs by the North Vietnamese was worse during some periods than others.  Someone taken prisoner in 1970, for example, would have had a very different experience from someone taken prisoner in 1965, because the overall treatment patterns changed significantly in late 1969.  It's also a fact that some POWs got singled out for worse treatment than others.  There are multiple good historical accounts of what happened in Vietnam POW camps that support the account given here, so the burden is on ''you'' to show sources saying that everyone in Vietnam POW camps was tortured randomly and equally.  And they have to be Vietnam War sources, not Korean War; two different wars, two different peoples, two different lengths of imprisonment, two different sets of circumstances.  [[User:Wasted Time R|Wasted Time R]] ([[User talk:Wasted Time R|talk]]) 11:28, 3 May 2012 (UTC)
::OK but then couldn't you ADD another statement which shows their memory is impaired by trauma and survivor's guilt.  Wouldn't that be fair?  I know you did good research and I would not say otherwise but in this one little area isn't it possible it was not complete that is that you did not tell the complete story (Not that it is easy to find as it is hidden away in psychlogical journals and a few books!).

::Also, while it may be true ( do not forget there were no video tapes of these interrogations) or written records, we are relying once again on the de-briefings of the individual POWs - that the techniques changed - still torture is torture.

::Yes, it is true that some were singled out - 2% were called &quot;resistors&quot; and they generally died during torture.  Some went completely and utterly mad and were killed because of the disruptions they caused.

::I am not trying to take anything away from your fine article - just asking that you add one little sentence after that one to make it completely true.  Would you consider it? 

::Also, while the torture changes, one's reaction to the mere captivity, in addition to the torture must be taken into account and one's ability to withstand torture cannot be measured by &quot;how many times&quot; they were tortured or &quot;how&quot; they were tortured.  It is much more complicated then that.  In Korea, it was found that persons who had grown up in a troubled environment were found to be to be able to resist more than other groups of men with different, perhaps, happier childhoods.  This is disputed.  I believe there was a study about Vietnam pows that showed that also to be true but one cannot rely on these studies because of the same problem.  ''The memory of the individual pow and the lack of a permanent record of the sessions.''

::Meanwhile I will look for definitive Vietnam Studies, but I do not have the access that I used to have; nevertheless I will look. That is fair to ask me to do.  Thanks [[User:Mugginsx|Mugginsx]] ([[User talk:Mugginsx|talk]]) 11:46, 3 May 2012 (UTC)

::Also, I will say again as I did before, that this article is one of the finest on Wikipedia and I congratulate [[User:Wasted Time R]] and all other editors on it. [[User:Mugginsx|Mugginsx]] ([[User talk:Mugginsx|talk]]) 12:31, 3 May 2012 (UTC)

:::There's a large body of medical literature on the after-effects of the Vietnam War POW experience (based upon their having had regular mental and physical follow-up exams every five years, I think).  For example, [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed?term=vietnam%20war%20prisoners this search here] lists some of them.  But just looking at abstracts, you can see that [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/7468825 this paper] says &quot;Data indicate a significant degree of psychiatric readjustment problems, which were greatest among POWs captured before 1969.&quot;  [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/7187219 Another paper] says &quot;the RPWs are designated Pre-69 and Post-69. The Pre-69 group had a significantly longer and harsher captivity experience.&quot;  [http://books.google.com/books?id=IGemFZmcn_AC&amp;pg=PR12 The preface of Rochester and Kiley's ''Honor Bound''] discusses the different factors that led to some POWs having a much worse experience than others:  &quot;Not every prisoner in North Vietnam, for example, encountered horrible torture or even excessive duress; for those seized late in the war, the experience, in most cases, was much less arduous than for their predecessors. Even among those in custody for the better part of the decade, there were notable variations in treatment — and performance — from one individual to another depending on where exactly he was held, the shifting character of the camps themselves, the extent of one's injuries, varying tolerances for pain and degradation, and many other factors of time, place, and personal idiosyncrasies.&quot;  The rest of the book goes on to describe just how this happened, in great detail as regards to prisoners' specific stories.  And I'm pretty sure that if you read this book, even the parts that available online at Google Books as linked above, you will realize the authors are quite serious and respectful and are not &quot;trying to make a buck with a sensational story&quot; as you claim.  So there just isn't support for your notion that there is no proof that some of the Vietnam War POWs were tortured more than others.  [[User:Wasted Time R|Wasted Time R]] ([[User talk:Wasted Time R|talk]]) 11:07, 4 May 2012 (UTC)
::::[[User:Wasted Time R|Wasted Time R]] - Just wanted you to know I am not ignoring you, I am still looking and reading. {{smiley}} [[User:Mugginsx|Mugginsx]] ([[User talk:Mugginsx|talk]]) 22:19, 4 May 2012 (UTC)
::::Studies I have read so far were done on men from 1 to 31 months of captivity or other lengths of captivity in other studies.  They are all bunched together.  They discuss types of torture and classify solitary confinement as one of the most powerful of all tortures which would suppose length of captivity in Vn experience since they were not allowed to talk for years.  They do not address the issue we have been discussing, but those studies could be used to say that the longer a man was a prisoner (in solitary as they were all in solitary (as opposed to those in group barracks such as in WWII European Theatre of Operations),  the worst shape he was, and therefore invalidate the MMPI results - your study mentioned here [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/7187219 This one].  Anyway the MMPI is not widely respected anymore by many professionals no matter what groups it is used on.   It has been shown, for instance, to be undependable with various cultures blended into the U.S.  Your other studies are more interesting. Lastly, another study talks about Viet Cong POW camps as opposed to those held by the NVA (Hanoi Hilton, etc.)  It is more definitive in that is covers reports by individual pows observation.  For instance, those held by Viet Cong in ad hoc type camps, had an extremely low survival rate. It is all very complicated and I think statistically impossible to calculate. ''Who speaks for the dead and 1,948 still unaccounted for?''  Will continue to look and read all of your material as well.  [[User:Mugginsx|Mugginsx]] ([[User talk:Mugginsx|talk]]) 22:30, 4 May 2012 (UTC)
::::Incidentally, I found some more information of McCain's time as a POW here www.publichealth.va.gov/docs/vhi/pow.pdf  Anyway, it may or may not be properly referenced for wikipedia. [[User:Mugginsx|Mugginsx]] ([[User talk:Mugginsx|talk]]) 23:05, 4 May 2012 (UTC)
:::::That piece mostly relies upon sources already used in this article, and gets the chronology confused a couple of times.  But it's mainly intended for its medical focus.  [[User:Wasted Time R|Wasted Time R]] ([[User talk:Wasted Time R|talk]]) 10:30, 5 May 2012 (UTC)
::::::Yes, I agree. The Ex-POW Organization makes some of its conclusion based on personal letters and interviews with POWs.  In some ways it might be seen the most valuable because POWs talk to other POWS no matter the war, but do not tend to tell all of their experiences to VA doctors, psychiatrists, etc.  There is a basic relunctance and distrust there.  [[User:Mugginsx|Mugginsx]] ([[User talk:Mugginsx|talk]]) 11:27, 5 May 2012 (UTC)
::::::[http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/7468825 This] is a conclusion to another study you have indicated - and shows only the conclusion rather than the actual study or the parameters of the study.  It seems to me to indicate that ''the longer a man was a pow, the greater the harm, rather than that there was a concerted effort to torture them more before 1969, it would mean to me that the fact that the men served more time in solitary, etc., as indicated in previous study, was the underlying reason.''  In other words, there was no concerted effort to be easier on the pows after 1969, it was rather, the TIME the individual spent that adversely affected them.  I think it you have made an understanable but basic misinterpretation of the '''conclusions of the study''' results which you interprete as saying that pre1969 pows were tortured more.  Again, I think, with exceptions noted by me in the beginning, this proves that the torture was random.  I hope I am explaining it clearly.  I will continue to read. [[User:Mugginsx|Mugginsx]] ([[User talk:Mugginsx|talk]]) 12:19, 5 May 2012 (UTC)
::::::MY CONCLUSION:  You state: ''Many, especially among those who had been captured earlier and imprisoned longer, endured even worse treatment than McCain.''  This statement is only true because those men captured on or before 1969 were there LONGER and IN THAT CONTEXT ONLY they suffered more.  The torture itself did NOT change after 1969 - it merely ''lasted less time'' due to the final disposition of that foul war.  ''That is what needs to be explained in that statement in an otherwise absolutely accurate and fine article.'' [[User:Mugginsx|Mugginsx]] ([[User talk:Mugginsx|talk]]) 13:03, 5 May 2012 (UTC)
:::::::That's simply not correct. Until you read Hubbell's ''P.O.W.: A Definitive History of the American Prisoner-Of-War Experience in Vietnam, 1964–1973'' and/or Rochester and Kiley's ''Honor Bound: American Prisoners of War in Southeast Asia, 1961–1973'', there's no point continuing this discussion. The discussion about the change in conditions beginning in late 1969 begins on p. 519 of Hubbell and p. 489 of Rochester &amp; Kiley. [[User:Wasted Time R|Wasted Time R]] ([[User talk:Wasted Time R|talk]]) 13:50, 5 May 2012 (UTC)
::::::::I will do so Sir.  Have some errands to run then will return. [[User:Mugginsx|Mugginsx]] ([[User talk:Mugginsx|talk]]) 14:49, 5 May 2012 (UTC)

::::::::Ok, I have read the preface and a little more of ''Honor Bound: American Prisoners of War in Southeast Asia, 1961–1973'', and will read the entire book but since you mentioned the preface it does indeed state in a sentence: pg xii beginning at line 16, ...''Nonetheless it is equally true that individual prisoners experienced a wide range of conditions and exhibited a wide range of behavior.  Not every prisoner in North Vietnam, for example, experienced horrible torture or even excess duress; for those seized late in the war, the experience, in most cases, was much less ardurous than for their predecessors.''  This would seem to indicate your statement is true, but then it goes on to say, same page no., ''Even among those is custody for over a decade there were notable variations in treatment and performance-from one individual to another depending upon where exactly he was held, the shifting character of the camps themselves, the extent of ones injuries, varying tolerances for pain and degradation and many other factors of time, place and personal idiosyncrasies.'' To me the first sentence seems to contradict the second. Then it goes on to state the men's poor memories and periods of memory loss , etc.,
::::::::It then sums up by stating it is based upon the interviews with the men. (IRemember a few lines below it states they were unable to get whatever records the Vietnmese officials claimed they had).  These same men with the poor memories and periods of memory loss who were in varying camps, i.e., VC ad hoc camps or Hanoi Hilton or others.  Obviously, it is there and you can keep it in but I think you would be hard put to find an actual POW who would agree.  These interrogators were sadist and not caring about information, though no doubt that is what they were supposed to illicit, they were just inflicting as much punishment on the most people.  If someone appeared strong, he was given more punishment, if someone appeared weak or wounded, they might cut the sessions short because they weren't really having that much fun with that one.  I will not argue with you anymore but I will always disagree with that sentence, especially after reading the information you point out.  It is almost a contradiction in terms the way the sentences are laid out.  The information totally and completely depends on the POWs themselves. This final study that you indicated [http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/7468825 here] just repeats that the longer a man served - the more he was harmed.
::::::::You are a good faith editor and I hope you know I am too.  We will have to respectfully agree to disagree on this one. [[User:Mugginsx|Mugginsx]] ([[User talk:Mugginsx|talk]]) 18:57, 5 May 2012 (UTC)

== WP:CFORK ==

I realize this was promoted to FA a while ago, but this basically seems like a giant WP:CFORK that could easily be summarized on McCain's main biography. It's well written, but I'm not sure what this offers that can't be included on McCain's article. '''[[User:SNUGGUMS|&lt;font color=&quot;454545&quot;&gt;Snuggums&lt;/font&gt;]] ([[User talk:SNUGGUMS|&lt;font color=&quot;454545&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]] / [[Special:Contributions/SNUGGUMS|&lt;font color=&quot;454545&quot;&gt;edits&lt;/font&gt;]])''' 05:21, 9 September 2014 (UTC)

:This is a detail article as part of [[WP:Summary style]].  The content of this article ''is'' summarized in the [[John McCain]] main article, but here it is presented in much more detail to more fully describe a famous part of his life and career that has been much written about.  As such it is entirely acceptable.  [[WP:CFORK]] says that the two unacceptable types of forking are unintentional duplications of content (but this subarticle is intentional and provides five times as much information as the main article) and forks designed to present a different POV (but this subarticle presents the same point of view as the main article and indeed was written by the same editors).  This is a fully acceptable article per [[WP:SPINOFF]].  [[User:Wasted Time R|Wasted Time R]] ([[User talk:Wasted Time R|talk]]) 10:18, 9 September 2014 (UTC)

::Interesting..... '''[[User:SNUGGUMS|&lt;font color=&quot;454545&quot;&gt;Snuggums&lt;/font&gt;]] ([[User talk:SNUGGUMS|&lt;font color=&quot;454545&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]] / [[Special:Contributions/SNUGGUMS|&lt;font color=&quot;454545&quot;&gt;edits&lt;/font&gt;]])''' 12:47, 9 September 2014 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>515poe98dwc0vzwy2o3wy7bhbsxenc2</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
