<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:British contribution to the Manhattan Project</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>44805487</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748101870</id>
      <parentid>748101785</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-06T10:00:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SineBot</username>
        <id>4936590</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Signing comment by [[Special:Contributions/95.150.18.150|95.150.18.150]] - &quot;/* British? */ Quote with ref&quot;</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13532">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=22:19, 29 December 2014 (UTC)
|action1link=Talk:British contribution to the Manhattan Project/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=640152292
|dykdate=8 January 2015
|dykentry= ... that four scientists who were part of the '''[[British contribution to the Manhattan Project]]''' became group leaders at the [[Los Alamos Laboratory]]?
|currentstatus=FA
|topic=Warfare
|maindate= 12 May 2016

|action2=WAR
|action2date=11:55, 30 January 2015 (UTC)
|action2link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/British contribution to the Manhattan Project
|action2result=approved
|action2oldid=644491378

|action3=FAC
|action3date=2015-05-16
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/British contribution to the Manhattan Project/archive1
|action3result=promoted
|action3oldid=661686542
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{MILHIST|class = FA|A-Class=pass|SciTech=y|Weaponry=y|British=y|WWII=y}}
{{WikiProject United Kingdom|class = FA|importance=mid}}
}}

== British ==

&lt;blockquote&gt;{{tq|James Chadwick was the head of a distinguished team of British scientists at the Los Alamos Laboratory that included Niels Bohr, Peierls, Frisch, Sir Geoffrey Taylor, James Tuck and Klaus Fuchs, who was later revealed to be a Soviet atomic spy.}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Even though Peierls, Frisch, Fuchs and Bohr fled Germany and Denmark for the United Kingdom during the war, and, in the case of the three former (I can find nothing on Bohr), gained British citizenships, it seems disingenuous to count them as &quot;British&quot; without any qualifiers. To the extent that holding a British citizenship makes someone British, they were only British because they were forced there by the war.--[[User:Anders Feder|Anders Feder]] ([[User talk:Anders Feder|talk]]) 02:47, 12 May 2016 (UTC)

:A number of the scientists left Europe and went to Britain pre-war and for the Manhattan Project the US made it a condition that only foreign scientists who were [[British subject]]s would be allowed to participate in the Project so all members of the British Mission who were not &quot;British&quot; were given British citizenship., i.e., were naturalised. Any German citizen was technically an &quot;Enemy Alien&quot; in the US and would have been arrested on arrival there by the FBI, and so, as with the other occupied countries, it was necessary them to possess British passports.

:Australian, Canadian, and other [[British Empire]] citizens were already British subjects, and so already had British passports.

:[[Leo Szilard]] and [[Edward Teller]] were not born as American citizens either, and nobody complains about them being classed as &quot;American&quot;. Neither was [[Albert Einstein]].  

:BTW, [[J. Robert Oppenheimer|Robert Oppenheimer]] stated that the British contribution was crucial and that without the British the Manhattan Project would almost certainly never have happened. And there was a properly-sourced and referenced quote of him saying so in the [[Manhattan Project]] article a number of years ago - long since removed.&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/95.145.115.114|95.145.115.114]] ([[User talk:95.145.115.114|talk]]) 09:35, 12 May 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

::Niels Bohr never became a British citizen. He remained a Dane. Otto Frisch and Rudolf Peierls not only took out British citizenship, but made Britain their home for the rest of their lives. Like Fuchs, they left Germany before the war. Only Bohr fled during the war. [[User:Hawkeye7|Hawkeye7]] ([[User talk:Hawkeye7|talk]]) 11:26, 12 May 2016 (UTC)
:::According to the [[Rudolf Peierls]] article, Peierls became UK citizen in 1940; according to the [[Otto Robert Frisch]] article, Frisch became UK citizen sometime between 1939 and 1943; according to the [[Klaus Fuchs]] article, Fuchs became UK citizen in or after 1939. Whether they &quot;left Germany before the war&quot; is completely irrelevant - merely leaving Germany makes no one British.--[[User:Anders Feder|Anders Feder]] ([[User talk:Anders Feder|talk]]) 11:56, 12 May 2016 (UTC)
::Whether British contribution was crucial is irrelevant - that isn't a question I commented on. My comment pertains solely to the four specifically named scientists whose entire lives and careers had taken place outside the UK until just two to three years before the Manhattan Project begun. I am not even saying they can't be mentioned in the article on account of their citizenship status - I'm just questioning whether it is honest and comprehensive to cast them as British without any qualifiers. They could be called &quot;naturalised British citizens&quot; and that would be enough to signal to the reader that they have another background than solely British. I just don't want to start a food fight over it in the edit box - by merely commenting on it here I have already evoked your defensive stance on the unrelated question of whether British contribution was crucial.--[[User:Anders Feder|Anders Feder]] ([[User talk:Anders Feder|talk]]) 11:42, 12 May 2016 (UTC)
::::::What would  you like to change? Perhaps we can come put an addition in the article that we can agree on? The article leans on the brilliantly sourced ''British scientists &amp; the Manhattan Project'' by Ferenc Morton Szasz. I must point out that Ralph Carlisle Smith's summary of the ''British Mission to Los Alamos'' list puts 32 members of that mission &amp; includes names like Niels &amp; Aage Bohr despite being Danish but also [[Egon Bretscher]], [[George Placzek]], [[Joseph Rotblat]].  So from a sourced point of view the article in not in the wrong. [[User:Lord Eastfarthing|Shire Lord ]] ([[User talk:Lord Eastfarthing|talk]]) 15:23, 12 May 2016 (UTC)
:::::::I suggest changing the sentence to something along the lines of: &quot;{{tq|[[James Chadwick]] was the head of a team of distinguished scientists at the [[Los Alamos Laboratory]] that included British-born Sir [[G. I. Taylor|Geoffrey Taylor]] and [[James L. Tuck|James Tuck]] as well as [[Niels Bohr]], Peierls, Frisch, and [[Klaus Fuchs]], who had all fled to the United Kingdom in the years leading up to the war.}}&quot;--[[User:Anders Feder|Anders Feder]] ([[User talk:Anders Feder|talk]]) 17:35, 12 May 2016 (UTC)
::::::::Might be better this way in reference to what I said above {{tq|As head of the British mission to [[Los Alamos Laboratory]] [[James Chadwick]] led a team of distinguished scientists that included Sir [[G. I. Taylor|Geoffrey Taylor]] and [[James L. Tuck|James Tuck]]. Also included were [[Niels Bohr]], Peierls, Frisch, and [[Klaus Fuchs]], who had all fled to the United Kingdom in the years leading up to the war.}} No need to mention where they were born. [[User:Lord Eastfarthing|Shire Lord ]] ([[User talk:Lord Eastfarthing|talk]]) 17:44, 12 May 2016 (UTC)
:::::::::I did [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=British_contribution_to_the_Manhattan_Project&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=719937504&amp;oldid=719936059 this].--[[User:Anders Feder|Anders Feder]] ([[User talk:Anders Feder|talk]]) 18:25, 12 May 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::But it's not correct. Niel Bohr fled ''during'' the war; Frisch, Peierls and Fuchs fled ''before'' the war. The latter three all jumped at the chance to become British citizens. I hope that readers will drill down and find the stories of the lesser lights like [[Joan Curran]] and [[Philip Baxter]]. I am concerned about the wording of Chadwick as the head of the British Mission to the Los Alamos Laboratory. This is correct; but he was became head of the entire British Mission, which included Peierls' team at Los Alamos, Oliphant's at Berkeley, and Cockcroft's at Montreal. I hope this comes across. [[User:Hawkeye7|Hawkeye7]] ([[User talk:Hawkeye7|talk]]) 22:48, 12 May 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::::::Oh good god is [[User talk:Hawkeye7]] going on about that factotum Baxter again? [[User:JuanRiley|Juan Riley ]] ([[User talk:JuanRiley|talk]]) 23:13, 12 May 2016 (UTC)
::::::::::::::::Well then change it to British mission of the Manhattan project? [[User:Lord Eastfarthing|Shire Lord ]] ([[User talk:Lord Eastfarthing|talk]]) 23:29, 12 May 2016 (UTC)

:::::::::::::::::Bohr didn't 'flee' Denmark before the war, he voluntarily left via Sweden ''during the war'' specifically to join the British Mission, as did his son, who were both flown out by the RAF/BOAC.  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/95.149.173.4|95.149.173.4]] ([[User talk:95.149.173.4#top|talk]]) 08:51, 10 October 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== British? ==

Sigh..there were significant British contributions to the Manhattan Project. But for example claiming Rudolf Peierls and Otto Frisch as British? Rather pathetic especially since the Maude committee did not let &quot;them&quot; know anything because they were &quot;enemy aliens&quot;. [[User:JuanRiley|Juan Riley ]] ([[User talk:JuanRiley|talk]]) 23:11, 12 May 2016 (UTC)
:They were naturalised British subjects. The point is not that they were British, but that they were part of the British Mission. [[User:Hawkeye7|Hawkeye7]] ([[User talk:Hawkeye7|talk]]) 23:26, 12 May 2016 (UTC)
::And enemy aliens? [[User:JuanRiley|Juan Riley ]] ([[User talk:JuanRiley|talk]]) 23:32, 12 May 2016 (UTC)
:::Then perhaps rename to British Mission Contribution to the Manhattan Project? [[User:JuanRiley|Juan Riley ]] ([[User talk:JuanRiley|talk]]) 23:34, 12 May 2016 (UTC)
::::The article covers the British contribution, not just the contribution of the British Mission. [[User:Hawkeye7|Hawkeye7]] ([[User talk:Hawkeye7|talk]]) 23:39, 12 May 2016 (UTC)
:::::History requires a wee bit more nuance than you seem to be able to bring to the table, Hawkeye7. [[User:JuanRiley|Juan Riley ]] ([[User talk:JuanRiley|talk]]) 23:40, 12 May 2016 (UTC)

::Actually at the time before their British naturalisation Peierls and Frisch were only &quot;enemy aliens&quot; to the US. Neither was required to obtain British citizenship for access to [[Tube Alloys]].

:: ... and the only reason there is all this arguing about all this is because of the widespread ignorance due to the US writing-out of history after World War II the British and Canadian contribution to the Manhattan Project and then in effect lying about it being a solely &quot;US&quot; project. Then it went back on the [[Quebec Agreement|1943 Quebec Agreement]] with the passing of the [[Atomic Energy Act of 1946|1946 MacMahon Act]], effectively forcing the UK to spend money it could little afford after the worst war in history in developing a bomb once again, this time on its own. Which it successfully did. And it didn't need anyone else's help, not did it need to &quot;steal secrets&quot; from someone else, to do it.

::British participants in both Tube Alloys and the Manhattan Projects were banned by the [[Official Secrets Act]] from divulging any information relating to these areas of work until around 1973. After that time information started to become available to those who knew where to look for it. That was presumably why the British scientists involved earlier in the Manhattan Project didn't give a loud collective equivalent of &quot;WTF!&quot; on hearing American reporting of its history. To be fair to many of the Americans involved most would have been aware that British participants would have been governed by the UK's own secrecy laws and so would have honoured the Official Secrets Act under reciprocal arrangements, and not mentioned their involvement without express permission from the UK's representatives in Washington.

::And BTW, the &quot;bomb&quot; wasn't developed for dropping on Japan. It was developed for dropping on Germany. And if the war in Europe hadn't ended in May 1945, it would have been.  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/95.145.115.114|95.145.115.114]] ([[User talk:95.145.115.114|talk]]) 10:03, 13 May 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:::&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;The United States would not, I think, have worked on the atomic bomb during the Second World War if it had not been for British input, and British encouragement, they agreed that they would share the technology during the war. It was part of the famous '[[Tizard Mission|trunkload of secrets]]' that were sent over here in the hopes of exchanging the information with us and  encouraging us to use our vast industrial capacity to help fight the war&quot; - [[Richard Rhodes]] - [[Equinox (TV series)|''Equinox'']] &quot;A Very British Bomb&quot;,  [[Channel 4]], 1997. From: [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Qk_zpjK3cTo]&lt;/blockquote&gt;  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/95.150.18.150|95.150.18.150]] ([[User talk:95.150.18.150#top|talk]]) 09:59, 6 November 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Edward Norris described as interior decorator ==

Hello, in the &quot;Gaseous Diffusion Project&quot; section, third paragraph, Edward Norris is currently described as an interior decorator. While this is a useful set of skills, I fail to see how it could help nuclear technology advances :D Have a nice day, [[Special:Contributions/77.204.56.112|77.204.56.112]] ([[User talk:77.204.56.112|talk]]) 05:32, 26 May 2016 (UTC)
: Well, now you know. {{smiley|grin}} [[User:Hawkeye7|Hawkeye7]] ([[User talk:Hawkeye7|talk]]) 12:06, 26 May 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>dk8bmoulo9tekj5x4kp4bw1ecbf5h3t</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
