<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Operation Crossroads</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2686053</id>
    <revision>
      <id>721626611</id>
      <parentid>721563205</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-05-23T02:37:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lowercase sigmabot III</username>
        <id>17518500</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Archiving 1 discussion(s) to [[Talk:Operation Crossroads/Archive 1]]) (bot</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12523">{{talkheader}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=PR
|action1date=17:22, 6 August 2009
|action1link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Operation Crossroads/archive1
|action1result=reviewed
|action1oldid=306426041

|action2=FAC
|action2date=14:44, 15 November 2009
|action2link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Operation Crossroads/archive1
|action2result=not promoted
|action2oldid=325580347

|action3=GAN
|action3date=21:31, 5 May 2013
|action3link=Talk:Operation Crossroads/GA1
|action3result=listed
|action3oldid=553685654

|action4=WAR
|action4date=12:35, 12 July 2013 (UTC)
|action4link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/Operation Crossroads
|action4result=approved
|action4oldid=563492705


|action5=FAC
|action5date=10:02, 09 November 2013
|action5link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Operation Crossroads/archive2
|action5result=promoted
|action5oldid=580875631
|currentstatus=FA
|maindate=December 4, 2013
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{MILHIST|class=FA|A-Class=pass|Maritime=y|Weaponry=y|US=y|Cold-War=y|old-peer-review=y}}
{{WikiProject Micronesia|class=FA|importance=|MarshallIslands=yes}}
{{WikiProject United States|class=FA|importance=|UShistory=yes|UShistory-importance=}}
}}
{{Archives|auto=yes|search=yes}} 
{{User:MiszaBot/config
| algo=old(90d)
| archive=Talk:Operation Crossroads/Archive %(counter)d
| counter=1
| maxarchivesize=75K
| archiveheader={{Automatic archive navigator}}
| minthreadsleft=5
| minthreadstoarchive=1
}}

== [[Activation product]]s ==

Not strictly true that &quot;only sodium becomes radioactive&quot;. Chlorine gives [[chlorine-36]], and [[oxygen-17]] gives [[carbon-14]] and an alpha particle on neutron absorption. --[[User:JWB|JWB]] ([[User talk:JWB|talk]]) 01:46, 29 October 2009 (UTC)

:You're right. How to fix the statement? I see that chlorine-36 has a 300,000 year half life, which would make its intensity low enough to be ignored by the Geiger men at Bikini. Oxygen-17 is a small fraction (0.04%) of natural oxygen, and the resulting carbon-14 also has a long half-life, 5,700 years. Also, carbon is not a component of sea water, and I assume it would have eventually settled out, like the fission products and plutonium. Radioactive sodium is the only radioactive seawater component mentioned in the Crossroads accounts. Its what caused problems with the ships' hulls and piping systems.

:How about &quot;only sodium becomes intensely radioactive&quot;, with a footnote mentioning chlorine-36 and carbon-14? [[User:HowardMorland|HowardMorland]] ([[User talk:HowardMorland|talk]]) 04:59, 29 October 2009 (UTC)
::That sounds good. I've edited (please revise as you see fit) and added a small table of neutron cross-sections and seawater abundances. From the latter, it looks like neutron absorption in seawater would be 97% on hydrogen, 3% on chlorine, and less than 0.1% each on sodium and oxygen.

::An isolated and probably ionized carbon atom would likely react with seawater producing a carbon compound. CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; in the oceans has a long lifetime and some other compounds would also or would be oxidized to CO2. --[[User:JWB|JWB]] ([[User talk:JWB|talk]]) 17:13, 29 October 2009 (UTC)
::No, I forgot to divide by the atomic weight of water - it should be 35% chlorine, 0.45% sodium, 0.02% oxygen.

:::I'm afraid I don't think the table actually works for this article. Its purpose would be to explain why sodium was the only isotope of concern for the radiation safety people. But most readers are going to be mystified by the table, and wonder why sodium was more of a problem than hydrogen. What really matters is the long half-life and correspondingly low intensity of the other isotopes, which readers don't need to know much about for this story. I don't think much technical detail is needed, other than to say that sodium is the problem. If you don't mind, I will summarize the explanation in a footnote. [[User:HowardMorland|HowardMorland]] ([[User talk:HowardMorland|talk]]) 16:13, 30 October 2009 (UTC)
::::That's fine, I was not pushing for the table to stay in the article, though it would be good to save it somewhere, like this talk page. However I think &quot;If all the neutrons ... were captured by sodium-23, 0.4 pounds of sodium-24 would result, but sodium did not capture all the neutrons.&quot; is a little misleading if only 1/200 of the neutrons were captured by sodium and should be rephrased to say the percentage was quite low. It could be more or less than 0.5% depending on epithermal cross sections and if epithermal absorption was significant, which I don't know so far. --[[User:JWB|JWB]] ([[User talk:JWB|talk]]) 20:08, 30 October 2009 (UTC)
:::::Resonance integrals are on the same order as the thermal cross sections, so shouldn't affect those statistics much. However I also found that Cl-35 more than 1% of the time will undergo a (n,p) reaction giving S-35 with a halflife of 87.7 days. The yield of S-35 should be almost as great as that of Na-24, but decay energy is less than 5% as great and decay rate is 140 times less. However after a week of decay, decay energy from Na-24 should drop below that from S-35. --[[User:JWB|JWB]] ([[User talk:JWB|talk]]) 22:48, 30 October 2009 (UTC)

::::::Here's the table.[[User:HowardMorland|HowardMorland]] ([[User talk:HowardMorland|talk]]) 21:58, 31 October 2009 (UTC)
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; align=&quot;right&quot;

|+[[Thermal neutron]] absorption of elements&lt;ref&gt;http://environmentalchemistry.com/yogi/periodic/crosssection.html&lt;/ref&gt; in [[seawater]]
!Element!![[neutron cross-section|Cross-section]]!![[Mole (unit)|Mole]]/kg
|-
|Hydrogen||0.3326 barns||106
|-
|Oxygen||0.00019 barns||53.5
|-
|Chlorine||35.5 barns||.54
|-
|Sodium||0.53 barns||.465
|}
{{-}}
:::::::The section on activation products needs major work.  There are so many problems, it is difficult to decide where to begin, but perhaps the knowledge that the discussion above, though well intentioned is completely off base by considering thermal neutrons, when fast neutrons are the major activation concern (and the cross sections are wildly different).
.
:::::::Just to point out how far from reality, even well intended logically guided scenarios can stray...Cl-38 is typically responsible for the highest radiation levels from activation for the first two hours.  &lt;ref&gt; http://www.dtic.mil/cgi-bin/GetTRDoc?AD=ADA382462 &lt;/ref&gt;http://www.dtic.mil/cgi-bin/GetTRDoc?AD=ADA382462
.

:::::::I am a bit disturbed at the above talking points, wherein it was asserted and apparently accepted that the only potential candidates for activation in the atoll, significant enough to be of concern, were Oxygen-16, Hydrogen-1, Sodium-24 and Chlorine-36.  Not only is that missing many significant components of sea water, it is missing the atoll floor 90 feet below!  Sea water and the atoll floor below are rich with isotopes that are readily converted by neutron activation in to dangerous short lived radioisotopes.  Iron, Cobalt, Iodine, Manganese......

:::::::Other significant activation products that play a important part are the shell casing and other parts of the weapon that were not the actual fissile material.  Once again, Iron, Cobalt and Manganese are very significant there.

[[Special:Contributions/70.171.44.124|70.171.44.124]] ([[User talk:70.171.44.124|talk]]) 10:03, 29 August 2013 (UTC)BGriffin
.
It is disappointing to find upon returning to this page nearly a year later, that misleading and inaccurate assumptions persist in this article relating to the radioactivity results of nuclear weapon detonation.
.
Among the more significant problems:
- The focus and time spent in the article on sodium activation with the implication it was one of the major problems.  With a 15 hour half life, although it would present a problem initially, it is certain not to have contributed to the problems decontaminating, as levels would be below detectable in a month from that activation product alone.
- The apparent exclusive consideration of thermal neutron cross sections when fast neutrons are going to be dominant.
- Assertion and reliance on unsupported ideas such as the idea that fission products are heavy and will sink to the bottom while sodium will stay in solution.  That particular one is interesting because two wrong ideas had to join to make it possible.  Not only are some very common fission products likely to end up in compounds that are unlikely to settle out...take xenon and iodine fission products for example, but atomic mass and solubility are not reliably correlated. 
- Completely ignoring the most important group of materials in respect to producing problematic activation products...the  structural material of the bomb itself.
- Problems that don't even require checking outside this reference to understand something is wrong. In the section on plutonium that hadn't undergone fission, at the top of the article, a 'tolerance dose', maximum allowable exposure, is noted as 1 microgram, yet at the end of that section 2 milligrams is claimed to be 2000 'lethal' doses.  Does anyone honestly believe the maximum allowable exposure is the same thing as a lethal dose? 
.
.
I'm sure the intentions were noble, but the outcome is regrettable.  Unfortunately there seems to be quite a bit of room for this type of inaccuracy.  I enjoy a good piece of fiction as much as the next person, but one qualification for fiction being good is that it isn't trying to pass itself off as legitimate truth. 
.
[[Special:Contributions/174.64.101.220|174.64.101.220]] ([[User talk:174.64.101.220|talk]]) 18:50, 23 July 2014 (UTC)BGriffin

== Citation/Reference behavior in mobile format viewing  ==

Let me first say I very much appreciate the copious and detailed references, cutes, and notes. Very helpful in learning deep detail.  But in just this particular article I'm seeing odd behavior not seen with any other article. And it's only seen when reading using the mobile format. Every citation (that i checked) from the &quot;Able&quot; header to the end of the article not only pops up the reference, but redirects your position in the article back to the beginning of the Able header. Even if you are reading in a different header (Baker), and even if you collapse the Able header, the redirect opens it.

What is the cause of this? I tried looking at the raw text but nothing stands out to me. Clearly though the behavior is different than any other article,  and it's maddeningly frustrating. Any clues?

[[Special:Contributions/24.15.12.200|24.15.12.200]] ([[User talk:24.15.12.200|talk]]) 09:54, 29 December 2014 (UTC)

== Unencyclopaedic language ==

'Had the Nevada been fully manned, she would likely have become a floating coffin, dead in the water for lack of a live crew.'

Not the right tone. Does this mean 'Had the Nevada been manned, all on board would probably have been killed.'?  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/2.98.178.11|2.98.178.11]] ([[User talk:2.98.178.11|talk]]) 18:52, 14 July 2015 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Atomic veterans ==

[[User:Johnfos|Johnfos]], the issue of military service members' exposure to radiation is already covered to some extent in the current article. Details about individual's exposure like that of John Smitherman and their battle to gain recognition and compensation are better handled in the [[Atomic veteran]] article. — [[User:btphelps|btphelps]] &lt;sup&gt;([[User_talk:Btphelps |talk to me]]) ([[Special:Contributions/Btphelps |what I've done]])&lt;/sup&gt; 18:09, 13 January 2016 (UTC)

:Thanks for that, Btphelps. I will write a paragraph on Smitherman and put it in the Atomic veterans article. [[User:Johnfos|Johnfos]] ([[User talk:Johnfos|talk]]) 06:26, 14 January 2016 (UTC)

{{reflist|talk}}

== Inaccuracy re: use of 'demon core' ==

A [http://www.newyorker.com/tech/elements/demon-core-the-strange-death-of-louis-slotin?intcid=mod-latest recent article] by Alex Wellerstein (who as far as I know is a well regarded nuclear historian) claims that the demon core was ''not'' used in Operation Crossroads: it had been scheduled to be used, but was still too radioactive by the time of the test and was later melted and used in a new bomb. Since there are cited claims to the contrary already in the article, it would be great if someone with the requisite knowledge in the field could look into this further and make the correction if necessary.

--[[User:Doncurzio|Doncurzio]] ([[User talk:Doncurzio|talk]]) 18:00, 22 May 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>i1x8won49qfkq934wj0k6jqkv1hl5x8</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
