<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:German battleship Bismarck</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>155986</id>
    <revision>
      <id>736457498</id>
      <parentid>723172992</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-27T16:52:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>66.214.105.178</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Messages decoded by Jane Fawcett (nee Hughes)? */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="41794">{{Skip to talk}}
{{talk header }}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 6
|minthreadsleft = 4
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:German battleship Bismarck/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{Auto archiving notice |bot=MiszaBot I |age=3 |units=months}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=WPR
|action1date=15:48, 6 July 2009 (UTC)
|action1link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Peer review/German battleship Bismarck
|action1result=reviewed
|action1oldid=300044123

|action2=GAN
|action2date=11:20, 6 July 2011
|action2link=Talk:German battleship Bismarck/GA1
|action2result=listed
|action2oldid=438034958

|action3=GTC
|action3date=02:55, 25 August 2011
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured topic candidates/Battleships of Germany/archive1
|action3result=promoted
|action3oldid=446317710

|action4=WAR
|action4date=08:29, 6 January 2012 (UTC)
|action4link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/German battleship Bismarck
|action4result=approved
|action4oldid=469377201

|action5=FAC
|action5date=20:56, 28 January 2012
|action5link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/German battleship Bismarck/archive1
|action5result=not promoted
|action5oldid=473568659

|action6=FAC
|action6date=15:07, 22 July 2012
|action6link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/German battleship Bismarck/archive2
|action6result=promoted
|action6oldid=503596344

|ftname=Battleships of Germany
|topic=war
|currentstatus=FA
|maindate=February 14, 2014
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Germany|class=FA
| b1 &lt;!--Referencing &amp; citations--&gt; = yes
| b2 &lt;!--Coverage &amp; accuracy    --&gt; = yes
| b3 &lt;!--Structure              --&gt; = yes
| b4 &lt;!--Grammar &amp; style        --&gt; = yes
| b5 &lt;!--Supporting materials   --&gt; = yes
|importance=mid}}
{{WPMILHIST|class=FA|OMT=1
|B1= yes |B2= yes |B3= yes |B4= yes |B5= yes
|German=yes|Maritime=yes|WWII=yes|old-peer-review=yes|A-Class=pass}}
{{WikiProject Ships|class=FA|importance=Top
|B-Class-1=yes &lt;!--It is suitably referenced, and all major points have appropriate inline citations.--&gt;
|B-Class-2=yes &lt;!--It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain obvious omissions or inaccuracies.--&gt;
|B-Class-3=yes &lt;!--It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content.--&gt;
|B-Class-4=yes &lt;!--It is free from major grammatical errors.--&gt;
|B-Class-5=yes &lt;!--It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams.--&gt;}}
{{WikiProject Shipwrecks |importance=top |class=FA }}
}}
{{On this day |date1=2004-05-24|oldid1=3767962 |date2=2005-05-24|oldid2=14219886 |date3=2006-05-24|oldid3=54912952 |date4=2007-05-24|oldid4=133149054 |date5=2012-05-24|oldid5=493946985 }}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn
|target=/Archive index |mask=/Archive &lt;#&gt; |leading_zeros=0 |indexhere=yes
}}

== Star-Sprangled Bismarck. ==

There will be another Bismarck. Press reports the US Navy is naming one FY2016 USNS-operated hydrofoil as Bismarck, named after the capital city. Thereby, Bismarck_(ship) article may soon need a disambiguation page for Wikipedia! [[Special:Contributions/82.131.219.55|82.131.219.55]] ([[User talk:82.131.219.55|talk]]) 19:26, 15 February 2015 (UTC)

:Unlikely - this ship will still be far more famous, and 99% of the time, when someone types in &quot;Bismarck ship&quot; to the search bar, they'll be looking for this one. A hatnote here will more than suffice. [[User:Parsecboy|Parsecboy]] ([[User talk:Parsecboy|talk]]) 01:28, 16 February 2015 (UTC)

== Main belt obsession in wreck expeditions ==

The obsession reflected in the wreck expedition treatment on the lack of penetration of the main belt armour (mentioned repeatedly in the text) should be moderated. It gives the misleading impression that (a) the Bismarck had amazingly effective armour, or (b) the British 16 in and 14 in armour-piercing shells were not effective. Neither of which impressions are based on fact. The main belt of Bismarck reached a maximum thickness of 12.6 inches, whereas the conning tower had 14 inch-thick armour. The conning tower on the wreck of the Bismarck is said to resemble a &quot;Swiss cheese&quot;.Brown (2006), pp. 31, 35. Brown, D K (2006). Nelson to Vanguard: Warship Design and Development 1923–1945. Chatham Publishing. I can think of reasons for this discrepancy: Bismarck had a very low freeboard and a remarkably wide beam, therefore plunging fire from a distance would have had a much higher probability of hitting the deck or superstructure than the main belt: very close range fire, especially after Bismarck had settled in the water due to flooding, would also have tended to pass over the main belt. Inclusion of a reference to the many penetrations of the conning tower would help to give the reader a more balanced impression of the effectiveness of the armour protection of this battleship. The main belt armour of the ship, intact or not, proved to be an irrelevance. It did nothing to prevent Bismarck from being reduced to a burnt-out, sinking (albeit slowly) wreck. [[User:Urselius|Urselius]] ([[User talk:Urselius|talk]]) 20:02, 7 June 2015 (UTC)
:Are there any specific changes to the article which you'd like to suggest? [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 01:02, 8 June 2015 (UTC)

::Yes, within the 'second wreck section' a reference to the state of the conning tower could be made using the reference given above, or in the earlier description of the final battle the following might be referred to, with reference that this structure had the thickest armour (along with the main turret faces) on the ship: Bismarck survivor Josef Statz stated that several shells had penetrated the port wall of the conning tower and had destroyed everything within. William H. Garzke, Robert O. Dulin (1985) ''Battleships: Axis and Neutral Battleships in World War II'', p. 491. This would effectively balance the descriptions of intact main belt armour in the text of the article, and correct the potential misapprehensions a reader might conceive concerning the relative effectiveness of armour and armour-piercing shells during the action. [[User:Urselius|Urselius]] ([[User talk:Urselius|talk]]) 08:41, 8 June 2015 (UTC)
:::What you're proposing is [[WP:SYN|synthetic]] and inappropriate. [[User:Parsecboy|Parsecboy]] ([[User talk:Parsecboy|talk]]) 10:02, 8 June 2015 (UTC)
::::No, it is not synthetic by any means, and is entirely appropriate. No novel conclusion is reached. It also does two very useful things, it gives the reader a more balanced account, as discussed above, and introduces an eyewitness account of the state of the battleship following the cannonade. In the article it states: &quot;Bismarck had been reduced to a shambles, aflame from stem to stern&quot;, but there is no detail describing this. The addition of an eyewitness anecdote would rectify this omission. The addition of a description of the ruined state of the most heavily armoured part of the battleship's superstructure is an eloquent testimony concerning the shambles the rest had been reduced to. [[User:Urselius|Urselius]] ([[User talk:Urselius|talk]]) 10:47, 8 June 2015 (UTC)
:::::Let's not backpedal now. Your point in wanting to include it, as you said in your first post, was to disprove the supposed implication that ''Rodney'' was unable to penetrate the belt. The archaeologists who examined the wreck were focused on finding penetrations in the belt (i.e., below the waterline), since those would settle the sunk vs. scuttled debate. You want to add mention of the fact that the conning tower was badly damaged, because if ''Rodney'''s 16-inch guns could penetrate the conning tower armor, they could surely penetrate the belt. In essence, you are using A, which says B, to disprove C, when A does not reference C - that is the definition of a synthetic argument.
:::::In any event, the article ''does'' mention the fact that the superstructure was riddled with holes - try reading further in the subsequent expeditions section. [[User:Parsecboy|Parsecboy]] ([[User talk:Parsecboy|talk]]) 12:04, 8 June 2015 (UTC)

I am not back-pedalling, I am arguing a case and bringing in further supporting material.  As you are undoubtedly aware, there is an element of &quot;fan-boy&quot; adulation of this ship out there. This includes the idea that the ship was scuttled with hardly its paint scratched, because its &quot;super-special-unbeatable-armour&quot; made it unsinkable. Being encyclopaedic and hopefully factual, Wikipedia editors should not pander to this view - even subconsciously. At present, the view that the armour on the Bismarck was &quot;super-special-unbeatable&quot; is supported indirectly by the text. Why did the Bismarck not sink due to gunfire as easily as some other ships did? Well, that had everything to do with its excellent magazine isolation, low freeboard and massive beam, together giving it great stability, and its watertight subdivisioning. It had nothing to do with the thickness, positioning or steel-composition of its armour. Indeed the conning tower armour, designed to withstand 15 inch shells from moderate range, seems to have been breached by 8 inch shells from HMS Dorsetshire. Thus the armour on the Bismarck was not only not &quot;super-special-unbeatable&quot;, it did not even achieve its design specifications. Your objections to this proposed addition - fully supported by respected secondary sources and designed to balance an imbalance in the text - seem to rely entirely on sophistry. [[User:Urselius|Urselius]] ([[User talk:Urselius|talk]]) 13:24, 8 June 2015 (UTC)

:Read whatever you like into the text, synthesis will not be tolerated. The problem with your &quot;respected secondary sources&quot; is that you're putting words into their mouths, which is as I said, inappropriate. That you've been editing here as long as you have and do not understand that is appalling.
:I've never seen any evidence that ''Dorsetshire''{{'}}s 8&quot; guns were capable of penetrating 14&quot; of armor, and frankly, it's a laughable suggestion. [[User:Parsecboy|Parsecboy]] ([[User talk:Parsecboy|talk]]) 13:54, 8 June 2015 (UTC)

::I cannot find the reference I was thinking of for the 8-inch penetration for the moment, it was a survivor account, mentioning an officer being killed in the conning tower by splinters from an 8-inch shell, but perhaps a director was meant? I have found another reference for the conning tower being breached by an 8-inch shell, but I do not think it is from a publication of sufficient quality. Just found this: Mr. Statz recalls he was momentarily stunned by the shell's explosion and subsequently received a wound some 8-inches long in his left shoulder from a shell from Dorsetshire which passed into the conning tower through the open starboard door. Open door - but my memory about it exploding in the conning tower was correct. The available photos of the wreck show a number of holes in the conning tower.
::Like I said your objections are mere sophistry and 'Wiki-legalism', no synthesis exists except in your mind. The text as it stands is unbalanced - this is a fact - the repeated mentions about the intact main belt armour are wide open to misinterpretation - the misinterpretation I have outlined in detail above. Your strange 'A-B algebra' is the mental equivalent of 'the shell game'. Please try to follow the logical progression. I am not seeking to prove that the main belt was breached or that it could be breached. What I am seeking to show to the reader is that the armour employed on the Bismarck in general could be penetrated, and was in fact penetrated, by the British armour piercing rounds used against it. This is very useful information that is lacking in the article as it stands. There is no synthesis! You have no legitimate grounds for objection on this count. The mere assertion that the superstructure was riddled with holes is not equivalent, as most of the superstructure would have had splinter-protection at best. [[User:Urselius|Urselius]] ([[User talk:Urselius|talk]]) 15:04, 8 June 2015 (UTC)

:::(EC) An 8&quot; shell ''cannot'' penetrate 14&quot; of steel under any circumstances, at any range. Even the super-heavy shells used in the American 8&quot;/55 could penetrate at most 10&quot;, and the British Mk VIII fired a significantly lighter shell. And a fragment would be even less capable of penetrating that much steel.
:::If you think the prohibition on [[WP:SYN|synthesis]] is &quot;Wiki-legalism&quot;, that's fine, but you ought to find somewhere else to spend your time, since it's policy. You ''are'' trying to prove that the belt could be breached - did you forget what you typed earlier? {{xt|&quot;It gives the misleading impression that (a) the Bismarck had amazingly effective armour, or (b) the British 16 in and 14 in armour-piercing shells were not effective.&quot;}} - obviously, your point is the inverse, or in other words, to demonstrate that (a) the armor was ineffective, or (b) that the 16&quot; and 14&quot; shells were effective. 
:::There's no synthesis? That's all you're doing! You infer that since the article mentions the fact that the belt was not penetrated, that means the belt couldn't be penetrated, when the article in no way makes that claim. You therefore have decided that pointing out that the conning tower was penetrated (A), that the belt could also be penetrated (B), when your source for (A) does not speak to (B). Do you really not see this?
:::I find it amusing that you call my &quot;A-B algebra&quot; a &quot;shell game&quot;, when it comes almost directly from the prohibition on synthetic arguments, which you apparently have not bothered to read. I don't link these things for my health. [[User:Parsecboy|Parsecboy]] ([[User talk:Parsecboy|talk]]) 15:59, 8 June 2015 (UTC)

You really have a problem with logic. No, I do not bother with wikilegalism at all.

I quote yourself: &quot;You infer that since the article mentions the fact that the belt was not penetrated, that means the belt couldn't be penetrated, when the article in no way makes that claim. You therefore have decided that pointing out that the conning tower was penetrated (A), that the belt could also be penetrated (B), when your source for (A) does not speak to (B). Do you really not see this?&quot;

Erm, No! No! No! I am inferring nothing, nothing at all - I know a number of cogent reasons why the main belt was not breached, none of them connected with the thickness or composition of the armour. What I am saying is that we owe it to the reader, who may know little about naval warfare or ship design, not to take away the impression that the armour of Bismarck was impervious. At present there is nothing in the article to prevent this, and indeed there is plenty to support such a misinterpretation. There is no synthetic component to what I am suggesting. In order to be synthetic a novel conclusion not evident in any single source would have to be elaborated. Merely saying that the armoured conning tower was penetrated by shellfire is not novel. I can use a single source to say this, therefore no synthesis is possible.

1) There is a widespread idea that the Bismarck class had unusually effective &quot;special composition&quot; steel armour.

2) This article, as it stands, does not counteract this fallacy. Indeed, it unintentionally supports it by some of its wording.

3) All informed Wikipedia editors should be eager to present a balanced picture to potentially uninformed readers.

4) There is a simple way of dispelling this fallacy by mentioning the penetration of the extremely well-armoured control tower. This also has the added bonus of introducing an extra eye-witness account to the text, and highlights the importance of control systems, control personnel and communications in the functioning of a naval vessel in action.

See this online: 
Bismarck's Final Battle by William H. Garzke, Jr. and Robert O. Dulin, Jr. Illustrations by Thomas G. Webb, Part 3 - which says &quot;Command and control spaces are always key targets for enemy fire.  During the battleship era, relatively heavily-armored conning towers were normally provided to protect key personnel.  Bismarck's conning tower was shielded by 350mm armor, which was riddled by close-range British battleship gunfire.&quot;

This is what I intend adding (in bold):

By 10:00, Tovey's two battleships had fired over 700 main battery shells, many at very close range; Bismarck had been reduced to a shambles, aflame from stem to stern. '''Even the well-armoured control tower, according to survivor Josef Statz, had been penetrated by several shells, destroying everything inside.''' ''ref William H. Garzke, Robert O. Dulin (1985) ''Battleships: Axis and Neutral Battleships in World War II'', p. 491. ref'' She suffered from a 20° list to port and was low in the water by the stern.

I really do not see how any objection to this scheme is editorially, logically or ethically valid. [[User:Urselius|Urselius]] ([[User talk:Urselius|talk]]) 16:42, 8 June 2015 (UTC)

:I'm starting to grow tired of this nonsense - but I'll give you the benefit of the doubt. Perhaps you have trouble with the definition of &quot;inference&quot;. Do you have any evidence that readers will interpret the article in the same biased manner that you did? No? Then you're inferring that they will (and that there is a problem with the article).
:You want objections? The world is filled with morons and crackpots - it's not Wikipedia's job to refute them. The [[Apollo 11]] article does not address the widely-known fringe theory that the landing was a hoax, for good reason. And even then, this article ''already'' makes clear that the ship was reduced to a shambles, that its heaviest armor (i.e., the main battery turrets) was repeatedly defeated. You are swinging at phantoms. Anyone who is currently under any misapprehension about the ability of ''Bismarck''{{'}}S (or any ship's) armor to defeat very large projectiles ''won't'' be swayed by additional evidence to the contrary.
:Do you know ''why'' the archaeologists (and thus, this article) focuses on the belt? [[User:Parsecboy|Parsecboy]] ([[User talk:Parsecboy|talk]]) 19:15, 8 June 2015 (UTC)

::OK, we are getting somewhere, slowly. We have at least disposed of the &quot;synthesis&quot; red herring. Hurrah! Good for you. The archaeologists are heavily concerned with the intactness of the belt armour because they are pursuing a similarly moronic and crackpot thesis as the &quot;special steel&quot;. To whit, &quot;Did the British sink the Bismarck or was she scuttled by her crew?&quot; The importance of this question is based on the fallacious relevance of sinking a warship. It matters not at all if a functionless wreck floats for days or sinks in minutes. The Bismarck had been rendered a burnt out hulk long before it slipped beneath the waves; it was unable to manoeuvre or effectively raise steam, it had lost its power, communications and ability to lay or fire its armament. There was no chance of it making meaningful repairs and it had no chance of reaching any port, friendly or otherwise. It is a part of the 'unsinkable' fallacy, just like the &quot;special steel&quot;. 
::Your real dislike of me adding an entirely relevant single sentence, with an entirely respectable citation, is that you have argued yourself into a logically indefensible position. And, yes, we owe it even to crackpot readers to present a balanced viewpoint in any article, especially one as surrounded by disinformation. [[User:Urselius|Urselius]] ([[User talk:Urselius|talk]]) 20:05, 8 June 2015 (UTC)
:::No, the point of what you're trying to accomplish here is still synthesis. I've just stopped bothering to try to explain it to you, since you apparently [[WP:IDHT|have your fingers in your ears]].
:::Bingo! But the difference between the two issues is really rather simple. Reliable sources ''have'' spent quite a bit of time debating the issue, unlike your &quot;special steel&quot; nonsense. ''That'' is why the article covers that debate and the state of the hull. 
:::I don't know what's more amusing - your inept condescension or your atrocious grasp of policy (and logic, apparently). [[User:Parsecboy|Parsecboy]] ([[User talk:Parsecboy|talk]]) 20:31, 8 June 2015 (UTC)

You must have a very 'special' concept of synthesis. How in the world of reason can a bare statement of a simple fact, drawn from a single secondary source, constitute a synthesis? Given that the definition of synthesis is &quot;the combination of components or elements to form a connected whole&quot;, I cannot be engaged in synthesis as I only have one component (I have some knowledge of synthetic chemistry BTW). Please explain to me how I could synthesise anything. You hide behind terms because your logic walks on crutches. You do not come across as being amused. :)

Why am I only conversing with you? Are no other editors interested? Or have you cowed them all with your grinding and misplaced zeal? 

As an aside, did you know that the separation of the stern of the ship was witnessed, about a minute before it sank? [[User:Urselius|Urselius]] ([[User talk:Urselius|talk]]) 21:01, 8 June 2015 (UTC)
:Ok, I'll spell it out for you. And I'll use small words, so I can't &quot;hide&quot; behind anything, and so we can be sure you'll understand (fingers crossed!). Your entire point in coming here is to disprove the apparent theory (which I have [[WP:FRINGE|never seen in a reliable source]], by the way) that ''Bismarck'' had some kind of special steel armor. We'll call that your conclusion C. You have a quote from Statz, we'll call that source A, that says the conning tower was penetrated by gunfire, which we'll call B. Of course, the other half of your argument is the basic logic that 350mm &gt; 320mm (which we'll call D) You, by your first statement here, came to prove C by combining A and D, which is the definition of synthesis.
:See, the thing is, if all you wanted to do was improve the coverage of battle damage (which I'd argue is not within the scope of the article, but that's beside the point), that would be fine. But you came here with an ax to grind, and you (rather foolishly) admitted it in your first post. 
:It's been, what, all of 11 hours that we've been discussing this? I have no idea why no one else has joined the debate yet - perhaps they have lives.
:It might be interesting to you that according to Herr Statz, the stern was still attached when the ship sank - do you trust your eye-witness or not? 
:I take it you have conceded my second point above? Assuming that's the case, since you have not addressed it, we can drop all this nonsense and move on with our lives. [[User:Parsecboy|Parsecboy]] ([[User talk:Parsecboy|talk]]) 22:20, 8 June 2015 (UTC)

:: &quot;Another popular fallacy is that Bismarck had an armour belt made from a special nickel-chrome steel alloy&quot; from ''British Battleships of World War Two: The Development and Technical History of the Royal Navy's Battleships and Battlecruisers from 1911 to 1946,'' Alan Raven, John Roberts, Arms and Armour Press, 1976.
::Anthony Preston, formerly of the National Maritime Museum, author of numerous books on ship design etc. and sometime co-author with DK Brown, also alludes to the special nickel-steel armour myth in ''Sea Power'', Exeter Books 1979, p. 113
::Thus the matter is definitely out there, it matters not what you consider a “reputable source” either, because any such myth, from whatever source, should be addressed here.

::However, the whole discussion above pales into insignificance next to the selective sourcing of evidence and avoidance of direct description that I have just recognised in this article.
::At some stage in the discussion you said that the article describes how the armoured turrets were penetrated, and therefore mention of the conning tower is superfluous. This is untrue; the use of periphrasis is employed within the article to avoid saying this in a suitably direct manner. In the article the after turrets are “put out of action”, which suggests some form of gentle euthanasia. The forward turrets are rendered inoperable by a single shell hit to the superstructure! This suggests that two heavily armoured barbettes ceased to function out of sympathy!

::The smoking gun:

::DK Brown (2012), p. 163 &quot;It is often suggested that Bismarck was much more resistant to damage than RN ships [i.e. the fallacy I have been expounding on], but examination of the wreck shows that this was not so. …. Fire was opened at 0847hrs and by 0900hrs B turret was out of action when a shell (probably 14in) went through the 340mm barbette armour and burst, blowing the back plate off [this is one of the turrets that apparently died of sympathy]…” “The belt [main belt of Bismarck wreck] is largely buried in silt but several penetrations can be seen.”

::This is an eminently respectable source and should be used to balance – my whole argument here has been for a more balanced text, not to create any synthetic construct – the biased text that stands at present.

::Use of the above description of the turret being blown apart by a direct AP round hit would be sufficient for addressing the ‘special armour’, the conning tower would indeed then be superfluous. The destruction of turret B (and A at much the same time - the barrels of this turret ended up resting on the gunwale) so early in the action is a very significant episode and is worthy of greater emphasis in any case. The description of penetration of the belt should also be included to balance the claims to the contrary. If there are two conflicting claims about any matter of importance, both should be mentioned in any encyclopaedic treatment. [[User:Urselius|Urselius]] ([[User talk:Urselius|talk]]) 09:15, 9 June 2015 (UTC)

:::Those are your smoking guns? Have you ever, in your life, read a page that starts with &quot;Wikipedia:&quot;? In all seriousness, I shudder to think of the articles you've written with the absurd understanding of our core content policies you apparently have. Per [[WP:FRINGE]] and [[WP:DUE]], we do not cover fringe/nonsense theories just because they've been mentioned in passing a reliable source. We address them only in the context of the notable nutjob advancing them (for example, we don't mention the asinine birther garbage on [[Barack Obama]], but we do mention it on [[Orly Taitz]]'s bio) - we do ''not'' reflect the noise of the internet. Since you obviously cannot be bothered to click the little blue links, I'll give you some direct quotes.
::::From FRINGE:
:::::{{xt|&quot;A conjecture that has not received critical review from the scientific community or that has been rejected may be included in an article about a scientific subject only if other high-quality reliable sources discuss it as an alternative position.&quot;}} - that means, if no one reputable is advancing a particular theory, we don't discuss it. Do you happen to have any?
::::From DUE:
:::::{{xt|&quot;Neutrality requires that each article or other page in the mainspace fairly represent all significant viewpoints that have been published by reliable sources, in proportion to the prominence of each viewpoint in the published, reliable sources&quot;}} - that means, we treat controversial issues in accordance with their prominence in the field of study. We do not address [[hydrino]]s [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Special%3AWhatLinksHere&amp;target=Hydrino&amp;namespace=0 anywhere], even though many reputable, prominent scientists have derided the idea. The idea that ''Bismarck'' had special steel armor (no doubt a fundamental misunderstanding of what ''Wotan Hart'' [which does in fact use nickel and chome, as do all contemporary armors]) is no different.
:::You, uh, may not know this, but barbettes are part of the superstructure, as they are, you know, structures built atop (i.e., superposed) the hull. And if you have a problem with phrases like &quot;put out of action&quot;, then perhaps you need to do a bit more reading, as the phrase is a very common one.
:::It seems you have an odd definition of &quot;encyclopedic&quot; - this article is written in a [[WP:SUMMARY|summary style]]. If you want to include more information on the last battle, there is [[Last battle of the battleship Bismarck]], which given its poor state of development, would be an excellent place for improvement. [[User:Parsecboy|Parsecboy]] ([[User talk:Parsecboy|talk]]) 13:13, 9 June 2015 (UTC)

Did you notice, I did as I am a scientist, that the subject of the article in question is not scientific - it is a battleship? A battleship is the product of technology, which in turn is dependant on scientific principles, but a battleship is not a scientific subject as such. I have had work published in 'Nature', written many peer-reviewed scientific papers and chapters for scientific textbooks: I have even had historical monographs published, born out of my 'spare-time' interests. So my intellectual credentials are fairly sound. 

The problem with you is, that when you and those like you (unfortunately not rare) have an article made into a 'Featured Article' (FA), it becomes in your mind a 'Sacred Object' (SO). No one, whatever the merits or minor nature of their desired changes, no matter what level of supporting evidence is brought to bear, can change the FA/SO if it does not suit your whim. Trying to influence a 'SO-guardian' is almost always futile, however, should a dispassionate third party see the talk page of a SO like this, the mere fact of it being filled with well-argued text may be beneficial in the long term.

Pinning down the 'SO-guardian' is always difficult, they are strong in their tenacity, however, they occasionally make indisputable errors of fact:

&quot;Superstructure consists of the parts of the ship or a boat, including sailboats, fishing boats, passenger ships, and submarines, that project above her main deck. '''This does not usually include its masts or any armament turrets.'''&quot; Wikipedia

&quot;A superstructure is an extended construction of any building or platform that rises above the rest of the building or platform in a distinct manner. The word comes from a combination of two Latin words, the Latin prefix ‘super’ means in addition or above or in excess of, whereas the stem word ‘structure’ means to build or to heap up. Thus, superstructure means to add a construction to an already existing structure. In ships this is the name given to the part of the ship that emerges from the deck. However any mast, sails, '''any armaments or arsenal are not included in this category'''&quot;. Marine World

Your view of naval terminology is, at best uncanonical and at worst just plain wrong. In either case the misleading wording of the events leading to the 'putting out of action' of turrets 'Anton' and 'Bruno' needs to be amended. [[User:Urselius|Urselius]] ([[User talk:Urselius|talk]]) 12:05, 13 June 2015 (UTC)

:Sure you have - oh, and didn't I tell you that I'm Robert Ballard? 
:Do you know the difference between a [[barbette]] and a [[gun turret]]? I would submit that, expert as you claim to be in other areas, you are quite out of your depth here. [[User:Parsecboy|Parsecboy]] ([[User talk:Parsecboy|talk]]) 13:30, 13 June 2015 (UTC)

::Hello Robert. Change the incorrect statement.

::The difference between the turret and barbette is essentially historical. In the early ironclad warships, such as USS Monitor, the turret was a revolving armoured structure enclosing heavy artillery at deck level. Being very heavy they caused stability problems. The result was to place guns in a lower position in open-roofed mounts within an armoured &quot;parapet&quot; called a barbette. Later still the open barbette was considered as very vulnerable, due to the increasing range of heavy guns allowing plunging fire. An armoured 'hood' was placed over the barbette as a remedy for this fault. This created as sort of pseudo-turret; later common-usage just referred to such a fully traversing mount for a gun as a turret once more. Technically the barbette was the non-rotational cylinder on which the guns in their pseudo-turret rotated.

::Change the demonstrably incorrect statement, or allow me to do it. A hit on the superstructure, as it is defined, above, would not prevent a single, never mind two, main armament turrets from functioning. Even should some authorities define a gun turret as part of the superstructure the statement is still too open to misinterpretation to stand. [[User:Urselius|Urselius]] ([[User talk:Urselius|talk]]) 13:47, 13 June 2015 (UTC)

:::Good, you ''do'' know how to read! Now that we know that turrets are barbettes are different things (although you are quite wrong about plunging fire, but that's another, minor point), shall we go back to that definition of &quot;superstructure&quot; you posted earlier? The non-rotating tube (eg., see [[:File:USS Maryland BB-46 Laid Down.jpg|here]]) is ''part'' of the ship and it extends above the upper deck, quite unlike the turret structure (eg., the blue parts [[:File:Animated gun turret.gif|here]]), which is ''not'' part of the ship, since they are generally held in place only by gravity. [[User:Parsecboy|Parsecboy]] ([[User talk:Parsecboy|talk]]) 14:47, 13 June 2015 (UTC)

Actually, I did not look at your links or any other information at all, the turret/barbette stuff was all &quot;out of me head&quot;.
I missed your meaning initially. Ah! You are trying a case of special pleading that the barbette is not part of the armament and is therefore superstructure. This sort of sophistry is typical of the FA 'article owner' pushed onto the defensive, unfortunately. No, the almost universal definition of ship's superstructure does not include barbettes. See the definition above: &quot;any armaments or arsenal are not included in this category&quot;. The barbette is an integral part of the &quot;armaments or arsenal&quot;. Besides, the major part of any WWII era ship's barbettes were below the upper deck. A structure cannot, from first principles of logic, be part of a superstructure if it's major component is sub-structural. The description of the rebuild of HMS Renown 1936-1939 - &quot;the superstructure was razed to upper deck level&quot; and the &quot;15in turrets were removed&quot; etc. etc. but the barbettes were not touched. The Royal Navy did not consider the barbettes as constituting part of the superstructure (Burt pp. 228-233, 2013 reprint). I know a lieutenant in the Royal Australian Navy who is a marine engineer and a former Lloyds marine insurance inspector, would you accept his opinion on this matter? It would have to be binding on both parties of course. [[User:Urselius|Urselius]] ([[User talk:Urselius|talk]]) 15:39, 13 June 2015 (UTC)

:Let's look at Bercuson &amp; Herwig, the source of the information, for what exactly they say:
::&quot;...a 16-inch shell from ''Rodney'' slammed into the ''Bismarck'''s upper deck forward. Sheets of fire engulfed her superstructure. Hundreds of men died at their battle stations. The forward turrets were reduced to 'shambles of riven metal'.&quot;
:Tell me why they would be referring to the damage this shell inflicted on the superstructure? Did a shell hit in the vicinity of the turrets cause a fire a hundred feet away? In any event, they don't feel the need to give the kinds of details on specific hits as you requested earlier, and theirs is a monograph, not an encyclopedia article.
:The other sources used in the article are less helpful. Garzke &amp; Dulin simply state that &quot;At 0902, a 406-mm shell from the ''Rodney'' heavily damaged turrets Anton and Bruno.&quot; Zetterling &amp; Tamerlander are even less detailed: &quot;During the following minutes, the fore fire control was also hit and both main turrets silenced&quot; - hey, there's one of those words you have such a problem with! What, are we to assume that the British merely muffled the guns? And von Mullenheim-Rechberg states &quot;...and around 0902, [''Rodney''] observed a spectacular hit on the forward part of the ''Bismarck''.&quot;
:What is it exactly that you want to change at this point? [[User:Parsecboy|Parsecboy]] ([[User talk:Parsecboy|talk]]) 18:22, 14 June 2015 (UTC)

::Please see: [https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=EQwO1N-d8tEC&amp;pg=PA152&amp;dq=Bismarck+main+belt+penetrated&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=Bismarck%20main%20belt%20penetrated&amp;f=false] &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Urselius|Urselius]] ([[User talk:Urselius|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Urselius|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;

:::That did not answer my question from nearly a year ago. [[User:Parsecboy|Parsecboy]] ([[User talk:Parsecboy|talk]]) 15:51, 10 May 2016 (UTC)

::::It says that the main belt was penetrated. There is a difference of opinion on the subject in the secondary sources. This should be included in the article. &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Urselius|Urselius]] ([[User talk:Urselius|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Urselius|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;

:::::So does this article. [[User:Parsecboy|Parsecboy]] ([[User talk:Parsecboy|talk]]) 11:53, 1 June 2016 (UTC)

::::::Where? Please quote. &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Urselius|Urselius]] ([[User talk:Urselius|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Urselius|contribs]]) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;

:::::::Do I really need to hold your hand?
:::::::{{xt|&quot;Ballard's survey found no underwater penetrations of the ship's fully armoured citadel. Eight holes were found in the hull, one on the starboard side and seven on the port side, all above the waterline. One of the holes is in the deck, on the bow's starboard side. The angle and shape indicates the shell that created the hole was fired from Bismarck's port side and struck the starboard anchor chain. The anchor chain has disappeared down this hole.[138] Six holes are amidships, three shell fragments pierced the upper splinter belt, and '''one made a hole in the main armour belt'''.[139]&quot;}}
:::::::Do please sign your posts, by the way. [[User:Parsecboy|Parsecboy]] ([[User talk:Parsecboy|talk]]) 12:28, 1 June 2016 (UTC)

== Stern ==

To continue from [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=German_battleship_Bismarck&amp;curid=141871&amp;diff=699644792&amp;oldid=699641175 this edit summary], Ballard goes on to outline the evidence that suggests the stern detached at the surface (basically what's covered in that paragraph in this article), and concludes that &quot;These facts suggest strongly that a structural failure occurred before the ship sank and that the stern broke off at the surface.&quot; [[User:Parsecboy|Parsecboy]] ([[User talk:Parsecboy|talk]]) 16:16, 13 January 2016 (UTC)
::Per Garzke and Dulin: &quot;Our examination of the wreck of Bismarck '''''does not permit us to conclusively determine exactly when the battered stern end fell away''''' - it had almost certainly failed structurally during the capsizing process.  Prior to the capsizing, the stern no longer contributed any buoyancy to the stability and survivability of the battleship. '''''We do know from the testimony of Mr. Statz that Bismarck's stern was in place when he was carried past it by the prevailing seas around 1035. Mr. Statz was within 50 meters of the ship when she capsized and sank.''''' There is the possibility that as the ship sank and righted herself, the hydrodynamic forces caused the stern to fail completely underwater.&quot; Thus an eyewitness saw that the stern was still attached to the hull when the ship finally sank. It probably broke off quite soon thereafter, thus it landed on the bottom far from the main hull, but it was still attached while the ship was on the surface. [[User:Wdford|Wdford]] ([[User talk:Wdford|talk]]) 18:27, 13 January 2016 (UTC)

:::I tend not to place a lot of faith in the testimony of an eyewitness who was in all likelihood in shock. Nevertheless, Ballard suggests the stern separated when the ship capsized, and Statz's account does not contradict that. This seems quite likely, especially when one considers the general weakness of the sterns of other German warships (particularly ''Deutschland'' and ''Prinz Eugen'') and there was no structural support to hold the stern in place upside down. [[User:Parsecboy|Parsecboy]] ([[User talk:Parsecboy|talk]]) 19:45, 13 January 2016 (UTC)

== Messages decoded by Jane Fawcett (nee Hughes)? ==

The main article mentions intercepted messages that helped lead to the sinking of the Bismarck. The decryption of these messages (or message?) was probably done by the recently deceased Jane Fawcett when she was working at Bletchley Park. She isn't even mentioned in that article, though she has her own Wikipedia article (that isn't very visible from external searches). There was once a time when I would have worked on this myself and spent the time to add the appropriate links to the main article (and probably the secondary articles), but mostly lost my motivation to support Wikipedia more actively... [[User:Shanen|Shanen]] ([[User talk:Shanen|talk]]) 07:49, 30 May 2016 (UTC)
:She's now mentioned [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 08:00, 30 May 2016 (UTC)

== Hood deck armor ==
In all likelihood, Hood was not penetrated in the deck, rather in the main belt or by a lucky hit **below** the main belt. [http://www.navweaps.com/Weapons/WNGER_15-52_skc34.php At 13 km, the Bismarck's shells were coming in nearly flat - less than 10 degree angle of fall]. See also [http://www.navweaps.com/index_inro/INRO_Hood_p1.htm this paper]; page 2 is the most relevant.
This misconception (probably originated because Royal Navy command was preoccupied with battlecruiser deck armor after Jutland) isn't present in other articles about Hood's sinking, why here? [[Special:Contributions/66.214.105.178|66.214.105.178]] ([[User talk:66.214.105.178|talk]]) 16:52, 27 August 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>2q1mnqd9s9vqh41sym2n0oc2p0jblxx</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
