<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Halifax Explosion</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>255478</id>
    <revision>
      <id>712422192</id>
      <parentid>712306582</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-03-29T00:33:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lowercase sigmabot III</username>
        <id>17518500</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Archiving 1 discussion(s) to [[Talk:Halifax Explosion/Archive 1]]) (bot</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="19011">{{ArticleHistory
|currentstatus=FA

|action1=WAR
|action1date=04:06, 6 July 2015 (UTC)
|action1link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/Halifax Explosion
|action1result=approved
|action1oldid=669904593

|action2=GAN
|action2date=13:02, 2 June 2015 (UTC)
|action2link=Talk:Halifax Explosion/GA1
|action2result=listed
|action2oldid=

|action3=FAC
|action3date=2015-08-01
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Halifax Explosion/archive1
|action3result=promoted
|action3oldid=673808983
}}

{{talkheader}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Canada|ns=yes|class = FA|importance=high|history=yes}}
{{WikiProject Disaster management|class = FA|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Shipwrecks|importance=high|class = FA}}
{{WPMILHIST|class = FA|A-Class=pass|Maritime=yes|French=yes|Canadian=yes|WWI=yes}}
{{WikiProject History|class = FA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Transport|class = FA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Maritime Trades|class = FA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Explosives|class = FA|importance=high}}
}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2005-12-06|oldid1=30295261|date2=2006-12-06|oldid2=92185179|date3=2007-12-06|oldid3=176113985|date4=2008-12-06|oldid4=256280281|date5=2009-12-06|oldid5=330062009|date6=2012-12-06|oldid6=526757867|date7=2015-12-06|oldid7=694056634}}

{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{talk archive navigation}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 1
|minthreadsleft = 5
|minthreadstoarchive = 1
|algo = old(60d)
|archive = Talk:Halifax Explosion/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{Archives |bot=MiszaBot I|age=60}}

== Largest conventional explosion ==

This page lists the Halifax as the largest conventional explosion in history, yet [[Largest artificial non-nuclear explosions]] lists it as third. This is a problem. [[User:Timothyjosephwood|Timothyjosephwood]] ([[User talk:Timothyjosephwood|talk]]) 03:12, 28 April 2015 (UTC)
:The lead states that &quot;the blast was the largest man-made explosion prior to the development of nuclear weapons&quot; - [[Largest_artificial_non-nuclear_explosions#Rank_order_of_largest_conventional_explosions.2Fdetonations_by_magnitude]] lists other explosions as being larger, but these all post-date the development of nuclear weapons. Later in the article we state that it is the largest ever only according to White's five criteria. [[User:Nikkimaria|Nikkimaria]] ([[User talk:Nikkimaria|talk]]) 12:50, 28 April 2015 (UTC)
::Wow, that's really misleading. Why is the development of nuclear weapons a meaningful date if not to juxtapose nuclear with conventional explosives? You may as well say &quot;the largest explosion prior to the development of chemical weapons&quot; or maybe &quot;the largest explosion prior to the development of tnt&quot; is a better example. If tnt doesn't eclipse the event in question, then there's no reason to mention it. If there were larger conventional explosions then the development of nuclear weapons is a completely arbitrary marker. As it turns out, the Maine was in fact the largest explosion in Cuba following Mark growing a mustache and prior to Mark deciding that mustaches look stupid. [[User:Timothyjosephwood|Timothyjosephwood]] ([[User talk:Timothyjosephwood|talk]]) 15:20, 28 April 2015 (UTC)
:::Seeing as it explicitly says largest prior to nuclear development, I can't agree that it's misleading, but what would you propose instead? The development of nuclear weaponry is relevant as a contrast to conventional explosions, and as eclipsing them. [[User:Nikkimaria|Nikkimaria]] ([[User talk:Nikkimaria|talk]]) 18:52, 28 April 2015 (UTC)
::::I would propose that the article lists it as the third largest single conventional explosion in history, as that seems to be the consensus. The statement as written is explicitly correct, but implicitly misleading. The development of nuclear weapons is relevant if you are comparing conventional explosions to nuclear explosions. The development of nuclear weapons is completely unrelated if you are comparing conventional to conventional. [[User:Timothyjosephwood|Timothyjosephwood]] ([[User talk:Timothyjosephwood|talk]]) 19:09, 28 April 2015 (UTC)
:::::Is that the consensus, though? Many sources name Halifax as &quot;the largest man-made explosion prior to Hiroshima&quot; or similar, relating this event to the development of nuclear weapons. That would be the origin of the phrasing this article currently uses. Any other watchers have thoughts on this? [[User:Nikkimaria|Nikkimaria]] ([[User talk:Nikkimaria|talk]]) 19:39, 28 April 2015 (UTC)
:::::I have never cared for placing anachronisms into articles, and prefer to note what was true at the time.  It is, of course, necessary to note when a 'record' is eclipsed, but that makes this a matter of semantics: Is it better to note it was the largest man-made explosion before Hiroshima?  Or that it was the largest &quot;conventional&quot; explosion until [[Heligoland]]? Personally, I would favour retainin the current wording.  First, because it doesn't artificially eliminate the nuclear events, and second, because being &quot;third largest 'conventional' explosion&quot; in history is rather meaningless in context - the ones ahead of it (and there were three, not two) were just tests done in unpopulated areas. Most importantly, however, is what sources say.  And the ones I have read also favour current wording. [[User:Resolute|Reso]][[User Talk:Resolute|lute]] 20:48, 28 April 2015 (UTC)
:::: I don't think the sentence is in any way misleading and is quite accurate for the lede. The force of the explosion is discussed in detail further down in the article. If any semantic clarifications are necessary they can be added there. The sentence is fine as it is. [[User:Mediatech492|Mediatech492]] ([[User talk:Mediatech492|talk]]) 21:13, 28 April 2015 (UTC)

::::Not misleading at all. It is often talked about in just such a manor. -[[User:Djsasso|DJSasso]] ([[User talk:Djsasso|talk]]) 17:51, 4 May 2015 (UTC)
:::::'''Agreed'''- Regards, &lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid #FFFFFF&quot;&gt;[[User:Aloha27|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#2B65EC;background:#FFFFFF&quot;&gt;'''&amp;nbsp;Aloha27'''&lt;/font&gt;]][[User talk:Aloha27|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#FFFFFF;background:#2B65EC&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;talk&lt;/small&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt; 19:03, 4 May 2015 (UTC)

== Discrepancy in monetary figures ==

I note that in the human loss and destruction section, it is claimed that $25 million was donated for reconstruction efforts and the like.  the Africville sub-section, however, gives a figure of $21 million.  I think we'll need to either determine which figure is correct and use for both, or clarify what each number is referring to if they are meant to represent different figures. [[User:Resolute|Reso]][[User Talk:Resolute|lute]] 16:58, 29 April 2015 (UTC)
:I don't have the Africville source to verify, do you? I've been going through and working on sourcing but haven't gotten to that section yet. [[User:Nikkimaria|Nikkimaria]] ([[User talk:Nikkimaria|talk]]) 17:06, 29 April 2015 (UTC)
::No, and neither does my local library system. [[User:Resolute|Reso]][[User Talk:Resolute|lute]] 19:19, 29 April 2015 (UTC)
:::Okay. The Armstrong source (p. 213) says around $30 million from all sources, including individuals. ''Shattered City'' (p. 83) gives numbers that add up to $24 million but also mentions donations from other sources for which numbers are not provided. ''Canadian Encyclopedia'' says $30 million. I think we'll go with $30 million total. [[User:Nikkimaria|Nikkimaria]] ([[User talk:Nikkimaria|talk]]) 13:04, 30 April 2015 (UTC)

{{Talk:Halifax Explosion/GA1}}

== Pre-collision sequence ==

An editor claims that the pre-collision sequence as presented is inaccurate. I've checked a few different sources and the current description appears to be supported by them, so I've invited him to expand on his concerns here. [[User:Nikkimaria|Nikkimaria]] ([[User talk:Nikkimaria|talk]]) 19:37, 1 September 2015 (UTC)

&lt;small&gt;Response copied from my talk page. [[User:Nikkimaria|Nikkimaria]] ([[User talk:Nikkimaria|talk]]) 14:49, 2 September 2015 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
With all due respect, you have not looked closely enough. It is also not good form to remove my cited source yet keep my text and not revert to the older version. However, let's leave that alone for the time being.

The following two key items in the paragraph were misrepresented or missing In the previous versions and are the ones I corrected: 

Firstly, the Niobe pinnace and the HMS Highflyer whaler were not in close proximity to Stella Maris at the same time as stated. The pinnace came out from Pier 6 as Stella Maris was returning to Mont Blanc after Captain Brannen had towed the whaler part way to Imo so Triggs could assess damages. 

Secondly, the older text went on to state the decision to tow the stern of Mont Blanc from Pier 6 was made by Mattison, Triggs and Brannen. This is not correct - obviously, because Acting Commander Triggs was not there. 

You must remember that not every author has read, let alone absorbed, all of the over 2100 pages of inquiry transcripts. They mostly refer to specific sections. The pagination numbers also differ from those in the shorter Appeals Book. 

Loke Bird, MacDonald is a journalist. Both books contain invented dialogue. Bird's account on pp. 59-60 of &quot;THe Town That Died&quot; is almost entirely fabricated. Although very interesting and useful to some degree, these are trade books. Most times, it is difficult to ascertain where the fiction ends and the actual history begins and vice versa. Laura MacDonald's story on pages 50-51 is also fabricated. No notes whatsoever are included on these pages to offer any credibility to her presentation. 

John Griffith Armstrong's book is a wonderful academic work and quite comprehensive. However, the aforementioned facts are also not represented accurately in his book on pp. 37-38. JGA cites Bird's book as his main source of information - in this instance, with a caveat in his notes that &quot;the book describes itself as a novel.&quot; 

Although he also cites the testimony of the two mates, he still places Triggs on board Stella Maris at the wrong time - even though Walter Brannen makes it crystal clear in his testimony that they had towed Triggs' whaler towards Imo well before the pinnace appeared and the use of the 5 and 10 inch hawsers were considered. Knowing John, I can assure you this was mere oversight. He is by all accounts, a meticulous researcher.

As well, according to the first-hand testimony, at no time were any lines ever attached to Mont Blanc.

It should be noted that these three books have been in circulation for several years. Some key points naturally become outdated as new information is unearthed and more attention is paid to the transcripts. Often, the transcript testimony becomes convoluted and the timelines seem as though they are bounced about like rubber balls. It is easy to understand how even the most experienced researcher can find the record confusing.

Presently, the accurate facts regarding the matter under discussion are found in two published sources only: &quot;Imo vs Mont Blanc&quot; (1919) which contains 800 pages of first-hand inquiry testimony, including that of the first and second mates, Walter Brannen and William Nickerson (resp.) of Stella Maris. The second source, and most recent serious book having to do with the Halifax Explosion, is a comprehensive, fully notated and indexed monograph, &quot;Scapegoat, the extraordinary legal proceedings following the 1917 Halifax Explosion&quot; - self-published, 2012, with a newer edition published by New World Publishing, 2014; also awarded the 2014 Dartmouth Book Award for Non-Fiction and 2015 Bronze IPPY (Independent Book Publisher Awards, NYC). 

In this instance, it was appropriate to choose &quot;Imo vs Mont Blanc&quot; as the cited primary source. This is an underused (with the exception of JGA's book) but exceptional resource. If you wish to view the content for yourself, the transcripts are available online at http://eco.canadiana.ca/view/oocihm.9_05977/2?r=0&amp;s=1 (pp. 376-381 and pp. 484-486, specifically) or read &quot;Scapegoat&quot; - available at  Amazon.ca, Chapters/Indigo, 49th shelf, New World Publishing or bookstores in all four Atlantic Provinces.

My research has been thorough. Primary sources are always the most sought after and utilized. I intend to reintroduce the transcripts citation once again and also put the reference in the bibliography this time - lengthy title et al. I trust my communication has had a positive effect and that you will show restraint and, at least, some appreciation by leaving this material intact. These days, I only contribute to the pages on a relatively small scale. I believe the precept of Wikipedia is: if anyone can make the pages better, then he or she is welcome to do so. That is all I have endeavoured to do.

Thank you and regards,

dheffernen [[User:Dheffernen|Dheffernen]] ([[User talk:Dheffernen|talk]]) 14:00, 2 September 2015 (UTC)

Secondary sources are fine if they are accurate. In this case, the three often cited sources are not accurate on this particular aspect that requires updating. If Wikipedia prefer secondary sources over primary sources, then I will cite the book, Scapegoat as the source because it is the most accurate source of this information to date. Thank you.

Regards, Dheffernen [[User:Dheffernen|Dheffernen]] ([[User talk:Dheffernen|talk]]) 14:07, 2 September 2015 (UTC)
&lt;small&gt;End copied text. [[User:Nikkimaria|Nikkimaria]] ([[User talk:Nikkimaria|talk]]) 14:49, 2 September 2015 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
:[[User:Dheffernen|Dheffernen]], thank you for your detailed response. However, I do have some concerns:
:''Scapegoat'' has a non-scholarly publisher and an author more noted for his work in music than his history background. Because of that, I would be very reluctant to prioritize that source over Armstrong or others
:This is particularly true given the weight of sources that agree with the particular sequence presented - it's not just Bird, Armstrong, and Macdonald, but pretty much every source that discusses the sequence agrees that Triggs headed for the ''Imo'' after the decision was made to tow the ''Mont-Blanc'' and efforts to that effect had begun.
:We could explain the disagreement among sources in the text - ie. this source says X but other source says Y. But we shouldn't ignore that most sources say X. It's not our job to decide that most sources are wrong, but to present what is reported by secondary sources.
:The issue of primary sources we have discussed elsewhere, but suffice it to say that in the context of Wikipedia they are not the most sought after and utilized. [[User:Nikkimaria|Nikkimaria]] ([[User talk:Nikkimaria|talk]]) 15:59, 2 September 2015 (UTC)
::&lt;small&gt;Copied from my talk page. [[User:Nikkimaria|Nikkimaria]] ([[User talk:Nikkimaria|talk]]) 00:22, 3 September 2015 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
::Your skewed logic is most disconcerting. Only a fool judges a book without reading it first. Even worse: making arbitrary conclusions based on what someone has done previously in his or her life, again without reading his work is just plain stupid. Many of the scholars of the explosion including Janet Kitz, Alan Ruffman, Garry Shtlak (Senior Advisor of the Nova Scotia Archives and John Griffith Armstrong have acknowledged the veracity of this work. 
::However, I am going to save you the trouble by reverting back to versions without any input from me. dheffernen [[User:Dheffernen|Dheffernen]] ([[User talk:Dheffernen|talk]]) 22:43, 2 September 2015 (UTC).&lt;small&gt;End copied section. [[User:Nikkimaria|Nikkimaria]] ([[User talk:Nikkimaria|talk]]) 00:22, 3 September 2015 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
:::That's why I'm not proposing removing the work entirely, nor asking you to revert all of your edits. But we need to balance what different sources say. I've made one suggestion above; we could also say that at the time of the explosion Trigg was near the ''Imo'', as sources appear to agree on this. [[User:Nikkimaria|Nikkimaria]] ([[User talk:Nikkimaria|talk]]) 00:45, 3 September 2015 (UTC)

== Page move: Halifax Explosion in popular culture ==


I nominate the page [[Halifax Explosion in popular culture]] be moved into this one, as it discusses aspects of the explosion. Several Wikipedia pages include &quot;In popular culture&quot; or &quot;Legacy&quot; sections on the same page as the main topic. [[User:Yoho2001|Yoho2001]] ([[User talk:Yoho2001|talk]]) 04:59, 3 December 2015 (UTC)
:Hi [[User:Yoho2001|Yoho2001]]. What you're proposing is a [[Help:Merge|merge]], but I disagree with your reasoning. This article already has a &quot;Legacy&quot; section that includes some key cultural works on the topic. However, there are many more cultural references that could be mentioned about the explosion, and including them all here would be [[WP:DUE|undue weight on a single aspect of the topic]]. That's why the more extensive pop-culture content was [[WP:SPLIT|split]] to a standalone article. There are many other examples of standalone &quot;in popular culture&quot; articles - take a look at [[:Category:Topics in popular culture]]. [[User:Nikkimaria|Nikkimaria]] ([[User talk:Nikkimaria|talk]]) 13:08, 3 December 2015 (UTC)

: I agree with Yoho. Not only is the &quot;in popular culture&quot; article hardly notable, it's also short enough to easily merge in. [[User:Prinsgezinde|Bataaf van Oranje]] ([[User talk:Prinsgezinde|talk]]) 12:28, 4 March 2016 (UTC)
::If it is 'hardly notable', then it sounds like trivia that should be deleted, not merged in. [[User:Resolute|Reso]][[User Talk:Resolute|lute]] 15:26, 4 March 2016 (UTC)
: A lot of the things on the in popular culture page would not pass [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Content guide#Popular culture|MILPOP]] and be deleted. [[User:Llammakey|Llammakey]] ([[User talk:Llammakey|talk]]) 16:38, 4 March 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:2|one external link|2 external links}} on [[Halifax Explosion]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=712306506 my edit]. You may add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it, if I keep adding bad data, but formatting bugs should be reported instead. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether, but should be used as a last resort. I made the following changes:
*Attempted to fix sourcing for http://www.forces.gc.ca/site/commun/ml-fe/article-eng.asp?id=2862
*Attempted to fix sourcing for http://www.halifax.ca/HalifaxExplosion/Monuments.html

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=failed}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 09:31, 28 March 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>mnpmqbhb7vrocf9h1lzgtny2p2nrj60</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
