<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Vladimir Lenin</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>41613040</id>
    <revision>
      <id>741271006</id>
      <parentid>741036371</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-26T13:00:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ugly Ketchup</username>
        <id>10884595</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="35238">{{Talk header}}
{{ArticleHistory
|currentstatus=FA

|action1=FAC
|action1date=11:07, 23 August 2006
|action1link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Vladimir Lenin
|action1result=not promoted
|action1oldid=71316682
|aciddate=14 March, 2007

|action2=PR
|action2date=00:24, 16 April 2015
|action2link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Vladimir Lenin/archive1
|action2result=reviewed
|action2oldid=656640752

|action3=GAN
|action3date=09:52, 30 September 2015 (UTC)
|action3link=Talk:Vladimir Lenin/GA1
|action3result=not listed
|action3oldid=683443529

|action4=GAN
|action4date=22:44, 14 April 2016
|action4link=Talk:Vladimir Lenin/GA2
|action4result=listed
|action4oldid=715298766

|action5=PR
|action5date=04:19, 8 May 2016
|action5link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Vladimir Lenin/archive2
|action5result=reviewed
|action5oldid=722876800

|otd1date=2004-04-16
|otd1oldid=6718191
|otd2date=2005-04-16
|otd2oldid=12561118
|otd3date=2006-04-16
|otd3oldid=48688594
|otd4date=2007-04-16
|otd4oldid=123313856
|otd5date=2008-04-16
|otd5oldid=205963014
|otd6date=2013-04-16
|otd6oldid=550595404
|otd7date=2014-04-16
|otd7oldid=604258641
|otd8date=2016-04-16
|otd8oldid=715546300

|action6=FAC
|action6date=2016-09-24
|action6link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Vladimir Lenin/archive1
|action6result=promoted
|action6oldid=740963294
}}
{{Vital article|level=3|topic=People|class=FA}}
{{British English}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Biography|living=no|class=FA|politician-work-group=yes|listas=Lenin, Vladimir Ilyich|core=yes|politician-priority=Top}}
{{WikiProject Soviet Union|class=FA|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Socialism|class=FA|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Russia|class=FA|importance=Top|hist=yes}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=FA
|B-Class-1=no
|B-Class-2=yes
|B-Class-3=yes
|B-Class-4=yes
|B-Class-5=yes
|Russian=yes|WWI=yes}}
{{WikiProject Atheism|class=FA|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Judaism|class=FA|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Politics|class=FA|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Economics|class=FA|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Philosophy|class=FA|importance=low|philosopher=yes}}
{{WP1.0|v0.5=pass|class=FA|importance=High|category=History|VA=yes|WPCD=yes}}|collapsed=yes}}
&lt;!-- please do not remove this tag --&gt;
{{Auto archiving notice|small=no
|age=90
|index=./Archive index
|bot=lowercase sigmabot III}}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn
|target=Talk:Vladimir Lenin/Archive index
|mask=Talk:Vladimir Lenin/Archive &lt;#&gt;
|leading_zeros=0
|indexhere=yes}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 8
|minthreadsleft = 5
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:Vladimir Lenin/Archive %(counter)d
}}

==Pipes quote==
&quot;He informed Gorky that &quot;an intelligent Russian is almost always a Jew or someone with Jewish blood&quot;,{{sfn|Pipes|1990|p=352}} believing that the country's Jewish community had helped to modernise Russia through their artistic, cultural, and scientific achievements, further expressing pride in having some Jewish ancestry.{{sfn|Service|2000|p=470}}&quot;. The original Lenin wording is different: &quot;Русский умник почти всегда еврей или человек с примесью еврейской крови.&quot; It translates as &quot;In Russia any smartass is almost always either a Jew or a halfbreed.&quot; Not very respectful.--[[User:Lute88|Lute88]] ([[User talk:Lute88|talk]]) 14:32, 13 February 2016 (UTC)
:Thanks for your comment [[User:Lute88|Lute88]], but do you have a reliable reference for that translation? Moreover, would not the Service information still stand even if the quote had been mistranslated by Pipes? Remember that the likes of Pipes and Service spent a great deal of time reading through all of Lenin's private and public writings; accordingly they should have a very good understanding of Lenin's personal beliefs and views, including with regard to his view of Jewish Russians. [[User:Midnightblueowl|Midnightblueowl]] ([[User talk:Midnightblueowl|talk]]) 18:48, 13 February 2016 (UTC)
:: It is mentioned by [[Yohanan Petrovsky-Shtern]] in his Lenin's origin study, but I don't have a page #. The quote is too [[WP:UNDUE]] I think.--[[User:Lute88|Lute88]] ([[User talk:Lute88|talk]]) 22:42, 13 February 2016 (UTC)

:::Google translate (for what it's worth) renders that as &quot;Russian nerd almost always a Jew or person with Jewish blood admixture&quot;. The quotation clearly does not use a bald term like &quot;half-breed&quot;, which is offensive in contemporary English. умник (umnik) could be translated as &quot;nerd&quot;, &quot;smartass&quot;, or &quot;clever man&quot;. See [http://translate.academic.ru/%D1%83%D0%BC%D0%BD%D0%B8%D0%BA/ru/en/1]. It seems clear that it is a slang term. The difference here concerns the tone of Lenin's comment (which cannot be discerned from the mere words) and the interpretation put on it. It was clearly true that many of the intellectuals, or educated professionals, in the Russian Empire had some Jewish ancestry, as exemplified by the Old Bolsheviks themselves. I agree that quoting a casual comment here gives undue weight. Lenin's political stance against antisemitism is important. As I said previously, I think his supposed Jewish ancestry should be noted only briefly and in the context of his mixed ethnic background. But this quotation isn't notable and it is possibly misleading.--[[User:Jack Upland|Jack Upland]] ([[User talk:Jack Upland|talk]]) 23:11, 13 February 2016 (UTC)

:::: Well, an intelligent person is UMNITSA, and a person who pretends to be intelligent is an UMNIK, as Lenin has it. PRIMES' is not an admixture, but has a nuance of an impurity.--[[User:Lute88|Lute88]] ([[User talk:Lute88|talk]]) 04:07, 14 February 2016 (UTC)
::::: Volkogonov (or rather his translator) says &quot;the clever Russian is almost always a Jew or has Jewish blood in him.&quot; Interesting quote but I agree probably [[WP:UNDUE]]. [[User:Qzd|Qzd]] ([[User talk:Qzd|talk]]) 21:48, 14 February 2016 (UTC)

:::::I'm not entirely convinced by the arguments presented (due to a lack of reliable sources provided), but there seems to be a broad consensus in favour of removing the prose in question. [[User:Midnightblueowl|Midnightblueowl]] ([[User talk:Midnightblueowl|talk]]) 11:27, 15 February 2016 (UTC)

::::::An &quot;umnik&quot; is NOT a &quot;smart-ass&quot;, though it is may be used sarcastically like anything else. An umnik is a clever or smart fellow. Anyone who can read a Russian dictionary should be able to verify this definition. Note that I am talking about the traditional - literary definition, one that is closer to Lenin's Russian. Of course in modern-day Russian vernacular, umnik is frequently used sarcastically (Russian vernacular is notorious for using positive words to imply the opposite of the formal definition). Volkogonov's translation is correct and stylistically accurate. Pipes is also correct, but less stylistically accurate. Lute88's unsourced translation is way off.[[User:Guccisamsclub|Guccisamsclub]] ([[User talk:Guccisamsclub|talk]]) 17:13, 13 March 2016 (UTC)

As an update, I have procured a copy of Yohanan Petrovsky-Shtern's ''Lenin's Jewish Question'' and have relied upon it when discussing Lenin's relationship with his Jewishness. Interestingly, on page 98 it states that &quot;Lenin mentioned to Gorky that a clever Russian &quot;was almost always a Jew or a person with mixed Jewish blood.&quot;&quot; Again, it goes for &quot;clever&quot; rather than &quot;smartass&quot;, although is not referring to that term as if it were a direct quote. [[User:Midnightblueowl|Midnightblueowl]] ([[User talk:Midnightblueowl|talk]]) 12:22, 22 February 2016 (UTC)
:YPS transslation is a bit &quot;polite&quot;: http://dictionary.reverso.net/russian-english/%D1%83%D0%BC%D0%BD%D0%B8%D0%BA . But the consensus seems to tend to WP:UNDUE anyway.--[[User:Lute88|Lute88]] ([[User talk:Lute88|talk]]) 14:27, 22 February 2016 (UTC)
::Considering Lenin worked with Trotsky, Zinoviev, Kamenev, Bela Kun etc, I don't think he was an anti-semite. Having read various works by Lenin, I don't think he would be fazed by being called a &quot;smartass&quot;. It's not an insult in his book(s). However, I think we should stick to unambiguous sources. With regard to his ancestry, I would describe it as Russian, Central Asian, and Jewish, and there are abundant sources which back this up.--[[User:Jack Upland|Jack Upland]] ([[User talk:Jack Upland|talk]]) 19:12, 25 February 2016 (UTC)
:::Yes, I don't think that anyone can present a serious argument that Lenin was anti-Semitic (and nor am I aware of any historians specialising in revolutionary Russia that have done so, although I could be wrong). As Petrovsky-Shtern's (very interesting) book makes plain, there is definitely evidence that Lenin himself identified as an ethnic Russian. This is accompanied by clear evidence that he had maternal Jewish ancestry, but it is unlikely that he was aware of the latter, which was only brought to light by the genealogical research of his sister Anna that she undertook after his death. Although treated as undisputed fact in some published sources, Lenin's paternal ethnic links to the non-Russian peoples of Central Asia seem more speculative; certainly Service suggests that it remains a case of 'not proven' and thus I think that in this article we should follow his lead by not presenting it as if it were an undeniable fact. [[User:Midnightblueowl|Midnightblueowl]] ([[User talk:Midnightblueowl|talk]]) 16:14, 29 February 2016 (UTC)
::::When you say that Lenin himself identified as an ethnic Russian, what do you mean? What did he actually say...?--[[User:Jack Upland|Jack Upland]] ([[User talk:Jack Upland|talk]]) 15:54, 2 March 2016 (UTC)

{{Reflist talk}}

== Semi-protected edit request on 23 February 2016 ==

{{edit semi-protected|Vladimir Lenin|answered=y}}
&lt;!-- Be sure to state UNAMBIGUOUSLY your suggested changes; editors who can edit the protected page need to know what to add or remove. Blank edit requests WILL be declined. --&gt;
&lt;!-- Begin request --&gt;
Lenin has never organized Gulag or sent people to Gulag. This concentration camp was established six years after his death under the rule of Stalin.
&lt;!-- End request --&gt;
[[Special:Contributions/162.44.245.110|162.44.245.110]] ([[User talk:162.44.245.110|talk]]) 18:25, 23 February 2016 (UTC)
: [[File:Red information icon with gradient background.svg|20px|link=]] '''Not done:''' please provide [[WP:RS|reliable sources]] that support the change you want to be made.&lt;!-- Template:ESp --&gt; [[User:EvergreenFir|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:#8b00ff;&quot;&gt;Eve&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#6528c2;&quot;&gt;rgr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#3f5184;&quot;&gt;een&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#197947;&quot;&gt;Fir&lt;/span&gt;''']] [[User talk:EvergreenFir|(talk)]] &lt;small&gt;Please &amp;#123;&amp;#123;[[Template:re|re]]&amp;#125;&amp;#125;&lt;/small&gt; 18:45, 23 February 2016 (UTC)

The anonymous claim is factually untrue. We have reliable sources testifying to the fact that the Soviet concentration camps were initially established under Lenin's government. They may well have been expanded under Stalin's regime, but their origins can be found with Lenin's administration and its Cheka. [[User:Midnightblueowl|Midnightblueowl]] ([[User talk:Midnightblueowl|talk]]) 13:06, 25 February 2016 (UTC)

:Essentially, a &quot;gulag&quot; is a prison. Lenin's Russia/USSR had prisons. But so what? Case closed.--[[User:Jack Upland|Jack Upland]] ([[User talk:Jack Upland|talk]]) 19:16, 25 February 2016 (UTC)
:: I have changed Gulag labor camps into concentration camps to avoid anachronism. They were not named like this in Lenin's time. I kept the wiki link to [[Gulag]] as more useful than [[concentration camp]] [[User:Alex Bakharev|Alex Bakharev]] ([[User talk:Alex Bakharev|talk]]) 06:25, 10 March 2016 (UTC)

:::&quot;Concentration camp&quot; is not appropriate and therefore shouldn't be used.--[[User:Jack Upland|Jack Upland]] ([[User talk:Jack Upland|talk]]) 11:36, 17 May 2016 (UTC)

{{Talk:Vladimir Lenin/GA2}}

== Second paragraph begins &quot;Born to a wealthy middle class family&quot; -- this is not accurate ==

Hello,

There is no such thing as a &quot;wealthy middle class family&quot;; if a family is &quot;wealthy&quot;, then you could say &quot;Born to a wealthy family&quot;. Lenin's family was middle-class; if they were doing very well as a middle-class family, then you could say &quot;Born to a well-to-do middle class familY...&quot;

Thank you,

Kim Iannone
American Public University
Touro University Moscow
facebook.com/kim.iannone  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/104.172.244.99|104.172.244.99]] ([[User talk:104.172.244.99|talk]]) 04:51, 6 May 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Aren't &quot;wealthy&quot; and &quot;well-to-do&quot; simply synonyms? [https://www.google.co.uk/#q=wealthy+define Google certainly seems to think so]. [[User:Midnightblueowl|Midnightblueowl]] ([[User talk:Midnightblueowl|talk]]) 18:23, 6 May 2016 (UTC)

:Generally we say Upper-Middle for middle class people that make several hundred thousand dollars a yr - lower-middle class are people that have risen above the financially lower-class but still have to watch their wallets.  [[Special:Contributions/98.67.180.196|98.67.180.196]] ([[User talk:98.67.180.196|talk]]) 19:31, 15 May 2016 (UTC)

::It seems biased in context (in the lead). His father was a child of serfs of a mixed, non-white ethnic background. The lead also says he died in a mansion. It sounds like the lead is trying to emphasise how wealthy Lenin was.--[[User:Jack Upland|Jack Upland]] ([[User talk:Jack Upland|talk]]) 11:58, 20 August 2016 (UTC)
:::Don't impose clueless American concepts of class identity on a Marxist topic.  The middle classes are professionals, the bourgeoisie, while the upper classes are the nobility and the large landowners, the leisured classes.  Remember that the means of production are owned by the bourgeoisie; how can this be possible if the wealthy aren't in the middle class?  [[User:Nyttend|Nyttend]] ([[User talk:Nyttend|talk]]) 13:45, 23 August 2016 (UTC)

::::He wasn't wealthy in a Russian context, which is what matters.--[[User:Jack Upland|Jack Upland]] ([[User talk:Jack Upland|talk]]) 20:44, 23 August 2016 (UTC)
:::::Or was he? Reading Orlando Figes, he seemed also to suggest that his family was rather wealthy. They family owned an estate, Lenin was therefore also a squire. He even sued his peasant neighbours for damage to the family estate in 1891, during the famine. He also lived 'handsomely of' the 'rents and interest from the sale of his mother's estate.' At one point in Geneva 1904, Lenin described himself as a 'scion of the landed gentry', during an argument where Olminsky attacked Valentinov for his gentry background, as Lenin himself came from a gentry background and had engaged in a nostalgic discussion with Valentinov. In the same quote he also elaborates on how he enjoyed eating strawberries and drinking fresh milk despite he not having planted/milked it. The Ulianov family's life is described as 'charmed' at one point too. Considering the extreme and widespread poverty of the Russian peasantry, which constituated most of Russia's population, the family was indeed wealthy. I think trying to say otherwise is to impose on him more humble origins than he had, when he by most aspects lived as a nobleman, priding himself at one point in writing 'hereditary nobleman' in front of his name signing a document. And, as I said, considering the general poverty of Russian society, his family was indeed wealthy.--[[User:Simen113|Simen113]] ([[User talk:Simen113|talk]]) 00:58, 24 August 2016 (UTC)

::::::He was a &quot;hereditary nobleman&quot; in that his father had been given the Order of Vladimir for his services to the education of ethnic minorities. A son of a school inspector did not really qualify as a &quot;hereditary nobleman&quot;! I think that document you are referring to was a personal favour to someone else, and he was trying to influence officialdom by claiming nobility. &quot;Gentry&quot; is more accurate than &quot;nobility&quot;. Which means middle class. He was better off than the peasants, but far beneath the top nobility who owned most of the land. Saying &quot;wealthy middle class&quot; is unnecessary. And possibly confusing. It could be used about the Fabergé family...--[[User:Jack Upland|Jack Upland]] ([[User talk:Jack Upland|talk]]) 02:36, 24 August 2016 (UTC)

== Kalmyk ==

I was directed here after trying to make a referenced addition to the text, which was removed. According to Orlando Figes, Lenin's ancestry was Kalmyk. I can't see that any of the other ethnic claims listed is referenced, so I do not understand why a referenced suggestion is removed.--[[User:Simen113|Simen113]] ([[User talk:Simen113|talk]]) 20:14, 11 July 2016 (UTC)
:Hello Simen113 and thanks for bringing this to the Talk Page. There were various reasons as to why why I removed your recent additions (which can be seen [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Vladimir_Lenin&amp;diff=729312981&amp;oldid=729289180 here]). First, this article is currently undergoing FAC, so we need to be cautious about any significant alterations or additions of text at this point, unless they are specifically required by the FAC commentators. Second, the text added was just too lengthy and introduced too much extraneous information on Lenin's childhood; we already have [[Early life of Vladimir Lenin]] for that extra material. Third, the referencing system used was different to that which this article employs, which creates inconsistency and would again cause problems at FAC. Fourth, the claims being made my Figes are not necessarily accurate. Figes' book is a general overview of the Russian Revolution, not a biography of Lenin specifically. Thus, can we believe him when he claims that Lenin's paternal ancestry was partly Kalmyk, particularly when biographers who have investigated this area in far greater depth, such as Robert Service, don't mention this at all, but rather cite other ethnic groups as possible antecessors? I'm not so sure. [[User:Midnightblueowl|Midnightblueowl]] ([[User talk:Midnightblueowl|talk]]) 22:53, 11 July 2016 (UTC)
::Thanks for replying. Orlando Figes is known for being his deep knowledge on the subject of the revolution, and there are no one more central to it than Lenin. I am therefore sure he can be cited on this. I do agree that it is not a book focusing on Lenin, but considering how Figes is known for diving into archives and uncover new material, one cannot exclude the possibility that this is something he has found clear indications for. Considering the book was written in 2014, it is also pretty recent. As for the reference style, I suggest you (with better  knowledge of the format) convert my reference into the system used. As Figes has written deeply on the Revolution, the book is sure to be referenced again. --[[User:Simen113|Simen113]] ([[User talk:Simen113|talk]]) 03:35, 12 July 2016 (UTC)
:::See &quot;Ethnic background&quot; above. Many people appear to claim he was Kalmyk.--[[User:Jack Upland|Jack Upland]] ([[User talk:Jack Upland|talk]]) 04:27, 12 July 2016 (UTC)
::What evidence does Figes provide to support his claim about Lenin's Kalmyk ancestry? If we can find good evidence then I'm more than happy to see it incorporated briefly, but I do think that we need to be cautious on this one. [[User:Midnightblueowl|Midnightblueowl]] ([[User talk:Midnightblueowl|talk]]) 13:35, 12 July 2016 (UTC)
:::There are no footnote directly after the claim in question, but the closest one, situated at the end of the paragraph, reads as follows: &quot;Kerensky, ''Crucifixion'', 13; Volkogonov, ''Lenin'', 5, 8–9, 13.&quot;. I therefore assume it is from Volkogonov Figes gets his information regarding Lenin, at least where he decides to cite it too (it may obviously be something he has found other places as well), and that the footnote is relevant to the claim as it cites several pages and sources.--[[User:Simen113|Simen113]] ([[User talk:Simen113|talk]]) 16:45, 12 July 2016 (UTC)
::::Thanks for checking, Simen113. I don't have a copy of Volkogonov's biography to hand but will try and check it out in the next few days. [[User:Midnightblueowl|Midnightblueowl]] ([[User talk:Midnightblueowl|talk]]) 16:56, 12 July 2016 (UTC)
:::::No problem. Thanks for being receptive of my feedback and comments. As for the other information, I will add it to the article on his chilhood and early life. Awaiting your reply upon checking Volkogonov in the meantime. Have a good day!--[[User:Simen113|Simen113]] ([[User talk:Simen113|talk]]) 17:47, 12 July 2016 (UTC)
::::::[[User:Simen113]] - I've accessed a copy of Volkogonov, and (on page 7) he does indeed suggest a Kalmyk origin for some of Lenin's ancestors. I'll add this into the article, alongside the mentions of the Chuvash and Mordvin. Best, [[User:Midnightblueowl|Midnightblueowl]] ([[User talk:Midnightblueowl|talk]]) 20:41, 16 July 2016 (UTC)
:::::::Thank you, good luck on the rest, and have a good day! I will add my information to the Early life of Lenin article.--[[User:Simen113|Simen113]] ([[User talk:Simen113|talk]]) 01:00, 17 July 2016 (UTC)

== Lede image in infobox ==

As part of the process of getting this article through FAC (which is still ongoing), I've found that there is a real issue in attaining a good quality portrait image of Lenin for the infobox. While we have plenty of old, black-and-white portrait photographs of Lenin circulating on Wikipedia and Wikimedia, it appears that in almost all cases the &quot;Public Domain&quot; tags that have been placed onto them are spurious: just because an image is old, taken in the 1920s or before, doesn't mean that it is in the public domain either within the Russian Federation or in the United States. Accordingly, I have been forced to resort to File:19190501-lenin speech red square.jpg, one of the few images that can be verified as being in the public domain (this is because we can ascertain that its author died prior to 1942, which makes it PD in Russia). However, this image isn't the best portrait of Lenin, and so I was hoping that anyone with a good understanding of PD issues and (ideally) access to original Russian language sources might be able to help choose a more appropriate alternative that can be properly verified as PD. For instance, a whole load of Lenin portraits can be found [https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Category:Portrait_photographs_of_Vladimir_Lenin here], but in almost every case the PD claims are dubious and need to be bolstered. Any help would be gratefully appreciated. [[User:Midnightblueowl|Midnightblueowl]] ([[User talk:Midnightblueowl|talk]]) 12:17, 7 August 2016 (UTC)
:Well, I hope you get one, because that current image makes it look like he is giving a Nazi salute (Trump-style!).--[[User:Jack Upland|Jack Upland]] ([[User talk:Jack Upland|talk]]) 13:19, 7 August 2016 (UTC)
:: Yep. [[User:NightShadow23|Federal Chancellor (NightShadow)]] ([[User talk:NightShadow23|talk]]) 11:10, 1 September 2016 (UTC)
:Maybe so, but the current image has to remain until we can find an alternative that has an appropriate Public Domain tag on it. [[User:Midnightblueowl|Midnightblueowl]] ([[User talk:Midnightblueowl|talk]]) 17:37, 1 September 2016 (UTC)
:I've added a new image that doesn't appear to have a copyright issue. -- [[User:Hazhk|Hazhk]] ([[User talk:Hazhk|talk]]) 17:59, 18 September 2016 (UTC)
::I've checked this new image. It has the same copyright problems. Someone has stuck a PD tag onto it but not provided the proper proviso for why this is the case. Accordingly, I've reverted to the previous image. Sorry, but it has to be done. [[User:Midnightblueowl|Midnightblueowl]] ([[User talk:Midnightblueowl|talk]]) 17:17, 19 September 2016 (UTC)

I've done some delving and [https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Lenin1897.jpg this image] (File:Lenin1897.jpg) would also be usable as we can clearly demonstrate why it is in the Public Domain. It shows Lenin's face in a clearer manner than the present image, although unfortunately depicts him in his younger years, long before he became Soviet leader. [[User:Midnightblueowl|Midnightblueowl]] ([[User talk:Midnightblueowl|talk]]) 18:17, 19 September 2016 (UTC)
:Further delving has produced [https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:LeninEnSuizaMarzo1916--barbaroussovietr00mcbr.png#.7B.7Bint:filedesc.7D.7D this image], which I am pretty sure is PD too. This depicts Lenin's facial features in far better detail and was taken only a year before he took power in Russia. It seems like our best bet right now, so I'll stick it into the lede infobox. [[User:Midnightblueowl|Midnightblueowl]] ([[User talk:Midnightblueowl|talk]]) 18:27, 19 September 2016 (UTC)

== Issues with the Lead ==

:Under Lenin's government, the Bolsheviks renamed themselves the Communist Party and established a one-party state. His regime abolished Russia's elected Constituent Assembly...
The state was not a one-party state at that point. The Constituent Assembly was abolished in favour of the soviet system, which was also elected. The summary seems to be biased and historically inaccurate.
:...critics on both the left and right see him as the founder of a totalitarian dictatorship responsible for civil war and mass human rights abuses.
Is there really any support for this??? In particular, was Lenin really responsible for the civil war??? Would other parties have really not started war if Lenin had adopted different policies???--[[User:Jack Upland|Jack Upland]] ([[User talk:Jack Upland|talk]]) 12:07, 20 August 2016 (UTC)

::I agree that the establishment of a one-party state was not something that happened as soon as the Bolsheviks took power — they were in a coalition with the Left Socialist Revolutionaries for six months or so — but I nevertheless feel that this is the best place to mention it in the lede (bear in mind that we have to keep things very concise and to the point in that lede). That being said, I'm open to suggestions if you feel that it would work better elsewhere. Perhaps we could replace &quot;established&quot; with &quot;gradually established&quot;? 

::Whether Lenin actually was or was not responsible for civil war is somewhat immaterial on this point. What is significant is that he was accused of having some responsibility for it. Indeed, as we mention in the article, the Mensheviks accused him of trying to foment civil war before it had even broken out! On a personal level I think it likely that reactionary and pro-Tsarist forces would have probably launched attacks on the government regardless of what policies Lenin pursued, but there appears to be a fairly strong argument that Lenin's antagonistic attitude toward other socialist and perhaps even liberal groups (Mensheviks, Socialist Revolutionaries, Kadets etc) really didn't help things. He had the opportunity to establish a pan-socialist coalition when he took power, and deliberately chose not to, despite the fact that the Socialist Revolutionary Party clearly held greater public support than his Bolsheviks. Instead he decided to crack down on many rival socialist groups, and certainly didn't seek to enter peace talks with them after the conflict broke out. [[User:Midnightblueowl|Midnightblueowl]] ([[User talk:Midnightblueowl|talk]]) 15:55, 21 August 2016 (UTC)

:::The Left SRs left the government because they didn't accept the peace treaty signed with Germany. They then tried to assassinate Lenin, killed the German ambassador, and joined the other side in the civil war. It wasn't the Bolsheviks who established the one-party state; it was other parties that abandoned the polity. The text in the lead is about present-day critics (who &quot;see him as&quot;...). However, the Legacy section quotes several people who deny Lenin was a dictator, and there is no mention of the civil war. That's why I asked what is the support for this.--[[User:Jack Upland|Jack Upland]] ([[User talk:Jack Upland|talk]]) 23:51, 21 August 2016 (UTC)

::::The idea that the Bolsheviks were not responsible for establishing a one-party state is highly debatable and very contentious. It is not a statement that I agree with; after all, the Bolshevik administration banned various rival parties like the Kadets and interned the members of many others, like the Mensheviks, in labour camps. However, this really isn't the place to discuss our respective opinions on such things. As to the idea that Lenin was responsible for civil war, we do cite that this was what the Mensheviks believed in the &quot;February Revolution and the July Days: 1917&quot; of the article. Admittedly however, we don't provide any evidence that later critics have charged him with responsibility of the Civil War. So perhaps a change is required on these grounds; either we remove mention of civil war from that final sentence in the lede, or we change the wording so that it is no longer only in the present tense. [[User:Midnightblueowl|Midnightblueowl]] ([[User talk:Midnightblueowl|talk]]) 10:33, 22 August 2016 (UTC)

:::::The Mensheviks weren't banned until 1921. It would be better to say &quot;gradually established&quot;, rather than just &quot;established&quot;. But, in context, the word &quot;established&quot; implies something like the [[Article 6 of the Soviet Constitution]]. This is misleading. Is it even necessary to mention it here? The lead has already said, &quot;Under his administration, Russia and then the wider Soviet Union became a one-party communist state governed by the Russian Communist Party.&quot; This is factual and undeniable. Why return to this point again? On the Civil War, I think the last sentence is an attempt to summarise the &quot;Legacy&quot; section, and that's what it should do. This sentence also implies that left and right critics agree, which isn't necessarily true. There are other issues in the same vein. &quot;His regime abolished Russia's elected Constituent Assembly...&quot; Well, it was his regime which held the election in the first place. Also, as I said before, the lead doesn't mention the soviets, which were also elected. &quot;Ruling by decree...&quot;. The article [[Rule by decree]], which is linked to, states, &quot;Rule by decree allows the ruler to arbitrarily create law, without approval by a legislative assembly.&quot; But the &quot;decrees&quot; mentioned were passed by the Congress of Soviets. I understand the need to summarise, but the lead seems slanted towards the view of Lenin as a totalitarian dictator, rather than something more nuanced.--[[User:Jack Upland|Jack Upland]] ([[User talk:Jack Upland|talk]]) 04:47, 23 August 2016 (UTC)

:::::I'm open to removing &quot;one-party state&quot; from that third paragraph if you feel it necessary, Jack. That would perhaps allow us greater space to make mention of the soviets, which I agree are worthy of a mention. [[User:Midnightblueowl|Midnightblueowl]] ([[User talk:Midnightblueowl|talk]]) 10:30, 23 August 2016 (UTC)
::::::I have now done this. Other issues are perhaps a little more controversial. Yes, the Constituent Assembly was elected under Lenin's period of governance, but he had personally opposed this election and it was, in effect, a hangover from the Provisional Government who had promised it in the first place. Conversely, the Assembly's abolition was all the work of Lenin and the Bolsheviks; so, in having to summarise things for the lede, I would say that the abolition is noteworthy, the establishment probably isn't. Moreover, I'm not sure that it is fair to say that the lede is &quot;slanted towards the view of Lenin as a totalitarian dictator&quot;, for I have tried very hard to steer a neutral path while sticking to the Reliable Sources (bear in mind that many editors would have it start with &quot;Lenin was a Russian communist dictator&quot; etc and I have to bear their attitudes in mind). Also bear in mind that most (not all) Reliable Sources produced by historians specialising in this period do tend to the view that he led a totalitarian dictatorship; that is, effectively, the &quot;standard view&quot; of Lenin. Sure, he has some admirers in the Marxist-Leninist movement and other sectors of the global Far Left, but even in that milieu he is widely despised by more libertarian-oriented Marxists, anarchists, and socialists, and certainly as you move toward the centre-left, into the centre and then on to the political Right you will find him vilified. Lenin is, on the whole, a pretty unpopular figure. [[User:Midnightblueowl|Midnightblueowl]] ([[User talk:Midnightblueowl|talk]]) 11:54, 23 August 2016 (UTC)

:::::::The question isn't whether he is popular. Readers can make up their own mind. Wikipedia is supposed to be neutral and factual.--[[User:Jack Upland|Jack Upland]] ([[User talk:Jack Upland|talk]]) 20:50, 23 August 2016 (UTC)

::::::::Very true, and I have always attempted to ensure that the lede and the article does provide an overview of the facts of his life, but we also have to rely on the Reliable Sources and not push fringe ideas. According to [[Wikipedia:Fringe theories]], &quot;Wikipedia summarizes significant opinions with representation in proportion to their prominence. A Wikipedia article should not make a fringe theory appear more notable or more widely accepted than it is.&quot; My point being that 'Lenin as leader of a totalitarian dictatorship' is the standard interpretation among his biographers and experts of this period of Russian history. The image of 'Lenin the radical democrat' is — comparatively speaking — a fringe perspective, held by very few people, the majority of them being Marxist-Leninists or adherents of other Far Left sects. I certainly wouldn't want to see the latter perspective eclipsed from the article, but at the same time it should not be given a prominence that it does not accord. [[User:Midnightblueowl|Midnightblueowl]] ([[User talk:Midnightblueowl|talk]]) 09:05, 24 August 2016 (UTC)

:::::::::Thank you for accepting some of the changes I made. I don't think I was attempting to portray Lenin as a radical democrat, or anything else. I think we have to set out the facts, and people can make up their own minds. Unlike &quot;reliable sources&quot;, Wikipedia has a NPOV policy. This is a significant difference. Neutrality can be difficult, but it can also be easy. The Constituent Assembly (for example) is hard to weave into a seamless narrative about the Russian Revolution. But we don't need to do that. We don't need to interpret it. Facts are facts. And, as Lenin himself said, facts are stubborn things.--[[User:Jack Upland|Jack Upland]] ([[User talk:Jack Upland|talk]]) 10:33, 24 August 2016 (UTC)

::::::::::I think that we are pretty much on the same page here with regard to how we want this article to look. However, I am perhaps not so eager as yourself to say &quot;Facts are facts&quot; and leave it that. Facts are indeed stubborn things. We have to select which facts to include in the article, which to put in the lede, and which to omit. We have to choose how to phrase information. We also have to acknowledge people's opinions, and present ''the existence'' of their opinion as a fact. It all gets quite complicated, for facts are intertwined in a whole quagmire of interpretation and subjective perspective. I hope that the page as it currently looks is pretty good though; certainly it is receiving a lot of support over at FAC. [[User:Midnightblueowl|Midnightblueowl]] ([[User talk:Midnightblueowl|talk]]) 20:39, 25 August 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>icqjztxfp5yeqw5t5mdzp5ud2c28m8w</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
