<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Canadian National Vimy Memorial</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>3478937</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749382491</id>
      <parentid>736365016</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-14T01:35:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Notification of altered sources needing review #IABot (v1.2.7.1)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="59886">
{{Talkheader}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN 
|action1date=2009-10-16 
|action1link=Talk:Canadian National Vimy Memorial/GA1 
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=320060639

|action2=WAR
|action2date=00:33, 25 November 2009 (UTC)
|action2link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/Canadian National Vimy Memorial
|action2result=approved
|action2oldid=326930909

|action3=FAC
|action3date=21:47, 19 January 2010
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Canadian National Vimy Memorial/archive1
|action3result=not promoted
|action3oldid=337356816

|topic =war and military
|currentstatus=FA

|action4=FAC
|action4date=2016-03-11
|action4link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Canadian National Vimy Memorial/archive3
|action4result=failed
|action4oldid=708596523

|action5=FAC
|action5date=2016-08-26
|action5link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Canadian National Vimy Memorial/archive4
|action5result=promoted
|action5oldid=736304902
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|collapsed=yes|1=
{{WikiProject Military history|class=FA|A-Class=pass|Canadian=yes|Memorials=yes|WWI=yes}}
{{WikiProject Canada|class=FA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject France|class=FA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Architecture|class=FA|importance=Mid }}
{{WikiProject Public art|class=FA}}
}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2005-06-29|oldid1=17825398|date2=2006-06-29|oldid2=61187225|date3=2007-06-29|oldid3=141285165|date4=2010-07-26|oldid4=375616726|date5=2012-07-26|oldid5=504032970|date6=2014-07-26|oldid6=618572703|date7=2016-07-26|oldid7=731421439}}
{{Canadian English}}

==Ownership==

Well it technically isn't in France as it's Canadian soil. It's surrounded by France, used to be part of France but is Canadian. - [[User:Burwellian|JVG]] 09:31, 20 December 2005 (UTC)
:The UN is in New York, even though it is international territory. Seems like splitting hairs to me, especially as its political status is mentioned in the next sentences. But I defer. - [[User:Randwicked|Randwicked]] 13:10, 20 December 2005 (UTC)
The Vimy Memorial Site is Canadian owned but it is not Canadian territory in the same sense as an embassy. French laws still apply to the site, of which there are a specific set for conduct of the memorial site. For instance, the ban on dogs at the site is in fact a french law. --[[User:Labattblueboy|Labattblueboy]] 05:16, 8 April 2006 (UTC)

::Indeed, it is ''owned by'' Canada, but that is totally a different issue from it being ''under the sovereignty of'' Canada.  I have added a fact tag to a statement that it is &quot;Canadian territory&quot; and will remove it unless a strong legal source is provided to back up this claim, which will not be forthcoming. [[User:Lexicon|Lexicon]] &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Lexicon|(talk)]]&lt;/small&gt; 18:38, 13 July 2007 (UTC)

==Working Statues==
Added section saying that the working copies of the statues at Vimy are now on display in Canada.  [[User:Burtonpe|Burtonpe]] 16:10, 6 January 2006 (UTC)

== trivia and the railway car ==

Although Hitler may have ordered the destruction of various memorials, is it not the case that these orders were not necessarily carried out? For example, wasn't the armistice railway car used again in WW2? [[User:203.198.237.30|203.198.237.30]] 05:10, 7 March 2006 (UTC)

Who said the orders were carried out?  Paris is still there, right?  The article clearly says &quot;ordered&quot;, nowhere does it indicate all those orders were carried out.  And no, the original railway car is not there, it was destroyed in WW II - AFTER Hitler made &lt;s&gt;them&lt;/s&gt; [France] sign the surrender to Germany in it, in a touch of deliberate historical irony.[[User:Michael Dorosh|Michael Dorosh]] 06:02, 7 March 2006 (UTC)

*&lt;s&gt;Mike&lt;/s&gt;''(Michael is the name given above, please do not assume familiarity, especially in the absence of any self identification on your part[[User:Michael Dorosh|Michael Dorosh]] 17:41, 7 March 2006 (UTC))'', I hope your first comment isn't an accurate reflection of your character. This kind of reaction is so over the top and against the very essence of WP that the decent thing would be to apologise. Leaving the ironic unpleasantness of your comment to one side, do I really need to point out that regardless of what actually happened, your earlier wording ''implied'' they were carried out: ''&quot;While other monuments in France were ordered destroyed by Hitler (ranging from the rail car in which the Armistice had been signed in 1918 to the entire city of Paris)...&quot;''. Mentioning the railway car (destroyed) and Paris (obviously not destroyed) together would be potentially confusing to some readers. So yes, obviously not all orders were carried out and I will reinstate mention of the railway car. We could also reinstate Paris but only if we removed any possibility of confusion by including a bit on how area commanders did not follow through. [[User:203.198.237.30|203.198.237.30]] 11:43, 7 March 2006 (UTC)
**The railway car was not destroyed by Hitler himself, but was transported to a museum in Germany, where it was promptly destroyed by an American or British bomb in the later years of the war. See Shirer. [[User:Gerolsteiner]] 16:10, 23 April 2006

My understanding is that Hitler never any intention at all of razing the Vimy Memorial. While it commemorated the defeat of German forces, he greatly respected the fact that there was no hint of triumphalism at all in the artwork.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Consulzephyr|Consulzephyr]] ([[User talk:Consulzephyr|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Consulzephyr|contribs]]) 00:01, 11 May 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Getting back to the comment, The information provided by the guides at the Memorial was that Hitler specifically ordered that WWI memorials not be touched. So I believe the posted information to be incorrect and should be removed. My understanding, There were only 2 WWI memorials destoryed between 1940-1944 one was an Austrailian that had the German eagle getting stomped on by a solider - in a fashion common in propoganda posters, and another memorial that referred to the Germans as &quot;barbarians&quot;. This Triva might be interesting for the Talk section but should be removed from the main article. [[User:Wakemp|Wakemp]] 15:41, 7 March 2006 (UTC)
:::Unfortunately, the &quot;anonymous&quot; user's edit completely changed the nature of the comments.  It was not meant to imply that Vimy was ever in danger of being destroyed - it clearly wasn't.  I did want to introduce the notion that while Hitler had no qualms about destroying culturally significant landmarks (he did order Paris burned, and he did destroy the railcar, which did not need such a lengthy rewording) he both visited Vimy and had respect for the soldiers that fought there - since he considered himself one of them.  I'm not happy with the rewording by &quot;anonymous&quot; and will change the wording to reflect Wakemp's comments.[[User:Michael Dorosh|Michael Dorosh]] 17:40, 7 March 2006 (UTC)
*MD, great maturity and integrity in your characterisations. My edits were based entirely on your material. The necessary elaborations we now have resulted from that. Nice way to conduct the genuine synthesis which we all usually attempt to strive for here. [[User:203.198.237.30|203.198.237.30]] 05:40, 9 March 2006 (UTC)

*Added in the pic of Hitler at the Memorial....not sure about copyright status of this pic, can anyone help with this?  [[User:Burtonpe|Burtonpe]] 14:43, 7 June 2006 (UTC)
:It's fair dinkum, mate, but I can't edit the licensing. Reupload it and identify it as public domain.[[User:Michael Dorosh|Michael Dorosh]] 15:11, 7 June 2006 (UTC)
::I'll take care of it. &amp;ndash; [[User:Ugen64|ugen64]] 05:02, 29 June 2006 (UTC)
::Just for future reference, the image isn't old enough to be public domain (specifically, the creator can't have died more than 70 years ago as per German copyright law because the picture's not that old). But it is fair use so I have tagged it that way. (I could have sworn there was a specific Nazi Germany copyright tag...) &amp;ndash; [[User:Ugen64|ugen64]] 05:10, 29 June 2006 (UTC)
:::Interesting info; is there a listing somewhere of all the copyright laws as they might pertain to WP listed in a central place somewhere I wonder?[[User:Michael Dorosh|&lt;font color=&quot;olive&quot;&gt;'''''Michael Dorosh'''''&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;small&gt;'''''[[User talk:Michael Dorosh|&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/font&gt;]]'''''&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 19:34, 30 July 2008 (UTC)

==the area==
how big is the park? [[User:Jackzhp|Jackzhp]] 18:12, 20 July 2007 (UTC)

*91 hectares[[User:Labattblueboy|Labattblueboy]] ([[User talk:Labattblueboy|talk]]) 21:59, 16 January 2008 (UTC)

* 107 hectares.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/83.152.49.18|83.152.49.18]] ([[User talk:83.152.49.18|talk]]) 21:52, 26 April 2009 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==pre-restoration photo==
I added three more photos, perhaps too many, but was going to replace the pre-restoration photo thinking it should be clearly labelled pre-restoration if it were left, which would be too awkward.  I thought better of replacing it though and left it since it is a useful shot.  But perhaps it should go on the grounds that the Memorial does not look that run down anymore.[[User:Bdell555|Bdell555]] 19:53, 13 November 2007 (UTC)

==Images==
It's a good probem to have, but the article contained too many images.  Too many photos had been crammed into the article, given the relatively short size of the article.  This isn't necessarily a bad thing -- not too long ago, we didn't have any real images of the memorial.  However, the layout looked terrible.  What I have done is I left the better images in the article, taken all the images and placed them in a Commons category, and then linked the Commons category in the article.  Therefore, the article looks better, and the full selection of images remains available to the reader through the Commons.--[[User:Skeezix1000|Skeezix1000]] ([[User talk:Skeezix1000|talk]]) 16:57, 6 January 2008 (UTC)

==Reorganization &amp; Improvement== 

I have begun a significant edit &amp; improvement of the information in this article. Is there anything in particular that is being requested?[[User:Labattblueboy|Labattblueboy]] ([[User talk:Labattblueboy|talk]]) 21:10, 12 January 2008 (UTC)

==Cemeteries==

I have created a page for each of the cemeteries on the site. Picture contributions would be appreciated.[[User:Labattblueboy|Labattblueboy]] ([[User talk:Labattblueboy|talk]]) 21:59, 16 January 2008 (UTC)
*[[Canadian Cemetery No. 2]]
*[[Givenchy Road Canadian Cemetery]]  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Labattblueboy|Labattblueboy]] ([[User talk:Labattblueboy|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Labattblueboy|contribs]]) 22:06, 16 January 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Merger with [[Canada Mourning]] ==

*'''Support'''.  Makes sense.  --[[User:Skeezix1000|Skeezix1000]] ([[User talk:Skeezix1000|talk]]) 16:45, 23 March 2009 (UTC)
*'''Support'''. --[[User:Brian Crawford|&lt;font color=&quot;DarkGreen&quot;&gt;'''''B'''''&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;DarkRed&quot;&gt;'''''C'''''&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;sub&gt;[[User talk:Brian Crawford|'''&lt;font color=&quot;DarkGray&quot;&gt;talk to me&lt;/font&gt;''']]&lt;/sub&gt; 16:51, 23 March 2009 (UTC)
*'''Support'''. [[User:MelicansMatkin|MelicansMatkin]] ([[User talk:MelicansMatkin|talk]]) 18:50, 23 March 2009 (UTC)
*'''Support'''. But I think it'd make more sense if [[Canada Mourning]] was just a separate subheading under this article [[User:TheStarter|TheStarter]] ([[User talk:TheStarter|talk]]) 09:10, 25 March 2009 (UTC)
::Merger Completed --[[User:Labattblueboy|Labattblueboy]] ([[User talk:Labattblueboy|talk]]) 21:50, 2 April 2009 (UTC)

== Infobox image ==

We have a number of pretty good images of the memorial as a whole.  Surely we can figure out a better one to use than the one that is currently in the infobox, which is way too dark.  --[[User:Skeezix1000|Skeezix1000]] ([[User talk:Skeezix1000|talk]]) 20:19, 2 April 2009 (UTC)
:Which image would you suggest? --[[User:Labattblueboy|Labattblueboy]] ([[User talk:Labattblueboy|talk]]) 21:50, 2 April 2009 (UTC)
::[[:File:Memorial Vimy face.jpg|This]] one is probably best for an infobox -- not the world's greatest image, but clearer and better than the one currently in use.  My favourite image is [[:File:Vimy Ridge Memorial - West side before a storm.jpg|yours]], but I am not sure that it would work for this purpose.  --[[User:Skeezix1000|Skeezix1000]] ([[User talk:Skeezix1000|talk]]) 22:02, 3 April 2009 (UTC)
:::[[:File:Memorial Vimy face.jpg]] is old and before the monument and landscaping restoration (which included the removal of the steps to the tomb) making it inaccurate. With regards to my [[:File:Vimy Ridge Memorial - West side before a storm.jpg]] you're completely right. Beautiful photo but it doesn't work for our purposes. For our purposes we need a quality front shot of the monument. Were stuck between a wall and a hard place on this one. Do you think the photo can be effectively lightened?--[[User:Labattblueboy|Labattblueboy]] ([[User talk:Labattblueboy|talk]]) 23:06, 3 April 2009 (UTC)
:::::I overlooked your question about lightening the photo earlier.  I dunno.  Maybe.  --[[User:Skeezix1000|Skeezix1000]] ([[User talk:Skeezix1000|talk]]) 18:25, 4 April 2009 (UTC)
::::I'm not sure whether it is any good, but there is also [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Vimymonument.JPG this photo] which I took on my trip to Vimy and was previously used in the article for a good amount of time. Just another option to consider. [[User:MelicansMatkin|MelicansMatkin]] ([[User talk:MelicansMatkin|talk]]) 23:22, 3 April 2009 (UTC)
:::::I agree that the fact that the image is old is a factor to consider, but I still think it's preferable to the one in use now.  Lesser of two evils.  Simply make sure the caption states &quot;Canadian National Vimy Memorial in 2003&quot; - we can even add the words &quot;prior to the restoration&quot; if you want.  I'm also happy with the image suggested by MelicansMatkin, although the problem with that one is that it doesn't show the whole memorial.  Perhaps the solution to this problem, given that all of the choices have drawbacks, is to look to Flickr.  There are no decent images of the memorial with licenses acceptable for the Commons on Flickr; however, if we can find one (or a handful) of good ones (without the right license), we can always flickrmail the creator and ask if they would be prepared to change the license so it can be used on Wikipedia.  I have had a lot of luck doing that lately.  --[[User:Skeezix1000|Skeezix1000]] ([[User talk:Skeezix1000|talk]]) 14:29, 4 April 2009 (UTC)
:::::#I did some trolling on flickr today and have sent a couple messages to see if they are willing to modify their license requirements so that they could be uploaded to the Commons (That was a good suggestion).
:::::#I'm not personally comfortable with the pre-restoration image. It's low resolution, grainy and was actually removed from the [[Battle of Vimy Ridge]] article as part of that article' A-level review, in favour of the current one. The current image is dark but certainly an improvement over the 2003 image.
:::::#For the infobox image, it should be an image of the memorial as a whole. The sub-section on the memorial itself is best used for partial images. If we keep looking and asking I am certain we can find a new image that will meet all our needs, so lets make that the goal for now. --[[User:Labattblueboy|Labattblueboy]] ([[User talk:Labattblueboy|talk]]) 17:07, 4 April 2009 (UTC)
:Thanks for #1, I'll defer to you on #2, and agree with #3.  --[[User:Skeezix1000|Skeezix1000]] ([[User talk:Skeezix1000|talk]]) 18:19, 4 April 2009 (UTC)

== Vmy memorial sub-section ==

'''HELP!:''' I need some help trying to format the Vimy memorial sub-section to incorporate all the images of the memorial. [[User:Tango7174|Tango7174]] uploaded a number of beautiful images that I feel should be incorporated. The issue is I'm not sure how to physically incorporate a lot of these images, there just isn't the next space but the statues themselves are each a piece of art. I was thinking a vertical image sticking template or a form or gallery at the bottom of the section. Thoughts? --[[User:Labattblueboy|Labattblueboy]] ([[User talk:Labattblueboy|talk]]) 02:05, 5 April 2009 (UTC)
:I quite like the idea of the gallery. Other articles such as [[Gold Beach]] have or have had them in the past, and I think it would be an excellent way to display the images. Though whether the gallery should be placed in the sub-section or at the bottom of the article (above the Notes) is up for discussion. [[User:MelicansMatkin|MelicansMatkin]] ([[User talk:MelicansMatkin|talk]]) 02:27, 5 April 2009 (UTC)
::Melicans, I undid your edit until we can come to a consensus as to what we do on these images. They won't be forgotten, they are too good. We just need to figure out how we are going to do the section to a GAN quality level and still include them. I think the gallery should be sub-section of vimy memorial, not towards the bottom of the article. Any GAN quality articles using galleries though? I am going to seek some help from project admin on this one --[[User:Labattblueboy|Labattblueboy]] ([[User talk:Labattblueboy|talk]]) 07:02, 5 April 2009 (UTC)
:::If you guys decide to go with a gallery, make sure it's consistent with [[WP:IG]].  Galleries need to be more than just a tool to accommodate additional images - they need to be encyclopedic in and of themselves.  A gallery showing the various aspects of the memorial, with appropriate and informative captions, would strike me as being consistent with [[WP:IG]].  --[[User:Skeezix1000|Skeezix1000]] ([[User talk:Skeezix1000|talk]]) 13:09, 5 April 2009 (UTC)
::::High on my list of concern is [[WP:IG]] given I want to work towards GAN. If we go with a gallery at the bottom of the section to showcase the individual statues which images (or type of images) would be most appropriate to accompany the article text? There is currently the nice shot of the model and there is, for instance, a map detailing the name locations, ideas? --[[User:Labattblueboy|Labattblueboy]] ([[User talk:Labattblueboy|talk]]) 06:18, 6 April 2009 (UTC)

== Further sources for expanding this article ==

I happened to be researching elements of this topic a few years ago and came across some further information that might be useful.
First, in contemporary sources, the name given for the “Mother Canada” statue is usually “The Spirit of Canada”, with “Mother Canada” being a later popular evolution.  I cannot recall seeing “Canada Bereft” – although quite the most fitting appellation given Allward’s expressed intent – in the early sources I found.  The model was Edna Jennings, ''née'' Moynihan, (1902-1995).  She modelled for Allward between 1927 and 1930 at Allward’s Maida Vale studio, during the course of which she met and married Charles Bertram Jennings in 1928.  She was not able to attend the 1936 dedication (which was King George VIII’s last official public engagement before abdicating) and ironically never did visit the Vimy site.  Some information can be found in Suzanne Evans’ recent book ''[http://books.google.com/books?id=s9B5xrHXt0sC&amp;pg=PT138&amp;lpg=PT138&amp;dq=Allward+Spirit+of+Canada&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=m3TsG3-Hxt&amp;sig=NUXOTquni8jDP96Mw7WTAknL6vY&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=gco-S-WbI42wngfLjbDtCA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=6&amp;ved=0CBYQ6AEwBQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Allward%20Spirit%20of%20Canada&amp;f=false Mothers of heroes, mothers of martyrs: World War I and the politics of grief (2007)]''.

The runner up design, The Brooding Soldier, was created by Frederick Chapman Clemesha, who was himself wounded during the war, and was built at Vancouver Corner near Ypres, Belgium.

The Maple Leaf Legacy Project used to have an article with a motley collection of background information, including details on the dedication ceremony itself.  Unfortunately, it’s only to be found on [http://web.archive.org/web/20071107055725/http://www.mapleleaflegacy.org/The_Spirit_Of_Canada_Uncloaked.htm Wayback], but it mentions a number of sources that could be mined. It also had some images which are now lost, including a picture of Edna Jennings. I gleaned an image for my files, but I don't know its provenance (probably a family portrait the author obtained from her daughter Drusilla).
That's all I really have to offer, I'm afraid. [[User:Askari Mark|Askari Mark]] &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Askari Mark|(Talk)]]&lt;/small&gt; 05:03, 2 January 2010 (UTC)

== Possibly useful sources ==

Some sources I found that might be useful for the article:
*[http://www.theglobeandmail.com/archives/article751234.ece Love among the ruins] - more details on the [[Vimy Pilgrimage]]; a mention that the memorial was over-budget: ''&quot;the monument had been 15 years in the design and assembly, ran over budget and was the subject of official inquiries and fact-finding tours&quot;''; and many years after that ''&quot;the government responded to the controversy over the deterioration of the Vimy monument&quot;'' - was the deterioration really controversial?
*[http://www.thestar.com/printArticle/200267 Botched French on signs 'negligent'] - a bit of critical news, though weighed against a 70+ year history, it is difficult to know what should be mentioned and what shouldn't.
*[http://www.hilltimes.com/page/view/.2007.april.9.jones Flags of our fathers, and then some] - politics over the flying of the Canadian Red Ensign.
*[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/france/2464790/Porn-film-made-at-First-World-War-memorial.html Porn film made at First World War memorial] and [http://www.vancouversun.com/news/Four+more+convicted+desecrating+Vimy+Memorial/1478305/story.html 4 more convicted for desecrating Vimy Memorial] - hmm, that wasn't quite the &quot;local response&quot; I was looking for. Still, there is a bit there about annual visitor numbers in the second article: ''&quot;the site attracts hundreds of thousands of visitors each year&quot;''.
*[http://www.thestar.com/article/200480 How Hitler spared Vimy Ridge] - extra detail about how SS troops were used to guard the memorial.
*[http://www.frenchstamps.info/2009/01/french-stamps-france-timbre-1936.html French stamps from 1936] - two to commemorate the Vimy memorial.
*[http://www.rpsc.org/Library/remembrance/remember.htm Stamps and Remembrance] - details of a 1968 stamp issues by Canada
*[http://www.kwstampclub.org/april07_cover.htm Canada's WW I Memorial at Vimy] - more stamps and a picture of an envelope sent from aboard one of the Vimy Pilgrimage ships.
*[http://news.google.co.uk/newspapers?id=Ca8yAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=Ne8FAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=2571,4550088&amp;dq=vimy-memorial&amp;hl=en November 1983] and [http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/thestar/access/472662331.html?dids=472662331:472662331&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;type=current&amp;date=Apr+09%2C+1987&amp;author=Michael+Hanlon+Toronto+Star&amp;pub=Toronto+Star&amp;desc=Vets+pay+poignant+visit+to+Vimy&amp;pqatl=google April 1987] - two of many news reports of Canadian veterans visiting the Vimy Memorial. Many more can be found using the Google News archive and other newspaper archives. Some are in April, commemorating anniversary of the battle. Others are in November, marking Remembrance Day.
*[http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/thestar/access/454319771.html?dids=454319771:454319771&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;type=current&amp;date=Apr+10%2C+1992&amp;author=Patrick+Doyle+Toronto+Star&amp;pub=Toronto+Star&amp;desc=Vimy+Ridge+%27sacrifice%27+forged+unity+PM+declares&amp;pqatl=google 75th anniversary in 1992], [http://vac-acc.gc.ca/general/sub.cfm?source=feature/week/pilgrimage/Reportnov7 Report with pictures on a 1998 ceremony] - that is the one where Canadian veterans were awarded the [[Legion of Honour]], also covered in this news article: [http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/thestar/access/444557561.html?dids=444557561:444557561&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;type=current&amp;date=Nov+08%2C+1998&amp;author=&amp;pub=Toronto+Star&amp;desc=France+gives+highest+honour+to+14+heroes+of+Vimy+Ridge&amp;pqatl=google France gives highest honour to 14 heroes of Vimy Ridge]. The VAC website will likely have lots more of these sort of reports (search [http://vac-acc.gc.ca/general/sub.cfm?source=feature this page] for &quot;Vimy&quot;).
*[http://vac-acc.gc.ca/remembers/sub.cfm?source=memorials/ww1mem/vimy/interpret Interpretive Centre at the Canadian National Vimy Memorial] - that page is the sort of thing I was looking for to tell readers what sort of facilities and services are provided at the memorial (i.e. a &quot;Visitor Centre&quot; and displays, but mostly an open-air site you walk round) - it would also be good to say that entry is free of charge (opening hours goes too far, but saying whether there is an entry fee or no entry fee is important, I think).
*[http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/thestar/access/449331171.html?dids=449331171:449331171&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;type=current&amp;date=Apr+07%2C+2001&amp;author=Reviewed+By+Andrew+Vowles&amp;pub=The+Spectator&amp;desc=Solidly+spellbinding%3B+Lyrical+novel+follows+the+path+of+immigrants+and+stone+carvers&amp;pqatl=google Review of the Stone Carvers novel] - already mentioned in article, but thought it might be of interest
*[http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/thestar/access/422140271.html?dids=422140271:422140271&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;type=current&amp;date=Nov+07%2C+2002&amp;author=Sarah+Govan&amp;pub=Toronto+Star&amp;desc=Standing+on+guard+for+them+%3B+Student+guides+at+Vimy+Memorial+put+off+their+studies+to+embark+on+a+different+sort+of+learning+experience+-+and+get+a+chance+to+tour+a+bit+of+Europe+at+the+same+time&amp;pqatl=google Standing on guard for them] - article on being a student tour guide at the Vimy Memorial.
*[http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/thestar/access/429406391.html?dids=429406391:429406391&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;type=current&amp;date=Feb+08%2C+2003&amp;author=ERIC+VOLMERS&amp;pub=Daily+Mercury&amp;desc=John+Richmond%27s+real+Canada&amp;pqatl=google John Richmond's real Canada] - more example of the symbolism of Vimy, this time in a mural.
*[http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/thestar/access/922603581.html?dids=922603581:922603581&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;type=current&amp;date=Nov+07%2C+2005&amp;author=&amp;pub=The+Record&amp;desc=Restoration+begins+on+Vimy+memorial&amp;pqatl=google Restoration begins on Vimy memorial] - one of doubtless many articles out there about the restoration.
*[http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/thestar/access/819561201.html?dids=819561201:819561201&amp;FMT=ABS&amp;FMTS=ABS:FT&amp;type=current&amp;date=Apr+09%2C+2005&amp;author=&amp;pub=The+Record&amp;desc=Vimy+poster+honours+vets+of+First+World+War&amp;pqatl=google Vimy poster honours vets of First World War] - could be relevant, as the Vimy Memorial being used symbolically again.
*[http://www.ccnmatthews.com/news/releasesfr/show.jsp?action=showRelease&amp;searchText=false&amp;showText=all&amp;actionFor=565601 Vimy Ceremony Concludes Aboriginal Spiritual Journey in Europe] - ceremony at Vimy Memorial that is interesting for two points: (1) the First Nations aspect, as part of the Aboriginal Spiritual Journey and a 'calling home ceremony'; and (2) it was part of Canada's Year of the Veteran activities. Also mentioned [http://www.wawataynews.ca/node/281 here], along with a statement that there is an &quot;annual Remembrance Day ceremony at the Canadian National Vimy Memorial&quot; (though that article says the calling home ceremony took place somewhere else).
*The painting ''Ghosts of Vimy Ridge'' by [[Will Longstaff]] is [[:File:Ghosts of Vimy Ridge.jpeg|here]].
*[http://vac-acc.gc.ca/remembers/sub.cfm?source=memorials/ww1mem/vimy/vimymap This map] mentions something called the &quot;Lions Club International Memorial&quot; - should that be mentioned?
::Already mentioned in the site section. No reliable source data available on the history of it though. --[[User:Labattblueboy|Labattblueboy]] ([[User talk:Labattblueboy|talk]]) 02:02, 10 January 2010 (UTC) 
*[http://vac-acc.gc.ca/remembers/sub.cfm?source=memorials/ww1mem/vimy/battle This page] says it became a Canadian National Historic Site on 10 April 1997 - presumably chosen to co-incide with the anniversary of the battle, but the date and year it became a Canadian National Historic Site should be mentioned in the article.
*[http://caliber.ucpress.net/doi/pdf/10.1525/tph.2009.31.1.89?cookieSet=1 “Battle and Burial”: Recapturing the Cultural Meaning of Canada's National Memorial on Vimy Ridge] - new paper by Hucker. You have references to her work, and list a work by her from 2007 in the bibliography, but I think this is new, from 2009.
Apologies if some of those sources or information are already in the article. It isn't possible to cover all the news and history of a memorial like this, but hopefully some sort of flavour is possible. There is one article that had lots and lots of information, so I'm posting that one separately. [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 08:35, 9 January 2010 (UTC)

==Informative article (2005)==
*[http://www.macleans.ca/article.jsp?content=20050701_108631_108631 It's sublime and deadly] - a 2005 article with some fascinating snippets of information and some support for some of the claims that could be made: ''&quot;Ottawa, flush with postwar pride, uncharacteristically chose the boldest, most expensive proposal&quot;'' (was it really the most expensive?); ''&quot;Allward laboured 14 years -- long past the point where his task had become a torment to him&quot;'' (was the project late and over budget and did it put strain on Allward?); ''&quot;the greatest monumental work of art ever created by a Canadian&quot;'' (do other sources agree? If so, this could be added); ''&quot;Many consider it the most beautiful of the combatant nations' memorials&quot;'' (again, do other sources say this? If so, this could be added); ''&quot;a tree replanting program&quot;'' (I read this somewhere else - is it worth mentioning? The description of the memorial park as a landscape of shell craters is also something that doesn't come across in the article at the moment - a picture would be good there); ''&quot;Vimy's on-site operations director [lives] about 200 m from the memorial in an incongruously pretty Arts and Crafts-style cottage designed by Allward&quot;'' (that is something that could go in the article as well); ''&quot;Seven of the 10-tonne Canadian mines failed to go off in 1917&quot;'' (wow... could easily be mentioned as well); ''&quot;Only three per cent of the 750,000 annual visitors to the site of Canada's greatest military triumph are Canadian. The rest are British and French, mostly schoolchildren&quot;'' (that is definitely worth saying); ''&quot;Allward expected most people to arrive via the rail station&quot;'' (but it is now accessed by road - that would be a perfect way to bring in Devloo and the lifts from the train station); ''&quot;nothing much is done there on Vimy or Remembrance days. Instead [the caretakers] attend a local ceremony. &quot;Last year we had a single Canadian couple here on Nov. 11. [We] asked if they wanted to come to town with us. The mayor lays a wreath at the town cenotaph, I lay a wreath, the band plays the [[Marseillaise]] and the French sing it, the band plays [[O Canada]] and the four of us sing it.&quot;'' (ah, so that answers the question of whether there are annual ceremonies to mark [[Remembrance Day]] and [[Vimy Day]], but it doesn't explain why some sources say there ''are'' annual ceremonies - maybe the ceremonies are the Sunday before the days themselves? Or maybe things have changed since 2005?).
Wonder how much of the above can be incorporated into the article without affecting the balance too much? [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 08:35, 9 January 2010 (UTC)

:It also repeats something else I've heard before, that &quot;For the first time, all four divisions of the Corps, men from every part of Canada, fought together...&quot;, which is something worth mentioning with regard to the &quot;national identity&quot; theme raised at the end of the Battle of Vimy section. [[User:Askari Mark|Askari Mark]] &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Askari Mark|(Talk)]]&lt;/small&gt; 23:45, 9 January 2010 (UTC)
::The Historic Sites statement, which I think is the bit at the bottom [http://vac-acc.gc.ca/remembers/sub.cfm?source=memorials/ww1mem/vimy/vimycerm here], is explicit about that as well. Among the seven points made were these two: ''&quot;the site of Vimy Ridge and its associations with the awakening of Canadian identity&quot;'' and  ''&quot;the first occasion on which the Canadian Corps fought as a unit, composed of men from every part of Canada, and the welding together of an efficient fighting organization&quot;''. The definitive source there is by searching [http://www.pc.gc.ca/apps/lhn-nhs/index_e.asp here] to get [http://www.pc.gc.ca/apps/lhn-nhs/det_E.asp?oqSID=1798&amp;oqeName=Vimy+Ridge&amp;oqfName=Cr%EAte+de+Vimy this], which confusingly says &quot;designated in 1996&quot; and &quot;plaqued in 1997&quot;, and give a much truncated citation. I will have to search by &quot;Statement of Commemorative Integrity&quot; instead... Here is an explanation of [http://www.pc.gc.ca/eng/lhn-nhs/qc/grosseile/docs/plan1/sec4.aspx Statement of Commemorative Integrity]. The one for the Beaumont-Hamel Memorial is [http://www.vac-acc.gc.ca/remembers/sub.cfm?source=memorials/ww1mem/beaumonthamel/bhcerm here] (VAC are responsible for both memorials). Looks like the VAC are the only sources, as the Historic Sites website doesn't seem to go into that level of detail. [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 04:48, 10 January 2010 (UTC)

== Latin inscription on the tomb and &quot;served as&quot; on name walls ==

I got lost in that VAC website (they have lots and lots of pages - the &quot;Honour the Legacy&quot; bit is particularly good), but found the tomb page again [http://vac-acc.gc.ca/remembers/sub.cfm?source=Memorials/ww1mem/vimy/expvimy/tomb here]. I've been trying to find a source for the Latin inscription there: &lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;IN MEMORIAM SEXIGINTA MILLIUM CANADENSIUM QUI ANNO DOMINI MCMXIV MCMXVIII IN ARMIS ULTRA MARE VITUM PRO PATRIA ULTRO DEDIDERUNT&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt; Google Translate tells me &quot;We are not yet able to translate from Latin into English.&quot; Er, so I make that &quot;In memory of 60 million Canadians who in the years 1914-1918 took arms and gave their lives for their country&quot;. (Dediderunt is presumably from &quot;dedere&quot; which means to give up or to render unto someone else). But without a source, this is a bit of a dead end, so I'm just popping it here in case someone else finds a source for this. Oh, hang on, I found [http://pierreswesternfront.punt.nl/?id=425582&amp;r=1&amp;tbl_archief=&amp; this]: ''&quot;The Latin inscription on the sarcophagus tells: &quot;In memory of the 60.000 Canadian soldiers, who in 1914-1918 were travelling overseas, and died far away for their fatherland&quot;.&quot;'' Looks like I need to go back to school for Latin lessons... It isn't a reliable source, but knowing what that inscription says does satisfy my curiosity. Anyway, one further point is the &quot;served as&quot; bits on the walls of names. That had puzzled me until I read an explanation on that page I just linked to: ''&quot;The phrase &quot;served as&quot; indicates the soldier's real name. Canada was a place for escape, a safe haven, and a place to hide. Soldiers were using other names also to enlist for several other reasons.&quot;'' Do any of the reliable sources mention or go into detail on this? All I've found so far is [http://www.cwgc.co.uk/Plaque-history.htm this]. [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 05:39, 10 January 2010 (UTC)

:Canada had a particular problem in recruiting throughout the war and took in quite a number of American volunteers from the very beginning; in fact Americans also joined British and other Commonwealth armies. Since the US was a neutral, it was an illegal activity, so often these volunteers joined up under ''[[nom de guerre|noms de guerre]]''. This explains some &quot;served as&quot; cases, although I do not know how many, if any, may be represented at Vimy. One place to begin looking for some information is the book mentioned in the first posting in [http://www.militaryphotos.net/forums/archive/index.php/t-22511.html Military Photos forum] on this topic. [[User:Askari Mark|Askari Mark]] &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Askari Mark|(Talk)]]&lt;/small&gt; 20:51, 10 January 2010 (UTC)

== British-Pathé footage of the memorial and its unveiling ==

I found some footage of the unveiling ceremony on the [[British-Pathé]] website. The main website is [http://www.britishpathe.com/ here], and a search for &quot;Vimy&quot; produces [http://www.britishpathe.com/results.php?search=vimy 18 hits]. There is the [http://www.britishpathe.com/record.php?id=6922 unveiling in 1936] (27/07/1936), and in addition to that, there is [http://www.britishpathe.com/record.php?id=25306 a memorial service by Canadian soldiers in 1940] (25/04/1940, during World War II), and also a [http://www.britishpathe.com/record.php?id=50749 visit by Vincent Massey] (some time in 1939, precise date unknown). The details of the unveiling ceremony are well-known. The memorial service in 1940 and the 1939 visit by [[Vincent Massey]], the Canadian High Commissioner to London, is something that could be looked at if they are a big part of the history of the memorial. I found an account of Massey's visit to the memorial on [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=Pf5y7sehRwAC&amp;pg=PT307 page 292 of Vimy Ridge: a Canadian reassessment] (the Durflinger chapter: 'Safeguarding Sanctity'). It seems the date was 1 May 1940, unless there were other visits as well (the reference to it being misty seems to indicate that this footage is of the 1 May 1940 visit, just before the Germans invaded and over-ran northern France). There is nice footage of them touring the preserved battlefields and trenches. Other people in that party seem to have been [[Norman McLeod Rogers|Norman Rogers]] (who died in a plane crash a few weeks later), [[H. D. G. Crerar]] and George Stubbs (the caretaker and custodian of the memorial). The other clip doesn't seem anything more than just a normal commemoration service, but is notable for being held in April 1940 just before the German invasion (May and June of that year). As an aside, the stuff in the 'Safeguarding Sanctity' chapter of ''Vimy Ridge: a Canadian reassessment'' is fascinating and goes into a bit more detail than the article does at the moment. Anyway, I hope the links to this footage help. I'm off to see how many clips of unveilings of memorials they have - quite a few by the looks of it! [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 05:56, 14 January 2010 (UTC)
:The clips are all really nice, they certainly add additional perspective. I personally like now you in the 1939 and 1940 films you can see that the memorial has been covered and sandbagged, in anticipation of conflict. Unfortunately, none of these films are in the public domain, so they can't be included on wikipedia.--[[User:Labattblueboy|Labattblueboy]] ([[User talk:Labattblueboy|talk]]) 12:31, 14 January 2010 (UTC)
::I hadn't noticed the sandbags! It is unfortunate that the dates are wrong here in terms of public domain, and very lucky that you managed to find the home-made film donated to a museum (or library) with no restrictions on its use (will that go in the article?). For other articles, I will be adding external links to let readers know that these news clips exist (there is a discussion about that on the external links noticeboard [[Wikipedia:External_links/Noticeboard#British-Path.C3.A9_news_clips_archive|here]]). For this article, I'll leave the matter of external links for you to consider. I am also about to go to the reliable sources noticeboard and ask if the Pathe title cards (these are silent news reels, remember) count as reliable sources! :-) The one on the Delville Wood memorial unveiling is 27 minutes long! [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 07:18, 15 January 2010 (UTC)
:::I was actually thinking a video could go in an article on the 1936 pilgrimage. There isn't much space here and the ceremony photo that is currently in the article is a fairly good one. I'm not sure when I could get around to working on such an article, but hte more it comes up the more it seams that it might be appropriate.--[[User:Labattblueboy|Labattblueboy]] ([[User talk:Labattblueboy|talk]]) 16:51, 15 January 2010 (UTC)

==Philip in uniform==
The fact that Prince Philip wore the Royal Canadian Regiment uniform is linked to the rededication of the memorial; the day prior to the rededication, 6 members of the RCR were killed in Afghanistan, and, in [http://www.royal.gov.uk/LatestNewsandDiary/Speechesandarticles/2007/TheQueensspeechatthe90thanniversaryoftheBattleofVi.aspx her speech], the Queen specifically mentioned the fallen in that conflict. For what reason should this detail (or even both details) not be mentioned in the article?  --&lt;span style=&quot;border-top:1px solid black;font-size:80%&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Miesianiacal|&lt;span style=&quot;background-color:black;color:white&quot;&gt;'''Ħ'''&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User:Miesianiacal|&lt;span style=&quot;color:black&quot;&gt;MIESIANIACAL&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt; 05:15, 16 February 2010 (UTC)
:The focus of the article is not Prince Philip. I am not extensively opposed to noting that he was dressed as Colonel-in-chief of the regiment although I personally believe its most appropriate for that information to be on the [[Royal Canadian Regiment]] page than here. IMO, the dress of the royals is not central to the details of the rededication. If the information is to be included it should be done in a manner that does not require parentheses, as they are generally discouraged and will certainly become a copy-editing issue when the article goes up for feature article again.--[[User:Labattblueboy|Labattblueboy]] ([[User talk:Labattblueboy|talk]]) 05:44, 16 February 2010 (UTC)
::No, of course that is not the focus of the article. However, the rededication ceremony of a monument to fallen Canadian soldiers is a germane part of this page, and a part of that event was Philip's attendance in an RCR uniform the day after 6 RCR personnel were killed in action. --&lt;span style=&quot;border-top:1px solid black;font-size:80%&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Miesianiacal|&lt;span style=&quot;background-color:black;color:white&quot;&gt;'''Ħ'''&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User:Miesianiacal|&lt;span style=&quot;color:black&quot;&gt;MIESIANIACAL&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt; 05:16, 17 February 2010 (UTC)

== Book and film and another painting and more ==

I found a bit [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=Pdd-TfPFTbAC&amp;pg=PA196#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false here] (''Rediscovering the British world'' - 2005) about the Canadian Legion and it's role in the Vimy Pilgrimage. What is also mentioned is a 225-page souvenir book published by the Legion, called ''The Epic of Vimy'' ([http://books.google.co.uk/books?q=%22the+epic+of+vimy%22+legion&amp;btnG=Search+Books Google Books hits], catalogue entry [http://openlibrary.org/b/OL18062959M/epic_of_Vimy here]), which may have more on the Pilgrimage and the memorial. There was also a film of the pilgrimage, ''Salute to Valour'' (several [http://books.google.co.uk/books?q=%22salute+to+valour%22+vimy&amp;btnG=Search+Books Google Books hits]), that came out in 1937. Might be worth mentioning both of those in this article somewhere. While looking up a catalgue entry for the book, I found [http://www.cqmsltd.com/vimy.htm this]! That's a really good summary of the pilgrimage and the unveiling - worth putting in the external links at least, I think, and using as a source if considered reliable enough - it looks like a version got published in a journal [http://www.journal.dnd.ca/vo8/no1/doc/reynolds-eng.pdf here]. The web page of that paper starts off with an impressive painting: CWM 20020045-425: ''Unveiling Vimy Ridge Monument'' (1937) by [[Georges Bertin Scott]] (a French war artist).  It is mentioned [http://www.civilization.ca/cwm/education/toolkit/kitwarart_e.shtml here], and a jpeg of the painting is [http://www.civilization.ca/cwm/education/toolkit/images/forcrown/art/pa210.jpg here]. Finally, some Vimy photographs are on [http://mikan3.archives.ca/pam/public_mikan/index.php?fuseaction=genitem.displayHierarchy&amp;lang=fra&amp;rec_nbr=3197840&amp;back_url=() this page]. And something on the Silver Cross Mothers [http://www.readingandremembrance.ca/forms/RR2009/LESSONADifficultCrossToBear.pdf here]. [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 14:48, 20 February 2010 (UTC)

== Article in Canadian Military Journal ==

Came across this while compiling a list of sources: [http://www.journal.forces.gc.ca/vol10/no1/12-grodzinski-eng.asp The Use and Abuse of Battle: Vimy Ridge and the Great War over the History of the First World War]. Thought it might be of interest for this article (couldn't find it referenced here). It looks like a reliable source. It is from volume 10, number 1, of the [[Canadian Military Journal|CMJ]], which is the &quot;current issue&quot; (it is a quarterly journal), but I can't work out when that issue actually came out - going by the back issues, they missed a year of publication if Volume 10 number 1 is the &quot;current issue&quot;, unless they delay online publication by a year. It seems that article was published around a year ago, but you might want to find some definition confirmation of when it was published. [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 02:13, 22 February 2010 (UTC) &lt;small&gt;Hang on - that article is about the battle, not the memorial... I was fooled by the big photo of the memorial at the top of the article. Sorry! [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 02:16, 22 February 2010 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;

== Infobox image nominated for deletion ==

This is a notice to the editors of this article that there is a [http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Commons:Deletion_requests/Canadian_National_Vimy_Memorial deletion request on Commons] for the current infobox image and two others.--[[User:Rockfang|Rockfang]] ([[User talk:Rockfang|talk]]) 05:45, 26 July 2010 (UTC)

== Status of land ==

The topic of whether the park land is Canadian enclave (e.g. Canadian national territory) has recently come up. So I thought it best to discuss the issue. My understanding has always been that the land was purchased from the landowners by France and then ceded to Canada in perpetuity. The issue was handled through accord because foreign countries were not allowed to own French land. The French exempted the land from tax but that no mention is made of the land being extraterritorial. Can anyone provide sources that this land is anything other than French sovereign territory?--[[User:Labattblueboy|Labattblueboy]] ([[User talk:Labattblueboy|talk]]) 03:25, 10 April 2012 (UTC)
::This theory about the memorial being Canadian territory is a bit of an urban legend.  Similar to the widespread (and mistaken) that embassies are extraterritorial their host countries.  The issue was most recently discussed over at Wikipedia Commons, as there was a question as to whether photographs of the memorial are covered by Canadian or French law.&lt;p&gt;It's hard to prove a negative, but I think the best evidence that the land remains French territory (albeit owned by Canada) is the fact that [http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/world/article662743.ece couples have in recent years been charged under French law and in French courts] for having sex and for exhibitionism on the memorial.  Just in case this Globe and Mail link stops functioning at some future date, some quote from the January 22, 2008 article (&quot;Swingers make love, not war, at Vimy Ridge&quot;):&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&quot;Monday, a French couple appeared at the courthouse in nearby Arras on charges of sexual exhibitionism at the First World War memorial.&quot;&lt;br&gt;&quot;A spokesman for Veterans Affairs Minister Greg Thompson said the Canadian government hopes Monday's court appearance will send a message.  “At this point, our participation in the French legal system will be enough of a deterrent,” said Richard Roik. “Inappropriate behaviour will not be tolerated.”&quot;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are other newspaper accounts from the period.  If the memorial had been Canadian territory, these couples would have to have been charged under Canadian law. --[[User:Skeezix1000|Skeezix1000]] ([[User talk:Skeezix1000|talk]]) 23:37, 12 April 2012 (UTC)
:::Well, that may be done by treaty.  It's kind of silly to have someone prosecuted for a minor, if not ridiculous, crime 5000 miles away.  The treated states that the land was &quot;ceded in perpetuity&quot; which, unless ceded has some different meaning in the Canadian language, appears to have given the land to Canada.  Gibraltar was &quot;ceded in perpetuity&quot; to Great Britain.  Though Spain seems to have another definition, most international law supports GB's claim.  However, Gibraltar has strategic importance (well in the past), so that's probably different than the Vimy Memorial.  The conditions of the ceding included that it would be only used for a memorial, and that one be built.  It is legally Canada.  [[User:SkepticalRaptor|SkepticalRaptor]] ([[User talk:SkepticalRaptor|talk]]) 00:41, 13 April 2012 (UTC)
::::If it was done by treaty, then you would have no problem providing the details of that arrangement.  It isn't enough to say it must be kind of like Gibraltar, so it is legally Canada.  If French law applies, it's France unless someone can show evidence to the contrary.  [[User:Skeezix1000|Skeezix1000]] ([[User talk:Skeezix1000|talk]]) 12:39, 14 April 2012 (UTC)
::::Appendix III of the treaty lays out the explanation of the process. In essence, its the same process that was followed for the Commonwealth War Graves cemeteries; &quot;the land is to be acquired by the French Government at the cost of the French nation, and held in perpetuity by it for use by the Canadian Government for a specific purpose, namely the erection of a monument and the creation of a park.&quot; In essence, granted free use, not sovereignty. This being said, if we have a reliable source, peer reviewed would likely be good in this case, than lays out that the land is &quot;legally Canada&quot; than I would defer to that.--[[User:Labattblueboy|Labattblueboy]] ([[User talk:Labattblueboy|talk]]) 10:14, 13 April 2012 (UTC)
The status of the land is an irrelevant technicality here as far as copyright is concerned.  The issue is what usages of the land and the fixtures upon it are restricted.  If French FOP restrictions constrain Canadian Freedom of Panorama the point of the &quot;cession&quot; disappears, does it not?  The whole point of French FOP restrictions is to protect the commercial interests of the original creators/artists which in this case are not French, and we've got an intergovernmental treaty restricting the application of French jurisdiction to at least some degree.  The fact that Canadian officials were involved at all in the French couple doing their deed indicates that Canadian policy objectives are a factor here, and Canadian policy is to not restrict FOP.--[[User:Bdell555|Brian Dell]] ([[User talk:Bdell555|talk]]) 18:04, 5 April 2014 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:2|one external link|2 external links}} on [[Canadian National Vimy Memorial]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=698866941 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20110614233601/http://www.cwgc.org/admin/files/Annual%20Report%202007-08%20Part1.pdf to http://www.cwgc.org/admin/files/Annual%20Report%202007-08%20Part1.pdf
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20071113094920/http://www.vac-acc.gc.ca:80/remembers/sub.cfm?source=memorials/ww1mem/vimy/interpret to http://www.vac-acc.gc.ca/remembers/sub.cfm?source=memorials/ww1mem/vimy/interpret

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=true}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 18:59, 8 January 2016 (UTC)

==Lt. Jones==
I am curious as to why there is a photo of Lieutenant Richard Jones and a  link to him. As far as I can determine, he was a British officer who had no link to the Battle Vimy Ridge or to Canada.
: Lt Jones won a VC at a previous battle on the same site. His photo is located to the section about previous battles, in which a link to his name is included. [[User:Llammakey|Llammakey]] ([[User talk:Llammakey|talk]]) 01:20, 2 February 2016 (UTC)

== Moving article to FA ==

{{ping|Skeezix1000}}, {{ping|Carcharoth}}, {{ping|Miesianiacal}} I was looking at the article a couple days ago an remarked that it seemed rather close to FA. I've made some edits to addressed concerns raised back in 2010 but would appreciate a copy edit or feedback before I put it forward.--[[User:Labattblueboy|Labattblueboy]] ([[User talk:Labattblueboy|talk]]) 13:19, 6 February 2016 (UTC)
:I've done a little copy editing concerning issues I saw during a quick skim of the article. I'll give it more glances over the next little while. --&lt;span style=&quot;border-top:1px solid black;font-size:80%&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Miesianiacal|&lt;span style=&quot;background-color:black;color:white&quot;&gt;'''₪'''&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User:Miesianiacal|&lt;span style=&quot;color:black&quot;&gt;MIESIANIACAL&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt; 17:04, 6 February 2016 (UTC)
:No immediate feedback. It does seem close to FA (and probably was last time around as well). If I am around, will try and weigh in at the discussion/nomination. [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 00:19, 7 February 2016 (UTC)

Is one of the, if not ''the'', highest circulation newspaper in Canada [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Canadian_National_Vimy_Memorial&amp;diff=703741899&amp;oldid=703739628 not a &quot;proper&quot; source]? It seems to easily meet [[WP:RS]]. --&lt;span style=&quot;border-top:1px solid black;font-size:80%&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Miesianiacal|&lt;span style=&quot;background-color:black;color:white&quot;&gt;'''₪'''&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User:Miesianiacal|&lt;span style=&quot;color:black&quot;&gt;MIESIANIACAL&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt; 19:24, 7 February 2016 (UTC)
::This source has bad news written all over it and is highly questionable or untrue. It's really rather embarrassing that it was ever in the article. None of the statements in the article are verifiable, which is pretty dangerous given it's the only source making them. Not a single source of the rather extensive list already in the article support any of the statements.
:::1.The statement &quot;all Australian World War I graves in France were destroyed during the war&quot; is flagrantly untrue and completely preposterous. There are no recorded events of any graves being purposefully damaged, let alone every single Australian grave. Some memorials like the [[Mont Saint-Quentin Australian war memorial]] were destroyed (hardly surprising, even at the time, given its an Australian soldier thrusting a bayonet through a German eagle).
:::2.The statement about there being Waffen SS guards posted at Vimy are nor supported by an other sources. Given that the article writer is not a historian or significant contributor in the field such a statement needs far more reliable source support than a passing statement, given none of the rather impressively long list of sources listed in this article support this statement. Durflinger is likely the source that most covers the Second World War period, in particular the propaganda on both sides and even there no mention Waffen-SS or any guards exist. 
:::3. No less than two discussions([http://1914-1918.invisionzone.com/forums/index.php?showtopic=163465] [http://1914-1918.invisionzone.com/forums/index.php?showtopic=73097&amp;st=0&amp;p=661846&amp;hl=]) threads at the Great War Forum have lambasted this article for it's historical inaccuracies and being effectively make believe.--[[User:Labattblueboy|Labattblueboy]] ([[User talk:Labattblueboy|talk]]) 23:02, 7 February 2016 (UTC)
::::I went through Durflinger last night just to ensure I wasn't missing something and came up empty. If a good source comes up re-insertion is obviously appropriate.--[[User:Labattblueboy|Labattblueboy]] ([[User talk:Labattblueboy|talk]]) 22:20, 9 February 2016 (UTC)

:Added a section to cover the history between end of WWII and the re-dedication. Likewise added an image to Hitler touring the memorial, uploaded a bunch of architectural drawing the to commons, and expanded the socio-influence section. I'll do a copy edit tomorrow and that I'll post to FA unless someone sees some glaring issues.--[[User:Labattblueboy|Labattblueboy]] ([[User talk:Labattblueboy|talk]]) 00:56, 10 February 2016 (UTC)

== Mother Canada ==

I wanted to see if there was an article on the recently cancelled &quot;Mother Canada&quot; monument but I see that Mother Canada redirercts here. I'm wondering if there should be a short section on the planned, but scrapped, companion monument that was to have been built in Cape Breton or if that merits a separate article? [[User:Alexander&amp;#39;s Hood|Alexander&amp;#39;s Hood]] ([[User talk:Alexander&amp;#39;s Hood|talk]]) 17:38, 8 February 2016 (UTC) 12:35, 8 February 2016 (UTC)
:I've created a short article at [[Mother Canada]] and listed it in the Vimy article in the &quot;see also&quot; section. I'll leave it to others to decide if more of a mention is required. [[User:Alexander&amp;#39;s Hood|Alexander&amp;#39;s Hood]] ([[User talk:Alexander&amp;#39;s Hood|talk]]) 17:38, 8 February 2016 (UTC)
::I've pointed the link towards [[Never Forgotten National Memorial]] given that was the planned memorial's name. It might be worth mentioning only because this is not the first time making a duplicate or inspiration version has come up. If I remember correctly, [[Roméo Dallaire]] argued sometime around 2014 that a replica should be built across from  the Canadian Parliament. A one-line mention might work. --[[User:Labattblueboy|Labattblueboy]] ([[User talk:Labattblueboy|talk]]) 19:14, 8 February 2016 (UTC)
:::re-jigged the last section and included a mention within the general theme of artistic inspiration.--[[User:Labattblueboy|Labattblueboy]] ([[User talk:Labattblueboy|talk]]) 21:35, 9 February 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:2|one external link|2 external links}} on [[Canadian National Vimy Memorial]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=749382483 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20141019160735/http://forgottenheroes.eu/EN_LR.pdf to http://www.forgottenheroes.eu/EN_LR.pdf
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20090305091036/http://www.wlu.ca/lcmsds/cmh/back%20issues/CMH/volume%201/issue%201-2/Pierce%20-%20Constructing%20Memory%20-%20The%20Vimy%20Memorial.pdf to http://www.wlu.ca/lcmsds/cmh/back%20issues/CMH/volume%201/issue%201-2/Pierce%20-%20Constructing%20Memory%20-%20The%20Vimy%20Memorial.pdf

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 01:35, 14 November 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>e0pht5npfgwi2jv4z2y7zorjia955bx</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
