<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Siward, Earl of Northumbria</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>10708905</id>
    <revision>
      <id>692409502</id>
      <parentid>673469737</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-11-25T13:55:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Deacon of Pndapetzim</username>
        <id>140005</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Dodgy titles */ re</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13188">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=01:01, 21 May 2009 (UTC)
|action1link=Talk:Siward, Earl of Northumbria/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=290666800

|action2=FAC
|action2date=02:00, 3 August 2009
|action2link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Siward, Earl of Northumbria/archive1
|action2result=promoted
|action2oldid=305629304

| dykdate       = 18 March 2009
| dyklink       = Wikipedia:Recent additions 242#19 March 2009
| topic         = history
| currentstatus = FA
| four          = no
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Anglo-Saxon Kingdoms|importance=low|class=FA}}
{{WikiProject Biography|living=no|class=FA|royalty-work-group=yes|royalty-priority=low|listas=Siward, Earl of Northumbria}}
{{WikiProject Middle Ages|class=FA|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Norse history and culture|class=FA|importance=Mid}}
{{WPMILHIST|class=FA|Medieval=yes|British=yes}}}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2011-07-27|oldid1=441715204|date2=2013-07-27|oldid2=565851340}}

==Siward and [[Malcolm III of Scotland]]==
Malcolm's article disagrees with Siwards. I'm not sure which is correct, but I thought I should leave a note here. [[User:Sectori|Sectori]] 19:07, 19 October 2007 (UTC)

:The Malcolm III article is more likely to be correct. This one needs updating. [[User:Angusmclellan|Angus McLellan]]  [[User talk:Angusmclellan|(Talk)]] 19:08, 19 October 2007 (UTC)

==Why discuss ''Sigvarðr''/''Sigurðr'' as if they were different names?==
''Sigvarðr'' and ''Sigurðr'' were two forms of the same name in Old Norse, and so I think it is misleading to introduce the topic by presenting the forms as different names:
:''His name is cognate to Old Norse Sigvarðr,[1] but may represent the name Sigurd, a name often rendered &quot;Siward&quot; in Anglo-Latin texts[2] and similar enough to Sigeweard to cause confusion.[3]''
The Norsemen did not pay attention to small details when they named each other, if they knew the forms were versions of the same name (cf. ''James'', ''Jim'', ''Jimmy'', ''Jimbo''). For a modern lexicon of Old Norse names, see [http://www.sofi.se/servlet/GetDoc?meta_id=1472 ''Nordisk runnamnslexikon''] (2002) by Lena Peterson at the Swedish Institute for Linguistics and Heritage (Institutet för språk och folkminnen). I'll be bold and remove the sentence.--[[User:Berig|Berig]] ([[User talk:Berig|talk]]) 08:06, 13 March 2009 (UTC)

: I was under the impression the names had two different etymologies, but were interchangable. I note that this Lexicon '''AND''' the Linguistic commentary on the Durham ''Liber Vitae'' (vol. ii) supports what you are saying. Thanks Berig. [[User:Deacon of Pndapetzim|Deacon of Pndapetzim]] (&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Deacon of Pndapetzim|Talk]]&lt;/small&gt;) 15:27, 13 March 2009 (UTC)
::There were surprisingly many varieties of names circulating in Norse society, and sometimes interchangeable names could indeed have different etymologies. You've written a good article.--[[User:Berig|Berig]] ([[User talk:Berig|talk]]) 15:52, 13 March 2009 (UTC)
::: Thank you. :) [[User:Deacon of Pndapetzim|Deacon of Pndapetzim]] (&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Deacon of Pndapetzim|Talk]]&lt;/small&gt;) 16:32, 13 March 2009 (UTC)

== Suggestions ==

:1) Give the dates of composition for the various sources? Not everyone is going to be familiar with them ...
:2) Ancestry: Who is &quot;Christiansen&quot; mentioned in the second paragraph?
:3) Emergence: Need to explain WHY the king couldn't have been E the C.
:4) A general trend at FAC is to ask for quick capsule explanations of folks mentioned. So for Robin Fleming, I put in &quot;the historian&quot;, etc. This helps folks who aren't necessarily familiar with the sources to understand why this person's opinion is important.
:5) Harold: Explain what an aetheling was. That one is definitely going to go over most folks at FAC's head. (I've been educated them on ecclesiastical matters, not royalty!) 
:6) Did Siward have anything to do with the death of Edward's brother Alfred? 
:7) When Siward helped put Emma in her place, did he help out with [[Stigand]]?
:8) When you do mention Stigand, suggest giving context on who he was then (Bishop of Winchester), so folks understand why his support was important.
:9) In the lead, give the usual English name for Mac Bethad? You're really going to lose folks if you don't.
:10) Double check that you're not overlinking. I know I saw William of Malmesbury linked at least three times.
:: Sources look good, and nothing jumped at me otherwise. I did some copyediting. I strongly suggest getting someone NOT a medievalist to look it over, as I've probably missed about 15 spots that make no sense to a non-medievalist. I know *I* make them all the time, why should you be immune? Hope this helps. [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 20:54, 13 March 2009 (UTC)
Oh! Images:
:11) EdtheCon.jpg - needs a source [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 20:58, 13 March 2009 (UTC)

: I'll respond to your suggestions/questions (here or in edits to the article) in a bit. Then I guess I'll ask that old workhorse Malleus if he's got anything to do. :) To add, I think the article may need a map, though that's not something I'm usually very good at. :'( Thanks. [[User:Deacon of Pndapetzim|Deacon of Pndapetzim]] (&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Deacon of Pndapetzim|Talk]]&lt;/small&gt;) 20:59, 13 March 2009 (UTC)
:: good luck with Malleus. He quit (or is quitting) this week. And I'm not sure that he's not a medievalist any more.. he's read enough of my bishops! [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 21:09, 13 March 2009 (UTC)

:::1), 2), 3), 5), 7), 8), 9) and 10) [hopefully] done. 6) I don't think can be answered, and as no historian I've come across speculates, I've not mentioned anything about this. 11) ... meh ... uploader didn't source it, so as I can't be bothered tracing it just now I just changed it to an image of one of his coins. I hope you don't mind me numbering your points for clarity. Btw, the dates in the boxes in the Stigand article are at odds with Barlow. Thanks for the suggestions, anything else? :) [[User:Deacon of Pndapetzim|Deacon of Pndapetzim]] (&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Deacon of Pndapetzim|Talk]]&lt;/small&gt;) 22:17, 13 March 2009 (UTC)

::::I think the dates on Stigand are from HBC. Don't get me started on Barlow... He is everywhere, but he's ... not always perfect either. [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 22:27, 13 March 2009 (UTC)
::::: Ahright ... HBC is in my little visited office. You should note thought that the dates contradict the text of the article (dep. 1043; rest. 1044 in Barlow and text; dep. 1042; rest. 1043 in suc. boxes -- see also [[Grimketel]]). Honestly couldn't say which one is right without doing actual research. [[User:Deacon of Pndapetzim|Deacon of Pndapetzim]] (&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Deacon of Pndapetzim|Talk]]&lt;/small&gt;) 01:15, 14 March 2009 (UTC)
::::: ARGH. I hate that.. sometimes dates just magically change themselves in infoboxes. I'll do a double check when I'm done with Gilbert Foliot... [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 01:19, 14 March 2009 (UTC)
:::::: Suc box now agrees with HBC (which should agree with article) My brain is mush after [[Gilber Foliot]] and [[Robert Burnell]] PR corrections tonight. Blech. [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 02:27, 14 March 2009 (UTC)
:::::::Thank you all for working through this. IMHO (as of this minute), this is the best article on Wikipedia. [[Special:Contributions/155.213.224.59|155.213.224.59]] ([[User talk:155.213.224.59|talk]]) 13:39, 28 July 2015 (UTC)

== Malcolm v Máel Coluim ==

There may be Irish sources but the source being quoted re the expedition of Siward and the son of the king of the Cumbrians is an English one written in Latin. The name in that is &quot;Malcolmum&quot; - in other words the English form &quot;Malcolm&quot; with a Latin declension stuck on. It is not Máel Coluim as your version would have it be. ''..et cum rege Scottorum Macbeotha proelium commisit, ac multis millibus Scottorum, et Nortmannis omnibus, quorum super fecimus mentionem, occisis, illum fugavit et '''Malcolmum''', regis Cumbrorum filium, ut rex jusserat, regem constituit''. [[User:Paul S|Paul S]] ([[User talk:Paul S|talk]]) 22:00, 4 March 2011 (UTC)

:OK, a couple of misunderstandings here. 1) The article is based on secondary sources, not John of Worcester; 2) The modern Anglo-Scottish name ''Malcolm'' derives from Latin form ''Malcolmus'', not the other way about. Malcolmus is one of many Latinizations of the Gaelic personal name Mael Coluim, 'devotee of Columba'. There was obviously no independent English form of the name, just variant attempts to write how the Scots pronounced it. As a casual browse of the Anglo-Saxon Chronicles (or a few charters) will show you Melcolm, Mælcolon, Malculm, so on. [[User:Deacon of Pndapetzim|Deacon of Pndapetzim]] (&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Deacon of Pndapetzim|Talk]]&lt;/small&gt;) 22:31, 4 March 2011 (UTC)
::Regardless of whether you think Malcolm derives from Latin (which would be unusual) does the chronicle say &quot;Máel Coluim&quot;? No, it doesn't. You are therefore ''assuming'' that the original form of his name was the Irish Máel Coluim when we don't know that. If the chronicle doesn't use the Irish name, you shouldn't put inverted commas around it as if it does and assign him an Irish/Scots identity when we don't know he had one. [[User:Paul S|Paul S]] ([[User talk:Paul S|talk]]) 12:03, 5 March 2011 (UTC)

::: You've lost me now! Irish/Scots identity? He's the Scottish king ... :o  Basically to all appearance what you seem to be saying is that you don't like the name because his name occurs in a Latin source with a Latin form, and that the Scottish form of a Scottish name hides the king's true Roman identity! Now that's not gonna be what you are saying, but I can't work it out otherwise. [[User:Deacon of Pndapetzim|Deacon of Pndapetzim]] (&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Deacon of Pndapetzim|Talk]]&lt;/small&gt;) 13:35, 5 March 2011 (UTC)

:::: I note that Woolf uses the &quot;Mael Coluim&quot; construction for the first citation changed. i'm not at home so can't check the others, but it appears that the secondary source used does indeed use the non-Malcolm form. [[User:Ealdgyth|Ealdgyth]] - [[User talk:Ealdgyth|Talk]] 13:59, 5 March 2011 (UTC)

:::::Duncan (''Kingship of the Scots'') refers to this person as &quot;Maelcoluim&quot;, the same form that he uses for Scots kings up to M. III inclusive. We follow the secondary sources unless we're directly quoting the primary ones (which the Strathclyde article wasn't). [[User:Angusmclellan|Angus McLellan]]  [[User talk:Angusmclellan|(Talk)]] 14:29, 5 March 2011 (UTC)
::::::So would anyone strongly object if I insert the original Latin with ''Malcolmus'' to stop people wondering, as I did, why an English chronicler was writing in Irish? [[User:Paul S|Paul S]] ([[User talk:Paul S|talk]]) 16:05, 5 March 2011 (UTC)
:::::::It might be all right to mention it, if it's not already. When we refer to him, however, we should use whatever the reliable (secondary) sources use. It appears that's &quot;Mael Coluim&quot;.--[[User:Cuchullain|Cúchullain]] [[User talk:Cuchullain|&lt;sup&gt;t&lt;/sup&gt;]]/[[Special:Contributions/Cuchullain|&lt;small&gt;c&lt;/small&gt;]] 21:28, 5 March 2011 (UTC)

== &quot;a member of Earl Ulf's kindred&quot; ==

&quot;a member of Earl Ulf's kindred&quot; is an odd phrase, at least to this native speaker of English.  Does &quot;kindred&quot; have a specialized meaning in this context? The fact that the word is just linking to [[kinship]] implies that it doesn't.  Is there any reason not to change this to the more idiomatic &quot;a relative of Earl Ulf&quot; or &quot;a member of Earl Ulf's family&quot;? --[[User:Jfruh|Jfruh]] ([[User talk:Jfruh|talk]]) 02:00, 27 July 2011 (UTC)

:Since nobody's replied to this, I'm going to make the change. --[[User:Jfruh|Jfruh]] ([[User talk:Jfruh|talk]]) 22:36, 27 July 2011 (UTC)

== Dodgy titles ==

So first it says &quot;dux&quot; means earl.  Doesn't it mean Duke ?   And then it says &quot;comes&quot; means earl.   Doesn't that mean &quot;Count&quot; ?[[User:Eregli bob|Eregli bob]] ([[User talk:Eregli bob|talk]]) 21:37, 27 July 2013 (UTC)
:It depends what the actual cited sources give for translations, but if you head over to [[Google Books]] and search &quot;earl comes latin jarl&quot;, or something like that, you should get some hits that note these Latin terms. The second hit for me, the book ''West Over Sea'', has an article that reads: &quot;... the term ''jarl'' would require an article in itself. Roughly translating as 'earl', it is represented in Latin by both ''dux'' and ''comes'', and is also apparently used in a Scottish context to represent both the Gaelic ''[[mormaer]]'' ('great steward') and the feudal earls of th twelfth century&quot;.--[[User:Brianann MacAmhlaidh|Brianann MacAmhlaidh]] ([[User talk:Brianann MacAmhlaidh|talk]]) 22:27, 27 July 2013 (UTC)

::''dux'' is used in England to refer to an 'earl' or 'earldorman up until c. 1070, after which the Norman administration begin using the term ''comes'', reserving the title ''dux'' for the king's status as ruler of Normandy.[[User:Deacon of Pndapetzim|Deacon of Pndapetzim]] (&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Deacon of Pndapetzim|Talk]]&lt;/small&gt;) 13:55, 25 November 2015 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>c87s3lbtp3jnss24t6x7lscm2ezxagz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
