<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:James II of England</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>566239</id>
    <revision>
      <id>724331950</id>
      <parentid>724326576</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-06-08T15:14:42Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Coemgenus</username>
        <id>203952</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>rv nonsense</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11508">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=FAC
|action1date=16:19, 19 Sep 2004
|action1link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/James II of England/archive1
|action1result=promoted
|action1oldid=6002687

|action2=FAR
|action2date=20:44, 5 January 2007
|action2link=Wikipedia:Featured article review/James II of England/archive1
|action2result=demoted
|action2oldid=98625091

|action3=FAC
|action3date=04:25, 4 November 2007
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/James II of England
|action3result=promoted
|action3oldid=168880627

|maindate=May 22, 2006
|currentstatus=FA
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|collapsed=yes|1=
{{WikiProject Biography
|living=no
|class=FA
|military-work-group=y
|military-priority=low
|peerage-work-group=yes
|peerage-priority=High
|politician-work-group=yes
|politician-priority=High
|royalty-work-group=yes
|royalty-priority=High
|listas=James 02 Of England
}}
{{WPMILHIST
|class=FA
|B-Class-1=no
|B-Class-2=no
|B-Class-3=yes
|B-Class-4=yes
|B-Class-5=yes
|British-task-force=yes
|Biography=yes
|Early-Modern=yes
}}
{{WP Scotland|class=FA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Ireland |class=FA |importance=high |attention= |peer-review= |old-peer-review=}}
{{ChristianityWikiProject
|importance=Low
|class=FA
|catholicism=yes
|catholicism-importance=High
|anglicanism=yes
|anglicanism-importance=Mid
}}
{{WikiProject Politics|class=FA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Scottish Royalty|class=FA|importance=Top}}
{{WP English Royalty|class=fa|importance=top}}
{{WikiProject New York|class=FA|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject England|class=FA|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject United Kingdom|class=FA|importance=high}}
}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{talk archive navigation}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 1
|minthreadsleft = 4
|minthreadstoarchive = 1
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:James II of England/Archive %(counter)d
}}

{{OnThisDay|date1=2005-02-12|oldid1=16335603|date2=2006-02-12|oldid2=39360303|date3=2007-02-12|oldid3=107111136|date4=2012-01-22|oldid4=472489846|date5=2015-01-22|oldid5=643604513|date6=2016-01-22|oldid6=700733927}}
{{archives |auto= short |index= /Archive index}}

== James II and VII ==

First I do know this has been discussed at length before.

However, the fact remains that James was not just King of England and Ireland but also that of Scotland. 

Many historians might refer to him as James II only but this is erroneous and perhaps influenced by the fact some are English and are therefore more inclined to call him by the name he was known by in that Kingdom. To an extent this is true of American historians especially as on the one hand they perhaps more identify with English historical tradition while on the other hand at the time of James' rule the North American colonies were under English control as Britain had yet to exist. 

However, even this tendency amongst US scholars is not always manifested as for instance N C Landsman in 'From Colonials to Provincials' (1997) refers to him as James II and VII. Also please note that Scottish historians refer to him as James VII and II and while I am not advocating that ordering of numerals it does give an indication that merely referring to this monarch as James II is not sufficient.  

Also, I think the arguments surrounding James' attention or lack thereof towards Scotland are largely irrelevant. After all George I and to an extent II were more concerned with their possessions in Germany yet they are still referred to by their British titles. The same can be said of Richard I of England who by all accounts seemed to have spent little time in the Kingdom compared to his French possessions. Using the logic put forth so far in discussions on this page they should not be referred to by there main English/British titles.   

To add the VII is a simple and historically accurate addition to James' name and therefore I cannot see why it should not be done. Wikipedia is supposed to be open to all and not just reflect the historical traditions of one nation no matter how dominate within their island they might be. If this is not undertaken then the best course would be to create a separate entry for James as the King of Scots entitled 'James VII' which would mainly concern his conduct towards that particular Kingdom.

[[User:Jalba51|Jalba51]] ([[User talk:Jalba51|talk]]) 12:01, 18 September 2013 (UTC)

:Your argument has been made in the section above and rejected.  You may be correct about what his name ought to be, but Wikipedia isn't about &quot;ought,&quot; it's about &quot;is.&quot;  The vast majority of scholars call him James II, and so must we.  For what it's worth, when I refer to him in my non-wiki life, I too call him James II &amp; VII. But my opinion is personal, and does not change the fact that all the books I own on the man (which were used in writing this article) call him James II.  --[[User:Coemgenus|Coemgenus]] ([[User talk:Coemgenus|talk]]) 13:45, 18 September 2013 (UTC)
::Certainly scholars refer to him as James II only but not all. Again I have given an example of a historian that has and can provide many more if necessary. Also this is a case of 'is' rather than 'ought' to be. James was the VII of his name who was King of Scotland, a separate nation (this is still prior to the act of Union) and therefore he was James VII no ifs, buts or maybes. Again this is a small inclusion and historically accurate regardless of what English centric historians might or might not think. Historians are as susceptible to national bias or focus as anyone else, any course on historiography would provide proof of that. Moreover, using that logic the UK should be known as England because the majority of US based historians refer to it erroneously by that tern or the USSR should be known as 'Russia' because western historians frequently call it by that name. I also would like to point out that the very fact that his name has been brought up time and time again indicates that true consensus has not yet been reached.--[[User:Jalba51|Jalba51]] ([[User talk:Jalba51|talk]]) 09:27, 19 September 2013 (UTC)
:::Nearly all historians who write about James II call him James II. I know of no biography of James II titled ''James VII'', only ''James II''. I know that is uncomfortable for you because it leaves out his Scotch title but there it is.--[[User:Britannicus|Britannicus]] ([[User talk:Britannicus|talk]]) 10:14, 19 September 2013 (UTC)
:::He is known as James VII of Scots, in Scotland, which was a separate Kingdom at this point. He was revered to as such in Scotland at that time and is still known as such in Scottish history classes etc. It makes people uncomfortable because it's bias and incorrect to only refer to his English title.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/86.156.32.169|86.156.32.169]] ([[User talk:86.156.32.169|talk]]) 18:11, 23 November 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:::I agree it is only right that the title be changed to James II and VII, in the same style as his grandfather. The case has been made well before. Additionally this is also a problem with the articles on Charles I and Charles II which only have England in the title.--[[User:Gealstrix|Gealstrix]] ([[User talk:Gealstrix|talk]]) 19:48, 19 February 2014 (UTC)

Surely there is an incongruity in having [[James VI and I]] reside at that address while this monarch is &quot;James II of England&quot;? [[User:Lacrimosus|Slac]] &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Lacrimosus|speak up!]]&lt;/small&gt; 02:24, 23 October 2015 (UTC)

== Burial ==

Just noting here, I don't mind if the footnote is removed from the infobox or information rejigged on that point, as long as the information is not misleading. [[User:DrKiernan|DrKiernan]] ([[User talk:DrKiernan|talk]]) 08:53, 14 February 2015 (UTC)

== Belloc ==

Identifying Belloc as a Catholic seems odd, considering that we don't identify Macaulay or Trevelyan as Protestants. Certainly, Belloc's Catholicism was an important part of his writing, but wasn't Lord Macaulay's identification with the Protestant establishment equally important to him?
:The motivations in writing on James by Macaulay and Belloc are not comparable. For example, the ''Oxford Dictionary of National Biography'' entry for [http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/14593?docPos=2 James II] describes Belloc as James' &quot;Catholic biographer&quot; and in Belloc's own [http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/30699?docPos=1 entry] it is stated: &quot;Most famously, Belloc became known as a polemical apologist for the Roman Catholic church...Roman Catholicism was central to Belloc's life and his writings&quot;. The ''[http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/olddnb/30699 Dictionary of National Biography]'' claims that Belloc &quot;devoted his pen increasingly through the twenties and thirties to the Catholic cause&quot; and mentions his 1928 biography of James. In contrast, [http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/17349?docPos=13 Macaulay] &quot;expected strong censure from the religious sects, ‘Papists, churchmen, puritans and Quakers’...He had expected criticism from churchmen, and especially Tractarians, for his description in the third chapter of the clergy in 1685. He had a courteous but bruising exchange with the high-church bishop of Exeter, Henry Phillpotts&quot;. In his ''History'', Macaulay is critical of the Church of England's political doctrines. Macaulay is not described by scholars as a Protestant apologist in the same way that Belloc was a Catholic apologist (the ''ODNB'' hints strongly that Macaulay abandoned his youthful evangelism and disliked &quot;religious enthusiasm&quot;).--[[User:Britannicus|Britannicus]] ([[User talk:Britannicus|talk]]) 21:58, 30 May 2015 (UTC)
:: These are good points. When I first wrote the historiography section, I left out religious identifiers but, having read more of Belloc since then, I agree that defense of the Catholic faith was foremost in his mind when he wrote about James. Maybe instead of the parenthetical, we could identify him in the flow of the prose. &quot;...a writer and Catholic apologist...&quot; makes the point just as well, don't you think? --[[User:Coemgenus|Coemgenus]] ([[User talk:Coemgenus|talk]]) 22:40, 30 May 2015 (UTC)
:::Yes, I think you are right. That sounds much better than the way I left it when I reverted the changes. Also, well done on editing this page to featured article status, impressive work.--[[User:Britannicus|Britannicus]] ([[User talk:Britannicus|talk]]) 22:54, 30 May 2015 (UTC)
::::Thanks, glad you like it. I haven't done much British history on here in a while, but I still keep an eye on things I've worked on. I'll make the change we agreed on to the article. --[[User:Coemgenus|Coemgenus]] ([[User talk:Coemgenus|talk]]) 12:35, 31 May 2015 (UTC)

== Charter Oak ==

There is no mention of James II demanding the Connecticut Charter in 1686 to consolidate the [[New England colonies]] and the colonists hiding it in the [[Charter Oak]]. When James II was the granted land as the Duke of York, the original boundary of New York included [[Connecticut]] west of the [[Connecticut river]] despite already been granted in the Connecticut Charter. This was resolved by swapping that area with [[Long Island]] which was originally was part of Connecticut. This trade occurred around 1675 according to The Story of Connecticut page 186 ©1932 by Lewis Sprague Mills. [[User:22yearswothanks|22yearswothanks]] ([[User talk:22yearswothanks|talk]]) 02:52, 10 April 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>sugcr4hbc9ppl1najgvg5uk4lzjytfz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
