<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:War of the League of Cambrai</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2639981</id>
    <revision>
      <id>694702803</id>
      <parentid>606442476</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-12-11T00:03:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Adding/updating {{OnThisDay}} for 2015-12-10.  Errors? [[User:AnomieBOT/shutoff/OnThisDayTagger]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10115">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=PR
|action1date=00:26, 4 October 2005
|action1link=Wikipedia:Peer review/War of the League of Cambrai/archive1
|action1result=reviewed
|action1oldid=24687301

|action2=FAC
|action2date=11:08, 4 November 2005
|action2link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/War of the League of Cambrai
|action2result=promoted
|action2oldid=27174020

|maindate=January 14, 2006
|currentstatus=FA
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WPMILHIST|class=FA
|portal1-name=Italian Wars|portal1-link=Selected event/2
|portal2-name=War|portal2-link=Featured article/8
|British-task-force=yes|Early-Modern-task-force=yes|French-task-force=yes|German-task-force=yes
|Italian-task-force=yes|Spanish-task-force=yes}}
{{WikiProject Germany|class=FA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Spain|class=FA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Italy|class=FA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Switzerland|class=FA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject France|class=FA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject England|class=FA|importance=High}}
{{WPMA|class=FA|importance=mid}}}}
{{V0.5|class=FA|importance=High|category=History}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2005-12-10|oldid1=30731698|date2=2006-12-10|oldid2=93105992|date3=2007-12-10|oldid3=176572801|date4=2008-12-10|oldid4=256989559|date5=2009-12-10|oldid5=330897923|date6=2012-12-10|oldid6=527375935|date7=2015-12-10|oldid7=694286160}}

== Early comments ==

Seamless meld! Was that all the material that wasn't already here? Good edit! --[[User:Wetman|Wetman]] 10:15, 8 September 2005 (UTC)

I think this article is ready for Primetime FA status. --[[User:R.D.H. (Ghost In The Machine)|R.D.H. (Ghost In The Machine)]] 12:24, 23 October 2005 (UTC)

:There are still some things I'd like to add, actually; maybe in a week or two. [[User:Kirill Lokshin|Kirill Lokshin]] 18:56, 23 October 2005 (UTC)

== alliances ==

I thought about making a war info box but its almost impossible because of the shifting alliances. Do I have this right: it starts out with 
the Pope &amp; France vs. Venice (1508-10), then its
the Pope &amp; Venice vs. France (1510-12).. and finally its
Venice &amp; France vs. the Pope (1512-1516) (not to mention all the other countries involved) [[User:Astrokey44|Astrokey44]] 12:11, 29 October 2005 (UTC)

:It's important to mention Spain and the HRE, at the very least.  We then have:
:#Pope + Spain/HRE + France v. Venice (1508&amp;ndash;1510)
:#Pope + Venice v. France + Spain/HRE (1510&amp;ndash;1511)
:#Pope + Venice + Spain/HRE v. France (1511&amp;ndash;1512)
:#Pope + Spain/HRE v. Venice + France (1513&amp;ndash;1516)

:I'll point out, however, that the reason there isn't a warbox on this article is because the [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history|Military history WikiProject]] is currently discussing a new (standard) format for them (partially to deal with complicated cases like this); I think a badly-written warbox using the existing template is worse than no warbox at all.  I encourage you to comment on the project page if the matter interests you further; we're happy for any suggestions. [[User:Kirill Lokshin|Kirill Lokshin]] 12:46, 29 October 2005 (UTC)

::Ok I tried making a box just to explain the alliances, not the standard one. but I didnt see Spain and the HRE on the French side 1510-1511. Is that right? [[User:Astrokey44|Astrokey44]] 12:55, 29 October 2005 (UTC)

:::They were formally in the League, but didn't really do anything.  I've left them omitted to avoid over-complicating things.  I've also moved the box down the page to where the League is first discussed; I don't think it's necessary to hit the reader with so many details as soon as they try to read the article, since the lead section is supposed to be of more general interest. [[User:Kirill Lokshin|Kirill Lokshin]] 13:14, 29 October 2005 (UTC)

== Result box ==


{| border=1 width=300 cellpadding=2 cellspacing=0 align=right style=&quot;margin-left:1em;margin-bottom:1em&quot;
|-
|colspan=2|
|-
!colspan=2  bgcolor=#00BFFF|War of the League of Cambrai results
|-
|colspan=2|
{| border=1 width=300 cellpadding=2 cellspacing=0
|-
!colspan=2 bgcolor=#00BFFF|1508-1510  League of Cambrai against Venice
|-
|colspan=2 bgcolor=#AFEEEE| Result: France defeated Venice, Venice defeated the HRE and the Papacy, but Venice surrendered to the Papacy; increased French presence in Italy
|-
!colspan=2 bgcolor=#00BFFF|1510-1511  Venice-Papal alliance against France
|-
|colspan=2 bgcolor=#AFEEEE|Result: French victory
|-
!colspan=2 bgcolor=#00BFFF|1511-1513  Holy League against France
|-
|colspan=2 bgcolor=#AFEEEE|Result: Holy League victory; Germans refuse to surrender territory to Venice - Venice turns to France for help
|-
!colspan=2 bgcolor=#00BFFF|1513-1516 Venetian-French alliance against Holy League
|-
|colspan=2 bgcolor=#AFEEEE|Result: Venice and French victory over the Holy League
|-
|-
|}
|}

I've removed the box listing the results.  It drastically over-simplifies both the phases of the war and the actual results; a correct description of the result would be a paragraph of text for each phase.  I see no need to use such simplified information merely for the dubious benefit of having another box on the page, which already has two. [[User:Kirill Lokshin|Kirill Lokshin]] 14:09, 31 October 2005 (UTC)

Some further clarification on why the result box is a bad idea:

# Unlike the alliances, there is little need for someone to refer back to the box as a reference while reading.  It is particularly useless in its place at the bottom of the article, since anyone seeing it will already have read through the relevant sections.  The text, I think, quite adequately explains the results of each phase without needing to resort to a special table.
# The results are simplified; in the case of the first phase, particularly, the over-simplification is a gross one: properly, France defeated Venice, Venice defeated the HRE and the Papacy, but surrendered to the Papacy.  Further, the large French presence in Italy is an artifact of the [[Second Italian War]], and was merely increased by the French victory here.  I believe that it is better to omit the box entirely rather than put a grossly simplified explanation into place.

Hopefully this makes clear why I decided to remove it.  [[User:Kirill Lokshin|Kirill Lokshin]] 16:37, 31 October 2005 (UTC)

:Ok fine, it just seems that the article needs some simplification. It seems to be one of the most confusing wars in history. I wanted it because theres always a &quot;result&quot; section of the standard warboxes. [[User:Astrokey44|Astrokey44]] 21:16, 31 October 2005 (UTC)

:: I've added a result section to the warbox at the top (thanks for pointing that out &amp;mdash; I'm surprised I missed its absence).  I think the result of the war as a whole should be quite sufficient for the casual reader; if anyone is really interested in finding out how each phase ended, they probably don't need a separate box to tell them, as they'll likely be reading the article fully. [[User:Kirill Lokshin|Kirill Lokshin]] 21:35, 31 October 2005 (UTC)

== Shaw citation ==

&quot;Christine Shaw, ''Julius II: the Warrior Pope'' (Oxford:Blackwell) 1993.&quot; - can we get a page number with that?  It's not really a citation, otherwise. 

(And, in any case, there's no need to revert stylistic cleanup merely because you want to add the citations back; nor to arbitrarily change citation styles; and particularly not to alter citations to point to an entirely different place without realizing that a different edition is being used.) [[User:Kirill Lokshin|Kirill]] 13:55, 12 July 2007 (UTC)
::Will do. How could I have thought the citations were being deleted? --[[User:Wetman|Wetman]] 19:20, 12 July 2007 (UTC)
:::Thanks for adding them.  (I suppose I ought to get a copy of that book at some point, so I can do that myself. ;-) [[User:Kirill Lokshin|Kirill]] 20:08, 12 July 2007 (UTC)

== Wow... ==

While I'm not suppose to make forum discussion comments, I just have to say, clicking on the link on the main page and reading the box.  I just can't help but laugh.  So much side switching!  [[User:DarkGhost89|DarkGhost89]] ([[User talk:DarkGhost89|talk]]) 12:07, 10 December 2008 (UTC)

==Emergency! Link is WRONG!==

Wowowow! All stop!

The link to the Council of Pisa, which occurred in the text that narrated how Julius and Spain agreed punish Florence because Florence had slighted the Pope by allowing Louis to hold the Council of Pisa in Florentine territory, incorrectly lead the reader to the Wiki article on the Council of Pisa (1409) during the Western Schism in which a second antipope was elected. This event transpired more than one century ago before the Wars of the League of Cambrai and obviously had nothing to do with Florence or Julius II or the Spaniards; the source of the confusion is that there were TWO Councils of Pisa, the First at 1409, the Second at 1511. The Second Council of Pisa was also known as the [[Fifth Council of the Lateran]], which was a debate over clerical reform and sovereignty of the monarchs v. Papal claims and the source of Julius II's irritation.

Jonathan Chin

:Good catch!  If I'm not mistaken, the 1511 Council of Pisa was the French-sponsored preliminary to the Fifth Lateran Council, not the Fifth Lateran itself; but, since the Lateran article seems to be the only one that mentions the events in Pisa, I've changed the link to point to that for the time being.  Eventually, we'll probably want either a full article on the earlier council, or more material in the Lateran article covering the full sequence of events. [[User:Kirill Lokshin|Kirill]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Kirill Lokshin|[talk]]]&amp;nbsp;[[User:Kirill Lokshin/Professionalism|[pf]]]&lt;/sup&gt; 05:01, 12 June 2009 (UTC)

==Discussion on major conflict infobox==

A  discussion on a major conflict infobox is taking place at [[Template talk:WW2InfoBox#Allies.]]. All input welcome. Thank you. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Victor_falk|''walk'']]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;[[user:victor falk|''victor falk'']]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt; &lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;[[user_talk:victor falk|''talk'']]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 07:12, 30 April 2014 (UTC)



.</text>
      <sha1>g1894g8c8kgv3uc9tplpvl9hw1m2be6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
