<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Byzantine Empire</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>21463780</id>
    <revision>
      <id>747350840</id>
      <parentid>747199774</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-01T21:42:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Kevinmuniz115</username>
        <id>26997326</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="41189">{{Skip to talk}}
{{Talk header|search=yes}}
{{Vital article|level=3|topic=History|class=FA}}
{{British English|date=September 2011}}
{{Article history|action1=RBP
|action1date=19 Jan 2004
|action1link=Wikipedia:Refreshing brilliant prose - History and religion
|action1result=kept
|action1oldid=2199146

|action2=FAR
|action2date=09:18, July 29, 2007
|action2link=Wikipedia:Featured article review/Byzantine Empire/archive1
|action2result=kept
|action2oldid=147816656

|action3=FAR
|action3date=13:47, 27 June 2012
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article review/Byzantine Empire/archive2
|action3result=kept
|action3oldid=499601234

|maindate=April 1,2004
|currentstatus=FA
}}
{{On this day|date1=2013-05-29|oldid1=557358919|date2=2016-05-29|oldid2=722608045}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|collapsed=yes|1=
{{WikiProject Military history|class=FA|Classical=y|Roman=yes}}
{{WikiProject History|class=FA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject European history|class=FA|importance=top}}
{{WikiProject Former countries|class=FA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Rome| class=FA |importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Greece|class=FA|importance=Top|topic=history|byzantine-task-force=yes}}
{{WikiProject Italy|class=FA|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Serbia|class=FA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Croatia|class=FA|importance=Low}}
{{WikiProject Bulgaria|class=FA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Romania|class=FA|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Dacia|class=FA|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Iran|class=FA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Syria|class=FA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Turkey|class=FA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Lebanon|class=FA|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Christianity|class=FA|importance=Mid|eastern-orthodoxy=yes|eastern-orthodoxy-importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Middle Ages|class=FA|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Egypt|class=FA |importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Albania|class=FA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Politics|importance=high|class=FA}}
}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{Automatic archive navigator}}
|maxarchivesize = 200K
|counter = 13
|minthreadsleft = 10
|algo = old(30d)
|archive = Talk:Byzantine Empire/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{tmbox
| type      = content
| image     = [[File:Exclam icon.svg|50px|center]]  
| textstyle = text-align: center; font-size: larger
| text      = '''Before discussing the naming and etymology of the Byzantine Empire, please visit the relevant archived discussions.'''
}}
{{WP1.0|v0.5=pass|class=FA|importance=mid|category=History|VA=yes|WPCD=yes|small=yes}}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn
|target=Talk:Byzantine Empire/Archive index
|mask=Talk:Byzantine Empire/Archive &lt;#&gt;
|leading_zeros=0
|indexhere=yes}}
{{Auto archiving notice|bot=MiszaBot I|age=30|small=yes|dounreplied=yes}}&lt;!-- Metadata: see [[User:MiszaBot I]] --&gt;
&lt;br&gt;

== Status text ==

In the article [[Western Roman Empire]], the status text of the infobox clearly shows it as the &quot;Provinces of the [[Roman Empire]] governed by the Western Court&quot;. Similarly for this article, it should show the Byzantine Empire as the &quot;Provinces of the Roman Empire governed by the Eastern Court (330-476)&quot; when it coexisted with the Western Roman Empire (and perhaps with added status text &quot;Sole court of the Roman Empire (476-1453)&quot; for the later periods). In order to be consistent, the status text should either be shown in both articles (the preferred solution), or shown in neither articles. Thanks. --[[User:Cartakes|Cartakes]] ([[User talk:Cartakes|talk]]) 16:24, 11 September 2015 (UTC)
: [[WP:OTHERSTUFFEXISTS|OTHERCRAPEXISTS]]. I don't care what the [[Western Roman Empire]] article does. Consistency is not a priority here; the only thing that matters is that each article does what locally makes sense. Putting &quot;provinces governed by the eastern court&quot; in the box here makes no sense, because the period label &quot;Byzantine&quot; conventionally refers ''primarily'' and prototypically to the time when there was no western court to contrast it with (which was true for at least 90% of the time we call Byzantine even by the widest defintion of this term, if not for 100% of the time, depending on where you draw the line). The &quot;Western&quot; and the &quot;Eastern&quot; empire are not historically symmetrical entities and never were; that's why it really makes no sense to impose artificial uniformity on the way we present them. As for the second addition (&quot;sole court 476-1453&quot;), that would at least make it not entirely factually wrong, but the two entries together are clumsy, unwieldy, pedantic and simply not the kind of stuff that should be in infoboxes, whose first and only priority must be to remain crisp and brief. There simply is no cmpelling reason at all why any of this should be in the infobox in the first place, these are things that must be presented in proper text. [[User:Future Perfect at Sunrise|Fut.Perf.]] [[User talk:Future Perfect at Sunrise|☼]] 16:36, 11 September 2015 (UTC)
:: The [[Byzantine Empire]] in fact had two periods of different nature: 1. as part of the Roman Empire, from 330 to 476; 2. as a standalone empire from 476 onward. There is an important relationship between the Byzantine Empire and the Roman Empire, which should be listed in the infobox similar to other articles such as the [[Western Roman Empire]] even if we don't consider the Byzantine Empire and the Western Roman Empire as historically symmetrical entities. With this two lines as the status text for this article, it would be much clearer to readers about the actual nature of the Byzantine Empire by simply looking at this even if we don't talk about consistency with the [[Western Roman Empire]] article here. Furthermore, it is definitely not clumsy or unwieldy to list both. Look at articles such as [[Joseon]], it is in fact a commonplace in Wikipedia to list such texts in the infobox. --[[User:Cartakes|Cartakes]] ([[User talk:Cartakes|talk]]) 16:47, 11 September 2015 (UTC)

Just for reference: this text was first added by [[User:Jack Gaines]] on 11 April 2015 [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Byzantine_Empire&amp;diff=656006242&amp;oldid=655945339], then removed (by me) on 26 April [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Byzantine_Empire&amp;diff=659344842&amp;oldid=659344658], then reinserted by [[User:Cartakes]] on 27 June [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Byzantine_Empire&amp;diff=668920281&amp;oldid=668451600], then removed by [[User:Swarm]] on 15 August [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Byzantine_Empire&amp;diff=676148369&amp;oldid=676025230], then reinserted and expanded again by Cartakes on 16 August [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Byzantine_Empire&amp;diff=676423297&amp;oldid=676342538], then removed again by me on 7 September [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Byzantine_Empire&amp;diff=679851937&amp;oldid=679851763], then re-added once again by [[User:I Feel Tired]] [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Byzantine_Empire&amp;diff=680127329&amp;oldid=679851995] and twice more by Cartakes [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Byzantine_Empire&amp;diff=680549439&amp;oldid=680174086][https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Byzantine_Empire&amp;diff=680552670&amp;oldid=680552438], with reverts back by myself and most recently by [[User:Dr.K.]] [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Byzantine_Empire&amp;diff=680553450&amp;oldid=680552670]. None of the three people who inserted it made even a single talkpage contribution here during all that time, until today. What a fucking pathetic story. [[User:Future Perfect at Sunrise|Fut.Perf.]] [[User talk:Future Perfect at Sunrise|☼]] 17:02, 11 September 2015 (UTC)
:It's always so with infoboxes! While we're at it &quot;Roman polytheism until 380&quot; is a very odd way indeed to describe the start of Byzantine religion. [[User:Johnbod|Johnbod]] ([[User talk:Johnbod|talk]]) 17:15, 11 September 2015 (UTC)
:Please note that at least two editors had thanked me for reinserting this text by now, including [[User:Swarm]] mentioned above after I expanded the text on 16 August. So it was not at all without support from other editors. --[[User:Cartakes|Cartakes]] ([[User talk:Cartakes|talk]]) 17:18, 11 September 2015 (UTC)
*I don't feel strongly about it either way and removed it because it was flat out misleading originally. I thanked Cartakes for his attempt at a compromise that rectified my concern and let it go. I do not think the article suffers in any sense from its removal though. I understand wanting to bring it in line with the WRE infobox, but if anything, it's a weird use of the &quot;status text&quot; parameter in the first place and I can't think of any other infoboxes that do something similar. [[User:Swarm|&lt;span style='color:black;text-shadow: 0.0em 0.0em 0.9em black'&gt;&lt;big&gt;'''S'''&lt;/big&gt;&lt;small&gt;'''''warm'''''&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Swarm|&lt;span style='color:black;text-shadow: 0.1em 0.1em 0.2em red'&gt;&lt;big&gt;♠&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 20:06, 11 September 2015 (UTC)
:*I agree that the use of the &quot;status text&quot; parameter is weird. It is also UNDUE and POV to put at the top of the infobox the description of a relatively short period of time from 330 to 476 AD on equal footing with the much longer period when  the Empire was the sole representative of the Roman Empire. It looks like POV-advertising to me. Another indicator of POV is the longterm edit-warring, as FPaS mentioned. [[User:Dr.K.|Δρ.Κ.]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup style=&quot;position:relative&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Dr.K.|λόγος]]&lt;span style=&quot;position:relative;bottom:-2.0ex;left:-5.5ex;*left:-5.5ex&quot;&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Dr.K.|πράξις]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 20:46, 11 September 2015 (UTC)
:::Status text in more than one line is not really uncommon in WP however. Also, if you look at the status text in articles such as [[Joseon]] (as mentioned earlier) and [[Goryeo]], there are line of texts in normal font and the other line in smaller font. So a suggestion: if you don't want to see the two lines in equal footing, then it's fine to make the shorter period in smaller fonts. I agree that in the longer period that Empire was the sole representative of the Roman Empire, which is in fact an important information for readers. You can see the demo of the status text in this way [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Byzantine_Empire&amp;oldid=680596204 here]. Thanks. --[[User:Cartakes|Cartakes]] ([[User talk:Cartakes|talk]]) 21:57, 11 September 2015 (UTC)
::::Thank you for the demo. I think it is ok. [[User:Dr.K.|Δρ.Κ.]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup style=&quot;position:relative&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Dr.K.|λόγος]]&lt;span style=&quot;position:relative;bottom:-2.0ex;left:-5.5ex;*left:-5.5ex&quot;&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Dr.K.|πράξις]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 01:38, 12 September 2015 (UTC)
::::: I see no improvement in this new version [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Byzantine_Empire&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=680691047&amp;oldid=680552670]. It's still quite as wordy, there's still no obvious explanation of why this piece of information is in the box in the first place, the difference in font size adds yet another layer of visual distraction (rather than being self-explanatory, it's another unexplained feature whose sense the reader has to figure out on their own somehow), and on top of all this, it's reversing the temporal order, again without explaining why. [[User:Future Perfect at Sunrise|Fut.Perf.]] [[User talk:Future Perfect at Sunrise|☼]] 19:05, 12 September 2015 (UTC)
::::::: (Adding to the above, because I forgot to point it out earlier: the proposed wording is also still factually wrong, because the Byzantine Empire wasn't &quot;the sole court&quot; of the Roman Empire. An empire isn't a court. It has a court. The &quot;sole court&quot; of the Roman Empire may have been the court at Constantinople, but it's just plain nonsensical to say that the empire itself &quot;was&quot; that court. [[User:Future Perfect at Sunrise|Fut.Perf.]] [[User talk:Future Perfect at Sunrise|☼]] 15:00, 13 September 2015 (UTC)
::::::The improvement I saw was regarding the previous description which mentioned  provinces and the eastern court. In my opinion the new description is more accurate. I can't argue about the wordiness or the temporal order because I can see the validity of both of these points. [[User:Dr.K.|Δρ.Κ.]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;&lt;sup style=&quot;position:relative&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Dr.K.|λόγος]]&lt;span style=&quot;position:relative;bottom:-2.0ex;left:-5.5ex;*left:-5.5ex&quot;&gt;[[Special:Contributions/Dr.K.|πράξις]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 23:25, 12 September 2015 (UTC) 
I don't see consensus for this addition.  I see one editor saying the demo looks OK.  I agree with Fut.Perf's remarks above.  This is unnecessary, undue weight, and worse, it takes us back into the Byzantine/Roman argument that has been beaten to death. We specifically distinguish between the Roman Empire and the Byzantine Empire, yet this addition confusingly calls the Byzantine Empire a court of the Roman Empire.  We've been down this road too many times (see my list of links to prior arguments on this point in the discussion above, beginning with the bolded text, &quot;Please discuss all changes to the lead&quot;).  The only use I see for this addition is for people who cannot be bothered to read the first two sentences of the article. It is just infobox bloat, trying to summarize complex content into soundbite size. It is unnecessary and introduces inconsistency at the very top of the page. [[User:Laszlo Panaflex|Laszlo Panaflex]] ([[User talk:Laszlo Panaflex|talk]]) 19:13, 12 September 2015 (UTC)
:::Agreed. [[User:Johnbod|Johnbod]] ([[User talk:Johnbod|talk]]) 15:04, 13 September 2015 (UTC)
:I have undone the edit for now because of your comment. However, from the discussions above I see it seems to be generally agreed that the Byzantine Empire was the sole representative of the Roman Empire after 476, although Fut.Perf. argued that there is no need to display the status text. I am wondering how you view the relationship between the Roman Empire and the Byzantine Empire then? Thanks! --[[User:Cartakes|Cartakes]] ([[User talk:Cartakes|talk]]) 22:12, 12 September 2015 (UTC)
::A &quot;Byzantine/Roman&quot; debate, whatever that is, which is not a legitimate topic for debate. The distinction between ERE and WRE is historical and not rooted in this project. The Byzantine Empire ''is'' the Roman Empire, everyone knows that, that's not being debated. Fact-wise, the infobox blurb isn't wrong nor is it confusing, misleading, undue weight or inconsistent with the rest of the article or with reliable sources. I agree that it's unnecessary infobox bloat and the exact same information can be found in the lead, the body, and summarized further down in the infobox in the &quot;historical era&quot; section, but I really don't understand where all this vitriol is coming from. [[User:Swarm|&lt;span style='color:black;text-shadow: 0.0em 0.0em 0.9em black'&gt;&lt;big&gt;'''S'''&lt;/big&gt;&lt;small&gt;'''''warm'''''&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Swarm|&lt;span style='color:black;text-shadow: 0.1em 0.1em 0.2em red'&gt;&lt;big&gt;♠&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 04:00, 13 September 2015 (UTC)
:::As I stated above, this has been debated ad nauseum and at last a consensus version of the opening was reached, at times after word-by-word debate (see the links I refer to above re the “Byzantine/Roman” debate).  Now we are trying to refine it even further, for an infobox blurb that needlessly attempts to summarize a complex issue that is discussed at the very beginning of the intro. It is reductive and unnecessary.  You say you don’t understand the vitriol, so I urge you to go back over the years-long debate over what you say &quot;is not a legitimate topic for debate&quot;; perhaps then you’ll understand the frustration. [[User:Laszlo Panaflex|Laszlo Panaflex]] ([[User talk:Laszlo Panaflex|talk]]) 15:08, 13 September 2015 (UTC)
::::I understand the frustration with users who endlessly try to argue that it should not be referred to as &quot;Byzantine Empire&quot; but that argument has literally no merit, never has, and as such it has never actually gained any traction. It's not fair to project your frustration with such ridiculous past debates onto this issue, which is obviously an editor trying to factually summarize two distinct stages in the infobox. Do you want a pat on the back for being able to form a consensus to back what is both the scholarly, common, and stable name? Distinguishing the Byzantine Empire and the Ancient Roman Empire as is done historiographically does not mean the edit was wrong or was attempting to rewrite history or ignore consensus. [[User:Swarm|&lt;span style='color:black;text-shadow: 0.0em 0.0em 0.9em black'&gt;&lt;big&gt;'''S'''&lt;/big&gt;&lt;small&gt;'''''warm'''''&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Swarm|&lt;span style='color:black;text-shadow: 0.1em 0.1em 0.2em red'&gt;&lt;big&gt;♠&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 17:10, 15 September 2015 (UTC)
Let's mantain a clear distinction between the Roman Empire (that fell duiring the fifht century) and the  Byzantine empire that fell in the 15th century. Moreover, I oppose to use the term &quot;eastern roman empire&quot; when there was not a western part. [[User:Barjimoa|Barjimoa]] ([[User talk:Barjimoa|talk]]) 11:25, 18 September 2015 (UTC)
:::::I saw my name mentioned and thought I might as well add in my two cents. The reason I hadn't been on this talk page is because I've been on break, because I was tired of dealing with [[User:Future Perfect at Sunrise|you]]. You treat anyone who makes an edit you don't like or disagrees with you like crap. Your attitude really makes me not want to spend time here. [[User:I Feel Tired|I Feel Tired]] ([[User talk:I Feel Tired|talk]]) 16:29, 11 October 2015 (UTC)

== First usage of the term ''Byzantine Empire'' ==

I'm removing these sentences:

:However, it was not until the mid-19th century that the term came into general use in the Western world. As regards the English historiography in particular, the first occasion of the &quot;Byzantine Empire&quot; appears in an 1857 work of [[George Finlay]] (''History of the Byzantine Empire from 716 to 1057'').&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Rosser|2011|p=2}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
:{{reflist}}

[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=qU9lmX2xYlUC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Rosser] says nothing of the kind on p. 2, though on p. xxxvii he calls that expression &quot;modern&quot;.  A search on [https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=EPwvAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA356&amp;dq=%22they+who+write+of+the+Byzantine+Empire%22&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiK1bWI86PJAhUDPhQKHTdpDDgQ6AEIIjAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22they%20who%20write%20of%20the%20Byzantine%20Empire%22&amp;f=false Google Books] shows it to have been used since at least 1704, and it's also used by [https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=JcxTAAAAcAAJ&amp;pg=PA519&amp;dq=inauthor:Gibbon+%22Byzantine+Empire%22&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiJvcDr-qPJAhUEuhQKHfnADMwQ6AEIJTAB#v=onepage&amp;q=inauthor%3AGibbon%20%22Byzantine%20Empire%22&amp;f=false Gibbon], but all that's just OR. The OED doesn't have an entry for ''Byzantine Empire''. --[[User:Antiquary|Antiquary]] ([[User talk:Antiquary|talk]]) 11:36, 22 November 2015 (UTC)
:Well now, it seems that when I look at [https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=AYpqikYr3Q8C&amp;pg=PA2&amp;dq=finlay+rosser+byzantine&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiR8JHU_KPJAhUHsxQKHZd9BvIQ6AEIIDAA#v=onepage&amp;q=finlay%20rosser%20byzantine&amp;f=false the right edition of Rosser] he really does say that.  I'm restoring the first of the sentences I removed, though the second is clearly wrong, as I've shown. --[[User:Antiquary|Antiquary]] ([[User talk:Antiquary|talk]]) 12:01, 22 November 2015 (UTC)

== &quot;Today part of...&quot; entry ==

Regarding this [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Byzantine_Empire&amp;type=revision&amp;diff=693467638&amp;oldid=693304793] attempt at reintroducing a &quot;today part of...&quot; entry with a list of modern countries in the infobox: please note that such a list was previously removed by consensus, most recently after this talkpage discussion in 2012: [[Talk:Byzantine Empire/Archive 12#List of Countries]]. Please don't reintroduce this without prior consensus. Thanks, – [[User:Future Perfect at Sunrise|Fut.Perf.]] [[User talk:Future Perfect at Sunrise|☼]] 20:15, 2 December 2015 (UTC)

@[[User:Future Perfect at Sunrise|Fut.Perf.]], with all due respect, information like that on infoboxes are required. I was the one who reintroduced the &quot;today part of...&quot; under an IP address, which by the way I'm not giving, before creating a new account. I regret not using consensus before reintroducing &quot;today part of...&quot; infobox. Other empire and country articles like the [[Russian Empire]] and the [[Spanish Empire]] have a &quot;today part of..&quot; entry too.  &lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt;&lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Kevinmuniz115|Kevinmuniz115]] ([[User talk:Kevinmuniz115#top|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Kevinmuniz115|contribs]]) &lt;/small&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:These are also being removed in places, and probably should be in others. As for the rationale, I second the comments of Athenean, EtienneDolet, and others in a similar discussion at [[Talk:Ottoman_Empire#.22Today_part_of.22|Ottoman Empire]]. Better off without them. There is a broader discussion of the issue [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template_talk:Infobox_former_country#.22Today_part_of.22_for_empires_spanning_lots_of_modern_countries here]. [[User:Laszlo Panaflex|Laszlo Panaflex]] ([[User talk:Laszlo Panaflex|talk]]) 00:45, 1 November 2016 (UTC)

:@[[User:Laszlo Panaflex|Laszlo Panaflex]] What you said that former country articles would be better off without them is your opinion. In the discussion that you brought up, it's important for users in the discussion to state their opinions whether or not we should have the &quot;today part of..&quot; entry removed. In my opinion, I would like for former country articles to keep them as long as they're useful. [[User:Kevinmuniz115|Kevinmuniz115]] ([[User talk:Kevinmuniz115|talk]]) 21:41, 1 November 2016 (UTC)

== Please discuss changes to the lead ==

After [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Talk:Byzantine_Empire&amp;diff=681178188&amp;oldid=680844785 this] comment by {{u|Swarm}}, I decided to refrain from editing the lead here, agreeing that perhaps I was no longer approaching that area with a clear view. A [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Byzantine_Empire/Archive_12#Use.2Fmention_mismatch_in_title.2C_again consensus version] of the lead was developed by multiple editors some time ago. I urged above for changes to the lead to be discussed before being made, but that is no longer being done. So we have returned to where the lead changes pretty much daily.  Now there is a lengthy edit war going on over the &quot;Greek-speaking&quot; phrasing. (That language was part of the consensus version, for what it's worth.)  I'll not take a position whether that version should be restored or on the current edit war. But I would urge again that edits to the lead be discussed. Having the intro change on a daily basis is not a good situation, and a name-calling edit war is certainly not constructive. [[User:Laszlo Panaflex|Laszlo Panaflex]] ([[User talk:Laszlo Panaflex|talk]]) 05:20, 6 December 2015 (UTC)
:Thanks for this, I agree. Looks like one editor decided to remove &quot;Greek-speaking&quot; and it was then warred over by a bunch of IPs. The article is semi-protected now and the edit is minor, not that controversial, and not incorrect per se, so I don't think it's worth edit warring over, but it is a long-term, stable wording that probably should not have been removed unilaterally. [[User:Swarm|&lt;span style='color:black;text-shadow: 0.0em 0.0em 0.9em black'&gt;&lt;big&gt;'''S'''&lt;/big&gt;&lt;small&gt;'''''warm'''''&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Swarm|&lt;span style='color:black;text-shadow: 0.1em 0.1em 0.2em red'&gt;♠&lt;/span&gt;]] 07:41, 6 December 2015 (UTC)
:: Just to fill in a few details about what actually happened: the removal of the &quot;predominantly Greek-speaking&quot; wording from the lead was first done by 2a02:2430:3:2500::b807:3da0 on 14 November [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Byzantine_Empire&amp;diff=690656121&amp;oldid=690651056], with the reasonable-sounding argument that &quot;Linguistic distribution of the east Empire was very complex&quot;. Their new wording was quite cumbersome overall and people began tinkering with it to smoothen it out, so I later reverted the rest of the intro to the old wording, but left the &quot;Greek-speaking&quot; bit out [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Byzantine_Empire&amp;diff=692379710&amp;oldid=692362298]. I believe the IP had a point about it, because the Greek-ness is not a necessary part of the ''definition'' of what the Byzantine Empire was, which is what the sentence should be about. It was then sneakily reinserted, without an explanation, by a sock IP of banned [[User:Deucalionite]] [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Byzantine_Empire&amp;diff=693180358&amp;oldid=693123375]. Note that Deucalionite also strengthened the wording from &quot;predominantly Greek-speaking&quot; to simply &quot;Greek-speaking&quot;, which makes it factually false. Deacon of Pndapetzim was the next to remove it [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Byzantine_Empire&amp;diff=693482446&amp;oldid=693480544], again with a reasonable edit summary. Then Deucalionite went on his usual socking spree to edit-war it back in again. I have no idea who the other IP was who was reverting against him though. [[User:Future Perfect at Sunrise|Fut.Perf.]] [[User talk:Future Perfect at Sunrise|☼]] 09:14, 6 December 2015 (UTC)

===A few improvement suggestions===
When editing any other article I would not be bothered to discuss anything as unimportant as this, but knowing how sensitive the lead section of this article is, I feel obliged to post here before changing anything myself. I would like to suggest the following, relatively unimportant, improvements:
*Lead, first paragraph, second sentence: change &quot;until it fell&quot; into [[Fall of Constantinople|until it fell]]
*Fourth sentence: wiki-link &quot;historiographical&quot;; I doubt the average reader knows what [[historiography]] (as opposed to history) is
*Same sentence: replace &quot;its citizens continued to refer to their empire&quot; with &quot;its citizens and contemporaries continued to refer to it&quot;; because just &quot;citizens&quot; implies only they themselves called their empire Romania etc., which is not true. The Arabs, Turkish, Rus, and many others also called it Rûm, Romania, etc., as is explained in more detail at the end of the &quot;Nomenclature&quot; section; 
I don't expect anything of this to be really controversial. That's it, thank you for your time. [[User:Michael!|Michael!]] ([[User talk:Michael!|talk]]) 16:18, 21 December 2015 (UTC)

:Furthermore, and this is probably more controversial, I would recommend removing &quot;rather than [[Religion in ancient Rome|Roman polytheism]]&quot; at the end of the second paragraph. Just &quot;characterised by [[Eastern Orthodox Church|Orthodox Christianity]]&quot; is much better. [[User:Michael!|Michael!]] ([[User talk:Michael!|talk]]) 16:35, 21 December 2015 (UTC)

:: Hi, thanks for your suggestions. About the first two, those two extra links, I'll have to declare myself responsible, because I think we used to have both of them at some time and it was me who removed them. About linking &quot;until it fell&quot; to the [[Fall of Constantinople]], I had the feeling it was a bit of an &quot;[[WP:EGG|easter-egg link]]&quot;, because it's difficult for a reader to predict what a sentence fragment like that would link to (There is a full and overt link to the same article a few paragraphs down at the end of the lede section). About linking &quot;historiographical&quot; to [[historiography]], I felt it was giving unnecessary visual weight to a term that isn't really that explanative in the context – the [[historiography]] article deals with &quot;the study of the methodology of historians in developing history as an academic discipline&quot;, but the use of &quot;Byzantine Empire&quot; isn't really linked to any specific theory or tradition of history-writing. If the term &quot;historiographical&quot; in our sentence here is felt to be difficult to understand, a better solution would be to reword the sentence. – About &quot;citizens and contemporaries&quot;, I have no objections; this too seems to be something we used to have; if it was removed it may have been out of some concern about the idea that not ''all'' of its contemporaries ''at all times'' continued to call it &quot;Roman empire&quot;, but then, that would be yet another instance of that perennial plague of pedantry. About your fourth suggestion, again, no particular objections as far as I'm concerned, but I have to say I don't really follow you why you feel the shorter version would be better. [[User:Future Perfect at Sunrise|Fut.Perf.]] [[User talk:Future Perfect at Sunrise|☼]] 20:17, 21 December 2015 (UTC)

:::Hi, thank you for your quick reply. Yeah, I think I recall a slightly different, older version.
:::*A valid point. And yes, there is already a clear link to the [[Fall of Constantinople]] in the last sentence of the last paragraph of the lead section. However, the wording &quot;until it fell in 1453&quot; implies a sudden major event which would justify a link here. Perhaps it could be better to rewrite that sentence into &quot;... and continued to exist for an additional thousand years until it was conquered by the [[Ottoman Turks]].&quot;
:::*Concerning the second point, I respectfully disagree with rewording this term; &quot;historiographical&quot; is an appropiate and precise term, which explains (to me, at least) exactly what ERE and BE are. 
:::*Well, I didn't propose &quot;all contemporaries at all times&quot;. Adding &quot;contemporaries&quot; would provide a better coverage of the second half of the &quot;Nomenclature&quot; section. Furthermore, as I read it, this lead sentence emphasizes that they didn't call it, nor were called in their own time, ERE or BE. 
:::*As to removing &quot;rather than Roman polytheism&quot;, I feel this creates a false dichotomy. Besides &quot;Roman polytheism&quot; redirects to [[religion in ancient Rome]], which is not about a single unified state religion: it also discusses, among other things, Christianity. Furthermore, it doesn't add anything substantial, and [[MOS:INTRO]] recommends a concise lead, representing the article's most important points. I could give a lengthier argumentation, even though I guess I seem to be a pedant already :) 
::: [[User:Michael!|Michael!]] ([[User talk:Michael!|talk]]) 19:04, 23 December 2015 (UTC)

{{noindent}}
Well, I've been bold and rewrote the second paragraph of the lead in line with the points discussed above, although I also inserted a sentence on Constantine, because I felt it was required by the already existing first sentence of this paragraph (which I didn't change). [[User:Michael!|Michael!]] ([[User talk:Michael!|talk]]) 19:45, 23 December 2015 (UTC)
:PS Throughout the article's body text &quot;Byzantium&quot; and &quot;Byzantine Empire&quot; are used interchangeably. Perhaps &quot;Byzantium&quot; ought to be mentioned as an equivalent term in the lead, e.g.: &quot;The '''Byzantine Empire''' or '''Byzantium''', sometimes referred to as the '''Eastern Roman Empire''', was ...&quot;
:By the way, why are there coordinates given at the top of the article? &quot;Coordinates: 41°00′N 28°58′E&quot; This seems nonsensical (and significantly too precise), perhaps those ought to be removed. [[User:Michael!|Michael!]] ([[User talk:Michael!|talk]]) 20:08, 23 December 2015 (UTC)

== Title Name Change ==
{{archive top|result=Fruitless rehashing of same old complaint. [[User:Future Perfect at Sunrise|Fut.Perf.]] [[User talk:Future Perfect at Sunrise|☼]] 11:56, 22 December 2015 (UTC)}}
I have been quite bothered by the name of this article as it does not all give an accurate picture of what this empire is.The term Byzantine Empire is to me too archaic as Byzantium was the name of Istanbul when it was  not the capital of the Roman Empire.Also I feel the term is misleading as it implies the Byzantine empire isn't the Roman Empire at all and also the article said it was a continuation of the Roman Empire but the Byzantine Empire and the Roman Empire are the exact same entities for goodness sake and most of all this misleads that all the Roman Empire died in 476 ad rather than 
1453 ad. All what I'm requesting is to correct any errors in the article.  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/89.106.142.1|89.106.142.1]] ([[User talk:89.106.142.1|talk]]) 11:43, 22 December 2015 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
: Per Wikipedia policy, we follow the naming practices used in scholarship. It doesn't matter if you or I find this name &quot;misleading&quot;; what matters is that scholarship unanimously uses it. Period. This has all been debated ''ad nauseam''. Please read the big notice at the top of this page: &quot;Before discussing the naming and etymology of the Byzantine Empire, please visit the relevant archived discussions.&quot; [[User:Future Perfect at Sunrise|Fut.Perf.]] [[User talk:Future Perfect at Sunrise|☼]] 11:56, 22 December 2015 (UTC)
{{archive bottom}}

== Religion ==


The first line under the heading 'Religion' is as follows: ''The Byzantine Empire was a Theocracy ruled by God working through the Emperor.''

This is presented as a statement of fact. My knowledge of the Byzantine Empire is very slim, but one thing I am sure of is that it was not ruled by a supernatural being. It seems to me also that Byzantium was an empire run by an emperor or a theocracy run by religious leaders, but that it cannot have been both. 

[[Special:Contributions/86.140.142.43|86.140.142.43]] ([[User talk:86.140.142.43|talk]]) 11:46, 28 January 2016 (UTC)

: Good point. Can somebody suggest a good replacement wording? [[User:Future Perfect at Sunrise|Fut.Perf.]] [[User talk:Future Perfect at Sunrise|☼]] 13:38, 28 January 2016 (UTC)

::I think that the concept of theocracy may have to be clarified. Otherwise the BE was a theocracy. There are many RS calling it so. [[User:Dr.K.|&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight:600;font-family: arial;color: steelblue;font-size: 1em;&quot;&gt;Dr.&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Dr.K.|&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight:600;font-family: arial;color: steelblue; font-size: 1em&quot;&gt;K.&lt;/span&gt;]] 16:40, 28 January 2016 (UTC)
::: Yeah, I don't think we're debating primarily whether or not the term &quot;theocracy&quot; applies (although we might have to clarify, because &quot;theocracy&quot; is often used to imply ruling by something like a priestly class, which wasn't the case here). The main issue is the purely semantic one that we are presenting it in a wording that, if taken literally, implies the real existence and the real activity of a &quot;God&quot; that actually was ruling the empire. [[User:Future Perfect at Sunrise|Fut.Perf.]] [[User talk:Future Perfect at Sunrise|☼]] 17:01, 28 January 2016 (UTC)
::::I agree. [[User:Dr.K.|&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight:600;font-family: arial;color: steelblue;font-size: 1em;&quot;&gt;Dr.&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Dr.K.|&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight:600;font-family: arial;color: steelblue; font-size: 1em&quot;&gt;K.&lt;/span&gt;]] 17:15, 28 January 2016 (UTC)
::::So the wording should simply indicate that this is how they saw it, rather than flatly stating that as the reality. Something like, &quot;The Byzantine Empire was a Theocracy, seen by its subjects as ruled by God working through the Emperor.&quot; [[User:Laszlo Panaflex|Laszlo Panaflex]] ([[User talk:Laszlo Panaflex|talk]]) 17:32, 28 January 2016 (UTC)
:::::I think it was more complex than that. For example, this [http://www.cambridge.org/ca/academic/subjects/history/european-history-450-1000/byzantine-theocracy-weil-lectures-cincinatti reference expands on the subtleties of the term] as applied to Byzantium. [[User:Dr.K.|&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight:600;font-family: arial;color: steelblue;font-size: 1em;&quot;&gt;Dr.&lt;/span&gt;]] [[User talk:Dr.K.|&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight:600;font-family: arial;color: steelblue; font-size: 1em&quot;&gt;K.&lt;/span&gt;]] 17:49, 28 January 2016 (UTC)
::::::Unlike rulers in medieval Europe, the Byzantines considered their emperor to be acting on behalf of God, but not appointed by God. So if an emperor fucked up in some way - was considered to be unlucky or contributed to a military disaster or whatever - he could be safely deposed of and replaced by an alternative who would more correctly act on His behalf (which equated to acting in the best interests of the empire and its people). [[User:Tiptoethrutheminefield|Tiptoethrutheminefield]] ([[User talk:Tiptoethrutheminefield|talk]]) 15:36, 31 January 2016 (UTC)
I clarified the sentence. [[User:Ugly Ketchup|Ugly Ketchup]] ([[User talk:Ugly Ketchup|talk]]) 08:37, 14 April 2016 (UTC)

== Thank you! ==

I just want to thank everyone who has contributed to this article. So impressive, and I just learned so much!  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/218.144.184.29|218.144.184.29]] ([[User talk:218.144.184.29|talk]]) 08:38, 21 February 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Why is the Ottoman Empire the only listed successor==
Their were multiple successor why is the Ottoman Empire the only listed one  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/2003:57:E36E:3841:5C09:5924:C72B:B08F|2003:57:E36E:3841:5C09:5924:C72B:B08F]] ([[User talk:2003:57:E36E:3841:5C09:5924:C72B:B08F|talk]]) 20:23, 5 March 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Romanization of Greek names==

Is it standard to transcribe all pre-Modern Greek words/names in a way that implies a classical pronunciation despite that in Byzantine times, 1000 AD to be precise, most (if not all) phonological changes were completed?  For example, Βασιλεία τῶν Ῥωμαίων is transcribed &quot;Basileia tōn Rhōmaiōn&quot;, with long vowels preserved: by this time, long and short vowel distinctions are lost.  I am not very familiar with how Greek is to be transcribed in generally, but are classical pronunciations still followed through even for Modern Greek (IE. with β as 'b' not 'v', αι as 'ai' not 'e', αυ/ευ as 'au/eu' not 'av/ev')?  If it is acceptable to transcribe these words in a way reflecting Byzantine-era pronunciation, it might be recommendable.  The page on &quot;Medieval Greek&quot; does this to some extent, with πεδιά as &quot;pediá&quot; not &quot;paidiá&quot;, and οἰκία as &quot;ykía&quot; not &quot;oikía&quot;.  
[[User:Iotacist|Iotacist]] ([[User talk:Iotacist|talk]]) 01:52, 26 March 2016 (UTC)Iotacist

== main map's errors ==

Some time now i 've noticed the byzantine empire's map of 555 is carrying some serious mistakes. The most striking is the capital mark on Rome. The empire's capital always had been Constantinople (which currently is incorectly titled Byzantium). Another mistake is the depiction of trajan's era province names in justinian's era (to many to be pointed). Could the map artist who made this please make some more research and fix  it?  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/31.217.176.12|31.217.176.12]] ([[User talk:31.217.176.12|talk]]) 17:07, 8 May 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Semi-protected edit request on 28 June 2016 ==

{{edit semi-protected|Byzantine Empire|answered=yes}}
&lt;!-- State UNAMBIGUOUSLY your suggested changes. Other editors need to know what to add or remove. Blank edit requests will be declined. --&gt;

So, I did some research onto this and the Klimata region of Crimea belonged in Byzantine hands prior to the early 8th century, and supporting this is the evidential citadel that Justinian I built in the city of Kerch. Also The use of Chersonesus as a place of Exile for Justinian II. This shows that byzantines controlled southern crimea from head to toe up to the bosphorus. I have modified the map of Tataryn to include this place. Please replace the map used in the page. Also the user above's concern is certainly an issue that needs fixing. But Im afraid I couldn't do it in the map I have produced.
My link: https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Justinian555AD_with_Klimata.png
Thank you.

&lt;!-- Write your request ABOVE this line and do not remove the tildes below. --&gt;
[[User:LaikasKruger|LaikasKruger]] ([[User talk:LaikasKruger|talk]]) 00:09, 29 June 2016 (UTC)
:[[File:Red question icon with gradient background.svg|20px|link=]] '''Not done:''' it's not clear what changes you want to be made. Please mention the specific changes in a &quot;change X to Y&quot; format.&lt;!-- Template:ESp --&gt; [[User talk:Becky Sayles|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:#0092d6; background:#bae9ff&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&amp;nbsp;B &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;E &lt;/small&gt;&lt;sub&gt;C &lt;/sub&gt;&lt;small&gt;K &lt;/small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Y &lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sub&gt;S &lt;/sub&gt;&lt;small&gt;A &lt;/small&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Y L &lt;/sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;E &lt;/small&gt;&lt;sub&gt;S&amp;nbsp;&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;''']] 14:03, 6 July 2016 (UTC)
:[[File:Red information icon with gradient background.svg|20px|link=]] '''Not done:''' please provide [[WP:RS|reliable sources]] that support the change you want to be made.&lt;!-- Template:ESp --&gt; {{re|Becky Sayles}} The user wants the image in the article to be replaced with the other one, but this would need reliable sources first, and it would be better to upload it as a new revision to the original image if it can be verified in RS. [[User:Nyuszika7H|nyuszika7h]] ([[User talk:Nyuszika7H|talk]]) 14:15, 6 July 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>l7vpienptn26kn6vciaybiks64p2597</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
