<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Władysław II Jagiełło</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>5706157</id>
    <revision>
      <id>741983365</id>
      <parentid>714098156</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-30T22:35:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dthomsen8</username>
        <id>6277327</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* top */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="101798">{{Talk header}}
{{Vital article|level=4|topic=People|class=FA}}
{{Article history
|action1=PR
|action1date=23:14, 16 November 2006 
|action1link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Jogaila/archive1
|action1result=reviewed
|action1oldid=88344934

|action2=GAN
|action2date=2006-11-23, 12:18:26 
|action2result=listed
|action2oldid=89498934

|action3=FAC
|action3date=22:53, 10 February 2007
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Jogaila
|action3result=promoted
|action3oldid=107137651

|currentstatus=FA
|maindate=November 30, 2007
}}
{{On this day|date1=2011-03-04|oldid1=417004972|date2=2012-03-04|oldid2=480196999|date3=2014-03-04|oldid3=597923242}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Biography|living=no|class=FA|royalty-work-group=yes|royalty-priority=High|listas=Jogaila|politician-work-group=yes|politician-priority=high}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=FA|Medieval-task-force=yes|Baltic=yes|Polish-task-force=yes}}
{{WikiProject Poland|class=FA|importance=Top|}}
{{WikiProject Lithuania|class=FA|importance=Top|comments= [[User:M.K|M.K.]] 14:25, 30 January 2007 (UTC)}}
{{WikiProject Belarus|class=FA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Russia|class=FA|importance=High|hist=yes|mil=yes|relig=yes}}
{{WikiProject Middle Ages|class=FA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Politics|class=FA|importance=mid}}}}

==Time for the F(A)inal?==
This article is a very good GA. There is not much standing between it and the FA status. What do you think we need to improve before it is FAced? From old discussions we all know that name was the stumbling point here, but I think we were making progress in agreeing that a variant combining both names (something like [[Jogaila (Władysław II Jagiello)]], while not perfect, would satisfy all concerned. Am I right on that? If so, and we can all agree on a final stable name, I believe a FA is within our reach without much work.--&lt;sub&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid #228B22;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Piotrus|&amp;nbsp;Piotr Konieczny aka Prokonsul Piotrus&amp;nbsp;]]|[[User_talk:Piotrus|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#7CFC00;background:#006400;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;talk&amp;nbsp;&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; 12:01, 24 December 2006 (UTC)

:I don't see that the naming issue would prevent a successful FA review. No move is going to take place without a debate, so it does not impact the stability of the article. I think the main focus needs to be on copyediting the article. There's no question that it is comprehensive, more or less balanced, and well-referenced, but I don't think it is quite there yet in terms of the prose style. As for the settling the name, Shilkanni suggested the Latin '''[[Jagello]]'''. It's short, simple, and not an anachronism. When it comes to my own stuff, I'm not keen on Latinate names, but here it's not so unreasonable. [[User:Angusmclellan|Angus McLellan]]  [[User talk:Angusmclellan|(Talk)]] 12:30, 24 December 2006 (UTC)
::[[WP:FA?]] critera 1e (stability) and 1d (neutral). Article which is subject to moving back and forth is not stable, and it shows a neutrality issue as well - I think we must have a consensus on a name to move forward toward FA. Not being a native English speaker, I cannot help with copyedit (perhaps Dr. Dan, who has shown interest here, and proficiency in English language, could help with that?--&lt;sub&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid #228B22;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Piotrus|&amp;nbsp;Piotr Konieczny aka Prokonsul Piotrus&amp;nbsp;]]|[[User_talk:Piotrus|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#7CFC00;background:#006400;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;talk&amp;nbsp;&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; 12:59, 24 December 2006 (UTC)

:::The factual content of this article is solid (though there's a little too much of it, in my opinion). What I think would fail this as an FA is the prose, which is a long way short of excellent, I would suggest. The basic accuracy of the English is very good, but the article is slightly tough going. About half the sentences start off with a preliminary clause, and many get snowed under with subsidiary clauses, muffling the main subject and verb and often restricting the directness of the information. 

:::I am willing to help with a copy-edit. Can anyone point me to the discussion that took place during the good-article assessment? I can't find it. Cheers. [[User:Qp10qp|qp10qp]] 23:11, 27 December 2006 (UTC)

::::Such as it is, it is in [[Talk:Jogaila/Archive_9]]. Ling.Nut, who reviewed this, did a fair bit of the copyediting himself. The changes during the review are about covered by [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Jogaila&amp;diff=89808871&amp;oldid=88068417 this diff]. Quite a bit, but still more to do. [[User:Angusmclellan|Angus McLellan]]  [[User talk:Angusmclellan|(Talk)]] 23:39, 27 December 2006 (UTC)

::::: I see congratulations are finally in order on FA status!! —[[User:Vecrumba|PētersV]] ([[User talk:Vecrumba|talk]]) 20:34, 28 March 2008 (UTC)

::::::This is very [[Rip Van Winkle]] of you, Pēters, but cheers! [[User:Qp10qp|qp10qp]] ([[User talk:Qp10qp|talk]]) 21:36, 28 March 2008 (UTC)

==Regent==

I'd like to ask about this sentence at the beginning: ''He was regent of Lithuania from 1377.'' Is that the right term? Lower down, it says that Algirdas was ''the Grand Duke of Lithuania...Jogaila's father was a de facto co-regent of Lithuania and ruled the country together with his brother, Kęstutis''. The terms seem a little over-nuanced and contradictory: it looks to me rather as if Algirdas and Kęstutis were co-rulers, and that on Algirdas's death, Jogaila became co-ruler with Kęstutis in his father's place. Is that an oversimplification? Whatever the case, I doubt &quot;regent&quot; is the ''mot juste''. [[User:Qp10qp|qp10qp]] 04:31, 29 December 2006 (UTC)

====First sign of madness: answering your own questions====

:I have looked into it a bit further, including at the page [[Coregency]]. On that basis, it would pass to call him a co-regent, I suppose, but the word ''regent'' on its own doesn't indicate the true position, in my opinion. In the absence of a reply to my query, I've changed the text to: &quot;He ruled in Lithuania from 1377, at first with his uncle, Kęstutis&quot;. (He inherited Algirdas's title of grand duke, while Kęstutis remained the duke of Trakai till he pinched Jogaila's title.) [[User:Qp10qp|qp10qp]] 15:47, 6 January 2007 (UTC)

::You're right and that's [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Jogaila&amp;diff=78069083&amp;oldid=78068188 precisely] what the original version of the header stated: he was a co-regent. However, it seems that someone couldn't stand that word and changed it to something definitely less accurate. ''&lt;font color=&quot;#901&quot;&gt;//&lt;/font&gt;''[[User:Halibutt|Halibu]][[User talk:Halibutt|tt]] 22:06, 9 January 2007 (UTC)

==Hospodar==

I'm not sure I grasp this term in the following, or its implication:

''Since for most of his subjects Jogaila was a [[hospodar]] rather than &quot;didysis kunigaikštis&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Łukowski&quot;/&gt; the adoption of Orthodox Christianity seemed more natural.''

The Wikipedia entry on [[hospodar]] wasn't too helpful to me on this. Is the point that his people in the Ruthenian lands regarded him as an overlord rather than a prince? If so, how does that affect the religious conversion point? (Was this something to do with the Patriarch of the Orthodox church being based in Moscow?) As far as I can gather from the footnote on ''didysis kunigaikštis'', the term means a high ruler with lordship over lower rulers, so the distinction from ''hospodar'' isn't entirely clear to me. I need to find some plain English here, to offset the difficult non-English terms which might count as specialist jargon. For the moment, I have left this point out and concentrated on the point that Jogaila's mother would have been Orthodox. [[User:Qp10qp|qp10qp]] 22:00, 29 December 2006 (UTC)

:The line seems unencylopedic and irrelevant.  I assume it's implying that because he had more Orthodox subjects, he would be more inclined to accept Orthodoxy.  It would make more sense as something like:  &quot;Jogaila, having far more Orthodox subjects than Catholic would seemingly have been more likely to accept Orthodox Christianity.&quot;  However, it's still not a good line because it's speculative and doesn't make sense because those who called him didysis kunigaikštis weren't Christian, they were pagan.

:[[User:Leo1410|Leo1410]] 22:32, 29 December 2006 (UTC)

::Yes; I have retained the point that Orthodoxy might have been the likelier choice but omitted the term ''hospodar'' in this context.  Cheers. [[User:Qp10qp|qp10qp]] 15:54, 6 January 2007 (UTC)

:::This is almost an exact quotation from the original source (cited) and I believe it should have stayed the way it was. However, you're right that the style might've implied too much in this context, and especially so for uninformed readers. ''&lt;font color=&quot;#901&quot;&gt;//&lt;/font&gt;''[[User:Halibutt|Halibu]][[User talk:Halibutt|tt]] 22:09, 9 January 2007 (UTC)

Höm, isn't &quot;hospodar&quot; the Romanian rendition of slavic &quot;overlord&quot;? and the Russian, presumably also Ruthenian, rendition would be &quot;gospodar&quot;?
Anyway, as Leo above opined, that word is not useful to give lucid explanation about the point that is intended here. The point is familiar from several books (of which I do not now remember to name any:) - his conversion was a thing rivalled between eastern and western christianity, ties to eastern were stronger (as was its &quot;expectancy value&quot;), but he chose western (which was regarded moe surprising than had been the choice of eastern). [[User:Shilkanni|Shilkanni]] 15:57, 5 February 2007 (UTC)

==Copy-edit==

I've finished a thorough copy-edit and made my best efforts towards the &quot;compelling prose&quot; required for FA. I've cut about 1500 words from the article to make it more sprightly (in fact, more than that from the narrative text, since I've added an alphabetical references section), but there remain a similar number of notes and references, so the sum of information is much the same. I have a long list of details to research now in order to check and sharpen the article further: so I'll be posting some questions here as I go along, if anyone can help. 

I find Halibutt's referencing excellent; I've checked most of his references to English books and they pan out exquisitely, and so I'm sure his Polish and Lithuanian ones are just as reliable. In my opinion, this is a watertight FA candidate, except for (sighs)....the wretched title business. For me, &quot;Jogaila (Wladyslaw II Jagiello)&quot; would be perfect; but obviously the FA scrutineers will want to roast that old chestnut all over again. Questions here soon. (If no one answers, I'll come knocking on your doors!) [[User:Qp10qp|qp10qp]] 01:20, 8 January 2007 (UTC)
:Thank you for your excellent copyedit. I am sure other editors will be happy to helfpul, alas, [[User:Halibutt]], who would likely be the best person to answer your questions, is now on extended wikibreak :( --&lt;sub&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid #228B22;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Piotrus|&amp;nbsp;Piotr Konieczny aka Prokonsul Piotrus&amp;nbsp;]]|[[User_talk:Piotrus|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#7CFC00;background:#006400;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;talk&amp;nbsp;&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; 01:23, 8 January 2007 (UTC)

==Angevin sickness?==

I haven't had any luck sourcing the following, and so—with reluctance because it is melodramatic—I've removed it till some evidence surfaces:

&lt;blockquote&gt;The deaths are often attributed to the so-called &quot;Angevin sickness&quot;, a supposed genetic defect that raised the mortality rate among children of Angevin blood very high. During the 19th-century exhumation of Jadwiga's remains, her [[pelvis]] was found to be unusually narrow, another factor which might have contributed to her death.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

At first I just wanted a source for the notion that Jadwiga and her daughter might have died for this reason, but I couldn't even find a source for the 'Angevin sickness' itself. Nor could I find a source for the exhumations (which are mentioned in Jadwiga's article), the commentary on which might shed light on these speculations (though I would think it unlikely a narrow pelvis caused the deaths; infections etc. being only too common). If someone can find anything in the Polish sources or through superior research skills to mine, please do, and perhaps we can restore this intriguing note. [[User:Qp10qp|qp10qp]] 00:17, 9 January 2007 (UTC)

::The Angevin disease was briefly mentioned in Jasienica (op.cit., the English note was pretty much a translation of the mention in the Polish book), who however was by no means a doctor and only briefly mentioned the sickness, without going into too much details. Does anyone have a decent monograph on Angevins to confirm the theory is cited anywhere else? As to the pelvis, this seems rather obvious: the narrower the pelvis, the higher risk for birth complications. This is true even in modern times, not mention Middle Ages. ''&lt;font color=&quot;#901&quot;&gt;//&lt;/font&gt;''[[User:Halibutt|Halibu]][[User talk:Halibutt|tt]] 22:23, 9 January 2007 (UTC)

::I cannot find evidence of this anywhere else. I've asked around among some medievalists and they haven't heard of it. But if Jasienica said it, I can put it back in under his general cite. I've introduced words like &quot;supposed&quot; so that it would then count as Jasienica's speculation—a valid enough cite. [[User:Qp10qp|qp10qp]] 22:57, 9 January 2007 (UTC)
:::The day before I asked a noted historian [[Jerzy Besala]] about the Angevin problem. The guy is quite a specialist as he recently published a 3-volume monograph on the private life of Polish monarchs. He confirmed that he had read about the problems Angevin women had, but he could not point me to any particular source. Which doesn't mean I'm not searching :) . ''&lt;font color=&quot;#901&quot;&gt;//&lt;/font&gt;''[[User:Halibutt|Halibu]][[User talk:Halibutt|tt]] 03:34, 4 February 2007 (UTC)

::::The Angevin also in other countries had unusually high rate of infant mortality. This led in quite a many genealogical branches to a situation of total extinction. Of king Charles II of Naples' numerous children's lineages, all those descending from his five or more sons died totally out. Only a couple of branches, descending from his daughters, survive. That's really unusual, and indicates there must be some systematical reason for it. [[User:Shilkanni|Shilkanni]] 16:05, 5 February 2007 (UTC)

==Władysław of Opole==

I removed the following note because I couldn't source it:

''Eventually Prince [[Władysław of Opole]] became Jogaila's godfather.''

I am sure it's true (because Władysław of Opole had been close to Jadwiga's father), but perhaps the source of the information lies in a Polish book. If any Polish editors can help, by all means  do; but I have to say that I don't think this fact will be much of a loss to the article. The other thing bothering me was that in places this chap was described as a duke, not a prince. [[User:Qp10qp|qp10qp]] 02:42, 9 January 2007 (UTC)

::AAMoF the person of Jagiello's godfather is a tad problematic as at least two people are mentioned as such. Jasienica suggests it was Władysław, but there was some other candidate as well (bishop of Cracow, if memory serves me). As to the titles - the problem is easier to solve than you think. Polish (and hence Lithuanian) system of honorary titles is fairly simple, mostly because of the post-Jagiello times. In short, the division into ''dux'' and ''princeps'' never fully developed in Poland as the earlier was more akin to [[Voivode]] and became a function rather than a title (do I make myself clear enough?). Hence in Poland there were common nobles (predecessors of the [[szlachta]]) and there were some people to hold the rank of ''książę'', which is translated to English as either ''Duke'' or ''Prince'', depending mostly on translator's choice. We might go either way here, as long as we're consistent. In the case of Władysław, he was a Duke of Opole (English meaning), but also a Prince of Opole (of princely family - the Piasts), a palatine of Hungary (hence also a Duke since palatine and dux were used interchangeably), and so on. And, last but not least, in his youth he was also a prince since his father was Bolko II, also a ruler. ''&lt;font color=&quot;#901&quot;&gt;//&lt;/font&gt;''[[User:Halibutt|Halibu]][[User talk:Halibutt|tt]] 22:35, 9 January 2007 (UTC)

==Pontoon bridge claim==

Angus further up this page quizzed the claim about the pontoon bridge. I have been able to find confirmation that the pontoon bridge was big, but I can't source the following note:

''It was one of the first uses of pontoon bridges in European warfare since the [[Battle of Garigliano]], and the first by a European power since antiquity.''

I can't find where this comes from. Once again, it may be in a Polish book; if someone can reference it from one, all the better. In any case, even if a historian said it, the note verges on peacockery, in my opinion, and isn't strictly necessary to the article—though it would be nice to reinsert it if someone finds a source. For the moment, I've removed it. [[User:Qp10qp|qp10qp]] 03:07, 9 January 2007 (UTC)

::Good spotting! Indeed, the remark was unsourced primarily because... I couldn't remember what the source was. Some time ago I was writing a paper on military engineering in late Middle Ages and dug up several works in the Central Military Library in Warsaw. However, both the paper and my notes are lost now - and the source is lost now. ''&lt;font color=&quot;#901&quot;&gt;//&lt;/font&gt;''[[User:Halibutt|Halibu]][[User talk:Halibutt|tt]] 22:43, 9 January 2007 (UTC)

== Languages ==

I wonder what is the source for Władysław never learning Polish. As far as I remember Długosz (who was far from being sympathetic to Jagiello, to put it mildly), he mocked his fancy accent and errors, but that would mean that Jagiello did learn Polish... ''&lt;font color=&quot;#901&quot;&gt;//&lt;/font&gt;''[[User:Halibutt|Halibu]][[User talk:Halibutt|tt]] 00:58, 11 January 2007 (UTC)

:You're right. I think I misremembered what I read in the ''Lituanus'' article. I was going to double check that, because even as  I wrote it, it didn't seem likely. (It actually says &quot;He never became fluent in Polish&quot;.) Good call; I'll change it. [[User:Qp10qp|qp10qp]] 01:42, 11 January 2007 (UTC)

== Audio samples ==

I think the article would benefit from audio samples of &quot;Jogaila&quot; and &quot;Władysław II Jagiełło&quot;, which would especially be good for a FAC. [[User:Olessi|Olessi]] 20:33, 11 January 2007 (UTC)

== Requested move - hopefuly the last and best compromise ==
&lt;div class=&quot;boilerplate&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #efe; margin: 2em 0 0 0; padding: 0 10px 0 10px; border: 1px dotted #aaa;&quot;&gt;&lt;!-- Template:polltop --&gt;
:''The following discussion is an archived debate of the {{{type|proposal}}}. &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/font&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on the talk page. No further edits should be made to this section. ''

{{{result|The result of the debate was}}} '''NO CONSENSUS''' to move page, per discussion below. -[[User:GTBacchus|GTBacchus]]&lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:GTBacchus|talk]])&lt;/sup&gt; 21:44, 10 February 2007 (UTC)
&lt;hr/&gt;
Jogaila → Jogaila (Władysław II Jagiełło) – The editors are divided around Jogaila and Władysław II Jagiełło. In the past, some controversial moves have led to heated debates (see archives if you dare). Using both names seems like the reasonable compromise that should satisfy both parties.--&lt;sub&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid #228B22;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Piotrus|&amp;nbsp;Piotr Konieczny aka Prokonsul Piotrus&amp;nbsp;]]|[[User_talk:Piotrus|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#7CFC00;background:#006400;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;talk&amp;nbsp;&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; 19:48, 31 January 2007 (UTC)

=== Survey ===
''Add &quot;* Support&quot; or &quot;* Oppose&quot; or other opinion in the appropriate section followed by a brief explanation, then sign your opinion with &lt;nowiki&gt;~~~~&lt;/nowiki&gt;

* '''Nominator support''', obviously.--&lt;sub&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid #228B22;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Piotrus|&amp;nbsp;Piotr Konieczny aka Prokonsul Piotrus&amp;nbsp;]]|[[User_talk:Piotrus|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#7CFC00;background:#006400;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;talk&amp;nbsp;&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; 18:19, 5 February 2007 (UTC)
* '''Support''' per Piotruś. Last debate was really very heated, too much heated. Both sides were right in some points and it really seems to me some hard-line ideas would never gain consensus here. Current proposal is good I think, kind of compromise which should satisfy both parties. Regards. - [[User:Darwinek|Darwinek]] 21:44, 31 January 2007 (UTC)
*'''Oppose''' We should use a single name; compromise would be to make that name ''Jagiello''. [[User:Pmanderson|Septentrionalis]] &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Pmanderson|PMAnderson]]&lt;/small&gt; 21:51, 31 January 2007 (UTC)
* '''Support'''. The &quot;Wladyslaw II Jagiello&quot; version would still be my first choice, since that is the spelling (with or without diacritics) that is used most often in English-language encyclopedias.  However, I would be willing to accept a combinatorial name as a compromise position. I would also prefer it without diacritics, since that makes it easier to link to, but again, I'll accept it ''with'' diacritics, in the interest of compromise.  Either way is fine with me, as long as a version of &quot;Wladyslaw II Jagiello&quot; is included somewhere in the title. --[[User:Elonka|El]][[User talk:Elonka|on]][[Special:Contributions/Elonka|ka]] 23:17, 31 January 2007 (UTC)
*'''Oppose''', of course. Why waste our time? [[WP:NOT|Wikipedia is not a democracy]] and [[WP:RM|requested moves are not a vote]]. Nothing that is decided here by a small number of editors can justify a title like [[Jogaila (Władysław II Jagiełło)]], a million miles from anything contained in [[WP:NAME]]. Elonka, at least, should know this. [[User:Angusmclellan|Angus McLellan]]  [[User talk:Angusmclellan|(Talk)]] 23:26, 31 January 2007 (UTC)
::''Why waste our time?'' - because given the choice of Jogaila (not used by majority of sources) and Jogaila (Władysław II Jagiełło - the most popular variant of the most popular 'W/L II J' name), it's better to chose one which will be recognized by most scholars and people familiar with that person. And as a gesture of good will I have no problem seeing Jogaila in the title, even if it breaks Wiki conventions and is not very popular but dear to our Lithuanian collegues.--&lt;sub&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid #228B22;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Piotrus|&amp;nbsp;Piotr Konieczny aka Prokonsul Piotrus&amp;nbsp;]]|[[User_talk:Piotrus|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#7CFC00;background:#006400;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;talk&amp;nbsp;&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; 00:39, 1 February 2007 (UTC)
* '''Oppose'''. I appreciate Piotrus' will to compromise, but it's not the way to go IMO. First of all it would create a bad precedent violating the current rules of naming and secondly would allow anyone to move the rest of articles on Polish monarchs to equally bizarre titles, despite all the previous compromises (like, say, [[Stanisław August Poniatowski]] moved to [[Stanislovas Augustas Poniatovskis (Stanisław August Poniatowski)]]). ''&lt;font color=&quot;#901&quot;&gt;//&lt;/font&gt;''[[User:Halibutt|Halibu]][[User talk:Halibutt|tt]] 09:40, 1 February 2007 (UTC)
*'''Oppose'''. The article currently reflects the essense of the new proposition. In short, both names are represented equally and in chronological order. It's just fine and should satisfy everyone. As to equating Jogaila to the absurd analogy regarding &quot;Lithuanianizing&quot; Stanislovas Augustas Poniatovskis, the fact is that Jagiełło is a &quot;Polonization&quot; of Jogaila. By now this should be the easiest issue to not have to deal with. [[User:Dr. Dan|Dr. Dan]] 15:35, 1 February 2007 (UTC)
*'''Oppose''' per Septentrionalis, sort of.  Neither of these are the names by which he is best known in English, and combining them isn't really an improvement.  Go with [[Jagiello]].  [[User:Gene Nygaard|Gene Nygaard]] 03:49, 2 February 2007 (UTC)
*'''Weak Support''' having both names is the only way to present this article with a NPOV.  He was the sovereign monarch of two distinct medieval states, and to present one over the other is inherently POV.  Parentheses are confusing, though, because on wiki they imply ambiguity.  [[User:Leo1410|Leo1410]] 03:55, 3 February 2007 (UTC)
*'''Oppose'''. Would those who support this double name also support [[History of Gdańsk|History of Danzig (Gdańsk)]]? - &amp;nbsp;[[User:Matthead|Matthead]]&amp;nbsp;[[User_talk:Matthead|&lt;sup&gt;discuß!&lt;/sup&gt;]]&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;[[EU|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#ffff00;background:#0000cc;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;O&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/font&gt;]]&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp; 23:36, 4 February 2007 (UTC)
*'''Support'''. The best that can be hoped for under the circumstances. [[User:Appleseed|Appleseed]] ([[User talk:Appleseed|Talk]]) 23:46, 4 February 2007 (UTC)
*'''Oppose'''. I still would support the simple &quot;Jagello&quot;. The proposal above is cluttered and besides contravenes naming convention. [[User:Shilkanni|Shilkanni]] 15:40, 5 February 2007 (UTC)
*'''Support'''. It could be good step to the compromise and to the more stable article name. [[User:Orionus|Orionus]] 16:03, 5 February 2007 (UTC)
*'''Oppose'''. [[User:M.K|M.K.]] 11:55, 6 February 2007 (UTC)
*'''Weak Support''' [[User:Szopen|Szopen]] 14:01, 6 February 2007 (UTC)
*'''Support'''.  [[User:logologist|logologist]]|[[User_talk:logologist|Talk]] 15:31, 7 February 2007 (UTC)
*'''Oppose'''. For the reasons stated by users [[User:Dr. Dan|Dr. Dan]] and [[User:Halibutt|Halibu]] as well as conflicting with [[WP:NAME| wikipedia naming conventions]]. [[User: Tautvydas|Tautvydas]] 22:44, 6 February 2007 (UTC)
*'''Support''' per Elonka and Orionus [[User:Space Cadet|Space Cadet]] 13:32, 8 February 2007 (UTC)
*'''Comment'''.  Just as a reminder to everyone, this is not a vote. You need to explain your actual thoughts on the matter, and simply posting your name with &quot;support&quot; or &quot;oppose&quot; has practically no weight with a closing admin.  See [[WP:DDV#Deletion and featuring]] --[[User:Elonka|El]][[User talk:Elonka|on]][[Special:Contributions/Elonka|ka]] 01:25, 8 February 2007 (UTC)
**Can you point me to relevant part of the WP:RM that states that? Not that I disagree with you.--&lt;sub&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid #228B22;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Piotrus|&amp;nbsp;Piotr Konieczny aka Prokonsul Piotrus&amp;nbsp;]]|[[User_talk:Piotrus|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#7CFC00;background:#006400;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;talk&amp;nbsp;&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; 01:49, 8 February 2007 (UTC)
*** I DO disagree on the other hand. It is on the actual vote where you have to state your reasons. Survey is just a survey. [[User:Space Cadet|Space Cadet]] 02:13, 8 February 2007 (UTC)
****This ''is'' the actual !vote. [[User:Pmanderson|Septentrionalis]] &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Pmanderson|PMAnderson]]&lt;/small&gt; 05:41, 8 February 2007 (UTC)
*****Speaking as someone who closes a lot of move requests, it's true that bare &quot;support&quot;s and &quot;oppose&quot;s have almost (but not quite) zero weight in my decision.  In this case, there's no clear consensus for any particular title, and numbers of &quot;votes&quot; or &quot;!votes&quot; can't really disguise that fact.  I think a survey listing several name choices and allowing participants to comment on any or all of them might be more effective in this situation, or maybe the Mediation Cabal will help out. &lt;p&gt; I'm going to bump this request to the top of [[WP:RM]] again and check back in five days. -[[User:GTBacchus|GTBacchus]]&lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:GTBacchus|talk]])&lt;/sup&gt; 21:04, 9 February 2007 (UTC)
******GTBacchus, is this a new policy, or does every &quot;closer&quot; interpret the votes as they see fit? I hope the short explanation won't lower the weight of my vote; I previously wrote pages upon pages explaining my position on this article's title, and I'm not inclined to rewrite my explanation every time it's under debate. Of course, since I don't believe you've taken part in the older discussions (which are now archived, out of sight and out of mind), you probably wouldn't know this. [[User:Appleseed|Appleseed]] ([[User talk:Appleseed|Talk]]) 21:16, 9 February 2007 (UTC)
*******Well, [[WP:NOT#Wikipedia is not a democracy|WP:NOT a democracy]] (policy) and [[WP:PNSD#Deletion, moving and featuring|WP:PNSD]] (guideline) aren't new, and administrators have always been allowed discretion in reading consensus out of discussions such as [[WP:RM]] and [[WP:AfD]].  In cases where you've commented previously, a link to a relevant section of archive discussion can save you lots of repetition, and have the benefit of directing the closing admin (or whoever) to previous relevant discussion.  Decisions here are based on arguments, not numbers, or else we've given up on our mission to aim for neutrality, because we allow history to be written by the majority. &lt;p&gt; In this case, it's clear to any &quot;closer&quot; that we're dealing with complex arguments, and that's why the request is still hanging out at [[WP:RM]].  It's difficult to read this talk page and see any kind of consensus in it. -[[User:GTBacchus|GTBacchus]]&lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:GTBacchus|talk]])&lt;/sup&gt; 22:24, 9 February 2007 (UTC)
* '''Support''', in spite of some drawbacks (to be worked on), I appreciate the idea of a compromise. By the way, I would support other more popular or more encyclopedic names as well (Jagiello, Jagello, WIIJ...) &lt;s&gt;[[User:Beaumont|Beaumont]] forgot to sign&lt;/s&gt; thanks, now signed! --[[User:Beaumont|Beaumont]] [[User_Talk:Beaumont|&lt;small&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#118811&quot;&gt;(@)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;]] 13:53, 8 February 2007 (UTC)
*'''Support''' [[User:LUCPOL|LUCPOL]] 21:04, 9 February 2007 (UTC)
*'''Support''', seems to be a fair compromise... &lt;b&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;#2EC401&quot;&gt;[[User:Jacek_Kendysz|Jacek]]&lt;/font&gt; &lt;font color=&quot;#206600&quot;&gt;[[User:Jacek_Kendysz|Kendysz]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/b&gt; 00:40, 10 February 2007 (UTC)

=== Discussion ===
''Add any additional comments''
For those opposed to diactrics, please wait until this dispute resolve and then suggest a move to undiactriciazed version; otherwise we will never settle this discussion.--&lt;sub&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid #228B22;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Piotrus|&amp;nbsp;Piotr Konieczny aka Prokonsul Piotrus&amp;nbsp;]]|[[User_talk:Piotrus|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#7CFC00;background:#006400;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;talk&amp;nbsp;&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; 19:48, 31 January 2007 (UTC)
:I don't believe ''Wladyslaw'' is English usage; I'm sure ''Władysław'' isn't. We can discuss ''Ladislaus''. Nevertheless, if the diacritics are to be postponed, the way to do that is to propose the ''diacriticless'' version, and then propose a change. [[User:Pmanderson|Septentrionalis]] &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Pmanderson|PMAnderson]]&lt;/small&gt; 21:57, 31 January 2007 (UTC)

Some of the actual data on this are to be found at [[Talk:Jogaila/Archive_7#Name_as_it_appears_in_encyclopedias_and_dictionaries]]

I am skeptical about this vote; we already tried various combinations of names, but they were resisted. Mediation probably would not solve the issue too, besides starting naming problems then article is in FAC is bad idea. [[User:M.K|M.K.]] 16:25, 1 February 2007 (UTC)

::# Moving the article against the consensus and against the rules was a bad idea
::# Defending the illegal move at all cost, further breaching a lot of policies (like NPA and CIV) was a bad idea
::# Expanding the article was a good idea
::# Nominating the article to FAC was a good idea
:: In which points of this story have you taken part? ''&lt;font color=&quot;#901&quot;&gt;//&lt;/font&gt;''[[User:Halibutt|Halibu]][[User talk:Halibutt|tt]] 00:25, 5 February 2007 (UTC)
:::: Consult [[WP:Dick]]. [[User:M.K|M.K.]] 11:55, 6 February 2007 (UTC)
:::[[User:Matthead]] just brought up a very relevant point (a point to keep in mind in the ensuing debate), i.e., the name of Danzig must certainly be the more prevalently used toponym in the English language, and in all historical and &quot;scholarly&quot; sources concerning it. [[User:Dr. Dan|Dr. Dan]] 03:45, 5 February 2007 (UTC)
::::And this is relevant to our discussion how...? Please keep on topic.--&lt;sub&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid #228B22;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Piotrus|&amp;nbsp;Piotr Konieczny aka Prokonsul Piotrus&amp;nbsp;]]|[[User_talk:Piotrus|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#7CFC00;background:#006400;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;talk&amp;nbsp;&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; 05:10, 5 February 2007 (UTC)

=== Comment on % ===
The [[Talk:Jogaila/Archive_7#Approval_poll_for_article_renaming|last, controversial RM]] resulted in a move to the version supported by ''only'' 33% of voters (16 out of 48). The current RM seems to have attracted fewer respondents so far (I count about 20) but the votes seem to be spread 50/50. While not perfect, it certainly appears that the name supported by half of discutants is a better choice then the one supported by one third...  --&lt;sub&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid #228B22;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Piotrus|&amp;nbsp;Piotr Konieczny aka Prokonsul Piotrus&amp;nbsp;]]|[[User_talk:Piotrus|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#7CFC00;background:#006400;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;talk&amp;nbsp;&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; 00:41, 10 February 2007 (UTC)

:There is clearly no consensus for any particular title for this article.  Moving articles from one controversial title to another is discouraged (50% versus 30% isn't really compelling), so I'm delisting the request from [[WP:RM]] until such time as people come to an agreement over what to call this page.  Redirects are in place, so readers can find the content, anyway. -[[User:GTBacchus|GTBacchus]]&lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:GTBacchus|talk]])&lt;/sup&gt; 21:41, 10 February 2007 (UTC)
:''The above discussion is preserved as an archive of the debate.  &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/span&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on this talk page. No further edits should be made to this section.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- Template:pollbottom --&gt;

==Request for mediation==
A mediation request concerning the naming of this article has been opened at [[Wikipedia:Requests for mediation/Jogaila]]. All interested editors should add themselves to the request, and sign acceptance. (You could add yourself and sign to reject, but that seems rather pointless). [[User:Angusmclellan|Angus McLellan]]  [[User talk:Angusmclellan|(Talk)]] 01:03, 1 February 2007 (UTC)
:If this happens, the Mediation will be summarily rejected.  Unless there is clear evidence that the refusals make mediation impossible, I will file with the Mediation Cabal, which is less particular about what it accepts. [[User:Pmanderson|Septentrionalis]] &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Pmanderson|PMAnderson]]&lt;/small&gt; 15:52, 1 February 2007 (UTC)
::The Mediation request was rejected. It was accepted by a large number of editors, and ignored to death by one. There are multiple sides here, besides the Polish-Lithuanian issue.  We could go back to the Mediation Committee with the eight of us who are interested, leaving Dr Dan to join us later if he likes; or we could invoke the [[Wikipedia:Mediation Cabal]]. Which? [[User:Pmanderson|Septentrionalis]] &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Pmanderson|PMAnderson]]&lt;/small&gt; 15:51, 8 February 2007 (UTC)
::: Coming back seem to be a good idea. Initially, we wanted to do that and at the moment I see no reason to change our minds (just don't want to formulate it more explicitly) --[[User:Beaumont|Beaumont]] [[User_Talk:Beaumont|&lt;small&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#118811&quot;&gt;(@)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;]] 16:31, 8 February 2007 (UTC)
:::: Those who want to discuss the matter should do so, those who prefer to snip with sarcasm during RM would not have helped much anyway and if the find themselves alone when it comes to the next RM... their loss.--&lt;sub&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid #228B22;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Piotrus|&amp;nbsp;Piotr Konieczny aka Prokonsul Piotrus&amp;nbsp;]]|[[User_talk:Piotrus|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#7CFC00;background:#006400;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;talk&amp;nbsp;&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; 17:13, 8 February 2007 (UTC)

This case appeas to have been '''rejected'''.  Good.  [[User:Gene Nygaard|Gene Nygaard]] 23:11, 9 February 2007 (UTC)
:Good how? -[[User:GTBacchus|GTBacchus]]&lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:GTBacchus|talk]])&lt;/sup&gt; 23:14, 9 February 2007 (UTC)
::Presumably because nothing good would have come of it. There's a perfectly reasonable compromise suggested by Shilkanni - use the Latin name Jagello because it represents what people at the time thought his name was. What could mediation somewhere else achieve that compromise here couldn't? A compromise on the &quot;a camel is a horse designed by committee&quot; principle, as proposed by Piotrus, is no compromise at all. There are at least five short, simple names that we could use: Jogaila, Jagailo, Jagello, Jahailo, and Jagiello (there being no reason to limit this to Polish, Lithuanian, and Latin). If someone can find a sixth name, we can roll a die and see what fate ordains for us. [[User:Angusmclellan|Angus McLellan]]  [[User talk:Angusmclellan|(Talk)]] 23:39, 9 February 2007 (UTC)
:::Leaving the page where it sits is better than moving from one controversial title to another. -[[User:GTBacchus|GTBacchus]]&lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:GTBacchus|talk]])&lt;/sup&gt; 23:41, 9 February 2007 (UTC)
::::Hmm, well I don't think that there's a much more controversial name than [[Jogaila (Władysław II Jagiełło)]], unless it's my (ha, ha, only serious) suggestion [[Jogaila (Władysław II Jagiełło) (Jagailo Olgerdovich)]]. [[User:Angusmclellan|Angus McLellan]]  [[User talk:Angusmclellan|(Talk)]] 23:47, 9 February 2007 (UTC)
:::::Due to an error on my part, I must apologize to all concerned for creating this new conundrum on this never ending debate. Before a new circus is started, I wish to remind all people of good will, that the current article and its title, cover the man and his original name, and his later name, chronologically and alphabetically, and historically. All of the possible links and redirects bring all those interested and looking for information about the man, to the article. The educational aspects of the the current title ('''Jogaila or Władysław II Jagiełło''') should easily assuage even the most rabid nationalists of any stripe, as all bases are covered. ''Chronologically'' and ''Alphabetically''! Let those most concerned with the issue, not masquerade or pretend that it is a scholarly or academic motive that makes them furious with the current title. Or makes them want to change the current title to something else. There is too much evidence that demonstrates the lack of consistency by those wanting a change for anything but for very personal reasons. Think about it. It's fine the way it is. [[User:Dr. Dan|Dr. Dan]] 00:41, 10 February 2007 (UTC)
:::Good because [[Wikipedia:Requested moves]] ''is'' (or at least should be) the primary dispute resolution process for following naming conventions.  Good because &quot;dispute resolution&quot; shouldn't come into it unless it involves some sort of abuse of process; inability to reach consensus isn't necessarily an abuse of process.  Good because mediation in particular is terribily unweildy and unlikely to achieve much with so many participants.  
:::What we really need is better spelled out provisions within the requested moves area for the default to go back to in case a dispute arises.  What we also need is a more rigorous notion that once it has come up for discussion on requested moves, future changes not going through requested moves should be reverted on sight. 
:::Furthermore, if there is going to be any sort of &quot;appeals&quot; process or whatever dealing with requested moves, there should be some provision for that being noted and linked to on the [[WP:RM]] page. [[User:Gene Nygaard|Gene Nygaard]] 14:51, 11 February 2007 (UTC)

Can we move this to the most common known name?  Jagiello please!!!  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/159.18.26.14|159.18.26.14]] ([[User talk:159.18.26.14|talk]]) 17:37, 21 September 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==ArticleHistory==
Anybody fills like implementing [[:Template:ArticleHistory]] here? It is very much needed.--&lt;sub&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid #228B22;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Piotrus|&amp;nbsp;Piotr Konieczny aka Prokonsul Piotrus&amp;nbsp;]]|[[User_talk:Piotrus|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#7CFC00;background:#006400;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;talk&amp;nbsp;&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; 01:29, 1 February 2007 (UTC)
::I gave it a try at [[User:Halibutt/test3]], but it seems it would replace only two tags at the top, so perhaps we should wait until the guys managing that template let us include all the other processes (mediation, moves and so on). ''&lt;font color=&quot;#901&quot;&gt;//&lt;/font&gt;''[[User:Halibutt|Halibu]][[User talk:Halibutt|tt]] 09:33, 1 February 2007 (UTC)
:::The dates were wrong - I corrected them - if you need help in understanding how to find dates in article history let me know.  It may only eliminate two boxes now, but there will be another line when the FAC is promoted or failed, and with subsequent action.  The template covers FAC/FAR history - it doesn't address the proliferation of WikiProject templates.  [[User:SandyGeorgia|Sandy&lt;font color=&quot;green&quot;&gt;Georgia&lt;/font&gt;]] ([[User talk:SandyGeorgia|Talk]]) 21:43, 1 February 2007 (UTC)
::::Another nice tool is the '|small=yes' command - see [[Talk:New York City]] where it is used with great effect.--&lt;sub&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid #228B22;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Piotrus|&amp;nbsp;Piotr Konieczny aka Prokonsul Piotrus&amp;nbsp;]]|[[User_talk:Piotrus|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#7CFC00;background:#006400;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;talk&amp;nbsp;&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; 02:29, 2 February 2007 (UTC)

== DOB ==

Before this article goes to FA, I would like to see the issue of W2J's date of birth addressed.  See [http://pl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dyskusja:W%C5%82adys%C5%82aw_II_Jagie%C5%82%C5%82o#Data_urodzenia here] for the discussion of new scholarship that places his DOB around 1362. Supposedly the earlier dates are based on bad research that was never corrected. [[User:Appleseed|Appleseed]] ([[User talk:Appleseed|Talk]]) 16:06, 1 February 2007 (UTC)

*Could you possibly give a translation and the source? At the moment, the article, like its sources, doesn't commit itself on the date of birth, so I don't think this question affects the FA candidacy, which is already in progress. But it would be nice to add a note of any new scholarship on the matter. --[[User:Qp10qp|qp10qp]] 16:32, 1 February 2007 (UTC)
::How about a paraphrase?
::''In 1991, Tadeusz Wasilewski published an article in the &quot;Eastern Review&quot; in which he places W2J's DOB around 62 or 63. In the article he puts forth that the commonly quoted dates of 43, 50, and 51 are from 19th-century scholarship by T. Narbutt, who was known for his forgeries. Other researchers based their scholarship on his, and the dates stuck.  The 62 or 63 dates pass the &quot;smell test&quot;, because that means W2J would have been 23 and not 35 when he married the 11-year-old Jadwiga, and 48 and not 60 at the Battle of Grunwald. Wasilewski's conclusions are supported by Jan Tęgowski and others.''
::It's not clear from the comment whether Narbutt created the forgeries or simply relied on them. [[User:Appleseed|Appleseed]] ([[User talk:Appleseed|Talk]]) 19:36, 1 February 2007 (UTC)

:::It's intriguing and would make an interesting addition to the article, if a full reference can be provided, and preferably a translation of some of Wasilewski's or Tęgowski's remarks (an extract could go in the notes). It passes a &quot;smell test&quot; in certain regards, but for me it fails that test in others. For example, Algirdas married Uliana in 1350 and Jogaila was her eldest son (Bojtár, 181); but apparently she had thirteen children, all between 1350 and Algirdas's death in 1377. The ca. 1351 date is given in Britannica, Wandycyz, Stone, and various others; Kucyzyński gives ca. 1350 and Rowell ca. 1356. It could be that the ball-park is indeed off the mark, but the most we should do, in my opinion, even with a full cite for the new research, is to add it as an alternative possibility, since we have so many cites to the present dates and &quot;verifiability, not truth&quot; is Wikipedia policy. [[User:Qp10qp|qp10qp]] 20:56, 1 February 2007 (UTC)
::::That seems reasonable. &quot;More recent research argues that...&lt;citation&gt;...&quot; and so forth, unless this has become ''consensus'' since 1991. [[User:Pmanderson|Septentrionalis]] &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Pmanderson|PMAnderson]]&lt;/small&gt; 00:39, 2 February 2007 (UTC)
:::::Good idea. However, I don't have access to the source they cite. Perhaps another editor can help with that. [[User:Appleseed|Appleseed]] ([[User talk:Appleseed|Talk]]) 02:20, 2 February 2007 (UTC)
Well, I can only search in English-language sources, but I have found something interesting. What do you think of this? As mentioned in the article, when Vytautas fled to Prussia for the second time in 1390, he gave an account of earlier events which was taken down in a document titled ''dis ist witoldes sache wedir jagaln und skirgaln''. In it, he makes the following statement:

&lt;blockquote&gt;After Algirdas's death, Kęstutis, instead of taking the grand ducal throne for himself, recognised Jogaila, still a minor, as grand duke and took care of him until Jogaila grew up and started fully exercising the office. [http://books.google.com/books?vid=ISBN9042008342&amp;id=Nl0_nXQD5i4C&amp;pg=PA157&amp;lpg=PA157&amp;vq=Jogaila&amp;dq=Wigand+Poland&amp;sig=DoKb27Z8XzT8ZZP3qQnwuL3-pqw (''sache'')]&lt;/blockquote&gt;

I had read that several times before, without noticing what was under my nose: Vytautas is saying that Jogaila was still a minor when he came to the throne on Algirdas's death in 1377!

Of course both Vytautas and the German scribe are extremely unreliable in this document, because they were both enemies of Jogaila; but I don't see why Vytautas should make up this particular detail, since Jogaila's approximate age would have been too well known at the time to risk a gross lie about it. If Vytautas is telling the truth, it might explain why Kęstutis and Jogaila fell out. Perhaps at the beginning of Jogaila's reign, when he was marginalised in eastern and southern territories, Kęstutis more or less took control of everything, meaning Jogaila had to find a way of ousting him using external help. [[User:Qp10qp|qp10qp]] 18:26, 9 February 2007 (UTC)

I just made a revert relevant to this question [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Jogaila&amp;diff=prev&amp;oldid=413444377]. I thought it was someone just trying to sneak some vandalism in but it seems it is a source of some kind of controversy. Encyclopedia Britannica does use 1351 apparently (under the article title of &quot;Wladyslaw II Jagiello&quot; but never mind that for now). I have no strong opinion on the matter.&lt;small&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid black;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Volunteer Marek|&lt;font style=&quot;color:blue;background:orange;font-family:sans-serif;&quot;&gt;'''&amp;nbsp;Volunteer Marek&amp;nbsp;'''&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 07:05, 12 February 2011 (UTC)

==State?==
AFAIK, Polish-Lithuanian state emerged after [[Union of Lublin]], not after Jogaila ascended to Polish throne. Until that time the states remained completely separate, except the common ruler, so formulation &quot;His overwhelming victory in the battle of Grunwald in 1410, followed by the First Peace of Toruń, secured the Polish and Lithuanian borders and marked the emergence of the '''Polish-Lithuanian state''' as a major European power&quot; is rather dubious.--[[User:Lokyz|Lokyz]] 19:22, 3 February 2007 (UTC)
:Indeed, [[Polish-Lithuanian union]] should be linked instead.--&lt;sub&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid #228B22;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Piotrus|&amp;nbsp;Piotr Konieczny aka Prokonsul Piotrus&amp;nbsp;]]|[[User_talk:Piotrus|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#7CFC00;background:#006400;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;talk&amp;nbsp;&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; 19:24, 3 February 2007 (UTC)

::LOL! That one crept under the radar; it's been there all along. Good spot, Lokyz. [[User:Qp10qp|qp10qp]] 04:13, 4 February 2007 (UTC)

==Language==
Just wondering if anyone knows, does any of the evidence comment on Jogaila's language skill. He must known both Lithuanian and Rus'ian because of his background; but when he became King of Poland, did he already know German or Polish, did he have to learn one of them, and to what extent did he master one or both of these languages? '''[[User:Calgacus|Calgacus]] (''[[User talk:Calgacus|ΚΑΛΓΑΚΟΣ]]'')''' 15:17, 4 February 2007 (UTC)
: According to Długosz he spoke both Lithuanian and Polish. Probably he also spoke Ruthenian, since it was pretty much a lingua franca back then. German on the other hand is a tad problematic. It seems Vytautas might have spoken German given the years he spent in Marienburg, but I never read anything about Władysław speaking German as well. Same goes for Latin: Władysław probably was taught Latin as its knowledge was a must back then, but whether his Latin letters were written with his own hand or did his chancellery write them is a mystery. ''&lt;font color=&quot;#901&quot;&gt;//&lt;/font&gt;''[[User:Halibutt|Halibu]][[User talk:Halibutt|tt]] 10:38, 5 February 2007 (UTC)
::Dud he speak Latin with foreign ambassadors, like [[Elizabeth of England|Queen Elizabeth]]? [[User:Pmanderson|Septentrionalis]] &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Pmanderson|PMAnderson]]&lt;/small&gt; 22:08, 6 February 2007 (UTC)
:::I don't think we can really know; but Latin was the official language of communication in the Catholic countries, at least on paper. My guess is that there were plenty of job opportunities for translators at his court. 

:::The emperor-elect Sigismund is supposed to have had fun poked at his Latin—so that's one monarch who did (try to) speak it. [[User:Qp10qp|qp10qp]] 18:04, 11 February 2007 (UTC)

:::: He did speak Ruthenian/Old Belarusian/Slavic language of the GDL (any name you prefer). I think that this language might be his native language rather than simply lingua franca of the country (3/4 of his blood was Slavic). [[User:CityElefant|CityElefant]] ([[User talk:CityElefant|talk]]) 13:54, 23 March 2009 (UTC)

::::: His native language was Lithuanian (see below). The Polish and Rus'ian Slavonics were so close then he probably didn't really need to learn Polish beyond adjusting some habits.  [[User:Deacon of Pndapetzim|Deacon of Pndapetzim]] (&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Deacon of Pndapetzim|Talk]]&lt;/small&gt;) 07:31, 10 April 2009 (UTC)

==Points left over from FAC==

The FAC was closed before I could respond to all the requests and queries, and so I'll address them here.

First, a few bits and pieces. I have added the grand-duke info to the infernal infobox. I hate the things, and the template has prevented me making the information look as clean as I would like (the &quot;to 1434&quot; business is a pain). I haven't mentioned the gap when he was deposed: it's impossible to indicate the complexities of his reign in such a box. If someone else wants to have a go, please do.

The succession boxes are also horrid, in my opinion. I have changed &quot;Supreme Prince&quot; to &quot;Supreme Duke&quot; because, though he was called both, the ducal terminology has been used in the other boxes. It was suggested that since Algirdas also called himself &quot;supremus princeps&quot; on occasion, that he go before Jogaila in that succession sequence, but I feel that Jogaila adopted the title as a way of distinguishing himself above Grand Duke Vytautas, and so it was a quasi-constitutional title. It's impossible to satisfactorily fit the round pegs of these overlapping Lithuanian royal titles into the square pegs of succession boxes, in my opinion.

Cquotes were mentioned as a possibility. I prefer the plain blockquote format because it makes the quotes look as they do in books. The big blue quote marks look to me like something from the glossy history magazines I used to read as a boy. I'm not going to fight if someone wants to do it that way, though.

[[User:Qp10qp|qp10qp]] 18:04, 11 February 2007 (UTC)

===Images===

The images, maps etc. were reduced to standard thumbs after a request at FAC, though someone has changed some of them again since. It's a shame: the maps were intended to be read at about 350px, because most readers would then be able to glance at them handily; very few will bother to click, I suspect, or adapt their preferences. I fear to mess with the image sizes, since apparently that might create havoc on some screens; I hope someone who understands such things will cleverly sort the matter out before long.

I will make some changes to the lower map, per various suggestions at FAC (Navahrudak, etc.). &quot;Conflict with Prussia&quot; may indeed not be a traditional form; I confess the longer-winded alternatives all took up too much elbow-room in the Baltic. But I will try to think of something better. The article caption has already been changed.

:Map has now been changed, using new title, Navahrudak, Dobrzyń, including Kaunas etc. per various suggestions. [[User:Qp10qp|qp10qp]] 23:39, 14 February 2007 (UTC)
:: Now it looks better, [[User:M.K|M.K.]] 11:39, 15 February 2007 (UTC)
As for better images overall, I agree that there are some better images out there. It's the copyright business that inhibits me from nabbing them. In my opinion, it would be nice to have a full-length tomb-effigy photo at the top instead of the nineteenth-century picture. [[User:Qp10qp|qp10qp]] 22:52, 11 February 2007 (UTC)

===Succession:===

''&quot;and Lithuania to his younger, Casimir, both still minors at the time.&quot; Not exactly correct Lithuania was ruled by Žygimatas at the moment, and Casimir would show in Lithuania`s throne a bit later, breaking personal union.''

I assumed that Władysław was enacting the provisions of Ostrów, by which his heirs, not Vytautas's, would inherit the Grand Duchy. However, I take your point, and I have added a note to that effect, referenced to Stone. I've accompanied it with references to Sedlar and Rowell (Cambridge Med), however, to back up the statement made in the article. I've not quoted them, but the references are to:

&quot;By Jogaila’s death in 1434 the two realms were securely in the hands of Jogaila’s own wife and sons, despite the death-throes of armed dynastic competition in the territories.&quot; (New Cambridge Medieval History, 711.)

&quot;When Jagiiello died in 1434, his younger son Casimir became grand duke of Lithuania, while Vladislav, the elder, was elected king of Poland.&quot; (Sedlar, 282.)

Of course, like everything else in this reign, the situation was not straightforward. The fact that Casimir was still a minor meant that Žygimantas was de facto grand duke. But it seems to me that the Poles helped Žygimantas against Švitrigaila, and so perhaps his position was technically grand duke to Casimir's nominal supreme duke. On the other hand, I have read suggestions that Žygimantas, like Švitrigaila, was not so much chosen as grand duke by Władysław as ratified; perhaps Žygimantas succeeded Vytautas in north-west Lithuania because it was seen as his right. Another oddity for me is that since the king of Poland was supposed on the basis of Ostrów to be the overlord of the grand duke of Lithuania, then should not Władysław III have succeeded Władysław II as both king of Poland and supreme duke of Lithuania? In that case, yes, Žygimantas, not Casimir, was the legitimate grand duke, standing to Władysław III in the same relation as Vytautas had stood to Władysław III. [[User:Qp10qp|qp10qp]] 00:25, 12 February 2007 (UTC)
:: Žygimantas was Grand Duke after Švitrigaila was defeated, Casimir became Grand Duke after assassination of Žygimantas, only then he was invited by Lithuanian nobles and proclaimed as Grand Duke, canceling personal union with Kingdom of Poland. [[User:M.K|M.K.]] 11:39, 15 February 2007 (UTC) 

===Background===

''At the beginning need background about state policy, what situation was then we access to the throne etc.''

''Early life - Kulikovo events, which provided the key character of young ruler is not discus at all! Probably solving this issue google books would not fit here.''

I've now added a general introduction to the Lithuanian state at the time of Jogaila's accession and mentioned his alliance with Mamai at Kulikovo. [[User:Qp10qp|qp10qp]] 07:26, 13 February 2007 (UTC)
: If you have time, you may include in notes different analysis why he failed to arrive in time and did he after battle beat lagging part of Moscow army after the battle. But I happy with your improvement.  [[User:M.K|M.K.]] 11:39, 15 February 2007 (UTC)

==Replies to the replies==

===Legal traditions===

One or two replies to replies at FAC to catch up with:

''Could you please elaborate remark about Lithuania began adopting Polish legal traditions here? Magdeburg Law is Polish law?''

It was not intended to read as if Magdeburg law is Polish; &quot;Polish legal traditions&quot; here means legal arrangements along the lines of those used in Poland, whether they originated outside Poland or not. &quot;Western&quot; traditions&quot; was objected to by Calgacus, which was why I changed it to &quot;Polish traditions&quot;. I've now removed the phrase altogether, since the paragraph makes the point well enough without it. [[User:Qp10qp|qp10qp]] 14:36, 14 February 2007 (UTC)

===1413===

''could you please explain here what you mean with 1413 event - Samogitia baptism?''

The 1413 event was that which happened at Horodło, when Lithuanian Catholic boyar families were granted the same privileges as their Polish counterparts.

&quot;[The Union of Horodło in 1413] enabled Polish social institutions to take firm root in Lithuania proper. Forty-seven Polish noble families adopted an equal number of Lithuanian boyars and granted them the use of their own coats of arms. This privilege was granted only to Catholic boyars…&quot; (Dvornik, 343)
 
&quot;By the terms of the Union of Horodło in 1413, only Catholic nobles received full political rights.&quot; (Sedlar, 171) 

&quot;The new union gave the Lithuanian nobles a broad range of privileges on condition that they become Catholics. These privileges did not extend to the Orthodox princely and nobiliary class. A legal barrier had been erected between the Poles and Lithuanians on the one hand and the Rus’ nobility on the other…the religious discrimination introduced by the Union of Horodło helped distinguish the Rus’ nobility in the grand Duchy from the Rurikid princes and their boyars outside it…&quot; (Plokhy, 97)

[[User:Qp10qp|qp10qp]] 15:25, 14 February 2007 (UTC)

==[[Polish-Teutonic War (1431-1435)]]==
I just created a stub about this war and it should not only be linked here (since Władysław died in 1334 we can assume he was involved in it) but also we need to correct the statement that &quot;Władysław fought one last war, known as the Gollub War, against the Teutonic Order&quot;. --&lt;sub&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid #228B22;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Piotrus|&amp;nbsp;Piotr Konieczny aka Prokonsul Piotrus&amp;nbsp;]]|[[User_talk:Piotrus|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#7CFC00;background:#006400;&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;talk&amp;nbsp;&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; 21:01, 13 July 2007 (UTC)

:I've made some minor adjustments to the article to take this into account. Add some more, if you need to; I find the last three or four years of his reign difficult to make sense of.[[User:Qp10qp|qp10qp]] 01:27, 18 July 2007 (UTC)

==European force?==
Do no exagarate, I don't see any evidence of any major influence in Western Europe, so let us be more precise: Central and Eastern European force. - [[User:80.126.207.225|80.126.207.225]] 20:49, 30 November 2007 (UTC)

:I think the Polish-Lithuanian bloc certainly became a European force. Wladyslaw was offered the crown of Bohemia, which was part of the Holy Roman Empire. He sponsored a regent there, from his own family. Vytautas was also offered the crown and took part in diplomacy there. Wladyslaw was writing to the crowned heads of Europe, and they sent him troops (no longer were his Lithuanian territories regarded as unassailably heathen or schismatic, but a part of the Catholic world). The envoys and scholars sent by Vytautas and Wladyslaw to the [[Council of Constance]] were influential; they were tasked with conversions on behalf of the official church and more bishoprics were developed. Polish-Lithuanian issues were a high-priority consideration for the council. Wladyslaw was a significant diplomatic factor in the quarrels within the Holy Roman Empire between [[Wenceslas IV of Bohemia]] and [[Sigismund, Holy Roman Emperor]]. Despite the papal schism, Catholic Christendom was very much a single entity, and one only has to look at a map to see that Poland-Lithuania was an enormous power bloc on the eastern rim of the Holy Roman Empire, and very much a part of an expanding Catholic Christendom.[[User:Qp10qp|qp10qp]] 14:26, 1 December 2007 (UTC)

== Lithuanian terms as primary forms - it's just unhistoric! ==

I would repeat my thesis from my comment on another article. I would oppose the use of the term &quot;Didysis Kunigaikštis&quot; in this text. '''I would also oppose usage of other Lithuanised terms related to social groups or state administration in the GDL- and Res Publica -related articles.''' It's just unhistoric since in the GDL &quot;the situation was disastrous for Lithuanian: it was not allowed to flourish, it was being pushed out of common usage and it was difficult to publish written Lithuanian texts&quot; (see Zinkevičius, Zigmas. History of the Lithuanian Language. Vilnius: Mokslo ir enciklopedijų leidybos institutas, 1998, p. 244). Moreover, &quot;the Lithuanian language had not been considered a language of politics for centuries&quot; and &quot;grand dukes had never published Lithuanian books&quot; (see Snyder Timothy, The Reconstruction of Nations: Poland, Ukraine, Lithuania, Belarus. 1569-1999, p. 32). Wikipedia shall be reliable source of information but in this form it provides a reader with a number of false impressions! [[User:CityElefant|CityElefant]] ([[User talk:CityElefant|talk]]) 17:58, 22 March 2009 (UTC)

: I'm afraid most of this is just anachronistic. Lithuanian was only a marginalised language much later. [[User:Deacon of Pndapetzim|Deacon of Pndapetzim]] (&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Deacon of Pndapetzim|Talk]]&lt;/small&gt;) 19:54, 22 March 2009 (UTC)

::The article follows terms used in history books. Although Latin terms were used in the treaties, historians, such as S. C. Rowell, equate them with terms used in Lithuanian, Russian, and Polish, etc. In many ways the Latin terms do not fully convey the complexity of Lithuanian titles. [[User:Qp10qp|qp10qp]] ([[User talk:Qp10qp|talk]]) 20:55, 22 March 2009 (UTC)

::: To [[User:Deacon of Pndapetzim|Deacon of Pndapetzim]]: It is not anachronistic! We cannot have any prove about the role of the Lithuanian language at the court of the Lithuanian Grand Dukes. Simply by the fact that it had not left written traces. If you are not satisfied with my argument I would quote another source which refers to Jagiełło/Jahajła/Jogaila's cousin Witold/Vitaut/Vytautas: &quot;Soll er [Witaut] sich doch mit Gedanken getragen haben, an Stelle des Russischen, d.i. Weißrussischen oder Weißruthenischen, das Litauische zur Hof- und Kanzleisprache zu machen&quot; (Source: Dr. W. Gaigalat. Litauen das besetzte Gebiet / sein Volk und dessen geistige Strömungen. Frankfurter Vereinsdruckerei, Verlag, Frankfurt a/M, 1917,  pp. 37-38) Brief translation: &quot;He ought to have thought, to abolish Belarusian as the language of court and chancery and introduce Lithuanian instead&quot;. It means that Lithuanian had not been the language of the court and chancery at the period contemporary to Jagiełło/Jahajła/Jogaila's lifetime. P.S. exact translation of the part regarding the language is &quot;Russian, i.e. Belarusian or Whiteruthenian... as the language of the court and chancery&quot; but it does not alter the meaning of the phrase. [[User:CityElefant|CityElefant]] ([[User talk:CityElefant|talk]]) 11:45, 23 March 2009 (UTC)

:::: The quote is from 1917, is outdated and is preposterous in the sense that there was no such thing as Belarusian in the 14th century (though the German is more open that your firm translation). I'll just give you a quote from the world's leading authority on 14th century Lithuania, S. C. Rowell:&lt;blockquote&gt;The influence of Rus' on Lithuania was important and remains undeniable. However the exaggerated claims made by the Polish historian Lowmianski for the Slavonic contribution to the formation of the Grand Duchy before 1282 should be tempered. The Rus'ian contribution to Lithuanian society began some six decades after the Grand Duchy had started to consolidate itself. That a west Rus'ian dialect eventually came to be used in grand ducal documents (largely after 1385) reveals the origin of most Lettovian scribes who had to deal with Rus'ian leaders of Church and state. It certainly does not mean that the grand dukes were Rus'ian. It is clear that Vytautas and Jogaila spoke with each other in Lithuanian.[9] Terms such as ''bajorai'' were borrowed from Rus' for native institutions. What the Rus'ians brought to Lithuania were the important commodities of men and money for the Prussian wars and control of several of the major trading posts of Rus'.&lt;/blockquote&gt; The proof that Lithuanian was used between Jogaila and Vytautas is from the ''Codex Epistolaris Vitoldi magni ducis Lithuaniae'', no. 1345. It's unfortunate to say that much communist and pre-communist eastern European history, as written in eastern Europe, is just a slave to historical nationalism and claims of Rus'ian or Slavic language dominance in Lithuanian-proper are based on historical misunderstandings piggy-backed by nationalist wishful thinking, allied to a contempt of Lithuanian culture comparable to English attitudes to the Welsh which, like those, were fostered by recent centuries of dominance. In reality, Lithuania (not the network of Rus cities under its rule) in the 14th cent. is dominated by an aristocracy using Lithuanian names, speaking Lithuanian but drawing on important traditions and expertise from the more advanced civilizations of Germany and Rus, something which is normal. To compare, medieval Germany uses the Roman language (clergy) and religion, but was outside the Roman Empire and was not Romance speaking. I read that your apparent purpose of editing wikipedia is to forward &quot;the consolidated version of the Grand Duchy of Lithuania history free from Lithuanian nationalism&quot;. I hope you'll treat all nationalisms, Polish, Lithuanian, Russian/Belarusian with equal contempt, and I really hope that I won't return here to find you're dismissing Rowell based on some pretext that just happens to further some ideology. We need actual unbiased editors! Happy editing! :) [[User:Deacon of Pndapetzim|Deacon of Pndapetzim]] (&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Deacon of Pndapetzim|Talk]]&lt;/small&gt;) 05:17, 9 April 2009 (UTC)
:: First, Gaigalat was not a German but an ethnic Lithuanian (from Lithuania Minor). It is sad to understand that you ignore the sources which are older than some 20 years. Second, bajorai is a clear Slavism. Third, you miss the point that Lithuanian language remained unwritten up to the 16th century. Next, you look to Lithuanians as an already formed nation at that time. It is also impossible to ignore the existence of a separate entity called Samogitia. Simultaneously, you consider Eastern Slavs (modern Belarusians, Ukrainians and Russians) as a sort of a common nation which is typical for Russian traditionalist/imperialist view on the matter. And finally, you forget that a written source is the best source. There is no document of that time where you can find such words as bajorai, etc. [[User:CityElefant|CityElefant]] ([[User talk:CityElefant|talk]]) 06:06, 9 April 2009 (UTC)
::: Thanks, you've said enough. It is plain that you're here to push some kind of Belarusian nationalist agenda. Can you please remove then &quot;the consolidated version of the Grand Duchy of Lithuania history free from Lithuanian nationalism&quot; quote from your user page. It creates an atmosphere of [[WP:BATTLE]]. I'd be really grateful if you did that. There is enough conflict in this area already! :) [[User:Deacon of Pndapetzim|Deacon of Pndapetzim]] (&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Deacon of Pndapetzim|Talk]]&lt;/small&gt;) 06:14, 9 April 2009 (UTC)
:::: I do not intend to remove this passage as it is my right to express my opinion. If I say something I refer to the sources. This is my position and I am a scholar myself. I'm here not to attack Lithuanian and not to defend Belarusians, Poles or Ukrainians. Btw, I request your apologies for labeling me a Belarusian nationalist. You have no reasons to say so. Or maybe you believe that there are some sources which are reliable and less reliable? Using your concept we may call [[Aleksander Brückner]] a Belarusian nationalist as well. [[User:CityElefant|CityElefant]] ([[User talk:CityElefant|talk]]) 06:34, 9 April 2009 (UTC) I am a casual user of Wikipedia, however this onslaught of modern Lithuanian terminology in the history on Wikipedia is a bit disturbing, to say at least. There has been well established English language terminology for all these historic personages (actors) and places. While it would be impossible and preposterous to disclaim the obvious very significant role of the pagan Lithuania and her rulers and their Christian descendants in the history of the Central Europe, it is quite clear from the primary sources what languages were spoken and used in writing by the Grand Dukes and their chanceries. It is also quite clear where their allegiances had been. Thanks to post-modern Wikipedia we are learning new terms that most likely never been used in the historic times outside the huts of Samogitian farmers and warriors. One of the most disturbing examples here in this entry is the way it was written that Jagellon dynasty was a branch of 'Gedymid dynasty' that ruled both states until 1572 - for 'uninformed' user that may mean that Gedymid dynasty was in fact ruling half of Europe from 14-16th centuries!! I really like to see various languages and terms used when explaining an entry, but this and many other Lithuanian history entries are in need of a gentle 'de-Lithuanizing' in favor of English terminology, por favor!

== Earliest mention ==

I wonder what's the earliest mention of the name &quot;Jogaila&quot; in sources in any language. I mean specifically the form &quot;Jogaila&quot;, not &quot;Jagiello&quot;, &quot;Jahaila&quot; or any other. Anyone? 

I'm asking because I recently discovered that the earliest mention of &quot;Vytautas&quot; came much later than his Slavic name of Vitold (he is cited as such in German chronicles). ''&lt;font color=&quot;#901&quot;&gt;//&lt;/font&gt;''[[User:Halibutt|Halibu]][[User talk:Halibutt|tt]] 16:54, 15 October 2009 (UTC)
: That is a question which I have asked myself, and others, in regard to names like &quot;Mikolaj Kopernik&quot;, &quot;Gdansk&quot; or &quot;Szczeczin&quot;. --&amp;nbsp;[[User:Matthead|Matthead]]&amp;nbsp;[[User_talk:Matthead|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#ffff00;background:#0000cc;&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&amp;nbsp;Discuß&amp;nbsp;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]]&amp;nbsp; 17:52, 15 October 2009 (UTC)
:: As to Szczecin, I guess this form is pretty modern, I mean 18th centurish. As far as I remember mediaeval municipal stamps mentioned a plethora of forms. It's not that uncommon, as it was always somehow difficult to put down Slavic names in Latin script. But the same thing happened also in the Netherlands, the names used on coinage and stamps varied from one to another. 
:: As to Kopernik, I have no idea. He himself used a plethora of variants, from ''Niclas Koppernigk'' to ''Nic Copernic''[http://pl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plik:Autograph-MikolajKopernik.png] to ''Nicolaus Copernic''[http://www.bj.uj.edu.pl/bjmanus/revol/titlpg_e.html] to ''Nicolaus Coppernic''[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Nicolaus_Coppernicus_iuro.png]. 
::But this is of course off-topic here. Anyone on-topic? ''&lt;font color=&quot;#901&quot;&gt;//&lt;/font&gt;''[[User:Halibutt|Halibu]][[User talk:Halibutt|tt]] 11:41, 16 October 2009 (UTC)
:::In any medieval document there is no &quot;Jogaila&quot;. There is only a form of &quot;Wladyslaw Jagiełło&quot;- eg. Jan Długosz, The Annals of Jan Dlugosz. Name &quot;Jogaila&quot; is only in this article. Even the books in the bibliography to this article They say &quot;Wladyslaw II Jagiełło&quot;. Ladislaus had a son named after his father:  Wladyslaw III , not Jogiala II.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/213.199.253.225|213.199.253.225]] ([[User talk:213.199.253.225|talk]]) 20:17, 25 August 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:::: Any document post-Polo-Lith union is going to have Jagiełło. There's no dispute that his Lithuanian given name was Jogaila, and it is stated as such in scholarly sources. There's no such title as Jogaila II for obvious reasons having nothing to do with Jogaila being his given name at birth. The &quot;earliest written document&quot; is a bit of a red herring as it applies only to when it was written/signed (if a treaty). [[User:Vecrumba|P&lt;small&gt;ЄTЄRS&lt;/small&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;s&gt;J&lt;/s&gt;&amp;nbsp;V]]&lt;small&gt; ►[[User_talk:Vecrumba|TALK]]&lt;/small&gt; 19:39, 21 September 2011 (UTC)

==Didysis Kunigaikštis==
Jagailo never held the title of &quot;Didysis Kunigaikštis&quot;, and it is not supported by any sources. This is a blatant lie, as is a half of the article. [[Special:Contributions/195.50.1.122|195.50.1.122]] ([[User talk:195.50.1.122|talk]]) 06:19, 11 June 2010 (UTC)
:a.) Jogaila. b.) references please. [[User:Lokyz|Lokyz]] ([[User talk:Lokyz|talk]]) 12:54, 13 June 2010 (UTC)
:: Didysis Kunigaikštis seems to be an original lithuanian translation for the &quot;grand duke&quot; title (Ruthenian/Old Belarusian: [http://litopys.org.ua/psrl3235/lytov09.htm kniaź weliki] or weliki kniaź ([[Bychowiec Chronicle]]), Polish: wielki książę. Didysis Kunigaikštis doesn't appear in any Grand Duchy references. The baltic variant seems to be an [[original research]]. --[[User:Jauhienij|Jauhienij]] ([[User talk:Jauhienij|talk]]) 01:29, 21 August 2010 (UTC)
:::Actually &quot;Old Belarusian&quot; is so [[WP:OR]], that any webpage will not convince anyone until a solid [[WP:RS]] based [[WP:UE|English]] publication will be provided, for an instace denouncing such usage. Simple question - did Jogaila konow his name and did he spoke Lithuanian, Polish or Belarusian (or rather Byelorusian in the older tradition)? It's referenced in the article. [[User:Lokyz|Lokyz]] ([[User talk:Lokyz|talk]]) 01:41, 21 August 2010 (UTC)
::::It's grand duke. That's no different from Duke Gothard Kettler  being &quot;Hercogs&quot; (duke) in Latvian. Exactly what else would Lithuanians have called him, in Lithuanian? Alas, a bit late to the conversation! [[User:Vecrumba|P&lt;small&gt;ЄTЄRS&lt;/small&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;s&gt;J&lt;/s&gt;&amp;nbsp;V]]&lt;small&gt; ►[[User_talk:Vecrumba|TALK]]&lt;/small&gt; 19:45, 21 September 2011 (UTC)

== Adoption by Elizabeth of Bosnia ==

Can someone please tell me where exactly does ''The New Cambridge Medieval History'' say that Jogaila was adopted by his future mother-in-law, [[Elizabeth of Bosnia]]? Is there any other source that confirms it? Thanks. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 16:11, 20 June 2012 (UTC)

==Requested move==
&lt;div class=&quot;boilerplate&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #efe; margin: 2em 0 0 0; padding: 0 10px 0 10px; border: 1px dotted #aaa;&quot;&gt;&lt;!-- Template:RM top --&gt;
:''The following discussion is an archived discussion of a [[WP:RM|requested move]]. &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/span&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on the talk page. No further edits should be made to this section.''
'''Moved per consensus'''. There is a clear consensus in favor of the proposed move, and proponents of the move have provided substantial evidence that this is the common name of the subject. [[User:BD2412|&lt;font style=&quot;background:gold&quot;&gt;'''''bd2412'''''&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:BD2412|'''T''']] 18:27, 28 January 2014 (UTC)

[[:Jogaila]] → '''{{no redirect|Władysław II Jagiełło}}''' – Per: [[Wikipedia:Naming conventions (royalty and nobility)]]. Jogaila was his pagan name before he became a [[King of Poland]].--[[User:Sobiepan|Sobiepan]] ([[User talk:Sobiepan|talk]]) 11:38, 29 December 2013 (UTC)
*'''Comment''' can you please explain the relevant section of WP:NCR, thanks. [[User:In ictu oculi|In ictu oculi]] ([[User talk:In ictu oculi|talk]]) 12:42, 29 December 2013 (UTC)
** 1. ''It is generally advisable to use the most common form of the name used in reliable sources in English (&quot;common name&quot; in the case of royalty and nobility may also include a person's title),'' - see: http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/646348/Wladyslaw-II-Jagiello or in the &quot;1911 Encyclopedia Britannica&quot;. --[[User:Sobiepan|Sobiepan]] ([[User talk:Sobiepan|talk]]) 13:00, 29 December 2013 (UTC)
**BTW: the common English version of his pagan name is '''Jagiello''' or sometimes '''Jagello''' and not ''Jogaila''.--[[User:Sobiepan|Sobiepan]] ([[User talk:Sobiepan|talk]]) 13:10, 29 December 2013 (UTC)
**Also an important point is that royal names are more important than birth names. For an example: the article about ''Mathilde Marie Christiane Ghislaine d'Udekem d'Acoz'' was created as [[Princess Mathilde, Duchess of Brabant]] and later moved to [[Queen Mathilde of Belgium]]. More examples: King [[John III Sobieski]] born as ''Jan Sobieski'', King [[Stanisław August Poniatowski]] born as ''Stanisław Antoni Poniatowski'', King [[Michał Korybut Wiśniowiecki]] born as ''Michał Wiśniowiecki'', King [[Augustus II the Strong]] born as ''Frederick Augustus I'', etc.--[[User:Sobiepan|Sobiepan]] ([[User talk:Sobiepan|talk]]) 13:58, 29 December 2013 (UTC)
*'''Support'''. About time to revisit this again. Not a dead horse, through it was discussed a number of times in the past; here's hoping that certain nationalist editors (see archives, particularly c. 2006) have matured and are willing to consider the rules and statistics. The simple rule to follow is &quot;use the most common English name&quot;, and the simple statistic to check common usage is Google Books. Relevant Google Books searches are pretty clear that the Władysław II Jagiełło is preferred here: 1) &quot;king Jogaila&quot;: 261 vs &quot;king Wladyslaw Jagiello&quot; at 860, &quot;king Władysław Jagiełło&quot; at 4340, &quot;king Wladyslaw II Jagiello&quot; at 263, and &quot;king Władysław II Jagiełło&quot; at 49 2) &quot;Jogaila king &quot;: 117 vs &quot;Wladyslaw Jagiello king &quot; at 150, &quot;Władysław II Jagiełło king&quot; at 60, &quot;Wladyslaw II Jagiello king&quot; at 131, and &quot;Władysław II Jagiełło king&quot; at 30 3) &quot;Jogaila&quot; at 16000 vs &quot;Wladyslaw Jagiello&quot; at 38800, &quot;Władysław Jagiełło&quot; at 31700, &quot;Wladyslaw II Jagiello&quot; at 24600 and &quot;Władysław II Jagiełło&quot; at 2700. While the search may be a bit compromised due to Google's still poor understanding of diacritics, and some non-English results might have crept into the search 3), I think the pattern is pretty clear: English language sources predominately use the Polish, post-baptism name, rather then the Lithuanian pagan one. That said, on the final note I support the old compromise of in-text using Jogaila for pre-baptism times, and WJ for post-baptism. --&lt;sub style=&quot;border:1px solid #228B22;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Piotrus|Piotr Konieczny aka Prokonsul Piotrus]]&amp;#124;[[User talk:Piotrus|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#7CFC00;background:#006400;&quot;&gt; reply here&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sub&gt; 15:31, 1 January 2014 (UTC)
*'''Support''' the renaming per nominator's rationale. Also support the proposal to use both name versions in the article according to the text emphasis on the pre/post baptism times. - [[User:Darwinek|Darwinek]] ([[User talk:Darwinek|talk]]) 15:45, 3 January 2014 (UTC)
*&lt;s&gt;'''Oppose'''. Keep this can of worms closed, and don't try to dance on the graves of editors that have been bullied away by &quot;certain nationalist editors&quot; that are still, or again, pushing Polish POV.&lt;/s&gt; --&amp;nbsp;[[User:Matthead|Matthead]]&amp;nbsp;[[User_talk:Matthead|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#ffff00;background:#0000cc;&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&amp;nbsp;Discuß&amp;nbsp;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]]&amp;nbsp; 12:52, 5 January 2014 (UTC)
**'''Comment'''. Isn't that editor still topic banned under [[WP:DIGWUREN]] from all Poland-related topics? An uninvolved admin may want to consider whether this vote is valid or not. --&lt;sub style=&quot;border:1px solid #228B22;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Piotrus|Piotr Konieczny aka Prokonsul Piotrus]]&amp;#124;[[User talk:Piotrus|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#7CFC00;background:#006400;&quot;&gt; reply here&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sub&gt; 13:45, 5 January 2014 (UTC)
***Opinion struck as violating an [[WP:AE|arbitration enforcement]] topic ban applying to this user, who I have [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Wikipedia:Arbitration/Requests/Enforcement&amp;oldid=589303659#Matthead blocked in enforcement of the ban]. &lt;small&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid black;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Sandstein|&lt;font style=&quot;color:white;background:blue;font-family:sans-serif;&quot;&gt;'''&amp;nbsp;Sandstein&amp;nbsp;'''&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 16:09, 5 January 2014 (UTC)
*'''Support'''. The article should be renamed from ''Jogaila'' to ''Władysław II Jagiełło'' not because of his nationality or background, but only because of the name that he is known best for. - [[User:Oliszydlowski|Oliszydlowski]] [[User talk:Oliszydlowski|(talk)]] 23:05, 5 January 2014 (UTC)
*'''Oppose'''. Why do you think one name is more widely used than another. There are living ~40 millions Poles in Poland and ~3 million Lithuanians in Lithuania. Thus we can expect about 10 times more Polish historians than Lithuanian. Nevertheless it is not the excuse to use Polish name ignoring his Lithuanian origin.[[User:Orionus|Orionus]] ([[User talk:Orionus|talk]]) 19:08, 5 January 2014 (UTC) 
::'''Comment''': This users only contribution on wikipedia is removing Polish names of cities and villages in Lithuania... [[Special:Contributions/Orionus]] --[[User:Sobiepan|Sobiepan]] ([[User talk:Sobiepan|talk]]) 20:25, 5 January 2014 (UTC)
:::I think all users will find this your argument very constructive and convincing in order to achieve final consensus. [[User:Orionus|Orionus]] ([[User talk:Orionus|talk]]) 22:59, 5 January 2014 (UTC)
:::{{Not sure}} about the vote above. With 966 edits since 2006 I urge User:Orionus to please reveal your primary Wikipedia account's name. We need to determine that account's DIGWUREN status if you have one. [[User:Poeticbent|&lt;font face=&quot;Papyrus&quot; color=&quot;darkblue&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Poeticbent&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User_talk:Poeticbent|&lt;font style=&quot;font-size:7.0pt;color:#FFFFFF;font-weight:bold;background:#FF88AF;border:1px solid #DF2929;padding:0.0em 0.2em;&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]] 18:03, 13 January 2014 (UTC)
*'''Support''' per nominator's rationale and comments above, as well as per frequency of name variants used in English reliable sources.&lt;small&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;border:1px solid black;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Volunteer Marek|&lt;font style=&quot;color:blue;background:orange;font-family:sans-serif;&quot;&gt;'''&amp;nbsp;Volunteer Marek&amp;nbsp;'''&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 19:54, 5 January 2014 (UTC)
*'''Support''' per nom and Piotrus. I also support the use of &quot;Jogaila&quot; in the text for those parts of the article dealing with his life before the unification and his conversion. [[User:Neljack|Neljack]] ([[User talk:Neljack|talk]]) 23:24, 7 January 2014 (UTC)
*'''Strongest OPPOSE''' despite claims no evidence were presented that modern Polish invention &quot;Władysław II Jagiełło&quot; is prevailing English name. As Lithuanian, Jogaila was known as by this name from the beginning of his life till the end. Current various name variations are present in the text, so IMO it is more than enough. [[User:M.K|M.K.]] ([[User talk:M.K|talk]]) 12:25, 13 January 2014 (UTC)
:::Please. [http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/646348/Wladyslaw-II-Jagiello], [http://www.merriam-webster.com/concise/wladyslaw%20ii%20jagiello] [http://books.google.com/books?id=N883AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA232&amp;dq=Jagiello+Cambridge&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=M93TUt6_BJHtqAGAq4HQBw&amp;ved=0CDsQ6AEwAw#v=onepage&amp;q=Jagiello%20Cambridge&amp;f=false] [http://books.google.com/books?id=bkhgAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT46&amp;dq=history+of+poland+jagiello&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=Yt3TUoaYIcTgqQHy2ICIDA&amp;ved=0CDoQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q=history%20of%20poland%20jagiello&amp;f=false] [http://books.google.com/books?id=tRpdAQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA49&amp;dq=history+of+poland+jagiello&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=Yt3TUoaYIcTgqQHy2ICIDA&amp;ved=0CC8Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=history%20of%20poland%20jagiello&amp;f=false]. Also writing 'strongest' in front of your !vote and slapping on the caps lock for the 'oppose' does not actually make your view more significant than that of others. [[User:Volunteer Marek|Volunteer Marek]] ([[User talk:Volunteer Marek|talk]]) 12:38, 13 January 2014 (UTC)
::::&lt;s&gt;Only more desperate... &lt;/s&gt; That was uncalled for, my apologies. --&lt;sub style=&quot;border:1px solid #228B22;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Piotrus|Piotr Konieczny aka Prokonsul Piotrus]]&amp;#124;[[User talk:Piotrus|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#7CFC00;background:#006400;&quot;&gt; reply here&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sub&gt; 14:51, 13 January 2014 (UTC)

::::I hope that uninvolved closing administrator would '''ACTUALLY''' look into those links above which, according to Polish activists, supposed to prove that invented name ''“Władysław II Jagiełło''” is more popular than proper name '''Jogaila'''. This, term “''Władysław II Jagiełło”'' , even not used in several provided links at all, despite a claims. Guys, are so desperate that by providing misleading links you think you can win a move? So, let’s see in major English and actual sources:

*'''Encyclopedia britannica''', ISBN 0852297874 , 2002, p.704, of course uses '''Jogaila''' 
*'''The New Cambridge Medieval History''': Vo. 6, C.1300-c.1415  p. 744  Here too is used '''Jogaila'''
*'''Britannica Concise Encyclopedia'''.  By Encyclopaedia Britannica p. 974 uses '''Jogaila''', aslo mentions and Polish modern name. 
*'''Encyclopedia of World Geography''', Volume 1.  P. 546 Uses '''Jogaila'''.
*'''Encyclopedia of Warrior Peoples and Fighting Groups'''. P. 328 uses '''Jogaila'''
*'''The Grove Encyclopedia of Northern Renaissance Art''', Vol. 2. p. 330 uses '''Jogaila'''.
*'''Worldmark Encyclopedia of Cultures and Daily Life: Europe''' p. 280 uses '''Jogaila'''.
*'''Encyclopedia of Contemporary Russian Culture'''. 2013 p. 362 uses as primary name '''Jogaila''' but mentions and Polish one. 
*'''Europe 1450 to 1789: encyclopedia of the early modern world''', Volume 3 p. 330 primary name '''Jogaila'''
*'''Martial Arts of the World: En Encyclopedia''', p.375 uses '''Jogaila'''.
*'''Lithuania Ascending: A Pagan Empire Within East-Central Europe''', 1295-1345 p. 68 uses '''Jogaila'''
*'''Worldmark Encyclopedia of the Nations'''. P.365 uses '''Jogaila'''. 
*'''Europe: A History''', By Norman Davies p.430 '''Jogaila''' as well 
*'''Historical Dictionary of Lithuania''' p. 143 primary name '''Jogaila'''
*'''A History of the Baltic States''', Palgrave Macmillan, 2010, p.24 primary name '''Jogaila''' 
*'''Estonia, Latvia, Lithuania, and Poland''', '''Britannica Educational Publishing''' p.77 '''Jogaila''',
*'''A History of Eastern Europe: Crisis and Change''',  By Robert Bideleux. Uses '''Jogaila'''
*'''The Teutonic Knights: a military history''', p. 178 uses '''Jogaila''' 
*'''Making a Great Ruler: Grand Duke Vytautas of Lithuania'''  p. 22 '''Jogaila'''
*'''History of Ukraine''', 2010 p. 138 Uses '''Jogaila'''
*'''Hundreds and hundreds other English sources''' [[User:M.K|M.K.]] ([[User talk:M.K|talk]]) 11:57, 14 January 2014 (UTC)
:*Nice, but irrelevant. Nobody is denying some sources use this term - but they are in ''minority'', as was shown above. --&lt;sub style=&quot;border:1px solid #228B22;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Piotrus|Piotr Konieczny aka Prokonsul Piotrus]]&amp;#124;[[User talk:Piotrus|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#7CFC00;background:#006400;&quot;&gt; reply here&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sub&gt; 15:18, 14 January 2014 (UTC)

::M.K., Your comment above borders on willful lying. Of course the sources I provided use the name. It is not a &quot;invented name&quot; - you just plain made that up. For example here is '''Encyclopedia Britannica''' article: http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/646348/Wladyslaw-II-Jagiello. What's the title? Oh. That's right. It's &quot;Władysław II Jagiełło&quot;.
::Or take your example of  '''History of Ukraine''' by Magosci which you list above. Does it use &quot;Jogaila&quot; on p. 138. Sure, it uses Jogaila in some instances. But look in the index under &quot;Jogaila&quot;. What does it say. Oh. it says: &quot;Jogaila. ''See'' Władysław II Jagiełło&quot;. In other words the author just notes that &quot;Jogaila&quot; is sometimes used but gives the ruler's name as is proposed above (and let's be clear, nobody is saying that the name &quot;Jogaila&quot; should be removed from the article). Urban also seems to primarily use &quot;Wladyslaw Jagiello&quot; [http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/cat/summary/v090/90.3knoll.html], while probably noting the usage of &quot;Jogaila&quot;.
::Pretty much is true of all the other sources you list. Which you are probably well aware of.[[User:Volunteer Marek|Volunteer Marek]] ([[User talk:Volunteer Marek|talk]]) 16:16, 14 January 2014 (UTC)
::Likewise The New Cambridge Medieval History does more or less the same thing as Magosci. It uses both &quot;Jogaila&quot; and &quot;Wladyslaw Jagiello&quot; at some points in the text (depending on the time period) but in the index the primary name is &quot;Władysław II Jagiełło&quot;. Please stop misrepresenting sources. [[User:Volunteer Marek|Volunteer Marek]] ([[User talk:Volunteer Marek|talk]]) 16:22, 14 January 2014 (UTC)
::Another falsehood: ''&quot;Europe 1450 to 1789: encyclopedia of the early modern world, Volume 3 p. 330 primary name Jogaila&quot;''. Nope. Not at all. What it actually says is ''&quot;'''Władysław II Jagiełło (Poland)''' (Lithuanian: Jogaila)&quot;'' [http://books.google.com/books?ei=52TVUs-JNcrnoATEm4CwBw&amp;id=CIYYAAAAIAAJ&amp;dq=Europe+1450+to+1789%3A+encyclopedia+of+the+early+modern+world&amp;focus=searchwithinvolume&amp;q=Jagiello]. That's suppose to be &quot;primary name Jogaila&quot;? How about you strike your claim since anyone who cares to double check it can easily verify that you're ... not telling the whole truth.[[User:Volunteer Marek|Volunteer Marek]] ([[User talk:Volunteer Marek|talk]]) 16:29, 14 January 2014 (UTC)
::Is everyone of the above claims an easily debunked piece of bunk? Here is '''Encyclopedia of Contemporary Russian Culture. 2013 p. 362 uses as primary name Jogaila but mentions and Polish one.'''. Nope, pg. 362 says: ''&quot;Lithuanian Prince Jogaila married a Polish princes and became Polish King Władysław II Jagiełło&quot;''. How is that &quot;primary name Jogaila&quot;? [[User:Volunteer Marek|Volunteer Marek]] ([[User talk:Volunteer Marek|talk]]) 16:36, 14 January 2014 (UTC)
::::Certain Polish activist have no skills with actual books. My questions do those activists know at least the difference between books volumes? Well reading amusing comments above it obviously that they don't, yet. Yet offending others by insisting of falsification is not only breach of good faith and constructive discussions but a typical tactics of Polish activists to win their case.  And I repeat myself a) &quot;Władysław II Jagiełło&quot; is invented name. b) *'''Europe 1450 to 1789: encyclopedia of the early modern world''', '''Volume 3''' p. 330 uses primary name '''Jogaila''' (that guy above even failed to notice a difference between my volume and his, which wad 6, not 3; typical). So my listed books a perfectly fine.[[User:M.K|M.K.]] ([[User talk:M.K|talk]]) 08:16, 15 January 2014 (UTC)  
:::::By referring to and judging other editors based solely on their ethnicity, you are not only being uncivil, but also expressing a pretty ugly form of prejudice. By claiming that '&quot;Władysław II Jagiełło' is invented name&quot; (sic) you are stating your own, completely baseless and frankly absurd opinion. By playing games with volume numbers you are engaging in simple obfuscation - the fact is that '''Europe 1450 to 1789: encyclopedia of the early modern world''' uses &quot;Władysław II Jagiełło&quot; as the TITLE of its section on this person, although sure, it uses &quot;Jogaila&quot; somewhere else (nota bene, NOT as a primary name, even there it states - &quot;Lithuanian Duke Jogaila who after his baptism became Władysław Jagiełło&quot;). In other words you just keep on willfully making false statements. You're really not helping yourself, just proving that your !vote should be heavily discounted, if considered at all.[[User:Volunteer Marek|Volunteer Marek]] ([[User talk:Volunteer Marek|talk]]) 09:31, 15 January 2014 (UTC)
::::::Oh, so you know arguing for the &quot;Władysław Jagiełło&quot; as primary name. What happened with &quot;Władysław '''II''' Jagiełło&quot;? It so easy to twist these names by adding or drooping '''&quot;II&quot;''' leaving or excluding &quot;Jagiello&quot;, of course if it servers certain Point of View. Really, its is embarrassing to read and &quot;arguments&quot; complaining that &quot;Władysław II Jagiełło&quot; is not an invented name. I can only suggest to read more books about Polish monarchs' naming nomenclature and how such the naming was made up by historians and why. And of course Jogaila and his contemporary never knew such thing as &quot;Władysław II Jagiełło&quot; and nobody did many centuries later after his death. [[User:M.K|M.K.]] ([[User talk:M.K|talk]]) 12:42, 15 January 2014 (UTC) 
:::::::I'm having trouble understanding what it is you're going on about. I'm sorry but your statement just doesn't make sense.[[User:Volunteer Marek|Volunteer Marek]] ([[User talk:Volunteer Marek|talk]]) 12:58, 15 January 2014 (UTC)
:::::::And please, at least bother reading [[WP:NCROY]].[[User:Volunteer Marek|Volunteer Marek]] ([[User talk:Volunteer Marek|talk]]) 13:08, 15 January 2014 (UTC)

* '''Support''' &quot;[[Władysław II Jagiełło]]&quot;, consistent with normal naming of monarchs of foreign origin.  [[User:Nihil novi|Nihil novi]] ([[User talk:Nihil novi|talk]]) 03:37, 21 January 2014 (UTC)
* '''Oppose''' per [[WP:COMMONNAME]] - google books search (in English language) returned 3.210 books for 'Jogaila grand duke' and 754 books for 'Władysław II Jagiełło'. [[User:GiW|GiW]] ([[User talk:GiW|talk]]) 22:23, 24 January 2014 (UTC)
**I cannot replicate your search result, but in any case, if you search for &quot;grand duke&quot;, it's clear you'll get biased results. Even we have agreed to use Jogaila for his time as a Grand Duke. On a sidenote, it's somewhat intriguing that all current three oppose votes come from Lithuanians. --&lt;sub style=&quot;border:1px solid #228B22;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Piotrus|Piotr Konieczny aka Prokonsul Piotrus]]&amp;#124;[[User talk:Piotrus|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#7CFC00;background:#006400;&quot;&gt; reply here&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sub&gt; 23:14, 24 January 2014 (UTC)

=== Alternate proposal ===
'''Recommendation''' &amp;mdash; @Piotrus, David Stone's history of Poland-Lithuania uses Jogaila until the unification and his conversion to Catholicism, subsequently Jagiełło, so we agree there. @All, if we're going to open this can of worms, then we must acknowledge that this represents a '''pivotal and unique individual''' in the history of Poland-Lithuania. Stone, in indexing his seminal work, does '''not''' use Jogaila's/Jagiełło's royal title as he uses directly or parenthetically &quot;(notes)&quot; for everyone else. Conforming to Stone's indexing syntax, I propose #1, below, and #2 and #3 associated:
# &quot;Jagiełło (Jogaila)&quot; as article title
# redirect &quot;Jogaila&quot; to the above
# redirect &quot;Władysław II Jagiełło&quot; to the above
Frankly, I don't see any other viable option which doesn't start the grinding wheels spinning sharpening axes&amp;mdash;which usually commences with dueling Google searches, regarding which the glove has already been thrown (in good faith, I should note). I suggest picking the glove back up before someone accepts the challenge. My solution follows the best scholarship and pleases no one identifiably Lithuanian or Polish--nor myself, personally, I would keep Jogaila, but this isn't about my preference. I would urge that quick agreement will prevent the piling on of &quot;outsiders&quot; unfamiliar with history and who inevitably throw gasoline on the embers to start the flames going in earnest. [[User:Vecrumba|VєсrumЬа]]&lt;small&gt; ►[[User_talk:Vecrumba|TALK]]&lt;/small&gt; 22:49, 1 January 2014 (UTC)

P.S. Obviously we'd redirect the non-diacritics versions of same as well. [[User:Vecrumba|VєсrumЬа]]&lt;small&gt; ►[[User_talk:Vecrumba|TALK]]&lt;/small&gt; 22:57, 1 January 2014 (UTC)
:I am afraid that [[Jagiełło (Jogaila)]] is going to get shot down due to problems with Manual of Style. It's a bit like the definition of compromise: it makes no-one happy. I know, I proposed [[Władysław II Jagiełło (Jogaila)]] as a compromise years back (search through archives...) and it didn't get anywhere. --&lt;sub style=&quot;border:1px solid #228B22;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Piotrus|Piotr Konieczny aka Prokonsul Piotrus]]&amp;#124;[[User talk:Piotrus|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#7CFC00;background:#006400;&quot;&gt; reply here&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sub&gt; 22:59, 1 January 2014 (UTC)
:: MOS cannot trump scholarship. If you're open to try for &quot;keeps no one happy&quot; but this time the title follows the convention used by a seminal work of scholarship dedicated to Poland-Lithuania and hailed in academia, then I am happy to fight the MOS is a convention, not a dictate, battle. [[User:Vecrumba|VєсrumЬа]]&lt;small&gt; ►[[User_talk:Vecrumba|TALK]]&lt;/small&gt; 23:07, 1 January 2014 (UTC)
:I would even doubt that the Lithuanian version of his name &quot;''Jogaila''&quot; was ever used in the times he lived - since the 13th/14th century old [[Ruthenian language|Ruthenian]] was spoken in the Grand Duchy by the upper class. 
:The only proper name for the article is his royal name, like for every other Polish or European King..., I see no reason to make here an exception--[[User:Sobiepan|Sobiepan]] ([[User talk:Sobiepan|talk]]) 10:11, 2 January 2014 (UTC)
::Don't forget, he was not only Polish king, but Grand Duke of Lithuania (1377–1434) also. I always was for the reasonable compromise between Lithuanian and Polish name, even if it will slightly break naming convention of the Wikipedia. [[User:Orionus|Orionus]] ([[User talk:Orionus|talk]]) 10:02, 13 January 2014 (UTC)

:''The above discussion is preserved as an archive of a [[WP:RM|requested move]].  &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/span&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on this talk page. No further edits should be made to this section.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- Template:RM bottom --&gt;

== Unfortunate (IMO) choice ==
I see we've gone from one not the best choice title to another. MOS is not a dictate to trump nomenclature as used in seminal works of scholarship on Poland-Lithuania. Registering my disappointment that at the face of it it looks like another Lithuanian &quot;he's ours&quot; versus Polish &quot;no, he's ours&quot;. [[User:Vecrumba|VєсrumЬа]]&lt;small&gt; ►[[User_talk:Vecrumba|TALK]]&lt;/small&gt; 23:51, 27 February 2014 (UTC)
:As I said before, I'd support [[Władysław II Jagiełło (Jogaila)]]. Nobody else ever was on board with that, however. --&lt;sub style=&quot;border:1px solid #228B22;padding:1px;&quot;&gt;[[User:Piotrus|Piotr Konieczny aka Prokonsul Piotrus]]&amp;#124;[[User talk:Piotrus|&lt;font style=&quot;color:#7CFC00;background:#006400;&quot;&gt; reply here&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sub&gt; 05:19, 28 February 2014 (UTC)
:: I would be fine with that too. This is a special case and strict application of MOS is completely inappropriate based on the best scholarship on the subject, including how his information is indexed. We probably know this topic better than most editors and arguably represent both sides &quot;claiming ownership,&quot; Polish versus Lithuanian kin to Latvian. I'm willing to open the can of worms one more time. [[User:Vecrumba|VєсrumЬа]]&lt;small&gt; ►[[User_talk:Vecrumba|TALK]]&lt;/small&gt; 04:13, 3 March 2014 (UTC)

== Old portrait versus 18th century portrait painting ==

While the 19th-century painting of Władysław II Jagiełło no doubt looks pretty nice, how nice a picture looks should always be secondary to the authenticity and accuracy of a picture. As such, when choosing what picture to use as a portrait in a biographical article on Wikipedia, it is generally best to choose a picture that is dated as close as possible to the time the person lived. The 19th-century painting cannot be accurate because it was painted over 400 years after the person in question died. If the painter used a good source for his portrait, then simply use that source as picture for this article. If the painter did not use a source, then the portrait is pure fiction. I have replaced the picture with what I thought was the best example in the commons directory. If there are better pictures, then please put them on top, as long as they are accurate depictions of the person in question. [[User:Omegastar|Omegastar]] ([[User talk:Omegastar|talk]]) 17:23, 25 July 2014 (UTC)
::Agree completely.  (That is why I've sometimes even used tomb effigies from the period.)  [[User:Nihil novi|Nihil novi]] ([[User talk:Nihil novi|talk]]) 03:55, 26 July 2014 (UTC)

==  Dubious map with millions of grammatical mistakes  ==

About your revert, my sources aren't more dubious than the ''Ilustrowany atlas historii Polski'', wyd. Demart, Warszawa 2006 who confuses &quot;wassal state&quot; with &quot;fief&quot; and anticipes &quot;hospodar&quot; for a century. About your &quot;millions of grammatical mistakes&quot;, into the &quot;Two nations&quot;, the names are in their POLISH form (used in this times, verify). Into Hungary, in their magyar form. Into Transylvania (under the Magyar names), Moldavia &amp; Wallachia (upper the polish names), in their romanian form (transcripted from the romanian medieval specific cyrillic script). Into the Crimean khanate, into their turkic form, transcritped from the arab script. All this are known by the historians of this area. But you prefer, for Wikipedia, a map who represents Bialgorod &amp; Akkerman as two different cities, and anticipes Akkerman (appeared after 1484 - ottoman conquest). Congratulations ! --[[User:Spiridon Ion Cepleanu|Spiridon Ion Cepleanu]] ([[User talk:Spiridon Ion Cepleanu|talk]]) 16:28, 6 December 2015 (UTC)

== Year of birth ==

His year of birth has been depicted as 1352/1362.... His exact year of birth seems to be unknown. However several users have changed it recently in 1352, also changing other text in related articles without any explanation or source. I will revert again. [[User:Hebel|Gerard von Hebel]] ([[User talk:Hebel|talk]]) 16:31, 7 April 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>tajh48mgfb6peeso498612guyu6q6vy</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
