<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:William McKinley</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>19728938</id>
    <revision>
      <id>746153570</id>
      <parentid>746140149</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-25T15:51:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Coemgenus</username>
        <id>203952</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>rvv</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17695">{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 250K
|counter = 1
|minthreadsleft = 10
|minthreadstoarchive = 1
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:William McKinley/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{Talk header}}
{{Article history|action1=PR
|action1date=18:53, 14 March 2012
|action1link=Wikipedia:Peer review/William McKinley/archive1
|action1result=reviewed
|action1oldid=481894448

|action2=FAC
|action2date=16:09, 28 March 2012
|action2link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/William McKinley/archive1
|action2result=promoted
|action2oldid=484386659

|currentstatus=FA
|maindate=September 14, 2012

|otd1date=2007-09-14
|otd1oldid=157536336
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Biography|living=no|class=FA|military-work-group=yes|military-priority=mid|politician-work-group=yes|listas=McKinley, William}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=FA|Biography=yes|ACW=yes}}
{{WikiProject Politics|class=FA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject U.S. Congress| class=FA |importance=mid | subject=person}}
{{WikiProject United States|class=FA|importance=High|OH=yes|OH-importance=High|USgovernors=yes|USgovernors-importance=low|USPresidents=yes|USPresidents-importance=High|USPE=Yes|USPE-importance=|listas=McKinley, William}}
}}
{{OhioSB}}
{{Wikipedia CD selection}}

== Sherman, Sherman, Sherman ==

The constant use of a last name is ridiculous. The name Sherman is used about a dozen times, sometimes as &quot;Senator Sherman&quot; but only once is John Sherman fully named. Honestly, I don't think wiki people understand how the average user uses these pages, as some of your &quot;rules&quot; are unhelpful. Only using a link once, for example. Often a person comes to an enormous page such as this for only one subheading, but is then forced to read the whole thing in search of links and full names. Not cool. More reasons WP sucks for research.
[[Special:Contributions/184.77.189.134|184.77.189.134]] ([[User talk:184.77.189.134|talk]]) 15:28, 6 March 2012 (UTC)
::I grant your point, but how would you see it done?--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 15:31, 6 March 2012 (UTC)

== Length ==

I think we are going to get comments we are too long, Brianboulton, who will review the article when he has a free moment, hinted as much.  I think we should look to cut by about 10 percent.  Presently, we are pushing 14,000 words.--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 18:40, 6 March 2012 (UTC)
:there is too much on the Civil war--the material says very little about McKinley and lowers the overall usefulness of the article. The danger is that students will spend too much time and miss the major story that in his last decade of life. [[User:Rjensen|Rjensen]] ([[User talk:Rjensen|talk]]) 00:16, 21 March 2012 (UTC)
::It's already been trimmed enough.  The article is the biography of a man, not just a political analysis.  People other than students read Wikipedia, and some of them might want to read a bit about McKinley's time at war.  His biographers certainly discuss it.  --[[User:Coemgenus|Coemgenus]] ([[User talk:Coemgenus|talk]]) 01:53, 21 March 2012 (UTC)
:::the section on the Civil War is poorly done. Mostly it's about the commanders of various units. What McK did and how he reacted to it and how it shaped his life is notable missing. What you get instead is useless info not about McK. for example  this sort of stuffing I(and all of the following section): ''he regiment resumed its advance that spring with Hayes in command (Scammon by then led the brigade) and fought several minor engagements against the rebel forces.[20] That September, McKinley's regiment was called east to reinforce General John Pope's Army of Virginia at the Second Battle of Bull Run.[21] Delayed in passing through Washington, D.C., the 23rd Ohio did not arrive in time for the battle, but joined the Army of the Potomac as it hurried north to cut off Robert E. Lee's Army of Northern Virginia as it was advanced into Maryland.[21] The 23rd was the first regiment to encounter the Confederates at the Battle of South Mountain on September 14.[22] After severe losses, Union forces drove back the Confederates and continued to Sharpsburg, Maryland, where they engaged Lee's army at the Battle of Antietam, one of the bloodiest battles of the war.[23] The 23rd was also in the thick of the fighting at Antietam, and McKinley himself came under heavy fire when bringing rations to the men on the line.[23][a] McKinley's regiment again suffered many casualties, but the Army of the Potomac was victorious and the Confederates retreated into Virginia.[23] The regiment was then detached from the Army of the Potomac and returned by train to western Virginia.[24]''  [[User:Rjensen|Rjensen]] ([[User talk:Rjensen|talk]]) 02:02, 21 March 2012 (UTC)
::::Would you mind keeping your edit summaries [[WP:CIVIL|civil]]?  I didn't call it &quot;useless stuffing&quot; when you addded your own book to the bibliography.  Rudeness won't help us to achieve consensus.  --[[User:Coemgenus|Coemgenus]] ([[User talk:Coemgenus|talk]]) 02:26, 21 March 2012 (UTC)
:::::I made the point that the war materials is not really about McKinley. too much of the war the text is superflous, unnecessary, useless, un-revealing of McKinley, old-fashioned,  not atuned with modern scholarship on soldier motivations, time-wasting and should be deleted to save space. To please Coemgenus I will withdraw the word he finds so dreadful, &quot;stuffing.&quot;  [[User:Rjensen|Rjensen]] ([[User talk:Rjensen|talk]]) 02:32, 21 March 2012 (UTC)
:::::: Can't this wait until after the FAC?--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 08:03, 21 March 2012 (UTC)
::::::: It can wait until Hell freezes over. ''Hard disks are cheap.'' [[User:Alarbus|Alarbus]] ([[User talk:Alarbus|talk]]) 09:27, 21 March 2012 (UTC)
::::::::article that are too long and too full of extraneous low-information material don't really deserve exemplary praise.  What's in short supply is not disk space but readers' attention. [[User:Rjensen|Rjensen]] ([[User talk:Rjensen|talk]]) 15:31, 21 March 2012 (UTC)

== Close PR? ==

Shall we close the PR and go for FAC?  Now that Brian's finished his excellent review and we've made adjustments, we may not get anymore comments, and we may as well get them at FAC.--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 20:19, 14 March 2012 (UTC)
:I don't have a problem with that.  I want to read over Brian's last few comments again, especially about the civil rights section, before FAC, but that shouldn't take long -- hopefully I can do it tonight.  You and I both have open FA noms -- will that be a problem?  --[[User:Coemgenus|Coemgenus]] ([[User talk:Coemgenus|talk]]) 20:48, 14 March 2012 (UTC)
:No, we're allowed a second nom if it's a joint one.  I'll keep Assassination away from FAC until this one's home free, though.  I would appreciate it if you would look over the civil rights thing, I'm a bit taken aback that &quot;black&quot; is so unacceptable and would be grateful for your view and that of Rjensen.--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 20:52, 14 March 2012 (UTC)
::I've written FAs before with that word, though I tend to use it only as an adjective.  Never had any complaints until now.  --[[User:Coemgenus|Coemgenus]] ([[User talk:Coemgenus|talk]]) 22:11, 14 March 2012 (UTC)
::Its' Afro-American that seems outdated to me, actually.  I wonder if there's anyone we can ask for an outside opinion.  Tony1, perhaps?--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 22:17, 14 March 2012 (UTC)
:::Yes, I haven't heard that since my school days, and even then only in lessons -- I don't remember a black student calling himself &quot;Afro-American&quot;.  But, yes, an outside opinion couldn't hurt.  Is there an MoS on the subject?  --[[User:Coemgenus|Coemgenus]] ([[User talk:Coemgenus|talk]]) 22:22, 14 March 2012 (UTC)
::::My high school had no &lt;s&gt;blacks&lt;/s&gt;African Americans for most of my time, which was simply the way things were there, &lt;s&gt;blacks&lt;/s&gt;African Americans went to high schools in more urban towns and generally cleaned our clocks in the state tournaments.  I didn't see anything obvious in the MOS, which means little, the MOS is probably larger than the ex-Encyclopedia Britannica.  I'm inclined to take our lumps on this one, on reflection.  Even if we're right, we could turn out wrong if Brian's attitude is more widely shared at FAC.--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 22:41, 14 March 2012 (UTC)
:::::Well, if you want to keep it as &quot;African American&quot;, I won't make any changes.  The rest of the language works as is.  --[[User:Coemgenus|Coemgenus]] ([[User talk:Coemgenus|talk]]) 00:37, 15 March 2012 (UTC)
::::::I closed the PR.  If you don't object, I'll launch the FA nom tonight.  --[[User:Coemgenus|Coemgenus]] ([[User talk:Coemgenus|talk]]) 12:11, 16 March 2012 (UTC)
:::::::FA nomination is live! --[[User:Coemgenus|Coemgenus]] ([[User talk:Coemgenus|talk]]) 23:52, 16 March 2012 (UTC)

== More on lead ==

The lead claims that McKinley's presidency began a period of Republican dominance. How can this be true? Republicans had been dominant ever since the Civil War, both in Congress and in the White House. If anything I would say he &quot;reaffirmed&quot; it after Grover Cleveland, but not &quot;began&quot; it. [[User:Brutannica|Brutannica]] ([[User talk:Brutannica|talk]]) 18:40, 14 September 2012 (UTC)
:Parties tended to lose control of Congress in the off-year election, sometimes very dramatically (1890 and 1894, for example), and no president had been re-elected since Grant.  It was a 50/50 nation.  Harrison had won the presidency with a minority thanks to the Electoral College, and 1880 and 1876 had been very narrow Republican wins (1876, well ...) Republicans didn't lose control of either again until Wilson, under internal dissent.--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 18:51, 14 September 2012 (UTC)
::And the FA summation says, &quot;but his presidency began a period of over a third of a century dominated by the Republican Party&quot;, which is totally meaningless.  At least the article is a bit better.
::However, Republican domination lasted from 1861 to 1933, with only 20 years out of 72 being led by Republicans.  [[User:Jim62sch|&lt;font face=&quot;Times New Roman&quot; color=&quot;FF2400&quot;&gt;&amp;#0149;Jim&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;Times New Roman&quot; color=&quot;F4C430&quot;&gt;62&lt;/font&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;Times New Roman&quot; color=&quot;000000&quot;&gt;sch&amp;#0149;&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Jim62sch|dissera!]]&lt;/sup&gt; 19:04, 14 September 2012 (UTC)
::::In 1893, the Democrats had gotten more votes in the last three presidential elections, and the Republicans had taken a terrible beating in Congress in back to back elections.  McKinley did something about that (although, granted, the Democrats had a very bad 1894 election).--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 20:35, 14 September 2012 (UTC)

== Postage Image Substitute ==

I have removed the following stamp image. It has been established by consensus in the GA and FA review of numerous presidential articles that postage commemorations lack appropriate significance per [[WP:Images]] and [[WP:MOS]] See Talk pages for Lincoln, Kennedy, Eisenhower, and Roosevelt. A link has been added for the reader to US Presidential Stamps. [[User:Hoppyh|Hoppyh]] ([[User talk:Hoppyh|talk]]) 22:26, 8 October 2012 (UTC)
[[File:William McKinley 1938 Issue-25c.jpg|thumb|right|upright|McKinley]]
:I suppose it was basically decorative.  The article's fairly stuffed with images, I won't look to replace it unless I see something interesting.--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 23:35, 8 October 2012 (UTC)
::A couple earlier sections may look crowded to the image experts but there is room for something in that section. How about Mt. McKinley image following? [[User:Hoppyh|Hoppyh]] ([[User talk:Hoppyh|talk]]) 13:36, 9 October 2012 (UTC) [[File:Mount McKinley and Denali National Park Road 2048px.jpg|thumb|right]]
:::I had the good fortune of seeing it on my only trip to inland Alaska, almost 30 years ago ... but I'm not sure it says anything about the man.--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 21:45, 9 October 2012 (UTC)

== Categorization - Freemason ==

Earlier, I removed [[:Category:American Freemasons]] from this article.  That has been reverted, so it is now time to discuss the issue.  The Wikipedia guideline that governs this is [[WP:Categorization of people]] (with an emphasis on the section: [[WP:COP#General considerations]].  It states that we are supposed to '''&quot;Categorize by those characteristics that make the person notable&quot;.''' 
 
If being a Freemason ''is'' a characteristic that makes McKinley notable, then I would expect at least a short paragraph on his membership in the article.  At the moment, all the article has is one &quot;in passing&quot; reference (&quot;''McKinley found time to join a Freemason lodge (later renamed after him) in Winchester, Virginia, before he and Carroll were transferred to Hancock's First Veterans Corps in Washington.''&quot;).  I don't think this is enough to justify the categorization.  We need more.  The question is... what more can we say? Ideas? [[User:Blueboar|Blueboar]] ([[User talk:Blueboar|talk]]) 14:06, 13 February 2013 (UTC)
:Probably not too much more.  I try not to get involved with categories because I don't greatly care about them and others do  I don't know what you would say more than we have also.  He was a freemason, and like many lawyer/politicians before and since joined everything in sight to drum up work/votes.--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 17:24, 13 February 2013 (UTC)

== 500-dollar bill ==

I think changing the obverse of the $500 bill from depicting Chief Justice Marshall to President McKinley in 1928 is a relevant legacy and should be included on William McKinley's page as more than just a point of trivia. I don't know the circumstances of why he was chosen but it is interesting that he was selected over other former presidents including fellow Republican Teddy Roosevelt. Is this an indication that he was he still quite popular 27 years after his death?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/173.70.75.113|173.70.75.113]] ([[User talk:173.70.75.113|talk]]) 14:19, 14 April 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Not really certain.  McKinley, I believe, appeared on several banknotes.  I'm not an expert on them.  He also appeared on several stamps into the 1920s (not counting the [[Presidential series]], on which every deceased president appeared).  We'd need to know more about the reasons for same.--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 17:37, 14 April 2013 (UTC)

== See also ==

Has that &quot;see also&quot; section always been there? It seems like unnecessary clutter. Anyone object to deleting it? --[[User:Coemgenus|Coemgenus]] ([[User talk:Coemgenus|talk]]) 18:01, 14 April 2013 (UTC)
::good idea [[User:Rjensen|Rjensen]] ([[User talk:Rjensen|talk]]) 18:35, 14 April 2013 (UTC)
:::I think at least the postal one has been there for a while.  No objection to deletion.  McKinley was on a fair number of regular-issue postage stamps in the first quarter of the 20th century, then dropped away, and except for the Prexy issue of 1938 and the AMERIPEX souvenir sheets of 1986 (in both cases honors shared by every other dead president), hasn't been on much since.  I don't think it needs to be there.--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 18:46, 14 April 2013 (UTC)
::::I deleted it.  --[[User:Coemgenus|Coemgenus]] ([[User talk:Coemgenus|talk]]) 21:22, 14 April 2013 (UTC)

== Last photograph?/painting? ==

Is the purported last photograph actually a photograph?  It looks more like a painting to me.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Slamdac|Slamdac]] ([[User talk:Slamdac|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Slamdac|contribs]]) 10:23, 6 September 2014 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Concur.  Looks like a painting.[[Special:Contributions/131.79.183.32|131.79.183.32]] ([[User talk:131.79.183.32|talk]]) 14:47, 19 May 2015 (UTC)
:I'm pretty sure it is a photo.  We're talking about the one entering the Temple of Music, right?--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 10:54, 6 September 2014 (UTC)

Yes the one where he is walking up the stairs.  Maybe it's the old technology but it looks more like a painting to me/  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Slamdac|Slamdac]] ([[User talk:Slamdac|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Slamdac|contribs]]) 13:36, 7 September 2014 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
::It's labeled in the source &quot;last known photographs&quot;.  There were undoubtedly a multitude of depictions of McKinley on his deathbed--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 13:00, 8 September 2014 (UTC)

== Philippine-American war ? ==

Mckinley was glorified in his actions that leads the United States Victory against Spain...but why does his involvment was never been mention in this article during the outbreak of Philippine-American?! In his term during his presidency (1899~1902). That also leads to another certain victory but causes more deaths than the Spanish-American war, that annexed or conquered the Philippine islands and its people? For more thay 40 years.
And it has labeled to be an imperislist?! [[User:FilBox101|FilBox101]] ([[User talk:FilBox101|talk]]) 22:59, 10 August 2015 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>hwgg6dk1ksmy30bp8wng3e7kmd6u7ib</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
