<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Byzantine navy</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2391896</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748976010</id>
      <parentid>743545793</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-11T15:27:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Notification of altered sources needing review #IABot (v1.2.7.1)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15531">{{Talk header}}
{{Article history|action1=WPR
|action1date=16 March 2008
|action1link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Peer review/Byzantine navy
|action1result=reviewed
|action1oldid=198630845
|action2=GAN
|action2date=16 March 2008
|action2link=Talk:Byzantine navy#GA passes
|action2result=listed
|action2oldid=198658651
|action3=WAR
|action3date=11:27, 31 May 2008
|action3link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/Byzantine navy
|action3result=approved
|action3oldid=216153825
|action4=FAC
|action4date=19:58, 8 November 2008
|action4link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Byzantine navy/archive1
|action4result=not promoted
|action4oldid=250093737
|action5=FAC
|action5date=21:34, 15 March 2009
|action5link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Byzantine navy
|action5result=promoted
|action5oldid=277039169
|topic=History
|currentstatus=FA
|maindate=October 1, 2009
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|collapsed=yes|1=
{{WikiProject Military history|class=FA|old-peer-review=yes|A-Class=pass|Maritime=yes|Medieval=yes|Roman=yes|European=yes|African=yes|Middle-Eastern=yes|Crusades=yes}}
{{WikiProject Middle Ages|class=FA|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Greece|class=FA|importance=Mid|topic=history|byzantine-task-force=yes}}
{{WikiProject Classical Greece and Rome|class=FA|importance=low}}
{{WP1.0|v0.7=pass|class=FA|category=History}}
}}

== Cleanup ==
Gosh darnit, this ''does'' need cleaned up. A lot. A pity I don't know anything about the Byzantine fleet...

---
You do have to admit, however, that it is a hilarious article, even if it doesn't conform to any standards of quality... [[User:Morgan2317|Morgan2317]] 17:28, 10 August 2005 (UTC)

I think the section for Greek fire is too long and needs to be merged with the [[Greek fire]] article--[[User:Cigor|Cigor]] 18:55, 21 August 2005 (UTC)

The article is in good shape, IMHO. 
Does anybody object if I remove context and cleanup tags?
--[[User:Cigor|Cigor]] 14:42, 29 September 2005 (UTC)

::Remove away - but maybe reword Context as introduction? I only put 'context' as the working title when I wrote it, forgot to change it. Or perhaps add the paragragh to the begining of the article in italics with no heading? [[User:Eliasbizannes|Elias Bizannes]] 16:20, 29 September 2005 (UTC)
:::Ok, I waited 10+ days, it appears nobody minds. Eliasbizannes, thanks for the feedback the article may needs couple of tweaks but I think it’s pretty decent (altough it’s imposible to cover 10 centuries history in such a short article). --[[User:Cigor|Cigor]] 07:47, 9 October 2005 (UTC)

I 've stumbled upon this article and while adding few wikilinks, I saw terms like &quot;desert people&quot;, &quot;police&quot;. I'm afraid it needs a little cleanup. [[User:Matia.gr|+MATIA]]  &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Matia.gr|&amp;#9742;]]&lt;/small&gt; 09:51, 9 October 2005 (UTC)
: Since I am the “culprit”  for both terms I feel the need to explain:
:*Police: This is directly from Britannica 1911: http://91.1911encyclopedia.org/N/NA/NAVY_AND_NAVIES.htm. Police here means mainly anti-pirate/smuggling  activities.
:*Desert: The original sentence from Ostrogorski’s book is ‘’…This was a completely new problem for a desert race…’’ . I thought the race is rather strong so I changed it. But Arabia is not quite the bread basket of the world.
:However you may be right about extra cleaning, so I’ll put that tag on. But as for context, I think we have more than enough. --[[User:Cigor|Cigor]] 14:20, 11 October 2005 (UTC)

:: How can one maintain the thought of the Arabs as a desert people, when they for centuries kept a virtual monopoly on spice, myrrhe and frankinsense trade to/from the far east? They were extremely verse in seafaring across long distances, since early Roman days (see [[Arabia Felix]]) or even before. [[User:Mhaesen|Mhaesen]] 14:47, 14 December 2005 (UTC)

:::Before 644, the Arabs had no fleet. As for the spice monopoly, the major trade route was the land route from India, Middle East which was controlled by the Arabs and then Europe. I really don’t understand why some people are having issues with this, nothing wrong being desert people.--[[User:Cigor|Cigor]] 14:58, 14 December 2005 (UTC)

::::Always good to split some hairs, that's what makes a good encyclopedia: before 644, the Arabs did not have a fleet in the '''Mediterranean'''. May I quote, as an example, from [[Dilmun]]: ''Dilmun (sometimes transliterated Telmun) is associated with ancient sites on the islands of Bahrain in the Persian Gulf. Because of its location along the sea trade routes linking Mesopotamia with the Indus Valley Civilization, Dilmun developed in the Bronze Age, from ca. 3000 BC, into one of the greatest entrepôts of trade of the ancient world.'' Indeed, nothing wrong with being a desert people, however, by denying the Arabs their rightfull legacy as seafarers, it would seem as if the Byzantine navy had a very hard time dealing with naval 'new kids on the block', which in turn begrudges the Byzantines of their actual marine power. [[User:Mhaesen|Mhaesen]] 16:17, 14 December 2005 (UTC)
::::: Good point, Mhaesen. I admit I was just putting the stuff about desert people from Ostrogorski’s book. No injustice intended.  --[[User:Cigor|Cigor]] 17:17, 14 December 2005 (UTC)

== Oarsmen and Marines ==

Should we open up a section on the Byzantines' naval strength? As shown by number of Marines and Oarsmen in the Aegean, Cibyrrhaeot, Hellas and Samos Themes, plus the Imperial Fleet? I have the 773 to 899 numbers. [[User:Dryzen|Dryzen]] 13:17, 4 July 2006 (UTC)

== Minor comment on Byzantine history ==

With regard to the following statment

''Although the Eastern Empire was a direct continuation of the Roman empire begun by Augustus, it developed its own unique culture and identity that in hindsight, appears to be Roman only in name.''

I believe that this a fairly controversial statement given the leanings of modern historians. That is, it can be said that arguing that the late &quot;Byzantine&quot; empire was very different from the earlier &quot;Roman&quot; empire is really a lot like saying the modern United States is a different nation from that founded in 1776. Certainly such an argument could be made but the reality is that it is still the same state and one would expect that any nation changes over time. In the case of the Roman Empire there was a span of over a thousand years so one would certainly expect substantial changes over that time (certainly the Roman state when Rome fell was quite different than the state that existed when G. Julius Caesar was born). The fact that the primary language of the Eastern court changed to Greek (it had been the language of the people long before the fall of Rome) is really no different from the fact that Norman Britain switched from French back to English as the language of the court. It was still the same state with a continuity of culture (i.e. continually changing culture) regardless of the change in language.

I believe a discussion of the continuity of the Roman heritage is probably best left for the article on the &quot;Byzantine Empire.&quot; I think this article should be more neutral on this point simply saying something to the effect that &quot;Byzantine&quot; is the name that western historians of the past few centuries (until recently) have assigned to the Eastern Empire after the Western Empire was lost.
--[[User:Mcorazao|Mcorazao]] 16:09, 11 September 2006 (UTC)

: I agree, this article spends too much time discussing the contunuity or otherwise with the earlier Roman Empire. Such a discussion is not directly applicable to the Byzantine navy, and merely makes the article appear contorted and apologetic. If no-one objects, I might cut these references down to a brief comment. --[[User:Iacobus|Iacobus]] 01:59, 13 December 2006 (UTC)

== {{user|71.113.102.33}} ==

I'm unsure at the veracity of user 71.113.102.33's adits, at the very least his numbers (unsourced) seems far too large. His delivery is also suspect. Hopefully clearity will be given.--[[User:Dryzen|Dryzen]] 15:56, 7 November 2006 (UTC)

== [[Dromon]] ==

Merging some of the text describing the different varieties of [[dromon]] into the more specific article -- [[User:Azeari|Matt]] 04:01, 17 May 2007 (UTC)

== GA passes ==
{{#if:aye|{{#ifeq:{{NAMESPACE}}|Talk||{{error:not substituted|GAList}}&lt;div style=&quot;display:none;&quot;&gt;}}}}
:'''[[Wikipedia:Good article nominations|GA]] review''' (see [[Wikipedia:What is a good article?|here]] for criteria)
{{#if:Great job! I'm impressed by the great usage of sources, the cleanliness of the article structure, and the comprehensiveness of the material covered.|&lt;hr width=50%&gt;Great job! I'm impressed by the great usage of sources, the cleanliness of the article structure, and the comprehensiveness of the material covered.|}}
#It is '''reasonably well written'''.
#:a ''(prose)'': {{GAList/check|aye}} b ''([[Wikipedia:Manual of Style|MoS]])'': {{GAList/check|aye}}
#:: {{#if:|{{{1com}}}|}}
#It is '''factually accurate''' and '''[[Wikipedia:Verifiability|verifiable]]'''.
#:a ''(references)'': {{GAList/check|aye}} b ''(citations to [[WP:RS|reliable sources]])'': {{GAList/check|aye}} c ''([[Wikipedia:No original research|OR]])'': {{GAList/check|aye}}
#:: {{#if:|{{{2com}}}|}}
#It is '''broad in its coverage'''.
#:a ''(major aspects)'': {{GAList/check|aye}} b ''(focused)'': {{GAList/check|aye}}
#:: {{#if:|{{{3com}}}|}}
Yep, no doubts there [[User:Tagmatarchos|Tagmatarchos]] ([[User talk:Tagmatarchos|talk]]) 08:47, 7 June 2008 (UTC)
#It follows the '''[[WP:NPOV|neutral point of view]] policy'''.
#:''Fair representation without bias'': {{GAList/check|aye}}
#:: {{#if:|{{{4com}}}|}}
#It is '''stable'''.
#:''No edit wars etc.'': {{GAList/check|aye}}
#:: {{#if:|{{{5com}}}|}}
#It is illustrated by '''[[Wikipedia:Images|images]]''', where possible and appropriate.
#:a ''(images are tagged and non-free images have [[Wikipedia:Image_description_page#Use_rationale|fair use rationales]])'': {{GAList/check|aye}} b ''(appropriate use with [[WP:CAP|suitable captions]])'': {{GAList/check|aye}}
#:: {{#if:There is a surprising lack of images for this article, but since all relevant images would be PD, it's not that big of a problem.|There is a surprising lack of images for this article, but since all relevant images would be PD, it's not that big of a problem.|}}
#'''Overall''': 
#:''Pass/Fail'': {{GAList/check|aye}}
#:: {{#if:I'm going to look for more images since some sections were a bit spotty. Overall, great work!|I'm going to look for more images since some sections were a bit spotty. Overall, great work!|}}&lt;!-- Template:GAList --&gt;&lt;/div&gt; --[[User:Hemlock Martinis|Hemlock Martinis]] ([[User talk:Hemlock Martinis|talk]]) 17:21, 16 March 2008 (UTC)

== Medieval ships ==

WP has a rather thin article on [[Medieval ships]], which would benefit from some fattening from here and cross-linking, if anyone's keen.  [[User:Gwinva|Gwinva]] ([[User talk:Gwinva|talk]]) 02:00, 5 March 2009 (UTC)

== Empty first sentence ==

&lt;blockquote&gt;The Byzantine navy comprised the naval forces of the Byzantine Empire.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Really, who'd've guessed that. [[User:Jimp|J&lt;small&gt;IM&lt;/small&gt;p]]&lt;sub&gt;&amp;nbsp;[[User talk:Jimp|talk]]·[[Special:Contributions/Jimp|cont]]&lt;/sub&gt; 04:13, 1 October 2009 (UTC)

: It's not unencyclopedic. Reader A thought maybe &quot;Byzantine navy&quot; was a color. Reader B hasn't heard of the &quot;Byzantine Empire&quot;. Such is the unglamorous, orienting purpose of the first sentence of most of our articles. I'm not saying it couldn't be improved, but the simple-definition aspect would still be there. [[User:Outriggr|Outriggr]] ([[User talk:Outriggr|talk]]) 04:32, 1 October 2009 (UTC)
: Nice article, by the way. Forest for the trees, as usual, around here. [[User:Outriggr|Outriggr]] ([[User talk:Outriggr|talk]]) 04:33, 1 October 2009 (UTC)
: Here's an opening sentence that combines the first two: &quot;The '''[[navy]] of the [[Byzantine Empire]]''', like the empire it served, developed directly from its earlier imperial Roman counterpart...[, but in comparison with its precursor played a far greater role in the defense and survival of the state.]&quot; Is something like that better? It's OK, but to me a dead simple topic sentence before that idea is presented is not a bad thing, given diverse readership. [[User:Outriggr|Outriggr]] ([[User talk:Outriggr|talk]]) 06:09, 1 October 2009 (UTC)

::Yes, the reason I included it like that was pretty much as Outriggr states. It serves the purpose of precisely identifying the scope of the article, i.e. the naval forces of the Byzantine Empire, handled as a single topic, from 330 to 1453. It is more important a point than it seems. Just as an example, the &quot;Byzantine navy&quot; of 400 AD was, as one would expect, quite different from that of 800 AD or 1280 AD, and the point where it changed from &quot;late Roman&quot; to &quot;Byzantine&quot; could also be a point of contention. On the other hand, I don't have a particular problem with Outriggr's suggestion either. Regards, [[User:Cplakidas|Constantine]]  [[User talk:Cplakidas| ✍ ]] 07:59, 1 October 2009 (UTC)

== Control of the sea ==
{{quote|...and control of the Aegean passed definitively to the Italian and Ottoman navies.}}

Not wanting to be picky, but as long as the Byzantine empire existed (-1453), the Ottomans did not have a navy worth its name. They only started to field one in the late 15th century in their wars against Venice. Until then, control of the Aegean Sea, as the whole Levante, lay with the Italians, mainly Venice and Genua. [[User:Gun Powder Ma|Gun Powder Ma]] ([[User talk:Gun Powder Ma|talk]]) 13:05, 14 March 2010 (UTC)

== ENGVAR ==

What dialect of English is this supposed to be in? --[[User:John|John]] ([[User talk:John|talk]]) 18:00, 22 April 2014 (UTC)

[[Category:Wikipedia pages referenced by the press]]

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just modified {{plural:4|one external link|4 external links}} on [[Byzantine navy]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=748976007 my edit]. If you have any questions, or need the bot to ignore the links, or the page altogether, please visit [[User:Cyberpower678/FaQs#InternetArchiveBot|this simple FaQ]] for additional information. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20091010222625/http://brunelleschi.imss.fi.it:80/michaelofrhodes/ships_galleys.html to http://brunelleschi.imss.fi.it/michaelofrhodes/ships_galleys.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20100505031013/http://brunelleschi.imss.fi.it/michaelofrhodes/ships_sailing.html to http://brunelleschi.imss.fi.it/michaelofrhodes/ships_sailing.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20120306070444/http://ina.tamu.edu/library/tropis/volumes/3/Tropis%20III%20Proceedings%201989.pdf to http://ina.tamu.edu/library/tropis/volumes/3/Tropis%20III%20Proceedings%201989.pdf
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/web/20110725230646/http://www.deremilitari.org/resources/pdfs/christides.pdf to http://www.deremilitari.org/resources/pdfs/christides.pdf

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' or '''failed''' to let others know (documentation at {{tlx|Sourcecheck}}).

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:InternetArchiveBot|'''&lt;span style=&quot;color:darkgrey;font-family:monospace&quot;&gt;InternetArchiveBot&lt;/span&gt;''']] &lt;span style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Rockwell&quot;&gt;([[User talk:InternetArchiveBot|Report bug]])&lt;/span&gt; 15:27, 11 November 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>fjqdoh22aq25ksbxgncqum8ptpdqmrb</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
