<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Castell Coch</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>8935158</id>
    <revision>
      <id>725243100</id>
      <parentid>725243025</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-06-14T12:56:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Chandim Sett</username>
        <id>15274192</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 725243025 by [[Special:Contributions/Chandim Sett|Chandim Sett]] ([[User talk:Chandim Sett|talk]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="40015">{{ArticleHistory
|currentstatus=FA

|action1=FAC
|action1date=2015-04-24
|action1link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Castell Coch/archive1
|action1result=promoted
|action1oldid=657424948
|maindate=13 August 2015

}}

{{Old peer review|archive =1}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Military history|class = FA
|&lt;!-- B-Class-1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points have appropriate inline citations. --&gt;
|B-Class-1=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain obvious omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|B-Class-2=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;
|B-Class-3=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;
|B-Class-4=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;
|B-Class-5=yes
|British-task-force=yes|Medieval-task-force=yes|Fortifications-task-force=yes}}
{{WikiProject Cardiff|class = FA|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Wales|class = FA|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Architecture|historic-houses=yes}}
}}

==Untitled==
Appearences in Movies and Popular Culture
The castle is mentioned in the Target novelisation of the Doctor Who Story The Ark where companion Dodo Chaplet impliesthat she has visited the castle.

The Castle has also been used as a location in many films;

Think we need to add to this if it is to be of real value.  Where it states &quot;many films&quot;, can we amplify?  I know of &quot;Sir Gawain and the Green Knight&quot; (Stephen Weeks, director, 1973) but can't immediately think of any more.  Often thought to have been used in &quot;Robin Hood: Prince of Thieves&quot; but I think this was actually Peckforton, Cheshire.  Any others?

[[User:KJP1|KJP1]] 19:40, 5 March 2007 (UTC)

Just watched a film called &quot;Siege of the Saxons&quot; in which Castle Coch features.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/90.240.41.248|90.240.41.248]] ([[User talk:90.240.41.248|talk]]) 23:10, 4 June 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Castle Coch's surroundings ==

I gather from [[Castell_Coch_Woodlands_and_Road_Section]] that the surrounding woodlands are listed as a site of special scientific interest. That is probably noteworthy [[User:EdwardLane|EdwardLane]] ([[User talk:EdwardLane|talk]]) 09:01, 13 April 2011 (UTC)

== Building stone ==

The current infobox lists the materials as ''[[Carboniferous]] [[Sandstone]] [[Ashlar]]'', without citing a source. I think it is built of [[Old Red Sandstone]] (Devonian, not Carboniferous), based on the colour of the stone and on this being a common local building stone. The [http://www.britishlistedbuildings.co.uk/wa-13644-castell-coch-tongwynlais listed building citation] does not mention the type of stone, nor does Newman in ''The Building of Wales: Glamorgan''. In the absence of a citable reference I will remove this. [[User:Verbcatcher|Verbcatcher]] ([[User talk:Verbcatcher|talk]]) 20:41, 13 November 2014 (UTC)

== Where to mention Listed Building status? ==


User [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) has reverted my removal of the Grade I listed building status and the listing date from the lead section with the comment ''&quot;I think the intro should state it's a Grade I listed building&quot;''. We also give the listed building status under ''Architecture''.

I feel that while the listed building status should be mentioned it is a relatively mundane and bureaucratic attribute which does not deserve a place in the lead section. It is not necessary to establish the ''notability'' of this building. For comparison, [[Windsor Castle]] (a ''[[Wikipedia:Featured articles|featured article]]'') only refers to its listed building status in its ''Categories''.

Even if we keep the Grade I listing status in the lead paragraph, what is the point of giving the date when the building was listed? Who is this for? [[User:Verbcatcher|Verbcatcher]] ([[User talk:Verbcatcher|talk]]) 22:13, 20 November 2014 (UTC)

:In my opinion, it's usually better to explain ''why'' a building has Grade I listed status in the lead, rather than simply noting its legal status. For example, if we explained in the lead that [[Peter Floud]] considered the castle to be &quot;one of the greatest Victorian triumphs of architectural composition&quot; (which is part of the reason for its Grade I status) it would tell the reader much more about the property than simply the status, which would then become superfluous. I'd recommend keeping the listed building protection in the architecture paragraph though. [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 22:50, 20 November 2014 (UTC)

::At the risk of opening a different can of worms, the Infobox is the place I would hope to find it. It currently uses {{Tl|Infobox Military Structure}} which doesn't have any place for that. {{Tl|Infobox historic site}} might make more sense, and from a quick look, would seem to cover the information it needs. I agree that as it stands it is very odd in the lead, and that it should be expanded on in the Architecture para. [[User:RobinLeicester|RobinLeicester]] ([[User talk:RobinLeicester|talk]]) 23:35, 20 November 2014 (UTC)

:::I also favour putting ''Grade I listed'' into the Infobox. Infobox Military Structure seems a poor fit for Castell Coch, although it is used for other Welsh castles. We could use ''[[Tower of London]]'' as a model, which uses Infobox historic site to indicate a Grade I listed building. Does anyone support retaining the date of the listing? [[User:Verbcatcher|Verbcatcher]] ([[User talk:Verbcatcher|talk]]) 02:08, 21 November 2014 (UTC)

::::Either in the Infobox or the lead would seem quite appropriate.  But not, I think, buried at the very end of the article.  I don't think that the Grade I listing can properly be considered a &quot;mundane and bureaucratic attribute&quot;.  It is a recognition, and confirmation, of the building's &quot;exceptional architectural and historical interest&quot;.  But I absolutely agree it would be better for the lead also to explain '''why''' it is exceptional. That was what the descriptive quotations - &quot;the most spectacular example of [Burges's] translation from High Gothic into High Victorian.&quot; -  it originally contained where intended to do.  But those were removed, along with the reference to its listing.  [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 07:33, 21 November 2014 (UTC)

:::::p.s. As to the date of its listing, there I agree I am just being pedantic! [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 07:39, 21 November 2014 (UTC)

For me, the Tower of London article is an example of where I don't think it should have been in the infobox at all (if a building is recognised and protected as a UNESCO World Heritage site, its grade I &amp; II listed status sort of fades into insignificance!) I'd support it being in the infobox ''and'' in the lead, but I'm not convinced of the logic of putting it in an infobox but ''not'' in the lead; for me, the infobox is about presenting &quot;key facts at a glance&quot;, and if its legal status is a key fact, then I think it should be in the lead as well. My preference would be to explain the significance of the architecture with one of the quotes in the lead, and leave its legal status for the main body of the text. [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 11:08, 21 November 2014 (UTC)

:As we do name have unanimity we must try for consensus. I ''think'' the consensus is that we add a quote praising the building in the lead section, but do not mention the listing there. We describe the listing in the architecture section. We are further from a consensus on the infobox, so I suggest we leave this as it is. Do we agree that this is the consensus from this discussion?

:If this is the consensus then someone needs to move the quote to the lead paragraph. I don't have access to the source for the quote from Peter Floud; someone who does should add it. The author should be named in the main text: see [[WP:MOSQUOTE]]. The existing text in the Architecture section on the Grade I listing can stand. [[User:Verbcatcher|Verbcatcher]] ([[User talk:Verbcatcher|talk]]) 20:17, 23 November 2014 (UTC)

::I have access to the Floud quote, and indeed loads of others, which indicate the castle's architectural and historical significance.  I shall therefore add them.  One point on attribution: I'm not sure I agree with Verbcatcher that this '''must''' be given.  The full [[WP:MOSQUOTE]] states &quot;The author of a quote ''of a full sentence or more'' should be named; this is done in the main text&quot; (my italics).  The Floud quote was not a full sentence.  Anyway, I shall have a go and people can see what they think.  [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 18:25, 27 November 2014 (UTC)
:::Quotations added.  I think the &quot;unrivalled intoxication&quot; conveys the impact of the castle quite well.  On the one occasion I persuaded my mother to visit, her only comment was that the building had given her &quot;a splitting headache.&quot;  [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 19:19, 27 November 2014 (UTC)

==Revisions to the article==

Overlooking the wanton destruction of some of my more flowery, Burges-obsessed, prose - although, at some point, I shall weave back in &quot;Together, at Cardiff and at Castell Coch, they would build their magnificent vision of a lost medieval world&quot; - I really like the way it's shaping up.  I thought it would help to have a space here where we could raise any issues, rather than spread them across our three talkpages.  If everyone's happy with the approach, let's crack on. Best regards, [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 20:49, 15 March 2015 (UTC)
:We're &quot;Edit-conflicting&quot; all over the bloody place!  [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 21:30, 15 March 2015 (UTC)
::&quot;Hock, not Coch&quot; as was said of the Marquess's wine.
:::NB: I'm using my copy of Floud for some of the physical details on the rooms; if the same details are in later guidebooks, pls feel free to replace the references with more up to date ones! [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 13:08, 21 March 2015 (UTC)

===Images===
{{Reply to|Dr. Blofeld}}

Dear Lord - we '''must''' get some better photos.  What are those benches doing stacked up in the Drawing Room?  Dr. B, get up there with your camera! [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 18:56, 21 March 2015 (UTC)
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt; The [[National Library of Wales]] have just added an 1808 oil painting to the article. This might replace the b&amp;W image of a similar date but I didn't want to delete anything without the knowledge of regular editors and contributors to this article. I hope the addition of the new image helps to improve the article. [[User:Jason.nlw|Jason.nlw]] ([[User talk:Jason.nlw|talk]]) 08:47, 9 April 2015 (UTC)
:Thanks {{ping|Jason.nlw}} - I'd seen it on the website before, but it wasn't free for use then; congrats to the NLW for releasing it! Could I ask a favour though? The metadata on the image in the Wikicommons says that &quot;this image and data related to the image may be reproduced for non-commercial research and private study purposes&quot;, which doesn't marry up with the licensing above it, which allows for any potential use (if you click &quot;expand&quot; on the metadata button near the bottom the details will come up). Although the licensing on the Commons looks correct, this default metadata could cause problems for users in the future, particularly since the image has a secure invisible digital watermark. Is there any possibility of uploading a replacement image with the licensing updated to reflect the donation to the Commons? [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 10:40, 9 April 2015 (UTC)

::Thanks {{ping|Hchc2009}} We hadn't thought of the Metadata. The copyright tag is old and actually goes against our latest policy on open access. I have fixed this by basically removing the Exif metadata, of which their was little besides the copyright tag. It's not ideal, but I hope it will suffice for now. We will be looking at changing these tags across our collections in the coming months and years. [[User:Jason.nlw|Jason.nlw]] ([[User talk:Jason.nlw|talk]]) 12:18, 9 April 2015 (UTC)
:::Cheers! [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 16:12, 9 April 2015 (UTC)

===Chapel stained glass===
We've got repetition on this in both the Reconstruction section and the Other rooms section.  I think I'd leave it in Other rooms and have the Reconstruction section read &quot;An oratory that had originally been built onto the Well Tower was removed before 1891.In other respects the completed castle was left unaltered.[49]&quot;. [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 18:14, 22 March 2015 (UTC)
:We probably need to mention their purchase in 2011 though as part of the history section, as its a notable recent event, which means we need some reference to their existence before then for the event to make sense... [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 18:20, 22 March 2015 (UTC)
::In fact, we've the same story three times - it's also in 20-21st century section. I'll have a look at re-wording. [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 18:26, 22 March 2015 (UTC)

===Terry Measham===
Does anyone have a copy of Measham to hand? The records for it suggest that it was aimed at children (a &quot;juvenile audience&quot;) and I was wondering if it was really a high-quality source or not? I'd be concerned if it was a book for youngsters, but the record might not be accurate! [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 18:23, 22 March 2015 (UTC)
:Looking at it now.  Definitely not a childrens' book.  Measham was an assistant Keeper at the Tate and it's not written for children - way too much text. [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 18:28, 22 March 2015 (UTC)
::Cheers! [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 18:46, 22 March 2015 (UTC)

===Quick thoughts===
A couple of things we probably need to work out (minor ones) before the article goes to peer review etc.:
* &quot;the Marquess&quot; or &quot;the marquess&quot;, as used as an alternative to Bute's name?
:'''M'''arquess, as it's Bute. 
* &quot;the Gatehouse&quot; or &quot;the gatehouse&quot;? Most of the sources (but not all) prefer &quot;the Hall Block&quot; etc., and I think &quot;the Gatehouse&quot; might also be preferred.
:after my furniture capitalization issues at the Tower House, I'd go for the Gatehouse.
* Metrics (x ft, y m etc.) - any preference for imperial or metric first? (either is acceptable, but we should be consistent) [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 19:17, 23 March 2015 (UTC)
:Sorry, not a clue.
:No expert on MoS but my suggestions above. [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 08:25, 24 March 2015 (UTC)
::Marquess done; I've updated the modern references to the Gatehouse accordingly as well. 17:39, 24 March 2015 (UTC)

===Model for Lady B's Bedroom===
Have de-emphasized Burges's involvement in the actual decoration.  Matthew Williams's article on the model in ''Architectural History'' (2003) says the model &quot;was made to show the intended structure, and may well have been left undecorated for some years. The decoration of (the) bedroom was not undertaken until 1887 and stylistically owes little to (Burges).&quot;  So he can't be held responsible for &quot;The Palace of the Saracen Princess&quot;!  It would be good to quote the article but I don't know how we cite it, as it's behind the JSTOR wall.  [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 06:20, 25 March 2015 (UTC)
:Have put in in, minus url.  [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 06:32, 25 March 2015 (UTC)
::I've got a copy, will work through it in a moment. [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 17:39, 25 March 2015 (UTC)

===A house for occasional occupation in the summer===

I'm wondering about the use of the term &quot;summer house&quot;.  Does it conjure up an image something like this [http://www.homebase.co.uk/en/homebaseuk/garden/garden-buildings-and-conservatories/summer-houses-and-log-cabins]?  What about if we give the full quote first time round?
:On a related point - I'm not seeing much else that needs doing/adding.  Is it nearly ready for peer review?  [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 06:16, 26 March 2015 (UTC)
::My image of a [[summer house]] is a bit broader, and I'm keen that we try to avoid too many quotes, as it is quite a &quot;quote heavy&quot; piece already, but happy to go with any consensus. Perhaps we can link it? I agree - I think it mostly just needs tidying up now - almost there! [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 07:05, 26 March 2015 (UTC)

===Burges's death===

Williams is specific, but Crook (p341) says Cardiff.  Could this be interpreted broadly as the Cardiff area?  Is it likely that, when in South Wales, at a point when he was working on both buildings, he'd have visited both?  Probably.  Not sure about wording.  [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 06:26, 27 March 2015 (UTC)
:He'd definitely have visited Cardiff in order to get a carriage up to Castell, both because of the transport links of the periods and, as you say, because he had ongoing projects in both locations. Indeed, some would consider Tongwynlais to be just on the outskirts of Cardiff, so I also buy the &quot;broad&quot; interpretation of the phrase &quot;Cardiff&quot; by Crook. [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 08:08, 27 March 2015 (UTC)

===Protocol for naming people===

I've been taking a quick look at the way we describe people in the article (e.g. &quot;the historian John Smith&quot;, &quot;John Smith&quot;, or just &quot;Smith&quot;). I'm going to suggest that to ensure consistency, we introduce with a full name when first used at the section level (e.g. &quot;History&quot;, &quot;Architecture&quot; sections) and thereafter in the section just use the surname. That means that we would introduce again if they reappear in a later section, which would be helpful for the reader flicking through it. What do you reckon? [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 13:03, 27 March 2015 (UTC)
:Sounds very sensible and helpful.  You ok to do it or do you want me to have a go?  [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 17:03, 28 March 2015 (UTC)

===bretache===

Do we need a note explaining this?  I can find only one other use on Wikipedia, at [[Threave Castle]] and it's at least as obscure as &quot;tourelle&quot;.  I'll try and put one in.  [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 14:22, 7 April 2015 (UTC)
:I learn that a bretache is also the noseguard on the helmet of a suit of armour.  Should we explain this, or is it clear that the note refers to a bretache '''''in this context'''''.  [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 15:35, 7 April 2015 (UTC)
::I think the note is probably clear enough; I don't think that it is likely to be confused with the noseguard! ;) [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 15:42, 7 April 2015 (UTC)
:::I think you're right, but I wanted my first footnote to be irreproachable! [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 16:54, 7 April 2015 (UTC)

: They're not obscure in Europe, just unknown as survivors in the UK and only rarely recreated (the two best known are both Bute's). See [[hoarding (castle)]] or maybe  [[brattice]] for our best hopes at a link. [[User:Andy Dingley|Andy Dingley]] ([[User talk:Andy Dingley|talk]]) 17:07, 7 April 2015 (UTC)
::I think [[hoarding (castle)]] works very well and will add.  What's the other Bute one you're thinking of?  The, now-disappeared, Cardiff Castle one, or another?  I have a great pair of photos of Cardiff, one showing the bretache on the walls and the other showing the, now equally-defunct, Swiss Bridge. [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 18:12, 7 April 2015 (UTC)
::: Cardiff Castle.  Even today there's a quantity of hoarding left (although not projecting outwards) that's more than almost any other UK castle. [[User:Andy Dingley|Andy Dingley]] ([[User talk:Andy Dingley|talk]]) 19:52, 7 April 2015 (UTC)

===Architecture and landscape===
Split the sections as thought Architecture was self-standing.  Others may disagree. [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 18:36, 9 April 2015 (UTC)

===Tripadvisor===
I love Tripadvisor reviews.  This one, of Cardiff, is particularly good:
:&quot;..the Earl of Bute's lodgings, which in a burst of high camp Victorian hysteria he had done up as Arabian fantasy chambers in the style of Walt Disney.&quot; [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 06:34, 10 April 2015 (UTC)

===[[Murder holes]] and other defences===
{{reply to|User:Hchc2009}} Out of interest, why was Burges probably mistaken as to the use of [[Murder holes]]?  While he surely constructed  them for fun, Girouard describes their &quot;gleeful&quot; insertion, how was he wrong as to their original use?  On a related point, I find that [[Bretèche]] is described on Wikipedia, but with this French spelling.  Would it be better to use that, and its link?  [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 07:45, 10 April 2015 (UTC)
:The late Victorians believed that murder holes were routinely used in medieval warfare to drop boiling water and oil on incoming attackers, which is where Burges drew his opinion, which was therefore accurate by the standards of the day. Modern historical opinion is inclined to be much more cautious about this; there are occasional comments by chroniclers, but only a few, and it seems more likely that murder holes were used to dispense arrows, rocks etc. [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 10:31, 11 April 2015 (UTC)

===&quot;Why should I hurry over what is my chief pleasure? I have comparatively little pleasure in a thing after it is finished.&quot;===

I know the article is already quote-heavy, but I wonder if there is space for the above?  I think it very well encapsulates why the castle was really little used, by Bute or afterwards.  [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 09:28, 10 April 2015 (UTC)
:To be honest, in my opinion I think there already enough quotes... [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 10:24, 11 April 2015 (UTC)

== Ready for peer review...? ==


I've got the references to names consistent now I think and done a final check for duplicate links etc. {{ping|KJP1}} and {{ping|Dr. Blofeld}} - does any further work look necessary from your perspectives, or do you reckon it is good to take to review? [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 16:39, 28 March 2015 (UTC)

I'll try to see if you've missed anything later. I added a fair bit earlier but you've developed it so quickly I got caught behind!♦ [[User:Dr. Blofeld|&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;color:#aba67e&quot;&gt;''Dr. Blofeld''&lt;/span&gt;]] 16:56, 28 March 2015 (UTC)

:Oh, I see you've done it.  No - it all looks good to go for me.  A splendid piece of work. [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 17:05, 28 March 2015 (UTC)
::Looking again, the big things missing are a couple of decent photos of the Drawing Room and Lady B's Bedroom.  As the &quot;crowning glories&quot; of the castle, it's a real pity there's nothing better. Like this [http://education.gtj.org.uk/storage/Components/305/30548_2.JPG] and [http://cadw.wales.gov.uk/fma/5253694/5254166/conservationatcadwsites/concadwcastellcoch.jpg] [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 17:11, 28 March 2015 (UTC)
:::Or this [http://www.pbase.com/moorlands/image/141774104] and this [http://www.pbase.com/moorlands/image/141580258].  [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 17:13, 28 March 2015 (UTC)
::::Dr., you're only round the corner - get up there!  [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 17:15, 28 March 2015 (UTC)
:::::I may be able to get over there in the next week or so, but it would depend on the light being good! [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 17:16, 28 March 2015 (UTC)
::::::NB: the Cadw photograph you've linked is freely available for use under the OGL license, btw, which is suitable for use on the Commons... (see http://cadw.wales.gov.uk/copyright/?lang=en for details of the OGL release). [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 17:17, 28 March 2015 (UTC)
::::::::Yes it's looking very impressive already. Perhaps myself and {{u|We hope}} can find more info from various news sources before it hits PR. No immediate rush though.♦ [[User:Dr. Blofeld|&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;color:#aba67e&quot;&gt;''Dr. Blofeld''&lt;/span&gt;]] 22:42, 28 March 2015 (UTC)
Are folks happy if I add the PR notice onto this under our collective names? [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 07:48, 2 April 2015 (UTC)
:I'm fine.  [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 10:04, 2 April 2015 (UTC)
::Can you wait a few days Hc, I still want to see if I can find anything further on this.♦ [[User:Dr. Blofeld|&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;color:#aba67e&quot;&gt;''Dr. Blofeld''&lt;/span&gt;]] 14:21, 2 April 2015 (UTC)
:::No problem, will do. [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 15:51, 2 April 2015 (UTC)
::::NB: I went over this morning and took some pictures, taking advantage of the spring sunshine. Very nice it was too. I've uploaded a few of them, and will try to get some more of the furniture up on the Commons in the next few days. [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 18:59, 6 April 2015 (UTC)
:::::Excellent!  It's years since I've been - I really must get back sometime.  Very much looking forward to seeing the photos.  Should have plenty of time for the Peer Review - just waiting on the Tower House's FAC, which seems to be stalled for some reason.  Plenty of support, no outstanding comments to address but it isn't moving.  [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 20:22, 6 April 2015 (UTC)
::::::Well done HC! I'm working on this now. [[:File:Castell Coch - Banqueting Room.JPG]] upload data says November 2001?? ♦ [[User:Dr. Blofeld|&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;color:#aba67e&quot;&gt;''Dr. Blofeld''&lt;/span&gt;]] 12:03, 7 April 2015 (UTC)

I think it's ready for PR now. I've looked through about 15 pages of google books and my news sources and think it's pretty comprehensive. Not sure if KJP wants to add anything first.♦ [[User:Dr. Blofeld|&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;color:#aba67e&quot;&gt;''Dr. Blofeld''&lt;/span&gt;]] 17:02, 7 April 2015 (UTC)

BTW Hc, I'm not sure why you removed the reference to it being 6.5 miles north of Cardiff. In many building articles we actually have a small section on location. I think it's important for readers to get an idea. At least there's mention of it in the body though, that's OK.♦ [[User:Dr. Blofeld|&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;color:#aba67e&quot;&gt;''Dr. Blofeld''&lt;/span&gt;]] 17:05, 7 April 2015 (UTC)

::No - I'm just messing around - I think it's good to go for PR.  One thought - I very much like the quote box from WB's report.  Would his other major quote, in the Exterior Section - look better in such a box?  I tried it but couldn't centralize it, which it needs to be as it flows in the text.  But maybe MOS says no?  I shall leave it to others to decide.  One other thing, whilst I'm here.  Dr. B. you suggested it could go straight from PR to FAC?  I think that's a good plan - is that what is intended?  And one last thing, where's the bloody Gold Star on the Tower House?  [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 17:18, 7 April 2015 (UTC)

::Agreed and done. Server takes a while to update with featured star!♦ [[User:Dr. Blofeld|&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;color:#aba67e&quot;&gt;''Dr. Blofeld''&lt;/span&gt;]] 17:28, 7 April 2015 (UTC)

:::I think that looks much better, and hope [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] likes it.  But should it say &quot;conical roofs&quot; in the plural?  [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 17:35, 7 April 2015 (UTC)

Peer review now open. HC, how much work do you reckon is needed for Cardiff Castle? I think we can get that up to FA status too, but let's get Castell Coch there first.♦ [[User:Dr. Blofeld|&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;color:#aba67e&quot;&gt;''Dr. Blofeld''&lt;/span&gt;]] 19:18, 7 April 2015 (UTC)
:I think Cardiff was in a reasonable state at GA; the prose could no doubt do with sharpening, and I'd be interested to work through the Commission's material on it again, but I don't think it's a huge leap. Definitely let's get Castell sorted first though! [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 19:28, 7 April 2015 (UTC)

===Ghosts===
{{u|Hchc2009}} I've encountered an article in the South Wales Echo mentioning ghosts in Castell Coch and Cardiff Castle. For Castell is says &quot; At Castell Coch it's all about the so-called White Lady who died a broken heart after her son drowned in a local pond. Some say there's a buried hoard of treasure here which is zealously protected by three eagles, while an ethereal cavalier walks the castle grounds.&quot; Cardiff Castle mention says &quot; There are quite a few spooky goings on at CardiffCastle. A coach is said to be heard when a member of the Hastings family is due to die. At the castle ¦it was heard by John Boyle, the night his cousin the Marquis Hastings died. Other ghosts reporteded to haunt the castle include the second Marques of Bute (who walks through several walls - apparently!), a faceless woman in a long skirt who is known as Sarah, and a 3m tall giant who walks around the park. This pictures was taken outside CardiffCastle around 1904. &quot; Would you accept mentioning it or shall we not bother? I'm not sure the Echo is an expert on ghosts! ♦ [[User:Dr. Blofeld|&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;color:#aba67e&quot;&gt;''Dr. Blofeld''&lt;/span&gt;]] 16:14, 8 April 2015 (UTC)

:I'm not sure I'd class the Echo as an expert on folklore either...(!) I'll keep an eye out, but it hasn't come up in the better sources so far. [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 16:34, 8 April 2015 (UTC)

I'm not sure anybody has a degree in Welsh ghosts! Perhaps {{u|Martinevans123}} has one.♦ [[User:Dr. Blofeld|&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;color:#aba67e&quot;&gt;''Dr. Blofeld''&lt;/span&gt;]] 16:38, 8 April 2015 (UTC)
::&lt;small&gt;Yes, I did. But it turned out to be a [[Degrees-R-Us|phantom]]. [[User:Martinevans123|Martinevans123]] ([[User talk:Martinevans123|talk]]) 17:16, 8 April 2015 (UTC) &lt;/small&gt;
:In all seriousness, I bet someone has done at least some post-grad work on it... there's some good research going on out there on medieval, early modern and modern approaches to folklore etc. I haven't read it, but &quot;Welsh Gothic&quot;, published in 2013, looks good for example. [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 16:44, 8 April 2015 (UTC)
:: What I've read so far on supernatural South Wales has been utter crap. It's not a subject I take an interest in, although I have a few friends who take it very seriously. The trouble is that when you look at the details of the published works, lots of it just doesn't hang together. Gross geographical errors, anachronisms, just a plain lack of on the ground research. My favourite was the ghost haunting the Old Ferry Inn, Beachley, the ghost of the chap who was burned to death in the pier fire. Except that the pier fire was of the high wooden pier at Black Rock, Portskewett, not the low stone slipway at Beachley.
:: If you want to talk seriously about this sort of thing though, try the Arthur Machen society. Gwilym Games (a librarian in Swansea) there seems to be one of the more knowledgeable people. [[User:Andy Dingley|Andy Dingley]] ([[User talk:Andy Dingley|talk]]) 17:08, 8 April 2015 (UTC)
:::The Dr. knows my prejudices here, from an earlier discussion on [[Bramshill House]], and our issues with [[Richard Harris]]'s, no-doubt drunken, ravings about spectral occupants of [[The Tower House]] nurseries.  No &lt;s&gt;hoard&lt;/s&gt; ghosts! [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 06:02, 10 April 2015 (UTC)
::::Not that I'd want to encourage the Dr., but the Marquess was a noted spiritualist himself [http://www.gutenberg.org/files/30823/30823.txt]. [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 09:40, 10 April 2015 (UTC)

== CE ==

Did a drive-by edit which turned out not to be as quick as I expected; what a thorough treatment, thanks all. [[User:Keith-264|Keith-264]] ([[User talk:Keith-264|talk]]) 11:51, 29 March 2015 (UTC)
:..and thanks for the copy-edit Keith! [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 07:47, 2 April 2015 (UTC)
:: I'm dubious about the [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Castell_Coch&amp;diff=next&amp;oldid=655358014 newly introduced] idea of the original castle as &quot;controlling Cardiff&quot; (a one horse town, without even the horse at that time, and with a pre-existing motte &amp; bailey) rather than controlling access to the Taff valley.
:: Also should we state that the castle &quot;occupies a stretch of woodland&quot; without qualifying it that the woodland was only planted after the castle was rebuilt? [[User:Andy Dingley|Andy Dingley]] ([[User talk:Andy Dingley|talk]]) 17:20, 7 April 2015 (UTC)
:::Not competent to comment on the first issue, so will leave to others.  On the second point, interestingly, Newman speculates on this very issue; &quot;Did Burges intend the bases of the drum towers to be visible from far off, or did he envisage the castle rising out of treetops as it does today?&quot;  I'll have a look at the wording.  [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 17:27, 7 April 2015 (UTC):
::::One other, tree-related point: the lede says; &quot;Bute reintroduced commercial viticulture into Britain just below the castle and wine production continued...&quot;  Should it say; Bute reintroduced commercial viticulture into Britain, '''planting a vineyard''' just below the castle and wine production continued ....&quot;?  [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 17:32, 7 April 2015 (UTC)
::::Much of the woodland was definitely here before the castle was renovated (you can see the trees in the photographs from the renovation, and its mentioned in one of the sources as having grown up in the early 19th century I think). On the viticulture, I think you're right KJP1. On Cardiff, the cited verb is &quot;protect&quot;, I've changed accordingly. [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 17:38, 7 April 2015 (UTC)
:::::Done the vineyard - so I think we're good for PR [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]].  [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 17:47, 7 April 2015 (UTC)
:: The town of Cardiff may not have been big enough to be worth protecting, but as it was presumably a port it may have been strategically significant. [[User:Verbcatcher|Verbcatcher]] ([[User talk:Verbcatcher|talk]]) 23:33, 15 April 2015 (UTC)

==Listed building status in infobox==
With some hesitation(!), I wonder whether the building's listed status, and the designation date, should appear in the infobox?  It's the kind of fact that could usefully appear there.  What do others think?  I have actually tried to put it in but can't make it work.  [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 18:31, 16 April 2015 (UTC)

It should appear either in the infobox or lede yup. I've asked {{u|Friejtes}} to look at the infobox.♦ [[User:Dr. Blofeld|&lt;span style=&quot;font-variant:small-caps;color:#aba67e&quot;&gt;''Dr. Blofeld''&lt;/span&gt;]] 19:34, 16 April 2015 (UTC)

:I think it belongs better in the infobox; the building's legal status isn't prominent in the literature, and I don't think it belongs in the lead for that reason. [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 19:39, 16 April 2015 (UTC)

::Fine - shall we go for the infobox if [[user|Friejtes]] can do what my techincal powers cannot.  [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 20:11, 16 April 2015 (UTC)
:::Ah, I see he's done it already.  [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 20:12, 16 April 2015 (UTC)

:This discussion should be treated as a continuation of ''[[Talk:Castell Coch#Where to mention Listed Building status?|Where to mention Listed Building status?]]'' above. I support including the listed building status in the infobox, but what is the point of giving the date of listed building designation. Who is this for? [[User:Verbcatcher|Verbcatcher]] ([[User talk:Verbcatcher|talk]]) 21:50, 16 April 2015 (UTC)
::I agree it is best to see this as a continuation of the earlier discussion.  I think this leads us to consensus that its listing sits best in the infobox.  As to the designation date, I personally think it '''is''' helpful; firstly, as a simple fact, secondly, as an indication of when the building's national importance was officially recognized and when it was afforded the legal protections that listed building status gives.  It also has some historic interest as a indication of changing tastes.  In the case of Coch, its listing in 1963 came quite late, 18 years before Burges's &quot;rehabilitation&quot; with the centenary exhibitions at Cardiff and the V&amp;A in 1981. For much of the twentieth century, like most of Burges's work, the Castle would generally have been viewed as a ridiculous sham.  In this regard, the much earlier listing date for [[The Tower House]] is interesting.  That said, it is not a deal-breaker for me, and if the consensus is to drop the date, I've very happy that we do so. [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 06:21, 17 April 2015 (UTC)
:::I'm with Verbcatcher on this one; I'd find it hard to imagine someone flicking through the article, looking at the infobox for the key bits of information, and expecting/needing to find the precise date of the listing. But, like KJP, it's not a dealbreaker for me! [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 06:35, 17 April 2015 (UTC)

:::KJP1's discussion of changing attitudes to Victorian architecture and design is interesting, and merits a place in this article if a suitable citation can be found, or in another article such as [[Victorian architecture]]. Without this context the listing date is unhelpful. Wikipedia should not include data without context (see [[WP:RAWDATA]]). [[User:Verbcatcher|Verbcatcher]] ([[User talk:Verbcatcher|talk]]) 14:54, 17 April 2015 (UTC)
::::I agree with that comment. [[User:Hchc2009|Hchc2009]] ([[User talk:Hchc2009|talk]]) 15:55, 17 April 2015 (UTC)
:::::I would argue that the context for the date of the designation is provided by the fact of the designation itself. The decision was taken to list the building as Grade I and that decision was taken in 1963.  But life's too short.  [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 17:18, 17 April 2015 (UTC)

I expected to see the listing date, which is clearly rather late, and I added it in the context of the architectural reappraisal in the 1950s and 1960s.  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/213.205.251.26|213.205.251.26]] ([[User talk:213.205.251.26|talk]]) 07:07, 13 August 2015 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== TFAR ==

[[Wikipedia:Today's featured article/requests/Castell Coch]] --[[User:Gerda Arendt|Gerda Arendt]] ([[User talk:Gerda Arendt|talk]]) 13:51, 27 July 2015 (UTC)

==''Arabian Knights''==
Super minor point, but is there a reason it's called ''Arabian Knights'' instead of ''Arabian Nights''? [[User:Brutannica|Brutannica]] ([[User talk:Brutannica|talk]]) 16:28, 15 August 2015 (UTC)
:Not minor at all.  Shocking error on my part, now corrected.  [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 20:28, 16 August 2015 (UTC) 
::Actually, on checking, I see it was a bit of unresolved vandalism.  Thanks for picking it up.  [[User:KJP1|KJP1]] ([[User talk:KJP1|talk]]) 20:36, 16 August 2015 (UTC)

== New images available ==

Hello everyone, I just noticed that [[:Commons:Category:Images by Nilfanion/Cardiff|this category on Commons]] has 90 new images of Castell Coch. There are some interesting ones, with nice photos of the courtyard and parts of the interior. [[User:Richard Nevell (WMUK)|Richard Nevell (WMUK)]] ([[User talk:Richard Nevell (WMUK)|talk]]) 12:31, 18 May 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>9mxh3pppz2x815xnbajj59qsd7r3vyt</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
