<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:George S. Patton</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>676428</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749758182</id>
      <parentid>749216453</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-16T01:08:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lowercase sigmabot III</username>
        <id>17518500</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Archiving 2 discussion(s) to [[Talk:George S. Patton/Archive 3]]) (bot</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12335">
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{talkarchivenav|noredlinks=y}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 3
|minthreadsleft = 4
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:George S. Patton/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{Talk header|noarchive=yes}}
{{ArticleHistory
|maindate= 11 November 2016
|action1=GAN
|action1date=20:25, 19 January 2013
|action1link=Talk:George S. Patton/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=533894513
|action2=WAR
|action2date=08:55, 3 March 2013
|action2link=Wikipedia:WikiProject_Military_history/Assessment/George_S._Patton
|action2result=approved
|action2oldid=541622782

|action3=FAC
|action3date=10:02, 08 September 2013
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/George S. Patton/archive1
|action3result=promoted
|action3oldid=572033975
|currentstatus=FA
|topic=war
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Biography|living=no|class=FA|military-work-group=yes|military-priority=top|listas=Patton, George S.}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=FA|A-Class=pass|B1=yes|B2=yes|B3=yes|B4=yes|B5=yes|Biography=yes|US=yes|WWII=yes}}
{{WikiProject Homeschooling|class=FA|importance=Low}}
{{WikiProject California|class=FA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Olympics|class=FA|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Pritzker-GLAM|class=FA|importance=mid}}
}}
{{archives |auto=long |search=yes |bot=MiszaBot I |age=3 |units=months|index=/Archive index}}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn
|target=/Archive index
|mask=/Archive &lt;#&gt;
|leading_zeros=0
|indexhere=yes}}

== Assassination? ==

Recently, evidence has arisen to suggest that Patton may have been assassinated by the NKVD in collaboration with the US Secret Service. It has been claimed that Patton was going to expose mistakes made by Dwight D. Eisenhower which led to the deaths of thousands of American troops. The allegations were made in Robert Wilcox's 1999 book Target Patton on the basis of testimony from ex-marksman Douglas Bazata, who is said to have orchestrated the car crash. It is alleged that, during the crash, Patton was hit by a projectile in the neck, which would explain the extent of his injuries compared to the others in the car. It has also been shown that the car shown on display in the Patton Museum was not the car driven on the day of Patton's accident, which has led Wilcox to believe that a Government cover-up took place to disguise the intent behind Patton's death. When the accident did not kill Patton, it is said that he was poisoned by NKVD officials.

source: http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/northamerica/usa/3869117/General-George-S.-Patton-was-assassinated-to-silence-his-criticism-of-allied-war-leaders-claims-new-book.html

seems like something which definitely ought to be mentioned. [[User:Hommedeterre1|Hommedeterre1]] ([[User talk:Hommedeterre1|talk]]) 15:05, 24 March 2016 (UTC)

:Your attempt is possibly tainted by the stupid (imho) book ''Killing Patton'' that came out earlier. At any rate, the subject doesn't seem to have any traction in mainstream media. I think a newspaper article about a book which is available on line makes a poor reference.--&lt;span style=&quot;background:#C2C2C2&quot;&gt;[[User:Gaarmyvet|&lt;font color=&quot;red&quot;&gt;'''Jim&amp;nbsp;in&amp;nbsp;Georgia'''&lt;/font&gt; ]][[Special:Contributions/Gaarmyvet|&lt;font color=&quot;white&quot;&gt;''Contribs''&lt;/font&gt; ]][[User Talk:Gaarmyvet|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;'''Talk'''&lt;/font&gt;]] &lt;/span&gt; 16:22, 24 March 2016 (UTC)

::This is not, IMHO, a legitimate use of a newspaper as a source. It's not as if the Telegraph itself is reporting this through investigative journalism, it's just an article about the book. The book itself (again IMHO), is not a reliable source. Multiple, additional, [[WP:RS|reliable sources]], independent of this book, claiming that Patton's accident was actually an assassination stemming from a conspiracy within the highest levels of the military and government, with facts, would be required here. And, a solid [[WP:CONSENSUS|consensus]] for inclusion. -  ''[[User: Thewolfchild|&lt;sup&gt;the&lt;/sup&gt;'''&lt;big&gt;&lt;em style=&quot;font-family:Matisse itc;color:red&quot;&gt;WOLF&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/big&gt;'''&lt;small&gt;child&lt;/small&gt;]]'' 18:47, 24 March 2016 (UTC)

:An argument that Patton was assassinated on the orders of &quot;Wild Bill&quot; Donovan in order to protect Eisenhower's reputation and with assistance from the NKVD is certainly novel... I agree that it shouldn't be included unless it's endorsed by experts on this topic per [[WP:FRINGE]]. The British media has an unfortunate habit of uncritically repeating far-fetched claims about World War II made in new books. [[User:Nick-D|Nick-D]] ([[User talk:Nick-D|talk]]) 22:56, 24 March 2016 (UTC)

::Unfortunately there are few &quot;experts&quot; on the topic of the death of Patton.  Anyone familiar with the long time, close and personal friendship between Eisenhower and Patton, as well as (familiar with) Patton's close professional relationship with Eisenhower, will find it impossible to believe Patton ever had any plans to expose some few perceived errors in judgment on the part of Eisenhower.  Patton was far more intellectual than he is ever given credit, and he realized, and wrote about how any overall successful decision made by a commanding officer during War will come with positive and negative consequences.  Second guessing his U.S. Military superior's was not something Patton would make public.  He did second guess overall political/philosophical themes by people like President Roosevelt, Churchill and Stalin, but that is different.  Wild Bill Donovan had no reason, therefore, to protect Eisenhower in any way from Patton.  Wild Bill Donovan was an alleged double agent working for the British, while officially reporting to Pres. Roosevelt.  Donovan had himself to protect, along with Roosevelt, Churchill and Stalin.  A point that has been (perhaps) obliterated by the Wikipedia process of &quot;reliable sources&quot; is that among U.S. Military people just after Patton's death, as well as for some time thereafter, talk and rumors of a plot to &quot;take care of&quot; Patton were everywhere.  It is well known that Patton saw Stalin's growing power as being a huge mistake allowed by Churchill and Roosevelt.  If anything/anyone  was to be protected from Patton's pen-strokes, it was the naivety of Churchill and Roosevelt, as well as the growing power of Stalin.  Wild Bill Donovan, or someone like him in the counterpart Soviet role, would have everything to gain from the untimely death of Patton.  People like Donovan had Churchill and Roosevelt's interests to protect, while Stalin had his own interests to be protected.  Donovan and/or some Soviet counterpart would be much to smart to leave any trail, or evidence, of any plot against Patton.  People like Donovan had the power, and ability, to make evidence simply disappear.  I find the evidence surrounding the actual crash to be quite an implication of at least a powerful cover up.  The arguments claiming confusion surrounding the actual accident, due to the winding down of the War, etc., are not believable when it is taken into account that General Patton was seriously injured in that accident, and any legitimate and unmolested investigation into such an accident involving such a tremendously important and worshipped &quot;local&quot; hero would have been conducted to a much greater level of professionalism than that which occurred.[[User:Bugatti35racer|Bugatti35racer]] ([[User talk:Bugatti35racer|talk]]) 21:13, 29 April 2016 (UTC)

:Concerning this subject an interesting article was published by Ron Unz ([http://www.unz.com/runz/was-general-patton-assassinated/ see here]) [[User:JRB-Europe|JRB-Europe]] ([[User talk:JRB-Europe|talk]]) 07:20, 22 August 2016 (UTC)
::indeed--the author praised by Unz has now moved well beyond small fry like Patton. The blurb on Amazon states: &quot;''The Truth About the Shroud of Turin'' offers new insight into this baffling mystery and offers compelling evidence that the shroud is the authentic burial shroud of Jesus Christ.&quot; [[User:Rjensen|Rjensen]] ([[User talk:Rjensen|talk]]) 07:37, 22 August 2016 (UTC)

::::It has been said that [[Werwolf]] operatives strung piano wire across the road that Patton's jeep traveled. He subsequently died from neck injury. [[Special:Contributions/173.72.63.96|173.72.63.96]] ([[User talk:173.72.63.96|talk]]) 19:17, 11 November 2016 (UTC)42nd Rainbow Div
:::::Yes but it is also said that US Army doctors sewed his head back on and he lived a few more weeks while plotting the invasion of Russia. [[User:Rjensen|Rjensen]] ([[User talk:Rjensen|talk]]) 19:22, 11 November 2016 (UTC)

== War with USSR ==

What about Patton's plan to invade the Soviet Union in 1945? ([[User:Nsjsksl|Nsjsksl]] ([[User talk:Nsjsksl|talk]]) 19:03, 15 September 2016 (UTC))
:Mentioned his idea of invading USSR in the post-war section. —[[User:Ed!|&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;'''Ed!'''&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Ed!|&lt;font color=&quot;black&quot;&gt;'''(talk)'''&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt; 20:41, 1 November 2016 (UTC)

== denazification ==

The statement in the lead paragraph ''&quot;but he was relieved of this post because of his statements on [[denazification]]&quot;'' is vague &amp; unclear -- what did he actually say? -- and is not explained further in the article.  I don't know that it's significant enough to add more details to this already long article, but just changing that statement to ''&quot;but he was relieved of this post because of his statements trivializing [[denazification]]&quot;'' seems to clarify this.

I considered other words like ''denigrate'' or ''oppose'', but that seems to indicate a more negative attitude than Patton showed.  He just said that it was unimportant; similar to a disagreement between Democrats &amp; Republicans.  I also considered ''depreciate'', but ''trivialize'' seemed a more common term for readers. Anybody have a better term to suggest?
[[User:T-bonham|T-bonham]] ([[User talk:T-bonham|talk]]) 20:45, 12 November 2016 (UTC)

:It is explained further in the article, as required by [[WP:LEAD]]:
{{Boxquote|Patton attracted controversy as military governor when it was noted that several former Nazi Party members continued to hold political posts in the region.[173] When responding to the press about the subject, Patton repeatedly compared Nazis to Democrats and Republicans in noting that most of the people with experience in infrastructure management had been compelled to join the party in the war, causing negative press stateside and angering Eisenhower.[178][179] On September 28, 1945, after a heated exchange with Eisenhower over his statements, Patton was relieved of his military governorship.}}
: [[User:Kendall-K1|Kendall-K1]] ([[User talk:Kendall-K1|talk]]) 22:18, 12 November 2016 (UTC)

== His sense of his ancestry was very important to shaping Patton's outlook ==

As his biographers point out, Patton himself repeatedly emphasized the central importance of his ancestry in defining his character as a warrior. For most people it is indeed a minor factor, but for Patton it's too important to ignore. The section follows the RS.  For example 1) Willard Sterne Randall &amp; ‎Nancy Nahra (2014) state: ''George Smith Patton, Jr., had few doubts, especially about himself. From his boyhood, he never doubted for a moment that he would be a soldier and a leader like so many of his ancestors, and that he would someday be a general and a hero.'' 2) Alden Hatch (2006) calls it ''the modern incarnation of the ancient virtues of his warrior ancestors.''  3) Mostafa Rejai &amp; ‎Kay Phillips (1996) write: ''Even as a boy George Patton had wanted to be a general and lead troops in battle. ... in an atmosphere of adulation for those in the family who had fallen in the War Between the States, with strong overtones of pride in their Virginia ancestry.'' 4) Lawrence R. Spencer (2008) writes: ''Patton was a staunch believer in reincarnation and, along with many other members of his family, often claimed to have seen vivid, lifelike visions of his ancestors.''  5) Michael Keane (2012) writes: ''he was referring to his desire to die in battle, as his ancestors had done.'' 6) Jerome Corsi (2014) says when he was wounded in 1918 ''Patton imagined he saw the faces of his ancestors: Gen. Hugh Mercer, wounded at the battle of Princeton in the Revolutionary War; grandfather Col. George Patton, killed at Winchester in the Civil War'' etc etc [[User:Rjensen|Rjensen]] ([[User talk:Rjensen|talk]]) 03:26, 13 November 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>5q91xavwqexy5cfr8tszxtsm183obz1</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
