<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:John Tyler</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>19732479</id>
    <revision>
      <id>751384207</id>
      <parentid>749992041</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-25T09:05:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lx 121</username>
        <id>6014795</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* lede photo */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14469">{{Talk header}}
{{User:MiszaBot/config
|archiveheader = {{aan}}
|maxarchivesize = 100K
|counter = 2
|minthreadsleft = 5
|minthreadstoarchive = 1
|algo = old(90d)
|archive = Talk:John Tyler/Archive %(counter)d
}}
{{ArticleHistory

|action1=PR
|action1date= 18:04, 16 Sep 2011
|action1link=Wikipedia:Peer review/John Tyler/archive1
|action1result=Not reviewed
|action1oldid=450720009
|action2=GAN
|action2date=04:30, 12 November 2011 (UTC)
|action2link=Talk:John Tyler/GA1
|action2result=listed
|action2oldid=460237135

|action3=FAC
|action3date=20:08, 23 January 2012
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/John Tyler/archive1
|action3result=not promoted
|action3oldid=471064960

|action4=PR
|action4date= 08:51, 18 May 2014
|action4link=Wikipedia:Peer review/John Tyler/archive2
|action4result=Reviewed
|action4oldid=608887616

|action5=FAC
|action5date=08:51, 12 June 2014
|action5link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/John Tyler/archive2
|action5result=promoted
|action5oldid=612511819

|topic=World history
|currentstatus=FA

|maindate=29 March 2015
}}
{{Auto archiving notice |bot=MiszaBot I |age=90  |units=days}}
{{User:HBC Archive Indexerbot/OptIn
|target=Talk:John Tyler/Archive index
|mask=Talk:John Tyler/Archive &lt;#&gt;
|leading_zeros=0 |indexhere=yes}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|collapsed=yes|1=
{{Wikipedia CD selection|importance=Mid|class=FA}}
{{WikiProject Biography
|living=no
|class=FA
|military-priority=low
|military-work-group=yes
|politician-priority=High
|politician-work-group=yes
|listas=Tyler, John}}
{{WikiProject Virginia
| class=FA
| importance=high}}
{{WikiProject U.S. Congress|class=FA|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject United States|class=FA|importance=low|USgovernors=yes|USgovernors-importance=low|USPresidents=yes|USPresidents-importance=Mid|USPE=Yes|USPE-importance=Mid|listas=Tyler, John}}
{{WPMILHIST|class=FA|Biography=yes|US=yes}}
{{Wikipedia CD selection}}
}}

== Capitalization of &quot;President&quot; (or the lack thereof) ==

There is serious inconsistency in this article with regard to the capitalization (or lack thereof) of the word &quot;President&quot;.  This situation also applies where &quot;Vice President&quot; is used.

I think capitalization should be used when referring directly to a title such as &quot;President Tyler&quot;.  All other occurrences of the word &quot;president&quot; should be in lower case.  If I can get [[Wikipedia:Consensus|consensus]] on this suggestion I will make the changes myself.  Any feedback on my suggestion from other editors would be appreciated.

I suggest a 3:5 consensus ratio if I can get 5 different editors to vote on this.--[[User:Michael W. Parker|EditorExtraordinaire]] ([[User talk:Michael W. Parker|talk]]) 23:25, 29 March 2015 (UTC)
:I think I'm OK with what you are saying.--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 01:18, 30 March 2015 (UTC)

:I prefer what you suggested, but note that the current guideline on titles encourages the awkward/inconsistent version. &quot;President of the United States&quot;, for example, is supposed to be capitalized for some reason. I would favor revising that guideline, but go ahead and change this article in the meantime. [[User:Designate|Designate]] ([[User talk:Designate|talk]]) 02:39, 30 March 2015 (UTC)

== Semi-protected edit request on 16 June 2015 ==

{{edit semi-protected|John Tyler|answered=yes}}
&lt;!-- Begin request --&gt;
john TYLER WAS BORN IN 1789
&lt;!-- End request --&gt;
[[User:Sscrowe13|Sscrowe13]] ([[User talk:Sscrowe13|talk]]) 12:20, 16 June 2015 (UTC)

:'''Not done'''.  He was born in 1790, see [https://www.whitehouse.gov/1600/presidents/johntyler here].--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 12:38, 16 June 2015 (UTC)

== Speaker of the Virginia House of Delegates? ==

According to the article, &quot;Tyler successfully sought election to the House of Delegates. He took his seat in 1838 and his peers unanimously elected him Speaker.&quot; If this is so, why is he is not included in the &quot;List of Speakers of the Virginia House of Delegates&quot; Wikipedia article? Was he ever speaker of the Virginia House of Delegates or no?[[Special:Contributions/71.29.48.171|71.29.48.171]] ([[User talk:71.29.48.171|talk]]) 04:23, 28 August 2015 (UTC)
::I don't remember checking that source I'll cut the reference pending a check.--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 07:42, 28 August 2015 (UTC)

== Tyler's family ==
The reference to ''an aristocratic Virginia family'' in the opening section of this article is preposterous and wrong, given the United States has no aristocracy, nor ever has. I would suggest changing it to ''prominent Virginia family'', or something similar.  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/69.124.156.177|69.124.156.177]] ([[User talk:69.124.156.177|talk]]) 14:47, 13 April 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Point taken. [[Aristocracy (class)]] may be used informally to designate &quot;people that a particular social order considered the highest social class of that society&quot; whereas [[Aristocracy]] specifically refers to a form of government. I changed the sentence to read &quot;Tyler, born to an eminent Virginia family, came to national prominence at a time of political upheaval.&quot; [[User:Peaceray|Peaceray]] ([[User talk:Peaceray|talk]]) 18:22, 13 April 2016 (UTC)

== lede photo ==

wikipedia policy:  accurate photographs take precedence over NNPOV artworks.

photo has been in place as lede on the article for years.

also, for the objecting user:  this photo was taken in 1845, WHILE tyler WAS PRESIDENT.

this is what he REALLY looked like.

wikipedia deals with reality.

[[User:Lx 121|Lx 121]] ([[User talk:Lx 121|talk]]) 20:03, 16 November 2016 (UTC)
:The LoC listing, [http://www.loc.gov/pictures/item/96522383/ here] says between 1860 and 1865 but as Tyler died in 1861 that may narrow it down. Thus, fifteen years after he was president, and it does not give the reader any sense of the dynamic man he was as president. If the only free photograph showed him as a baby, would that be superior to a painting? Please read the various discussions.  Remember, you must build consensus for your change, as it is contentious.--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 20:25, 16 November 2016 (UTC)

::the date seems to be in dispute, but we do have other PHOTOGRAPHS to choose from.  it's not a photo of him as a baby, it's a photo of him as a mature, healthy adult male; WHILE he was an active, PUBLIC FIGURE. the rest of your arguement is nnpov. it is NOT our job to &quot;romanticise&quot; the subject, it is to show his physical appearance ACCURATELY.  there is nothing &quot;contentious&quot; here; we've been using a photo as lede for ''YEARS''. AFTER discussing it &amp; reaching agreement.   the &quot;contentious&quot; action was to '''remove''' the longstanding image, &amp; replace it with a painting.   wp favours accuracy over &quot;prettiness&quot;.   a careful comparision of the painting with the photograph'''s''' also &amp; clearly shows just how inaccurate &amp; nnpov the painting really is.  

::people in the 19th century did not have perfect skin, particularly males.  this is history &amp; reality. that is what we do here.

::we don't use heroic paintings for historic/biographical subjects where we have photographs.  we would not even be having this discussion if the subject was someone regarded negatively.  

::[[User:Lx 121|Lx 121]] ([[User talk:Lx 121|talk]]) 20:50, 16 November 2016 (UTC)*

* here is the cite for an 1840s date for the photo. https://books.google.ca/books?id=Gp0fPG7UcXwC&amp;pg=PA114-IA9&amp;redir_esc=y&amp;hl=en#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false &amp; a quick perusal of the sources of several photos suggests that the loc/archive date is arbitrary &amp; inaccurate.  '''especially'''  as it estimates a range including 4 years after the subject has died. AND it gives the same date estimate for photos clearly taken some time apart.  i would tentatively assume that the date is taken from when the ''copy'' was made. [[User:Lx 121|Lx 121]] ([[User talk:Lx 121|talk]]) 20:59, 16 November 2016 (UTC)
::So what precludes it from being taken in 1860?--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 21:08, 16 November 2016 (UTC)
:::same arguement back.  ''but '''also''''': tyler was 50 in 1840, he was 70 in 1860, 71 &amp; change when he died. go with the 1845 date &amp; he is 55.  the man in the photo looks more likely to be an 1840s version of a 55 year old, than an 1860 70 year old.  for one thing, he still has a significant amount of colour in his hair.  for another, the original is a [[daguerreotype]]; which was common in the 1840s &amp; &quot;obsolete&quot; by 1860. 

:::additional point:  it is worth noting that these photographs are ''professional portraits'', not &quot;snapshots&quot;, not &quot;paparazzi&quot;.  the man sat/posed for a hired photographers to take these pictures.  the images were retained &amp; circulated.  presumably the subject was satisfied with the quality of the work. [[User:Lx 121|Lx 121]] ([[User talk:Lx 121|talk]]) 21:21, 16 November 2016 (UTC) 


* here is the commonscat:  https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Category:John_Tyler  basically, we have 2 &quot;source photos&quot; to choose from there.  &lt;s&gt;plus this:  https://www.flickr.com/photos/tonythemisfit/2847524764 &lt;/s&gt;

&amp; the &quot;rule of thumb&quot; would be that, of the photographs we have available for a subject, we use the best likeness. 

[[User:Lx 121|Lx 121]] ([[User talk:Lx 121|talk]]) 21:11, 16 November 2016 (UTC)
::::&lt;s&gt;uploaded the &quot;new&quot; photo-image of tyler to commons, [[File:John_tyler_pic_from_photo.jpg|thumb]] [[User:Lx 121|Lx 121]] ([[User talk:Lx 121|talk]]) 21:45, 16 November 2016 (UTC),&lt;/s&gt;

::::strike that; it's a zoomed in version of an early photo of the npg version of the healy painting, my bad. [[User:Lx 121|Lx 121]] ([[User talk:Lx 121|talk]]) 22:31, 16 November 2016 (UTC)

|
::It was likely taken in 1861 when Tyler was in Washington chairing the peace conference. This is a Brady-Handy photo and he was in New York during Tyler's presidency. Our watchword should be to aid the reader, and will a photo of Tyler in his decrepitude help him than the hale, hearty man we see in the painting?  One shows us an old man, the other the man who was a force in this nation for twenty years.  I think the one that will best aid the reader is the latter.--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 21:23, 16 November 2016 (UTC)

:::brady &amp; co. took lots of photographs of notable individuals, not all of them in nyc.  tyler wasn't immobilised in dc, &amp; by 19th century standards, he hardly looks 71 years old in the full image.  also, tangentially, IF that photo was taken during the conference, that would make it even '''more''' historically noltable.  ''if'' you can prove it.  also, the clothing doesn't really look 1860s to me; &amp; he still has some colour in his hair, but it's natural, not a dye job.

:::&amp; with respect, the other part of your arguement is still nnpov.  the purpose of the lede image is to capture an ''accurate likeness'' of the subject.  [[User:Lx 121|Lx 121]] ([[User talk:Lx 121|talk]]) 21:45, 16 November 2016 (UTC)


:::[[User:Lx 121|Lx 121]] is correct with regards to the photo. The consensus rule about pictures in infoboxes is that whenever available a photo always trumps a painting. That is the general rule that as result has come out of many an edit war about this topic. The dating of the photo is of less significance. -- [[user:fdewaele|fdewaele]], 16 November 2016, 22:27 CET.
::::Those do not trump the discussions on this page, as they are assuredly not policy. By the way, I note a retreat from the claim that this dates from Tyler's presidency.  We're back to why a photo of a man who looks little like he did as president should be included.--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 21:34, 16 November 2016 (UTC)
:::::yes it is both policy &amp; practice; as both '''accuracy''' &amp; '''npov'''. it is also a common standard in for historians:  photographs are more accurate than paintings. &amp; you &quot;note&quot; incorrectly. he was president 1841-45;  a circa 1845 daguerreotype would be a pretty accurate depiction of what he looked like as president. &amp; a careful perusal of the images we have on file suggests that the photo is pretty close to what he looked like @ the time, only with more detailed accuracy, &amp; less &quot;airbrush&quot;.  [[User:Lx 121|Lx 121]] ([[User talk:Lx 121|talk]]) 21:54, 16 November 2016 (UTC)
::::::It is from the Brady-Handy collection.  Brady was in New York in 1845. I would suggest the Library of Congress is the best authority on its own collection. And from what I can see from other photographs the 1860-65 dating is pretty common for Civil War era photographs.--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]])
::::::::yes, but he ''died'' in january 1862.  are you suggesting that the photograph was taken ''AFTER'' he died?  because otherwise the date-estimate is pretty sloppy &amp; inaccurate. [[User:Lx 121|Lx 121]] ([[User talk:Lx 121|talk]]) 09:05, 25 November 2016 (UTC)
:::::::[[User:Lx 121|Lx 121]], please link to the policy you say favors photos over paintings. Please note that the bio of a POTUS should have a likeness of him ''while in office.'' That's not a policy, afaik, but common sense generally adhered to. Thanks, [[User:Yopienso|YoPienso]] ([[User talk:Yopienso|talk]]) 06:55, 17 November 2016 (UTC)

as i have told you before, repeatedly, it falls under both wp:accuracy &amp; wp:npov.  i have explained the reasons why before &amp; above as well.

your &quot;afaik&quot; is an ''opinion'', neither policy nor guideline; &amp; in this case it '''fails to support your arguement'''.  for at least 2 reasons:

1. the painting you are advocating was created AFTER he died.

2. the daguerreotype may have been created WHILE he was president.

&amp; here is a third reason: IF no photograph exists of the person taken while they served as president, a photograph ''STILL'' beat an interpretive artwork, for both accuracy &amp; npov.

&amp; established policy &amp; practices BOTH favour use of photographs, whwn available, over non-photographic portraits on ALL bio-articles. there is nothing &quot;special&quot; about us presidents that changes that; see &quot;nnpov&quot; for that.

AND we discussed ALL of this, THOROUGHLY, ''on this article'', a couple of years ago; we settled on using a photograph.  nothing has changed with regards to the subject of the article, to alter that consensus.

cheers

[[User:Lx 121|Lx 121]] ([[User talk:Lx 121|talk]]) 09:05, 25 November 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>civ0lcpxogb1rmd86aj4yy11qk5qkcl</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
