<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Canoe River train crash</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>32044137</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750874155</id>
      <parentid>524271057</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-22T00:02:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Adding/updating {{OnThisDay}} for 2016-11-21.  Errors? [[User:AnomieBOT/shutoff/OnThisDayTagger]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22271">{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=16:06, 1 July 2011 (UTC)
|action1link=Talk:Canoe River train crash/GA1
|action1result=Listed
|action1oldid=436675454

|action2=PR
|action2date=12:28, 11 July 2011
|action2link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Canoe River train crash/archive1
|action2result=reviewed
|action2oldid=438899351

|action3=FAC
|action3date=16:50, 21 July 2011
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Canoe River train crash/archive1
|action3result=promoted
|action3oldid=440677190

| topic         = Transport
| dykdate       = 20 June 2011
| dykentry      = ... that when railway telegrapher Alfred Atherton was accused of manslaughter for his role in the '''[[Canoe River train crash]]''', he hired his [[Member of Parliament (Canada)|MP]], [[John Diefenbaker]] as defence counsel, who won an acquittal?
|currentstatus=FA
|maindate=November 21, 2011
|four=yes
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Canada|class=FA|importance=low|geography=yes|bc=yes}}
{{WikiProject Trains|class=FA|importance=low|operations=yes|portalSAweek=28, 2011}}
{{WPMILHIST|class=FA|Korean=yes|Canadian-task-force= yes}}
}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2012-11-21|oldid1=524218992|date2=2016-11-21|oldid2=750749299}}

== Couple more thoughts ==

Couple more thoughts, branching off from the FAC comments:
*Number of injuries is in the infobox but not the main body of the article or the lead. Should probably be added somewhere, as this will also need sourcing (the sources I have looked at give different numbers for the injured).
*Several source mention a poem (inscribed on some of the memorials). It would be nice to know more about this poem and have it mentioned in the article, including when it was composed and first published (which I've been unable to ascertain).
*Was reading [http://www.orwelltoday.com/foxkorea.shtml this] and if you can get past the formatting, there are some interesting bits there. Mostly not relevant, but I thought the mention that Mount Diefenbaker is not far from the crash site was interesting. It also has a copy of the poem I mentioned above.
*I got from there to [http://www.railways.incanada.net/Circle_Articles/Article_Meldrum06.html here], which doesn't add anything new, but it did lead to [http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=MvpRtwAACAAJ Korea: Canada's Forgotten War]. That is a link to the revised edition in 2011. The earlier edition has references to this crash, so it might be useful.
*It is worth making clearer why there were only injuries on the Continental train - was it not because that had steel passenger coaches, rather than the wooden ones used on the troop train? You do say &quot;eleven all-steel cars&quot; earlier, but repeating this at the point where talk about the damage and injuries to the eastbound train might make it clearer.
*I just read the bit in the [http://www.archive.org/stream/canadiannurse101952cana/CnVol.48No10Oct1952_djvu.txt nursing journal] (for others reading this, search for &quot;canoe river&quot;). That's an amazing part of the story, and a very readable account. I hope some of the readers of this article end up reading that.
*In the memorials and tributes section, the RCHA acronym is not immediately obvious as it is not used previously in the main text. It is a pity there are no more details about the CNR memorial (e.g. erection or dedication date). Personally, I would add the dates of when the Korea Book of Remembrance was set up, when the Wall of Remembrance was dedicated, and when the Korea Cairn at Winnipeg Brookside Cemetery was dedicated. Dates for all three should be possible.
*I'm tentatively wondering if linking to a list of those killed, including the names of those killed in the train locomotives, would be desirable (I know a list in the article isn't really suitable). Also, maybe it should be made clearer in the article that more detailed information on each soldier is recorded at the Virtual Memorial? ([http://www.veterans.gc.ca/eng/sub.cfm?source=collections/virtualmem/Detail&amp;casualty=80000495 William David Wright] and [http://www.veterans.gc.ca/eng/sub.cfm?source=collections/virtualmem/Detail&amp;casualty=80000351 David Owens]). If you click on the additional information links there, you will probably pick up any additional memorials.
*There is a photo of the Continental locomotive 6004 out there on a webpage somewhere, but I can't find it now. Will add a link here later if manage to locate it again. It seems to have vanished or I'm searching with the wrong keywords. (Update: the photo is [http://yourrailwaypictures.com/CNRsteamengines/CNR_6004_Toronto_%5BSpadina%5D_ON_1943-05-09.jpg here], from [http://yourrailwaypictures.com/CNRsteamengines/ this page] - probably not freely licensed, but I thought it was worth pointing it out).
*Sources seem to differ on the precise spelling of the doctor's name.
*There are some other Canadian Korean War memorials where all 516 soldiers that died (that being the official figure) are commemorated, such as the one [http://www.canadascapital.gc.ca/bins/ncc_web_content_page.asp?cid=16297-24563-24548-69265&amp;lang=1&amp;bhcp=1 here]. Maybe a note saying that the figure of 516 includes these 17 might be warranted, rather than mentioning memorials that don't list them separately (as the Brookside Cemetery one does)?
*Also, if some of the soldiers are to be mentioned individually here (e.g. the gunner that had a lake named after him in Manitoba), then it is worth pointing out here that at least one of them is also mentioned on another 'state' memorial, such as this one [http://www.veterans.gc.ca/content/collections/virtualmem/photoview.cfm?casualty=80000883&amp;photo=73367 here]. I know the line has to be drawn somewhere, but having found that, I wanted to point it out on the talk page at least. I also looked through the records for each of the soldiers here, as the article says that four bodies were not found or not recovered, and all but three were buried or commemorated individually in a cemetery. It is not possible to be certain about this, but again thought it worth pointing out that the Virtual Memorial entries do list burial details where known (though it does also have a fair number of errors).
Those are all the notes I have left over from reading through the article. [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 08:11, 20 July 2011 (UTC) &lt;small&gt;Updated: 06:17, 21 July 2011 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;
:Thanks for your help.  I will work though these gradually as time permits and as more info becomes available (I hope to visit the area of the crash next month, and may find useful things at the Valemount library).--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 13:06, 23 July 2011 (UTC)
::Sounds good. Hope the trip goes well. As far as the number of missing goes, have a look at the report [http://news.google.com/newspapers?id=OSdgAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=7G4NAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=4633,2863777 here]. That is from 24 November (the Friday) and states that a military funeral was held on Thursday for 12 of the dead (three then taken by train to their hometowns, and nine by airplane to more distant locations). Presumably those twelve funerals included soldiers from the 6 bodies that were recovered on Thursday (the crash took place on the Tuesday), with two bodies still missing (a locomotive engineer and a soldier). The two soldiers reported still missing at the end of the article are presumably the other two of the four bodies never found, though that does presume that the number of four bodies never recovered is correct. I'm sure there are other articles around as well that reported on the funerals and recovery efforts. I'll post here if I come across anything more. [[User:Carcharoth|Carcharoth]] ([[User talk:Carcharoth|talk]]) 16:20, 23 July 2011 (UTC)

== Fixed image sizes ==

Is there any specific reason for forcing the image sizes in this article? I can only speak for my self obviously, but the images look disproportionately large on my screen. Doesn't [[WP:IMGSIZE]] dictate to not use forced image sizes? --[[User:Eisfbnore|&lt;font color=&quot;Navy&quot; face= &quot;Times New Roman&quot;&gt;'''''Eisfbnore'''''&lt;/font&gt;]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Eisfbnore|&lt;font color=&quot;#009900&quot;&gt;• ''talk''&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/small&gt; 10:42, 29 August 2011 (UTC)
:I have no strong view on the subject.  Should I change them to &quot;thumb&quot;, then?--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 10:51, 29 August 2011 (UTC)
::Yes, please. Thanks for the article, btw; that was an interesting read. :) --[[User:Eisfbnore|&lt;font color=&quot;Navy&quot; face= &quot;Times New Roman&quot;&gt;'''''Eisfbnore'''''&lt;/font&gt;]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Eisfbnore|&lt;font color=&quot;#009900&quot;&gt;• ''talk''&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/small&gt; 10:53, 29 August 2011 (UTC)
:::Glad you liked it.  I'm still inserting random facts from a research trip to British Columbia into it.--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 11:15, 29 August 2011 (UTC)

== Distances ==

I have obtained a copy of a Canadian National Railways passenger timetable and the distances for places mentioned are:
{| class=wikitable
! Station !! Miles from&lt;br&gt;Montreal
|-
| Jasper || 2395.1
|-
| Red Pass Junction || 2438.9
|-
| Jackman (end of ABS signalling) || 2460.6
|-
| Valemount || 2469.6
|-
| Cedarside || 2473.5
|-
| Canoe River || 2478.4
|-
| Gosnell || 2498.4
|-
| Blue River || 2527.5
|-
| Vancouver || 2924.2
|-
|}
Reference: {{cite book |author=Canadian National Railways |title=Passenger Time Tables: April 28 to October 26, 1957 |page=51. Table 135}}

Hope this helps — [[User:Iain Bell|Iain Bell]] ([[User talk:Iain Bell|talk]]) 10:00, 9 October 2011 (UTC)

:Nice!  Thanks.  It seems to bear out both the distances in the article and also my personal experience from my visit there this summer.  The Canoe River station is long gone.  Cedarside is still there but it is not a public area, I sort of snuck in after hours.  The Valemount station has been moved and it's now the local museum.  I drove by some of the other places, but there was nothing of interest to see.--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 12:09, 9 October 2011 (UTC)
::Does it actually say Gosnall with a a?  I would be surprised if I were screwing up that badly, though I've made some howlers in my time.  I drove past a &quot;Gosnell Road&quot; on my way up Highway 5 to Valemount, but as nothing actually happened there, I did not bother to stop.--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 12:13, 9 October 2011 (UTC)
:::Oops, my error. Should be ‘Gosnell’. I have corrected it in the table above. — [[User:Iain Bell|Iain Bell]] ([[User talk:Iain Bell|talk]]) 14:01, 3 February 2012 (UTC)

== Was the bar exam easy or hard? ==

The part on the bar exam doesn't make much sense. It says the BC bar was notoriously difficult, but then it says it consisted of one simple question. Why was it just one? Did they change it for him or something? --[[User:Awiseman|AW]] ([[User talk:Awiseman|talk]]) 08:03, 24 November 2011 (UTC)
:Yes.  Although we don't have reliable sources that get into the bar examiners' head, I do have one article from the Ottawa ''Citizen'' that notes that Dief was taking the case for free and maybe the examiners shouldn't be charging him so much money (that would be maybe $20,000 today).  I can't put it in the article because it is speculation, but they caved.  Dief was not yet a national figure, but he was well-known in the West and in Ottawa and if they had failed a ''very'' prominent lawyer from another province, after taking his money (and him freshly widowered) it would have looked bad.  So to speak, they gave him a pass.--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 09:16, 24 November 2011 (UTC)
::Hm, interesting, thanks. Maybe yu could put it in with the speculation, like &quot;The Ottawa Citizen speculated that...&quot; --[[User:Awiseman|AW]] ([[User talk:Awiseman|talk]]) 19:37, 27 November 2011 (UTC)
:::I'm reluctant.  The ''Citizen'' didn't do any speculating, I guess that's me!  I don't want to imply possibly false causes and effect.--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 19:41, 27 November 2011 (UTC)

== picture layout ==

Very important that pictures are relevant to the sections.  they are not just &quot;eye candy&quot; to place in the golden text...but really are very powerful methods of communication.  That is why AP pays money for stringers to take pics of Green Helmet man and the like.

Anyhow, let me just see what the article looks like with the newspaper up top.  The crash map with the crash section.  The siding thing with the inquiry.  (MUCH better fits for those last two).  And the train, I guess under rescue (no good home for it).

The Infobox gone (we could keep it, also, but really not helpful, this is not an &quot;almanac&quot; type of topic).

And getting rid of the L-R alternation (so 2007).

Feel free to revert after.  Just want to see what it looks like.

[[Special:Contributions/64.134.168.97|64.134.168.97]] ([[User talk:64.134.168.97|talk]]) 04:14, 24 June 2012 (UTC)

:Note, the picture has been looked at by THE BEST minds at the Commons copyright question desk (I know those peeps).  And has even had the tilt taken out because of some worry about that.  It is legit.  Maybe looks like we are getting away with something...but are not.  So no skirts fluttering...[[Special:Contributions/64.134.168.97|64.134.168.97]] ([[User talk:64.134.168.97|talk]]) 04:17, 24 June 2012 (UTC)
:My preference is to keep the infobox where it is.  The headline is nice, but it doesn't need to lead off the article because it isn't &quot;telling&quot; anything that we don't already know.  The images in the infobox were calculated to orient.  People don't know where Canoe River is for a very good reason.  It is the hell and gone in BC, it took me nine hours from Vancouver with some stops.  I'd like to hear what people watching the article think.--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 09:31, 24 June 2012 (UTC)

: I've {{diff|Canoe River train crash|499113859|499088461|restored}} things. The IP lost me at &quot;golden text&quot;. I suggest specific changes be proposed here before such disruptive edits ''so you can see it'' are made (try preview for 'seeing'). [[User:Br&amp;#39;er Rabbit|Br&amp;#39;er Rabbit]] ([[User talk:Br&amp;#39;er Rabbit|talk]]) 10:28, 24 June 2012 (UTC)

OK.  I just wanted you to look at it.  Still think the bulk of the infobox is not very interesting (doesn't have almanacy things like the height of the Statue of Liberty).

And since the average person has NEVER heard of this crash, a headline makes them &quot;care&quot; more quickly and viscerally.  And the &quot;big crash, # dead&quot; is the more quick thing to want to grapple with (to put this mystery term in context), not &quot;in the mountains&quot;.  Also, that the details of geometry and such fit better within the crash section.  And in general, a more fast understood and emotionally compelling picture is more important for a lead, than one that requires a lot of looking at and thinking about (like a two-panel map with geometry of rail lines). ''Think about what kind of picture would be featured on the front page of the newspaper?  A map?? or dead bodies??''  If it bleeds, it leads...;-)

And the other moves as discussed.  But I'm fine.  Just wanted you to look at it.  [[Special:Contributions/64.134.168.97|64.134.168.97]] ([[User talk:64.134.168.97|talk]]) 13:45, 24 June 2012 (UTC)

And for Brer, the intention was pretty clearly to do a &quot;trial&quot; for appearance.  Not to drive some revert war crap.  You can't assess this stuff without actually making the change and taking a look at it.  Ideally giving it a day or so of getting used to it.  Anyhoo, the author has at least had a look, so I have reverted.[[Special:Contributions/64.134.168.97|64.134.168.97]] ([[User talk:64.134.168.97|talk]]) 13:49, 24 June 2012 (UTC)

::I did look at it.  I have no objection to rearranging the images, but I think probably we should keep the infobox as is.  I'm not the biggest fan of infoboxes, but if we want to do something else, we probably should discuss in detail.  I would welcome your thoughts on the article.  I welcome feedback and react to it.  I don't always see the article from a reader's perspective.--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 13:55, 24 June 2012 (UTC)

:Maybe we could find a way by rearranging the maps?  Feel free to experiment.--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 14:03, 24 June 2012 (UTC)

If you want to re-arrange the pictures and keep the infobox that is an option (I even mentioned it in my first post...of course you'd have to read past the slight bodycheck on golden text.  ;-))  I've put a substantial &quot;version B&quot; forward.  If you see anything worthwhile, will leave it up to you to implement.  (I'm not trying to drive a version...could care less...but to show you something.)  If the map formatting or the like gives you a hard time, get MissMJ to help or just look at my revision code and figure it out.  Chaka, bra.  :-)  [[Special:Contributions/64.134.168.97|64.134.168.97]] ([[User talk:64.134.168.97|talk]]) 14:07, 24 June 2012 (UTC)

You could maybe do something like having the headline up top and the map lower down (within the infobox).  Sort of like this:

{{Taxobox
| name = Arabian Wolf&lt;/br&gt;{{lang-ar|ذئب عربي}}
|status=CR |status_system=IUCN3.1                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       | image = Canis lupus arabs head front.JPG
| regnum = [[Animal]]ia
| phylum = [[Chordate|Chordata]]
| classis = [[Mammal]]ia
| ordo = [[Carnivora]]
| familia = [[Canidae]]
| genus = ''[[Canis]]''
| species = ''[[Gray Wolf|C. lupus]]''
| subspecies = '''''C. l. arabs'''''
| trinomial = ''Canis lupus arabs''
| trinomial_authority = [[Reginald Innes Pocock|Pocock]], 1934&lt;ref&gt;{{ITIS |id=726811 |taxon=''Canis lupus arabs'' |accessdate=27 October 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| range_map = Present distribution of wolf subspecies arab.jpg
| range_map_caption = Arabian wolf range
}}

I'm not crazy about infoboxes since they get long and since they reduce the image size (to fit inside).  But in this case, layout &quot;B&quot; had the pics all on the right anyway, so it is basically same thing, but within an infobox.  Also, if you consider how the species infoboxes &quot;work&quot;, you see that people have an iconic (fast processed) picture of the animal on top and then the map lower down (as it is more detailed reading really, to parse a map).[[Special:Contributions/64.134.168.97|64.134.168.97]] ([[User talk:64.134.168.97|talk]]) 14:26, 24 June 2012 (UTC)

:I'm not sure the template will support that?--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 14:30, 24 June 2012 (UTC)

: {{ec}} I'm in favour of retaining the infobox. They're useful as a précis. We can see your version {{oldid|Canoe River train crash|499087519|here}} (and {{oldid|Canoe River train crash|499088461|here}}, and {{oldid|Canoe River train crash|499134775|here}}). I've no particular objection to the newspaper image being used or images nudged to more relevant locations. I am concerned that we could get into a too many images to content ratio situation, resulting in overall layout problems. And I'm pretty much with you on the L-R alternation issue. Of course you're [{{fullurl:Canoe River train crash|action=edit}} free to experiment]; just take modest steps, please. [[User:Br&amp;#39;er Rabbit|Br&amp;#39;er Rabbit]] ([[User talk:Br&amp;#39;er Rabbit|talk]]) 14:34, 24 June 2012 (UTC)

W: Well...what is it doing for you?  Can you explain why you like it? I mean the text fields in there are pretty uninteresting. It's not like a country where you would have some almanac info like population and area and the like. 

(and in any case, the template can be tweaked or an alternative used.  Don't let the format affect the layout...drive for the reader...and you don't even know that this is a real problem.)

(and the lead is the precis.  it is even a &quot;short&quot; lead...one more reason an infobox not needed.) 

I put a substantial revision in.  If you all like any of it...ball.  your side of the court.  (your turn.)  If you don't want to bother, than maybe the changes are not that compelling.  Peace.[[Special:Contributions/64.134.168.97|64.134.168.97]] ([[User talk:64.134.168.97|talk]]) 14:39, 24 June 2012 (UTC)

:I need to look closer at how your images do better for the various sections.  Perhaps my like of the infobox is creator's pride, doing the maps that way was my idea, and I was thinking that despite how obscure Canoe River is, people will know at a glance right where it happened.  But that's not a reader's perspective.  Also, we do have some obligation to make articles as uniform as possible.  To my mind, that makes a presumption that we should have an infobox, to quickly set forth what happened, where, and how.  But the other images, as you can probably tell, were added later, after my visit to Canoe River and Cedarside, and have not been reviewed by the community, except the very few people who read this article, and who may not even realize they can comment.--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 14:49, 24 June 2012 (UTC)

Another idea:  You could put one of the memorial pics in the lead spot.  (It is interesting that the TFA used one of them...it needed an iconic graphic.)  The rest of the layout as discussed in version B, except put the headline down in the rescue section.  (since it concerns casualties.)  Still not sure where the train goes, but wedge it in somewhere.[[Special:Contributions/64.134.168.97|64.134.168.97]] ([[User talk:64.134.168.97|talk]]) 15:34, 24 June 2012 (UTC)

:You know your stuff.  We can, I think, put any two images we like in the infobox, but I'm concerned that if we have the maps right below that, it might be image overload.--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 18:53, 24 June 2012 (UTC)

::If you want to put the headline in the infobox, fine, but I'd like to keep at least one map image, with the others further south.  Thanks for your attention, surprised you've &quot;heard of it&quot;.--[[User:Wehwalt|Wehwalt]] ([[User talk:Wehwalt|talk]]) 12:28, 25 June 2012 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>kozccgfkc4uubmw72sq3l9lhr616b0k</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
