<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Battle of Vukovar</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2489147</id>
    <revision>
      <id>751165188</id>
      <parentid>750306192</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-23T20:03:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tzowu</username>
        <id>20198953</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Displaced civilians */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13030">{{talkheader}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=WPR
|action1date=00:21, 25 July 2006
|action1link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Peer review/Battle of Vukovar
|action1result=reviewed
|action1oldid=65656662

|action2=FAC
|action2date=00:24, 19 September 2011
|action2link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Battle of Vukovar/archive1
|action2result=not promoted
|action2oldid=451120486

|action3=WAR
|action3date=01:17, 4 October 2011
|action3link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/Battle of Vukovar
|action3result=not approved
|action3oldid=453744885

|action4=FAC
|action4date=15:05, 28 October 2011
|action4link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Battle of Vukovar/archive2
|action4result=promoted
|action4oldid=457824884

|currentstatus=FA
|maindate=November 18, 2011
}}
{{British English|date=September 2011}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WPMILHIST|class=FA
|A-Class=fail
&lt;!-- B-Class checklist --&gt;
&lt;!-- 1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points are appropriately cited. --&gt;
|B-Class-1= yes
&lt;!-- 2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain major omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|B-Class-2= yes
&lt;!-- 3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;
|B-Class-3= yes
&lt;!-- 4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;
|B-Class-4= yes
&lt;!-- 5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;
|B-Class-5= yes|old-peer-review=yes
|Balkan-task-force=yes
}}
{{WikiProject Yugoslavia|class=FA|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Croatia|class=FA|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Serbia|class=FA|importance=mid}}
}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2006-11-18|oldid1=88597137|date2=2007-11-18|oldid2=172297783|date3=2008-11-18|oldid3=252656328|date4=2009-11-18|oldid4=326455917|date5=2010-11-18|oldid5=397522517|date6=2012-11-18|oldid6=523493002|date7=2014-11-18|oldid7=634194888|date8=2016-11-18|oldid8=750003534}}
{{press
| title = Simbol pobjede, ambijent poraza
| author = Robert Bajruši
| date = 18 November 2011
| url = http://www.nacional.hr/clanak/120018/simbol-pobjede-ambijent-poraza
| org = [[Nacional (weekly)|''Nacional'']]
| accessdate = 30 June 2012
| archiveurl = http://www.webcitation.org/68ocyqDsC
| archivedate = 30 June 2012
}}

== Thatcher ==

: In September 1998, [[Margaret Thatcher]] visited the ruins of the city and used it in a speech as a symbol for &quot;eight years of Western weakness&quot; and &quot;failure of appeasement&quot; when compared to &quot;naive negotiators trying to reason with Milošević&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Congressional Record|Congressional Record]], page 8957&lt;/ref&gt;
{{reflist}}
* {{cite web|ref=Congressional Record|title=Congressional Record, V. 145, Pt. 6, April 28, 1999 to May 10, 1999|year=2004|url=http://books.google.hr/books?id=8hGwXHr0eNEC&amp;dq=margaret+thatcher+vukovar&amp;hl=hr&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s|publisher=Government Printing Office|accessdate=14 April 2012}}

I'm removing the above part of [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Battle_of_Vukovar&amp;diff=487367925&amp;oldid=486438252 this edit] - the edit is hardly self-explanatory and Thatcher's opinion seems largely inconsequential. --[[User:Joy|Joy &amp;#91;shallot&amp;#93;]] ([[User talk:Joy|talk]]) 16:54, 10 June 2012 (UTC)
:What exactly is the problem with Thatcher visiting Vukovar? You have to be more precise about that than just saying she was &quot;inconsequential&quot;. Currently, under reference no. 167, even this kind of language is tolerated (&quot;''They were helped by Central European scum. They crawled from under the papal tiara, as a dart of the serpent's tongue that protruded from the bloated Kraut and overstretched Eurocommunal anus''&quot;), but her's is problematic?--[[User:Justice and Arbitration|Justice and Arbitration]] ([[User talk:Justice and Arbitration|talk]]) 12:25, 11 June 2012 (UTC)

:: The problem is [[WP:FACR]], as usual - additions of paragraphs of, well, less than brilliant prose, need to be substantiated with edit summaries at the very least. In particular, this doesn't seem like a secondary source. Does anyone else other than Thatcher think that her opinion on that is important enough to mention? That's the kind of content that wouldn't be a problem. --[[User:Joy|Joy &amp;#91;shallot&amp;#93;]] ([[User talk:Joy|talk]]) 18:48, 11 June 2012 (UTC)

::: I haven't found a single news article about it. It simply doesn't seem to have made much public impact. Thatcher is not exactly a consequential figure in the story of Vukovar anyway, considering she was out of office at the time of the battle. [[User:Prioryman|Prioryman]] ([[User talk:Prioryman|talk]]) 19:26, 11 June 2012 (UTC)

::::I think that the visit of a former prime minister of UK is far more noteworthy than including rants and silly phrases of no-name nationalists like Stanković and others. At least a mention that she visited the town should be warranted.--[[User:Justice and Arbitration|Justice and Arbitration]] ([[User talk:Justice and Arbitration|talk]]) 07:09, 12 June 2012 (UTC)

:::::Tell you what, could you see if you can find any news articles about it? That way we would be able to get a better idea of its noteworthiness. [[User:Prioryman|Prioryman]] ([[User talk:Prioryman|talk]]) 07:13, 12 June 2012 (UTC)

== DW reference ==

* {{cite news | ref =Seeney | last =Seeney | first = Helen | url = http://www.dw.de/dw/article/0,,2129420,00.html| title = Croatia: Vukovar is Still Haunted by the Shadow of its Past| newspaper = Deutsche Welle | date = 22 August 2006 | accessdate = 14 April 2012}}

This reference is missing newspaper page number, which is FA standard (at least it was when the article passed FA). --[[User:Joy|Joy &amp;#91;shallot&amp;#93;]] ([[User talk:Joy|talk]]) 16:56, 10 June 2012 (UTC)

:It's OK, Joy - if it's an online news story it doesn't need a page number. [[User:Prioryman|Prioryman]] ([[User talk:Prioryman|talk]]) 18:48, 10 June 2012 (UTC)

== Archiving ==

I have archived the &quot;News reports&quot; sub-section in the &quot;References&quot; section. Few links have been left unarchived because I was unable to archive them due to errors that occure during the process of archiving. --&lt;font face=&quot;Old English Text MT&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Wustenfuchs|&lt;font size=&quot;3&quot; color=&quot;Black&quot;&gt;Wustenfuchs&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;/font&gt; 16:25, 26 July 2012 (UTC)

== Early shelling ==

I reverted [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Battle_of_Vukovar&amp;diff=614149096&amp;oldid=613316432 this edit] which had added July text in May content:

: Major shelling of Vukovar began on 4 July 1991 and thereafter the town was shelled regularly by the JNA and Croatian Serb forces, inflaming tension further. ref Prosecutor vs Mile Mrksic et al, 33-34 /ref

But it stands to reason that this claim does indeed exist in the relevant [http://www.icty.org/x/cases/mrksic/tjug/en/070927.pdf Trial Chamber Judgement] on pages 12-13:

: JNA forces sporadically shelled parts of Vukovar in June, July and August 1991. Houses in the centre of Vukovar as well as the Vukovar hospital were hit and damaged and civilians were wounded. The first significant shelling occurred on 4 July 1991. The predominately Croat Borovo Naselje was targeted from the direction of the predominately Serb Borovo Selo. In June and July 1991, shelling would take place once a day or every two days in Vukovar. The intensity grew on a daily basis.

The Appeals Judgements don't seem to mention this (I searched for &quot;July&quot;, didn't find anything of relevance), so it seems that it stands. The association of JNA with these early mortars in Borovo Selo is somewhat tenuous, but the court did in fact seem to make it there. The article currently mentions 'repeated gun and bomb attacks' in the relevant place, referenced to a BBC report at the time. This source may have issues, but it's certainly better than news reports. --[[User:Joy|Joy &amp;#91;shallot&amp;#93;]] ([[User talk:Joy|talk]]) 22:48, 23 June 2014 (UTC)

== Duplicated ref argument ==

There are two cite news templates with duplicate refs:
* &quot;Preminuo general Veljko Kadijević&quot;
* &quot;Blagoje Adžić je poveo totalni rat protiv Hrvatske&quot;
Just a heads up, not sure which is correct. [[User:GregorB|GregorB]] ([[User talk:GregorB|talk]]) 12:27, 13 December 2014 (UTC)

== Serial commas ==

[[User:Geraldshields11]], I noticed you added a lot of commas. This is a featured article that has been proofread numerous times, so I'm not sure if we really need this mass style change. I agree with some of those placements, but some others appear excessive (cf. [[MOS:COMMA]]). I'm also not sure if we need to change to use the [[serial comma]] here, because a) the article is tagged as written in British English where this practice is less common, so it could be argued that you're messing with [[MOS:ENGVAR]] b) the article becomes internally inconsistent while you're changing this, which is against [[MOS:SERIAL]]. --[[User:Joy|Joy &amp;#91;shallot&amp;#93;]] ([[User talk:Joy|talk]]) 10:19, 1 January 2015 (UTC)
: Dear {{ping|user:Joy}}, Thank you for mentioning my wikignome work with the '''Oxford comma'''. Perhaps, editors can recast the sentences to remove whatever becomes internally inconsistent. Let us work together to make good articles great. [[User:Geraldshields11|Geraldshields11]] ([[User talk:Geraldshields11|talk]]) 17:40, 2 January 2015 (UTC)

== Displaced civilians ==

Knowing this is a Featured Article, I was expecting a certain amount of verifiability. You can imagine my shock and surprise when I found that one of the sources used to uphold the figure of 31,000 ethnically cleansed residents (the ICTY indictment of Milosevic) actually states 20,000 were deported. The other source mentions 31,732 people displaced from the Vukovar region as a whole, but gives no timetable as to when this displacement occurred nor a breakdown of who carried out the expulsions, if indeed every single one of the people included in the aforementioned figure was indeed forcibly expelled/ethnically cleansed.

Snooping around the Internet, it soon became clear that the figures 20,000/22,000 are almost always used (in news articles, scholarly literature, etc.), though genocide scholar Bartrop has published two books using the 31,000 figure (probably a case of [[WP:MIRROR]]). 

Am I missing something here? [[User:23 editor|23 editor]] ([[User talk:23 editor|talk]]) 23:32, 3 August 2016 (UTC)

:Davor Marijan in his 2004 book ''[https://books.google.hr/books?id=Y6EkPwAACAAJ Bitka za Vukovar]'' wrote about 22,000 civilians, not 31,000.

:&quot;Prema podacima Glavnog sanitetskog stožera Republike Hrvatske, u Vukovaru je poginulo oko 1100 civila i oko 600 branitelja. Među poginulima bilo je i 86 djece. Ranjeno je 2500 osoba, od čega su 570 ostali trajni invalidi. Bez jednog ili oba roditelja ostalo je 858 djece. Prognano je 22.000 Vukovaraca, a oko 1500 ih je odvedeno u srpske logore.&quot; Croatian Wikipedia also gives the 22,000 number. [[User:Tzowu|Tzowu]] ([[User talk:Tzowu|talk]]) 22:43, 5 August 2016 (UTC)

I would like the input of other users if possible. Perhaps we're missing something? The 22,000 figure should be used, all things considered, IMO. If we fail to attract much attention, I'll be [[WP:BOLD|BOLD]] and make the change. [[User:23 editor|23 editor]] ([[User talk:23 editor|talk]]) 05:35, 7 August 2016 (UTC)

::{{ping|Tzowu}} Which page is that on? [[User:23 editor|23 editor]] ([[User talk:23 editor|talk]]) 18:00, 15 October 2016 (UTC)
:::page 284.[[User:Tzowu|Tzowu]] ([[User talk:Tzowu|talk]]) 12:09, 16 October 2016 (UTC)
:I've made the revision. Open to further discussion if necessary, as always. [[User:23 editor|23 editor]] ([[User talk:23 editor|talk]]) 16:52, 22 October 2016 (UTC)

==A couple of issues==

&quot;Although the Croatian government sent some supplies and reinforcements in the early stages, the defenders received little of significance. This was partly because of the difficulty of reaching the town, but may also have been a result of the Croatian government's decision to supply large quantities of arms to the [[Croatian Republic of Herzeg-Bosnia|Bosnian Croats]] in advance of the [[Bosnian War]]. In doing so, it starved its own forces of weapons and ammunition.&quot;

Vukovar was indeed short of ammunition, but so was the entire HV. Official documents on the deployment of weapons and ammunition show that &quot;the total amount of resources provided for equipping the HV&quot;, primarily ammunition, &quot;55-60% was engaged for the purpose of the defense of Vukovar and OG Vukovar - Vinkovci - Županja&quot;. (Marijan, ''[https://books.google.hr/books?id=Y6EkPwAACAAJ Bitka za Vukovar]'', p. 281. From page 278 to 282 he writes about the weaponry and ammunition that Vukovar received).

The second content in question is this: &quot;A 300-strong HOS battalion named the Black Legion led by Alija Šiljak operated in Vukovar under the Croatian Ministry of the Interior as an &quot;anti-terrorist brigade&quot;.&quot; [https://hr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alija_Šiljak Alija Šiljak] fought in eastern Bosnia, and the HOS had 58 fighters in Vukovar (Marijan, p. 29), not 300. [[User:Tzowu|Tzowu]] ([[User talk:Tzowu|talk]]) 20:02, 23 November 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>bfcsuct8fia70omj3hsneh9s9je08nu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
