<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Manzanar</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>279583</id>
    <revision>
      <id>723652140</id>
      <parentid>716723876</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-06-04T09:30:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Gmatsuda</username>
        <id>334311</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="21346">{{Talk header}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=GAN
|action1date=2007-06-30
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid=143613009

|action2=PR
|action2date=06:23, 12 August 2007
|action2link=Wikipedia:Peer review/Manzanar/archive1
|action2result=reviewed
|action2oldid=150719273

|action3=FAC
|action3date=14:14, 17 September 2007
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Manzanar
|action3result=promoted
|action3oldid=158445618

|topic=History
|currentstatus=FA
|maindate=April 26, 2008
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject United States|class=FA|importance=High|AsianAmericans=yes|AsianAmericans-importance=High|USMIL=Yes|portal1-name=United States|portal1-link=Selected article/9}}
{{WikiProject National Register of Historic Places|class=FA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject California|class=FA|importance=High|southerncalifornia=yes|southerncalifornia-importance=High|la=yes|la-importance=High}}
{{WikiProject History|class=FA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Protected areas|class=FA|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Museums|class=FA|importance=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=FA|importance=High|US-task-force=yes|WWII-task-force=yes}}
{{WikiProject Japan|class=FA|importance=Low}}
}}
{{United States SA}}
{| class=&quot;infobox&quot; width=&quot;150&quot;
|- align=&quot;center&quot;
| [[Image:Vista-file-manager.png|50px|Archive]]

==Archive==
'''[[Wikipedia:How to archive a talk page|Talk Page Archive]]'''

|- align=&quot;center&quot;
|[[Talk:Manzanar/Archive1|Archive 1, 08/02/07]]
[[Talk:Manzanar/Archive2|Archive 2, 09/16/07]]
[[Talk:Manzanar/Archive3|Archive 3, 09/23/08]]
|}

==Manzanar on front page, April 26, 2008 ==
[[Image:ManzanarOnFrontPg.jpg|thumb|left|400px|Manzanar on English Wikipedia's front page, April 26, 2008]]

Since we probably won't see [[Wikipedia:Today's featured article/April 26, 2008|Manzanar]] on Wikipedia's main/front page again anytime soon, here it is, for perpetuity... -- [[User:Gmatsuda|Gmatsuda]] ([[User talk:Gmatsuda|talk]]) 05:06, 26 April 2008 (UTC)

==Interesting comparison==
I wonder whether a link to some of the Japanese-run internment camps in the Far East would be of interest to readers of this article?  Camps like [[Stanley Internment Camp]] and [[Batu Lintang camp]].  It is interesting to compare the ''very'' different ways the two governments dealt with their civilian internees.  The Japanese treated their internees with great brutality.  Internees died as a result of lack of food, illness and violence.  Death orders were made at the end period of the war, stating that all surviving internees and POWs in the camps were to be murdered.  The Japanese ignored international conventions for the treatment of prisoners and regularly denied Red Cross aid. There is a culture of denial or at best collective amnesia in Japan about this shameful period in its history.  The treatment of the internees at Manzanar was decidedly humane in contrast. [[Special:Contributions/86.134.50.59|86.134.50.59]] ([[User talk:86.134.50.59|talk]]) 12:36, 26 April 2008 (UTC)

:I don't think this is appropriate at all.  The Japanese camps were in areas they occupied as a result of war, and held POW's and citizens of nations with which they were at war, not residents of their own nation. 
:By contrast, the US gave in to its own racial fears, and arbitrarily interned law-abiding legal residents and US citizens whose &quot;fault&quot; was they were descended from nations with which we were at war.  That's quite a difference. In retrospect, most historians think that economic competition and fearfulness on the West Coast played a bigger basis in the plan for the internment camps than any realistic assessment of wartime risk by the Japanese American populations. These are not the same case at all.--[[User:Parkwells|Parkwells]] ([[User talk:Parkwells|talk]]) 13:40, 26 April 2008 (UTC)
::Over the years I've met a few people (not Japanese-Americans) who lived in California during WWII. Based on these conversations, it seems to me that the major factor in the creation of thees camps in the US was the fear of invasion, however realistic or unrealistic that fear was. They described as similar to, but much more intense than, the anti-Arab feelings in America after the 9/11 attacks. I'm not saying this justifies what occurred, but it does perhaps provide some explanation.&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: verdana;&quot;&gt; — [[User:Rlevse|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#060;&quot;&gt;'''''R''levse'''&lt;/span&gt;]] • [[User_talk:Rlevse|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#990;&quot;&gt;Talk&lt;/span&gt;]] • &lt;/span&gt; 11:07, 27 April 2008 (UTC)

:::When I was growing up,  I had neighbors for a while who were Japanese Americans from CA.  The woman of the couple had parents who had moved her family from CA to TX to avoid the internment. Her father was a dentist and had a hard time reestablishing his profession.  Yes, fear runs wild, especially when linked to other kinds of difference, and in CA the anti-Japanese/Chinese discrimination had been deep. Part of the problem was that the national government, rather than acting with a larger strategic view, gave in to CA's hysteria, and authorized carting off a huge batch of people, non-citizens and '''citizens''' alike, for internment.  The national government's failure is one reason why a bill for compensation finally passed.--[[User:Parkwells|Parkwells]] ([[User talk:Parkwells|talk]]) 11:56, 27 April 2008 (UTC)
:::::There were some who correctly labeled what was happening at the time.  Japanese Americans did challenge the internment. [[Associate Justice]] [[Frank Murphy]] introduced the word &quot;racism&quot; into the lexicon of [[U.S. Supreme Court]] opinions in ''[[Korematsu v. United States]]'', [[Case citation|323 U.S. 214]] ([[1944]])&lt;ref&gt;[http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?court=us&amp;vol=323&amp;invol=214 Full text of Korematsu v. United States opinion courtesy of Findlaw.com.]&lt;/ref&gt;, in which he charged that by upholding the forced relocation of [[Japanese-Americans]] during [[World War II]], the Court was sinking into &quot;the ugly [[abyss]] of racism.&quot; This was the first time that the word &quot;racism&quot; found its way into the lexicon of words used in Supreme Court opinion.--[[User:Parkwells|Parkwells]] ([[User talk:Parkwells|talk]]) 12:11, 27 April 2008 (UTC)
::It also turned out (I'm reading from cases in Wikipedia), that later it was found that the government suppressed evidence in the Supreme Court case that said the military did not think a real emergency existed. &quot;Korematsu v. US&quot; was overturned.  Judge Patel concluded:

:&quot;''Korematsu'' remains on the pages of our legal and political history. As a legal precedent it is now recognized as having very limited application. As historical precedent it stands as a constant caution that in times of war or declared military necessity our institutions must be vigilant in protecting constitutional guarantees. It stands as a caution that in times of distress the shield of military necessity and national security must not be used to protect governmental actions from close scrutiny and accountability. It stands as a caution that in times of international hostility and antagonisms our institutions, legislative, executive and judicial, must be prepared to exercise their authority to protect all citizens from the petty fears and prejudices that are so easily aroused.&quot;--[[User:Parkwells|Parkwells]] ([[User talk:Parkwells|talk]]) 12:24, 27 April 2008 (UTC)

:: Actually, the ruling in the case was not overturned. A lower court cannot overturn a decision of the US Supreme Court. Rather, the ruling was vacated. Technically, the rulings in the 1944 cases are still the law of the land. However, based on the falsified, altered and omitted evidence that the government used in 1944, the ruling in the 1984 cases completely undermines the evidence upon which the 1944 cases were based on. -- [[User:Gmatsuda|Gmatsuda]] ([[User talk:Gmatsuda|talk]]) 17:10, 27 April 2008 (UTC)

:::More to the point, this kind of moral reductionism is the equivalent of kid's on the playground who claim &quot;Billy did it first!&quot; or &quot;Jane stole more cookies than I did!&quot; when caught by the schoolteacher. It wasn't a good excuse when we were schoolchildren, and its not an especially great one now. It also presumes that pointing out one's own flaws means an instant support of the opposing side; a kind of extrapolated &quot;the enemy of my enemy is my friend&quot;. This too is flawed, and reduces everything into a &quot;us vs them&quot; mentality. The world, despite how much people want to say otherwise, is a morally complicated place, with a great amount of gray. The fact that this perturbs people who want their decisions quick and simplistic is not something Wikipedia should cater to. [[User:SiberioS|SiberioS]] ([[User talk:SiberioS|talk]]) 07:26, 27 April 2008 (UTC)

== Do not edit others statements... ==

I came back today to find my statement not only erased, but merged with Parkwell's and signed with my user ID. I  presume, looking at the history, that the person who did this was Parkwells. I presume it was intentional because you modified the dates and times on my signature to fit it. For obvious reasons, this sort of thing is forbidden on WP. Don't try and modify the talk page and other peoples statements.(Edited later after logging in) [[User:SiberioS|SiberioS]] ([[User talk:SiberioS|talk]]) 19:15, 27 April 2008 (UTC)

:Don't presume anything. I did not alter your statement.  I don't even know how to alter the dates and times of signatures. Someone else apparently did.  A third person interposed another statement between ours.--[[User:Parkwells|Parkwells]] ([[User talk:Parkwells|talk]]) 23:43, 27 April 2008 (UTC)
:There appears to be other vandalism going on, as the level of protection was raised on the article.--[[User:Parkwells|Parkwells]] ([[User talk:Parkwells|talk]]) 23:49, 27 April 2008 (UTC)

== Additional photos from HABS and NPS are available ==

I just added a link to the 1984 NRHP Inventory/Nomination document that supported NRHP and NHL designation of the site, with accompanying 8 photos (now footnote 101 or so in the article).  It includes one dramatic HABS pic of the guardpost, and 7 photos by NPS employee E. N. Thompson taken in February 1984.  All of these are public domain.  Thompson's photos can be obtained individually as high quality JPG files by searching on Manzanar [http://nrhp.focus.nps.gov/natreghome.do?searchtype=natreghome here in the National Register search site].  There are also many other HABS photos available, [http://lcweb2.loc.gov/pp/hhquery.html obtainable by searching here in the HABS search screen], which are also all in the public domain.

The article is illustrated already, but perhaps some of these photos could be rotated in, or could be added to a Commons gallery on Manzanar that could be linked to the article.  I leave it to editors more involved with this article, however.  Hope this helps! [[User:Doncram|doncram]] ([[User talk:Doncram|talk]]) 19:35, 29 May 2008 (UTC)

: I tidyed up the citation you added and moved the PDF citation for the photos to an external link (more appropriate there) until I find time to find the jpegs of those photos and put them in the Commons. Thanks for fixing the infobox too! -- [[User:Gmatsuda|Gmatsuda]] ([[User talk:Gmatsuda|talk]]) 20:04, 29 May 2008 (UTC)

== Notable prisoners ==

In the course of identifying notable Japanese American internees at other war relocation camps, I found a few Manzanar internees with wikipedia articles that weren't mentioned in this article's Notable prisoners section.  In case anyone thinks it's appropriate to integrate these persons into that section, I am listing them here for reference: [[Koji Ariyoshi]], [[Paul Bannai]], [[Jeanne Wakatsuki Houston]] (mentioned in another section of the article), [[Gordon H. Sato]], [[Larry Shinoda]], [[Iwao Takamoto]], [[Takuji Yamashita]], [[Wendy Yoshimura]], and possibly [[Tommy Kono]].  This is an incomplete list.  &amp;mdash; [[User:Myasuda|Myasuda]] ([[User talk:Myasuda|talk]]) 21:10, 1 August 2008 (UTC)

: Yeah, but keep in mind that these camp articles are about the camp, not specifically about those who were imprisoned there. Yes, the prisoners  made and lived that history, but the focus of the article, after all, is the camp. As such, I actuallly removed Koji Ariyoshi and Iwao Takamoto in favor of those included in the Manzanar article because they are, I believe, more important to the history of Manzanar and of the Japanese American Internment. Perhaps the same focus would be best for the other camp articles as well. They should not become a list of all &quot;notable&quot; former prisoners. -- [[User:Gmatsuda|Gmatsuda]] ([[User talk:Gmatsuda|talk]]) 22:15, 1 August 2008 (UTC)

:: BTW: Eventually, the notable prisoners sections in the other camp articles will need to be more thoroughly researched with more detail added. Then, assuming those sections grow significantly, they will likely need to be pruned a bit, as we had to do with this article. :-) -- [[User:Gmatsuda|Gmatsuda]] ([[User talk:Gmatsuda|talk]]) 22:19, 1 August 2008 (UTC)

:::Right now each notable prisoner is profiled. For those with articles of their own it's sufficient to list them, or at most add a short description of the event surrounding their internment. Some of the folks already in the artilce might be spun off with articles of their own. Sue Kunitomi Embrey, for example, may be notable enough for an article. [[Special:Contributions/Will_Beback| ·:· ]][[User:Will Beback|Will Beback]]  [[User talk:Will Beback|·:·]] 22:26, 1 August 2008 (UTC)

== Wonderful image of farm work at Manzanar ==

[[File:Ansel Adams - Farm workers and Mt. Williamson.jpg|thumb|right|Farm work at Manzanar]]

I came across this image from 1943 at commons. I think it might be useful in this article. The source at the [http://lcweb2.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/h?pp/ils:@field%28NUMBER+@band%28ppprs+00370%29%29 Library of Congress] identifies it as &quot;Farm, farm workers, Mt. Williamson in background, Manzanar Relocation Center, California / photograph by Ansel Adams.&quot; –&lt;font style=&quot;color:#355E3B&quot;&gt;[[User:Droll|'''droll''']]&lt;/font&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;font style=&quot;color:#704214&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Droll|'''&amp;#91;chat&amp;#93;''']]&lt;/font&gt; 05:58, 6 September 2009 (UTC)

== Sadao Munemori ==

In the section [[Manzanar#Notable_prisoners]], it is stated that [[Sadao Munemori]] &quot;volunteered for service with the US Army directly from Manzanar&quot;.  This particular claim is not supported by a reference.  In fact, the following reference
*{{cite web | last = Tamashiro | first = Ben H. | title=The Congressional Medal of Honor: Sadao Munemori |url=http://nisei.hawaii.edu/object/io_1149130450078.html| date=March 15, 1985 | publisher=The Hawaii Herald}}
seems to contradict this when it states that Munemori had been inducted the month before the evacuation and was in an Army training center.  Is there any reliable reference that indicates that Sadao Munemori was actually interned at Manzanar? &amp;mdash; [[User:Myasuda|Myasuda]] ([[User talk:Myasuda|talk]]) 01:38, 18 October 2009 (UTC)
:With the assistance of [[Japanese American National Museum|JANM]] staff, I have links that support the above reference and invalidate the claim that [[Sadao Munemori]] volunteered for service with the US Army directly from Manzanar. The link [http://aad.archives.gov/aad/record-detail.jsp?dt=893&amp;mtch=1&amp;cat=WR26&amp;tf=F&amp;sc=24994,24995,24996,24998,24997,24993,24981,24983&amp;bc=,sl,fd&amp;txt_24995=munemori&amp;op_24995=0&amp;nfo_24995=V,24,1900&amp;rpp=10&amp;pg=1&amp;rid=7559539] shows that Munemori enlisted from Fort MacArthur in San Pedro, California in February of 1942 -- prior to the arrival of the first internees at Manzanar.  Also, the link [http://aad.archives.gov/aad/display-partial-records.jsp?dt=2003&amp;sc=24943%2C24947%2C24948%2C24949%2C24942%2C24938%2C24928%2C24940&amp;cat=WR26&amp;tf=F&amp;bc=%2Csl%2Cfd&amp;q=&amp;btnSearch=Search&amp;as_alq=&amp;as_anq=&amp;as_epq=&amp;as_woq=&amp;nfo_24943=V%2C10%2C1900&amp;op_24943=0&amp;txt_24943=munemori&amp;nfo_24947=V%2C8%2C1900&amp;op_24947=0&amp;txt_24947=&amp;nfo_24948=V%2C1%2C1900&amp;op_24948=0&amp;txt_24948=&amp;nfo_24949=V%2C1%2C1900&amp;cl_24949=&amp;nfo_24942=V%2C1%2C1900&amp;cl_24942=&amp;nfo_24938=V%2C5%2C1900&amp;cl_24938=&amp;nfo_24928=V%2C6%2C1900&amp;op_24928=0&amp;txt_24928=&amp;nfo_24940=V%2C2%2C1900&amp;op_24940=0&amp;txt_24940=] shows that the rest of the Munemori family arrived at Manzanar without Sadao and that Sadao Munemori is not listed as an internee in the database. &amp;mdash; [[User:Myasuda|Myasuda]] ([[User talk:Myasuda|talk]]) 01:00, 24 October 2009 (UTC)

== Updated reference/citation links ==

I went through each of the citations (under References) and updated any URL's that needed to be updated. Also fixed the format of one of the citations. -- [[User:Gmatsuda|Gmatsuda]] ([[User talk:Gmatsuda|talk]]) 23:02, 18 November 2010 (UTC)

== Forced relocation ==

Regarding the current debate over a sentence in the lead, tying together the three &quot;eras&quot; of Manzanar's history with the common thread of forced relocation, this is detailed (and referenced) later in the article. The Manzanar National Historic Site even documents this in their exhibit at their Interpretive Center. As such, I'm reverting the edits that removed it. -- [[User:Gmatsuda|Gmatsuda]] ([[User talk:Gmatsuda|talk]]) 03:58, 31 March 2011 (UTC)

I'm sorry, which group was displaced other than the Japanese - there are two other groups mentioned. the Ranchers and the Indians. Maybe they were all displaced. The statements seems ambiguous to me. Maybe It could be reworded. &amp;nbsp;–&lt;font style=&quot;color:#355E3B&quot;&gt;[[User:Droll|'''droll''']]&lt;/font&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;font style=&quot;color:#704214&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Droll|'''&amp;#91;chat&amp;#93;''']]&lt;/font&gt; 07:26, 31 March 2011 (UTC)

: It's in the body of the article pretty clearly. -- [[User:Gmatsuda|Gmatsuda]] ([[User talk:Gmatsuda|talk]]) 18:17, 31 March 2011 (UTC)

::As it stood the statement was ambiguous. Maybe just reword it a little. &amp;nbsp;–&lt;font style=&quot;color:#355E3B&quot;&gt;[[User:Droll|'''droll''']]&lt;/font&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;font style=&quot;color:#704214&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Droll|'''&amp;#91;chat&amp;#93;''']]&lt;/font&gt; 19:25, 31 March 2011 (UTC)

:::I think it stands on its own two feet, so to speak, just fine. -- [[User:Gmatsuda|Gmatsuda]] ([[User talk:Gmatsuda|talk]]) 10:06, 2 April 2011 (UTC)

::::I support Droll's proposal to reword the text.  As stated, it appears that the relocation thread applies to the ranchers and miners. &amp;mdash; [[User:Myasuda|Myasuda]] ([[User talk:Myasuda|talk]]) 14:12, 2 April 2011 (UTC)

:::::As it should. The ranchers and miners were forced to relocate from Manzanar when LADWP denied them water, another example of a governmental agency with political power forcing a group of people from their homes and communities. It was a different means of forced relocation, to be sure. Nevertheless, it is what it is. That's the common thread. -- [[User:Gmatsuda|Gmatsuda]] ([[User talk:Gmatsuda|talk]]) 07:51, 3 April 2011 (UTC)

== Problematic category ==
The problem with tagging this article in [[:Category:Concentration camps]] is that the main article for the category is [[Nazi concentration camp]]. I think there's something to be said for the use of the phrase, but... Manzanar is obviously not a &quot;Nazi concentration camp&quot;. [[User:NorthBySouthBaranof|NorthBySouthBaranof]] ([[User talk:NorthBySouthBaranof|talk]]) 07:14, 10 May 2013 (UTC)

: Yeah, that's an issue. Sadly, the root of the problem is that assumption that only the Nazi camps can be called &quot;concentration camps.&quot; It's only a category, though... -- [[User:Gmatsuda|Gmatsuda]] ([[User talk:Gmatsuda|talk]]) 07:19, 10 May 2013 (UTC)
:: Yeah. I was just looking for relevant categories, and kind of recoiled for a moment when I clicked through, which is why I initially knee-jerk deleted it... but I realized it's not really wrong, it's probably been discussed before and the problem is more as you say, that the relevant article doesn't have as broad a point of view as is really necessary to discuss the phenomenon. We really should have an expanded article on the term &quot;Concentration camp&quot; and its various uses through time. One more project for the [[Augean stables]], I suppose. [[User:NorthBySouthBaranof|NorthBySouthBaranof]] ([[User talk:NorthBySouthBaranof|talk]]) 15:50, 10 May 2013 (UTC)

==IPC==
Per [[Wikipedia_talk:Verifiability/Archive_63#popular-culture-RfC|this RFC]], IPC entries need reliable secondary sourcing to support the significance of entries to the topic. The books and movies listed are not secondary with regards to information about themselves, and IMDB and similar are not reliable. [[User:Nikkimaria|Nikkimaria]] ([[User talk:Nikkimaria|talk]]) 18:04, 22 April 2016 (UTC)

: Right. But your first &quot;solution&quot; was to delete those works that didn't have the sources, rather than flag them or find the refs yourself, which is what I initially took issue with. You're not helping the situation by doing that. -- [[User:Gmatsuda|Gmatsuda]] ([[User talk:Gmatsuda|talk]]) 08:12, 23 April 2016 (UTC)
::[[User:Gmatsuda|Gmatsuda]], that simply isn't true. I first [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Manzanar&amp;diff=716494618&amp;oldid=713101368 added the IPC template], and then later [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Manzanar&amp;diff=716559531&amp;oldid=716518181 removed some inappropriate sources and flagged the unsourced entries]. At no point did I delete any works here, regardless of sourcing. [[User:Nikkimaria|Nikkimaria]] ([[User talk:Nikkimaria|talk]]) 12:56, 23 April 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>jarmdfe8eb9ny0pvdl7s925v0h86u04</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
