<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:HMS Nairana (1917)</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>16051310</id>
    <revision>
      <id>697096607</id>
      <parentid>677709307</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-12-28T06:22:06Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Adamdaley</username>
        <id>2669838</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Cleanup.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8874">{{talkheader}}
{{ArticleHistory
| action1       = GAN
| action1date   = 11:06, 12 May 2013 (UTC)
| action1link   = Talk:HMS Nairana (1917)/GA1
| action1result = listed
| action1oldid  = 554718202
| dykdate= 4 May 2013
| dykentry= ... that after surviving service as a [[aircraft carrier|aircraft]]/[[seaplane carrier]] in [[World War I]], the '''[[HMS Nairana (1917)|''Nairana'']]''' was twice almost capsized by [[rogue wave]]s during her career as a [[Bass Strait]] ferry?
| currentstatus=FA
| topic= Warfare

|action2=WAR
|action2date=23:06, 6 March 2015 (UTC)
|action2link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/HMS Nairana (1917)
|action2result=approved
|action2oldid=650093983

|action3=FAC
|action3date=2015-05-13
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/HMS Nairana (1917)/archive1
|action3result=promoted
|action3oldid=661567934

|maindate=21 June 2015
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Military history|class=FA|A-Class=pass|Aviation=y|Maritime=y|British=y|WWI=y}}
{{WikiProject Ships|class=FA}}
{{WikiProject Australia|class=FA|importance=Low|maritime=y|military=y|maritime-importance=Low|military-importance=Low}}
}}

== Name? ==
Any idea as to the meaning of the name? (I am getting &quot;the Lion, Witch and the Wardrobe&quot; for some reason. [[User:PaulinSaudi|Paul, in Saudi]] ([[User talk:PaulinSaudi|talk]]) 15:41, 23 October 2010 (UTC)

== Expansion ==
Incorporated material on her trans-Tasman service -- plus the meaning of her name and a bit on her carrier fitout/service -- using ''Ferry to Tasmania''. There might be a bit between 1936 and 1948 that I've still to grab, but most of the remaining detail in the book on ''Nairana'' was about scheduling, too detailed for here.  I think I've captured most of the notable events, especially her twin encounters with rogue waves that give lie to the suggestion in an earlier version of the article that her 26 years of ferry service were &quot;without incident&quot;... ;-) Cheers, [[User:Ian Rose|Ian Rose]] ([[User talk:Ian Rose|talk]]) 14:29, 26 April 2013 (UTC)
:Thanks a bunch, Ian. When I submit this for DYK and GAN, I'll add you as a co-nom.--[[User:Sturmvogel 66|Sturmvogel 66]] ([[User talk:Sturmvogel 66|talk]]) 15:23, 26 April 2013 (UTC)
::Does the book have any info on her stats either before or after RN service?--[[User:Sturmvogel 66|Sturmvogel 66]] ([[User talk:Sturmvogel 66|talk]]) 17:29, 26 April 2013 (UTC)
:::Also need a page # for when she was laid up.--[[User:Sturmvogel 66|Sturmvogel 66]] ([[User talk:Sturmvogel 66|talk]]) 18:01, 26 April 2013 (UTC)
::::Tks re. the co-nom, always happy to collaborate anew. BTW pls don't hesitate to tweak my phrasing, as ships aren't my specialty... ;-) I have the book on loan in the library till at least Monday, so get it in as final a state as you can this w/e and note (fact-tag if you like) any unsourced bits. Re. stats, looks like you have most everything cited, perhaps better spell out what in particular you're after, although of course if Plowman includes details in an appendix or something I'll double-check them all... Cheers, [[User:Ian Rose|Ian Rose]] ([[User talk:Ian Rose|talk]]) 04:45, 27 April 2013 (UTC)
:::::We're about 2K of text short of a DYK, which is probably out of our reach, but the GAN isn't a problem. One other source to check, if a copy is close to you, is ''The Denny List'' as that's supposed to have stats for every ship built by Denny, listed by shipyard #, which is in the infobox. If not, I'll order it and sit on the nomination until it arrives. I'm curious what her designed stats were compared to what they were in RN service and postwar. I don't think that much changed other than draught, but her original passenger capacity and crew size would be nice to get if available. And the same information after she was reconverted back to civilian life, although you've already provided her passenger capacity. Things we do need to confirm: Date taken out of service; Wrecked at anchor or while under tow to the breakers and date of sale back to Huddart Parker since my sources are saying both 1920 and 1921.--[[User:Sturmvogel 66|Sturmvogel 66]] ([[User talk:Sturmvogel 66|talk]]) 05:15, 27 April 2013 (UTC)
::::::Okay, will do. Cheers, [[User:Ian Rose|Ian Rose]] ([[User talk:Ian Rose|talk]]) 23:24, 27 April 2013 (UTC)
:::::::Right, per my latest edits, got what I could re. return to Huddart, plus some worthwhile detail on her fitout during WWII and her final days (sounds like she was wrecked at anchor, not being towed) but no add'l stats except WWII armament -- I'll leave to you to add/alter the infobox as you see fit. I can get the ''Denny List'' (four volumes!) for next-day delivery to the Mitchell Library, and will probably be back in there this Thursday night, so let me know if that’s quicker than you can accomplish and I'll go ahead and order it. Cheers, [[User:Ian Rose|Ian Rose]] ([[User talk:Ian Rose|talk]]) 23:12, 29 April 2013 (UTC)
::::::::Looks pretty good. I'm leaning towards not adding gun performance data for her WW2 outfit as she never had to use them and she was just a merchant ship. Go ahead and order Denny. Her yard # was 543; I forget whether that's volume one or two, but you shouldn't need to order all four volumes since the list is organized by yard #. With that data we'd probably have enough for the DYK, but the 5-day rule will have passed by the time that you get Denny.--[[User:Sturmvogel 66|Sturmvogel 66]] ([[User talk:Sturmvogel 66|talk]]) 23:32, 29 April 2013 (UTC)
:::::::::Heh, you read my mind re. DYK -- by my calc we have barely 1,000 characters to go. I'll order it today and if I happen to get to the Mitchell by 1 May (DYK Day 5, I believe) then well and good. Cheers, [[User:Ian Rose|Ian Rose]] ([[User talk:Ian Rose|talk]]) 23:38, 29 April 2013 (UTC)
::::::::::Sound like a plan.--[[User:Sturmvogel 66|Sturmvogel 66]] ([[User talk:Sturmvogel 66|talk]]) 00:10, 30 April 2013 (UTC)
:::::::::::Hmm, the first two ''Denny'' volumes seem to be arranged by ship number, and only go up to 1906... :-P So no luck there. However I did improve the shining hour by gleaning more interesting info from Plowman, to the extent that I think we might be able to go for DYK anyway... Cheers, [[User:Ian Rose|Ian Rose]] ([[User talk:Ian Rose|talk]]) 07:22, 1 May 2013 (UTC)
::::::::::::I've tweaked a bit more because we seemed to have a slight contradiction in that Plowman stated she was released by the British Govt soon after the Armistice, but you had that she was still used by the RN in 1919. Since the only actions mentioned were in 1918, I've taken Plowman to be correct and made the article consistent with release to Denny's soon after Nov 1918. Let me know if that's an issue. Anyway, I think we're eligible for DYK with 2-300 chars to spare now, so will nom -- feel free to tweak or suggest an alt... ;-) Cheers, [[User:Ian Rose|Ian Rose]] ([[User talk:Ian Rose|talk]]) 09:50, 1 May 2013 (UTC)
{{od}}You missed the bit where she ferried aircraft to North Russia in June 1919, so I've made it a bit vaguer as to when she was reconverted. Tweak it as you see fit. Thanks for handling the DYK nom, I'll do the GAN later today. If we can get her original design info, it might be worth making a run at FAC. This went very smoothly, if you're ever minded to work on other Australian warships, let me know.--[[User:Sturmvogel 66|Sturmvogel 66]] ([[User talk:Sturmvogel 66|talk]]) 13:31, 1 May 2013 (UTC)
:Heh, I did miss that bit in 1919 -- anyway, it looks good/plausible now. Yep, I think this has worked well.  Missing out on ''Denny'' might've been a blessing in disguise 'cos otherwise I wouldn't have bothered to pore through Plowman again and get the plaque thing and especially the Tassie Devil story, which I liked so much I almost used it for the DYK... ;-) Anyway, I'll order Denny Vol. 3 and add what's there in the next week or so. Cheers, [[User:Ian Rose|Ian Rose]] ([[User talk:Ian Rose|talk]]) 13:47, 1 May 2013 (UTC)

== Tonnages ==
I note that the tonnage is given as tons displacement. Doesn't this refer to her service as HMS ''Nairana''. The Lloyd's Register entries give GRT and NRT figures for her service as SS ''Nairana'', although I have had a report that the links don't work - they work fine for me using Firefox. Should these figures be added to the article? [[User:Mjroots|Mjroots]] ([[User talk:Mjroots|talk]]) 07:33, 22 June 2015 (UTC)
:Look at the second para of the background section.--[[User:Sturmvogel 66|Sturmvogel 66]] ([[User talk:Sturmvogel 66|talk]]) 13:45, 22 June 2015 (UTC)
::Shouldn't GRT and NRT be in the infobox? I'm surprised that BOM is quoted, thought that was a sailing ship measurement! [[User:Mjroots|Mjroots]] ([[User talk:Mjroots|talk]]) 19:35, 22 June 2015 (UTC)
:::Sure, go ahead.--[[User:Sturmvogel 66|Sturmvogel 66]] ([[User talk:Sturmvogel 66|talk]]) 20:39, 22 June 2015 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>fjkm411ej3c9n2f2jpakm52630opy02</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
