<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Charles I of England</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>163259</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745276701</id>
      <parentid>745276559</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-20T06:47:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Celia Homeford</username>
        <id>28078513</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Sign someone else's comment.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="35968">{{Talk header}}
{{Vital article|level=4|topic=People|class=FA}}
{{ArticleHistory
|action1=FAC
|action1date=23:41, 13 Sep 2004
|action1link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Charles I of England/archive1
|action1result=promoted
|action1oldid=5866194

|action2=FAR
|action2date=07:48, 3 June 2007
|action2link=Wikipedia:Featured article review/Charles I of England/archive1
|action2result=removed
|action2oldid=135332961

|action3=FTC
|action3date=14 June 2007
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured topic candidates/British monarchy/archive1
|action3result=failed

|action4=GAN
|action4date=01:34, 6 June 2010 (UTC)
|action4link=Talk:Charles I of England/GA1
|action4result=failed
|action4oldid=366038757

|action5=GAN
|action5date=15:08, 4 November 2013 (UTC)
|action5link=Talk:Charles I of England/GA2
|action5result=listed
|action5oldid=580164397

|action6=FAC
|action6date=10:01, 18 December 2013
|action6link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Charles I of England/archive2
|action6result=promoted
|action6oldid=586619548

|topic=Royalty, nobility and heraldry
|maindate=January 30, 2006
|currentstatus=FA

|otd1date=2005-01-30
|otd1oldid=16335124
|otd2date=2007-01-30
|otd2oldid=104327631
|otd3date=2008-01-30
|otd3oldid=187909847
|otd4date=2009-01-30
|otd4oldid=267423220
|otd5date=2010-01-30
|otd5oldid=340832226
|otd6date=2012-01-30
|otd6oldid=473988719
|otd7date=2015-01-30
|otd7oldid=644523912
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|collapsed=yes|1=
{{WikiProject Biography|living=no|class=FA|peerage-work-group=yes|peerage-priority=High|royalty-work-group=yes|royalty-priority=High|listas=Charles 01 Of England}}
{{WikiProject England|class=FA|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Saints|class=FA|importance=High|past-biography=yes}}
{{WikiProject Ireland |class=FA|importance=Mid|attention= |peer-review= |old-peer-review= |image-needed=no |needs-infobox=no }}
{{WPMILHIST
|class=FA
&lt;!-- 1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points are appropriately cited. --&gt;
|GA-Class-1=yes
&lt;!-- 2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain major omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|GA-Class-2=yes
&lt;!-- 3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;
|GA-Class-3=yes
&lt;!-- 4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;
|GA-Class-4=yes
&lt;!-- 5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;
|GA-Class-5=yes
|British-task-force=yes
|Early-Modern-task-force=yes
}}
{{WikiProject English Royalty|class=FA|importance=top}}
{{WikiProject Scottish Royalty|class=FA|importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Christianity
|class=FA
|importance=low
|catholicism=yes
|catholicism-importance=low
|anglicanism=yes
|anglicanism-importance=Top
}}
}}

== Page title: King of Scotland (and England) ==

Why does the title page restrict his title to King of England, omitting Scotland (and Ireland)? His father was King of Scots (there were no monarchs of Scotland, only the Scots people, for more details, please see the Declaration of Arbroath for more information ), before his acquistion of the kingdom of England. Further, Charles was born in Scotland. To that extent, he and his father were primarily Kings of Scots and only subsequently of England. To restrict his title to one of his kingdoms, England, thereby rewriting history, is not only historically inaccurate and, therefore, out of place in this encyclopaedia, but smacks of English cultural imperialism.
:I disagree that this is a matter of cultural imperialism, but I do agree that the title is problematic. Yes, Charles' father James VI&amp;I was king of Scots before he acceded the throne of England also, and yes, Charles was born in Scotland as a Scottish royal exclusively, but Charles' rule of all his kingdoms was conducted from England, and he is far more significant in English history than Scottish history. I could only propose that the article is moved to &quot;Charles I of England, Scotland and Ireland&quot;. I believe it would be correct to list his kingdoms in order of precedence and that this order is correct. Correct me if I am wrong. [[Special:Contributions/78.86.61.94|78.86.61.94]] ([[User talk:78.86.61.94|talk]]) 02:34, 14 May 2012 (UTC)
::The longer title would presumably be more accurate, if a little more cumbersome. I appreciate the point being made, but the simple &quot; .. of England&quot; is sufficient to identify and distinguish him from other monarchs named Charles I, while also focusing - for better or worse - on the most significant of his titles, and at the same time being the description that is probably found most often in reliable sources. I'm easy as to whether it's worth changing it to the longer form. &lt;small&gt;'''[[User:N-HH|&lt;font color=&quot;navy&quot;&gt;N-HH&lt;/font&gt;]]''' '''[[User talk:N-HH|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]]/[[Special:Contributions/N-HH|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;edits&lt;/font&gt;]]'''&lt;/small&gt; 13:59, 14 May 2012 (UTC)
::How is this not cultural imperialism?  Charles was a Stuart and the Stuarts originated in Scotland.  Yes you probably could argue that England was more powerful, or that Charles cared a lot more for the English crown over the Scottish crown, but the fact remains he was originally Scottish.  To be truly neutral, the article title needs to include Scotland, and realistically Wikipedia pages for all the Stuart monarchs should have Scotland in the article title as well as England.    &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Sowelilitokiemu|Sowelilitokiemu]] ([[User talk:Sowelilitokiemu|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Sowelilitokiemu|contribs]]) 15:44, 14 November 2015 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
::: He was also the [[British claims to the French throne#The Stuart dynasty claimants|king of France]]! :D --[[User:AnAbsolutelyOriginalUsername42|AnAbsolutelyOriginalUsername42]] ([[User talk:AnAbsolutelyOriginalUsername42|talk]]) 19:15, 3 June 2012 (UTC)
&quot;The simple &quot;...of England&quot; is sufficient to identify and distinguish him... while focusing... on the most significant of his titles&quot;. In saying that, I would suggest that you don't in fact appreciate the point being made. Why is his title to England the &quot;most significant&quot; of his titles, and who decided that this was the case? In Scotland his title to Scotland was of considerably more important.  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/81.98.179.223|81.98.179.223]] ([[User talk:81.98.179.223|talk]]) 07:27, 20 August 2015 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== &quot;Saint&quot; ==

[http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Charles_I_of_England&amp;oldid=492385321 Currently] we have an explicit reference in the first sentence to a claim that Charles is &quot;a saint in the Church of England&quot;, with a section in the main body that claims he was &quot;officially canonised&quot; as a saint. I'm not an expert on royalty or the Anglican Communion, but this leaps out slightly. The only source cited in this article for the claim - [http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/historic_figures/charles_i_king.shtml this BBC profile] - makes no such assertion. Researching it further, the issue seems a little more complex than that - he does possibly have some form of status as a &quot;martyr&quot; and is the object of special reverence by some Anglo-Catholic groups, but it seems a bit of a stretch to say that he is &quot;officially&quot; or formally a saint; or indeed that the CoE has saints at all in the sense they are commonly understood. Regardless, it is hardly the main thing he is known for, or something that is given quite such prominence in other profiles. It's a fairly arcane and technical issue that doesn't need to be among the first things said about him here. &lt;small&gt;'''[[User:N-HH|&lt;font color=&quot;navy&quot;&gt;N-HH&lt;/font&gt;]]''' '''[[User talk:N-HH|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]]/[[Special:Contributions/N-HH|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;edits&lt;/font&gt;]]'''&lt;/small&gt; 12:24, 14 May 2012 (UTC)

:The [[Oxford Dictionary of National Biography]] notes [http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/5143?docPos=1 &quot;In 1660 parliament declared Charles a martyr, added him to the calendar of Anglican saints, and ordered prayers to be said in his memory and honour on the anniversary of his death, a practice that quickly became a duty cheerfully taken up by some and ignored by others.&quot;] It has a single sentence on the subject, and it's not as prominent as the first sentence, perhaps indicating that it's not as significant as Wikipedia's article may suggest. [[User:Nev1|Nev1]] ([[User talk:Nev1|talk]]) 12:34, 14 May 2012 (UTC)
::My &quot;research&quot; (aka Google search), which found the main results thrown up were either WP-derived pages or links to obscure groups such as [http://skcm.org/ this one], with none to serious biographies or profiles, suggest the same - both that the WP page is giving too much prominence to this and also that some groups have taken up the issue &quot;cheerfully&quot;. Anyway, it should definitely be in the body with a bit of explanation and qualification, as currently, but I'm minded to remove the bold explicit statement about sainthood from the first sentence of the lead. I would also lose the BBC source along with it; it's also cited for some other content, about the execution, but doesn't seem to support that either so is redundant both ways. &lt;small&gt;'''[[User:N-HH|&lt;font color=&quot;navy&quot;&gt;N-HH&lt;/font&gt;]]''' '''[[User talk:N-HH|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/font&gt;]]/[[Special:Contributions/N-HH|&lt;font color=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;edits&lt;/font&gt;]]'''&lt;/small&gt; 13:51, 14 May 2012 (UTC)
:::I was about to assure everyone that the independent Church of England has never &quot;done&quot; Saints (in the Roman sense of accrediting miracles and canonising deceased souls), but then I did some research (excluding this 'pedia) and founds claims that he is either the first or the only Anglican Saint. I even found a claim he was &quot;canonised&quot; (although that may just be used to mean &quot;made a saint&quot; rather than refer to the Roman church's processes). Certainly the Anglican Communion commemorates saints (small s), and King Charles the Martyr is among those, but whether he was ''canonised'' as a ''Saint'' (in a Romanish sort of way), I'm not completely sure... '''[[User:DBD|D]][[User talk:DBD|B]][[Special:Contributions/DBD|D]]''' 17:40, 14 May 2012 (UTC)
:Yes, the Church of England and broader Anglican Communion does 'canonise' in dividuals, though not frequently. St6 Charles the Martyr was commemmorated every year in the Book of Common Prayer until 1859, when the service was removed. The Collect from January 30: 'BLESSED Lord, in whose sight the death of thy saints is precious; We magnifie thy name for that abundant grace bestowed upon our late Martyred Soveraign; by which he was enabled so chearfully to follow the steps of his blessed Master and Saviour, in a constant meek suffering of all barbarous indignities, and at last resisting unto bloud; and even then, according to the same pattern, praying for his murderers. Let his memory, O Lord, be ever blessed among us, that we may follow the example of his patience, and charity. And grant, that this our Land may be freed from the vengeance of his bloud, and thy mercy glorified in the forgiveness of our sins: and all for Jesus Christ his sake. Amen'

:Though C of E doesn't follow the same exacting process as the Roman, the Sovereign, as Governor of the Church, may declare some individuals worthy of commemmoration. [[User:Gazzster|Gazzster]] ([[User talk:Gazzster|talk]]) 21:28, 20 September 2012 (UTC)
===April 2013 Charles as saint===
I've removed references to Charles being a saint in this article, [[Canonization]] and [[Society of King Charles the Martyr]]. I don't claim special expertise and I'm open to considering sourcing, but at the moment it doesn't look to me like there is a basis for saying that he was canonised. He does have a day dedicated to him in the Anglican calendar, but this doesn't seem to be any indication of sainthood. There are many people also commemorated in the same way who are clearly not saints (e.g. [[Samuel Johnson]], [[Florence Nightingale]], [[William Wilberforce]], [[Josephine Butler]] - also, surprisingly, non-Anglicans such as [[Dietrich Bonhoeffer]], [[Martin Luther]] and, though strictly not a non-Anglican, [[John Wesley]]). [[User:FormerIP|Formerip]] ([[User talk:FormerIP|talk]]) 22:14, 21 April 2013 (UTC)

:The Anglicans have  different ways of doing things and formal canonization is not something they do.  However Charles I has been considered a saint (martyr to the faith) by certain parts of the Anglican church for centuries  (other parts have less kind words to say about him).  They also tend to be broad in who they consider Christians in good standing (Catholic Archbishop Romero is considered a saint by many Anglicans).  [[User:Erp|Erp]] ([[User talk:Erp|talk]]) 23:21, 21 April 2013 (UTC)

::OK, so, with appropriate sourcing, we might say that a handful of/some/many Anglicans consider Charles to be a saint. But that would be very different from saying that he has been canonised or describing him as a saint in Wikipedia's voice. [[User:FormerIP|Formerip]] ([[User talk:FormerIP|talk]]) 23:59, 21 April 2013 (UTC)

== Executioners' masks ==

This article states that the executioners of Charles I wore masks. Is this correct? It would be unusual and against custom.  Most drawings of Charles's execution do not show masks and there is no reference.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/212.159.101.77|212.159.101.77]] ([[User talk:212.159.101.77|talk]]) 11:01, 17 September 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Impeachment of Henrietta Maria ==

The article says that Charles moved to arrest the pym et al when he heard that Parliament was intending to impeach Henrietta Maria, and the authority cited is Loades, D.M. (1974), Politics and the Nation, London: Fontana. There is no mention of any such threat in Adamson, Noble Revolt, but only mention of the Parliament moving against her Capuchin monks. I wonder if anyone could shed further light on this?
[[User:1f2|1f2]] ([[User talk:1f2|talk]]) 07:41, 11 February 2013 (UTC)

== date (and day of week) of Charles I's execution ==

For his execution, I am seeing (in this Wikipedia article) &quot;Tuesday, 30 January 1649&quot;.  When I run &quot;cal 1 1649&quot; (the Unix calendar command, to plot out January 1649) I do get 30 Jan. on a Tuesday, but the problem is that this is before 1752, and that command, for that time period, is using the calendar of England and its colonies, so I expect to see &quot;Old Style&quot; (Julian).  What we now call &quot;New Style&quot; (the Gregorian calendar) wasn't in use yet, and at the time it was 10 days ahead of Julian.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/128.63.16.20|128.63.16.20]] ([[User talk:128.63.16.20|talk]]) 14:43, 23 August 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Both Gregg and Cust say it was a Tuesday. From [[Cal (Unix)#Features]], it looks as though the dates went forward but the days of the week stayed the same. [[User:DrKay|DrKay]] ([[User talk:DrKay|talk]]) 15:03, 23 August 2013 (UTC)
::  Precisely.  Over in France, where the Gregorian was in full swing, the same day was called Tuesday 9 February 1649. --  [[User:JackofOz|&lt;font face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;Jack of Oz&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:JackofOz#top|&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:85%&quot;&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;Verdana&quot; &gt;&lt;sup&gt;[pleasantries]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 20:42, 23 August 2013 (UTC)

Oops, you may already understand this but I need to be explicit: Gregorian calendar wasn't in use yet IN ENGLAND, but it's pointed out it was already in use in France.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/128.63.16.20|128.63.16.20]] ([[User talk:128.63.16.20|talk]]) 22:03, 23 August 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

: Yes, that's clear.  It was in force in France, Spain, Portugal and Poland from 1582, but was not adopted in England until 1752.  See my post above.  --  [[User:JackofOz|&lt;font face=&quot;Papyrus&quot;&gt;Jack of Oz&lt;/font&gt;]] [[User talk:JackofOz#top|&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:85%&quot;&gt;&lt;font face=&quot;Verdana&quot; &gt;&lt;sup&gt;[pleasantries]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/span&gt;]] 22:08, 23 August 2013 (UTC)

Do we or do we not assume that event dates from England before 1752 are understood to be noted here in Wikipedia as New Style?  I recall reading that Jan. 30, 1649 date for Charles I execution very long ago.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/128.63.16.20|128.63.16.20]] ([[User talk:128.63.16.20|talk]]) 15:27, 26 August 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:Guideline for this is at [[WP:OSNS]]. Dates in this article are OS. [[User:DrKay|DrKay]] ([[User talk:DrKay|talk]]) 15:48, 26 August 2013 (UTC)

OK, I will try to look at that.  A footnote would help; consider this from the Wikipedia article about Queen Anne:

&quot;All dates in this article are in the Old Style Julian calendar used in Great Britain throughout Anne's lifetime; however, years are assumed to start on 1 January rather than 25 March, which was the English New Year.&quot;

Queen Anne's lifetime stretched across 1700, the year when the gap between Old &amp; New styles widened from 10 to 11 days, but is still entirely during England's use of Old Style.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/128.63.16.20|128.63.16.20]] ([[User talk:128.63.16.20|talk]]) 15:51, 26 August 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:There is a footnote. [[User:DrKay|DrKay]] ([[User talk:DrKay|talk]]) 15:59, 26 August 2013 (UTC)

Did I overlook an existing footnote?  Apparently, the footnote has been shifted to the death date, which is where Queen Anne's Wikipedia article has it.  Looking at 1 or 2 &quot;selected anniversaries&quot; pages (links provided on the page you are reading), I discovered Charles I's execution listed on Jan. 30, but it seems we have an Old-Style date included with at least some events of Jan. 30 New Style.  Maybe someone should review the anniversaries pages (and consider footnotes when Old Style is used), because of Charles I's execution being listed with an Old Style date.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/128.63.16.20|128.63.16.20]] ([[User talk:128.63.16.20|talk]]) 14:26, 27 August 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

{{Talk:Charles I of England/GA2}}

== Citations format ==

I think the appendix section for notes and citations would be better if the short citations were laid out as they are in the [[Charles II of England]]. Unless any objects I will implement the change. -- [[User:PBS|PBS]] ([[User talk:PBS|talk]]) 13:15, 26 October 2013 (UTC)

== Too many citations ==

There are many comprehensive biographies on Charles I, as there is a limit to the primary sources available give or take a few facts they all say much the same.

I think that this article has too may citations. Here are four examples, although there are hundreds (I exaggerate not) of others:
*{{green|Charles assented to the petition on 7 June (Carlton 1995, p. 101; Cust 2005, p. 74; Quintrell 1993, p. 39.)}} – Three citations for one date.
* {{green| the indictment held him &quot;guilty of all the treasons, murders, rapines, burnings, spoils, desolations, damages and mischiefs to this nation, acted and committed in the said wars, or occasioned thereby.&quot; (Gardiner 1906, pp. 371–374; Gregg 1981, p. 437; Robertson 2005, pp. 15, 149.)}} — Three citations for one quote.
*{{green|Fifty-nine of the commissioners signed Charles's death warrant (Edwards 1999, p. 162; Hibbert 1968, p. 267.)}} — Two citations for one fact
*{{green|The following morning, he called for two shirts to prevent the cold weather causing any noticeable shivers that the crowd could have mistaken for fear: (Official website of the British monarchy; Carlton 1995, p. 352; Edwards 1999, p. 168.)}} – A very well known  fact such as this does not need three citations.
-- [[User:PBS|PBS]] ([[User talk:PBS|talk]]) 17:07, 30 October 2013 (UTC)

==Lead picture== 

If you check out the picture on Wikimedia Commons, (which I have just corrected) you'll find that the painting that was first uploaded there was the original by van Dyck. But someone uploaded a larger clearer image ''of a studio copy'' over the top. That is the painting that you are currently looking at.  The description says, correctly, that it is a studio copy, but the '''artist''' was still listed as Van Dyck (which is what I have corrected. 

I was alerted because, on enlarging the image (the lead image) it was clear to me that it was a studio copy and ''definitely not'' by Van Dyck.  The name of the file still attributes it to the Master, and that should be fixed, except that I don't know how one goes about changing the file names of images. 

I would go for the triple portrait as the lead pic, or the Daniel Mijtens, rather than having an image of very dull colouration that turns out of the page instead of inwards.  
[[User:Amandajm|Amandajm]] ([[User talk:Amandajm|talk]]) 07:52, 31 October 2013 (UTC)
:Thanks for requesting the move on Commons Amandajm -[[User:PBS|PBS]] ([[User talk:PBS|talk]]) 17:03, 10 November 2013 (UTC)

==King of England?==
Why is Charles listed here in the title only as King of England? He was a half-Scot, half-Dane by birth. Born in Scotland and Crowned King of Great Britain and Ireland he is likely to have taken a dimm view of his reduction to monarch of only one of three kingdoms. After all, even when in arms agains the Scots he referred to Scotland as &quot;his native and ancient kingdom&quot;. Moreover, he writes his letters not as king of England, but as King of Great Britain. Should we update the rather parochial title here, or should we create duplicate entries for Charles I King of Scotland and Charles I king of Ireland?  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Tentsmuir|Tentsmuir]] ([[User talk:Tentsmuir|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Tentsmuir|contribs]]) 12:11, 28 January 2015 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:As the article title has been discussed before (above), if you wish it to be changed you will need to gain consensus for the move through the process detailed at [[Wikipedia:Requested moves#Requesting controversial and potentially controversial moves]]. Duplicate articles are avoided per [[Wikipedia:Content forking]]. [[User:DrKay|DrKay]] ([[User talk:DrKay|talk]]) 13:06, 28 January 2015 (UTC)

== Canonization ==

A new editor has twice added this sentence: &quot;He is the only [[saint]] to be canonized by the [[Anglican Communion]] that was not already a saint prior to the split with the Catholic Church.&quot;

I've removed that because I don't think it is correct. There are other people recognized as saints in at least parts of the Anglican Communion who are not recognized as such in the Roman Catholic Church. 

However, the fact that some (but not all) Anglicans have considered him a saint should be discussed. [[User:Jonathunder|Jonathunder]] ([[User talk:Jonathunder|talk]]) 00:46, 5 February 2015 (UTC)
:His recognition as a martyr is in the Legacy section already. I'd need to see a reliable source to convince me that he was recognized as a saint. [[User:DrKay|DrKay]] ([[User talk:DrKay|talk]]) 08:08, 5 February 2015 (UTC)
::[http://skcm.org/about-s-charles/ This page] is a good place to start. [[User:Jonathunder|Jonathunder]] ([[User talk:Jonathunder|talk]]) 15:06, 5 February 2015 (UTC)
:::I remain unconvinced. He was added to the calendar; so were William Wilberforce and Edith Cavell. And you can find sources calling them saints[http://www.britsattheirbest.com/heroes_adventurers/h_saints.htm]. [[User:DrKay|DrKay]] ([[User talk:DrKay|talk]]) 15:46, 5 February 2015 (UTC)
::::I think we agree, then. He has been considered a saint in at least part of the Anglican Communion, [[Saints in Anglicanism|as have many others]]. [[User:Jonathunder|Jonathunder]] ([[User talk:Jonathunder|talk]]) 16:27, 5 February 2015 (UTC)
:::::I agree that Charles I has been considered a saint in the Anglican Communion; I actually added a very small and well referenced section about this, but it was rapidly [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Charles_I_of_England&amp;diff=604130870&amp;oldid=604130160 removed]. I would support reinstating it, if others here feel the same way. With regards, [[User:Anupam|Anupam]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:Anupam|Talk]]&lt;/sup&gt; 00:57, 6 February 2015 (UTC)

== short section on id of exectioners ==

If this is going to be extensively discussed as it is being it should have a subsection. There is no value in having nothing but main sections with a grab bag of subjects in them.[[User:Overagainst|Overagainst]] ([[User talk:Overagainst|talk]]) 21:10, 12 July 2015 (UTC)
:The section length looks appropriate to me, and the material in the section is relevant to it. [[User:DrKay|DrKay]] ([[User talk:DrKay|talk]]) 21:13, 12 July 2015 (UTC)
::The length is no the problem it's padding and the different subjects under one heading. The ID of the executioners in my version is consistant with the recent book Killers of the King: The Men Who Dared to Execute Charles I. That and the  interment are  subjects deserving of a subsection. The encyclopedic account is  Brandon assisted by  Peter are thought to have did it. Cut the waffle, which makes the section all over the place. I don't know what you have against  subsections.[[User:Overagainst|Overagainst]] ([[User talk:Overagainst|talk]]) 21:22, 12 July 2015 (UTC)
:::Per [[WP:WIAFA]], the table of contents should not be too long - short sections should be merged or use a proper system of daughter pages as per [[Wikipedia:Summary style]]. Wikipedia does not select one view (that it was Brandon and Peters) over other views (that it was others); all views should be represented with due weight, as they are in the article by mentioning Brandon and Peters as candidates but not the only ones. [[User:DrKay|DrKay]] ([[User talk:DrKay|talk]]) 21:30, 12 July 2015 (UTC)
::::A couple of subsections for the ID and interment is not excessive. They are the ones witnesses and circumstantial evidence from Hugh Peter's trial make a powerful case against. If it is going to be gong into so deep as to cite everyone whose name was put up as a possibility then that is all the more reason for a subsection. Sections should not have unlabeled subsections. It makes finding information in the the article too difficult when  people come to find out one thing. This is supposed to be an encyclopedia. [[User:Overagainst|Overagainst]] ([[User talk:Overagainst|talk]]) 15:36, 13 July 2015 (UTC)
:::::If someone wishes to find out about the executioners, they have only to go to the &quot;Execution&quot; section. [[User:DrKay|DrKay]] ([[User talk:DrKay|talk]]) 15:47, 13 July 2015 (UTC)
::::::At least make it clear who is the likely suspect: Brandon. Peter could not possibly have been selected as the headsman, he had no experience, beheading with an axe was easily botched, he  was in late middle age and in bad health. I note that heraldry has little subsections. People are interested in that subject, and can find it easily. That is the way it ought to be.[[User:Overagainst|Overagainst]] ([[User talk:Overagainst|talk]]) 16:14, 13 July 2015 (UTC)

== Finances, especially forests ==

This line: 

''In addition, the boundaries of the [[royal forest]]s in England were extended to their ancient limits as part of a scheme to maximise income by exploiting the land and fining land users within the re-asserted boundaries for encroachment.''

seems to me to be rather misleading. From the texts I've read about the actual deforestation programme, fines were just a mechanism for sale, not really an object of policy. Nothing seems to suggest that boundary changes occurred, except in removing the legal forest. The process was one of (a) assessment of value and compensation needed to those entitled to use the common, especially manorial landlords; (b) sale, or agreement to &quot;fines&quot;, to be paid by new landlords, in return for enclosure; (c) enclosure, removal of forest law and often riot; (d) legal challenges to enclosure and (d) occasional reversals on the removal of forest law.

I think the general sources may have got this detail a little wrong in their emphasis. But I am only going on the texts I've been reading.  [[User:JimKillock|Jim Killock]] [[User_talk:JimKillock|(talk)]] 19:56, 23 August 2015 (UTC)
:Gregg, Quintrell and Sharpe say the forest courts and law had fallen into disuse and that the policy was to re-assert them to their fullest extent as a means of raising revenue, with an emphasis on (b) above and development of the land. You can't have (a), (b), (c), (d) or (e) without first re-asserting the ancient boundary of the forest. Otherwise, you'd just be continuing as before, allowing the current occupiers to enclose and use the land for free or commoners free access to open land, and operating under common law rather than forest law. [[User:DrKay|DrKay]] ([[User talk:DrKay|talk]]) 10:37, 25 August 2015 (UTC)

::OK, but the sentence says: &quot;extended to their ancient limits as part of a scheme to maximise income by exploiting the land and fining land users&quot;– (a) re-asserted is not the same as extended; (b) fining land users—I am a bit worried that this mainly took place as part of a &quot;sale&quot;. If so, the sentence is misleading. If other fines regularly took place with a large income resulting, then it is fair enough. According to those sources, was fining land users a major source of revenue? [[User:JimKillock|Jim Killock]] [[User_talk:JimKillock|(talk)]] 16:27, 25 August 2015 (UTC)

:::Gregg and Quintrell do not mention sales. Gregg says there were new licences to depark and enclose land, and that Charles enclosed his own land. She does say there were some sales of Crown land, which is not the same thing, but that it was less than in Elizabeth's and James's time. Quintrell says the smaller forests were disafforested and the larger ones exploited for their natural resources. Sharpe says inhabitants were offered the opportunity to either pay a fine for encroachment or pay to have their land disafforested, but only gives figures for fines and does not explicitly talk of sales. Gregg gives a figure of £37000 received in fines over 1636–40 and Sharpe gives a figure of £25000 received in fines over 1636–38. [[User:DrKay|DrKay]] ([[User talk:DrKay|talk]]) 10:47, 26 August 2015 (UTC)

::::Thanks, yes. I'll try to get some other sources on this for you. This page [[Western Rising and disafforestation riots]] and this [[Royal_forest#Disafforestation.2C_sale_of_forest_lands_and_the_Western_Rising|summary]] gives a picture of how it seems to have worked in practice, mostly from a book by Buchanan Sharp, but also from some articles about the individual forests that were affected. I've been a bit loose with the term &quot;sold&quot; on these pages but each &quot;sale&quot;, usually to a prominent courtier took the form of a &quot;fine&quot; for [[assart]]. There's a good description of the process on p56-57 of Sharp's book (and he cites some other general texts on the forests). License to depark may be the same as a sale, or a fine.

== Semi-protected edit request on 17 November 2015 ==

{{edit semi-protected|Charles I of England|answered=yes}}
&lt;!-- Begin request --&gt;
Suggested external resource -

* [http://www.olivercromwell.net/london-gazette-1648.html Contemporary London Gazette report on the trial and execution of Charles I]
&lt;!-- End request --&gt;
[[User:Spuddha|Spuddha]] ([[User talk:Spuddha|talk]]) 12:29, 17 November 2015 (UTC)
:Added to [[High Court of Justice for the trial of Charles I#Further reading]]. [[User:DrKay|DrKay]] ([[User talk:DrKay|talk]]) 12:58, 17 November 2015 (UTC)

== Semi-protected edit request on 8 February 2016 ==
{{edit semi-protected|Charles I of England|answered=yes}}
Charles has the official fault of causing English Civil War in 1642,These was the declared by the european union in 1989. [[User:SaladinoIII|SaladinoIII]] ([[User talk:SaladinoIII|talk]]) 18:06, 8 February 2016 (UTC)
:Please provide [[Wikipedia:identifying reliable sources|reliable sources]] for any new content and establish [[Wikipedia:Consensus|consensus]] for the inclusion of potentially controversial content. [[User:DrKay|DrKay]] ([[User talk:DrKay|talk]]) 18:12, 8 February 2016 (UTC)

{{edit semi-protected|Charles I of England|answered=yes}}
&lt;!-- Be sure to state UNAMBIGUOUSLY your suggested changes; editors who can edit the protected page need to know what to add or remove. Blank edit requests WILL be declined. --&gt;
&lt;!-- Begin request --&gt;
Charles I (19 November 1600 – 30 January 1649[a]) was monarch of the three kingdoms of England, Scotland, and Ireland from 27 March 1625 until his execution in 1649,He was executed by creating the English Civil war in 1642,This house was approved by the Unesco in 1989.
&lt;!-- End request --&gt;
[[User:SaladinoIII|SaladinoIII]] ([[User talk:SaladinoIII|talk]]) 18:15, 8 February 2016 (UTC)
:Not done. See above. [[User:DrKay|DrKay]] ([[User talk:DrKay|talk]]) 18:31, 8 February 2016 (UTC)

== Semi-protected edit request on 7 July 2016 ==

{{edit semi-protected|Charles I of England|answered=yes}}
&lt;!-- State UNAMBIGUOUSLY your suggested changes. Other editors need to know what to add or remove. Blank edit requests will be declined. --&gt;

Charles I of England should not be listed as Charles I of England.
He should be listed by his title of primacy; Charles I of Scotland.
The reason is both simple and clear. James VI of Scotland inherited the English crown in 1603, making the English crown a secondary title of King's or Queen's of Scots. 
The primary or correct title of Charles I is Charles I of Scots or Scotland.
Changing the nomenclature accordingly will make the article more technically correct.     
&lt;!-- Write your request ABOVE this line and do not remove the tildes below. --&gt;
[[User:Kez321|Kez321]] ([[User talk:Kez321|talk]]) 22:45, 7 July 2016 (UTC)
:[[File:Red information icon with gradient background.svg|20px|link=]] '''Not done:'''&lt;!-- Template:ESp --&gt; According to our article on [[James VI and I]], once James inherited the crown of England, he made that his primary title and went back to Scotland only once in his life. Charles I himself was raised in England, so it's unlikely that he would have styled himself &quot;of Scotland&quot;. If you have [[WP:RS|reliable sources]] to the contrary, I'll be happy to reconsider. [[User:Clpo13|clpo13]]&lt;sub&gt;([[User_talk:Clpo13|talk]])&lt;/sub&gt; 22:49, 7 July 2016 (UTC)

Was he Charles I during his lifetime? The seals and paraphernalia should show the &quot;I&quot;.  Should be on post boxes too! He would have been Charles of Scotland. Scotland ceased to exist as a separate royal title with the Act of Union in 1702.[[Special:Contributions/220.240.229.144|220.240.229.144]] ([[User talk:220.240.229.144|talk]]) 11:12, 20 September 2016 (UTC)

== Spelling error ==

End of paragraph 3 of lead subject mentions Charles's son.  Correct spelling is Charles' son. [[User talk:Sagavanirktok|Sagavanirktok]] 23:12, 19 October 2016‎
:Charles's is correct. See [[Wikipedia:Manual of Style#Possessives]]. [[User:Celia Homeford|Celia Homeford]] ([[User talk:Celia Homeford|talk]]) 06:45, 20 October 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>oy0mybjjzuxlfcly5s1whiy8m8oiste</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
