<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Calutron</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2677474</id>
    <revision>
      <id>735401395</id>
      <parentid>718200585</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-20T13:16:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Brianboulton</username>
        <id>5765342</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>maindate</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7658">
{{talkheader}}
{{ArticleHistory
| action1       = GAN
| action1date   = 22:52, 26 September 2015 (UTC)
| action1link   = Talk:Calutron/GA1
| action1result = listed
| action1oldid  = 682909079
| dykdate= 12 October 2015
| dykentry= ... that the [[Manhattan Project]]'s '''[[calutron]]s''' used {{convert|14700|ST}} of silver?
| action2=WAR
| action2date=01:06, 15 November 2015 (UTC)
| action2link=Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Assessment/Calutron
| action2result=approved
| action2oldid=690120825
| currentstatus=FA
| topic= Natsci
|maindate= 5 September 2016
|action3=FAC
|action3date=2016-02-22
|action3link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Calutron/archive1
|action3result=promoted
|action3oldid=706366192
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Physics|class=FA|importance=mid}}
{{WikiProject Mass spectrometry|class=FA|importance=Mid|comments=}}
{{WikiProject California|class=FA|importance=low|sfba=yes|sfba-importance=low}}
{{WikiProject University of California|UCB=yes|UCB-importance=|class=FA|importance=Mid}}
{{WPMILHIST|class=FA|A-Class=pass|WW2=yes|USA=yes|Cold-War=yes}}
}}

==Iraq's Calutrons==

You must be more objective in your comments. Developing an atom bomb and believe than Irak developed this arm, are two thinks very different.
Thierry
----
:You seem to be mistaken about what the text means. It says that ''before'' the war over Kuwait, Iraq had a nuclear program which employed calutrons. This is well known and not a controversial statement. The question which &quot;Bush Jr.&quot; was trying to settle -- and was apparently quite incorrect on -- was whether they ''continued'' to have one ''after'' the war. --[[User:Fastfission|Fastfission]] 13:11, 14 September 2005 (UTC)

The IEEE article &quot;how iraq reverse engineered the bomb&quot; mentioned something about calutrons - in 1945 they were all manually controlled - but in 1980 they could all be automatically controlled for greater efficiency  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Feldercarb|Feldercarb]] ([[User talk:Feldercarb|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Feldercarb|contribs]]) 02:01, 10 August 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;


== Gladys Owens ==

No part of the reference claims that Ms. Owens only learned the purpose of her work when she toured the site. I can't fathom why [[User:Greensburger|Greensburger]] would revert my removal of that sentence. [[User:Deltabeignet|Deltabeignet]] 05:48, 31 July 2007 (UTC)

I replaced the deleted sentence with exact quotes from the angeltowns reference - one clause from a caption and another clause from the first paragraph of the reference. [[User:Greensburger|Greensburger]] 12:56, 31 July 2007 (UTC)

== Copied material in article, unreferenced ==

This article seems well-written and reasonably well-sourced.  However, two tags in the article imply material in article is copied from two published source.  Such material needs to be referenced properly: copied text needs quotation marks and in-line citations.  It may not be copyright violation if the source is public domain, but any copying from published sources, PD or not, requires referencing.  Why not identify the copied material, put it in quotes properly, and not require the tag?  The tag is an insult to the work of wikipedia editors of the article, whose wording is implied to be copied, too. [[User:Doncram|doncram]] ([[User talk:Doncram|talk]]) 20:14, 14 January 2008 (UTC)

:From my reading of [[WP:PDR]] and [[WP:PD]], the material is being used properly and is properly cited. I don't think that it is possible to segregate public domain material in the way that you describe nor have I seen it done that way in articles that rely heavily on public domain sources (e.g. [[DANFS]]). --[[User:Kkmurray|Kkmurray]] ([[User talk:Kkmurray|talk]]) 05:03, 28 February 2008 (UTC)

::It certainly is possible to &quot;segregate&quot; public domain material, just treat it like any other copyrighted material: use quotations if you copy passages word-for-word, use in-line citations when you rely upon it as the source.  If you do not treat this source in that way, then all material in the article is suspect, because it is unclear which material is from what source or which material is new original research, not from any source at all.  By the way,the Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships (DANFS), often used in articles about ships, is itself a very-well-verified, well-maintained encyclopedia, and is better-than-average public domain material.  This, however, is not an article about a ship.  There exists inaccurate, outdated, really lousy public domain material as well, which I am familiar with.  I don't know about the quality of the material cited in this article, but certainly not all public domain material is encyclopedic.  Whether it is encyclopedic or not, you can (and in my opinion should) use quotations and treat it like any other source. [[User:Doncram|doncram]] ([[User talk:Doncram|talk]]) 05:22, 28 February 2008 (UTC)

:This entire article is plagiarized from [http://www.lbl.gov/Science-Articles/Research-Review/Magazine/1981/81fepi2.html]. This is not public domain material—LBL is operated by a contractor to the DOE and has its own copyright policies (its works are not automatically &quot;works of the federal government&quot;), and while LBL makes its materials available for public reuse they specifically clarify that it is not for commercial purposes, which is not public domain. In any case it is not being used in an intellectually honest way—this is largely the work of the historians [[John Heilbron]], Robert W. Seidel, and Bruce R. Wheaton, who deserve to have their authorship noted. This text should be blanked and re-written. --[[User:Captain Ref Desk|Captain Ref Desk]] ([[User talk:Captain Ref Desk|talk]]) 04:46, 19 March 2008 (UTC)

==Scaling up at Oak Ridge==
Could someone please verify:

&quot;Want of copper for the large coils to produce the magnetic fields prompted a solution possible only in wartime: Groves drafted 14,700 tons (13,300 tonne) of pure silver from a government vault for the purpose. &quot;
Should this read 14 700 lbs(fourteen thousand seven hundred)? Or maybe 14,7 tons (fourteen decimal seven)? Fourteen thousand tons of silver seems excessive, even in this context. [[User:Dvermeirre|Denis]] ([[User talk:Dvermeirre|talk]]) 14:28, 7 January 2009 (UTC)

:It's in the references. It's not all that much; remember that umpteen millions of silver dollars were around. Actually it's a perfectly sensible thing to do at any time, including peacetime: having the metal doing something useful rather than sitting in a vault is eminently sane. Security wouldn't be a problem in a top-secret military installation. And it was returned when no longer needed. So long as you don't need to spend it! &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt; The physical properties of silver actually make it better than copper for electrical wiring (and heatsinks and cooking utensils); the only reason silver isn't routinely used is the cost. [[User:Pol098|Pol098]] ([[User talk:Pol098|talk]]) 15:25, 22 April 2009 (UTC)

==Edit comment and question==
In Construction section, paragraph 6, the following sentence makes no sense to me, &quot;The first Beta racetrack and the third and repaired first became operational in March 1944, and the fourth in April 1944.&quot; Does it mean 1st Beta and the 1st (repaired) and 3rd Alphas? Please clarify. Thanks. [[User:Djmaschek|Djmaschek]] ([[User talk:Djmaschek|talk]]) 04:16, 7 September 2015 (UTC)
:WPMILHIST=B class. [[User:Djmaschek|Djmaschek]] ([[User talk:Djmaschek|talk]]) 04:22, 7 September 2015 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>gec3547xojo2ihd2hmlxhhg1jw3u8jt</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
