<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Mahan-class destroyer</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>6373488</id>
    <revision>
      <id>670567130</id>
      <parentid>643670041</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-07-08T20:11:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>RobDuch</username>
        <id>19476564</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Engineering Plant */ added remarks on steam conditions</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6249">{{talkheader}}
{{Article history
|action1=GAN
|action1date=01:32, 15 December 2013 (UTC)
|action1link=Talk:Mahan-class destroyer/GA1
|action1result=listed
|action1oldid= 586124554
|maindate=16 January 2015

|action2=FAC
|action2date=23:02, 7 August 2014 (UTC)
|action2link=Wikipedia:Featured article candidates/Mahan-class destroyer/archive1
|action2result=promoted
|action2oldid=620321245
|currentstatus=FA
}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Military history|class=FA|A-Class=pass|Maritime=y|US=y|WWII=y}}
{{WikiProject Ships|class=FA|importance=high}}
{{WikiProject Guild of Copy Editors|date=October 4, 2013}}
}}

== Dunlap class ==
See &quot;by which passed a shell hoist that revolved with the gun.&quot; I do not understand what action is being described here. Please clarify. [[User:Folklore1|Folklore1]] ([[User talk:Folklore1|talk]]) 13:40, 4 October 2013 (UTC)

:Unlike the Mahans, the Dunlaps differed in their incorporation of a base ring for each forward 5”/38 caliber gun through which passed a projectile hoist that rotated the gun. [[User:Pendright|Pendright]] ([[User talk:Pendright|talk]]) 22:32, 4 October 2013 (UTC)

== Dunlap ==
See the sentence beginning ”In the [[Battle of Vella Gulf]]&quot;. The person quoted should be named in the text. [[User:Folklore1|Folklore1]] ([[User talk:Folklore1|talk]]) 17:48, 4 October 2013 (UTC)

:Theodore Roscoe said, ”In the Battle of Vella Gulf, as this engagement was called, the enemy had not laid a hand on the American ships.”[86] [[User:Pendright|Pendright]] ([[User talk:Pendright|talk]]) 22:35, 4 October 2013 (UTC)

==B-class assessment==
G'day, as per the request on my talk page, I've have assessed this article as C-class on the Milhist rating scale, although it is very close to B-class, IMO. If you could add citations to the following areas, I'd be happy to upgrade the assessment:
* the paragraph ending with: &quot;At that point, she proceeded to the west coast for overhaul, leaving the yard in July 1944 for Pearl Harbor.&quot;
* the paragraph ending with: &quot;After participating in the bombardment of Iwo Jima in November 1944 and January 1945, she escorted an ammunition ship to the newly invaded Iwo Jima. There, Cassin did radar picket and air-sea rescue duty.&quot;
* the &quot;Ships in class&quot; table - these could either be added by including a citation at the top of each column, or by including them in each line. For instance, please see the tables in [[List of light cruisers of Germany]] (which is currently rated A-class on the Milhist assessment scale).

Please let me know if you have any further questions. Thanks for your efforts on the article. Regards, [[User:AustralianRupert|AustralianRupert]] ([[User talk:AustralianRupert|talk]]) 02:15, 10 October 2013 (UTC)
:I've updated the assessment now. Good work. Regards, [[User:AustralianRupert|AustralianRupert]] ([[User talk:AustralianRupert|talk]]) 07:10, 14 October 2013 (UTC)

{{Talk:Mahan-class destroyer/GA1}}

== Engineering Plant ==

&quot;The traditional destroyer machinery was replaced with a new generation of land-based machinery. This change ushered in a new steam propulsion system that combined increases in pressure and temperature with a new type of lightweight steam turbine, which proved simpler and more efficient to operate. These changes led to a ten percent increase in displacement over the Farraguts.&quot; Anyone know what pressure and temperature these boilers operated at. Most U.S. Navy ships built during the war, and survived into the Cold War, had boiler that operated at about 600 PSI, were called M-type separate sides/furnaces one for steam generation, one for superheat of the steam- the design allowed them to control the amount of superheat, and could get above 700 degrees Fahrenheit for the superheat. Was this perhaps the first class with this type boilers. 
[[User:Wfoj3|Wfoj3]] ([[User talk:Wfoj3|talk]]) 01:31, 16 January 2015 (UTC)

:I'm working my way through improving USN destroyer class articles. I'm including steam conditions for each class in an &quot;Engineering&quot; subsection in those cases where I have a good reference for them. Basically, steam conditions increased rapidly from 300 psi saturated in the ''Clemson''s of the 1920s through 600 psi/850 F in the ''Fletcher''s. In the 1950s this was further raised to 1200 psi/950 F. A guide to the increase with each class is at [http://destroyerhistory.org/goldplater/1500ton/ 1500 ton comparison at DestroyerHistory.org]. This site also includes the shipyards' General Information Books for many of the lead ships, some of which give steam conditions. The steam conditions for the lead ships are listed in the appendices of Friedman's ''US Destroyers: An Illustrated Design History''. There seems to be some variation among ships of a class, as some ''Mahan''s are listed at 400 psi and others at 465 psi.[[User:RobDuch|RobDuch]] ([[User talk:RobDuch|talk]]) 02:42, 26 June 2015 (UTC)

== Featured article? ==

I find this article lacking in significant ways. Ok, it's the first destroyer class type article to make it to FA status, so perhaps there's some work to be done to understand how a class with many members in it (as opposed to all the battleship class FAs (&quot;BFA&quot; from here on)) should be structured. I find this article to be completely overwhelmed by the Service History section breaking out all 18 ships of the class. This is not unprecedented in the BFAs, but is uncommon. Far more useful would be discussion of the class in general with regards to their service history. In service, were they tough? Under/over gunned? Maneuverable enough? Fast enough? How did they fare, as a class, in combat? Better than predecessors? The service histories ''of each ship'' are not very relevant in this context. Further, what about a specifications section? Perhaps something like [[Pennsylvania-class_battleship#Specifications|this]] or [[Almirante_Latorre-class_battleship#Specifications|this]]. The new steam turbine changed the propulsion picture for a few ship classes, but we spend just _one_ sentence on this propulsion plant. What? This article I think could be improved when compared to the battleship class brethren already in FA. --[[User:Hammersoft|Hammersoft]] ([[User talk:Hammersoft|talk]]) 21:22, 16 January 2015 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>9kolg13pr7aemrpxjs4pv6cgbw2817y</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
