<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>12th Light Horse Regiment (Australia)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>27681208</id>
    <revision>
      <id>739381275</id>
      <parentid>733349218</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-14T10:18:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mr Stephen</username>
        <id>863017</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* References */clean up, ISBN format using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="51129">{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2013}}
{{Use Australian English|date=January 2013}}
{{Good Article}}
{{Infobox military unit
|unit_name=12th Light Horse Regiment
|image=[[File:12thALHRbadge.jpg|220px|alt=Line drawing depicting a military unit badge with a kangaroo between the numerals 1 and 2, above a scroll with a latin inscription]]
|caption=12th Australian Light Horse Regiment hat badge
|dates=1915–19&lt;br&gt;1921–36&lt;br&gt;1938–43
|country= Australia
|allegiance=
|branch=[[Australian Army]]
|type=[[Australian Light Horse|Light Horse]]
|role= [[Mounted Infantry]]
|size=~ 500 men
|command_structure= [[4th Light Horse Brigade]]
|garrison=
|garrison_label=
|nickname=
|motto={{lang-la|Virtutis Fortuna Comes}}&lt;br&gt;(&quot;Fortune Comes&quot;)
|colors=
|colors_label=
|march=
|mascot=
|equipment=
|equipment_label=
|battles=[[First World War]]
* [[Gallipoli campaign]]
**[[Landing at Suvla|Suvla]]
**[[Battle of Sari Bair|Sari Bair]]
* [[Sinai and Palestine campaign]]
**[[Battle of Beersheba (1917)|Beersheba]]
**[[Battle of Mughar Ridge|El Mughar]]
**[[Battle of Nebi Samwil|Nebi Samwill]]
**[[Battle of Jerusalem (1917)|Jerusalem]]
**[[Second Transjordan attack on Shunet Nimrin and Es Salt (1918)|Jordan (Es Salt)]]
**[[Battle of Megiddo (1918)|Megiddo]]
**[[Battle of Sharon|Sharon]]
**[[Battle of Samakh|Samakh]]
**[[Capture of Damascus (1918)|Damascus]]

|anniversaries=
|decorations= 
|battle_honours=
|disbanded= 
&lt;!-- Commanders --&gt;
|commander1=
|commander1_label=
|notable_commanders= 
&lt;!-- Insignia --&gt;
|identification_symbol=[[File:12th Light Horse Regiment UCP.PNG|100px|alt=A two-toned symbolic rectangular image]]
|identification_symbol_label=[[Unit Colour Patch]]
}}

The '''12th Light Horse Regiment''' was a mounted unit of the [[Australian Army]]. It was raised in [[New South Wales]] in 1915 as part of the [[First Australian Imperial Force|Australian Imperial Force]] (AIF) for service during the [[First World War]]. After fighting at [[Gallipoli campaign|Gallipoli]] as reinforcements, the regiment served in the [[Sinai and Palestine campaign]] against the [[Ottoman Empire]], seeing action in several notable battles including [[Battle of Beersheba (1917)|Beersheba]], the [[Battle of Jerusalem (1917)|capture of Jerusalem]], [[Battle of Megiddo (1918)|Megiddo]] and the [[Capture of Damascus (1918)|capture of Damascus]]. In the aftermath of the war, the regiment was used to suppress the [[Egyptian Revolution of 1919|1919 Egyptian Uprising]], before being disbanded in late 1919.

In 1921, as part of a re-organisation of Australia's military following the disbandment of the AIF, the regiment was re-raised as a part-time unit of the [[Australian Army Reserve|Citizens Force]] based in New South Wales. It remained in existence throughout the inter-war years until it was amalgamated with the 24th Light Horse Regiment in 1936 as a result of manpower shortages. The 12th Light Horse Regiment was re-formed in 1938 and undertook garrison duties in Australia during the [[Second World War]], having been converted first to a motor regiment and then to an armoured car regiment. It was disbanded in 1943 without having seen action and was never re-raised. Its honours and traditions are perpetuated in the [[12th/16th Hunter River Lancers]].
{{TOC limit|2}}

==History==

===Formation and training===
The 12th Light Horse Regiment was established on 1 March 1915{{#tag:ref|A previous 12th Light Horse Regiment had been formed in Tasmania in 1903, although that unit is not a predecessor of the 12th Light Horse Regiment that was raised during the First World War. The Tasmainan unit subsequently contributed a squadron to the [[3rd Light Horse Regiment (Australia)|3rd Light Horse Regiment]] during the war and was later re-raised as the 22nd Light Horse Regiment.{{sfn|Festberg|1972|p=54}}|group=Note}} at [[Liverpool, New South Wales|Liverpool]], [[New South Wales]], and two days later began forming at [[Holsworthy, New South Wales|Holsworthy]] as part of the all-volunteer [[First Australian Imperial Force|Australian Imperial Force]] (AIF), which was raised for service overseas during the [[First World War]]. Drawing the majority of its personnel from [[outback]] New South Wales, the regiment was assigned to the [[4th Light Horse Brigade]] along with the [[11th Light Horse Regiment (Australia)|11th]] and [[13th Light Horse Regiment (Australia)|13th Light Horse Regiments]] and was placed under the command of Lieutenant Colonel [[Percy Abbott (Australian politician)|Percy Abbott]].{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=1}} Upon establishment, the regiment had an authorised strength of 25 [[Officer (armed forces)|officers]] and 497 [[Other ranks (UK)|other ranks]], who were organised into a regimental headquarters and three [[Squadron (cavalry)|squadrons]], each of which consisted of six [[troop]]s.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=2}} Armed usually with standard infantry weapons instead of swords or lances, and mounted on Australian [[Waler horse]]s, the [[Australian light horse]] regiments performed several roles and were similar to both [[cavalry]] and [[mounted infantry]]. They mainly fought dismounted, using their horses to obtain mobility that foot soldiers did not possess, but they could also conduct certain cavalry roles, such as scouting and screening, while mounted.{{sfn|Bou|2010a|p=14}}{{sfn|Gullett|1941|pp=29 &amp; 39}}

Following this, the regiment undertook basic training including weapons handling, ceremonial drill, mounted and dismounted tactics and regimental manoeuvres. In late April, they marched through the centre of [[Sydney, New South Wales|Sydney]] as part of a farewell before deploying overseas. On 11 June, after the brigade had concentrated, the regiment embarked upon the troopship [[SS Suevic|SS ''Suevic'']].{{sfn|Hollis|2008|pp=2–3}} After four days steaming, the ship put into [[Adelaide, South Australia|Adelaide]], [[South Australia]], where the regiment disembarked their horses due to concerns about death rates among horses travelling at that time of year. The men continued on their journey three days later, undertaking rifle and signals training on deck during the day. They crossed the [[equator]] in the early afternoon on 5 July; a short time later an epidemic of measles broke out.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=4}}

[[File:AWM A03421 12th Light Horse Regiment training Liverpool NSW c 1915.jpg|thumb|right|Members of the 12th Light Horse training at Holsworthy, 1915.|alt=A large formation of soldiers riding horses pass a shallow dam]]

On 11 July, the 4th Light Horse Brigade received orders to interrupt its journey to Egypt and instead disembark at [[Aden]], where an [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] attack was expected. They were briefly put ashore during this time and conducted a reconnaissance to the frontier, before undertaking a {{convert|6|mi|km|adj=on|abbr=on}} route march. The expected attack did not come and on 18 June the regiment re-embarked, arriving at [[Suez]] on 23 June. Moving into a camp at [[Heliopolis (Cairo suburb)|Heliopolis]], near [[Cairo]],{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=5}} after receiving a draft of 54 reinforcements and about 350 replacement horses, the regiment began a period of intense training and guard duties as they acclimatised to the local conditions.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=6}}

===Gallipoli===
Elsewhere, the [[Gallipoli campaign]] had developed into a stalemate. The regiments of the [[1st Light Horse Brigade|1st]], [[2nd Light Horse Brigade|2nd]] and [[3rd Light Horse Brigade]]s had already been sent to the peninsula as reinforcements; however, the failed [[August Offensive]] had resulted in heavy casualties for the Australians and further reinforcements were required. As a result, the regiments of the 4th Light Horse Brigade were broken up to make up the losses in the other brigades.{{sfn|Gullett|1941|p=54}} The troops were not initially informed of this, and following a train trip to [[Alexandria]] on 25 August they embarked upon the transport SS ''Marquette'' and sailed to [[Lemnos Island]] where they were transferred to ''Prince Abbas''. Early on the morning of 29 August, the regiment went ashore at [[Anzac Cove]] upon [[Lighter (barge)|lighters]],{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=9}} and later that afternoon received the news that they were to be broken up and distributed among the other New South Wales light horse regiments that were already ashore.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=10}} The Machine-Gun Section and 'A' Squadron were sent to the [[1st Light Horse Regiment (Australia)|1st Light Horse Regiment]] around &quot;Walker's Ridge&quot;, becoming that regiment's 'B' Squadron; 'B' Squadron went to the [[7th Light Horse Regiment (Australia)|7th Light Horse Regiment]] at &quot;Ryrie's Post&quot;, adopting the designation of 'D' Squadron; and 'C' Squadron went to the [[6th Light Horse Regiment (Australia)|6th Light Horse Regiment]] around &quot;Holly Spur&quot; and &quot;Lone Pine&quot;, becoming their 'D' Squadron. The Regimental Headquarters was absorbed by the 3rd Light Horse Brigade's headquarters, while Abbott took command of the [[10th Light Horse Regiment (Australia)|10th Light Horse Regiment]].{{sfn|Hollis|2008|pp=10–15}}

For the remainder of the campaign, about 600 men from the regiment&amp;nbsp;– including a batch of reinforcements that arrived in early October&amp;nbsp;– carried out mainly defensive duties before leaving with the last Australian troops to be evacuated from the peninsula on 20 December.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=23}} They did not take part in any large-scale battles, but were involved in fighting off a number of sharp attacks. The exact number of casualties suffered is not known, but 18 men from the regiment are known to have been killed in this time.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=25}}

===Sinai===
Following their evacuation from Gallipoli, the regiment was reconstituted on 22 February 1916 when all three squadrons assembled at Heliopolis.{{sfn|Australian War Memorial|}} Under a new commanding officer, Lieutenant Colonel [[John Royston]]&amp;nbsp;– a veteran of the [[Second Boer War|Boer War]] who had replaced Abbott after the latter had been sent to England&amp;nbsp;– the regiment began to re-form.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=26}} At the time of re-forming, it had been intended that the 12th would be assigned to the [[5th Division (Australia)|5th Division]] as its divisional light horse regiment; however, it was decided to reduce the size of divisional light horse components to a squadron, and the 12th were removed from the 5th Division's order of battle.{{sfn|Mallett|1998|p=63}} Although other units, such as part of the [[4th Light Horse Regiment (Australia)|4th]] and all of the 13th Light Horse Regiment, were sent to Europe to fight on the [[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]],{{sfn|Gullett|1941|p=54}} the 12th, along with the bulk of the Australian light horse units, were to remain in the Middle East, where they would take part in the [[Sinai and Palestine campaign]]. Initially, the regiment was not brigaded and served as a detached unit.{{sfn|Australian War Memorial|}}{{sfn|Gullett|1941|p=54}}

After conducting infantry training around [[Tel-el-Kebir]] in early April, the regiment crossed the [[Suez Canal]] along a new railway that was being constructed through the [[Sinai Peninsula|Sinai]] towards [[Palestine (region)|Palestine]]. Here it was established around [[Al Qantarah El Sharqiyya|Kantara]] and a position known as &quot;Hill 70&quot;.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=26}} The following month, Ottoman forces clashed with positions around the [[railhead]] and on 14 May, a British garrison was attacked at Dueidar, about {{convert|15|km|mi|abbr=on|order=flip|sigfig=1}} away from the regiment's positions at Hill 70. Tasked with relieving the [[Royal Scots Fusiliers]], two squadrons were dispatched. Delayed by a navigational error, and suffering from heat, the regiment arrived in some disorder. After this, they began work on constructing defences, while one squadron was detached to garrison [[Qasr el-Nil Street|Kasr-el-Nil]]; in early July they were sent on to Moascar.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=28}}

[[File:AWM H16043 12th Light Horse Regiment in Sinai Sept 1916.jpg|thumb|left|Men and horses from the 12th Light Horse Regiment rest at Mahadat, Sinai, in September 1916 following the conclusion of fighting around Romani. |alt=Rows of horses and men stand distant from the camera in a desert.]]

Later that month, the 12th were relieved at Dueidar and moved back to Heliopolis. While there, Lieutenant Colonel Harold McIntosh took command of the regiment following Royston's elevation to temporary commander of the 2nd Light Horse Brigade.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=28}} On 27 July the regiment, without its machine-gun section which had been detached to the 2nd Light Horse Brigade, was sent to [[Gebel Habeita]] to relieve the [[9th Light Horse Regiment (Australia)|9th Light Horse Regiment]]. After undertaking the first part of the journey to [[Seraphum]] by train, they marched the rest of the way.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=28}} In early August, Ottoman forces launched an attack in the [[Battle of Romani]]. During this fighting, the 12th Light Horse Regiment provided flank protection, carrying out patrols, and was not directly engaged except for its machine-gun section.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=29}}

In early September, the regiment moved to Bayoud where they were attached to a British column along with the 11th Light Horse Regiment, a regiment from the [[City of London Yeomanry]], and an artillery battery.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=30}} Under the command of Major General A.G. Dallas,{{sfn|Gullett|1941|p=200}} they carried out a [[Sinai and Palestine Campaign#Maghara Hills Raid, October 1916|raid in the Maghara Hills]] on an Ottoman position {{convert|60|km|mi|abbr=on|order=flip}} away. Upon arrival, after discovering that the Ottoman force was greater than expected, Dallas decided to limit the operation to a [[Demonstration (military)|demonstration]] rather than a full attack. Within this plan, the 12th was allocated the task of advancing on the right flank during the attack. They proceeded to advance across the open ground on their horses, before dismounting to ascend towards the high ground. As the Ottoman fire increased, the 12th provided covering fire with machine-guns and rifles while the 11th came forward using their bayonets to clear the defenders from the forward position. The light horsemen were then ordered to withdraw, instead of assaulting the main position.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|pp=32–33}}{{sfn|Gullett|1941|pp=201–202}}

In early October, while at Mageibra, the regiment received orders that they were to be remounted on camels and be re-designated as the &quot;2nd Australian Camel Regiment&quot;, but largely the regiment continued to refer to itself by its old designation.{{sfn|AWM 4 10/17/2|p=27}} This was due to a plan to convert both the 11th and 12th Light Horse Regiments to cameleers; however, it did not occur.{{sfn|Bou|2010b|p=152}} In late October, the 12th were sent to the rear to rest, arriving at the railhead at El Ferdan on the Suez. 'A' Squadron established itself there, while 'B' and 'C' Squadrons and the Machine-Gun Section were sent to Ferry Post. During this time they undertook frequent patrols, with 'A' Squadron permanently detaching a troop to Badar Mahadat.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=33}}

===Palestine===
In early 1917, the 4th Light Horse Brigade was reconstituted at Ferry Post on 13 February under the command of Brigadier General [[John Meredith (general)|John Meredith]]. Assigned to the brigade along with the 4th and 11th Light Horse Regiments, the regiment's time of operating as a detached unit came to an end;{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=34}}{{sfn|Gullett|1941|p=255}} they officially readopted the designation of 12th Light Horse Regiment at this time.{{sfn|AWM4 10/17/3|pp=1–8}} For the next month they undertook training exercises before joining the advance into Palestine,{{sfn|Australian War Memorial|}} while some men from the regiment were also detached to join [[Dunsterforce]] in [[Persia]].{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=34}} In April, the regiment took part in the [[Second Battle of Gaza]]. Assigned the task of attacking the Atawineh Redoubt early in the morning of 19 April, the regiment dismounted about {{convert|3.5|km|mi|abbr=on|order=flip|sigfig=1}} from it and advanced on foot. Initially, they made good progress and captured a ridge about {{convert|1.8|km|mi|abbr=on|order=flip|sigfig=1}} from their objective without even firing a shot. As the defensive fire grew more intense, the men were forced to the ground and began fire and movement drills. Spread thinly across a {{convert|900|m|yd|adj=on|abbr=on|order=flip|sigfig=1}} front with just 500 men,{{sfn|Hollis|2008|pp=37–38}} the 12th was dangerously exposed as machine-gun fire began to inflict casualties, checking the Australians' advance. Nevertheless, the regiment held its position throughout the day until being withdrawn to a nearby hill that night, by which time it had suffered more than 30 percent casualties.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=39}} These included the commanding officer, McIntosh, who was gravely wounded and subsequently died of his wounds. He was replaced by the second-in-command, Major Donald Cameron, who was later promoted to lieutenant colonel.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|pp=38–39}}{{sfn|Gullett|1941|p=321}}

The day after the attack, the 12th Light Horse Regiment dug-in and sent out patrols in preparation for a possible Ottoman counterattack. Although they were harassed throughout the day with sniper fire, the attack never came.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=39}} After three days they were withdrawn back to Shaquth, where they worked to improve defences and conducted patrols for the next fortnight before dispatching two squadrons in early May to attack an Ottoman foraging party at Esani. The attack proved unsuccessful, as the Australians' approach was spotted, allowing the Ottomans and their [[Bedouin]] workers to withdraw before they could be engaged.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=42}}

[[File:4th Light Horse Brigade Beersheba.jpg|thumb|alt=Mounted soldiers charge towards the camera over rocky ground|Light horse charge]]

A [[Stalemate in Southern Palestine|period of stalemate]] followed, during which time the regiment, along with the rest of the brigade, rotated between the forward position at Fara and other positions in support and reserve at Kukhari and Marakeb as preparations were made for a future offensive.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|pp=43–44}} The regiment's next major action came in October 1917. Conceived as part of an attack towards the Jerusalem to Jaffa line,{{sfn|Falls|1930|vol=2|p=27}} the regiment took part in the [[Battle of Beersheba (1917)|Battle of Beersheba]].{{sfn|Australian War Memorial|}} During this battle, along with the 4th Light Horse Regiment, the 12th Light Horse carried out a successful mounted charge, advancing over open ground late in the afternoon to get under the Ottoman guns and capture the town and its vital water supplies.{{sfn|Coulthard-Clark|1998|pp=134–135}}{{sfn|Perry|2009|pp=318–323}} Late in the afternoon, the 12th Light Horse Regiment advanced, according to historian [[Henry Gullett]], on a &quot;squadron frontage in three lines&quot; {{convert|300|-|500|yd|m|abbr=on}} apart, with the 4th Light Horse Regiment to launch a &quot;pure cavalry&quot; charge, the troopers advancing with bayonets in their hands.{{sfn|Gullett|1941|p=395}} Advancing over {{convert|6,000|m|yd|abbr=on|order=flip}},{{sfn|Coulthard-Clark|1998|p=135}} the light horsemen were subjected to rifle and machine-gun fire and artillery bombardment from the flanks and trenches to their front. Supporting artillery helped suppress the machine-gun fire from the flanks,{{sfn|Gullett|1941|p=396}} and the speed of the charge made it difficult for the Ottoman gunners to adjust their range. The Ottoman trenches were not protected with wire and after jumping over the trenches, the light horsemen dismounted and hand-to-hand fighting followed.{{sfn|Coulthard-Clark|1998|pp=135–136}}{{sfn|Bou|2007|p=108}} While most of the 4th Light Horse and some of the 12th Light Horse dismounted, the remainder stayed mounted, continuing their charge into the town.{{sfn|Gullett|1941|pp=398–400}} The British official historian claims &quot;more than half the dismounted troops in the town were captured or killed,&quot; while 15 of the 28 guns in the town were captured by the Desert Mounted Corps and XX Corps.{{sfn|Falls|1930|vol=2|p=60}} Over 700 Ottoman soldiers were captured and, more significantly for the Australians, over 400,000 litres of water secured. In achieving this, the 12th lost 24 men killed and 15 wounded;{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=59}}{{sfn|Gullett|1941|p=401}} 44 horses were also killed, while another 60 were wounded or became sick.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=60}}

The success at Beersheba significantly reduced Ottoman resistance,{{sfn|Australian War Memorial|}} but heavy fighting continued around Gaza and elsewhere, including the [[Battle of Tel el Khuweilfe]], and the regiment remained at Beersheba for four days to receive remounts.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=61}} Gaza fell in early November and, as Ottoman forces fell back, the British Empire troops followed them in pursuit.{{sfn|Australian War Memorial|}} The 12th advanced further into Palestine as part of the plan to [[Battle of Jerusalem (1917)|capture Jerusalem]]. On 7 November, during the [[Battle of Hareira and Sheria]], the regiment joined the 11th Light Horse Regiment in an attack in support of the [[60th (2/2nd London) Division|60th Division]] around Khurbet Buteihah, but was forced to halt their charge and dismount amidst artillery and machine-gun fire as their horses needed water.{{sfn|Gullett|1941|p=432}}{{sfn|Hollis|2008|pp=62–63}} The following day, the 12th was sent to Beit Hanun to contact the [[Imperial Service Cavalry Brigade]], before searching for water around Sin Sin and [[Al-Faluja|Faluje]], where they captured a number of Ottoman troops before rejoining the [[Australian Mounted Division]] at [[Huj, Gaza|Huj]]. On 10 November, the 12th provided support to the 11th Light Horse Regiment when they came under attack at Hill 248 by a strong Ottoman counterattack, which was turned back. After moving on to [[Summil|Summeil]] the next day, one of the regiment's squadrons received heavy fire while providing flank protection to the [[54th (East Anglian) Infantry Division|54th Division]] as it attacked to the south of [[Al-Tina|Et Tine]].{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=63}}

Early on 14 November, in the aftermath of the [[Battle of Mughar Ridge]], a reconnaissance patrol to Et Tine found it had been evacuated and the 12th occupied the town. In doing so, they secured a water source and a quantity of supplies, although a large amount of equipment was lost to a fire that had been set by the withdrawing garrison.{{sfn|Gullett|1941|p=473}} The 12th then took up an observation position at El Dhenebbe to support the British flank before moving to Wadi Menakh on 18 November to water their horses. They were then ordered to launch an attack around Latron during the [[Battle of Nebi Samwil]], but after moving to Abu Shushen where they dismounted, the regiment was recalled to Junction Station. From there, the following day amidst heavy rain they moved to Deiran. Three days later, the 12th encamped at Mejdel for a week of rest along with the majority of the Australian Mounted Division.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|pp=63–64}} After a brief respite, as the 4th Light Horse Brigade was sent to El Burj to relieve British forces there, the 12th went in to reserve; the horses were sent back to Deiran, and dismounted patrols and reconnaissance parties were sent out.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=64}}

[[File:AWM H15216 12th Light Horse at Beersheba 1917.jpg|right|thumb|Horses from the 12th Light Horse Regiment drink at Beersheba. |alt=A line of horses drink from a wooden trough]]

In early December, the 12th relieved the Scots Fusiliers in the [[Judean Hills]] to the north of Jerusalem. Supported by artillery, the regiment advanced and on 6 December established itself along the Khed–Daty–Kureisnneh line. Upon arrival, they moved into a defensive position about {{convert|800|m|yd|abbr=on|order=flip|sigfig=1}} from Ottoman positions.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|pp=64–66}} Initially, it had only been planned for the unit to stay there for one night and as a result most of the cold weather equipment had been left behind. Nevertheless, the stay was extended and as winter came to Judea, heavy rain set in and the temperature dropped. Redoubts were established along the front for shelter, while the men also took to caves in the hills briefly to escape the elements, although these were soon abandoned when they were found to contain lice.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|pp=64–65}} On 11 December, the 4th Light Horse Brigade, having been relieved by the 3rd Light Horse Brigade, was withdrawn back to Khed Daty, where they became the Australian Mounted Division's reserve formation. On 28 December, the brigade advanced to the Jurdeh–Kuddis–Nalin line to hold ground that had been captured as part of the advance on Jerusalem, and the 12th established itself at Kuddis.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=66}}

In early in January 1918, the regiment received orders to move to Belah, on the coast near Gaza. For the next three months they undertook training there.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=66}} In March, the 4th Light Horse Brigade, commanded by Brigadier General [[William Grant (general)|William Grant]], was inspected by the [[Duke of Connaught]] who, according to author Kenneth Hollis, likened the &quot;snap and automatic precision&quot; of their ceremonial drill to &quot;a battalion of Grenadiers&quot;.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|pp=67–69}} The following month they moved to Selmeh, near [[Jaffa]], to support the attack on the Ottoman position that had been established around Jiljulah and [[Qalqilya|Kalkileh]] on the [[Palestine Railways#Palestine Military Railway|railway line]] that stretched north in the direction of [[Haifa]]. Although the [[74th (Yeomanry) Division|74th Division]] made some progress on the flank, the regiment's involvement in the attack was called off due to heavy resistance and the 12th, along with the rest of the 4th Light Horse Brigade, was sent to the [[Jordan Valley (Middle East)|Jordan Valley]], which had been [[Occupation of the Jordan Valley|occupied]] by British Empire forces. Taking up positions near [[Jericho]], they then sent out patrols to the [[Jordan River|Jordan]] and the river el Auja.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=69}}{{sfn|Preston|1921|p=186}}

===Jordan and Syria===
In late April 1918, the regiment joined an [[Second Transjordan attack on Shunet Nimrin and Es Salt|attack on Es Salt]],{{sfn|Australian War Memorial|}}{{sfn|Hollis|2008|pp=69–70}} which was undertaken as part of a plan to capture the village so it could be used as a staging point for a further advance towards the railway junction at [[Deraa]].{{sfn|Coulthard-Clark|1998|p=145}} The regiment's role in the raid was to advance up the eastern side of the Jordan River to capture a crossing {{convert|19|mi|km|abbr=on}} to the north of Es Salt at Jisr ed Damieh to stop Ottoman reinforcements being sent to Es Salt from [[Nablus]].{{sfn|Coulthard-Clark|1998|p=146}} Initially, the operation met with success, and although two of the 12th's squadrons met strong resistance and were stopped at the bridge on the Es Salt track,{{sfn|Gullett|1941|p=605}} the village was secured by dusk on 30 April by troops of the 3rd Light Horse Brigade. Throughout the night, the 4th Light Horse Brigade assumed defensive positions: the 12th in the centre with the 4th on their left and the 11th on their right.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=71}} The following day, they were confronted by a force of around 4,000 Ottoman infantry along the Es Salt track, while another force of 1,000 infantry and 500 cavalry were further south, ready to force a second crossing.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=71}}{{sfn|Gullett|1941|p=615}} After coming under attack, and finding themselves hard pressed, the 4th Light Horse Brigade was forced back to the south,{{sfn|Gullett|1941|p=619}} exposing the rear of the troops holding Es Salt. Over the course of next few days little progress was made by the British Empire troops and, despite the arrival of reinforcements, the commander of the operation, Lieutenant General [[Harry Chauvel]], decided that it was necessary to withdraw from the position on 3 May.{{sfn|Coulthard-Clark|1998|p=146}} The regiment crossed the Jordan and two days later had returned to its previous positions around Jericho.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=73}}

Throughout May the regiment constructed defences around Musallabeh in temperatures as high as {{convert|50|°C|°F}}, and flies, scorpions, spiders and snakes also infested the regiment's camp.{{sfn|Perry|2009|p=397}} Many men from the 12th became sick with [[malaria]] and other conditions, before they were moved to [[Solomon's Pools]], where the climate was more bearable.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=76}} In late June, the regiment manned defences in the Jordan Valley before being sent to a camp amongst the olive groves at [[Lod|Ludd]] in early August.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=77}} While there, the regiment received cavalry training and was issued swords,{{sfn|Perry|2009|p=399}} along with the rest of the Australian Mounted Division.{{sfn|Bou|2007|p=119}}

[[File:General Chauvel leading march through Damascus (2 October 1918) (IWM Q012379).jpg|thumb|left|Chauvel enters Damascus on 2 October 1918.|alt=Soldiers on horseback trot along a road past several buildings watched by a group of civilians]]

The regiment departed Ludd on 18 September, taking up camp near Jaffa. Before dawn the next morning, the regiment led the Australian Mounted Division's advance towards Semakh and [[Tiberias]], moving by day to a position near Nahr Iskanderuneh where they rested until midnight. The 12th then trotted on to Liktera, {{convert|60|km|mi|abbr=on|order=flip}} behind the original Ottoman front line.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=78}} There the regiment rested again until midday before making for Keikur Beidas; encountering a number of surrendering Ottoman troops along the way, it arrived there in the afternoon but halted only briefly before continuing on to the mouth of the Plain of Esdraelon, where they bivouacked for the night. The next morning, the regiment moved to support the 3rd Light Horse Brigade, which had taken between 8,000 and 9,000 prisoners during the [[capture of Jenin]]. They also sent out patrols to the outlying villages and hills and established signal stations.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=79}}

On 22 September, following the 4th Light Horse Brigade's relief by the [[5th Light Horse Brigade]], the regiment was tasked with escorting 5,000 prisoners to El Lejjun before moving to Jisr ed Mejamie, along the Jordan River near its confluence with the [[Sea of Galilee]] at [[Lake Tiberias]].{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=79}} From there, in the early hours of 25 September, the 12th Light Horse Regiment, along with the rest of the brigade and one regiment from the 5th Light Horse Brigade, departed to conduct a dawn attack during the [[Battle of Samakh]] before rejoining the division's advance to Tiberias.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=80}}{{sfn|Bou|2007|p=121}} It was still dark when the advancing Australians came under heavy rifle and machine-gun fire from German and Ottoman positions near the railway station about {{convert|1.5|km|mi|abbr=on|order=flip|sigfig=1}} away.{{sfn|Perry|2009|pp=435–436}} In response, the 11th Light Horse Regiment conducted a mounted charge that was checked just short of the objective, and one squadron from the 12th advanced along the left flank on horseback, while the other squadrons attempted to draw fire. Once close enough, the squadron from the 12th dismounted and attacked with their bayonets, which forced most of the defenders out of the village, except the Germans defending the fortified railway station house.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=80}} At this point, the defenders raised a white flag of truce, and as several Australians from the 11th and 12th Light Horse advanced to take their surrender, the Germans manning the station killed them. The Australians then attacked, clearing the building, and later refused to bury the German dead, which amounted to 98,{{sfn|Perry|2009|p=437}} leaving their bodies to be looted by villagers.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|pp=80–81}} In the battle, the regiment lost one man killed and 10 wounded; losses suffered by the horses amounted to 61 killed and 27 injured.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=81}}

The regiment then moved towards the high ground on the western side of the Jordan River. Mid-morning on 25 September they reached El Menarah. In the afternoon, after the garrison was seen to withdraw, they advanced in concert with a number of armoured cars and at 3:00&amp;nbsp;pm the regiment [[Capture of Tiberias|entered Tiberias]], capturing 200 German and Ottoman troops and a large amount of stores.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=81}}{{sfn|Gullett|1941|p=736}} From there, on 27 September, they began the final advance to [[Damascus]], crossing the Jordan River and, early the following day, established a divisional bridgehead around Et Min during the [[Battle of Jisr Benat Yakub]].{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=83}} On 30 September, about {{convert|15|km|mi|abbr=on|order=flip|sigfig=1}} from their objective, the 12th, along with the 4th, mounted a [[charge at Kaukab]]. Forming up with the 4th on their left, the regiment attacked across a maize field towards a spur near the Jebel es Aswad, advancing on a position that they believed was strongly held.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|pp=84–85}} In the end, the defenders did not fire a shot before withdrawing and the Australians took the position without suffering a casualty, capturing 12 machine-guns and taking 22 prisoners.{{sfn|Gullett|1941|pp=746–749}} The 12th then spent the night south-west of the city and the following day, 1 October 1918, it was one of the first Australian units to enter Damascus, sending patrols in ahead of the main advance. A period of guard duty followed before the regiment was withdrawn to the city's outskirts, suffering heavily from illness.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|pp=86–88}} Shortly after this, on 30 October, while the regiment was moving towards [[Homs]], the [[Armistice of Mudros]] came into effect, ending the fighting.{{sfn|Australian War Memorial|}}

===Disbandment===
Following the end of the war, the 12th Light Horse Regiment remained in the Middle East for a number of months, during which time, under the command of Lieutenant Colonel Phillip Chambers,{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=94}} they were used to suppress the [[Egyptian Revolution of 1919|1919 Egyptian Uprising]].{{sfn|Australian War Memorial|}} During the uprising, the 12th carried out security operations to protect infrastructure in the [[Ismailia]] area.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=93}} As the situation was resolved, the regiment handed back its stores and equipment in preparation for repatriation back to Australia and most of their horses were transferred to the Australian Remount Depot at Moascar.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|pp=94–95}} Due to concerns about costs, availability of shipping and quarantine restrictions, the decision was made that the horses would not be returned to Australia, but that they would be sold to the British Indian Army for further service, or to local Egyptians.{{sfn|Perry|2009|p=497}} According to Hollis, though, many were also put down by the troopers due to concerns they might be mistreated.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=114}}

Mid-morning on 22 July the 12th Light Horse Regiment's personnel embarked upon the transport ''Morvada'' at Kantara. Cruising via [[Colombo, Sri Lanka|Colombo]], in [[Ceylon]], the regiment made landfall at [[Fremantle, Western Australia|Fremantle]] on 17 August 1919. There the men were granted a brief period of leave before the ship continued on to Sydney. After stops at Adelaide and Melbourne, they arrived on 28 August, and the regiment was disbanded.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|pp=95–96}}

During the war, the regiment lost 67 men killed and 401 men wounded.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=111}}{{#tag:ref|These figures differ slightly from those provided by the Australian War Memorial, which lists: 53 killed and 401 wounded.{{sfn|Australian War Memorial|}}|group=Note}} Members of the regiment received the following decorations: three [[Distinguished Service Order]]s (DSOs) and one [[Medal bar|Bar]]; five [[Military Cross]]es with one Bar; nine [[Distinguished Conduct Medal]]s with one Bar; 14 [[Military Medal]]s and 17 [[Mentioned in Despatches|Mentions in Despatches]].{{sfn|Australian War Memorial|}} One member of the regiment, Major Eric Hyman, was nominated for the [[Victoria Cross]] for his involvement in the fighting around Beersheba. The award was never approved and instead Hyman received a DSO.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|pp=100 &amp; 104}}

===Inter-war years and subsequent service===
In 1921, the [[Australian Army Reserve|Citizens Force]] was reorganised to replicate the numerical designations of the AIF units and perpetuate their honours and traditions.{{sfn|Grey|2008|p=125}} As a result, the 12th Light Horse Regiment was re-raised in the [[New England (New South Wales)|New England]] region of New South Wales and headquartered at [[Armidale, New South Wales|Armidale]].{{sfn|12th/16th Hunter River Lancers|}} In re-forming, the regiment drew lineage from the Citizens Forces' 12th (New England) Light Horse, which had existed parallel to the AIF light horse regiment and had remained in Australia during the war. This regiment, through a complex series of reorganisations, traced its lineage to the 6th Australian Light Horse Regiment, which had been raised in 1903 and perpetuated units that had contributed personnel to fight in South Africa during the Boer War.{{sfn|Festberg|1972|p=47}}

During this time, the regiment was assigned to the [[2nd Cavalry Brigade (Australia)|2nd Cavalry Brigade]], along with the 15th and 16th Light Horse Regiments.{{sfn|Palazzo|2001|p=102}} In 1927, when territorial designations were adopted,{{sfn|Stanley|}} the 12th Light Horse Regiment became known as the &quot;New England Light Horse&quot;. At the same time, the regiment adopted the motto of ''Virtutis Fortuna Comes'' (&quot;Fortune Comes&quot;).{{sfn|Festberg|1972|p=47}} Initially, the strength of part-time units was maintained through both voluntary and [[Conscription in Australia|compulsory service]],{{sfn|Grey|2008|pp=125 &amp; 138}} but after the election of the [[James Scullin|Scullin]] [[Australian Labor Party|Labor]] government in 1929–30, compulsory service ended and the Citizens Force was replaced with the all-volunteer &quot;Militia&quot;. The economic hardships of the [[Great Depression]] and reduced training opportunities resulted in a decline in the number of volunteers and consequently a number units were disbanded or amalgamated.{{sfn|Keogh|1965|p=44}}

Amidst the austerity of the inter-war years, the regiment remained in existence until 1 October 1936 when it was merged with the 24th (Gwydir) Light Horse to form the 12th/24th Light Horse.{{sfn|Festberg|1972|p=47}}{{sfn|Bou|2010b|p=245}} These two units were later delinked in 1938 as the Militia was expanded following increased political tensions in Europe.{{sfn|12th/16th Hunter River Lancers|}}{{sfn|Keogh|1965|p=49}} In March 1942, during the [[Second World War]], the 12th Light Horse was converted to a motor regiment, known as the 12th Motor Regiment.{{sfn|Festberg|1972|p=47}}{{sfn|Hall|1968|p=60}} In September 1942, it was redesignated the 12th Armoured Car Regiment,{{sfn|Festberg|1972|p=47}}{{sfn|Hall|1968|p=60}} and assigned to the [[3rd Armoured Division (Australia)|3rd Armoured Division]].{{sfn|Hopkins|1978|p=104}} During this period a process of mechanisation resulted in the last of the light horse units giving up their horses.{{sfn|Bou|2010b|pp=251–254}}{{sfn|Morrison|2006|pp=66–69}} Throughout 1943, the Australian Army was faced with a manpower shortage and as the Japanese threat to mainland Australia decreased many Militia armoured units were broken up and their personnel sent to other units as reinforcements.{{sfn|Hopkins|1978|pp=125–130}} As a result, the regiment was disbanded on 19 October 1943, having only undertaken garrison duty within Australia.{{sfn|Festberg|1972|p=47}}{{sfn|Hall|1968|p=60}}

When Australia's part-time military force was reformed in 1948 as the Citizens Military Force,{{sfn|Grey|2008|p=200}} the regiment was not re-raised in its own right, although an amalgamated unit known as the [[12th/16th Hunter River Lancers]] was established. Through this unit the 12th Light Horse Regiment's honours and traditions are perpetuated.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=viii}}{{sfn|Hall|1968|p=60}}

==Alliances==
The 12th Light Horse Regiment held the following alliances:{{sfn|Festberg|1972|p=47}}
* United Kingdom&amp;nbsp;– [[King Edward's Horse|The King's Colonials (Yeomanry)]];
* United Kingdom&amp;nbsp;– [[Royal Scots Greys]].

==Battle honours==
The 12th Light Horse received the following [[battle honour]]s:
* [[Second Boer War|South Africa 1899–1902]];{{#tag:ref|Inherited through predecessor units, having been originally awarded in 1908 to the 8th Australian Light Horse Regiment (New England Light Horse).{{sfn|Festberg|1972|p=47}}|group=Note}}{{sfn|Festberg|1972|p=47}}
* '''First World War''': [[Gallipoli campaign|Gallipoli 1915]], [[Landing at Suvla|Suvla]], [[Battle of Sari Bair|Sari-Bair]], [[Sinai and Palestine Campaign#Defence of the Suez Canal .281915.E2.80.931916.29|Egypt 1915–1917]], [[Battle of Romani|Rumani]], [[Sinai and Palestine campaign|Palestine 1917–1918]], [[Battle of Beersheba (1917)|Gaza–Beersheba]], [[Battle of Mughar Ridge|El Mughar]], [[Battle of Nebi Samwil|Nebi Samwill]], [[Battle of Jerusalem (1917)|Jerusalem]],  [[Second Transjordan attack on Shunet Nimrin and Es Salt|Jordan (Es Salt)]], [[Battle of Megiddo (1918)|Megiddo]], [[Battle of Sharon|Sharon]], [[Capture of Damascus (1918)|Damascus]].{{sfn|Australian War Memorial|}}{{#tag:ref|This list differs from that of Hollis who details the regiment's battle honours as: South Africa 1899–1900, Suvla, Sari Bair, Gallipoli 1915, Nebi, Samwill, Jerusalem, Jordan (Es Salt), Megiddo, Sharon, Damascus, Palestine 1917–1918.{{sfn|Hollis|2008|p=ii}}|group=Note}}

==Commanding officers==
The following is a list of the 12th Light Horse Regiment's [[commanding officer]]s from 1915 to 1919:
* Lieutenant Colonel [[Percy Abbott (Australian politician)|Percy Abbott]] (1915);{{#tag:ref|Following the end of the war, Abbott resumed command of the regiment after it was re-raised as a part-time Citizens Forces unit, remaining in command until 1929.{{sfn|Hogan|1979|pp=2–3}}|group=Note}}{{sfn|Hogan|1979|pp=2–3}}
* Lieutenant Colonel [[John Royston]] (1916);{{#tag:ref|Royston was a South African-born officer who had fought during the [[Siege of Ladysmith]] and later commanded the Western Australian Mounted Infantry during the Boer War. Later he served during the [[Zulu Rebellion]] before organising the [[Natal light horse|Natal Light Horse]] upon the outbreak of the First World War. After commanding the 12th Light Horse, Royston attained the rank of [[brigadier general]] and commanded the 2nd Light Horse Brigade temporarily, before taking command of the 3rd Light Horse Brigade, leading them until October 1917 when he returned to South Africa.{{sfn|Jones|1988|pp=472–473}}|group=Note}}
* Lieutenant Colonel Harold McIntosh (1916–17);
* Lieutenant Colonel Donald Cameron (1917–19);
* Lieutenant Colonel Philip Chambers (1919).{{sfn|Australian War Memorial|}}{{sfn|Hollis|2008|pp=183–188}}

==Notes==
;Footnotes
{{reflist|group=Note}}

;Citations
{{Reflist|3}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite web|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/units/unit_10571.asp|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110313194702/http://www.awm.gov.au/units/unit_10571.asp|title=12th Light Horse Regiment|work=First World War, 1914–1918 units|publisher=Australian War Memorial|accessdate=12 June 2010|archivedate=13 March 2011 |ref=CITEREFAustralian_War_Memorial}}
* {{cite web|url=http://www.lighthorse.org.au/resources/units-in-service/12th-16th-hunter-river-lancers|title=12th/16th Hunter River Lancers|publisher=Australian Light Horse Association|accessdate=12 June 2010| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20100612123244/http://www.lighthorse.org.au/resources/units-in-service/12th-16th-hunter-river-lancers| archivedate= 12 June 2010 |ref=CITEREF12th/16th_Hunter_River_Lancers}}
* {{cite web |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1012567/ |title=AWM 4 10/17/12: February to December 1916 (12th Australian Light Horse Regiment) |work=Australian Imperial Force Unit War Diaries, 1914–18 War |publisher=Australian War Memorial |accessdate=16 August 2015 |ref=CITEREFAWM_4_10.2F17.2F2 }}
* {{cite web |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1012960// |title=AWM 4 10/17/3: January to April 1917 (12th Australian Light Horse Regiment) |work=Australian Imperial Force Unit War Diaries, 1914–18 War |publisher=Australian War Memorial |accessdate=16 August 2015 |ref=CITEREFAWM4_10.2F17.2F3 }}
* {{cite journal |last=Bou |first=Jean |title=Cavalry, Firepower, and Swords: The Australian Light Horse and the Tactical Lessons of Cavalry Operations in Palestine, 1916–1918 |year=2007 |journal=The Journal of Military History |volume=71 |issue=1 |pages=99–125 |issn=0899-3718|publisher=Society for Military History |location=Lexington, Virginia |ref=harv |doi=10.1353/jmh.2007.0009}}
* {{cite book |last=Bou |first=Jean |title=Australia's Palestine Campaign |series=Australian Army Campaign Series # 7 |year=2010a |publisher=Army History Unit |location=Canberra, Australian Capital Territory |isbn=978-0-9808100-0-4 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Bou |first=Jean |title=Light Horse: A History of Australia's Mounted Arm |year=2010b |location=Port Melbourne, Victoria |publisher= Cambridge University Press |isbn=978-0-521-19708-3 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Coulthard-Clark |first=Chris |title=Where Australians Fought: The Encyclopedia of Australia's Battles |year=1998 |edition=1st |publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin |location=St Leonards, New South Wales |isbn=1-86448-611-2 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=Military Operations Egypt &amp; Palestine from June 1917 to the End of the War |last=Falls |first=Cyril |series=Official History of the Great War Based on Official Documents by Direction of the Historical Section of the Committee of Imperial Defence |others=A.F. Becke (maps) |year=1930 |volume=Volume 2 Part I |publisher=HM Stationery Office |location=London|oclc=644354483 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Festberg |first=Alfred |title=The Lineage of the Australian Army |year=1972 |publisher=Allara Publishing |location= Melbourne, Victoria |isbn= 978-0-85887-024-6 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Grey|first=Jeffrey|authorlink=Jeffrey Grey |title=A Military History of Australia|edition=3rd|year=2008|publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=Melbourne, Victoria|isbn= 978-0-521-69791-0 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Gullett |first=Henry |authorlink=Henry Gullett |title=The Australian Imperial Force in Sinai and Palestine, 1914–1918|url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1069924/ |series=Official History of Australia in the War of 1914–1918 |volume=Volume VII |edition=10th |year=1941 |publisher=Angus &amp; Robertson |location=Sydney, New South Wales |oclc=220624545 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Hall|first=Richard John|title=The Australian Light Horse|year=1968|publisher=W.D. Joynt &amp; Co.|location=Blackburn, Victoria|oclc=59504|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Hogan|first=Terry|chapter=Abbott, Percy Phipps (1869–1940)|title=Australian Dictionary of Biography |volume=Volume 7|publisher=Melbourne University Press|location=Melbourne, Victoria |year=1979|pages=2–3|chapter-url=http://adbonline.anu.edu.au/biogs/A070003b.htm |ref=harv|isbn=978-0-522-84185-5 |accessdate= 3 July 2010}}
* {{cite book|last=Hollis|first=Kenneth|title=Thunder of the Hooves: A History of 12 Australian Light Horse Regiment 1915–1919|year=2008|publisher=Australian Military History Publications|location=Loftus, New South Wales|isbn=978-0-9803796-5-5 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Hopkins |first=Ronald |authorlink=Ronald Hopkins |year=1978 |title=Australian Armour: A History of the Royal Australian Armoured Corps 1927–1972 |publisher= Australian Government Publishing Service |location=Canberra |isbn=0-642-99407-2 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Jones |first=Ian |chapter=Royston, John Robinson (1860–1942) |title=Australian Dictionary of Biography |volume=Volume 11 |publisher=Melbourne University Press |location=Melbourne, Victoria|pages=472–473 |chapter-url= http://adb.anu.edu.au/biography/royston-john-robinson-8290/text14529 |year=1988 |ref=harv| accessdate= 19 December 2011}}
* {{cite book|last=Keogh|first=Eustace|title=South West Pacific 1941–45|year=1965|publisher=Grayflower Publications|location=Melbourne, Victoria|isbn=|oclc=7185705|ref=harv}}
* {{cite thesis |last=Mallett |first=Ross |author= |date=1998 |title=The Interplay Between Technology, Tactics and Organisation in the First AIF  |type=Masters |chapter= |publisher=University of New South Wales |docket= |oclc=222659270 |url=http://unsworks.unsw.edu.au/fapi/datastream/unsworks:3244/SOURCE01?view=true |access-date=16 August 2015 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Morrison|first=James|year=2006|url=http://www.army.gov.au/~/media/Files/Our%20future/LWSC%20Publications/SP/sp307_Mechanising_An_Army-James%20C%20Morrison.pdf|title=Mechanising An Army: Mechanisation Policy and the Conversion of Light Horse, 1920–1940|series=Land Warfare Studies Centre Study Papers|volume=Study Paper No. 307|publisher=Land Warfare Studies Centre|location=Duntroon, Australian Capital Territory |issn=1442-8547|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Palazzo |first=Albert |authorlink= |title=The Australian Army: A History of its Organisation 1901–2001 |year=2001 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=South Melbourne, Victoria |isbn=0-19-551507-2 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Perry |first=Roland |title=The Australian Light Horse |year=2009 |publisher= Hachette Australia |location= Sydney, New South Wales |isbn=978-0-7336-2272-4 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |title=The Desert Mounted Corps: An Account of the Cavalry Operations in Palestine and Syria 1917–1918 |last=Preston |first=Richard |year=1921 |publisher=Constable &amp; Co. |location=London|oclc=3900439 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite web |url=http://www.army.gov.au/AHU/docs/A_Century_of_Service_Stanley.pdf |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110321213145/http://www.army.gov.au///AHU/docs/A_Century_of_Service_Stanley.pdf |archivedate=21 March 2011 |author=Stanley, Peter |title=Broken Lineage: The Australian Army's Heritage of Discontinuity |publisher=Army History Unit |work=A Century of Service: 100 Years of the Australian Army. The 2001 Chief of Army's History Conference |accessdate=21 November 2011 |isbn=978-0-642-70822-9 |ref=CITEREFStanley}}
{{refend}}

{{Australian Light Horse}}

[[Category:Mounted regiments of Australia]]
[[Category:Military units and formations established in 1915]]
[[Category:Military units and formations disestablished in 1919]]
[[Category:1915 establishments in Australia]]</text>
      <sha1>s2ou1zfthfdm1t5z4v2cskxna3diynq</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
