<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>27th Infantry Division Savska</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>46681894</id>
    <revision>
      <id>740754097</id>
      <parentid>731783407</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-23T02:30:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Books */http&amp;rarr;https for [[Google Books]] and [[Google News]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="37113">{{DISPLAYTITLE:27th Infantry Division ''Savska''}}
{{Infobox military unit
| unit_name = 27th Infantry Division ''Savska''
| image =
| caption =
| dates = 
| country = {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Yugoslavia}}
| countries = 
| allegiance =
| branch = [[Royal Yugoslav Army]]
| type = [[Infantry]]
| role = 
| size = [[division (military)|Division]] (26,000–27,000 officers and men)
| command_structure = [[4th Army (Kingdom of Yugoslavia)|4th Army]]
| garrison =
| garrison_label =
| nickname =
| patron =
| motto =
| colors =
| colors_label =
| march =
| mascot =
| equipment =
| equipment_label =
| battles =[[Invasion of Yugoslavia]] (1941)
| anniversaries =
| decorations =
| battle_honours =
| battle_honours_label =
| disbanded =
| flying_hours =
| website =
| notable_commanders = [[August Marić]]
&lt;!-- Insignia --&gt;
| identification_symbol =
| identification_symbol_label =
| identification_symbol_2 =
| identification_symbol_2_label =
| identification_symbol_3 =
| identification_symbol_3_label =
| identification_symbol_4 =
| identification_symbol_4_label =
}}

The '''27th Infantry Division ''Savska''''' was an [[infantry]] [[formation (military)|formation]] of the [[Royal Yugoslav Army]] that formed part of the Yugoslav [[4th Army (Kingdom of Yugoslavia)|4th Army]] during the [[Nazi Germany|German]]-led [[Axis Powers|Axis]] [[invasion of Yugoslavia|invasion]] of the [[Kingdom of Yugoslavia]] in April 1941. It was raised from the ''Savska'' military district, and was a very large and unwieldy formation which was almost entirely reliant on animal transport for mobility. Largely manned by [[Croats|Croat]] troops, many of whom saw the Germans as potential liberators from [[Serbs|Serbian]] oppression during the [[interwar period]], the division also lacked modern arms and sufficient ammunition.

Along with the rest of the Yugoslav Army, the 27th Infantry Division ''Savska'' began [[Mobilization|mobilising]] on 3 April 1941, and was still engaged in that process three days later when the Germans began an air campaign and a series of preliminary operations against the Yugoslav frontiers. These attacks ignited rebellion within the Croat troops of the division. Even the chief of staff of the division became involved, countermanding orders for the sabotage of a bridge over the [[Drava]] river at [[Zákány]]. The division briefly established a defensive line on the Yugoslav side of the river, but German troops began crossing on 7 April, forcing the division to begin withdrawing. A planned [[counterattack]] delayed the Germans for a day, but the division began to disintegrate due to [[fifth column]] actions, rebellion and desertion. When the German [[14th Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|14th Panzer Division]] broke out of the bridgehead at Zákány on 10 April, the 27th Infantry Division ''Savska'' numbered only 2,000 men, mostly Serbs. In a single day, the German panzers with overwhelming air support brushed aside the remnants of the division and captured Zagreb, covering nearly {{convert|160|km}} and meeting little resistance. On that day the divisional headquarters was captured, and the division effectively ceased to exist.
[[File:Operation25yu.jpg|thumb|350px|Map of the German invasion of Yugoslavia|alt=a black and white map]]

==Background==
The [[Royal Yugoslav Army]] ({{lang-sh-Latn|Vojska Kraljevine Jugoslavije}}, VKJ) was formed after [[World War I]] as the army of the [[Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes]] (Kingdom of SCS), when that country was created on 1 December 1918. To defend the new kingdom, an army was formed around the nucleus of the victorious [[Royal Serbian Army]] combined with armed formations raised in the former parts of the [[Austro-Hungarian Empire]] that joined with the [[Kingdom of Serbia]] to form the new state. Many former Austro-Hungarian officers and soldiers became members of the new army.{{sfn|Figa|2004|p=235}} From its beginning, the army, like other aspects of public life in the new kingdom, was dominated by ethnic Serbs, who saw the army as a means by which to secure Serb hegemony in the new kingdom.{{sfn|Hoptner|1963|pp=160–161}}

The development of the army was hampered by the poor economy of the kingdom, and this continued through the 1920s. In 1929, King [[Alexander I of Yugoslavia|Alexander]] changed the name of the country to the [[Kingdom of Yugoslavia]], at which time the army became the VKJ. The army budget remained tight, and as tensions rose across Europe during the 1930s, it became hard to secure weapons and munitions from other countries.{{sfn|Tomasevich|1975|p=60}} Consequently, at the time [[World War II]] broke out in September 1939, the VKJ had several serious weaknesses, which included reliance on draught animals for transport, and the large size of its [[military organisation|formations]]. For example, Yugoslav [[infantry]] [[Division (military)|divisions]] had twice the number of men of contemporary British infantry divisions.{{sfn|Tomasevich|1975|p=58}}{{sfn|Brayley|Chappell|2001|p=17}} These characteristics resulted in slow, unwieldy formations, and the inadequate supply of arms and munitions meant that even the very large Yugoslav formations had low firepower.{{sfn|Tomasevich|1975|pp=58–59}} Older generals better suited to the trench warfare of World War I{{sfn|Hoptner|1963|p=161}} were combined with an army that was not equipped or trained to resist the fast-moving [[combined arms]] approach used by the [[Nazi Germany|Germans]] in [[invasion of Poland|Poland]] and [[Battle of France|France]].{{sfn|Tomasevich|1975|p=57}}

The weaknesses of the VKJ in strategy, structure, equipment, mobility and supply were exacerbated to a significant degree by the lack of unity across Yugoslavia which had resulted from two decades of Serb hegemony,{{sfn|Tomasevich|1975|p=63}} and the attendant lack of political legitimacy achieved by the central government.{{sfn|Ramet|2006|p=111}} Attempts to address the lack of unity came too late to ensure that the VKJ was a cohesive force. [[Fifth column]] activity was also a serious concern, not only from the Croatian nationalist ''[[Ustaše]]'', but from the [[Slovenes|Slovene]] and [[Germans of Yugoslavia|ethnic German]] minorities in the country.{{sfn|Tomasevich|1975|p=63}}

==Structure==

===Peacetime organisation===
According to regulations issued by the Royal Yugoslav Army in 1935,{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=99}} the ''Savska'' divisional district was headquartered in [[Zagreb]] during peacetime, and was under the control of the 4th Army district also headquartered in Zagreb. The division was named for the [[Sava]] river, a tributary of the [[Danube]] that flows along the northern border of modern-day [[Bosnia and Herzegovina]]. In peacetime, the ''Savska'' divisional district included:{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=101}}
*35th Infantry Regiment, based in Zagreb
*36th Infantry Regiment, based in [[Varaždin]]
*53rd Infantry Regiment, based in [[Karlovac]]
*14th Artillery Regiment, based in Varaždin
*30th Artillery Regiment, based in Zagreb

===Wartime organisation===
The wartime organisation of the Royal Yugoslav Army was laid down by regulations issued in 1936–37,{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=104}} and the strength of an infantry division was 26,000–27,000 men.{{sfn|Tomasevich|1975|p=58}} A total of 11,200 horses and other [[Pack animal|pack]] and [[Working animal#Harness animals|draught animals]] were required to provide mobility for each infantry division. The theoretical wartime organisation of a fully mobilised Yugoslav infantry division was:{{sfn|Niehorster|2015b}}{{sfn|Terzić|1982|pp=104, 106–107}}
*headquarters
*divisional infantry headquarters, with three or four infantry [[regiment]]s
*divisional artillery headquarters, with one or two artillery regiments
*a cavalry [[battalion]] with two [[Squadron (army)|squadrons]], a bicycle squadron and a machine gun platoon
*a pioneer battalion of three [[Company (military unit)|companies]]
*an anti-tank company, equipped with twelve {{convert|37|mm|abbr=on}} or {{convert|47|mm|abbr=on}} [[anti-tank gun]]s
*a machine gun company
*an anti-aircraft machine gun company
*a signals company
*logistics units

Each infantry regiment was to consist of three infantry battalions, a machine gun company,{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=104}} and the divisional artillery regiments were animal-drawn and largely equipped with World War I-vintage pieces.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|pp=107, 119}} An artillery regiment consisted of four battalions, one of {{convert|100|mm|abbr=on}} light [[howitzer]]s, one of {{convert|65|mm|abbr=on}} or {{convert|75|mm|abbr=on}} [[mountain gun]]s, and two of {{convert|75|mm|abbr=on}} or {{convert|80|mm|abbr=on}} [[field gun]]s.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|pp=106–107}} The 36th Infantry Regiment and the 14th and 30th Artillery Regiments, which were administered by the ''Savska'' divisional district in peacetime, were earmarked to join other formations when they were mobilised, and the division was brought up to its wartime strength by the 104th Infantry Regiment and the 27th Artillery Regiment.{{sfn|Niehorster|2015b}}

==Planned deployment==
{{Location map+
| Yugoslavia (1939-41)
| width          = 300
| float          = 
| border         =
| caption        = Planned deployment location of the division
| alt            =
| relief         =
| AlternativeMap =
| overlay_image  =
| places         =
{{Location map~
 | Yugoslavia (1939-41)
 | label = 27th Inf Div
 | label_size = 75
 | lat = 45.98
 | long = 16.85
 | mark = Red pog.svg
 | position = right
 }}
}}
The 27th Infantry Division ''Savska'' was a component of the [[4th Army (Kingdom of Yugoslavia)|4th Army]] as part of the [[1st Army Group (Kingdom of Yugoslavia)|1st Army Group]], which was responsible for the defence of northwestern Yugoslavia.{{sfn|Geografski institut JNA|1952}} In the event of mobilisation, the 4th Army was to deploy in a cordon along the western sector of the [[Kingdom of Hungary (1920–46)|Hungarian]] border, with the 27th Infantry Division ''Savska'' positioned opposite the Hungarian village of [[Gyékényes]], between the confluence of the [[Mur (river)|Mura]] at [[Legrad]] and [[Kloštar Podravski]]. In this disposition, the divisional headquarters was planned to be located at [[Kapela, Bjelovar-Bilogora County|Kapela]], north of [[Bjelovar]].{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=257}} On the left flank of the division it was planned that the [[42nd Infantry Division Murska|42nd Infantry Division ''Murska'']] would be positioned opposite the Hungarian city of [[Nagykanizsa]],{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=258}} and on the right flank the [[40th Infantry Division Slavonska|40th Infantry Division ''Slavonska'']] was to establish itself opposite the Hungarian town of [[Barcs]].{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=256}} Border guard units in the division's area of responsibility would consist of the 3rd Battalion of the 393rd Reserve Regiment and 576th Independent Battalion.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|pp=256–258}}

==Operations==

===Mobilisation===
As the Axis invasion began, the 27th Infantry Division ''Savska'' had only commenced mobilisation,{{sfn|Barefield|1993|pp = 52–53}} and was largely in its mobilisation centres or moving to concentration areas.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=257}} On 4 April, the commander of the 4th Army, ''Armijski đeneral''{{refn|Equivalent to a U.S. Army [[Lieutenant general (United States)|lieutenant general]].{{sfn|Niehorster|2015a}}|group = lower-alpha}} [[Petar Nedeljković]] had reported that the division could not move for another 24 hours due to lack of vehicles.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=269}} Only a small proportion of the division was in its planned positions on 6 April:{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=257}}
*the divisional commander ''Divizijski đeneral''{{refn|group=lower-alpha|Equivalent to a U.S. Army [[Major general (United States)|major general]].{{sfn|Niehorster|2015a}}}} [[August Marić]] and his headquarters staff were mobilising in Zagreb
*the 35th Infantry Regiment (less its 3rd Battalion) was marching from Zagreb to [[Križevci, Croatia|Križevci]], with its 3rd Battalion still in Zagreb
*the 53rd Infantry Regiment, with about 50 percent of its troops and 15 percent of its animals, was moving by rail from its mobilisation centre in [[Karlovac]] via Križevci to Koprivnica, with its 1st Battalion detraining in Koprivnica
*the 104th Infantry Regiment was marching from its mobilisation centre in [[Sesvete]] via Dugo Selo to [[Bjelovar]]
*Two battalions of the 27th Artillery Regiment were in position in [[Novigrad Podravski]] and near Koprivnica, with the rest of the 27th Artillery Regiment still mobilising in Zagreb and Varaždin
*the divisional cavalry battalion was mobilising in Čakovec but had no horses, and the divisional machine gun battalion was mobilising in Zagreb but also had no animal transport
*the remainder of the divisional units were at their mobilisation centres in and around Zagreb

===6 April===
Early on 6 April 1941, the German [[XLVI Panzer Corps (Wehrmacht)|XLVI Motorised Corps]] launched preliminary attacks along the Drava between [[Ždala]] and [[Gotalovo]] in the area of the 27th Infantry Division ''Savska'' with the intention of securing crossings over the river, but they were unsuccessful.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=293}} By the evening, German successes along the Hungarian border made it clear to the Germans that the Yugoslavs would not be resisting stubbornly at the frontier. The XLVI Motorised Corps was then ordered to begin seizing bridges over the Drava right along the 4th Army front, including at [[Zákány]] near Gyékényes. These local attacks were sufficient to inflame dissent within the largely Croat 4th Army, who refused to resist the Germans which they considered their liberators from [[Serb]]ian oppression during the [[interwar period]].{{sfn|U.S. Army|1986|pp = 52–53}}

The continuing mobilisation and concentration of the division and the whole of the 4th Army was hampered by escalating fifth column activities and propaganda fomented by the Croatian nationalist ''Ustaše''. Some units stopped mobilising, or began returning to their mobilisation centres from their concentration areas. During the day, Yugoslav sabotage units attempted to destroy the bridge over the Drava at Zákány. This attempt was only partially successful, due to the influence of ''Ustaše'' propaganda and the countermanding of the demolition orders by the chief of staff of the 27th Infantry Division ''Savska'', Major Anton Marković.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=293}} The Yugoslav radio network linking the division with the 4th Army and flanking divisions was sabotaged by the ''Ustaše'' on 6 April, and radio communications within the 4th Army remained poor throughout the fighting.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=265}}

===7 April===
About 05:00 on 7 April, two to three battalions of the XLVI Motorised Corps commenced crossing the Drava at  Zákány,{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=308}} and attacked towards Koprivnica.{{sfn|Krzak|2006|p = 583}} In response to the German crossing, the 53rd Infantry Regiment withdrew towards Koprivnica and took up defensive positions in a series of villages including [[Torčec]]. In order to stop this German penetration and gain more time for the concentration of the division, elements of the 27th Artillery Regiment were sent to support the defensive line near Torčec, which was placed under the command of the division's commanding officer for infantry.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=308}} About 07:30, the commander of the Yugoslav 1st Army Group, ''Armijski đeneral'' [[Milorad Petrović]] met with Nedeljković at Zagreb and ordered him to go to Koprivnica and prepare a [[counterattack]] against the bridgehead, to commence at 15:00. The counterattack plan was unable to be carried out, as the necessary units could not reach their positions.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=308}}

About 10:30, the Germans reached the defensive line near Torčec, and fighting began.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=308}} A few [[Breguet 19]]s of the 4th Air Reconnaissance Group attached to the 1st Army Group which had survived an early morning raid on their airfield the previous day, mounted attacks on the bridge over the Drava at Zákány.{{sfn|Shores|Cull|Malizia|1987|p = 213}} After the Germans reinforced their bridgehead with two more battalions, they overcame the Yugoslav defenders, who had suffered significant losses and were running low on artillery ammunition. About 18:00, the 53rd Infantry Regiment withdrew to Koprivnica along with its artillery support, and remained in the town during the night.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|pp=308–310}} The bridge at Zákány was destroyed later that day by sabotage units.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=308}} At 23:00, following orders from Petrović that he was to attack on 8 April at all costs, Nedeljković issued orders for a counterattack to be carried out early on 8 April.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=312}}

===8 April===
On 8 April, the German XLVI Motorised Corps continued with its limited objective attacks to expand their bridgeheads on the 4th Army front, including at Zákány. The resistance offered by both flanking divisions was very limited. The 36th Infantry Regiment of the 42nd Infantry Division ''Murska'', which had been concentrating in the [[Ludbreg]] district northwest of Koprivnica, was transferred to the 27th Infantry Division ''Savska'', in an attempt to bolster the left flank of the divisional sector.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|pp=329–331}}
[[File:Skoda 75 mm Model 1928 (AM Žižkov).jpg|thumb|left|Two batteries of Skoda 75 mm Model 1928 mountain guns were deployed in support of the counterattack by 27th Infantry Division ''Savska'' on the Zákány bridgehead|alt=a colour photograph of an artillery piece in a museum building]]
On the morning of 8 April, the 27th Infantry Division ''Savska'' was deployed around Koprivnica. The 104th Infantry Regiment supported by elements of the 27th Artillery Regiment was deployed northeast of the town behind the Drava between [[Molve]] and [[Hlebine]]. The 2nd Cavalry Regiment of the [[1st Cavalry Division (Kingdom of Yugoslavia)|1st Cavalry Division]], which had been riding from its mobilisation centre in Virovitica to Zagreb, was allocated to the 27th Infantry Division ''Savska'' to assist with establishing its forward defences, and was deployed with two artillery batteries between the outskirts of Koprivnica and [[Koprivnički Bregi|Bregi]]. The 53rd Infantry Regiment, and the remnants of the 2nd Battalion of the 36th Infantry Regiment and the 1st Battalion of the 35th Infantry Regiment (totalling around 500 men), and the 1st Battery of the 27th Artillery Regiment were located in the town itself. The 2nd Battalion of the 36th Infantry Regiment had not yet arrived in Koprivnica, and the divisional cavalry squadron had reached as far as [[Ivanec]]. The majority of the 81st Cavalry Regiment, which were army-level troops, were on the road from Zagreb to Koprivnica, although its 1st Squadron, which had been transported to Koprivnica in cars on 7 April, was deployed as part of an outpost line forward of Koprivnica supporting the 1st Battalion of the 53rd Infantry Regiment. The divisional headquarters was located {{convert|5|km}} southwest of Koprivnica at [[Reka, Croatia|Reka]].{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=331}}

In accordance with Nedeljković's orders, Marić's 27th Infantry Division ''Savska'' was to undertake a counterattack against the Zákány bridgehead on 8 April. Supported by two batteries of [[Skoda 75 mm Model 1928]] mountain guns of the 27th Artillery Regiment, the attack consisted of three columns converging on the bridgehead. The right column, attacking from the area of Bregi, was to consist of the 2nd Cavalry Regiment supported by the divisional machine gun company. The centre column, consisting of the 53rd Infantry Regiment and the remnants of the 2nd Battalion of the 36th Infantry Regiment and the 1st Battalion of the 35th Infantry Regiment, directly supported by the 1st Battery of the 27th Artillery Regiment, would attack from Koprivnica. The left column, attacking from the vicinity of [[Herešin]], was to consist of the dismounted 81st Cavalry Regiment.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=331}} As promised support from the 36th Infantry Regiment, 81st Cavalry Regiment and army-level artillery had not materialised, Marić postponed the counterattack to 16:00.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=332}} By noon, a full-scale revolt had broken out within the flanking 40th Infantry Division ''Slavonska'', resulting in the capture of the town of Bjelovar and a large portion of the 4th Army headquarters by the rebels that afternoon.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|pp=329–331}} When the attack on the bridgehead at Zákány was eventually launched, only the 2nd Cavalry Regiment and the 1st Squadron of the 81st Cavalry Regiment remained in contact with the Germans, south of [[Peteranec]], and the 2nd Cavalry Regiment held that area throughout the night of 8/9 April, despite heavy German artillery fire. Of the other units involved in the counterattack, most were only at 25 percent of their full strength due to ''Ustaše''-influenced desertions sparked by the rebellion within the 40th Infantry Division ''Slavonska''. Two battalions of the 36th Infantry Regiment deserted during the day.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=332}}

===9 April===
 [[File:Heinrich von Vietinghoff.jpg|thumb|''General der Panzertruppe'' [[Heinrich von Vietinghoff]] commanded the XLVI Motorised Corps|alt=male in German uniform with peaked cap and toothbrush moustache]]
On 9 April, the left flanking 42nd Infantry Division ''Murska'' withdrew from the Drava to conform with the line being held by forward elements of the 27th Infantry Division ''Savska'',{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=348}} while the German XLVI Motorised Corps completed its preparations for full-scale offensive action by expanding its bridgehead at Zákány.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=345}} The cavalry units continued to fight the Germans around Peteranec, but the left sector of the divisional front line began to disintegrate. The commander of the right sector, ''Pukovnik''{{refn|Equivalent to a U.S. Army [[Colonel (United States)|colonel]].{{sfn|Niehorster|2015a}}|group = lower-alpha}} Mihailo Georgijević ordered his troops to hold their positions and went to divisional headquarters to ask approval to discharge the Croats in his units. Marić would not inform 4th Army headquarters of this idea, so Georgijević went to Zagreb to speak to Petrović, and to further urge him to withdraw all troops that still wanted to fight to a line south of the Sava. According to Georgijević, Petrović ordered him to tell Marić to consider disarming his Croat troops, and to continue to hold positions on the line of the Bilogora hills, but to conduct a fighting withdrawal towards Zagreb and Sisak if the German pressure was too great. The intent of these orders was not implemented, as fifth column elements changed the wording so that orders were issued to discharge Croat troops and to retreat towards Zagreb without fighting.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=347}}

About 09:00, Marić and Marković went to Zagreb to see Petrović, who ordered them to immediately return to their division and continue to resist the Germans. On the return journey, they encountered most of their division withdrawing towards Križevci, with the exception of the cavalry units still fighting north of Koprivnica. Marić halted the retreat, and established positions around [[Mali Grabičani]], making his headquarters at Križevci.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=347}} Georgijević dismissed his Croat troops and retreated with the rest of his force towards Zagreb, and the commander of the 104th Infantry Regiment discharged all his troops. In the afternoon, the hard-pressed cavalry units began to withdraw. About 14:00, the 2nd Cavalry Regiment withdrew to Novigrad Podravski via Bregi, but receiving a hostile reception from the Croat population, continued towards Bjelovar. About 18:00, the 1st Squadron of the 81st Cavalry Regiment withdrew via Koprivnica, reaching the rest of the division about 23:00. About 19:00, the Germans occupied Koprivnica without resistance. By evening, Marić's division numbered about 2,000 troops, the 36th Infantry Regiment and 81st Cavalry Regiment were widely dispersed, the 53rd Infantry Regiment had effectively ceased to exist, and his artillery regiment had only two horses to pull guns.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=348}}

Prior to its disbandment, the rebels in Bjelovar had used the telegraph station and telephone exchange in the town to issue false orders to parts of the 104th Infantry Regiment directing them to withdraw from their positions. The rebels also contacted the Germans by telephone and sent representatives to meet the Germans at the Drava bridgeheads, to advise them that the roads had been cleared of obstacles, and the rebels invited them to enter Bjelovar. Rebels and deserters began to converge on Bjelovar, bringing with them many Serb officers and soldiers who soon filled the town's jails.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=345}}

Elements of the 4th Army began to withdraw southwards on 9 April.{{sfn|Tomasevich|1975|p = 68}} On the evening of 9 April, ''[[Generaloberst]]'' [[Maximilian von Weichs]], commander of the German 2nd Army, was ready to launch major offensive operations from the bridgeheads on the following day.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=361}} His plan involved two main thrusts. The first would be spearheaded by the [[14th Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|14th Panzer Division]] breaking out of the Zákány bridgehead and drive towards Zagreb,{{sfn|U.S. Army|1986|p = 58}} and the second would see the [[8th Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|8th Panzer Division]] break out of the bridgehead in the sector of the 40th Infantry Division ''Slavonska'' and turn east between the Drava and Sava to attack towards Belgrade.{{sfn|U.S. Army|1986|p = 53}} On the night of 9/10 April, those Croats that had remained with their units also began to desert or turn on their commanders,{{sfn|Krzak|2006|pp = 583–584}} and in the 40th Infantry Division ''Slavonska'' on the right flank of the 27th Infantry Division ''Savska'', almost all the remaining troops were Serbs.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=346}} Due to the increasing momentum of the revolt, Petrović concluded that the 4th Army was no longer an effective formation and could not resist the Germans.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=345}}

===Fate===
Early on 10 April, ''Pukovnik'' Franjo Nikolić, the head of the operations staff with the headquarters of the 1st Army Group,{{sfn|Krzak|2006|p = 585}} left his post and visited the senior ''Ustaše'' leader [[Slavko Kvaternik]] in Zagreb. He then returned to headquarters and redirected 4th Army units around Zagreb to either cease operations or to deploy to innocuous positions. These actions reduced or eliminated armed resistance to the German advance.{{sfn|Tomasevich|2001|p = 55}} On the same day, the 14th Panzer Division, supported by dive bombers, crossed the Drava and drove southwest towards Zagreb on snow-covered roads in extremely cold conditions. Initial air reconnaissance indicated large concentrations of Yugoslav troops on the divisional axis of advance, but these troops proved to be withdrawing towards Zagreb.{{sfn|U.S. Army|1986|p = 58}}
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-185-0137-14A, Jugoslawien, Panzer III in Fahrt.jpg|thumb|left|German tanks brushed aside Yugoslav resistance|alt=a black and white photograph of a moving tank]]
Degraded by revolt and fifth-column activity, the 27th Infantry Division ''Savska'' numbered about 2,000 effectives when the German attack began. The 14th Panzer Division vanguard reached their positions in the Bilogora range around 08:00, and the remnants of the division began withdrawing towards Križevci under heavy air attack. When they reached the town around 14:00, they were quickly encircled by German motorised troops that had outflanked them. The divisional headquarters staff escaped, but were captured a little further down the road at [[Bojnikovec]]. The remnants of the 2nd Cavalry Regiment had to fight its way towards Bjelovar, but was attacked by German tanks on the outskirts, captured and detained.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=367}} The 14th Panzer Division continued its almost completely unopposed drive on Zagreb using two routes, Križevci{{snd}}Dugo Selo{{snd}}Zagreb and Bjelovar{{snd}}Čazma{{snd}}[[Ivanić-Grad]]{{snd}}Zagreb.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|pp=367–368}}

About 17:45 on 10 April, Kvaternik and SS-''[[Standartenführer]]''{{refn|group=lower-alpha|Equivalent to a U.S. Army colonel.{{sfn|Stein|1984|p=295}}}} [[Edmund Veesenmayer]] went to the radio station in Zagreb and Kvaternik proclaimed the creation of the [[Independent State of Croatia]] ({{lang-hr|Nezavisna Država Hrvatska}}, NDH).{{sfn|Tomasevich|2001|pp = 52–53}} The 35th Infantry Regiment of the 27th Infantry Division ''Savska'' was disbanded by its commander when he heard news of the proclamation.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=257}} By 19:30 on 10 April, lead elements of the 14th Panzer Division had reached the outskirts of Zagreb, having covered nearly {{convert|160|km|mi|abbr=off}} in a single day.{{sfn|U.S. Army|1986|p = 58}} By the time it entered Zagreb, the 14th Panzer Division was met by cheering crowds, and had captured 15,000 Yugoslav troops, including 22 [[General officer|generals]].{{sfn|U.S. Army|1986|p = 60}}
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1975-036-23, Jugoslawien, gefangene serbische Offiziere.jpg|thumb|A group of captured Yugoslav generals in Zagreb|alt=a black and white photograph of four older males in military uniform wearing peakless caps]]
About 19:45, the 1st Army Group held a conference in Zagreb, just as German tanks were entering the city. Nedeljković told Petrović that he could no longer hold his positions, but despite this, Petrović ordered him to hold for at least 2–3 days to enable the withdrawal of the 7th Army to the [[Kupa]] river. Nedeljković replied that he no longer had an army, and suggested that all Serb officers and men be ordered back to form a defensive line along the Sava and [[Una (Sava)|Una]] rivers. Petrović refused to consider this, but ordered the 1st Cavalry Division to form a defensive line along the Sava between [[Jasenovac, Sisak-Moslavina County|Jasenovac]] and Zagreb.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|pp=364–366}} The XLVI Motorised Corps encountered little resistance from the 4th Army, particularly from the 27th Infantry Division ''Savska'' and 40th Infantry Division ''Slavonska'' on its right, and by the evening of 10 April the whole 4th Army was disintegrating. Petrović wanted to dismiss Marić as commander of the 27th Infantry Division ''Savska'' due to suspicions that he was an ''Ustaše'' sympathiser, but could not identify a suitable replacement.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=364}}

On 11 April, Petrović and the staff of 1st Army Group headquarters were captured by ''Ustaše'' at [[Petrinja]], and the rear area staff of 4th Army headquarters were captured by ''Ustaše'' at [[Topusko]]. The personnel of both headquarters were soon handed over to the Germans by their captors. Nedeljković and his operations staff escaped to fight on for a few days, but the 27th Infantry Division ''Savska'' had ceased to exist.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|pp=386–388}} On 15 April, Nedeljković received orders that a ceasefire had been agreed, and that all 4th Army troops were to remain in place and not fire on German personnel.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|pp=444–445}} After a delay in locating appropriate signatories for the surrender document, the Yugoslav Supreme Command unconditionally surrendered in Belgrade effective at 12:00 on 18 April.{{sfn|U.S. Army|1986|pp=63–64}}

==Notes==
{{reflist|group=lower-alpha}}

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|30em}}

==References==

===Books===
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite book
  | last = Brayley
  | first = Martin
  | last2 = Chappell
  | first2 = Mike
  | title = British Army 1939–45 (1): North-West Europe
  | year = 2001
  | publisher = Osprey Publishing
  | location = Oxford, England
  | isbn = 978-1-84176-052-0
  | ref = harv
  }}
*{{cite book
  | last = Figa
  | first = Jozef
  | title = Civil-Military Relations, Nation Building, and National Identity: Comparative Perspectives
  | year = 2004
  | chapter = Framing the Conflict: Slovenia in Search of Her Army
  | publisher = Praeger
  | location = Westport, Connecticut
  | isbn = 978-0-313-04645-2
  | ref = harv
  | subscription = yes
  | via = [[Questia]]
  }}
* {{cite book
  | author = Geografski institut JNA
  | url = http://www.znaci.net/00003/385.htm
  | title = Istorijski atlas oslobodilačkog rata naroda Jugoslavije
  | trans_title = Historical Atlas of the Yugoslav Peoples Liberation War
  | chapter = Napad na Jugoslaviju 6 Aprila 1941 godine
  | trans_chapter = The Attack on Yugoslavia of 6 April 1941
  | publisher = Vojnoistorijskog instituta JNA [Military History Institute of the JNA]
  | location = Belgrade, Yugoslavia
  | year = 1952
  | oclc = 	504206827
  | ref = harv
  }}
*{{cite book
  | last = Hoptner
  | first = J.B.
  | title =  Yugoslavia in Crisis, 1934–1941
  | year = 1963
  | publisher = Columbia University Press
  | location = New York, New York
  | oclc = 404664
  | ref = harv
  | subscription = yes
  | via = [[Questia]]
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Ramet
  | first = Sabrina P.
  | year = 2006
  | title = The Three Yugoslavias: State-Building and Legitimation, 1918–2005
  | publisher = Indiana University Press
  | location = Bloomington, Indiana
  | isbn = 978-0-253-34656-8
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=FTw3lEqi2-oC
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Shores
  | first1 = Christopher F.
  | last2 = Cull
  | first2 = Brian
  | last3 = Malizia
  | first3 = Nicola
  | title = Air War for Yugoslavia, Greece, and Crete, 1940–41
  | year = 1987
  | publisher = Grub Street
  | location = London, England
  | isbn = 978-0-948817-07-6
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Stein
  | first = George H.
  | title = The Waffen SS: Hitler's Elite Guard at War, 1939–45
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=-KEtPlNQJNgC
  | year = 1984
  | publisher = Cornell University Press
  | location = Ithaca, New York
  | isbn = 978-0-8014-9275-4
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Terzić
  | first = Velimir
  | title = Slom Kraljevine Jugoslavije 1941 : uzroci i posledice poraza
  | trans_title = The Collapse of the Kingdom of Yugoslavia in 1941: Causes and Consequences of Defeat
  | language = Serbo-Croatian
  | volume = 2
  | publisher = Narodna knjiga
  | location = Belgrade, Yugoslavia
  | year = 1982
  | oclc = 10276738
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Tomasevich
  | first = Jozo
  | authorlink = Jozo Tomasevich
  | year = 1975
  | title = War and Revolution in Yugoslavia, 1941–1945: The Chetniks
  | publisher = Stanford University Press
  | location = Stanford, California
  | isbn = 978-0-8047-0857-9
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=yoCaAAAAIAAJ
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Tomasevich
  | first = Jozo
  | year = 2001
  | title = War and Revolution in Yugoslavia, 1941–1945: Occupation and Collaboration
  | publisher = Stanford University Press
  | location = Stanford, California
  | isbn = 978-0-8047-3615-2
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=fqUSGevFe5MC
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | author = U.S. Army
  | url = http://www.history.army.mil/books/wwii/balkan/intro.htm
  | title = The German Campaigns in the Balkans (Spring 1941)
  | publisher = United States Army Center of Military History
  | location = Washington, D.C.
  | id = CMH Pub 104-4
  | year = 1986
  | oclc= 16940402
  | origyear = 1953
  | ref = harv
  }}
{{refend}}

===Journals and papers===
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite journal | last = Barefield | first = Michael R. | title = Overwhelming Force, Indecisive Victory: The German Invasion of Yugoslavia, 1941 | publisher = School of Advanced Military Studies, United States Army Command and General Staff College |location = Fort Leavenworth, Kansas | url = http://www.dtic.mil/cgi-bin/GetTRDoc?AD=ADA274019 | date = May 1993  |oclc=32251055 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite journal | last = Krzak | first = Andrzej | title = Operation &quot;Marita&quot;: The Attack Against Yugoslavia in 1941 | journal = The Journal of Slavic Military Studies | year = 2006 | volume = 19 | issue = 3 | pages = 543–600 | issn = 1351-8046 | ref = harv | doi=10.1080/13518040600868123}}
{{refend}}

===Websites===
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite web
| url =  http://www.niehorster.org/040_yugoslavia/_ranks.htm
| title = Royal Yugoslav Armed Forces Ranks
| accessdate = 7 December 2015
| publisher  = Dr. Leo Niehorster
| year   = 2015a
| last = Niehorster
| first = Dr. Leo
| ref = harv
}}
* {{cite web
| url =  http://www.niehorster.org/040_yugoslavia/41_org/div-inf/_div-inf.html
| title = Royal Yugoslavian Army Infantry Division 6th April 1941
| accessdate = 7 December 2015
| publisher  = Dr. Leo Niehorster
| year   = 2015b
| last = Niehorster
| first = Dr. Leo
| ref = harv
}}
{{refend}}
{{good article}}

[[Category:Military units and formations of Yugoslavia in World War II]]
[[Category:Military units and formations disestablished in 1941]]</text>
      <sha1>sljnnwwby8f6qirnawecr6n0tag4p2i</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
