<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>2/15th Battalion (Australia)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>36380570</id>
    <revision>
      <id>733346088</id>
      <parentid>733019434</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-07T05:10:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Hawkeye7</username>
        <id>302229</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* References */ Jeffrey Grey</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="34368">{{good article}}
{{Other uses|15th Battalion (Australia)}}
{{Infobox military unit
|unit_name=2/15th Battalion
|image=[[File:2-15th Inf Bn at Tripoli in Syria (AWM image 024142).jpg|250px|alt=Soldiers marching on a road through an arid area]]
|caption=Troops from the 2/15th Battalion at Tripoli, Syria, April 1942
|country=Australia
|allegiance=
|type=[[Infantry]]
|branch=[[Australian Army]]
|dates=1940–46
|specialization=
|command_structure=[[20th Brigade (Australia)|20th Brigade]], [[7th Division (Australia)|7th Division]]&lt;br&gt;20th Brigade, [[9th Division (Australia)|9th Division]]
|size=~800–900 personnel{{#tag:ref|By the start of World War II, the authorised strength of an Australian infantry battalion was 910 men all ranks; later in the war it fell to 803.{{sfn|Palazzo|2004|p=94}}|group=Note}}
|current_commander=
|garrison=
|ceremonial_chief=
|ceremonial_chief_label=
|nickname=
|motto=''Caveant Hostes'' (Let Enemies Beware){{sfn|Austin|1995|p=1}}
|colors=
|identification_symbol=[[File:2-15th Battalion original unit colour patch.jpg|100px|alt=A multi-toned rectangular organisational symbol inside a diamond of grey]]
|identification_symbol_label=[[Unit Colour Patch]] (1940–42)
|identification_symbol_2= [[File:2 15th Battalion Australia Unit Colour Patch.png|100px|alt=A multi-toned 'T' shaped organisational symbol]]
|identification_symbol_2_label=(1942–46)
|march=
|mascot=
|battles=World War II
*[[Siege of Tobruk]]
*[[First Battle of El Alamein]]
*[[Second Battle of El Alamein]]
*[[Huon Peninsula campaign]]
*[[Borneo Campaign (1945)|Borneo Campaign]]
|notable_commanders=
|anniversaries=
}}

The '''2/15th Battalion''' was an [[infantry]] [[battalion]] of the [[Australian Army]] that served during [[World War II]]. Formed in May 1940 primarily from [[Queensland]] volunteers, the battalion saw action in [[North African campaign|North Africa]] in 1941–42 as part of the [[20th Brigade (Australia)|20th Brigade]], which was part of the [[7th Division (Australia)|7th Division]] before being reassigned to the [[9th Division (Australia)|9th Division]].

After completing training in Palestine, in early 1941, the 2/15th took up positions along the front line in the [[Libyan Desert|Western Desert]], before being pushed back to [[Tobruk]]. Between April and October 1941, along with a garrison of British and other Australian personnel, the battalion helped to hold the strategically important port, which had been surrounded following the landing of German troops at [[Tripoli]]. It was withdrawn by sea in late October 1941 as the 9th Division was relieved by the British [[70th Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|70th Division]]. Following its withdrawal from Tobruk, the battalion re-formed at [[Gaza City|Gaza]] before undertaking garrison duties in Syria. In mid-1942, the 2/15th returned to North Africa to fight in the [[First Battle of El Alamein|First]] and [[Second Battle of El Alamein|Second Battles of El Alamein]].

In early 1943, the 2/15th returned to Australia and was re-organised and re-trained for jungle warfare. It took part in campaigns against the Japanese in [[New Guinea campaign|New Guinea]] in 1943–44 and [[Borneo campaign (1945)|Borneo]] in 1945, before being disbanded in 1946.

==History==

===Formation===
The 2/15th Battalion{{#tag:ref|The numerical designation of 2nd AIF units was prefixed by &quot;2/&quot;, which was used to set them apart from Militia units with corresponding numerical designations that had no prefix.{{sfn|Long|1952|p=51}} |group=Note}} was raised at [[Victoria Barracks, Brisbane|Victoria Barracks]] in [[Brisbane, Queensland|Brisbane]] on 26 April 1940 from [[Second Australian Imperial Force]] (2nd AIF) volunteers. It was one of three infantry battalions assigned to the [[20th Brigade (Australia)|20th Brigade]] that were initially part of the [[7th Division (Australia)|7th Division]], the other two being the [[2/13th Battalion (Australia)|2/13th]] and [[2/17th Battalion (Australia)|2/17th Battalions]].{{sfn|Austin|1995|p=2}}&lt;ref name=AWM&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.awm.gov.au/units/unit_11266.asp |title=2/15th Battalion  |work=Second World War, 1939–1945 units |publisher=Australian War Memorial |accessdate=11 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; The battalion had an authorised strength of around 900 personnel like other Australian infantry battalions of the time,{{sfn|Long|1952| p=52}} and was organised into four rifle [[Company (military unit)|companies]]&amp;nbsp;– designated 'A' through to 'D'&amp;nbsp;– each consisting of three [[platoon]]s; these were supported by a battalion headquarters and a headquarters company with six specialist platoons: signals, [[Assault pioneer|pioneer]], anti-aircraft, transport, administrative and [[Mortar (weapon)|mortars]].{{sfn|Kuring |2004|p=494}}

Upon formation, the 2/15th was placed under the command of [[Lieutenant Colonel]] Robert Marlan, an [[Australian Staff Corps]] officer of the Permanent Military Forces who arrived on promotion from [[major]], having previously served in World War I with the [[20th Battalion (Australia)|20th Battalion]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/people/P10680719/ |title=Lieutenant Colonel Robert Francis Marlan |work=People |publisher=Australian War Memorial |accessdate=28 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=wardiarymay40&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1025657/?image=2 |title=AWM52 8/3/15/6: May&amp;nbsp;– June 1940  |work=Unit war diaries |publisher=Australian War Memorial |accessdate=28 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; The colours initially chosen for the battalion's [[Unit Colour Patch]] (UCP) were the same as those of the [[15th Battalion (Australia)|15th Battalion]], a unit that had served during World War I before being raised as a [[Australian Army Reserve|Militia]] formation in 1921. These colours were initially purple and red in a diamond shape, but after representations from World War I veterans the colour patch was changed to brown over dark blue, in a rectangle shape.{{sfn|Austin|1995|pp=14–15}} The patch was placed inside a grey diamond border added to distinguish the battalion from its Militia counterpart; this would change following the unit's involvement in the fighting at [[Tobruk]], when it adopted a 'T'-shaped UCP consisting of blue and green.{{sfn|Long |1952| pp= 321–323}}

[[File:Australian 2-15th Battalion signallers at Sydney December 1940 (AWM photo 005560).jpg|thumb|left|alt=Soldiers in service dress uniform stand near a train |Signallers from the 2/15th Battalion prior to embarkation on the ''Queen Mary'' in [[Sydney, New South Wales|Sydney]], December 1940]]

Following the battalion's establishment, Marlan set about choosing a cadre of senior commissioned and non-commissioned personnel around which to build the battalion. These personnel included the battalion second-in-command, the [[quartermaster]] and [[adjutant]], as well as senior enlisted soldiers to undertake administrative and instructional work. These were recruited from several of the existing Queensland-based Militia battalions including the [[25th Battalion (Australia)|25th]], [[42nd Battalion (Australia)|42nd]] and [[47th Battalion (Australia)|47th Battalions]]. One member recruited at the time had served with the 15th Battalion that had been raised as part of the [[First Australian Imperial Force]], during World War I.{{sfn|Austin|1995|pp=2–3}}

After the first groups of personnel began arriving at [[Redbank, Queensland|Redbank]], in south-east [[Queensland]], in the middle of May, the battalion's headquarters moved to the camp and basic training commenced in June under instructors from the [[Australian Instructional Corps]].&lt;ref name=wardiarymay40/&gt; In early July, the majority of the battalion was transported by train to [[Pinkenba]], and from there to [[Darwin, Northern Territory|Darwin]], in Australia's north, aboard the troopship [[SS Zealandia (1910)|''Zealandia'']].&lt;ref name=wardiaryjuly40&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1025658/ |title=AWM52 8/3/15/7: July 1940 |work=Unit war diaries |publisher=Australian War Memorial |accessdate=28 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tasked with defending the port and its surrounds, the battalion was based around Vestey's meatworks near [[Mindil Beach]], and in the months that followed was occupied with vital asset protection and area defence in between individual and collective training exercises. Personnel were joined by the majority of their vehicles, including 14 tracked [[Universal carrier|Bren carriers]] in August, as well as a group of reinforcements. In October, elements of the battalion were used as stevedores during a wharf labourers' strike.{{sfn|Austin|1995|pp=10–22}}

In the absence of the Darwin personnel, the battalion's rear details shifted from Redbank to [[Grovely railway station|Grovely]] where route marches were carried out in the [[Samford Valley]]. In late October, the rear details personnel returned to Redbank at the end of the month where more equipment was received. The main body of the battalion remained in Darwin, forming part of the town's defensive garrison. They were relieved by the [[2/25th Battalion (Australia)|2/25th Battalion]] in late October 1940,{{sfn|Austin|1995|p=23}} and embarked again on the ''Zealandia''. Sailing via [[Bowen, Queensland|Bowen]] where shore leave was granted, the 2/15th reached Hamilton, in Brisbane, in early November to marry up with the rear details at Redbank.&lt;ref name=wardiaryoct&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1025661/ |title=AWM52 8/3/15/10: October&amp;nbsp;– November 1940 |work=Unit war diaries|publisher=Australian War Memorial |accessdate=28 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Further training was undertaken at Redbank at this time before the whole battalion entrained for Brisbane on Christmas Day, embarking aboard the [[RMS Queen Mary|''Queen Mary'']] bound for Sydney. There, the ship joined up with a larger convoy that was bound for the [[Mediterranean and Middle East theatre of World War II|Middle East theatre]].&lt;ref name=wardiarydecjan41&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1025662/ |title=AWM52 8/3/15/11: December 1940&amp;nbsp;– January 1941 |work=Unit war diaries|publisher=Australian War Memorial |accessdate=28 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Middle East===
Sailing via [[Colombo]], the battalion disembarked in [[Bombay]], transferring to the [[HMT Rohna|''Rohna'']] for the remainder of the journey. Transitting the [[Suez Canal]], it disembarked at [[El-Qantarah el-Sharqiyya|El Kantara]], in Egypt, in February 1941. En route to the Middle East, the 20th Brigade was reassigned to the [[9th Division (Australia)|9th Division]],&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; as part of a reorganisation of the Australian divisions in the Middle East prior to [[I Corps (Australia)|I Corps]]' deployment to [[Battle of Greece|Greece]].{{sfn|Wilmot|1993|p=68}} Upon arrival in Egypt, the battalion moved to a base in [[Gaza City|Gaza]] dubbed Kilo 89, where it concentrated with the 2/13th and 2/17th Battalions, which had arrived earlier&lt;ref name=wardiaryfebapr41&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1025663/ |title=AWM52 8/3/15/12: February&amp;nbsp;– April 1941 |work=Unit war diaries|publisher=Australian War Memorial |accessdate=28 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; in Palestine as the 9th Division attempted to make good its equipment and training deficiencies.{{sfn|Thompson|2010|p=112}} The battalion's war equipment, including vehicles, arrived in mid-February and throughout the month the troops were introduced to the [[Bren light machine gun]], firing it for the first time at the Jaffa Range and practicing constructing defensive systems in preparation for desert warfare. Individual training undertaken at this time was aimed at identifying those who would be unfit for the coming battle, and many were subsequently transferred to the divisional guard battalion.{{sfn|Austin|1995|p=37}}

[[File:Alexander inspects the Australian 2-13th and 2-15th Battalions (AWM image 024882).jpg|thumb|right|alt=Soldiers on parade in the desert |Troops from the 2/13th and 2/15th Battalions on parade, August 1942]]

In early March 1941, the 2/15th entrained at Gaza and moved to [[Mersa Matruh]],&lt;ref name=wardiaryfebapr41/&gt; as the 9th Division began to relieve the [[6th Division (Australia)|6th Division]] along the front line in the [[Libyan Desert|Western Desert]] so that the latter could be transferred to Greece, where a [[Battle of Greece|German invasion]] was expected. A few days later the battalion was moved to Tobruk. From there it moved by road in captured Italian vehicles to [[Derna, Libya|Derna]] and on to Tochra, then [[Benghazi]], and eventually [[Marj|Barce]].&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; Throughout early April, the 2/15th became involved in the large-scale withdrawal that followed the [[Operation Sonnenblume|landing of German forces]] around [[Tripoli]] as part of Axis efforts to reinforce the Italians in North Africa following British gains in  western Egypt and [[Cyrenaica]] during [[Operation Compass]] in 1940–41. The battalion subsequently fell back east along the coast towards Tobruk. During the retreat about 180 men, including the battalion's commanding officer, Marlan, were taken prisoner when their headquarters was surrounded by a force of 18 tanks and unsuccessfully attempted to fight their way out.{{sfn|Wilmot|1993|p=78}} These men spent several years in captivity, being held initially in camps in North Africa before moving to Italy and later Germany; some managed to escape either in North Africa, or from Italy; several eventually rejoined the battalion, while others linked up with [[Italian resistance movement|Italian]] or [[Yugoslav Partisans|Yugoslavian partisans]] with whom they fought against German forces later in the war.{{sfn|Austin|1995|pp=178–208}}{{sfn|Field|1966|pp=768–769}}

Lieutenant Colonel Robert Ogle took over command of the battalion following Marlan's capture.{{sfn|Maughan|1966|p=88}} It subsequently joined the [[Siege of Tobruk|defence of Tobruk]], as part of the defensive garrison that held the strategically important port after it was placed under siege by the advancing German and Italian forces. The battalion remained there for over six months conducting patrols and raids, and holding positions around the perimeter until late October 1941, when the bulk of the 9th Division, less the 2/13th Battalion and two companies from the 2/15th, were withdrawn by sea and replaced by British troops from the [[70th Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|70th Division]].{{sfn|Wilmot|1993|pp=281–289}} The 2/15th's casualties during the withdrawal from Benghazi and the siege of Torbuk amounted to 45 killed in action or died of wounds, one accidentally killed, 103 wounded in action and 205 captured.{{sfn|Johnston|2002|p=248}}

The 2/15th was subsequently withdrawn to Gaza, where it stayed into the new year, before moving to Syria, where it formed part of the Allied occupation force established there at the end of the [[Syria–Lebanon campaign]]. In July 1942, in the face of a heavy German onslaught that threatened to break through to [[Suez]], the 9th Division was hurriedly moved back to North Africa. The 2/15th subsequently took part in the [[First Battle of El Alamein|First]] and [[Second Battle of El Alamein|Second Battles of El Alamein]] during the remainder of the year.&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; Throughout August, the 2/15th subsequently held a position in the north-east sector of the line from Hill 33 to the coast. On 1 September, the 2/15th participated in the 9th Division's diversionary attack south of Tel-el-Eisa, codenamed Operation Bulimba, which was planned as a response to German offensive actions further south during the lead-up to the final assault in late October and early November 1942. In heavy fighting near Point 23, a low rocky outcrop, the battalion lost about half of its fighting strength, sustaining 183 casualties, amidst heavy hand-to-hand fighting as the battalion came up against heavy resistance after penetrating a German minefield.&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; Ogle's carrier struck a mine during the operation, and he was seriously wounded.{{sfn|Maughan|1966|p=231}} The battalion's role in the September attack, including the efforts of [[Corporal]] Horton McLachlan, who received the [[Distinguished Conduct Medal]], was later depicted in a painting by [[Ivor Hele]].{{sfn|Austin|1995|loc=Frontispiece}} Among the casualties at El Alamein was the 2/15th's recently appointed replacement commanding officer, Lieutenant Colonel Keith Magno, who was mortally wounded by artillery fire after the battalion was heavily shelled while forming up during an attack around Trig 29&amp;nbsp;– a valuable piece of high ground south-west of Tel-el-Eisa&amp;nbsp;– on 28 October.{{sfn|Maughan|1966|pp=691 &amp; 701}} Casualties over both periods the battalion fought around Alamein totaled 81 killed, 23 died of wounds, 276 wounded and seven captured.{{sfn|Johnston|2002|pp=248–249}}

===New Guinea and Borneo===

By early 1943 the Australian Army's focus had shifted to operations in the Pacific theatre against the Japanese, and the 9th Division received orders to return to Australia to join the other two 2nd AIF divisions, the 6th and 7th, which had departed earlier in 1942. A divisional parade was held in Gaza, after which the 2/15th embarked upon the transport [[RMS Aquitania|''Acquitania'']] and sailed with a large convoy established under [[Operation Pamphlet]] as part of the final stage in the withdrawal of the 2nd AIF divisions from the Middle East. After a journey of just over a month, the ''Acquitania'' berthed at Sydney in late February 1943.&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; During this time the battalion was under the command of Lieutenant Colonel Raymond Barham.{{sfn|Maughan|1966|p=64}}

After disembarking in Sydney, the troops received three weeks of leave during which time they were allowed to return to their homes. The 9th Division then carried out welcome home marches across Australia, with the 2/15th taking part in the march through Brisbane.{{sfn|Austin|1995|p=206}} After this, the division was transported to [[Kairi, Queensland|Kairi]] on the [[Atherton Tableland]] in north Queensland where it was converted to the [[Jungle division|jungle establishment]] and began training for operations against the Japanese.{{sfn|Coates |1999|p=44}} The reorganisation saw the battalion establishment drop to around 800 men, and the loss of many vehicles and heavy equipment.{{sfn|Palazzo|2004|p=94}} Lieutenant Colonel Colin Henry Grace was appointed to command the battalion in May 1943 and would do so for the rest of the war.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/people/P10680680/|title=Lieutenant Colonel Colin Henry Grace|work=People |publisher=Australian War Memorial |accessdate=30 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Amphibious training was carried out at Trinity Beach, near [[Cairns, Queensland|Cairns]], with the US [[532nd Engineer Boat and Shore Regiment]] in July 1943.{{sfn|Austin|1995|p=209}}

Following training, the battalion was deployed to [[New Guinea]], arriving in [[Milne Bay]] in early August 1943. It saw action in the final stages of the [[Salamaua–Lae campaign]] in September 1943. The 2/15 took part in the [[landing at Lae]], the first amphibious operation undertaken by Australian forces since the failed [[Gallipoli campaign]] in 1915. During the operation, the 2/15th was initially assigned the task of securing the beachhead following the 20th Brigade's landing. After being relieved it joined the advance west towards the town, slowed by heavy rains that turned the many creeks in the area into raging torrents, which were invariably covered by heavy Japanese fire from the opposite bank.{{sfn|Austin|1995|p=215}}{{sfn|Keogh|1965|pp=307–310}}

Later in September, after Lae had fallen to troops of the 7th Division advancing from [[Nadzab]], the 20th Brigade undertook a follow-up operation further east, an opposed [[Landing at Scarlet Beach|amphibious landing at Scarlet Beach]], as part of Allied efforts to [[Huon Peninsula campaign|secure the Huon Peninsula]]. During the landing, the 2/15th formed the 20th Brigade's reserve force, coming ashore around Katika due to a navigational error; here it fought to dislodge strongly entrenched Japanese forces as the Australians established a beachhead.{{sfn|Keogh|1965|pp=319–320}} This was followed by the [[Battle of Finschhafen|capture of Finschhafen]], during which the 2/15th advanced alongside the 2/17th Battalion. The battalion's main effort was focused around securing a crossing over the Bumi River northwest of [[Finschhafen]].{{sfn|Coates|1999|pp=99–100}} After the town had been captured, it was tasked with expanding the Australian beachhead further west towards Kumawa as part of the drive on Sattelberg.{{sfn|Coulthard-Clark|1998|p=244}} For his actions during the battalion's attack around Kumawa on 13 October 1944, Corporal William Woods&amp;nbsp;– who had destroyed two machine gun positions singlehandedly after most of his section had been wiped out{{sfn|Dexter|1961|p=520}}&amp;nbsp;– was recommended for the [[Victoria Cross]], the only member of the battalion to be nominated for the award. It was subsequently downgraded to a Distinguished Conduct Medal.{{sfn|Austin|1995|p=236}}

After a short period of rest while Sattelberg was captured by the 26th Brigade, in late November the 2/15th joined the [[Battle of Wareo|advance to Wareo]], capturing Nongora village, crossing the Song River, and then undertaking patrols through the Christmas Hills until relieved by elements of the [[4th Brigade (Australia)|4th Brigade]], which pushed the Australian advance along the coast, forcing the Japanese north towards [[Battle of Sio|Sio]] as the Australians sought to secure the Huon Peninsula.&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; In late December, the 20th Brigade rotated back into the lead, and the 2/15th took over from the [[22nd Battalion (Australia)|22nd Battalion]] around the Tunom River, where the battalion headquarters came under aerial attack. After a brief pause near the flood swollen Tunom, the advance continued throughout December and into January 1944 with minor skirmishes punctuating the battalion's advance. Finally, on 21 January, at the edge of the Sazomu River, the order arrived for the 2/15th to be withdrawn to Finschhafen for rest prior to repatriation to Australia.{{sfn|Austin|1995|pp=240–248}}{{sfn|Keogh|1965|pp=310–343}} The fighting in New Guinea cost the battalion 30 killed in action, six dead from wounds, four dead from accidents and 119 wounded.{{sfn|Johnston|2002|p=249}}

[[File:Australian 2-15th Infantry Bn at Limbang Borneo August 1945 (AWM image 114550).jpg|thumb|right|alt=Soldiers disembark from a landing craft |A platoon from the 2/15th lands at Limbang, Borneo, August 1945]]

The 2/15th Battalion returned to Australia in mid-March 1944 aboard the ''Klipfontein''. After docking in Brisbane, a 42-day leave period followed before the battalion came together again at [[Ravenshoe]] to begin the process of rebuilding in preparation for the next phase of the war. Between June and August, training progressed from individual instruction up to brigade-level exercises as the unit was re-constituted for its next campaign.{{sfn|Austin|1995|p=251}} During training it experienced a high turnover of personnel and a large influx of reinforcements, including several officers, was received in the middle of 1944 from the disbanded [[62nd Battalion (Australia)|62nd Battalion]], a Queensland-based Militia battalion that had previously been assigned to [[Merauke Force]].{{sfn|Austin|1995|pp=251–254}} A long period of training followed the battalion's return to Australia in early 1944, as there was a degree of uncertainty about the Australian Army's role in future operations in the Pacific after the US military assumed primary responsibility for combat operations in the theatre.{{sfn|Johnston|2005|p=14}} Nevertheless, in the final months of the war the 2/15th took part in efforts to recapture [[Battle of North Borneo|North Borneo]] as part of Operation Oboe Six. After a battalion-level exercise in early 1945, the 2/15th sailed from Australia aboard the ''Charles Lummis'' in early May.{{sfn|Austin|1995|pp=264–266}}

Staging out of [[Morotai Island]], a detachment of the battalion landed on Muara Island on 10 June 1945, disembarking from US-operated [[Landing Vehicle Tracked|LVT]]s and securing the island without opposition,{{sfn|Austin|1995|pp=271–272}} while later, other elements from the 2/15th were put ashore on the peninsula around [[Brunei Town]], as part of [[Battle of North Borneo|Allied operations to secure northern Borneo]]. While the main Australian force advanced towards [[Kuching]] and the oil fields around Seria,{{sfn|Coulthard-Clark|1998|p=252}} two companies of the 2/15th served as a &quot;floating reserve&quot; for the 2/13th Battalion's landing around Lutong, while the main body of the 2/15th subsequently moved inland towards Limbang, and began patrolling along the Limbang and Pandaruan Rivers that forked inland from the bay, using landing craft for mobility, and securing several small villages around the edge of the bay. Limbang was taken on 18 June, and two days later the two detached companies rejoined the battalion. Subsequently, several engagements were fought with the Japanese during patrols in June and July, but these were mainly small-scale; two members of the battalion were killed in an ambush around Brunei in late June,{{sfn|Long|1963|pp=484–486 &amp; 490}} the heaviest fighting occurring in early July, when a patrol killed over 20 Japanese in a short but sharp encounter.{{sfn|Austin|1995|p=280}}{{sfn|Long|1963|p=20}} By the end of July, a draft of 170 long-service personnel were released to return to Australia in early August, just as the war came to an end.{{sfn|Austin|1995|pp=283–284}} Casualties for the 20th Brigade were light; the 2/15th suffered five battle casualties during its last campaign, two killed and three wounded.{{sfn|Johnston|2002|p=250}}{{sfn|Long|1963|p=501}}

===Disbandment===

After the war, the 2/15th remained on Brunei until November when it moved to Mempakul as personnel were returned to Australia in drafts based on priority of discharge.&lt;ref name=wardiaryoct45/&gt; A small group of personnel volunteered at this time to undertake occupation duties in Japan and were subsequently transferred to the [[66th Battalion (Australia)|66th]] or [[67th Battalion (Australia)|67th Battalions]].{{sfn|Austin|1995|p=348}} In early December, the battalion's vehicles were returned and after the appropriate clearances were received, the remaining cadre was transported to [[Labuan]]. From there, they sailed back to Australia aboard the ''Pachaug Victory'',{{sfn|Austin|1995|p=293}} arriving at Brett's Wharf, in Brisbane on 19 December. The cadre moved into a camp at [[Chermside, Queensland|Chermside]], where they completed unloading of stores and equipment before a short Christmas leave. Early in the new year, the final administrative tasks were completed and the last group of personnel were posted for demobilisation and discharge. Finally, the 2/15th was officially disbanded on 21 January 1946.&lt;ref name=wardiaryoct45&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1024301/ |title=AWM52 8/3/15/45: October 1945&amp;nbsp;– January 1946 |work=Unit war diaries |publisher=Australian War Memorial |accessdate=29 May 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During its service a total of 2,758 men served with the 2/15th Battalion, of whom 191 were killed or died of wounds, another 25 died on active service, 501 were wounded, and 212 were captured.{{sfn|Johnston|2002|p=247}} Members of the 2/15th received three [[Distinguished Service Order]]s, 10 [[Military Cross]]es, seven Distinguished Conduct Medals, 18 [[Military Medal]]s, one [[British Empire Medal]], 47 [[Mentioned in Despatches|Mentions in Despatches]] and nine Commander-In-Chief Commendation Cards. In addition, four were appointed [[Order of the British Empire|Members of the Order of the British Empire]].{{sfn|Johnston|2002|p=253}}

==Battle honours==
The 2/15th Battalion received the following [[battle honour]]s:&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt;{{sfn|Austin|1995|loc=Backcover}}
* North Africa 1941–43, El Adem Road, Alam el Halfa, West Point 23, Finschhafen, Scarlet Beach, Bumi River, Defence of Scarlet Beach, Nongora, Borneo, Brunei, Miri, Defence of Tobruk, The Salient 1941, El Alamein, South-West Pacific 1943–45, Lae–Nadzab, Liberation of Australian New Guinea and Sio.

These honours were subsequently entrusted to the 15th Battalion in 1961, a Queensland-based part-time unit that was the successor to the unit of the same designation that had been raised during World War I.{{sfn|Festberg|1972|p=76}}

==Commanding officers==
The following officers served as [[commanding officer]] of the 2/15th:&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt;{{sfn|Maughan|1966|p=64}}{{sfn|Johnston|2002|p=xv}}
* Lieutenant Colonel Robert Francis Marlan (1940–41);
* Lieutenant Colonel Robert William George Ogle (1941–42);
* Lieutenant Colonel Charles Keith Massy Magno (1942);
* Lieutenant Colonel Raymond James Barham (1942–43);
* Lieutenant Colonel Colin Henry Grace (1943–45).

==Notes==
;Footnotes
{{reflist|group=Note}}

;Citations
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
*{{Cite book| title=Let Enemies Beware! &quot;Caveant Hostes&quot;: The History of the 2/15th Battalion, 1940–1945| last=Austin |first=Ronald |year=1995| publisher=The 2/15th Battalion, AIF, Remembrance Club in association with Slouch Hat Publications|location=McCrae, Victoria|isbn=978-0-646-21594-5|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last1=Coates|first1=John|title=Bravery Above Blunder: The 9th Australian Division at Finschhafen, Sattelburg, and Sio|date=1999|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=South Melbourne, Victoria |isbn=0-19-550837-8|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Coulthard-Clark|first=Chris|title=Where Australians Fought: The Encyclopaedia of Australia's Battles|year=1998| publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin|location=St Leonards, New South Wales|isbn=1-86448-611-2 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Dexter|first=David|title=The New Guinea Offensives|series=[[Australia in the War of 1939–1945]]. Series 1&amp;nbsp;– Army|volume=Volume VI |edition=1st |location=Canberra, Australian Capital Territory|publisher=Australian War Memorial|year=1961|url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070205/|oclc=2028994 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Festberg |first=Alfred |title=The Lineage of the Australian Army |year=1972 |publisher=Allara Publishing |location= Melbourne, Victoria |isbn= 978-0-85887-024-6 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Field |first=A.E. |chapter-url=https://www.awm.gov.au/images/collection/pdf/RCDIG1070090--1-.pdf |chapter=Appendix 1: Prisoners of the Germans and Italians |editor=Maughan, Barton|title=Tobruk and El Alamein|series=Australia in the War of 1939–1945. Series 1&amp;nbsp;– Army|volume=Volume III |location=Canberra|publisher=Australian War Memorial |year=1966 |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070202/ |pp=755–822 |oclc= 954993 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Johnston|first=Mark|authorlink=Mark Johnston (historian)|title=That Magnificent 9th: An Illustrated History of the 9th Australian Division 1940–46|year=2002|publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin|location=Sydney, New South Wales |isbn=1-86508-654-1|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Johnston |first=Mark |title=The Huon Peninsula 1943–1944 |series=Australians in the Pacific War |year=2005 |publisher=Department of Veterans' Affairs |location=Canberra |isbn=1-920720-55-3 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Keogh|first=Eustace|title=The South West Pacific 1941–45|year=1965|publisher=Grayflower Productions|location=Melbourne, Victoria|isbn= |oclc=7185705 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Kuring|first=Ian|title=Redcoats to Cams: A History of Australian Infantry 1788–2001|year=2004|publisher=Australian Military History Publications|location=Loftus, New South Wales |isbn=1-876439-99-8 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Long|first=Gavin |authorlink=Gavin Long |title=To Benghazi|year=1952|series=Australia in the War of 1939–1945. Series 1&amp;nbsp;– Army|volume=Volume I|edition=1st|publisher=Australian War Memorial|location=Canberra, Australian Capital Territory|url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070200/ |oclc=18400892 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Long|first=Gavin|title=The Final Campaigns|series=Australia in the War of 1939–1945. Series 1&amp;nbsp;– Army |volume=Volume VII|year=1963|edition=1st|publisher=Australian War Memorial|location=Canberra, Australian Capital Territory |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070206/|oclc=1297619 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Maughan|first=Barton|title=Tobruk and El Alamein|series=Australia in the War of 1939–1945. Series 1&amp;nbsp;– Army|volume=Volume III |location=Canberra|publisher=Australian War Memorial|year=1966|url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070202/|oclc=
954993|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Palazzo|first=Albert|chapter=Organising for Jungle Warfare|title=The Foundations of Victory: The Pacific War 1943–1944|year=2004|editor=Dennis, Peter |editor2=Grey, Jeffrey|editorlink2=Jeffrey Grey|publisher=Army History Unit|location=Canberra, Australian Capital Territory|url=http://www.army.gov.au/Our-history/Army-History-Unit/Chief-of-Army-History-Conference/Previous-Conference-Proceedings/~/media/Files/Our%20history/AAHU/Conference%20Papers%20and%20Images/2003/2003-The_Pacific_War_1943-1944_Part_1.ashx|pages=86–101|isbn=978-0-646-43590-9 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Thompson |first=Peter |title=Anzac Fury: The Bloody Battle of Crete 1941 |year=2010 |publisher=William Heinemann |location=North Sydney, New South Wales |isbn= 978-1-86471-131-8|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last=Wilmot |first=Chester |authorlink=Chester Wilmot |title=Tobruk 1941 |origyear=1944 |year=1993 |publisher=Penguin Books Australia |location= Ringwood, Victoria |isbn=0-14-017584-9 |ref=harv}}

==External links==
* [https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/ART27559/ ''Operation Bulimba'' by Ivor Hele, a painting depicting the 2/15th in action at Tel el Eisa]

{{Infantry formations of the Second Australian Imperial Force |state=collapsed}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:2 15th Battalion (Australia)}}
[[Category:Australian World War II battalions|15]]
[[Category:Military units and formations established in 1940|15]]
[[Category:Military units and formations disestablished in 1946|15]]</text>
      <sha1>402lm0uyksbuvmxub30drkvihefree1</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
