<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>2/17th Battalion (Australia)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>30519036</id>
    <revision>
      <id>739461299</id>
      <parentid>739255183</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-14T20:45:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mr Stephen</username>
        <id>863017</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Further reading */clean up, ISBN format using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="29661">{{Other uses|17th Battalion (Australia)|2nd/17th Battalion, Royal New South Wales Regiment}}
{{good article}}
{{Infobox military unit
|unit_name=2/17th Battalion
|image=[[File:Destroyed Panzer III near Tobruk 1941.jpg|300px|alt=A tank lies crippled in the desert with soldiers standing around it]]
|caption=A destroyed Panzer III near Tobruk, 1941, beside which the 2/17th's commanding officer, John Crawford, is standing.
|dates=1940–46
|country=Australia
|branch=[[Australian Army|Army]]
|type=
|command_structure=[[20th Brigade (Australia)|20th Brigade]], [[9th Division (Australia)|9th Division]]
|role=[[Infantry]]
|size=~800–900 men{{#tag:ref|By the start of World War II, the authorised strength of an Australian infantry battalion was 910 men all ranks, however, later in the war it fell to 803.&lt;ref name=Palazzo94&gt;Palazzo 2004, p. 94.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=Note}}
|garrison= 
|ceremonial_chief=
|ceremonial_chief_label=
|colonel_of_the_regiment= 
|nickname= 
|motto= ''What We Have We Hold''
|colors= White and Green
|colors_label=Colours
|identification_symbol=[[File:2-17th Battalion original colour patch.jpg|90px|alt=A two toned diamond organizational symbol]]
|identification_symbol_label=[[Unit Colour Patch]] &lt;br&gt; (1940–42)
|identification_symbol_2=[[File:2 17th Battalion Australia Unit Colour Patch.PNG|90px|alt=A two-toned T-shaped organizational symbol]]
|identification_symbol_2_label=&lt;br&gt; (1942–46)
|march=
|mascot=
|battles=[[World War II]]
* [[North African campaign]]
* [[Salamaua–Lae campaign]]
* [[Huon Peninsula campaign]]
* [[Borneo campaign (1945)|Borneo campaign]]
|notable_commanders=[[John Wilson Crawford|John Crawford]]&lt;br&gt;[[John Raymond Broadbent (Major General)|John Broadbent]] &lt;br&gt; [[Maurice Fergusson]]
|anniversaries=
}}
The '''2/17th Battalion''' was an [[infantry]] [[battalion]] of the [[Australian Army]]. Raised in April 1940 in [[New South Wales]], it formed part of the [[20th Brigade (Australia)|20th Brigade]], and was eventually allocated to the [[9th Division (Australia)|9th Division]]. After completing basic training in Australia, the unit was deployed to the [[Middle East]]. In early 1941, it took part in the  [[Siege of Tobruk|fighting at Tobruk]], defending the port until relieved. A period of garrison duties followed in Syria and Lebanon before the battalion took part in the [[First Battle of El Alamein|First]] and [[Second Battle of El Alamein|Second Battles of El Alamein]] in mid-1942. As the focus of the Australian Army's operations shifted to the Pacific theatre to fight the Japanese, the 2/17th Battalion returned to Australia early in 1943.

In 1943–44, the battalion fought in [[New Guinea]], conducting an amphibious landing as part of operations to [[Landing at Lae|capture Lae]] in early September at the end of the [[Salamaua–Lae campaign]], before participating in the follow-up [[Huon Peninsula campaign|landing on the Huon Peninsula]] as Japanese forces withdrew inland from Lae. In early 1944, the battalion was withdrawn to Australia for rest and reorganisation and a long period of inactivity followed before it returned to combat. Its final campaign came late in the war when it was committed to the fighting in [[Borneo campaign (1945)|Borneo]] in June 1945, [[Battle of North Borneo|landing on Brunei]]. Following the end of the war, the battalion was disbanded in early 1946.

==History==

===Formation===
Formed for service during the [[World War II]], the 2/17th Battalion{{#tag:ref|The numerical designation of 2nd AIF units was prefixed by &quot;2/&quot;, which was used to set them apart from Militia units with corresponding numerical designations.&lt;ref&gt;Long 1952, p. 51.&lt;/ref&gt; |group=Note}} was raised on 26 April 1940 from [[Second Australian Imperial Force]] (2nd AIF) volunteers at [[Ingleburn, New South Wales]].&lt;ref name=AWM&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/units/unit_11268.asp|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110315140744/http://www.awm.gov.au/units/unit_11268.asp|title=2/17th Battalion|work=Second World War, 1939–1945 units|publisher=Australian War Memorial|accessdate=18 January 2011|archivedate=15 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; With an authorised strength of around 900 personnel, like other Australian infantry battalions of the time,&lt;ref&gt;Long 1952 p. 52.&lt;/ref&gt; the 2/17th was formed around a nucleus of four rifle [[Company (military unit)|companies]]&amp;nbsp;– designated 'A' through to 'D'&amp;nbsp;– each consisting of three [[platoon]]s; these were supported by a battalion headquarters and a headquarters company with six specialist platoons:&lt;ref&gt;2/17 Battalion History Committee 1998, pp. 12–13.&lt;/ref&gt; signals, pioneer, anti-aircraft, transport, administrative and mortars.&lt;ref&gt;Kuring 2004, p. 494.&lt;/ref&gt;

Upon formation, the battalion was placed under the command of Lieutenant Colonel [[John Wilson Crawford|John Crawford]], who had previously served in the [[Australian Army Reserve|Militia]] and commanded the [[Sydney University Regiment]] and the [[4th Battalion (Australia)|4th Battalion]].&lt;ref&gt;2/17 Battalion History Committee 1998, p. 1.&lt;/ref&gt; The colours initially chosen for the battalion's [[Unit Colour Patch]] (UCP) were the same as those of the [[17th Battalion (Australia)|17th Battalion]], a unit which had served during World War I before being raised as a Militia formation in 1921. These colours were black over green, in a diamond shape, although a border of gray was added to the UCP to distinguish the battalion from its Militia counterpart; this was later changed, though, following the unit's involvement in the fighting at [[Tobruk]], when it adopted a 'T'-shaped UCP.&lt;ref&gt;Long 1952, pp. 321–323.&lt;/ref&gt;

After completing individual training at Ingleburn, the battalion moved on foot to [[Bathurst, New South Wales|Bathurst]] to complete collective training. Following this, the 2/17th embarked for the [[Middle East]] from Sydney on 20 October 1940, on board the ''[[RMS Queen Mary|Queen Mary]]''.&lt;ref&gt;2/17 Battalion History Committee 1998, p. 8.&lt;/ref&gt; Moving in convoy the ''Queen Mary'' briefly stopped in [[Fremantle]], before continuing to [[Bombay]] in early November where the battalion was disembarked. Following a few days in camp ashore they were transferred to the [[HMT Rohna|''Rohna'']] for the next leg of the voyage. The convoy continued, sailing via the African coast into the [[Gulf of Aden]] and then through the [[Suez Canal]], before finally berthing at [[El Kantara]] in [[Egypt]].&lt;ref&gt;2/17 Battalion History Committee 1998, pp. 9–15.&lt;/ref&gt; The battalion was assigned to the [[20th Brigade (Australia)|20th Brigade]], along with the [[2/13th Battalion (Australia)|2/13th]] and [[2/15th Battalion (Australia)|2/15th Battalion]]s, which were initially allocated to the [[7th Division (Australia)|7th Division]]; however, following its arrival in the Middle East in November 1940, the battalion was transferred along with the rest of the brigade to the [[9th Division (Australia)|9th Division]].&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt;

===Middle East===

Arriving in the Middle East in late November, the battalion undertook further training near [[Gaza City|Gaza]] in [[Palestine (region)|Palestine]], before moving to [[Port Said]] in mid-December to relieve the garrison there. Returning to Palestine in early January they conducted a number of exercises until late February.&lt;ref&gt;2/17 Battalion History Committee 1998, pp. 16–19.&lt;/ref&gt; In March 1941 the battalions of the 9th Division were sent into the desert to relieve the [[6th Division (Australia)|6th Division]] that was deploying to [[Battle of Greece|Greece]]; as part of this the 2/17th garrisoned [[Mersa Brega]], near [[Tripoli]]. Shortly after this, the Germans landed forces in Africa to reinforce the Italians and the British forces in [[Italian Libya|Libya]] were forced to retreat from [[Benghazi]] to the strategically important port town of Tobruk. The 2/17th fell back as part of the general retreat and subsequently took part in the [[Siege of Tobruk|defence of Tobruk]], remaining there for almost seven months during which time the battalion's personnel alternated between conducting patrols in no man's land, raiding, occupying the main defensive position and working in the rear areas.&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wilmot 1993, pp. 219, 224 &amp; 238.&lt;/ref&gt; On the night of 13/14 April 1941, a party of about 30 Germans broke into the Australian position and set up eight machine-guns, a couple of mortars and two field guns.&lt;ref&gt;Wilmot 1993, p. 97.&lt;/ref&gt; Seeing this, the nearest platoon commander, Lieutenant Austin Mackell, launched a counterattack with a small party of men consisting of one corporal and five soldiers.&lt;ref&gt;Wilmot 1993, p. 98.&lt;/ref&gt; Covered by fire from a position on their flank, the small party was able to successfully attack the position, and as a result, Corporal [[John Edmondson (VC)|John Edmondson]], who single-handedly accounted for a number of Germans despite being mortally wounded, was later posthumously awarded the [[Victoria Cross]], the nation's highest military decoration.&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; It was the first such award to a member of the 2nd AIF.&lt;ref&gt;Wilmot 1993, p. 99.&lt;/ref&gt; The battalion's losses during the fighting around Tobruk, including the withdrawal prior to the siege, consisted of 32 dead from all causes, 127 wounded and 14 captured.&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2002, p. 248.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:John Edmondson 010576.JPG|left|thumb|Corporal John Edmondson, c. 1941|alt=A portrait photo of a corporal in service dress uniform]]

Following their relief from Tobruk by units of the [[70th Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|British 70th Division]], the 2/17th Battalion was evacuated by the sea to [[Alexandria]], and then moved to Palestine, arriving there in mid-October, establishing a camp at Julis.&lt;ref&gt;Maughan 1966, p. 514.&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly afterwards, a company was detached from the battalion to undertake guard duties in Broumane, in [[Syria]], and in January 1942 the rest of the battalion followed. There, they were tasked with undertaking garrison duties as part of the occupation force that had been established there after the [[Syria–Lebanon campaign]],&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; to defend against a possible German attack on the Allied flank through the [[Caucasus]]. Relieving the [[2/12th Battalion (Australia)|2/12th Battalion]], the battalion established itself around Afrine, north of [[Aleppo]]; in March, after the [[2nd New Zealand Division]] arrived, the battalion moved to [[Latakia]].&lt;ref&gt;Maughan 1966, pp. 515–516 &amp; 529.&lt;/ref&gt;

Later, in July, as Axis forces launched an offensive in the [[Libyan Desert|Western Desert]] that threatened Egypt, during the [[First Battle of El Alamein]] the units of the 9th Division were moved back to North Africa to help stem the advance. The 2/17th Battalion subsequently carried out a blocking operation and then occupied a position around Tel el Eisa,&lt;ref&gt;Maughan 1966, p. 618.&lt;/ref&gt; from where it conducted patrols and observed German movements.&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; In September, the 2/17th was relieved by the 2/15th Battalion, and went into reserve around Shammama to prepare for further operations. The battalion was subsequently tasked with active patrolling in the area, and clashed with German parties on a number of occasions, while its positions were also heavily shelled on a number of occasions which resulted in a few casualties. Meanwhile, several exercises and other training was undertaken prior to the upcoming offensive.&lt;ref&gt;2/17 Battalion History Committee 1998, pp. 129–136.&lt;/ref&gt; During this time it had an effective strength of 30 officers and 731 other ranks.&lt;ref&gt;2/17 Battalion History Committee 1998, p. 136.&lt;/ref&gt;

In late October and early November 1942, the battalion took part in the [[Second Battle of El Alamein]] as the British Commonwealth forces went on the offensive.&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; Engaged on the right of the Allied line around the coast, at dawn on 24 October, the Australians left their assembly area and advanced westward astride the coast road towards Tel el Eisa, and then cut inland towards the &quot;Kidney Ridge&quot;, with the 2/17th on the right of the brigade during the initial advance, attacking with three companies forward.&lt;ref&gt;Maughan 1966, pp. 668–669.&lt;/ref&gt; As the battle continued, they endured heavy counterattacks as the Germans sought to regain control of the strategically important coast road. Once these had been repelled, the focus of the fighting shifted away from the Australians as British forces were able to launch a break out, which subsequently forced the Germans to withdraw.&lt;ref&gt;Coulthard-Clark 1998, pp. 230–232.&lt;/ref&gt; The 9th Division was subsequently withdrawn to Gaza. During the battle, the 2/17th was heavily committed, losing 62 men killed in action or died of wounds, 203 wounded and four captured.&lt;ref&gt;2/17 Battalion History Committee 1998, p. 175.&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|Johnston provides two sets of figures for the battalion's casualties at El Alamein: two killed in action, one died of wounds, one died from accident, and 27 wounded for the period 7 July to 22 October 1942; and 40 killed in action, 20 died of wounds, 203 wounded in action and four captured for the period 23 October to 5 November 1942.&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2002, pp. 248–249.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=Note}}

===Pacific===
In early 1943, along with the rest of the 9th Division, the battalion was brought back to Australia in order to take part in fighting against the Japanese in the Pacific.&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; This was the final stage in the withdrawal of the 2nd AIF divisions from the Middle East, as the Australian Army's focus had shifted to operations in the Pacific theatre against the Japanese. As part of this process the 6th and 7th Divisions had been brought back to Australia earlier the previous year. Embarking upon the transport ''[[RMS Aquitania|Aquitania]]'' on 27 January 1943, the battalion sailed as part of a large convoy established as part of [[Operation Pamphlet]]; this convoy included the transports ''Ile de France'', ''Nieuw Amsterdam'', and the armed merchant cruiser ''Queen of Bermuda'', and was escorted by HMS ''Devonshire'' and several destroyers.&lt;ref&gt;2/17 Battalion History Committee 1998, pp. 186–187.&lt;/ref&gt; The voyage lasted a month, with the troops arriving in Sydney on 27 February.&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt;

Converted to the [[jungle division]]al establishment on their return to Australia, the battalions of the 9th Division were reorganised to prepare them for the rigours of jungle warfare. This saw their establishment drop to around 800 men, and the loss of much of their vehicles and heavy equipment.&lt;ref name=Palazzo94/&gt; Following training on the [[Atherton Tablelands]] in [[Queensland]], the battalion was deployed to [[New Guinea]] where it took part in the [[Salamaua–Lae campaign|Salamaua–Lae]] and [[Huon Peninsula campaign]]s in 1943–44.&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; During this time, after concentrating at [[Milne Bay]] in August 1943, the 2/17th was involved in the first amphibious landing conducted by Australian soldiers since the [[landing at Anzac Cove]] on 25 April 1915, when it took part in the [[landing at Lae]] as part of [[Salamaua–Lae campaign#Operation Postern|Operation Postern]] on 4 September 1943.&lt;ref&gt;2/17 Battalion History Committee 1998, p. 213.&lt;/ref&gt; Lae fell more quickly than the Allied planners expected, and as a result, a quick follow-up operation was planned to secure the Huon Peninsula.&lt;ref&gt;Keogh 1965, p. 315.&lt;/ref&gt; On 22 September, the battalion [[Battle of Scarlet Beach|landed at Scarlet Beach]] and, tasked with securing the beachhead and the flank,&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2002, p. 158.&lt;/ref&gt; proceeded to move inland towards [[Battle of Sattelberg|Sattelberg]] as part of efforts to capture [[Battle of Finschhafen|Finschhafen]].&lt;ref&gt;2/17 Battalion History Committee 1998, p. 224.&lt;/ref&gt; Finding their way blocked, the battalion later took part in significant actions around [[Jivevaneng]] and [[Kamaua, Papua New Guinea|Kumawa]], and then, after Sattelberg finally fell, the drive towards [[Battle of Sio|Sio]].&lt;ref&gt;2/17 Battalion History Committee 1998, pp. 245 and 275.&lt;/ref&gt; The battalion's casualties during this time amounted to 53 killed in action, 10 died of wounds, five died from accident, and 160 wounded in action.&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2002, p. 249.&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 1944, the battalion returned to Australia for rest and re-organisation, sailing on the transport ''Clip Fontain''.&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; Although the Australian Army had been heavily committed to combat operations in the Pacific in the early years of the war against Japan, by 1944 the United States military had assumed primary responsibility for combat operations in the Pacific and this had resulted in uncertainty about the role of the Australian Army in future operations.&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2005, p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dexter 1961, p. 763.&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, a long period of training followed, and there was a significant turn over of personnel within the 9th Division as many men were discharged due to medical reasons or transferred to other units and young replacements were brought in.&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2002, p. 186.&lt;/ref&gt; After concentrating at [[Ravenshoe]] in May 1944, the battalion was rebuilt, focusing on individual training and then collective training up to battalion level. After this, in September 1944, the battalion moved to [[Trinity Beach]], close to [[Cairns]], where amphibious training was conducted. Further training continued throughout October and November 1944. At the end of the year, the tempo dropped off and the battalion's personnel were occupied with sporting activities prior to leave in February and March 1945. Finally, in early May 1945, the battalion moved to [[Townsville]] where it boarded the transport [[USNS David C. Shanks (T-AP-180)|''David C. Shanks'']], bound for [[Morotai Island]].&lt;ref&gt;2/17 Battalion History Committee 1998, pp. 284–288.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:HMS LST-9 AWM.jpg|thumb|right|Troops from the 2/17th landing on Labuan in November 1945 after being withdrawn from Seria|alt=A landing ship disembarks troops]]

On Morotai, the 2/17th concentrated along with the rest of the 9th Division, which had been allocated to take part in operations to [[Borneo campaign (1945)|recapture Borneo]] as part of Operation Oboe. The battalion's part in this plan saw them land on [[Battle of North Borneo|Brunei]] on 10 June 1945 as part of Operation Oboe Six.&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; Coming ashore near [[Brooketon]],&lt;ref name=bnhist487&gt;2/17 Battalion History Committee 1998, p. 487.&lt;/ref&gt;  the battalion took part in capturing the capital before dispatching companies to secure individual objectives in the outlying areas as the Australians advanced along the coast towards the oilfields at [[Seria]].&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; In mid-July, 'D' Company carried out a patrol along the [[Baram River]] on board [[HMAS Tiger Snake|HMAS ''Tiger Snake'']].&lt;ref&gt;2/17 Battalion History Committee 1998, pp. 313–314.&lt;/ref&gt; On 13 August, following the [[atomic bombings of Hiroshima and Nagasaki]], the order to cease offensive action was received from 20th Brigade headquarters and two days later the war came to an end with [[Surrender of Japan|Japan's capitulation]].&lt;ref name=bnhist487/&gt; Despite this, it was not until 10 September that the Japanese on Borneo formally surrendered, and the bulk of the battalion remained deployed until the end of the month. During this time they were involved in ensuring all Japanese forces in the area received the surrender instructions and complied with them, and with collecting and escorting surrendered Japanese soldiers and former Indian prisoners of war, with the battalion's last operation being completed in early October.&lt;ref&gt;2/17 Battalion History Committee 1998, pp. 317–318.&lt;/ref&gt; The battalion's final campaign cost 24 men killed or wounded.&lt;ref&gt;Long 1963, p. 501.&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|Johnston provides the following figures: seven killed in action, two died of wounds, one died from accident, and 15 wounded in action.&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2002, p. 250.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=Note}}

===Disbandment===
Following the end of hostilities the [[Demobilisation of the Australian military after World War II|demobilisation process]] began,&lt;ref&gt;James 2009, p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt; and personnel began to be repatriated to Australia to return to civilian life or were transferred to units of the [[34th Brigade (Australia)|34th Brigade]] for further service during the [[occupation of Japan]].&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; On 29 October, the battalion was declared &quot;redundant&quot; and was transferred to [[Labuan Territory|Labuan]] having been withdrawn from the Seria area; personnel were subsequently occupied with various sporting competitions and education programs intended to help them transition into civilian life upon their return to Australia.&lt;ref&gt;2/17 Battalion History Committee 1998, p. 318.&lt;/ref&gt; This return was eagerly awaited, but the Australian troops remained for several months until  British and Indian troops arrived to relieve the 9th Division of its occupation duties.&lt;ref&gt;Long 1963, p. 565.&lt;/ref&gt; In mid-December what remained of the 2/17th embarked upon the ''Pachaug Victory'' for the return to Australia. Arriving in Brisbane, from there the battalion's personnel moved to Sydney and went on Christmas leave.&lt;ref name=bnhist487/&gt; On 8 February 1946, while at Ingleburn, the 2/17th Battalion was disbanded.&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt;

During the course of the war, a total of 2,903 personnel served in the battalion, of whom 177 were killed in action or died of wounds, three died on active service, 542 were wounded in action and 18 were taken prisoner.&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2002, p. 247.&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|The Australian War Memorial provides slightly different figures: 188 men were killed in action or died on active service, and  573 wounded.&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt;|group=Note}} Members of the 2/17th received the following decorations: one Victoria Cross, four [[Distinguished Service Order]]s and one [[Medal bar|bar]],  one [[British Empire Medal]], 11 [[Military Cross]]es, three [[Distinguished Conduct Medal]]s, 11 [[Military Medal]]s and 46 [[Mentioned in Despatches|Mentions in Despatches]]. In addition, three members of the battalion were appointed [[Order of the British Empire|Officers of the Order of the British Empire]], and one was appointed as a [[Member of the Order of the British Empire]].&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; In 1997, a memorial to the 2/17th Battalion was built at Jivevaneng.&lt;ref&gt;2/17 Battalion History Committee 1998, pp. 273&amp;ndash;274, 366.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battle honours==
For their service during World War II, the 2/17th Battalion received the following [[battle honour]]s:&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt;

* [[North African campaign|North Africa 1941–42]], [[Siege of Tobruk|Defence of Tobruk]], [[Siege of Tobruk|El Adem Road]], [[Second Battle of El Alamein|El Alamein]], [[Second Battle of El Alamein|Alam el Halfa]], [[South West Pacific Area|South-West Pacific 1943–45]], [[Salamaua–Lae campaign|Lae–Nadzab]], [[Battle of Finschhafen|Finschhafen]], [[Battle of Scarlet Beach|Scarlet Beach]], [[Battle of Scarlet Beach|Defence of Scarlet Beach]], [[Battle of Jivevaneng|Jivenaneng–Kumawa]],{{#tag:ref|The correct spelling is &quot;[[Jivevaneng]]&quot;; however, when the battle honour was awarded in 1961 by the Australian Army it appears to have been misspelt as &quot;Jivenaneng&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Rodger 2003, p.361.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=Note}} [[New Guinea campaign|Liberation of Australian New Guinea]], [[Battle of Sio|Sio]], [[Borneo campaign (1945)|Borneo]], [[Battle of North Borneo|Brunei]].

In 1961, these battle honours were entrusted to the 17th/18th Battalion (North Shore Regiment),&lt;ref&gt;2/17 Battalion History Committee 1998, p. 319.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Festberg 1972, p. 79.&lt;/ref&gt; which had been formed in 1948, when Australia's part-time military force was re-raised under the guise of the Citizens Military Force.&lt;ref&gt;Grey 2008, p. 200.&lt;/ref&gt; Through a series of re-organisations, these battle honours were passed to the [[2nd/17th Battalion, Royal New South Wales Regiment]], an [[Australian Army Reserve]] infantry battalion that is currently based in central New South Wales.&lt;ref&gt;2/17 Battalion History Committee 1998, p. 333.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Commanding officers==

The following [[Officer (armed forces)|officers]] served as [[commanding officer]] of the 2/17th Battalion:&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;2/17 Battalion History Committee 1998, p. xii.&lt;/ref&gt;

* Lieutenant Colonel [[John Wilson Crawford|John Crawford]] (26 April 1940&amp;nbsp;– 14 January 1942);
* Lieutenant Colonel [[Maurice Fergusson]] (15 January 1942&amp;nbsp;– 6 March 1942);
* Lieutenant Colonel [[Noel Simpson (general)|Noel Simpson]] (7 March 1942&amp;nbsp;– 27 February 1944); and
* Lieutenant Colonel [[John Raymond Broadbent (Major General)|John Broadbent]] (28 February 1944&amp;nbsp;– 8 February 1946).

==Notes==
;Footnotes
{{Reflist|group=Note}}

;Citations
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
{{Refbegin}}
* {{cite book|author=2/17 Battalion History Committee|title=What We Have We Hold: A History of the 2/17 Australian Infantry Battalion, 1940–1945|year=1998|origyear=1990|edition=Revised|publisher=Australian Military History Publications|location=Loftus, New South Wales |isbn=1-876439-36-X}}
* {{cite book|last=Coulthard-Clark|first=Chris|title=The Encyclopaedia of Australia's Battles|year=1998|publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin|location=Sydney, New South Wales |isbn=1-86448-611-2}}
* {{cite book|last=Dexter|first=David|title=The New Guinea Offensives| series=Australia in the War of 1939–1945, Series 1&amp;nbsp;– Army|volume=VII|year=1961|edition=1st|publisher=Australian War Memorial|location=Canberra, Australian Capital Territory |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070205/|oclc=2028994}}
*{{cite book |last=Festberg |first=Alfred |year=1972 |title=The Lineage of the Australian Army |location=Melbourne, Victoria |publisher=Allara Publishing |isbn=978-0-85887-024-6 }}
* {{cite book|last=Grey |first=Jeffrey|authorlink=Jeffrey Grey  |title=A Military History of Australia |edition=3rd |publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=Melbourne, Victoria |year=2008|series= |url= |isbn=978-0-521-69791-0}}
* {{cite journal|last=James|first=Karl|year=2009|title=Soldiers to Citizens|journal=Wartime|publisher=Australian War Memorial|location=Canberra, Australian Capital Territory |issue=45|pages=|issn=1328-2727}}
*{{cite book |last=Johnston |first=Mark |authorlink=Mark Johnston (historian) |title=That Magnificent 9th: An Illustrated History of the 9th Australian Division 1940–46 |publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin |location=Crows Nest, New South Wales |year=2002 |isbn=1-74114-643-7 }}
* {{cite book |last=Johnston |first=Mark |title=The Huon Peninsula 1943–1944 |series=Australians in the Pacific War |year=2005 |publisher=Department of Veterans' Affairs |location=Canberra |isbn=1-920720-55-3}}
* {{cite book|last=Keogh|first=Eustace|title=South West Pacific 1941–45|year=1965|publisher=Grayflower Publications|location=Melbourne, Victoria|oclc=7185705}}
* {{cite book|last=Kuring|first=Ian|title=Redcoats to Cams: A History of Australian Infantry 1788–2001|year=2004|publisher=Australian Military History Publications|location=Loftus, New South Wales |isbn=1-876439-99-8}}
* {{cite book|last=Long|first=Gavin |authorlink=Gavin Long |title=To Benghazi|year=1952|series=[[Australia in the War of 1939–1945]]. Series 1&amp;nbsp;– Army|volume=I|edition=1st|publisher=Australian War Memorial|location=Canberra, Australian Capital Territory|url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070200/ |oclc=18400892 }}
* {{cite book|last=Long|first=Gavin|title=The Final Campaigns|series=Australia in the War of 1939–1945. Series 1&amp;nbsp;– Army |volume= VII|year=1963|edition=1st|publisher=Australian War Memorial|location=Canberra, Australian Capital Territory |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070206/|oclc=1297619}}
* {{cite book |last = Maughan |first = Barton |title = Tobruk and El Alamein |series = Australia in the War of 1939–1945. Series 1&amp;nbsp;– Army|volume=III|edition=1st |url = https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070202/ |location=Canberra |year = 1966 |publisher = Australian War Memorial |oclc=954993 }}
* {{cite book|last=Palazzo|first=Albert|chapter=Organising for Jungle Warfare|title=The Foundations of Victory: The Pacific War 1943–1944|year=2004|editor=Dennis, Peter |editor2=Grey, Jeffrey |editorlink2=Jeffrey Grey  |publisher=Army History Unit|location=Canberra, Australian Capital Territory|url=http://www.army.gov.au/Our-history/Army-History-Unit/Chief-of-Army-History-Conference/Previous-Conference-Proceedings/~/media/Files/Our%20history/AAHU/Conference%20Papers%20and%20Images/2003/2003-The_Pacific_War_1943-1944_Part_1.ashx|isbn=978-0-646-43590-9 |pp=86–101}}
* {{cite book|last=Rodger|first=Alexander|title=Battle Honours of the British Empire and Commonwealth Land Forces 1662–1991|year=2003|publisher=The Crowood Press |location=Marlborough, Wiltshire|isbn=1-86126-637-5}}
*{{cite book |last=Wilmot |first=Chester |authorlink=Chester Wilmot |title=Tobruk 1941 |origyear=1944 |year=1993 |publisher=Penguin Books Australia |location= Ringwood, Victoria |isbn=0-14-017584-9 }}
{{Refend}}

==Further reading==
{{Refbegin}}
* {{cite book |first=H.D. |last=Wells |title=B Company, Second Seventeenth Infantry |year=1984 |location=Toowoon Bay, New South Wales |publisher=H.D. Wells |isbn=978-0-9590178-0-9}}
{{Refend}}

==External links==
* [http://second17battalion.wikispaces.com/home Second Seventeenth Battalion]

{{Infantry formations of the Second Australian Imperial Force |state=collapsed}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:2 17th Battalion (Australia)}}
[[Category:Australian World War II battalions|1]]
[[Category:Military units and formations established in 1940|1]]
[[Category:Military units and formations disestablished in 1946|1]]</text>
      <sha1>a7ucwjtokmi6gcr31a70s3f0lwkpsxi</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
