<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>2/5th Battalion (Australia)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4658935</id>
    <revision>
      <id>739804923</id>
      <parentid>733333951</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-17T03:32:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 3 sources and tagging 0 as dead. #IABot (v1.2.4)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="32803">{{Other uses|5th Battalion (Australia)|5th Battalion, Royal Australian Regiment}}
{{good article}}
{{Infobox military unit
|unit_name=2/5th Battalion
|image=[[File:2 5th Bn AIF in Syria November 1941.jpg|250px|alt=A military officer on a podium delivers a speech to gathered troops]]
|caption=2/5th Battalion being addressed by Major General [[Edmund Herring]] in Syria, November 1941
|dates=1939–46
|country=Australia
|allegiance=
|branch=[[Australian Army]]
|type=[[Infantry]]
|role= 
|size=~800–900 men{{#tag:ref|By the start of World War II, the authorised strength of an Australian infantry battalion was 910 men all ranks; later in the war it fell to 803 after the Army adopted the jungle divisional establishment.&lt;ref name=Palazzo94&gt;Palazzo 2004, p. 94.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=Note}}
|command_structure=[[17th Brigade (Australia)|17th Brigade]], [[6th Division (Australia)|6th Division]]
|garrison=
|garrison_label=
|nickname=
|patron=
|motto=
|colors=Black over Red
|colors_label=Colours
|march=
|mascot=
|equipment=
|equipment_label=
|battles=World War II
* [[North African campaign]]
* [[Battle of Greece]]
* [[Battle of Crete]]
* [[Syria-Lebanon Campaign|Syrian campaign]]
* [[New Guinea campaign]]
** [[Salamaua–Lae campaign]]
** [[Aitape–Wewak campaign]]
|anniversaries=
|decorations=
|battle_honours=
|disbanded=
&lt;!-- Commanders --&gt;
|commander1=
|commander1_label=
|notable_commanders=
&lt;!-- Insignia --&gt;
|identification_symbol=[[Image:2nd 5th Battalion AIF UCP.PNG|90px|alt=A two toned rectangular organizational symbol]]
|identification_symbol_label=[[Unit Colour Patch]]
|identification_symbol_2=
|identification_symbol_2_label=
}}
The '''2/5th Battalion''' was an [[infantry]] [[battalion]] of the [[Australian Army]] that operated during [[World War II]]. It was raised at [[Melbourne]], Victoria, on 18 October 1939 as part of the [[Second Australian Imperial Force]] (2nd AIF), attached to the [[17th Brigade (Australia)|17th Brigade]] of the [[6th Division (Australia)|6th Division]]. The 2/5th was one of only two Australian infantry battalions to fight against all of the major [[Axis powers]] during the war, seeing action against the Germans and Italians in Egypt, Libya, Greece and Crete, and the [[Vichy France|Vichy French]] in Syria, before returning to Australia in 1942 to fight the Japanese following a period of garrison duties in [[Ceylon]], where it formed part of an Australian force established to defend against a possible Japanese invasion.

Following its return to Australia, the battalion was re-organised for jungle warfare and took part in two campaigns in New Guinea. The first of these campaigns came in 1942–43 when it was involved in the [[Battle of Wau|defence of Wau]] and the [[Salamaua–Lae campaign]], and then again in 1944–45 when it took part in the [[Aitape–Wewak campaign]]. Following the end of the war, the battalion embarked for Australia on 1 December 1945 and disbanded at [[Puckapunyal]] in early February 1946. Its battle honours are maintained by the [[5th/6th Battalion, Royal Victoria Regiment]].

==History==

===Formation and training 1940–41===
Following the outbreak of [[World War II]] on 3 September 1939, the Australian government announced the decision to raise the all-volunteer [[Second Australian Imperial Force]] (2nd AIF), since the Defence Act precluded sending Australia's part-time military forces overseas.&lt;ref&gt;Grey 2008, p. 146.&lt;/ref&gt; As part of the force, the 2/5th Battalion{{#tag:ref|The numerical designation of 2nd AIF units was prefixed by &quot;2/&quot;, which was used to set them apart from Militia units with corresponding numerical designations.&lt;ref&gt;Long 1952, p. 51.&lt;/ref&gt; |group=Note}}  was raised in [[Melbourne, Victoria]], on 18 October 1939 and began to receive its first intake of men on 2 November 1939 when it moved to [[Puckapunyal]].&lt;ref name=AWM&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/units/unit_11256.asp |title=2/5th Battalion |work=Second World War, 1939–1945 units |publisher=Australian War Memorial |accessdate=23 April 2009 |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5iiKr3FNY?url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.awm.gov.au%2Funits%2Funit_11256.asp |archivedate=1 August 2009 |deadurl=no |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Many of the battalion's initial recruits came from the [[Victorian Scottish Regiment]], a [[Citizens Military Force|Militia]] unit associated with the [[5th Battalion (Australia)|5th Battalion]], which had been raised as part of the [[First Australian Imperial Force]] during [[World War I]].&lt;ref name=Digger&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.diggerhistory.info/pages-army-today/state-regts/victorian_scottish-5th.htm |title=History of the Victorian Scottish Regiment |last=Harris |first=Ted |publisher=Digger History |accessdate=9 May 2009 |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5io7KsOxF?url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.diggerhistory.info%2Fpages-army-today%2Fstate-regts%2Fvictorian_scottish-5th.htm |archivedate=5 August 2009 |deadurl=no |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; The battalion's first commanding officer was Lieutenant Colonel Thomas Cook,&lt;ref name=Johnston5/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Trigellis–Smith 1994, p. 22.&lt;/ref&gt; although he was replaced as commander by Major [[Hugh Wrigley]] before the battalion went into combat, as Cook was considered too old to lead troops in combat.&lt;ref&gt;Thompson 2010, p. 81.&lt;/ref&gt;

Along with the [[2/6th Battalion (Australia)|2/6th]], [[2/7th Battalion (Australia)|2/7th]] and [[2/8th Battalion (Australia)|2/8th Battalions]], the 2/5th formed the [[17th Brigade (Australia)|17th Brigade]], and was assigned to the [[6th Division (Australia)|6th Division]],&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; the first infantry division formed as part of the 2nd AIF. The colours chosen for the battalion's [[Unit Colour Patch]] (UCP) were the same as those of the 5th Battalion. These colours were black over red, in a horizontal rectangular shape, although a border of gray was added to the UCP to distinguish the battalion from its Militia counterpart.&lt;ref&gt;Long 1952, pp. 321–323.&lt;/ref&gt; With an authorised strength of around 900 personnel,&lt;ref name=Palazzo94/&gt; like other Australian infantry battalions of the time, the battalion consisted of four rifle [[Company (military unit)|companies]], from 'A' to 'D', each consisting of three [[platoon]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Long 1952, p. 52.&lt;/ref&gt; These companies were supported by a battalion headquarters and a headquarters company with six specialist platoons: signals, pioneer, anti-aircraft, transport, administrative and mortars.&lt;ref&gt;Kuring 2004, p. 494.&lt;/ref&gt; The battalion also had a [[regimental aid post]] attached.&lt;ref name=Bradley2010_31&gt;Bradley 2010, p. 31.&lt;/ref&gt; The battalion's personnel assembled between November 1939 and April 1940, undertaking basic training in Australia before embarking for the Middle East on 14 April 1940 aboard the transport [[HMT Ettrick|HMT ''Ettrick'']] from [[Port Melbourne, Victoria|Port Melbourne]].&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Trigellis–Smith 1994, p. 29.&lt;/ref&gt;

===North Africa, Greece and Syria 1941–42===
The battalion arrived in Egypt on 18 May 1940,&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; and joined the 17th Brigade's other two infantry battalions in camp at Beit Jirja.&lt;ref&gt;Thompson 2010, p. 30.&lt;/ref&gt; A further period of training in [[Palestine (region)|Palestine]] followed before the battalion took part in the fighting against the Italians in Libya in January–February 1941, during which the 2/5th was involved in attacks on [[Battle of Bardia|Bardia]] and [[Siege of Tobruk#Capture of Tobruk|Tobruk]], as the Australians went into battle for the first time.&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; During the fighting around Bardia, the battalion's commander, Wrigley, was seriously wounded in an artillery bombardment, and was temporarily replaced by Major George Sell, as the battalion was committed to the fighting in the second phase of the assault, advancing through the bridgehead that had been established towards the [[Railroad switch|railway switchline]].&lt;ref&gt;Thompson 2010, pp. 77–82.&lt;/ref&gt; Later, during the assault on Tobruk, the 2/5th was tasked with conducting a diversionary attack to the east of the Italian perimeter.&lt;ref&gt;Thompson 2010, p. 93.&lt;/ref&gt; The battalion's time in Libya cost it 32 killed, and 60 wounded.&lt;ref name=Johnston242&gt;Johnston 2008, p. 242.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:2-5th Battalion troops in action around Khalde (AWM photo 042172).jpg|thumb|left|2/5th Battalion troops in action around Khalde, July 1941 |alt=Soldiers advance under fire along a desert road towards a wireless station]]

A few months later in April the 6th Division was sent to [[Battle of Greece|Greece]] in order to defend against a possible German invasion of that nation. The invasion took place as anticipated, although in the end the British and Commonwealth forces were unable to stem the tide of the German onslaught. The 2/5th Battalion began the campaign at [[Kalambaka]] on 14 April. In a series of withdrawals made necessary by the lightning advance of German forces, it was pushed back all the way to the port of [[Kalamata]], where it was evacuated a couple of weeks later on 27 April 1941. The battalion lost 21 men killed, 26 wounded and 47 as prisoners of war;&lt;ref&gt;Long 1953, p. 183.&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|These figures differ from Johnston who provides 18 killed in action, two died of wounds, 28 wounded, and 55 captured.&lt;ref name=Johnston243&gt;Johnston 2008, p. 243.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=Note}} most of the prisoners were drivers who were captured having been unable to make it out in time.&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; The majority of the battalion, consisting of 560 personnel, was evacuated to [[Alexandria]], and from there concentrated in Palestine; a few&amp;nbsp;–  74 men&lt;ref&gt;Long 1953, p. 336.&lt;/ref&gt;&amp;nbsp;– in the confusion of the evacuation were landed on [[Crete]], where they formed a composite battalion along with other 17th Brigade units and personnel, including about 260 personnel from the 2/6th Battalion.&lt;ref&gt;Thompson 2010, p. 216.&lt;/ref&gt; These personnel were assigned to Cremor Force in the Suda Sector, and occupied a position around Kalami.&lt;ref&gt;Long 1953, pp. 218–219.&lt;/ref&gt; They then took part in the [[Battle of Crete]] following the German invasion on 20 May, during which the majority of the 2/5th personnel assigned to the composite battalion were captured.&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; The battalion's casualties for the campaign amounted to three killed in action or died of wounds, three wounded and 58 captured.&lt;ref name=Johnston243&gt;Johnston 2008, p. 243.&lt;/ref&gt; Six men from the battalion are known to have evaded capture during the fighting in Greece or Crete, although one of these was later killed in action while fighting alongside Yugoslav resistance forces.&lt;ref&gt;Trigellis–Smith 1994, p. 111.&lt;/ref&gt; Those that were taken prisoner were eventually moved to camps in Germany or Poland until they were liberated at the end of the war.&lt;ref&gt;Trigellis–Smith 1994, pp. 111–133.&lt;/ref&gt;

In June–July 1941, the Australians were deployed to [[Syria-Lebanon campaign|Syria and Lebanon]] for the campaign against the Vichy French, which was launched by the British in order to prevent the French-held colonies from being controlled by the Germans; the majority of the Australian forces were drawn from the [[7th Division (Australia)|7th Division]], although the 17th Brigade was called upon to provide reinforcements, detaching the [[2/3rd Battalion (Australia)|2/3rd]] and 2/5th Battalions.&lt;ref&gt;Long 1953, pp. 335–336.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Coulthard-Clark 1998, pp. 190 &amp; 193.&lt;/ref&gt; The 2/5th Battalion's initial involvement in the campaign came in mid-June during the French counterattack, when one of its companies went into action around [[Battle of Merdjayoun|Merdjayuon]].&lt;ref&gt;Long 1953, pp. 396–400.&lt;/ref&gt; After this, the battalion's main involvement came in early July, when it took part in the [[Battle of Damour]],&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; which proved to be the final battle of the campaign. After a preliminary move across the [[Damour River]],&lt;ref&gt;Long 1953, p. 491.&lt;/ref&gt; during the final assault on Damour, the 2/5th Battalion, in concert with the 2/3rd, advanced from El Boum, moving through the [[21st Brigade (Australia)|21st Brigade]]'s position, to cut the road to the north of the Damour, while other forces advanced from the east.&lt;ref&gt;Coulthard-Clark 1998, pp.193–194.&lt;/ref&gt; In the days following the capture of Damour, the 2/5th had continued the advance north towards [[Khalde]] on the coastal road to [[Beirut]];&lt;ref&gt;Long 1953, p. 503.&lt;/ref&gt; meanwhile, the Vichy commanders sought an armistice, bringing the campaign to an end on 12 July.&lt;ref&gt;Coulthard-Clark 1998, p. 194.&lt;/ref&gt; The 2/5th's casualties during the brief campaign amounted to 41 men killed or wounded.&lt;ref&gt;Long 1953, p. 526.&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|Johnston provides nine killed, five died of wounds, 28 wounded and two captured.&lt;ref name=Johnston243/&gt;|group=Note}} In the aftermath, the battalion remained in the Middle East, serving as an occupation force in Syria and Lebanon until January 1942. Following [[Imperial Japan|Japan]]'s entry into the war, the Australian government requested the return of the battalion as it was needed for the fighting in New Guinea and elsewhere in the Pacific.&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt;

===New Guinea 1942–45===
[[File:2 5th Bn AIF gun pits in New Guinea August 1943.jpg|right|thumb|Members of the 2/5th Battalion man defensive positions in New Guinea, August 1943 |alt=Soldiers in slouch hats occupy a defensive position in a jungle clearing]]
The battalion departed the Middle East on 10 March 1942 aboard the troopship [[RMS Otranto (1925)|SS ''Otranto'']]; however, on the voyage back to Australia the 16th and 17th Brigades were disembarked in [[Sri Lanka|Ceylon]], due to fears of a Japanese attack.&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Trigellis–Smith 1994, pp. 180–181.&lt;/ref&gt; For nearly four months they were stationed on the island, initially in [[Galle]], around the fort, and then later around the bay, where observation posts and section defensive positions were established. Throughout April and May, the 2/5th Battalion endured heavy rains but nevertheless undertook a series of exercises and training. In early July, the battalion finally received orders to return to Australia and, after being relieved at the [[Galle Fort]] by the [[8 Gorkha Rifles|3rd Battalion, 8th Gurkhas]], was transported to [[Colombo]] to embark upon the ''Athlone Castle''.&lt;ref&gt;Trigellis–Smith 1994, pp. 180–184.&lt;/ref&gt; On 4 August 1942, the battalion arrived in Melbourne, having been away for over two years.&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt;

A short period of home leave followed, before the battalion's personnel concentrated at Royal Park for a march through Melbourne. A draft of reinforcements arrived around this time also, incorporating men from New South Wales and several others states. In mid-September, the battalion moved to [[Greta, New South Wales]], travelling by rail through [[Shepparton]], [[Tocumwal]] and [[Newcastle, New South Wales|Newcastle]]. A brief period of training was undertaken there, during which the battalion's khaki uniforms were dyed green.&lt;ref&gt;Trigellis–Smith 1994, pp. 186–188.&lt;/ref&gt; During this time, the battalion was re-organised and converted to the [[Jungle division|jungle establishment]]; as part of this process its authorised strength was reduced to around 800 personnel of all ranks.&lt;ref name=Bradley2010_31/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Palazzo 2004, pp. 86–101.&lt;/ref&gt; The situation in the [[Pacific War|Pacific]] had deteriorated dramatically, and the Australian forces holding out against the Japanese in New Guinea were hard-pressed and desperately in need of reinforcement. Thus in early October 1942, not more than two months after returning to Australia, the 2/5th moved to [[Brisbane]], Queensland, where it deployed to [[Milne Bay]],&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; which had only recently been held in the face of a [[Battle of Milne Bay|Japanese landing]],&lt;ref&gt;Keogh 1965, pp. 185–202.&lt;/ref&gt; aboard the Dutch transport ''Maetsuyker''.&lt;ref&gt;Trigellis–Smith 1994, p. 189.&lt;/ref&gt;

The battalion did not take part in any fighting until a few months later when, in January 1943, it took part in the [[Battle of Wau|defence of Wau]] after the 17th Brigade was despatched to reinforce [[Kanga Force]].&lt;ref&gt;Coulthard-Clark 1998, p. 237.&lt;/ref&gt; Sailing to [[Port Moresby]] from Milne Bay on the [[MV Duntroon|MV ''Duntroon'']], an advance party of two companies from the battalion was flown into [[Wau, Papua New Guinea|Wau]] on 24 January to hastily reinforce the small force around Ballams. The remainder&amp;nbsp;– totalling about 450 men&amp;nbsp;– arriving on 29 January, after which they secured the airfield, which was now under direct Japanese fire, as the two companies that had arrived earlier were pulled back from Ballams.&lt;ref&gt;Bradley 2008, pp. 127 &amp; 172.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Keogh 1965, pp. 283–284.&lt;/ref&gt; In early February, as the Australians gained the initiative, the battalion was relieved from holding the airfield, and went on the offensive, attacking alongside the 2/7th Battalion, in an effort to push the Japanese away from their positions on the bank of the Bulolo River, around Crystal Creek, to the south-west of Wau. The fighting was intense, and over the course of three days, the battalion lost 27 killed and 31 wounded.&lt;ref&gt;Bradley 2008, pp. 223–226.&lt;/ref&gt;

After Wau was secured, the battalion undertook patrolling operations around [[Battle of Mubo|Mubo]], along with the rest of Kanga Force,&lt;ref&gt;Dexter 1961, pp. 18 &amp; 24.&lt;/ref&gt; before joining the advance on [[Salamaua–Lae campaign|Salamaua]] in support of the [[3rd Division (Australia)|3rd Division]],&lt;ref&gt;Dexter 1961, p. 16.&lt;/ref&gt; with a view to drawing Japanese reinforcements away from [[Lae]], where a [[Landing at Lae|landing was planned for September]].&lt;ref&gt;Keogh 1965, pp. 298 &amp; 304.&lt;/ref&gt; The Japanese put up a strong resistance and the battalion became involved in heavy fighting around Mubo in May,&lt;ref&gt;Bradley 2010, pp. 110–118.&lt;/ref&gt; before fighting at Goodview Junction and [[Battle of Mount Tambu|Mount Tambu]] in July and August as part of actions to secure Komiatum;&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dexter 1961, p. 198.&lt;/ref&gt; around Goodview, two companies were deployed in a holding action and to attempt to outflank Mount Tambu to cut the Japanese line of communication, while the other two companies attacked Mount Tambu itself.&lt;ref&gt;Trigellis–Smith 1994, pp. 221–236.&lt;/ref&gt; Casualties for the battalion between April and September amounted to 34 killed and 95 wounded.&lt;ref&gt;Dexter 1961, p. 324.&lt;/ref&gt; As the [[5th Division (Australia)|5th Division]] arrived to take over from the 3rd following the capture of Mount Tambu and the link up with US forces,&lt;ref&gt;Dexter 1961, pp. 199–200.&lt;/ref&gt; the 2/5th Battalion was withdrawn from the line, concentrating around [[Nassau Bay]] in late August as the 17th Brigade was relieved by the [[29th Brigade (Australia)|29th]].&lt;ref&gt;Dexter 1961, p. 286.&lt;/ref&gt; After a fortnight of unloading ships around the bay, the battalion was moved by landing craft to Milne Bay, where it embarked on the [[Liberty ship]] ''Charles Steinmetz'' and the Dutch transport ''Boschfontein''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.vns-voe.nl/M014reisverhalen/Bboschf.html |title=Reisverhalen ms &quot;Boschfontein&quot; |author=Storm, Jan |language=Dutch |accessdate=6 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|Trigellis–Smith identifies this ship as the ''Barsfontein''.&lt;ref name=TrigellisSmith241/&gt;|group=Note}} On 23 September 1943, the battalion arrived back in Australia, landing at [[Cairns, Queensland]].&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt;&lt;ref name=TrigellisSmith241&gt;Trigellis–Smith 1994, p. 241.&lt;/ref&gt; The fighting in the Salamaua area resulted in the following losses for the 2/5th: 94 killed and 165 wounded.&lt;ref name=Johnston244&gt;Johnston 2008, p. 244.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Australian 2-5th Inf Bn Yamil July 1945 (AWM photo 093843).jpg|thumb|left|A patrol from the 2/5th around Yamil, July 1945 |alt=Soldiers patrol through a jungle setting, passing a makeshift grave marker made out of bamboo]]

Concentrating at Wondecla, on the [[Atherton Tableland]]s in north [[Queensland]], after an extended period of home leave during which time the Victorian and South Australian personnel took part in a march through Melbourne,&lt;ref&gt;Trigellis–Smith 1994, pp. 251–252.&lt;/ref&gt; the 2/5th Battalion spent the next year training on the Tablelands along with the rest of the 6th Division. There was also a large turn over in the battalion's personnel at this time, as it had been severely depleted due to illness during its previous campaign, and it was brought up to strength by April 1944 with several drafts of reinforcements, with the majority coming from New South Wales. To counter boredom and malaise amongst the men during late 1944, the battalion was occupied with a series of various sporting events and further leave. In the new year, a series of amphibious exercises were undertaken during this time with a view to preparing the battalion for future operations.&lt;ref&gt;Trigellis–Smith 1994, pp. 254–260.&lt;/ref&gt;

Finally, late in the war, the battalion received orders to deploy overseas again. Boarding the ''Duntroon'' on 24 November 1944, a week later the battalion arrived at [[Aitape]] in New Guinea. There, the 6th Division took over from the American garrison in order to free up the US troops for further fighting in the Philippines. Following disembarkation, the 2/5th concentrated around [[Tadji, Papua New Guinea|Tadji]] airstrip.&lt;ref&gt;Trigellis–Smith 1994, p. 265.&lt;/ref&gt; In December, the Australians began offensive operations against the Japanese forces that were operating in the surrounding areas.&lt;ref&gt;Long 1963, pp. 271–281.&lt;/ref&gt; For the next seven months until the war ended the 2/5th undertook patrols through the [[Torricelli Range|Torricelli]] and [[Prince Alexander Mountains|Prince Alexander mountain ranges]],&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; as the 17th Brigade worked to initially establish and hold the Australian base around Aitape, before moving inland towards [[Maprik]] and then on to Kiarivu to pursue the Japanese forces that had withdrawn into the interior. Although only intended as a mopping up campaign, it was an arduous and costly period. Consisting primarily of small unit actions which resulted in disproportionately heavy casualties for the Australians, throughout the course of the campaign the 2/5th suffered 146 casualties, including eight officers killed or wounded.&lt;ref&gt;Long 1963, p. 385.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Keogh 1965, pp. 400–408.&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|Johnston provides 39 killed  and 116 wounded.&lt;ref name=Johnston244/&gt;|group=Note}}

===Disbandment and legacy===
Following the end of the war, the 2/5th remained in New Guinea as personnel were posted into the unit from other units that were being disbanded. In September, the battalion was withdrawn from the Kaboibus area and flown back to Wewak.&lt;ref&gt;Trigellis–Smith 1994, pp. 305–307.&lt;/ref&gt; The battalion took part in a divisional parade in October while later that month it was declared &quot;redundant&quot; under demobilisation plans, and during this time many soldiers undertook educational or vocational training to prepare them for civilian life while they waited to return to Australia. In November, there was a considerable turn over in the battalion's troops, as members were posted to other units depending upon their demobilisation priority: these units included the [[2/1st Battalion (Australia)|2/1st]], the [[2/2nd Battalion (Australia)|2/2nd]], the 2/6th, the 2/7th, and the [[30th Battalion (Australia)|30th Infantry Battalion]]s. After this, the battalion was left with only 108 personnel, all of whom possessed the required points for discharge. Finally, on 1 December 1945, the remaining personnel embarked upon the transport ''Duntroon'', bound for Brisbane. A brief stay in camp at [[Chermside, Queensland|Chermside]], in the Brisbane suburbs, followed before the battalion moved by rail to Victoria. Personnel detrained at [[Seymour, Victoria|Seymour]] and then moved by road to Puckapunyal. From there the Victorian, South Australian and Western Australian contingents marched out for discharge, leaving behind a small cadre staff.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1027201/?image=3 |title=AWM52 8/3/5/24: October&amp;nbsp;– December 1945 |work=Unit War Diaries |publisher=Australian War Memorial |accessdate=30 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The battalion was subsequently disbanded in early February 1946 while at Puckapunyal.&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; Throughout its involvement in the war, a total of 2,967 men served with the 2/5th Battalion&lt;ref name=Johnston242&gt;Johnston 2008, p. 242.&lt;/ref&gt; of whom 216 were killed, and 390 wounded.&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt;{{#tag:ref|These figures differ from Johnston who provides 149 killed in action, 39 died of wounds, 5 died on active service, 401 wounded in action, and 115 captured.&lt;ref name=Johnston242/&gt;|group=Note}} Members of the battalion received two [[Distinguished Service Order]]s, 14 [[Military Cross]]es, six [[Distinguished Conduct Medal]]s, 20 [[Military Medal]]s, and 56 [[Mentioned in Despatches|Mentions in Despatches]]; one member of the battalion was appointed as an [[Officer of the Order of the British Empire]] and three were appointed [[Member of the Order of the British Empire|Members of the Order of the British Empire]].&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2008, p. 247.&lt;/ref&gt; Alongside the 2/3rd Battalion,&lt;ref&gt;Pearson 1998, p. 7.&lt;/ref&gt; the 2/5th was the only other Australian infantry battalion to fight against all the major Axis powers during the war.&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt;

In 1948, the Citizen Military Forces was re-constituted and the 5th Battalion, Victorian Scottish Regiment was re-raised.&lt;ref name=Digger/&gt; At the time many of its members were drawn from the 2/5th Battalion and because of its territorial and personnel links it was decided that the Victorian Scottish Regiment would take custody of the 2/5th Battalion's World War II battle honours. As a result of the reorganisation of the Australian Army in the 1960s, which saw the disbandment of the regionally-based single battalion regiments and the raising of new multi-battalion state-based regiments&lt;ref&gt;Grey 2008, p. 228.&lt;/ref&gt; these battle honours were inherited by the [[5th/6th Battalion, Royal Victoria Regiment]], an [[Australian Army Reserve]] battalion based around Melbourne.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.diggerhistory.info/pages-army-today/state-regts/rvr.htm |title=Royal Victoria Regiment: A Full History |publisher=Digger History |last=Harris |first=Ted |accessdate=2 August 2009 |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5io7LGmBa?url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.diggerhistory.info%2Fpages-army-today%2Fstate-regts%2Frvr.htm |archivedate=5 August 2009 |deadurl=no |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battle honours==
The 2/5th Battalion received the following [[battle honour]]s for its service during World War II:&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt;
*[[North African campaign|North Africa]], [[Battle of Bardia|Bardia 1941]], [[Battle of Tobruk (1941)|Capture of Tobruk]], [[Syria-Lebanon campaign|Syria 1941]], [[Battle of Merdjayoun|Merjayun]], [[Battle of Damour|Damour]], [[Battle of Greece|Greece 1941]], [[Pacific War|South-West Pacific 1942–1945]], [[Battle of Wau|Wau]], [[Battle of Bobdubi|Bobdubi II]], [[Battle of Mubo|Mubo II]], [[Battle of Mount Tambu|Mount Tambu]], [[Salamaua–Lae campaign|Komiatum]], [[New Guinea campaign|Liberation of Australian New Guinea]], [[Aitape-Wewak campaign|Perimbil]], [[Aitape-Wewak campaign|Balif]], [[Aitape-Wewak campaign|Yamil–Ulupu]], [[Aitape-Wewak campaign|Kaboibus–Kiarivu]].

In 1961–62, these battle honours were entrusted to the 5th Battalion, and through this link are maintained by the [[Royal Victoria Regiment]].&lt;ref&gt;Festberg 1972, pp. 30 &amp; 63.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Commanding officers==
The following officers commanded the 2/5th Battalion during the war:&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt;&lt;ref name=Johnston5&gt;Johnston 2008, p. 5.&lt;/ref&gt;
* Lieutenant Colonel Thomas Page Cook (1939–40);
* Lieutenant Colonel [[Hugh Wrigley]] (1940–41);
* Lieutenant Colonel Roy King (1941);
* Lieutenant Colonel Patrick Daniel Sarsfield Starr (1942–43);
* Lieutenant Colonel Thomas Mayo Conroy (1943–44);
* Lieutenant Colonel Alfred William Buttrose (1944–45).

==See also==
* [[Military history of Australia during World War II]]

==Notes==
;Footnotes
{{Reflist|group=Note}}

;Citations
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
* {{cite book|last=Bradley |first=Phillip |authorlink=Phillip Bradley |title=The Battle for Wau: New Guinea's Frontline 1942–1943 |year=2008 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=Port Melbourne, Victoria |isbn=978-0-521-89681-8}}
* {{cite book |last=Bradley |first=Phillip |title=To Salamaua |year=2010 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=Port Melbourne, Victoria |isbn=978-0-521-76390-5 }}
* {{cite book|last=Coulthard-Clark|first=Chris|title=Where Australians Fought: The Encyclopaedia of Australia's Battles|year=1998 |edition=1st | publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin|location=St Leonards, New South Wales|isbn=1-86448-611-2}}
* {{cite book|last=Dexter|first=David |title=The New Guinea Offensives| series=Australia in the War of 1939–1945, Series 1&amp;nbsp;– Army |volume= VI|year=1961|edition=1st|publisher=Australian War Memorial|location=Canberra, Australian Capital Territory |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070205/|oclc=2028994}}
* {{cite book|last=Festberg |first=Alfred |title=The Lineage of the Australian Army |year=1972 |publisher=Allara Publishing |location= Melbourne, Victoria |isbn= 978-0-85887-024-6 }}
* {{cite book|last=Grey |first=Jeffrey |authorlink=Jeffrey Grey  |title=A Military History of Australia |edition=3rd |publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=Melbourne, Victoria|year=2008|series= |url= |isbn=978-0-521-69791-0}}
*{{cite book|last=Johnston|first=Mark |authorlink=Mark Johnston (historian)|title=The Proud 6th: An Illustrated History of the 6th Australian Division 1939–46|year=2008|publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=Cambridge |isbn=978-0-521-51411-8}}
* {{Cite book|last=Keogh|first=Eustace|title=South West Pacific 1941–45|year=1965|publisher=Grayflower Publications|location=Melbourne, Victoria|oclc=7185705}}
* {{cite book|last=Kuring|first=Ian|title=Redcoats to Cams: A History of Australian Infantry 1788–2001|year=2004|publisher=Australian Military History Publications|location=Loftus, New South Wales |isbn=1-876439-99-8}}
* {{cite book|last=Long|first=Gavin |authorlink=Gavin Long |title=To Benghazi|year=1952|series=Australia in the War of 1939–1945. Series 1&amp;nbsp;– Army|volume=I|edition=1st|publisher=Australian War Memorial|location=Canberra, Australian Capital Territory|url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070200/|oclc=18400892}}
* {{cite book|first=Gavin|last=Long|title=Greece, Crete and Syria|series=Australia in the War of 1939–1945. Series 1&amp;nbsp;– Army |volume=II |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070201/|publisher=Australian War Memorial|location=Canberra, Australian Capital Territory|year=1953|isbn=0-00-217489-8}}
*{{cite book|last=Long|first=Gavin|title=The Final Campaigns|series=Australia in the War of 1939–1945. Series 1&amp;nbsp;– Army |volume=VII|year=1963|publisher=Australian War Memorial|location=Canberra, Australian Capital Territory |isbn=|url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070206/|oclc=1297619}}
* {{cite book|last=Palazzo|first=Albert|chapter=Organising for Jungle Warfare|title=The Foundations of Victory: The Pacific War 1943–1944|year=2004|editor1-last=Dennis |editor1-first=Peter |editor2-last=Grey |editor2-first=Jeffrey |editorlink2=Jeffrey Grey  |publisher=Army History Unit|location=Canberra, Australian Capital Territory|url=http://www.army.gov.au/Our-history/Army-History-Unit/Chief-of-Army-History-Conference/Previous-Conference-Proceedings/~/media/Files/Our%20history/AAHU/Conference%20Papers%20and%20Images/2003/2003-The_Pacific_War_1943-1944_Part_1.ashx |accessdate=22 December 2015|isbn=978-0-646-43590-9 |pp=86–101}}
* {{cite journal |last=Pearson |first=Ross |title=The 2/3rd Australian Infantry Battalion, 16th Brigade, 6th Division, Australian Imperial Force |journal=Despatch |volume=XXXIII |issue= 2: March/April |year=1998 |publisher=Military Historical Society of New South Wales | issn=0046-0079 |pages=6–15 }}
* {{cite book |last=Thompson |first=Peter |title=Anzac Fury: The Bloody Battle of Crete 1941 |year=2010 |publisher=William Heinemann |location=North Sydney, New South Wales |isbn= 978-1-86471-131-8}}
*{{cite book|last=Trigellis–Smith|first=Syd|title=All the King's Enemies: A History of the 2/5th Australian Infantry Battalion|year=1994 |origyear=1988|publisher=2/5 Battalion Association|location=Ringwood East, Victoria |isbn=9780731610204}}

{{Infantry formations of the Second Australian Imperial Force |state=collapsed}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:2 5th Battalion (Australia)}}
[[Category:Australian World War II battalions|0]]
[[Category:Military units and formations established in 1939]]
[[Category:Military units and formations disestablished in 1946]]</text>
      <sha1>lh3pmtvrzblmoylm490zt6g7nzhldo0</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
