<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>2/9th Battalion (Australia)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>23547066</id>
    <revision>
      <id>739805032</id>
      <parentid>721560677</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-17T03:34:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 1 sources and tagging 0 as dead. #IABot (v1.2.4)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="35023">{{Other uses|9th Battalion (Australia)|9th Battalion, Royal Australian Regiment}}
{{Infobox military unit
|unit_name=2/9th Battalion
|image=[[File:Battle for Shaggy Ridge 2.jpg|250px|alt=Soldiers wearing slouch hats dug in along a ridge]]
|caption='C' Company, 2/9th Battalion during the fighting on Shaggy Ridge, January 1944
|dates=1939–46
|country=Australia
|allegiance=
|branch=[[Australian Army]]
|type=[[Infantry]]
|role= 
|size=~800–900 men{{#tag:ref|By the start of World War II, the authorised strength of an Australian infantry battalion was 910 men all ranks; however, later in the war it fell to 803 after the Army adopted the jungle divisional establishment.&lt;ref&gt;Palazzo 2004, p. 94.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=Note}}
|command_structure=[[18th Brigade (Australia)|18th Brigade]], [[7th Division (Australia)|7th Division]]
|garrison=
|garrison_label=
|nickname=
|patron=
|motto=''Never Late''&lt;ref&gt;Dickens 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;
|colors=Black over Light Blue
|colors_label=Colours
|march=
|mascot=
|equipment=
|equipment_label=
|battles=[[World War II]]
* [[North African campaign]]
* [[Syria–Lebanon campaign]]
* [[New Guinea campaign]]
* [[Borneo campaign (1945)|Borneo campaign]]
|anniversaries=
|decorations=
|battle_honours=
|disbanded=
&lt;!-- Commanders --&gt;
|commander1=
|commander1_label=
|commander2=
|commander2_label=
|commander3=
|commander3_label=
|notable_commanders=
&lt;!-- Insignia --&gt;
|identification_symbol=[[File:2nd 9th Battalion AIF UCP.PNG|100px|alt=A two-toned rectangular organizational symbol]]
|identification_symbol_label=[[Unit Colour Patch]]
}}
The '''2/9th Battalion''' was an [[infantry]] [[battalion]] of the [[Australian Army]] during [[World War II]]. Raised in [[Queensland]] as part of the [[Second Australian Imperial Force]] (2nd AIF) shortly after the outbreak of the war, it formed part of the [[18th Brigade (Australia)|18th Brigade]] and over the course of the war it was attached to the [[6th Division (Australia)|6th]], [[9th Division (Australia)|9th]] and [[7th Division (Australia)|7th Divisions]] due to several re-organisations. It served in the [[United Kingdom]] in 1940, forming part of a small Australian garrison sent there to help defend against a possible German invasion, before being transferred to North Africa where it took part in the [[Siege of Tobruk]] and then undertook garrison duties in Syria following the [[Syria–Lebanon campaign]] in 1941.

In early 1942, the 2/9th was brought back to Australia where it was re-organised for jungle warfare and took part in the [[New Guinea campaign]]. Throughout 1942–44, the battalion was committed twice to the fighting against the Japanese in New Guinea. In 1942–43, the 2/9th fought actions at [[Battle of Milne Bay|Milne Bay]] and [[Battle of Buna–Gona|Buna–Gona]]  before being withdrawn to Australia for rest prior to returning to New Guinea to take part in the advance through the [[Finisterre Range]] where the battalion took part in the [[Battle of Shaggy Ridge]] in 1943–44. The battalion's final involvement in the war came during the [[Borneo campaign (1945)|Borneo campaign]] in mid-1945, when it took part in the [[Battle of Balikpapan (1945)|landing at Balikpapan]]. It was disbanded shortly after the war in early 1946.
{{TOC limit|2}}

==History==

===Formation===
Formed on 13 November 1939 at [[Redbank, Queensland|Redbank Camp]], [[Brisbane]], the 2/9th Battalion{{#tag:ref|The numerical designation of 2nd AIF units was prefixed by &quot;2/&quot;, which was used to set them apart from Militia units with corresponding numerical designations.&lt;ref&gt;Long 1952, p. 51.&lt;/ref&gt; |group=Note}} was the first of four infantry [[battalion]]s raised in [[Queensland]] for the all-volunteer [[Second Australian Imperial Force]] (2nd AIF).&lt;ref&gt;Spencer 1999, p. 24.&lt;/ref&gt; Initially assigned to the [[6th Division (Australia)|6th Division]], the battalion formed part of the [[18th Brigade (Australia)|18th Brigade]], along with the [[2/10th Battalion (Australia)|2/10th]], [[2/11th Battalion (Australia)|2/11th]] and [[2/12th Battalion (Australia)|2/12th Battalions]]. Its first commanding officer was Lieutenant Colonel James Eric Gifford Martin, formerly of the [[42nd Battalion (Australia)|42nd Battalion]], a [[Citizens Military Force|Militia]] battalion based in [[Rockhampton, Queensland|Rockhampton]].&lt;ref name=Dickens5&gt;Dickens 2005, p. 5.&lt;/ref&gt; The majority of the battalion's officers were drawn from the Militia; although, like many of the 2nd AIF units, it was initially supplied with a Regular officer to serve in the role as [[adjutant]].&lt;ref&gt;Dickens 2005, p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt;

In terms of structure, the early months of the battalion's existence was a period of flux. The early 2nd AIF infantry battalions were established with a structure that was unique to the Australian Army; however, shortly after formation it was decided that they would adopt the British Army battalion structure.&lt;ref&gt;Long 1952, p. 52.&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, by December 1940, the 2/9th had an authorised strength of around 900 personnel and consisted of four rifle [[company (military unit)|companies]] (each consisting of three platoons with three [[Section (military unit)|sections]]), a battalion headquarters, a support company, and a headquarters company consisting of six platoons performing specialist roles including signals, [[mortar (weapon)|mortar]], and anti-tank. The four rifle companies were designated 'A' through to 'D'.&lt;ref&gt;Dickens 2005, p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2008, p.3.&lt;/ref&gt; The colours chosen for the battalion's [[Unit Colour Patch]] (UCP) were the same as those of the [[9th Battalion (Australia)|9th Battalion]], a unit which had served during World War I before being raised as a Militia formation in 1921. These colours were black over light blue, in a horizontal rectangular shape, although a border of gray was added to the UCP to distinguish the battalion from its Militia counterpart.&lt;ref&gt;Long 1952, pp. 321–323.&lt;/ref&gt;

Following training at Redbank and then later in [[New South Wales]] at [[Rutherford, New South Wales|Rutherford]] and [[Ingleburn, New South Wales|Ingleburn]], the 2/9th was among the force of 8,000 Australians sent to the [[United Kingdom]] in early 1940. It had been planned to send this force to France to serve alongside the [[British Expeditionary Force (World War II)|British Expeditionary Force]] (BEF), but [[Fall of France|France had fallen]] by the time the Australians arrived in Scotland on 16 June 1940, so they remained in the United Kingdom to help defend against a possible German cross-Channel invasion, which was feared following the capture of part of the BEF in France and the loss of much of its equipment.&lt;ref&gt;Spencer 1999, pp. 27–28.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dickens 2005, pp. 32–45.&lt;/ref&gt;

After their arrival in the United Kingdom, the battalion was transported by rail to the south of England where it set up a camp at Lopcombe Corner, on [[Salisbury Plain]] in [[Wiltshire]].&lt;ref&gt;Dickens 2005, p. 32.&lt;/ref&gt; Amidst the backdrop of the [[Battle of Britain]], the battalion's personnel used their integral [[Vickers machine-gun]]s and [[Bren gun]]s to provide self defence against air attack and to bolster the anti-aircraft defences of local areas. They also undertook training exercises and formed a mobile striking force tasked with rapidly responding in the event of an invasion.&lt;ref&gt;Dickens 2005, pp. 33–41.&lt;/ref&gt; In September, the 18th Brigade was transferred to the [[9th Division (Australia)|9th Division]].&lt;ref&gt;Dickens 2005, p. 367.&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|The division, when raised, consisted of the 18th and 25th Brigades.  The latter was initially a temporary improvised formation. It was created by reorganising other divisional units of the 6th and some 450 infantry reinforcements that had also embarked with the convoy transporting the 18th Brigade. Consequently, these units had also been diverted to Britain.&lt;ref&gt;Long 1952, pp. 306–310.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=Note}} On 14 October the battalion moved to Meeanee Barracks in [[Colchester]], [[Essex]], where it took over responsibility for a defence sector from a British officer training battalion. The 2/9th remained in Colchester until 10 November when orders came for the 18th Brigade to hand over to the [[25th Brigade (Australia)|25th Brigade]], and the 2/9th was relieved by the [[2/31st Battalion (Australia)|2/31st Battalion]].&lt;ref&gt;Dickens 2005, p. 45.&lt;/ref&gt; With the threat of invasion passing as winter came, the decision was made to redeploy the Australians to [[North African campaign|North Africa]] where they might be actively employed in combat operations. Following this, preparations for embarkation began as orders were received for the battalion to entrain for [[Glasgow]] where, on 15 November 1940, it boarded [[RMS Strathaird|HMT ''Strathaird'']].&lt;ref&gt;Dickens 2005, p. 46.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Middle East===
Sailing via the longer, but safer southern route, on the way to the Middle East the convoy carrying the Australians made a port call at [[Durban, South Africa|Durban]], [[South Africa]]. While there, the battalion marched through the city under arms on 13 December 1940, before re-embarking. Disembarking in [[Alexandria, Egypt|Alexandria]], [[Egypt]], on 31 December 1940, the battalion went into camp at [[Ikingi Maryut]] with 33 officers and 707 men.&lt;ref&gt;Dickens 2005, pp. 47–49.&lt;/ref&gt; In February 1941, the battalion was transferred once more, as the 18th Brigade was reassigned to the [[7th Division (Australia)|7th Division]].&lt;ref&gt;Wilmot 1993, p. 68.&lt;/ref&gt; Around the same time, the brigade was reduced to only three infantry battalions as part of an Army-wide re-organization, and the 2/11th Battalion was transferred to the [[19th Brigade (Australia)|19th Brigade]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/unit/U56054/ |title=2/11th Battalion |work=Second World War, 1939–1945 units|publisher=Australian War Memorial|accessdate=21 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; With the 7th Division the battalion fought its first major engagement of the war on 21 March 1941, when it led the [[Siege of Giarabub|18th Brigade's assault]] on the Italian fortress at [[Giarabub]], which was held by about 1,500 Italians.&lt;ref&gt;Coulthard-Clark 1998, p. 179.&lt;/ref&gt; Advancing from [[Siwa Oasis|Siwa]] in Egypt, the battalion, supported by elements of the 2/10th and 2/12th Battalions, attacked from the south across marshland, while cavalry from the [[6th Division Cavalry Regiment (Australia)|6th Division Cavalry Regiment]] feigned an attack against the strongest point of the fortress. Amidst a sandstorm that limited visibility, heavy fighting ensued and the garrison surrendered at around 2:00&amp;nbsp;pm; 250 Italians were killed, while 1,300 were taken as prisoners of war.&lt;ref&gt;Coulthard-Clark 1998, p. 180.&lt;/ref&gt; A total of 17 Australians were killed and 77 were wounded, with the majority of these being men from the 2/9th Battalion.&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2005, p. 22.&lt;/ref&gt; Afterwards, the battalion was sent to [[Ikingi Maryut]]&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2005, p. 25.&lt;/ref&gt; and the following month the 2/9th was transported to [[Tobruk]] by road and sea to reinforce the garrison there as German forces surrounded the strategic port in an effort to capture it.&lt;ref&gt;Wilmot 1993, p. 80.&lt;/ref&gt; The 2/9th would remain in there for the next five months as [[Siege of Tobruk|Tobruk fell under siege]].&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt;

[[File:Australian soldiers capture Giarabub in 1941 (AWM photo 042188).jpg|left|thumb|alt=Soldiers stand at the base of a sandstone structure in the desert whilst a flag is unfurled on top of the building |Soldiers from the 2/9th hoist a flag consisting of the battalion's Unit Colour Patch over the recently captured Italian fort at Giarabub.]]

On 3 May, the 2/9th Battalion launched a counter-attack on the German forces around &quot;the Salient&quot; in order to retake some of the posts that had previously been lost to the Germans. After being subjected to a heavy German artillery bombardment at their form up point, at 8:45&amp;nbsp;pm the battalion attacked from the southern flank under the cover of considerable counter-battery fire from the British artillery.&lt;ref&gt;Wilmot 1993, p. 149.&lt;/ref&gt; After capturing a number of positions and inflicting heavy losses upon the defenders, the Australians were eventually forced to withdraw at around 3:00&amp;nbsp;am on 4 May when it became apparent that they would not be able to complete the advance before daylight. Having lost three men killed, three missing and 51 wounded, at dawn the 2/9th Battalion returned to the &quot;Blue Line&quot;,{{#tag:ref|The defence system at Tobruk consisted of several lines: the outer position consisted of scattered perimeter posts and reserve company positions and was dubbed the &quot;Red Line&quot;, while the secondary defence system, which was about {{convert|2|mi|km}} behind the &quot;Red Line&quot;, was dubbed the &quot;Blue Line&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Wilmot 1993, pp. 85–86.&lt;/ref&gt; |group=Note}} where it took over a defensive position south of Bianca.&lt;ref&gt;Wilmot 1993, pp. 150–151.&lt;/ref&gt; Here a series of small skirmishes ensued during which time the battalion was able to extend their lines by about {{convert|0.5|mi|km}}.&lt;ref&gt;Wilmot 1993, p. 151.&lt;/ref&gt;

For the rest of May the battalion undertook defensive construction tasks and raids into &quot;[[no mans land]]&quot; south-west of Bianca before being relieved by the [[2/17th Battalion (Australia)|2/17th Battalion]] on the night of 4/5 June 1941. Following this, the 18th Brigade went into reserve and the battalion saw little action for the next month as it was moved back to the Bardia–El Adem Road junction.&lt;ref&gt;Dickens 2005, p. 105.&lt;/ref&gt; In July, the battalion returned to &quot;the Salient&quot;, where it spent a period of time in brigade reserve in the Pilastino sector. Later, it was moved back up to the &quot;Red Line&quot; in the El Adem sector where the battalion's personnel undertook aggressive patrols into no mans' land, penetrating a number of minefields and moving booby traps.&lt;ref&gt;Dickens 2005, pp. 108–109.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wilmot 1993, pp. 227–228.&lt;/ref&gt; On 23 July, the battalion launched a major raid in their sector in an effort to gauge German responses, penetrating over {{convert|800|m|yd}} through the German lines, but after finding their objective unoccupied, the raiders withdrew.&lt;ref&gt;Dickens 2005, p. 110.&lt;/ref&gt;

Following this the battalion went back into reserve for a period, before briefly returning to the &quot;Red Line&quot; at the start of August.&lt;ref&gt;Dickens 2005, p. 111.&lt;/ref&gt; This was short-lived, though, for later in the month the decision was made to withdraw the 18th Brigade from Tobruk and the 2/9th Battalion was subsequently sent to [[Palestine (region)|Palestine]] to undertake training. Later the battalion was transferred to Syria where it was employed on occupation duties following the defeat of the [[Vichy France|Vichy French]] forces in that country in the recently concluded [[Syria–Lebanon campaign]].&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Spencer 1999, pp. 75–77.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Pacific===
[[File:Australian 2-9th Inf Bn at Shaggy Ridge in 1944 (AWM photo 064253).jpg|thumb|Troops from the 2/9th resting prior to joining the fighting around Shaggy Ridge, January 1944 |alt=Soldiers rest in the jungle]]
In February 1942, along with the majority of the 2nd AIF, the 2/9th was withdrawn to Australia in response to the threat posed by [[Japan]]'s entry into the war following the [[Attack on Pearl Harbor|attacks on Pearl Harbor]] and in [[Malayan campaign|Malaya]].&lt;ref&gt;Spencer 1999, p. 83.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dickens 2005, p. 137.&lt;/ref&gt; Returning via [[Mumbai|Bombay]] and [[Colombo]], the 2/9th arrived in Australia, landing in [[Port Adelaide, South Australia]], in March 1942 and from there proceeded to camp in Sandy Creek, near [[Gawler, South Australia|Gawler]].&lt;ref&gt;Dickens 2005, pp. 143–145.&lt;/ref&gt; The battalion remained there until April when it was moved to [[Tenterfield, New South Wales]], and then [[Kilcoy, Queensland]],&lt;ref&gt;Dickens 2005, pp. 147–149.&lt;/ref&gt; where it carried out training prior to departure overseas.&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; At this time, the strategic situation in the Pacific was finely balanced. In July, the Japanese had landed on the northern New Guinea coast and had began advancing along the [[Kokoda Track]] towards [[Port Moresby]], amidst heavy fighting. On 6 August 1942, the order to deploy came and the battalion embarked from Brisbane along with the rest of the 18th Brigade,&lt;ref&gt;Thompson 2008, p. 339.&lt;/ref&gt; bound for [[Battle of Milne Bay|Milne Bay]] in [[New Guinea]] where the 2/9th arrived on 21 August to help reinforce the garrison there, due concerns about a possible Japanese landing there to secure the adjacent airfields.&lt;ref&gt;Brune 2004, p. 279.&lt;/ref&gt;

From the beginning of August the Japanese had been bombing the troops of the [[7th Brigade (Australia)|7th Brigade]] which had initially been sent to garrison the Milne Bay area, and as a Japanese invasion force was expected, the three battalions of the 18th Brigade were quickly placed into positions where they could be most effective. The 2/9th was assigned the task of defending Milne Force Headquarters at Hagita House and the Number 1 Strip (also known as Gurney Field).&lt;ref&gt;Brune 2004, p. 282.&lt;/ref&gt; Upon arrival, the 2/9th Battalion was used to construct roads and lay steel matting on the airstrip as well as unloading stores from ships as they arrived, and carrying out patrolling operations.&lt;ref&gt;Dickens 2005, p. 161.&lt;/ref&gt; Following the Japanese landing on 25 August, the battalion was placed on alert and increased its patrolling operations around the airfield; however, for five days no contact was made. On 3 September, the battalion moved from Gili Gili to KB Mission and alongside the 2/12th Battalion, which had launched a counteroffensive along the north coast of the bay, went into battle with the Japanese for the first time.&lt;ref&gt;Dickens 2005, p. 167.&lt;/ref&gt; Over the course of the next two days the Japanese were beaten back and eventually a withdrawal was ordered by the Japanese commanders. This represented the first full-scale defeat of the Japanese on land during the war;&lt;ref&gt;Harries &amp; Harries 1991, p. 404.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McCarthy 1959, p. 187.&lt;/ref&gt; it came at a cost for the 2/9th, though, with the battalion losing 29 men killed and a further 86 wounded in action, seven of whom later died of wounds. Disease took a far greater toll, with a further 308 men being hospitalised due to illness.&lt;ref&gt;Dickens 2005, p. 181.&lt;/ref&gt;

As the tide in the New Guinea campaign began to turn in favour of the Allies, the Japanese, having reached the zenith of their advance in New Guinea, were forced to withdraw back towards [[Battle of Buna–Gona|Buna and Gona]]. Fierce fighting subsequently followed as Australian and US troops fought to reduce the Japanese beachhead. After taking part in defeating the Japanese at Milne Bay, the 18th Brigade was transferred to Buna. The 2/9th arrived at [[Oro Bay]] aboard [[HMAS Broome (J191)|HMAS ''Broome'']] on 14 December.&lt;ref&gt;McCarthy 1959, p. 452.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Milner 1957, p. 258.&lt;/ref&gt; It was the first battalion of the brigade committed to this battle. Leading the attack of 18 December, with support of [[M3 Stuart]] tanks from the [[2/6th Armoured Regiment (Australia)|2/6th Armoured Regiment]], it made significant gains. The 18th Brigade (and the 2/9th) continued to fight, attached to the [[32nd Infantry Division (United States)|US 32nd Division]] until the fall of Buna at the start of January 1943.  It was returned to command of the Australian 7th Division in time to participate in an attack on 12 January against Japanese positions on the Sanananda Track that had been holding up the Australian advance there. The battalion continued fighting in the [[Sanananda]] area until it concluded with an Allied victory on 22 January. By this time its strength had fallen from over 600 to just under 100 men due to the effects of tropical diseases and heavy fighting;&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dickens 2005, p. 157.&lt;/ref&gt;  combat losses were recorded as 95 killed in action or died of wounds, 32 missing, and 247 wounded.&lt;ref&gt;McCarthy 1959, p. 484.&lt;/ref&gt; These losses were offset by the arrival of 300 reinforcements during the battle, but nevertheless losses were so heavy, particularly from disease, that in February the 2/9th Battalion was transported back to Port Moresby, before returning to Australia the next month.&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; 

[[File:2-9th Australian Infantry Battalion march through Brisbane 1944 (AWM photo 068260).jpg|thumb|left|alt=Soldiers in service dress march past a building in a city |Members of the 2/9th march past Brisbane City Hall, August 1944]]

Following the battalion's return, it undertook further jungle training at [[Ravenshoe]] on the [[Atherton Tablelands]].&lt;ref&gt;Dickens 2005, p. 239.&lt;/ref&gt; In August 1943, after embarking at [[Townsville]] the 2/9th returned to Port Moresby, where it continued further training in the areas surrounding the port.&lt;ref&gt;Bradley 2004, p. 179.&lt;/ref&gt; It remained there until 31 December when the battalion deployed into the Finisterre Range, being flown into [[Dumpu, Papua New Guinea|Dumpu]] and joining the Allied advance inland. In early January 1944, the battalion took part in the [[Battle of Shaggy Ridge]], capturing &quot;Green Sniper's Pimple&quot; on 21 January as part of a brigade-level operation to carry the ridge.&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bradley 2004, p. 180.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Thompson 2008, p. 381.&lt;/ref&gt; Following the conclusion of the fighting around Shaggy Ridge in February, the battalion occupied a position around the western side of the saddle before being relieved by the [[57th/60th Battalion (Australia)|57th/60th Battalion]],&lt;ref&gt;Bradley (2004), p. 241.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dexter 1961, p. 771.&lt;/ref&gt; as the [[15th Brigade (Australia)|15th Brigade]] relieved the 18th and continued the advance on [[Bogadjim]] as the Australians linked up with US forces on the coast, prior to capturing [[Madang]] and securing the [[Huon Peninsula]] in late April.&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2007, p. 29.&lt;/ref&gt; During this period the battalion occupied a defended locality about {{convert|15|km|mi}} downstream from Dumpu, from which they conducted patrols long-range fighting patrols to prevent the Japanese from infiltrating back into the [[Ramu Valley]] over the months which followed. Training activities and work parties were also conducted.&lt;ref&gt;Dickens 2005, pp. 290–294.&lt;/ref&gt;

In May 1944, the battalion was brought back to Australia,&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; as part of a broader plan to return the three AIF divisions to Australia for &quot;training and rehabilitation&quot;&lt;ref name=Dexter763&gt;Dexter 1961, p. 763.&lt;/ref&gt; while the United States military assumed primary responsibility for combat operations in the Pacific.&lt;ref name=Dexter763/&gt; A period of operational uncertainty followed regarding the future combat role of the Australian Army, and consequently a long period of training in Australia followed for the AIF battalions. After a period of leave the battalion's personnel concentrated at [[Strathpine, Queensland]], in July. In August, the battalion moved to the Atherton Tablelands again, establishing themselves at [[Kairi, Queensland|Kairi]]. After this, the battalion conducted exercises which included collective training up to brigade level, while amphibious training was also undertaken at [[Trinity Beach, Queensland|Trinity Beach]] near [[Cairns]] aboard the British troopship [[HMS Glenearn|HMS ''Glenearn'']], working in concert with [[Royal Marines]].&lt;ref&gt;Dickens 2005, pp. 302–309.&lt;/ref&gt; In December 1944, the battalion participated in a divisional exercise. During this period the unit was also introduced to several new weapons, including [[flame throwers]] and the [[PIAT]] anti-tank weapon, and undertook training in infantry/tank co-operation.&lt;ref&gt;Dickens 2005, pp. 307–311.&lt;/ref&gt; A range of training exercises, competitions, sporting events, and recreational activities continued early in the new year to keep the men busy and combat possible feelings of &quot;anti-climax&quot; and &quot;boredom&quot; that may have been associated with the granting of limited local leave after the delay of their expected deployment overseas.&lt;ref&gt;Dickens 2005, pp. 313–318.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Captured Japanese Type 92 tankette Borneo 1945 AWM P02125.001.jpg |thumb|alt=Soldiers sitting on a small armoured vehicle in front of a grounded aircraft |A [[Type 92 Heavy Armoured Car|Type 92 Japanese tankette]] captured by soldiers of the 2/9th Battalion, 1 July 1945.]]

In the final months of the war, the battalion was committed to the [[Borneo campaign (1945)|Borneo campaign]]. Embarking from Cairns in May on several tank landing ships, the battalion concentrated on [[Morotai Island]].&lt;ref&gt;Dickens 2005, p. 319.&lt;/ref&gt; On 1 July 1945, the 2/9th took part in the [[Battle of Balikpapan (1945)|landing at Balikpapan]], the final Australian amphibious operation of the war.&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; At the start of the attack, the battalion was assigned the role of being the 18th Brigade's reserve;&lt;ref&gt;Long 1963, p. 511.&lt;/ref&gt; however, by mid-morning on the opening day it was ordered forward to relieve the 2/10th Battalion, taking [[Klandasan]] before noon, and commencing house-to-house clearances in concert with a troop of tanks.&lt;ref name=Long519&gt;Long 1963, p. 519.&lt;/ref&gt; From there it forced a small Japanese force off Santosa Hill, before tying in its positions at 6:00&amp;nbsp;pm and digging-in for the night.&lt;ref name=Long519/&gt; On 5 July, the 2/9th landed on the western side of Balikpapan Bay. Along with a small force of armour, artillery, mortars and other supporting arms, it began to clear inland from Penadjam. Over the course of the following month the battalion sent detachments south along the coast towards the Semsumpu River and north towards the Riko River and onto the Parehpareh River via Separi.&lt;ref&gt;Long 1963, p. 540.&lt;/ref&gt; By 12 August, posts had been established astride the Pamaluan–Bandjermasin Road, and a detachment from 'C' Company had reached Pamaluan, where the 2/9th linked up with elements from the [[2/1st Pioneer Battalion (Australia)|2/1st Pioneer Battalion]].&lt;ref&gt;Dickens 2005, p. 342.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Disbandment===

Finally, in mid-August, the fighting on Borneo came to an end following the [[atomic bombings of Hiroshima and Nagasaki]] and the subsequent [[surrender of Japan]]. After this the 2/9th Battalion carried out various garrison duties such as guarding prisoners of war and maintaining internal security while the [[Demobilisation of the Australian military after World War II|demobilisation process]] took place.&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt; As personnel were repatriated back to Australia or transferred to other units for further service, the battalion's strength dropped until it was finally disbanded on 3 January 1946 while still at Balikpapan.&lt;ref name=AWM&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/units/unit_11260.asp |title=2/9th Battalion |work=Second World War, 1939–1945 units |publisher=Australian War Memorial |accessdate=22 July 2009 |archiveurl=http://www.webcitation.org/5iSt43QSe?url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.awm.gov.au%2Funits%2Funit_11260.asp |archivedate=22 July 2009 |deadurl=no |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the course of the war, a total of 4,107 men served with the 2/9th Battalion&lt;ref name=Johnston248&gt;Johnston 2005, p. 248.&lt;/ref&gt; of whom 319 were killed in action or died on active service, and a further 726 wounded.&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt;{{#tag:ref|There is a discrepancy in these figures to those provided by the battalion historian, who lists the following: 218 killed in action, 69 died of wounds and a further 688 wounded.&lt;ref&gt;Dickens 2005, p. 369.&lt;/ref&gt; Johnston's figures also vary, citing 218 killed in action, 72 died of wounds, eight died on active service and 755 wounded in action.&lt;ref name=Johnston248/&gt;|group=Note}} One of its members, [[John Alexander French]], was posthumously awarded the [[Victoria Cross]] for his actions during the fighting around Milne Bay in September 1942.&lt;ref&gt;Dickens 2005, p. 172.&lt;/ref&gt; Other decorations that men of the 2/9th received were: four [[Distinguished Service Order]]s, nine [[Military Cross]]es, three [[Distinguished Conduct Medal]]s, nineteen [[Military Medal]]s and sixty-eight [[Mentioned in despatches|mentions in despatches]]; in addition, one member of the battalion was appointed as a [[Commander of the Order of the British Empire]], one was appointed an [[Officer of the Order of the British Empire]], and one was appointed a [[Member of the Order of the British Empire]].&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt;{{#tag:ref|There is a discrepancy in these figures to those provided by the battalion historian, who lists the following awards: one VC, four DSOs, nine MCs, eighteen MMs, three DCMs and sixty-nine MIDs.&lt;ref&gt;Dickens 2005, p. ix.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=Note}}

==Battle honours==
For their service during World War II, the 2/9th Battalion received 10 [[battle honours]]:&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt;
* North Africa, Giarabub, Defence of Tobruk, The Salient 1941, South-West Pacific 1942–1945, Buna–Gona, Sanananda Road, Cape Endaiadere–Sinemi Creek, Sanananda–Cape Killerton, Milne Bay.

In 1961–62, these battle honours were entrusted to the [[Royal Queensland Regiment]] and are maintained through the [[9th Battalion, Royal Queensland Regiment]].&lt;ref&gt;Festberg 1972, pp. 26 &amp; 68.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Commanding officers==
The following officers commanded the 2/9th during the war:&lt;ref name=AWM/&gt;
* Lieutenant Colonel James Eric Gifford Martin (1939–41)
* Lieutenant Colonel Clement James Cummings (1941–44)
* Lieutenant Colonel Arthur James Lee (1944–45)

==Notes==
;Footnotes
{{Reflist|group=Note}}

;Citations
{{reflist|3}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book|last=Bradley|first=Phillip |authorlink=Phillip Bradley |title=On Shaggy Ridge: The Australian Seventh Division in the Ramu Valley from Kaiapit to the Finisterres|year=2004|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Melbourne, Victoria|isbn=978-0-19-555100-6}}
* {{cite book|last=Brune|first=Peter|title=A Bastard of a Place: The Australians in Papua|publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin|location=Crows Nest, New South Wales|year=2004 |origyear=2003|isbn=1-74114-403-5}}
* {{cite book |last=Coulthard-Clark |first=Chris |authorlink=|year=1998 |title=Where Australians Fought: The Encyclopaedia of Australia's Battles |edition=1st |publisher=Allen and Unwin |location=St Leonards, New South Wales |isbn=1-86448-611-2}}
* {{cite book|last=Dexter|first=David|title=The New Guinea Offensives| series=[[Australia in the War of 1939–1945]], Series 1&amp;nbsp;– Army|volume=VII|year=1961|edition=1st|publisher=Australian War Memorial|location=Canberra, Australian Capital Territory |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070205/|oclc=2028994}}
* {{cite book|last=Dickens|first=Gordon|title=Never Late: The 2/9th Australian Infantry Battalion 1939–1945|year=2005|publisher=Australian Military History Publications|location=Loftus, New South Wales|isbn=1-876439-47-5}}
* {{cite book |last=Festberg |first=Alfred |year=1972 |title=The Lineage of the Australian Army |location=Melbourne, Victoria |publisher=Allara Publishing |isbn=978-0-85887-024-6 }}
* {{cite book |last1=Harries |first=Meirion |last2=Harries |first2=Susie |title=Soldiers of the Sun: The Rise and Fall of the Imperial Japanese Army |publisher=Random House |location=New York |year=1991 |isbn=978-0-679-75303-2}}
* {{cite book|last=Johnston|first=Mark |authorlink=Mark Johnston (historian)|title=The Proud 6th: An Illustrated History of the 6th Australian Division 1939–1945|year=2008|publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=Port Melbourne, Victoria|isbn=978-0-521-51411-8}}
* {{cite book|last=Johnston|first=Mark|title=The Australian Army in World War II|year=2007|publisher=Osprey Publishing|location=Botley, Oxford|isbn=978-1-84603-123-6}}
* {{cite book|last=Johnston |first=Mark |title=The Silent 7th: An Illustrated History of the 7th Australian Division 1940–46 |year=2005 |location=Crows Nest, New South Wales |publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin |isbn=1-74114-191-5}}
* {{cite book|last=Long|first=Gavin|authorlink=Gavin Long|title=The Final Campaigns|series=Australia in the War of 1939–1945, Series 1&amp;nbsp;– Army |volume=VII|year=1963|publisher=[[Australian War Memorial]]|location=Canberra, Australian Capital Territory|url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070206/ |accessdate=22 December 2015|oclc=1297619}}
* {{cite book|last=Long|first=Gavin|title=To Benghazi|year=1952|series=Australia in the War of 1939–1945. Series 1&amp;nbsp;– Army|volume=I|edition=1st|publisher=Australian War Memorial|location=Canberra, Australian Capital Territory|url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070200/ |accessdate=22 December 2015|oclc=18400892}}
* {{cite book|last=McCarthy|first=Dudley |authorlink=|title=South–West Pacific Area&amp;nbsp;– First Year: Kokoda to Wau|url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070204/ |accessdate=22 December 2015|series=Australia in the War of 1939–1945. Series 1&amp;nbsp;– Army |volume=V|year=1959| publisher=Australian War Memorial|location=Canberra, Australian Capital Territory|oclc=186193870}}
*{{cite book |last1=Milner |first1=Samuel |last2= |first2= |year=1957 |title=Victory in Paupa|url=http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/USA/USA-P-Papua/|series=United States Army In World War II |location=Washington, DC |publisher=Center of Military History, United States Army |isbn= |lccn=56-60004 |page= }}
* {{cite book|last=Palazzo|first=Albert|chapter=Organising for Jungle Warfare|title=The Foundations of Victory: The Pacific War 1943–1944|year=2004|editor1-last=Dennis |editor1-first=Peter |editor2-last=Grey |editor2-first=Jeffrey|publisher=Army History Unit|location=Canberra, Australian Capital Territory|url=http://www.army.gov.au/Our-history/Army-History-Unit/Chief-of-Army-History-Conference/Previous-Conference-Proceedings/~/media/Files/Our%20history/AAHU/Conference%20Papers%20and%20Images/2003/2003-The_Pacific_War_1943-1944_Part_1.ashx |accessdate=22 December 2015|isbn=978-0-646-43590-9 |pp=86–101}}
* {{cite book|last=Spencer|first=Bill|title=In the Footsteps of Ghosts: With the 2/9th Battalion in the African Desert and the Jungles of the Pacific|year=1999|publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin|location=St Leonards, New South Wales|isbn=1-86508-145-0}}
* {{cite book|last=Thompson|first=Peter|title=Pacific Fury: How Australia and Her Allies Defeated the Japanese Scourge|year=2008|publisher=William Heinemann|location=North Sydney, New South Wales|isbn=978-1-74166-708-0}}
* {{cite book|last=Wilmot|first=Chester|authorlink=Chester Wilmot|title=Tobruk 1941 |origyear=1944 |year=1993 |publisher=Penguin Books Australia |location=Ringwood, New South Wales |isbn=0-14-017584-9}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
* [https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1020413/ Official 2/9th Battalion war diaries]
* [http://www.9bnassoc.org 9th Battalions Association Inc.]

{{Good article}}

{{Infantry formations of the Second Australian Imperial Force |state=collapsed}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:2 9th Battalion (Australia)}}
[[Category:Australian World War II battalions|0]]
[[Category:Military units and formations established in 1939|0]]
[[Category:Military units and formations disestablished in 1946|0]]
[[Category:1939 establishments in Australia]]</text>
      <sha1>10qyozuwa8eotoxkneilq2i7wlk007s</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
