<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>2/48th Battalion (Australia)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>23749351</id>
    <revision>
      <id>739052578</id>
      <parentid>731126372</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-12T14:29:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GreenC bot</username>
        <id>27823944</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[User:Green Cardamom/WaybackMedic 2|WaybackMedic 2]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="40507">{{Other uses|48th Battalion (Australia)}}
{{Good article}}
{{Infobox military unit
|unit_name= 2/48th Battalion
|image=[[File:AWM 089471 2 48th Battalion advance on Tarakan 1945.jpg|250px|alt=An armoured vehicle moves along a sandy road surrounded by jungle. Infantrymen advance alongside]]
|caption=Troops from 'C' Company, 2/48th Battalion advance alongside Matilda tanks from the 2/9th Armoured Regiment during the attack on the &quot;Sykes&quot; feature on Tarakan in April 1945
|dates= 1940–45
|country= Australia
|allegiance=
|branch= [[Australian Army]]
|type= [[Infantry]]
|role=
|size= ~800–900 all ranks{{#tag:ref|The establishment of a standard infantry battalion was 35 officers and 875 other ranks. Under the [[Jungle division|jungle organisation]] each battalion was reduced by one officer and 106 other ranks.&lt;ref&gt;Kuring 2004, p. 47.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Palazzo94&gt;Palazzo 2004, p. 94.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=Note}}
|command_structure= [[26th Brigade (Australia)|26th Brigade]], [[9th Division (Australia)|9th Division]]
|garrison=
|garrison_label=
|nickname=
|patron=
|motto=
|colors=White and Light Blue
|colors_label=Colours
|march=
|mascot=
|equipment=
|equipment_label=
|battles= [[Second World War]]
* [[North African Campaign]]
** [[Siege of Tobruk]]
** [[First Battle of El Alamein]]
** [[Second Battle of El Alamein]]
* [[New Guinea campaign]]
** [[Salamaua–Lae campaign]]
** [[Huon Peninsula campaign]]
* [[Borneo Campaign (1945)|Borneo campaign]]
** [[Battle of Tarakan (1945)|Battle of Tarakan]]
|anniversaries=
|decorations=
|battle_honours=
|disbanded=
&lt;!-- Commanders --&gt;
|commander1=
|commander1_label=
|commander2=
|commander2_label=
|commander3=
|commander3_label=
|notable_commanders= [[Victor Windeyer]]
&lt;!-- Insignia --&gt;
|identification_symbol=[[File:2-48th Battalion original colour patch.jpg|90px|alt=A two tone circular organizational shape inside a diamond]] 
|identification_symbol_label=[[Unit Colour Patch]] &lt;br&gt; (1940–42)
|identification_symbol_2= [[File:2 48th Battalion Australia Unit Colour Patch.PNG|90px|alt=A two toned T-shaped image]]
|identification_symbol_2_label=(1942–45)
|identification_symbol_3=
|identification_symbol_3_label=
|identification_symbol_4=
|identification_symbol_4_label=
}}

The '''2/48th Battalion''' was an [[infantry]] [[battalion]] of the [[Australian Army]] which served during the [[Second World War]]. Raised in [[Adelaide]] in [[South Australia]] in August 1940, the battalion formed part of the [[26th Brigade (Australia)|26th Brigade]] and was initially assigned to the [[7th Division (Australia)|7th Division]], although it was later transferred to the [[9th Division (Australia)|9th Division]] in 1941 when it was deployed to the Middle East. While there, it saw action during the [[siege of Tobruk]] and the [[First Battle of El Alamein|First]] and [[Second Battle of El Alamein|Second Battles of El Alamein]] before being returned to Australia to take part in the [[New Guinea campaign|fighting in New Guinea]] following [[Japan]]'s entry into the war.

During the campaign in [[New Guinea]], the battalion took part in the advance on [[Lae]] during the [[Salamaua–Lae campaign]] and the fighting around [[Battle of Finschhafen|Finschhafen]] and [[Battle of Sattelberg|Sattelberg]], during the [[Huon Peninsula campaign]]. Following this it was withdrawn to Australia, where it remained for over a year. In mid-1945, the 2/48th Battalion took part in the [[Battle of Tarakan (1945)|landing on Tarakan]], which was its final involvement in the war. It was disbanded in October 1945 and is considered to be Australia's most highly decorated unit of the war, with four members receiving the [[Victoria Cross]], the nation's highest decoration for [[Courage|gallantry]], while over 90 other decorations were also made to its members.&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM2/48&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.awm.gov.au/units/unit_11288.asp|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090809142613/http://www.awm.gov.au/units/unit_11288.asp |title=2/48th Battalion |work=Second World War, 1939–1945 units |publisher=Australian War Memorial |accessdate=26 July 2009|archivedate=9 August 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{TOC limit|2}}

==History==

===Formation===
The 2/48th Battalion{{#tag:ref|The numerical designation of 2nd AIF units was prefixed by &quot;2/&quot;, which was used to set them apart from Militia units with corresponding numerical designations.&lt;ref&gt;Long 1952, p. 51.&lt;/ref&gt; |group=Note}} was raised on 9 August 1940 at the [[Wayville Showgrounds]], in [[Adelaide]], under the command of Lieutenant Colonel [[Victor Windeyer]], a former [[Citizens Military Force|Militia]] officer who had previously commanded the [[Sydney University Regiment]].&lt;ref&gt;Glenn 1987, pp. 1–2.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/units/people_1080621.asp|title=NX396 Major General William John Victor Windeyer, KBE, CB, DSO &amp; Bar |work=People|publisher=Australian War Memorial|accessdate=10 January 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; A unit of the all-volunteer [[Second Australian Imperial Force]] (2nd AIF), the 2/48th Battalion was formed specifically for service overseas and recruited mainly from the state of [[South Australia]].&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2002, p. xii.&lt;/ref&gt; The battalion's headquarters staff began arriving early in the month, with many of the key personnel having served previously in South Australian Militia units, including the [[27th Battalion (Australia)|27th Battalion (South Australian Scottish Regiment)]]. At the end of August, a large draft of recruits arrived from the 2nd Infantry Training Depot, and rudimentary individual training was undertaken in the nearby park lands.&lt;ref&gt;Glenn 1987, pp. 2–4.&lt;/ref&gt; The colours initially chosen for the battalion's [[Unit Colour Patch]] (UCP) were the same as those of the [[48th Battalion (Australia)|48th Battalion]], a unit which had served during the First World War before being raised as a Militia formation in 1921. These colours were white over dark blue, in a circle shape, although a diamond-shaped border of gray was added to the UCP to distinguish the battalion from its Militia counterpart; this was later changed, though, following the unit's involvement in the fighting at [[Tobruk]], when it adopted a 'T'-shaped UCP.&lt;ref&gt;Long 1952, pp. 321–323.&lt;/ref&gt;

With an authorised strength of around 900 personnel,&lt;ref name=Palazzo94/&gt; like other Australian infantry battalions of the time, the battalion was formed around a nucleus of four rifle [[Company (military unit)|companies]]—designated 'A' through to 'D'—each consisting of three [[platoon]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Long 1952 p. 52.&lt;/ref&gt; These companies were supported by a battalion headquarters and a headquarters company with six specialist platoons: signals, pioneer, anti-aircraft, transport, administrative and mortars.&lt;ref&gt;Kuring 2004, p. 494.&lt;/ref&gt; Forming part of the [[26th Brigade (Australia)|26th Brigade]] along with the [[2/23rd Battalion (Australia)|2/23rd]] and [[2/24th Battalion (Australia)|2/24th Battalions]], it was assigned to the [[7th Division (Australia)|7th Division]] during its initial training period but was later transferred with the rest of the 26th Brigade to the [[9th Division (Australia)|9th Division]]. After pre-embarkation leave, the battalion undertook three weeks of collective training at [[Woodside Barracks|Woodside]], in October.&lt;ref&gt;Glenn 1987, p. 5.&lt;/ref&gt; The following month, the battalion marched through the city of Adelaide prior to its deployment overseas, and shortly afterwards embarked for North Africa.&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM2/48&quot;/&gt; Entraining at [[Oakbank, South Australia|Oakbank]], after undertaking a {{convert|4.5|mi|km|adj=on}} route march in full equipment,&lt;ref&gt;Glenn 1987, p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt; the battalion embarked upon the troopship ''Stratheden'' on 17 November 1940; the large transport set sail the following day.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1023187/?image=7|title=AWM52 8/3/36/3&amp;nbsp;– November 1940, p. 7 |work=Unit war diaries |publisher=Australian War Memorial |accessdate=7 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Macklin136&gt;Macklin 2008, p. 136.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Actions in North Africa===
Sailing via [[Colombo]] where the troops were given a brief shore leave, the ''Stratheden'' entered the [[Suez Canal]] in mid-December 1940.&lt;ref&gt;Glenn 1987, p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt; Upon arrival in the Middle East, the battalion briefly occupied a camp at [[El Kantara]],&lt;ref name=Macklin136/&gt; before moving to [[Dimra]], in Palestine.&lt;ref&gt;Glenn 1987, p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt; At Dimra, the battalion joined the rest of the 26th Brigade for the first time,&lt;ref&gt;Glenn 1987, p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt; and undertook further training until March 1941. At this time, it moved to [[Cyrenica]],&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM2/48&quot;/&gt; along with the rest of the 9th Division, to undertake further training in the desert and to relieve the [[6th Division (Australia)|6th Division]] which was deploying to [[Battle of Greece|Greece]]. Shortly after this, the Germans landed forces in Africa to reinforce the Italians and as the Axis went on the offensive, the British and Commonwealth forces in [[Libya]] were forced to retreat from [[Benghazi]] to the strategically important port town of Tobruk. In early April, the 2/48th fell back as part of the general retreat, setting up a blocking position around Tmimi during the withdrawal to prevent a German force cutting the division's route along the coast road.&lt;ref&gt;Wilmot 1993, p. 77.&lt;/ref&gt; After eight days of constant movement through the desert, the battalion reached the port.&lt;ref&gt;Wilmot 1993, p. 82.&lt;/ref&gt; They subsequently took part in the [[Siege of Tobruk|defence of Tobruk]], where the battalion saw its first action of the [[North African Campaign]] for which it would receive one of its many [[battle honour]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM2/48&quot;/&gt;

The 2/48th first entered Tobruk's defences on 9 April 1941 with the rest of the 9th Division commanded by Lieutenant General [[Leslie Morshead]]. Instructed to hold the fortress for eight weeks by General [[Archibald Percival Wavell, 1st Earl Wavell|Archibald Wavell]], Commander-in-Chief of British [[Middle East Command]], the 9th Division ended up defending the fortress for over eight months before being gradually withdrawn. The defensive system at Tobruk consisted of several lines: the outer position consisted of scattered perimeter posts and reserve company positions and was dubbed the &quot;Red Line&quot;, while the secondary defence system, which was about {{convert|2|mi|km}} behind the &quot;Red Line&quot;, was dubbed the &quot;Blue Line&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Wilmot 1993, pp. 85–86.&lt;/ref&gt; During this time the battalion alternated between occupying part of the main defence line, working in the rear areas, and conducting patrols. In mid-April, while the battalion was stationed in the western sector, these patrols resulted in the battalion capturing virtually the entire 1st Battalion of the [[102 Motorised Division Trento|Italian 62nd Regiment, Trento Division]], totalling nearly 800 officers and men.&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM2/48&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Coulthard-Clark 1998, p. 183.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wilmot 1993, pp. 116–118.&lt;/ref&gt; Later that month, the 2/48th took part in a daylight raid on a hill opposite their perimeter, behind which the Italians were massing artillery, tanks and infantry. Supported by British tanks from the [[7th Royal Tank Regiment]], the raid caught the defenders by surprise, resulting in the capture of over 360 more Italians, as well as large quantities of weapons and vehicles for only light casualties.&lt;ref&gt;Wilmot 1993, pp. 120–121.&lt;/ref&gt; In late May, a 2/48th patrol snuck out from the perimeter overnight, and evading German patrols, pushed {{convert|5|mi|km}} south, where they set up an ambush and laid a series of land mines along a bypass track that was being used by German supply lorries, two of which were subsequently destroyed. In July, the battalion moved to the Bardia road sector, opposite the Italians.&lt;ref&gt;Wilmot 1993, pp. 222 &amp; 233.&lt;/ref&gt; By October, the majority of the 9th Division, including the 2/48th Battalion, was withdrawn by sea as the [[70th Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|British 70th Division]] arrived to take over the garrison.&lt;ref&gt;Wilmot 1993, pp. 280–287.&lt;/ref&gt; Overall, the 2/48th suffered 160 casualties at Tobruk, including 38 men killed and another 18 who died of their wounds.&lt;ref name=John248&gt;Johnston 2002, p. 248.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:AWM 020073 2 48th Battalion Tobruk 1941.jpg|right|thumb|Members of the 2/48th Battalion manning a defensive position around Tobruk in 1941|alt=Soldiers wearing helmets sit in a sandbagged position near a machine gun]]

After Tobruk, the 9th Division was sent to [[Palestine (region)|Palestine]] and [[Syria]] in order to train and rest, and to undertake garrison duties as part of the Allied occupation force that had been established their following the [[Syria–Lebanon campaign]]. Under their new commander, Lieutenant Colonel [[Heathcote Howard Hammer|Heathcote Hammer]]—who had assumed command after Windeyer took over the [[20th Brigade (Australia)|20th Brigade]]—the 2/48th proceeded to train in high terrain and temperatures.&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2002, p. 68.&lt;/ref&gt;

In late June 1942, [[Axis forces]] commanded by General [[Erwin Rommel]], crossed the Egyptian frontier as part of an offensive aimed at capturing [[Alexandria]]. After making a brief stand around [[Mersa Matruh]], the British [[Eighth Army (United Kingdom)|Eighth Army]] was forced to withdraw towards the Alamein line.&lt;ref&gt;Glenn 1987, p. 101.&lt;/ref&gt; In response, the 9th Division was transported south from Syria, and hurriedly committed to [[First Battle of El Alamein]]. On 1 July, Rommel's forces launched a determined assault on the Alamein line, and on 7 July the 9th Division was ordered to launch a counter-attack. As part of this plan, the 2/48th was ordered to traverse the coastline and capture the Trig 33 ridge north of the &quot;Tel el Eisa&quot; station,&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM2/48&quot;/&gt; commencing their attack shortly before dawn on 10 July.&lt;ref&gt;Glenn 1987, p. 105.&lt;/ref&gt; After an initial artillery bombardment that disrupted the Italian troops, the main objective of the attack (Trig 33) was captured and 400 Italians were taken prisoner. The 2/48th then advanced south and captured Tel el Eisa station, which was successfully defended against a number of Axis counter-attacks.&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2002, p. 77.&lt;/ref&gt; On 22 July, the battalion was ordered to capture West Point 24 on the Tel El Eisa ridge which was held by heavily entrenched Axis forces. However, after initial success, the 2/48th came under heavy artillery and mortar fire and was forced to withdraw, having suffered over 100 casualties.&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2002, p. 87.&lt;/ref&gt; For actions during this attack, Private [[Stan Gurney]] was awarded the battalion's first [[Victoria Cross]] (VC) after he captured a machine-gun post and bayoneted the gun crew that was firing on his company, and then went on to capture a second post before being killed while taking a third. In total, the 2/48th suffered 215 casualties in the period 7 July to 23 October 1942, with 64 men killed, six dying of their wounds and 125 wounded.&lt;ref name=John248/&gt;

In August, [[Lieutenant General]] [[Bernard Montgomery, 1st Viscount Montgomery of Alamein|Bernard Montgomery]] took over command of the British Eighth Army and he succeeded in preventing the Axis advance during the [[Battle of Alam el Halfa]]. Montgomery then began preparing for an Allied offensive against the Axis forces that were now entrenching themselves. The [[Second Battle of El Alamein]] started on 23 October and finished on 7 November with Axis forces withdrawing westwards towards [[Fukah|Fuka]] to avoid encirclement. The 2/48th Battalion was engaged around Tel el Eisa, on the right of the Allied line near the coast, during this period, as the 20th and 26th Brigades pushed westwards and then endured numerous counterattacks as the Germans sought to regain control of the strategically important coast road. By the end of the month, the battalion had been heavily depleted. Having started with nearly 700 men in the line, after a week of fighting, the battalion could field only 41 fit men. As a result, the 26th Brigade was rotated out of the line just before the final German counterattack was repulsed, allowing the Allies to launch the final breakout phase of the operation.&lt;ref&gt;Coulthard-Clark 1998, pp. 230–232.&lt;/ref&gt;

For their actions during this offensive two members of the 2/48th were awarded  Victoria Crosses. The battalion's second VC was awarded to Sergeant [[Bill Kibby]] for actions across a one-week period. Kibby had charged several Axis positions and was subsequently killed attacking an enemy position with grenades on 31 October.&lt;ref name=Arthur248&gt;Arthur 2005, pp. 248–249.&lt;/ref&gt; Private [[Percy Gratwick]] earned the battalion's third VC on 25 October in the same area as Kibby. His platoon had been reduced to seven men by enemy fire so Gratwick charged the nearest enemy position of his own volition. He killed the occupants, destroyed the post with grenades and was proceeding to neutralise another position when he too was killed.&lt;ref name=Arthur248/&gt; Overall, the 2/48th suffered a further 344 casualties in the period 23 October to 5 November 1942 with 85 men killed, 13 dying of their wounds and 243 wounded.&lt;ref name=John249&gt;Johnston 2002, p. 249.&lt;/ref&gt; These losses resulted in the battalion being withdrawn from the line just as the battle reached its climax in early November. As the Allies went on the advance, the battalion moved back to Tel el Eisa, during which time it was slowly rebuilt as men who had been wounded were returned to unit, or replaced by reinforcements; this process would continue into the new year.&lt;ref&gt;Glenn 1987, pp. 171&amp;ndash;181.&lt;/ref&gt;

After helping to secure victory at El Alamein the 9th Division moved to [[Gaza City|Gaza]] in Palestine on 3 December. Since the previous October, the Australian government had sought to bring the division back to Australia in order to use it against the [[Empire of Japan|Japanese]] in the Pacific, along with the 6th and 7th Divisions which had been withdrawn the year before, and on 15 December the British prime minister, [[Winston Churchill]], had finally agreed to provide the necessary shipping.&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2002, p. 135.&lt;/ref&gt; Following a divisional parade at Gaza, the 2/48th Battalion embarked upon the troopship [[SS Nieuw Amsterdam (1937)|''Nieuw Amsterdam'']] on 24 January 1943.&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM2/48&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2002, pp. 138–140.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fighting in New Guinea===

The convoy carrying the battalion put into [[Fremantle]] in mid-February, where the small number of Western Australian personnel disembarked to begin their home leave. The rest of the battalion continued on to Port Melbourne, before moving to Adelaide by rail. In late March, after the South Australian personnel had completed their leave, the battalion was re-constituted.&lt;ref&gt;Glenn 1987, pp. 184&amp;ndash;185.&lt;/ref&gt; At that time, a series of parades were held in every Australian capital city to welcome home the 9th Division;&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2002, p. 141.&lt;/ref&gt; the 2/48th marched through Adelaide. After this, the 2/48th were transported to the [[Atherton Tableland]]s in [[Queensland]], where they established a camp on the [[Barron River (Queensland)|Barron River]], near [[Kairi, Queensland|Kairi]].&lt;ref&gt;Glenn 1987, p. 187.&lt;/ref&gt; In April 1943, the battalion was re-organised and re-trained for jungle operations in the [[South West Pacific theatre of World War II|South-West Pacific theatre]] in order to prepare it for the conditions in [[New Guinea]].&lt;ref name=Johnston143&gt;Johnston 2002, p. 143.&lt;/ref&gt; Undertaking training on the Tablelands, the battalion was converted to the [[Jungle division|tropical establishment]]. Warfare in the Pacific posed unique problems and differed greatly to that which the 2/48th had experienced in North Africa. In the jungles of New Guinea logistics and transport were significant challenges and in order to meet them, the battalion's size was reduced by over 100 men, to around 800, as its anti-aircraft and [[Universal Carrier|Bren carrier]] platoons were disbanded, while each of the battalion's four rifle companies lost most of their organic motor transport; the mobility issue would be solved by marching on foot as vehicles were relatively useless in dense jungle, while supplies would be brought up using native carriers as well as by air.&lt;ref&gt;Coates 1999, p. 49.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Palazzo 2001, p. 184.&lt;/ref&gt; In July 1943, the battalion moved to [[Cairns, Queensland|Cairns]] where they undertook amphibious training with the American [[532nd Engineer Boat and Shore Regiment]] around [[Trinity Beach]] as part of their final preparations before being committed to the fighting in New Guinea.&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2002, p. 146.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Macklin 2008, pp. 144–145&quot;&gt;Macklin 2008, pp. 144–145.&lt;/ref&gt;

Sailing aboard the [[USS Henry T. Allen (APA-15)|''Henry T. Allen'']], after arriving in New Guinea in early August, the 2/48th established a camp around [[Milne Bay]] where they undertook further amphibious training,&lt;ref&gt;Glenn 1987, pp. 194–196.&lt;/ref&gt; before taking part in the landing around [[Landing at Lae|Lae]] on 4 September 1943, as part of the final phase of the [[Salamaua–Lae campaign]]. This was the first large-scale amphibious landing conducted by the Australian forces since the landings at Gallipoli in 1915, and the battalion, along with the rest of the 26th Brigade, landed on Red Beach, about {{convert|10|mi|km}} north-west of Lae.&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2002, pp. 147–148.&lt;/ref&gt; They subsequently advanced westwards, and on 14 September captured Malahang airstrip.&lt;ref name=&quot;Macklin 2008, pp. 144–145&quot;/&gt; Following the fall of Lae to the 7th Division—which had advanced from [[Landing at Nadzab|Nadzab]] as part of the two-pronged assault—on 16 September, the Allies hurriedly launched a follow up campaign on the [[Huon Peninsula campaign|Huon Peninsula]]. Initially, only one brigade was committed to the operation, and so the 2/48th Battalion remained around Lae until the 26th Brigade was transported by sea to [[Finschhafen]] in late October in order to reinforce the 20th Brigade, which had landed the month previous in an effort to follow up troops withdrawing from Lae, before coming under heavy Japanese counterattack.&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2002, pp. 159–160.&lt;/ref&gt; During this time the battalion took part in repelling an attempted landing at Scarlet Beach, as the Japanese launched a counteroffensive against the Australian lodgement.&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM2/48&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Derrick VC flag 016246.JPG|left|thumb|Tom Derrick raising the Australian flag over Sattelberg mission|alt=A soldier raises the Australian flag]]

After the Japanese counteroffensive was defeated in late October 1943, Australian attention turned to [[Battle of Sattelberg|Sattleberg]], the site of an abandoned Lutheran mission. The newly arrived 26th Brigade was chosen to lead the assault as it was fresher than the division's other brigades.&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2002, pp. 162–163.&lt;/ref&gt; The main advance began on 17 November, although the battalion took part in a preliminary attack on Green Ridge the previous day in order to secure the start line for the advance.&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2002, pp. 167–168.&lt;/ref&gt; Pushing north-west from [[Jivevaneng]] in company with [[Matilda II (tank)|Matilda]] tanks from the [[1st Royal New South Wales Lancers|1st Tank Battalion]], the 2/48th began the drive towards Sattleberg.&lt;ref&gt;Keogh 1965, p. 329.&lt;/ref&gt; In difficult terrain and against stubborn Japanese defence,&lt;ref&gt;Keogh 1965, p. 330.&lt;/ref&gt; the advance made slow progress, nevertheless by 22 November Steeple Tree Hill was captured and the battalion reached the southern slopes of the Sattelberg feature, about {{convert|600|yd|m}} from its summit.&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2002, p. 179.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 24 November, the 2/48th's 'C' Company carried out a surprise attack on the position from the south-east. Crossing Siki Creek, the company stepped off shortly before 17:30 hours and reached the base of a steep cliff, from where they began their assault on the summit.&lt;ref name=Johnston180&gt;Johnston 2002, p. 180.&lt;/ref&gt; Held up by machine gun fire and grenades that were lobbed from the Japanese position above, and finding it almost impossible to move up the hill which had a gradient of between 45 and 60 degrees, the attack appeared in danger of failure as light began to fade and ammunition ran low. However, the actions of one of the company's platoon commanders, Sergeant [[Tom Derrick]], reinvigorated the attack. Laying his sections down to provide covering fire, he went forward alone armed with a rifle and a quantity of grenades, attacking the Japanese positions as he went. In the end he accounted for 10 such posts, before the attack was halted {{convert|100|yd|m}} from the summit.&lt;ref name=Johnston180/&gt;

During the night, the company clung to the edge of the [[plateau]] upon which the Sattelberg mission was situated, as fresh supplies were brought up from the rear. The attack was resumed at 08:35 hours the next day, supported by heavy artillery and mortar fire, however, as the 2/48th crested the ridge they found the position unoccupied, with the Japanese having abandoned it the previous night.&lt;ref&gt;Keogh 1965, p. 332.&lt;/ref&gt; For his actions the previous day, Derrick was given the honour of raising the Australian flag over the mission and was later awarded a Victoria Cross—the battalion's fourth—to go with the [[Distinguished Conduct Medal]] he had received for actions during the fighting around El Alamein.&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2002, pp. 180–181.&lt;/ref&gt; Later, Derrick was sent to an Officer Training Unit, after which he was commissioned and, returned to the battalion as a [[lieutenant]];&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2002, p. 191.&lt;/ref&gt; this was a departure from usual Army policy and was the result of intensive lobbying on Derrick's behalf.&lt;ref&gt;Long 1963, p.&amp;nbsp;77.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Stanley 1997, p.34.&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the capture of Sattelberg, the 2/48th continued the advance north along with the rest of the 26th Brigade, pushing on over difficult terrain to [[Battle of Wareo|Wareo]], where they arrived on 8 December.&lt;ref&gt;Keogh 1965, pp. 332–334.&lt;/ref&gt; Following this, the Japanese began to fall back to [[Battle of Sio|Sio]] in retreat and the battalion's involvement in combat operations on the peninsula came to an end as troops from the [[5th Division (Australia)|5th Division]] arrived to relieve them. In January, the battalion camped around the Dallman River before being withdrawn back to Finschhafen, camping around the Song River.&lt;ref&gt;Glenn 1987, p. 225.&lt;/ref&gt; In February 1944, the 2/48th was withdrawn back to Australia along with the 9th Division.&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM2/48&quot;/&gt; Sailing aboard an American [[Liberty ship]], the battalion landed in Brisbane on 20 February, and made camp at [[Kalinga, Queensland|Kalinga]] before personnel marched out for a long period of home leave.&lt;ref&gt;Glenn 1987, p. 226.&lt;/ref&gt; During its time in New Guinea, the battalion had suffered 125 casualties, of which 36 were killed, three died of wounds, eight died of illness and 77 were wounded.&lt;ref name=&quot;John249&quot;/&gt;

===Landing on Tarakan===

The battalion began reforming near [[Ravenshoe, Queensland|Ravenshoe]], on the Atherton Tablelands in April 1944.&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM2/48&quot;/&gt; During this time the composition of the units of the 9th Division underwent significant changes as many men were discharged due to medical reasons or transferred to other units and young replacements were brought in;&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2002, p. 186.&lt;/ref&gt; many of the battalion's original members had been struck down by sickness during the fighting in New Guinea.&lt;ref&gt;Glenn 1987, p. 227.&lt;/ref&gt; A long period of training followed during which the battalion undertook a number of exercises, including amphibious operations with British [[Royal Marines]] on the ''Glenearn'' and [[HMS Empire Spearhead|''Empire Spearhead'']]. Finally, following more than a year training in Australia the battalion was committed to its final deployment of the war, moving to [[Morotai Island]] in April 1945 in order to take part in the [[Battle of Tarakan (1945)|landing on Tarakan]] as part of [[Borneo Campaign (1945)|Operation Oboe]].&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM2/48&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Long406&gt;Long 1963, p. 406.&lt;/ref&gt; Embarking from Cairns, the battalion was transported in two ships, the ''Sea Cat'' and the ''Van Heutz'', the battalion arrived on Morotai later in the month, where the battalion undertook a series of manoeuvres, exercising with armour and at night, to prepare them for the coming campaign. On 22 April, the battalion embarked upon the [[HMAS Manoora (1935)|HMAS ''Manoora'']], practicing beach landings for a week before setting sail for their objective.&lt;ref&gt;Glenn 1987, pp. 233–235.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Mortar Tarakan (089460).jpg|right|thumb|A 3-inch mortar team from 2/48th Battalion during the fighting on Tarakan|alt=Soldiers operating a mortar amidst a jungle scene]]

The entire 26th Brigade group was assigned the task of capturing [[Tarakan Island]] and destroying the Japanese garrison and the assault began on 1 May 1945.&lt;ref name=Long406/&gt; Embarking on ''Manoora'', the 2/48th was in the first wave of the attack, leading the brigade in at 07:15 hours, landing on Red Beach, on the left flank of the lodgement, {{convert|2|mi|km}} from Tarakan town on the western side of the island, with the 2/23rd on their right.&lt;ref&gt;Keogh 1965, p. 441.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Long 1963, p. 414.&lt;/ref&gt; The preliminary bombardment had been successful, and as the battalion came ashore they were largely unopposed, allowing the landing craft to get in close to the shore.&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM2/48&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Long415&gt;Long 1963, p. 415.&lt;/ref&gt; Pushing inland, the 2/48th had secured its primary objectives by 08:38 hours. The right forward company took sporadic fire as it secured the oil tanks, while the battalion's left hand company was able to capture the bridge over the Sibengkok River and the high feature overlooking the landing beach without meeting any resistance.&lt;ref name=Long415/&gt;

Advancing inland, the Japanese pillboxes that had fired on the right forward company were secured after they were abandoned by the defenders. A company was then sent along the Anzac Highway to secure Collins Highway ridge. By 13:40 hours the western end of the ridge had been secured, however, the battalion began taking fire from the east.&lt;ref name=Long415/&gt; Forward momentum was maintained, although the 2/48th suffered a number of casualties, and by the end of the day a {{convert|2000|yd|m|adj=on}} by {{convert|2800|yd|m|adj=on}} beachhead had been established, and the battalion had companies on Collins Highway ridge, one on the &quot;Parks&quot; feature and another at &quot;Finch&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2002, p. 201.&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|During the planning stage, the Australian staff had named a number of hills and features in order to make passing orders and planning simpler.&lt;ref&gt;Long 1963, p. 408.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=Note}}

Over the course of the next couple of days, Japanese resistance to the Australian advance increased. After the Australians secured the island's airfield and the low ground along the west coast, throughout May and into June significant engagements took place in the hills surrounding Tarakan town.&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM2/48&quot;/&gt; On 2 May, the 2/48th captured Lyons Ridge, before pressing on towards Tarakan Hill, where they assaulted the &quot;Sykes&quot; feature supported by Matilda tanks from the [[2/9th Armoured Regiment (Australia)|2/9th Armoured Regiment]]. Here they experienced their heaviest losses of the campaign, losing six killed and 26 wounded during the three assaults up the steep slopes of the feature.&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2002, pp. 209–210.&lt;/ref&gt; Their next major engagement came in late May when the 2/48th took part in fighting around Freda Ridge as part of the drive on the main Japanese position around Fukukaku.&lt;ref name=Johnston216&gt;Johnston 2002, p. 216.&lt;/ref&gt; A company-level attack was put in and after stiff resistance the ridge was captured. The following morning, as the battalion waited for a Japanese counterattack,  Tom Derrick, who had played a key role in capturing the position the previous day, was mortally wounded. He subsequently died on 24 May 1945.&lt;ref&gt;Stanley 1997, p. 147.&lt;/ref&gt;

In June, major combat operations on the island ceased and the Australians began the mopping up phase of the campaign as the Australians sought to clear isolated pockets of Japanese troops that had evaded capture.&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2002, p. 218.&lt;/ref&gt; These operations continued into July.&lt;ref&gt;Keogh 1965, p. 443.&lt;/ref&gt; During this time, the 2/48th was assigned a sector near the Pamusian River on the eastern coast, as well as Tarakan town and the centre of the island.&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM2/48&quot;/&gt; The battalion's involvement in the Borneo campaign resulted in 174 casualties, including 37 killed and nine died of wounds or from accident.&lt;ref&gt;Long 1963, p. 451.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Glenn 1987, p. 272.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Disbandment===
Following the end of hostilities in August, the battalion remained on Tarakan to undertake garrison duties. During this time it undertook patrol operations to bring in the various pockets of Japanese troops who had not learned of the surrender; these were dangerous operations and in an effort to reduce casualties, the patrols went out with several Japanese prisoners to help talk their former comrades into surrendering.&lt;ref&gt;Glenn 1987, p. 261.&lt;/ref&gt; As the [[Demobilisation of the Australian military after World War II|demobilisation process]] began, its numbers dwindled as long-serving men were repatriated back to Australia, while others with only limited service were transferred to other units for further service. Finally, on 25 October 1945, while still on Tarakan, the battalion was disbanded.&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM2/48&quot;/&gt; The occasion was marked by a small ceremony at Tarakan involving the unit's remaining members.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article48676250 |title=Famous S.A. Battalion Goes Off The Order Of Battle |newspaper=[[The Advertiser (Adelaide)|The Advertiser (Adelaide, SA: 1931–54)]] |location=Adelaide, South Australia |date=7 November 1945 |accessdate=1 January 2014 |page=6 |publisher=National Library of Australia}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the course of the war a total of 2,838 men served with the 2/48th Battalion, of whom 343 men were killed in action or died on active service, 675 were wounded, and 20 captured.&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2002, p. 247.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the Australian War Memorial the 2/48th Battalion was &quot;Australia's highest decorated unit of the Second World War&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM2/48&quot;/&gt; Four members of the battalion received the Victoria Cross, three of them posthumously. Other decorations awarded to members of the 2/48th included: four [[Distinguished Service Order]]s, 12 [[Military Cross]]es, 10 Distinguished Conduct Medals, 24 [[Military Medal]]s and 36 [[Mentioned in Despatches|Mentions in Despatches]].&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2002, p. 253.&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|These figures vary slightly from those of the AWM, which are: four VCs, four DSOs, 11 MCs, 10 DCMs, 23 MMs and 39 MIDs.&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM2/48&quot;/&gt;|group=Note}}

==Commanding officers==
The following officers commanded the 2/48th Battalion during the war:&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM2/48&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Johnston 2002, p. xvi.&lt;/ref&gt;
* Lieutenant Colonel [[Victor Windeyer]] (9 August 1940&amp;nbsp;– 6 January 1942);
* Lieutenant Colonel [[Heathcote Howard Hammer|Heathcote Hammer]] (8 January 1942&amp;nbsp;– 18 June 1943);
* Lieutenant Colonel Robert Ainslie (22 July 1943&amp;nbsp;– 12 August 1945).

==Battle honours==
The 2/48th Battalion was awarded the 14 [[battle honours]] for its service during the war:&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM2/48&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Maitland 1999, pp. 139–145.&lt;/ref&gt;
*  [[North African Campaign|North Africa 1941–42]], [[Siege of Tobruk|Defence of Tobruk]], [[North African Campaign|El Adem Road]], [[North African Campaign|The Salient 1941]], [[First Battle of El Alamein|Defence of Alamein Line]], [[North African Campaign|Tell el Eisa]], [[Second Battle of El Alamein|El Alamein]], [[South West Pacific theatre of World War II|South-West Pacific 1943–45]], [[Salamaua-Lae campaign|Lae–Nadzab]], [[Battle of Finschhafen|Finschhafen]], [[Huon Peninsula campaign|Defence of Scarlet Beach]], [[Battle of Sattelberg|Sattelberg]], [[Borneo Campaign (1945)|Borneo]], [[Battle of Tarakan (1945)|Tarakan]].

==Notes==
;Footnotes
{{reflist|group=Note}}

;Citations
{{reflist|3}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book |last=Arthur |first=Max |title=Symbol of Courage: Men Behind the Medal |publisher=Pan Books |location=London |year=2005 |isbn=978-0-330-49133-4}}
* {{cite book |last=Coates |first=John |authorlink= |title=Bravery Above Blunder: The 9th Australian Division at Finschhafen, Sattelberg, and Sio |year=1999 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=South Melbourne, Victoria |isbn=0-19-550837-8}}
* {{cite book|last=Coulthard-Clark|first=Chris|title=The Encyclopaedia of Australia's Battles|year=1998|publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin|location=Sydney, New South Wales |isbn=1-86448-611-2}}
* {{cite book|last=Glenn|first=John|title=Tobruk to Tarakan: The Story of the 2/48th Battalion, A.I.F|year=1987 |origyear=1960|publisher=John Burridge Military Antiques|location=Swanbourne, Western Australia |oclc=220180650}}
* {{cite book |last=Johnston |first=Mark |authorlink=Mark Johnston (historian) |title=That Magnificent 9th: An Illustrated History of the 9th Australian Division 1940–46 |publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin|location=Crows Nest, New South Wales  |year=2002 |isbn=1-86508-654-1}}
* {{cite book|last=Keogh|first=Eustace|title=The South West Pacific 1941–45|year=1965|publisher=Grayflower Productions|location=Melbourne, Victoria |oclc=7185705}}
* {{cite book|last=Kuring|first=Ian|title=Redcoats to Cams: A History of Australian Infantry 1788–2001|year=2004|publisher=Australian Military History Publications|location=Loftus, New South Wales |isbn=1-876439-99-8}}
* {{cite book|last=Long|first=Gavin |authorlink=Gavin Long |title=To Benghazi|year=1952|series=Australia in the War of 1939–1945. Series 1—Army|volume=I|edition=1st|publisher=Australian War Memorial|location=Canberra, Australian Capital Territory|url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070200/ |oclc=18400892 }}
* {{cite book|last=Long|first=Gavin|title=The Final Campaigns|series=Australia in the War of 1939–1945, Series 1—Army |volume= VII|year=1963|edition=1st|publisher=Australian War Memorial|location=Canberra, Australian Capital Territory|url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070206/|oclc=1297619}}
* {{cite book|last=Macklin|first=Robert|authorlink=Robert Macklin|title=Bravest: How Some of Australia's War Heroes Won Their Medals|year=2008|publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin|location=Crows Nest, New South Wales, Australia|isbn=978-1-74114-882-4}}
* {{cite book|last=Maitland|first=Gordon|title=The Second World War and its Australian Army Battle Honours|year=1999|publisher=Kangaroo Press|location=East Roseville, New South Wales|isbn=0-86417-975-8}}
* {{cite book |last=Palazzo |first=Albert |authorlink= |title=The Australian Army: A History of its Organisation 1901–2001 |year=2001 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=South Melbourne, Victoria |isbn=0-19-551507-2}}
* {{cite book|last=Palazzo|first=Albert|chapter=Organising for Jungle Warfare|title=The Foundations of Victory: The Pacific War 1943–1944|year=2004|editor=Dennis, Peter |editor2=Grey, Jeffrey|publisher=Army History Unit|location=Canberra, Australian Capital Territory |url=http://www.army.gov.au/Our-history/Army-History-Unit/Chief-of-Army-History-Conference/Previous-Conference-Proceedings/~/media/Files/Our%20history/AAHU/Conference%20Papers%20and%20Images/2003/2003-The_Pacific_War_1943-1944_Part_1.ashx|pages=86–101|isbn=978-0-646-43590-9}}
* {{cite book|last=Stanley|first=Peter |authorlink=Peter Stanley |title=Tarakan: An Australian Tragedy|year=1997|publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin|location=Sydney, New South Wales|isbn=1-86448-278-8}}
* {{cite book|last=Wilmot|first=Chester|authorlink=Chester Wilmot|title=Tobruk 1941 |origyear=1944 |year=1993 |publisher=Penguin Books Australia |location=Ringwood, New South Wales |isbn=0-14-017584-9}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
* [https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1020301/ 2/48th War Diaries (AWM52, Item 8/3/36)]

{{Infantry formations of the Second Australian Imperial Force |state=collapsed}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:2 48th Battalion (Australia)}}
[[Category:Australian World War II battalions|48]]
[[Category:Military units and formations established in 1940|48]]
[[Category:Military units and formations disestablished in 1945|48]]</text>
      <sha1>brs5w6b1i84vxza41jeqp1svgs5a0vu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
