<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>40th Infantry Division Slavonska</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>46681890</id>
    <revision>
      <id>740754569</id>
      <parentid>723298516</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-23T02:34:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Books */http&amp;rarr;https for [[Google Books]] and [[Google News]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="38474">{{DISPLAYTITLE:40th Infantry Division ''Slavonska''}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2016}}
{{Good article}}
{{Infobox military unit
| unit_name = 40th Infantry Division ''Slavonska''
| image =
| caption =
| dates = 
| country = {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Yugoslavia}}
| countries = 
| allegiance =
| branch = [[Royal Yugoslav Army]]
| type = [[Infantry]]
| role = 
| size = [[division (military)|Division]] (26,000–27,000 officers and men)
| command_structure = [[4th Army (Kingdom of Yugoslavia)|4th Army]]
| garrison =
| garrison_label =
| nickname =
| patron =
| motto =
| colors =
| colors_label =
| march =
| mascot =
| equipment =
| equipment_label =
| battles =[[Invasion of Yugoslavia]] (1941)
| anniversaries =
| decorations =
| battle_honours =
| battle_honours_label =
| disbanded =
| flying_hours =
| website =
| notable_commanders = [[Ratko Raketić]]
&lt;!-- Insignia --&gt;
| identification_symbol =
| identification_symbol_label =
| identification_symbol_2 =
| identification_symbol_2_label =
| identification_symbol_3 =
| identification_symbol_3_label =
| identification_symbol_4 =
| identification_symbol_4_label =
}}

The '''40th Infantry Division ''Slavonska''''' was an [[infantry]] [[formation (military)|formation]] of the [[Royal Yugoslav Army]] that formed part of the Yugoslav [[4th Army (Kingdom of Yugoslavia)|4th Army]] during the [[Nazi Germany|German]]-led [[Axis Powers|Axis]] [[invasion of Yugoslavia|invasion]] of the [[Kingdom of Yugoslavia]] in April 1941. It was raised from the ''Slavonska'' military district, and was a very large and unwieldy formation which was almost entirely reliant on animal transport for mobility. Largely manned by [[Croats|Croat]] troops, many of whom saw the Germans as potential liberators from [[Serbs|Serbian]] oppression during the [[interwar period]], the division also lacked modern arms and sufficient ammunition.

The preliminary attacks launched across the Drava by the Germans on 6 April were enough to spark revolts within the units of the division. One of its three infantry [[regiment]]s rebelled the following day, and by 8 April the rebels had taken over [[Bjelovar]]. The division continued to disintegrate over the following days, then crumbled in the face of the [[combined arms]] assault of the [[8th Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|8th Panzer Division]] when it broke out of its bridgehead at [[Barcs]] on 10 April. A few mainly Serb remnants of the division continued to withdraw into [[Bosnia (region)|Bosnia]] over the next week until a [[ceasefire]] was negotiated on 15 April. The Yugoslav Army [[Surrender (military)|surrendered]] on 18 April.
[[File:Operation25yu.jpg|thumb|350px|Map of the German invasion of Yugoslavia|alt=a black and white map]]

==Background==
The [[Royal Yugoslav Army]] ({{lang-sh-Latn|Vojska Kraljevine Jugoslavije}}, VKJ) was formed after [[World War I]] as the Army of the [[Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes]] (Kingdom of SCS), when that country was created on 1 December 1918. To defend the new kingdom, an army was formed around the nucleus of the victorious [[Royal Serbian Army]] combined with armed formations raised in the former parts of the [[Austro-Hungarian Empire]] that joined with the [[Kingdom of Serbia]] to form the new state. Many former Austro-Hungarian officers and soldiers became members of the new army.{{sfn|Figa|2004|p=235}} From its beginning, the army, like other aspects of public life in the new kingdom, was dominated by ethnic Serbs, who saw the army as a means by which to secure Serb [[hegemony]] in the new state.{{sfn|Hoptner|1963|pp=160–161}}

The development of the army was hampered by the poor economy of the kingdom, and this continued through the 1920s. In 1929, King [[Alexander I of Yugoslavia|Alexander]] changed the name of the country to the [[Kingdom of Yugoslavia]], at which time the army became the VKJ. The army budget remained tight, and as tensions rose across Europe during the 1930s, it became hard to secure weapons and munitions from other countries.{{sfn|Tomasevich|1975|p=60}} Consequently, at the time [[World War II]] broke out in September 1939, the VKJ had several serious weaknesses, which included reliance on [[Working animal#Transportation|draught animals]] for transport, and the large size of its [[military organisation|formations]]. For example, Yugoslav [[infantry]] [[division (military)|divisions]] had twice the number of men of contemporary British infantry divisions.{{sfn|Tomasevich|1975|p=58}}{{sfn|Brayley|Chappell|2001|p=17}} These characteristics resulted in slow, unwieldy formations, and the inadequate supply of arms and munitions meant that even the very large Yugoslav formations had low firepower.{{sfn|Tomasevich|1975|pp=58–59}} Older generals better suited to the [[trench warfare]] of World War I,{{sfn|Hoptner|1963|p=161}} were combined with an army that was not equipped or trained to resist the fast-moving [[combined arms]] approach used by the [[Nazi Germany|Germans]] in [[invasion of Poland|Poland]] and [[Battle of France|France]].{{sfn|Tomasevich|1975|p=57}}

The weaknesses of the VKJ in strategy, structure, equipment, mobility and supply were exacerbated to a significant degree by the lack of unity across Yugoslavia which had resulted from two decades of Serb hegemony,{{sfn|Tomasevich|1975|p=63}} and the attendant lack of political legitimacy achieved by the central government.{{sfn|Ramet|2006|p=111}} Attempts to address the lack of unity came too late to ensure that the VKJ was a cohesive force. [[Fifth column]] activity was also a serious concern, not only from the Croatian nationalist ''[[Ustaše]]'', but from the [[Slovenes|Slovene]] and [[Germans of Yugoslavia|ethnic German]] minorities in the country.{{sfn|Tomasevich|1975|p=63}}

==Structure==

===Peacetime organisation===
According to regulations issued by the Royal Yugoslav Army in 1935,{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=99}} the 40th Infantry Division ''Slavonska'' was to be raised from the ''Slavonska'' military district, which was headquartered in [[Bjelovar]]. The ''Slavonska'' military district was under the command of the 4th Army district headquartered in [[Zagreb]]. It was named after the [[Slavonia]] region.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=102}} In September 1939, after the German invasion of Poland, the division underwent a trial [[mobilization|mobilisation]] which included a large proportion of its units.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=202}} The divisional district included the [[regiment]]al districts of the 42nd, 43rd and 108th Infantry Regiments.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=226}}

===Wartime organisation===
The wartime organisation of the Royal Yugoslav Army was laid down by regulations issued in 1936–37,{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=104}} and the strength of an infantry division was 26,000–27,000 men.{{sfn|Tomasevich|1975|p=58}} A total of 11,200 horses and other [[Pack animal|pack]] and draught animals were required to provide mobility for each infantry division. The theoretical wartime organisation of a fully mobilised Yugoslav infantry division was:{{sfn|Niehorster|2015b}}{{sfn|Terzić|1982|pp=104, 106–107}}
*headquarters
*divisional infantry headquarters, with three or four infantry regiments
*divisional artillery headquarters, with one or two artillery regiments
*a cavalry [[battalion]] with two [[squadron (military)|squadron]]s, a bicycle squadron and a machine gun [[platoon]]
*a pioneer battalion of three [[company (military)|companies]]
*an anti-tank company, equipped with twelve {{convert|37|mm|abbr=on}} or {{convert|47|mm|abbr=on}} [[anti-tank gun]]s
*a machine gun company
*an [[Anti-aircraft warfare|anti-aircraft]] machine gun company
*a [[Military communications|signals]] company
*logistics units

Each infantry regiment was to consist of three infantry battalions, a machine gun company,{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=104}} and the divisional artillery regiments were animal-drawn and largely equipped with World War I-vintage pieces.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|pp=107, 119}} An artillery regiment consisted of four battalions, one of {{convert|100|mm|abbr=on}} light [[howitzer]]s, one of {{convert|65|mm|abbr=on}} or {{convert|75|mm|abbr=on}} [[mountain gun]]s, and two of {{convert|75|mm|abbr=on}} or {{convert|80|mm|abbr=on}} [[field gun]]s.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|pp=106–107}}

==Planned deployment==
{{Location map+
| Yugoslavia (1939-41)
| width          = 300
| float          = 
| border         =
| caption        = Planned deployment area of the division
| alt            =
| relief         =
| AlternativeMap =
| overlay_image  =
| places         =
{{Location map~
 | Yugoslavia (1939-41)
 | label = 40th Inf Div
 | label_size = 75
 | lat = 45.713056
 | long = 17.48
 | background = 
 | mark = Red pog.svg
 | position = right
 }}
}}
The 40th Infantry Division ''Slavonska'' was a component of the [[4th Army (Kingdom of Yugoslavia)|4th Army]] as part of the [[1st Army Group (Kingdom of Yugoslavia)|1st Army Group]], which was responsible for the defence of northwestern Yugoslavia.{{sfn|Geografski institut JNA|1952}} The 4th Army was to deploy in a cordon along the western sector of the [[Kingdom of Hungary (1920–46)|Hungarian]] border, with the 40th Infantry Division ''Slavonska'' opposite the Hungarian town of [[Barcs]], between [[Kloštar Podravski]] and [[Čađavica, Croatia|Čađavica]], with the main line of defence along the northern slopes of the [[Bilogora]] mountain range, and divisional headquarters at [[Pivnica Slavonska]].{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=256}} On the left flank of the division was the [[27th Infantry Division Savska|27th Infantry Division ''Savska'']] opposite the Hungarian village of [[Gyékényes]],{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=257}} and on the right flank was the [[17th Infantry Division Vrbaska|17th Infantry Division ''Vrbaska'']] of the [[2nd Army (Yugoslavia)|2nd Army]], which formed part of the [[2nd Army Group (Yugoslavia)|2nd Army Group]], with the boundary running from just east of Slatina through [[Požega, Croatia|Požega]] towards [[Banja Luka]].{{sfn|U.S. Army|1986|p = 37}} Border guard units in the division's area of responsibility consisted of the 2nd Battalion of the 393rd Reserve Regiment.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|pp=256–258}}

==Operations==

===Mobilisation===
As the Axis invasion began, the 40th Infantry Division ''Slavonska'' was partially mobilised,{{sfn|Barefield|1993|pp=52–53}} with some elements of the division still mobilising, some in concentration areas, and only a small proportion actually deployed in their planned positions:{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=256}}
*the divisional commander ''Brigadni đeneral''{{refn|Equivalent to a U.S. Army [[Brigadier general (United States)|brigadier general]].{{sfn|Niehorster|2015a}}|group = lower-alpha}} [[Ratko Raketić]] and his headquarters staff were mobilising in Bjelovar
*the 42nd Infantry Regiment with two battalions was marching towards their positions near [[Daruvar]], while the rest of the regiment was mobilising in Bjelovar and could not move due to lack of draught animals
*the 43rd Infantry Regiment, with about 75–80 percent of its troops and 30 percent of its animals, was marching from its mobilisation centre in Požega towards [[Našice]], but had only reached [[Jakšić, Croatia|Jakšić]], {{convert|9|km|mi|links=no}} northeast of Požega
*the 108th Infantry Regiment was marching from Bjelovar but had only reached [[Severin, Bjelovar-Bilogora County|Severin]]
*the 40th Artillery Regiment was still mobilising with the headquarters and one battalion in [[Osijek]] and two battalions in Varaždin
*the divisional cavalry battalion and machine gun battalion were unable to deploy from [[Virovitica]] due to lack of animals, although on 5 April, Nedeljković had requisitioned private cars for the machine gun battalion and ordered it to concentrate at [[Lukač, Croatia|Lukač]] northeast of Virovitica
*the remainder of the divisional units were at their mobilisation centres in and around Bjelovar

The 43rd Infantry Regiment was ordered to march east to join the 17th Infantry Division ''Vrbaska'', which was part of the 2nd Army Group's 2nd Army. The 89th Infantry Regiment, originally allocated to the 17th Infantry Division ''Vrbaska'', was ordered to march from its mobilisation location in Sisak and join the 40th Infantry Division ''Slavonska'' to replace the 43rd Infantry Regiment. The divisional cavalry battalion did not receive sufficient horses, and had to deploy on foot as infantry. The division was without artillery support throughout the fighting because the 40th Artillery Regiment did not complete mobilisation.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|pp=256–257}}

===6 April===
[[Oberkommando des Heeres|German Army headquarters]] wanted to capture the bridges over the Drava intact, and from 1 April had issued orders to the [[2nd Army (Wehrmacht)|2nd Army]] to conduct preliminary operations aimed at seizing the bridge at Barcs and the railway bridge northeast of Koprivnica by ''[[coup de main]]''. As a result, limited objective attacks were launched along the line of the Drava by the [[XLVI Panzer Corps (Germany)|XLVI Motorised Corps]], despite the fact that they were not expected to launch offensive operations until 10 April.{{sfn|U.S. Army|1986|p = 52}} During the day, the German ''[[Luftwaffe]]'' bombed and strafed Yugoslav positions and troops on the march, and by the evening it had become clear to the Germans that the Yugoslavs would not be resisting stubbornly at the border. XLVI Motorised Corps was then ordered to begin seizing bridges over the Drava, including at Barcs. The local attacks were sufficient to inflame dissent among the Croat troops of the 4th Army, who refused to resist Germans they considered their liberators from [[Serb]]ian oppression during the [[interwar period]].{{sfn|U.S. Army|1986|pp = 52–53}}{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=293}}

The continuing mobilisation and concentration of the 4th Army was hampered by escalating fifth column activities and propaganda fomented by the ''Ustaše''. Some units stopped mobilising, or began returning to their mobilisation centres from their concentration areas.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=293}} The Yugoslav radio network linking the division with the 4th Army and flanking divisions was sabotaged by the ''Ustaše'' on 6 April, and radio communications within the 4th Army remained poor throughout the fighting.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=265}}

===7 April===
About 19:00 on 7 April, German units in regimental strength with a few tanks began to cross the Drava near Barcs in the divisional sector. They quickly overcame the resistance of the 2nd Battalion of the 393rd Reserve Regiment, which was influenced by ''Ustaše'' propaganda. The border guards abandoned their positions and weapons and retreated to Virovitica.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=312}} The 108th Infantry Regiment of the division had mobilised in Bjelovar and on 7 April was marching towards Virovitica to take up positions. That night, Croat members of the regiment revolted, arresting the Serb officers, [[non-commissioned officer]]s and soldiers. The regiment then marched back to Bjelovar, where it joined up with other rebellious units about noon on 8 April.{{sfn|Krzak|2006|p = 583}}

As the 108th Infantry Regiment was responsible for the right sector of the divisional defence, this meant that the 42nd Infantry Regiment, which was originally responsible only for the left sector, had to extend across the entire divisional frontage.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=257}} During the night, the commander of the divisional cavalry battalion sent patrols towards the German bridgehead, but local ''Ustaše'' sympathisers misled them into believing the Germans were already across the Drava at Barcs in strength.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=312}} The Germans were subsequently able to consolidate their bridgehead at Barcs overnight.{{sfn|Krzak|2006|p = 583}}

===8 April===
On 8 April, the German XLVI Motorised Corps continued with its limited objective attacks to expand their bridgehead at Barcs. A German regiment broke through the border troops and approached Virovitica. At this point, the entire divisional sector was defended by a single unit, the divisional cavalry battalion, which had been transported there in requisitioned cars due to the lack of horses. Two understrength and wavering battalions of the 42nd Infantry Regiment arrived at [[Pčelić]], {{convert|15|km|links=no}} southwest of Virovitica.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=329}}
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-185-0137-15A, Jugoslawien, Panzer III im Feld.jpg|thumb|left|The Germans expanded their bridgehead over the Drava at Barcs on 8 April|alt=two tanks with crews]]
By noon, the rebels of the 108th Infantry Regiment were approaching Bjelovar, and were joined by elements of the 42nd Infantry Regiment and other units of the division. The leader of the rebels in Bjelovar was ''Kapetan''{{refn|Equivalent to a U.S. Army [[Captain (armed forces)|captain]].{{sfn|Niehorster|2015a}}|group = lower-alpha}} [[Ivan Mrak]], a reserve aviator. When 4th Army commander ''Armijski đeneral''{{refn|Equivalent to a U.S. Army [[Lieutenant general (United States)|lieutenant general]].{{sfn|Niehorster|2015a}}|group = lower-alpha}} [[Petar Nedeljković]] became aware of the rebels' approach, he ordered the local [[gendarmerie]] commander to maintain order, but was advised this would not be possible, as local gendarmerie conscripts would not report for duty.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=329}} His headquarters reported the presence of the rebels to the headquarters of the 1st Army Group, suggesting that the [[Royal Yugoslav Air Force]] could bomb the rebel units.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=330}} The 8th Bomber Regiment at [[Rovine, Gradiška|Rovine]] was even warned to receive orders to use its [[Bristol Blenheim]] Mk I [[light bombers]] to bomb the 108th Infantry Regiment, but the idea was subsequently abandoned.{{sfn|Shores|Cull|Malizia|1987|p=215}} Instead, it was decided to request that the leader of the [[Croatian Peasant Party]], [[Vladko Maček]] intervene with the rebels.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=330}}

[[Josip Broz Tito]] and the Central Committee of the [[League of Communists of Yugoslavia|Communist Party of Yugoslavia]], then located in Zagreb, along with the Central Committee of the [[League of Communists of Croatia|Communist Party of Croatia]], sent a delegation to 4th Army headquarters in Bjelovar urging them to issue arms to workers to help defend Zagreb. [[Pavle Gregorić]], who was a member of both Central Committees, went to the headquarters twice, and was able to speak briefly with Nedeljković, but could not convince him to do so. On the same day, Maček, who had returned to Zagreb after briefly joining the post-[[Yugoslav coup d'état]] government of [[Dušan Simović]], agreed to send an emissary to the 108th Infantry Regiment urging them to obey their officers, but they did not respond to his appeal.{{sfn|Tomasevich|2001|pp = 50–52}}

Later in the day, two trucks of rebels arrived at 4th Army headquarters with the intention of killing the staff. The headquarters guard force prevented this, but the operations staff immediately withdrew from Bjelovar to [[Popovača]].{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=330}} After the rebels issued several unanswered ultimatums, around 8,000 rebels attacked Bjelovar, assisted by fifth-columnists within the city. The city then surrendered, and many Yugoslav officers and soldiers were captured by the rebels. When Nedeljković heard of the fall of the city, he called the Mayor of Bjelovar, [[Julije Makanec]] and threatened to bomb the city if the prisoners were not immediately released. Detained officers from 4th Army headquarters and the 108th Infantry Regiment were then sent to Zagreb. About 16:00, Nedeljković informed the [[Ban of Croatia]], [[Ivan Šubašić]] of the revolt, but Šubašić was powerless to influence events. About 18:00, Makanec proclaimed that Bjelovar was part of an independent Croatian state.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=331}}

===9 April===
On the morning of 9 April, the German bridgehead at Barcs had expanded to Lukač, {{convert|7|km}} north of Virovitica.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=346}} Following up the withdrawal of the divisional cavalry battalion, the Germans seized [[Suho Polje]], west of Virovitica, cutting the main road to Slatina,{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=346}} and the rebel Croat troops at Bjelovar made contact with them.{{sfn|Krzak|2006|p = 583}} By 11:00, the divisional front line consisted of the 1st and 2nd Battalions of the 42nd Infantry Regiment and a company of the divisional cavalry battalion on the right, and the 4th Battalion of the 42nd Infantry Regiment and a company of the divisional cavalry battalion on the left. The 3rd Battalion of the 42nd Infantry Regiment was held in depth. The left flank was screened by the rest of the divisional cavalry battalion deployed around [[Pitomača]].{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=346}} The 89th Infantry Regiment, marching from its concentration area in Sisak, arrived at divisional headquarters at Pivnica Slavonska,{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=346}} to replace the 43rd Infantry Regiment, which had been transferred to the 17th Infantry Division ''Vrbaska''.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=257}}

Other reinforcements included elements of the 4th Army anti-aircraft units sent from Lipik, but the divisional artillery regiment had not completed mobilisation.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=346}} The rebels in Bjelovar issued false orders to the 1st Battalion of the 42nd Infantry Regiment, directing it to fall back to Bjelovar.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=345}} At 11:15, Nedeljković arrived at divisional headquarters and shortly afterwards ordered Raketić to launch a counterattack on the German bridgehead at Barcs at dawn the following day. Nedeljković also visited ''Divizijski đeneral''{{refn|Equivalent to a U.S. Army [[Major general (United States)|major general]].{{sfn|Niehorster|2015a}}|group=lower-alpha}} [[Dragoslav Milosavljević]], the commander of the 17th Infantry Division ''Vrbaska'' on the right flank of the 4th Army, to arrange support from that division during the pending attack.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=346}} However, because the majority of that division's troops had yet to arrive from Bosnia, all it was able to do was advance its left flank, stationing battalions in [[Čačinci]] and [[Crnac, Virovitica-Podravina County|Crnac]] west of Slatina.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=347}} The 40th Infantry Division ''Slavonska'' spent the remainder of the day preparing for the counterattack, but were hindered by German artillery and air attacks. In an indication of the state of his division, during a visit to the front line, Raketić and his chief of staff were fired at by troops of the 42nd Infantry Regiment.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=346}}

Elements of the 4th Army began to withdraw southwards on 9 April.{{sfn|Tomasevich|1975|p = 68}} On the night of 9/10 April, those Croats that had remained with their units also began to desert or turn on their commanders,{{sfn|Krzak|2006|pp = 583–584}} and in the 40th Infantry Division ''Slavonska'', almost all the remaining troops were Serbs.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=346}} Due to the increasing momentum of the revolt, the commander of the 1st Army Group, ''Armijski đeneral'' [[Milorad Petrović]] concluded that the 4th Army was no longer an effective formation and could not resist the Germans.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=345}} Maček issued a further ineffectual plea to calm the rebellion.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=348}} On the evening of 9 April, ''[[Generaloberst]]''{{refn|Equivalent to a U.S. Army [[General (United States)|general]].{{sfn|Stein|1984|p=295}}|group=lower-alpha}} [[Maximilian von Weichs]], commander of the German 2nd Army, was ready to launch major offensive operations from the bridgeheads on the following day.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=361}} His plan involved two main thrusts. The first would be spearheaded by the [[14th Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|14th Panzer Division]] breaking out of the Gyékényes bridgehead and drive towards Zagreb,{{sfn|U.S. Army|1986|p = 58}} and the second would see the [[8th Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|8th Panzer Division]] break out of the Barcs bridgehead and turn east between the Drava and [[Sava]] rivers to attack towards Belgrade.{{sfn|U.S. Army|1986|p = 53}}

===10 April===
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-185-0137-14A, Jugoslawien, Panzer III in Fahrt.jpg|thumb|The 8th Panzer Division broke out of the Barcs bridgehead  on 10 April|alt=a black and white photograph of a moving tank]]
The 40th Infantry Division ''Slavonska'' was battered by German artillery fire during the night 9/10 April. Seriously depleted by desertion and weakened by revolt, it was unable to mount the ordered counterattack against the Barcs bridgehead on the morning of 10 April. The 42nd Infantry Regiment could only muster 600 men, and the 89th Infantry Regiment only slightly more. The divisional cavalry battalion was also heavily reduced in strength, and divisional artillery amounted to one anti-aircraft battery. The border units, responsible for demolition tasks on the line from Bjelovar south to [[Čazma]], refused to follow orders. Having abandoned the counterattack, Raketić decided to establish a defensive line at Pćelić to hinder German movement east towards Slatina.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=366}}

Soon after dawn, the main thrust of the XLVI Motorised Corps, consisting of ''[[Generalmajor]]'' [[Walter Neumann-Silkow]]'s 8th Panzer Division leading the [[16th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|16th Motorised Infantry Division]], crossed the Drava at Barcs.{{sfn|U.S. Army|1986|p = 53}} Anti-tank fire destroyed a few of the lead tanks, but after the Germans reinforced their vanguard, the resistance of the 40th Infantry Division ''Slavonska'' had been broken by noon. The remaining troops of the 42nd Infantry Regiment were either captured or fled into the hills to the south. Units of the 89th Infantry Regiment, which had been providing depth to the defensive position, began retreating south towards Slavonska Požega. ''Ustaše'' sympathisers and Yugoslav ''[[Volksdeutsche]]'' (ethnic German) troops either ran away or surrendered.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=366}} By 13:30, the hard-pressed divisional cavalry battalion began to withdraw south towards Daruvar, attacking rebelling troops along their route. Raketić himself fled to [[Nova Gradiška]] via [[Voćin]] and Slavonska Požega, during which his car was again fired on by rebel troops.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=367}} The 8th Panzer Division continued southeast between the Drava and Sava rivers, and meeting almost no further resistance, had reached Slatina by evening.{{sfn|U.S. Army|1986|p = 53}} Right flank elements of the 8th Panzer Division penetrated south into the Bilogora range, reaching [[Daruvar]] and Voćin by evening.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=366}}

Late in the day, as the situation was becoming increasingly desperate throughout the country, Simović, who was both the [[Prime Minister of Yugoslavia|Prime Minister]] and [[Chief of the General Staff (Yugoslavia)|Yugoslav Chief of the General Staff]], broadcast the following message:{{sfn|U.S. Army|1986|p = 53}}&lt;blockquote&gt;All troops must engage the enemy wherever encountered and with every means at their disposal. Don't wait for direct orders from above, but act on your own and be guided by your judgement, initiative, and conscience.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The XLVI Motorised Corps encountered little resistance from the 40th Infantry Division ''Slavonska'', and by the evening of 10 April the whole 4th Army was disintegrating.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=364}} About 23:00, German 2nd Army headquarters directed the 8th Panzer and 16th Motorised Infantry Division to drive to the north of Belgrade to link up with the [[1st Panzer Army|First Panzer Group]] which was thrusting to towards Belgrade from the east. At midnight, 2nd Army headquarters declared that the Yugoslav northern front had been decisively defeated, and tasked corps engineer units to consolidate bridging across major rivers. The main body units of the XLVI Motorised Corps moved forward to Virovitica and Slatina. At midnight, the corps commander, ''[[General der Panzertruppe]]'' [[Heinrich von Vietinghoff]] issued orders for the 8th Panzer Division to continue towards Belgrade via [[Osijek]], but directed the 16th Motorised Infantry Division to thrust west as far as [[Sremska Mitrovica]] then turn south to drive towards [[Sarajevo]] via [[Zvornik]].{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=364}}

===11 April===
On 11 April, the rear area staff of 4th Army headquarters were captured by ''Ustaše'' at [[Topusko]], and were soon handed over to the Germans by their captors. Nedeljković and his operations staff escaped, and made their way to [[Prijedor]].{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=386}} Other units were retreating into Bosnia, including two battalions and 2–3 artillery batteries from the 40th Infantry Division ''Slavonska''. Nedeljković attempted to deploy rear area units of the 17th Infantry Division ''Vrbaska'' into a defensive line along the Una at [[Dubica, Bosnia-Herzegovina|Bosanska Dubica]], [[Kostajnica, Bosnia and Herzegovina|Bosanska Kostajnica]], [[Novi Grad, Bosnia and Herzegovina|Bosanski Novi]], [[Bosanska Krupa]] and [[Bihać]], and called Yugoslav Supreme Command in Sarajevo to request reinforcements. With his remaining troops, Raketić attempted to establish a defensive line along the Sava between [[Jasenovac, Sisak-Moslavina County|Jasenovac]] and the mouth of the [[Vrbas (river)|Vrbas]]. These efforts were significantly hampered by ''Ustaše'' propaganda.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|pp=386–387}} The German orders for the following day were to pursue the remnants of the Yugoslav Army through Bosnia towards Sarajevo, where they would be met by the First Panzer Group attacking from the south and east. The 8th Panzer Division and 16th Motorised Infantry Division faced almost no resistance as they drove east towards Belgrade, capturing Našice, Osijek, Vinkovci and [[Vukovar]] during the day. On the night of 11/12 April, they captured Sremska Mitrovica, Ruma and secured a crossing over the Danube via an undamaged bridge near [[Bogojevo]].{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=388}}

===Fate===
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1975-036-24, Jugoslawien, serbische Gefangene.jpg|thumb|left|Surrendered Yugoslav troops handing in their weapons|alt=a black and white photograph of soldiers in helmets watching other soldiers laying down rifles in a pile]]
The following day, the northern column of the 14th Panzer Division drove via [[Glina, Croatia|Glina]] and crossed the Una at both Bosanska Kostajnica and Bosanski Novi before continuing its push east. Elements of the LI Corps also pushed east, establishing bridgeheads over the Kupa. A fragment of the 40th Infantry Division ''Slavonska'', numbering around 300 troops, which had been holding a position on the Sava at Bosanska Gradiška, retreated to Jajce via Banja Luka. When they arrived at Jajce, Nedeljković ordered them to take up blocking positions in the narrow Vrbas valley at [[Krupa na Vrbasu|Krupa]] on the road between Banja Luka and [[Mrkonjić Grad]]. The rear area units of the 17th Infantry Division ''Vrbaska'' were ordered to block the road from [[Kotor Varoš]] to Doboj.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=415}}

In response to Nedeljković's request for reinforcements, Simović had sent a number of units by rail via [[Tuzla]]. These included a cadet battalion and a company of the 27th Infantry Regiment, detached from the [[1st Infantry Division Cerska|1st Infantry Division ''Cerska'']]. By the time the reinforcements arrived, Banja Luka had been evacuated in the face of German tanks and an ''Ustaše''-led revolt. The cadet battalion was redirected to [[Ključ, Una-Sana Canton|Ključ]] to block the road Ključ{{snd}}Mrkonjić Grad{{snd}}Jajce. Nedeljković did not have the option of withdrawing via [[Bugojno]] or [[Prozor-Rama|Prozor]] as those towns had been taken over by the ''Ustaše''.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=415}}

On 14 April, under pressure from the 14th Panzer Division, remnants of the 4th Army continued to withdraw towards Sarajevo via Jajce and Travnik. The cadet battalion at Ključ managed to briefly delay the German advance through Mrkonjić Grad, but were overcome by tanks and air attacks. The bridge at Jajce was demolished at 23:15, and Nedeljković withdrew his headquarters to Travnik. The remaining units of the 4th Army continued to disintegrate.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=430}} The vanguard of the northern column of 14th Panzer Division surged forward to [[Teslić]], with the central column only reaching Jajce.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|p=431}}

Early on 15 April, the northern column of the 14th Panzer Division closed on Doboj, and after overcoming resistance around that town, arrived in Sarajevo at 20:45. Before noon, Nedeljković received orders that a ceasefire had been agreed, and that all 4th Army troops were to remain in place and not fire on German personnel.{{sfn|Terzić|1982|pp=444–445}} After a delay in locating appropriate signatories for the surrender document, the Yugoslav Supreme Command unconditionally surrendered in Belgrade effective at 12:00 on 18 April.{{sfn|U.S. Army|1986|pp=63–64}}

==Notes==
{{reflist|group=lower-alpha}}

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|30em}}

==References==

===Books===
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite book
  | last = Brayley
  | first = Martin
  | last2 = Chappell
  | first2 = Mike
  | title = British Army 1939–45 (1): North-West Europe
  | year = 2001
  | publisher = Osprey Publishing
  | location =
  | isbn = 978-1-84176-052-0
  | ref = harv
  }}
*{{cite book
  | last = Figa
  | first = Jozef
  | title = Civil-Military Relations, Nation Building, and National Identity: Comparative Perspectives
  | year = 2004
  | chapter = Framing the Conflict: Slovenia in Search of Her Army
  | publisher = Praeger
  | location = Westport, Connecticut
  | isbn = 978-0-313-04645-2
  | ref = harv
  | subscription = yes
  | via = [[Questia]]
  }}
* {{cite book
  | author = Geografski institut JNA
  | url = http://www.znaci.net/00003/385.htm
  | title = Istorijski atlas oslobodilačkog rata naroda Jugoslavije
  | trans_title = Historical Atlas of the Yugoslav Peoples Liberation War
  | chapter = Napad na Jugoslaviju 6 Aprila 1941 godine
  | trans_chapter = The Attack on Yugoslavia of 6 April 1941
  | publisher = Vojnoistorijskog instituta JNA [Military History Institute of the JNA]
  | location = Belgrade, Yugoslavia
  | year = 1952
  | ref = harv
  }}
*{{cite book
  | last = Hoptner
  | first = J.B.
  | title =  Yugoslavia in Crisis, 1934–1941
  | year = 1963
  | publisher = Columbia University Press
  | location = New York, New York
  | oclc = 422318009
  | ref = harv
  | subscription = yes
  | via = [[Questia]]
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Ramet
  | first = Sabrina P.
  | year = 2006
  | title = The Three Yugoslavias: State-Building and Legitimation, 1918–2005
  | publisher = Indiana University Press
  | location = [[Bloomington, Indiana]]
  | isbn = 978-0-253-34656-8
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=FTw3lEqi2-oC
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Shores
  | first1 = Christopher F.
  | last2 = Cull
  | first2 = Brian
  | last3 = Malizia
  | first3 = Nicola
  | title = Air War for Yugoslavia, Greece, and Crete, 1940–41
  | year = 1987
  | publisher = Grub Street
  | location = London
  | isbn = 978-0-948817-07-6
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Stein
  | first = George H.
  | title = The Waffen SS: Hitler's Elite Guard at War, 1939–45
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=-KEtPlNQJNgC
  | year = 1984
  | publisher = Cornell University Press
  | location = Ithaca, New York
  | isbn = 978-0-8014-9275-4
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Terzić
  | first = Velimir
  | title = Slom Kraljevine Jugoslavije 1941 : uzroci i posledice poraza
  | trans_title = The Collapse of the Kingdom of Yugoslavia in 1941: Causes and Consequences of Defeat
  | language = Serbo-Croatian
  | volume = 2
  | publisher = Narodna knjiga
  | location = Belgrade, Yugoslavia
  | year = 1982
  | oclc = 10276738
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Tomasevich
  | first = Jozo
  | authorlink = Jozo Tomasevich
  | year = 1975
  | title = War and Revolution in Yugoslavia, 1941–1945: The Chetniks
  | publisher = Stanford University Press
  | location = Stanford, California
  | isbn = 978-0-8047-0857-9
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=yoCaAAAAIAAJ
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Tomasevich
  | first = Jozo
  | year = 2001
  | title = War and Revolution in Yugoslavia, 1941–1945: Occupation and Collaboration
  | publisher = Stanford University Press
  | location = Stanford, California
  | isbn = 978-0-8047-3615-2
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=fqUSGevFe5MC
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | author = U.S. Army
  | url = http://www.history.army.mil/books/wwii/balkan/intro.htm
  | title = The German Campaigns in the Balkans (Spring 1941)
  | publisher = United States Army Center of Military History
  | location = Washington, D.C.
  | id = CMH Pub 104-4
  | year = 1986
  | oclc= 16940402
  | origyear = 1953
  | ref = harv
  }}
{{refend}}

===Journals and papers===
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite journal | last = Barefield | first = Michael R. | title = Overwhelming Force, Indecisive Victory: The German Invasion of Yugoslavia, 1941 | publisher = School of Advanced Military Studies, United States Army Command and General Staff College |location = Fort Leavenworth, Kansas | url = http://www.dtic.mil/cgi-bin/GetTRDoc?AD=ADA274019 | date = May 1993  |oclc=32251055 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite journal | last = Krzak | first = Andrzej | title = Operation &quot;Marita&quot;: The Attack Against Yugoslavia in 1941 | journal = The Journal of Slavic Military Studies | year = 2006 | volume = 19 | issue = 3 | pages = 543–600 | issn = 1351-8046 | ref = harv | doi=10.1080/13518040600868123}}
{{refend}}

===Websites===
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite web
| url =  http://www.niehorster.org/040_yugoslavia/_ranks.htm
| title = Royal Yugoslav Armed Forces Ranks
| accessdate = 7 December 2015
| publisher  = Dr. Leo Niehorster
| year   = 2015a
| last = Niehorster
| first = Dr. Leo
| ref = harv
}}
* {{cite web
| url =  http://www.niehorster.org/040_yugoslavia/41_org/div-inf/_div-inf.html
| title = Royal Yugoslavian Army Infantry Division 6th April 1941
| accessdate = 7 December 2015
| publisher  = Dr. Leo Niehorster
| year   = 2015b
| last = Niehorster
| first = Dr. Leo
| ref = harv
}}
{{refend}}

[[Category:Military units and formations of Yugoslavia in World War II]]</text>
      <sha1>khuwespddl10og50mdaztmkspwjnhda</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
