<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>76th Infantry Division (United Kingdom)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5048914</id>
    <revision>
      <id>735337664</id>
      <parentid>697762526</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-20T01:47:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>EnigmaMcmxc</username>
        <id>5473743</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Background */Per Nazi Germany RFC</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23927">{{good article}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2015}}
{{Use British English|date=March 2015}}
{{Infobox military unit
|unit_name= 76th Infantry Division&lt;br&gt;76th Infantry (Reserve) Division
|image=File:76th Infantry vector2.svg
|caption=The shoulder insignia of the division
|dates=18 November 1941–1 September 1944{{sfn|Joslen|2003|p=99}}
|country={{flag|United Kingdom}}
|branch={{army|United Kingdom|23px}}
|type=[[Infantry]]
|role=Home defence, training and deception.
|size=
}}
The '''76th Infantry Division''' of the [[British Army]] was raised during the [[World War II|Second World War]] to defend the [[Norfolk]] coast against a possible [[Operation Sea Lion|German invasion]], before being transformed into a training [[Division (military)|division]] in late 1942. New recruits to the Army were assigned to the division to complete their training. Once fully trained, the recruits were allocated to formations fighting overseas. The formation was used as a source of reinforcements for the [[21st Army Group]], that was fighting in [[Operation Overlord|Normandy]]. After all available British army troops left the United Kingdom for France, the division was disbanded in September 1944.

In addition to the actual formation, a phantom 76th Infantry Division was formed for [[Military deception|deception]]. The phantom division was part of the notional [[Fourth Army (United Kingdom)|British Fourth Army]], to be used for the fictitious [[Operation Trolleycar]]. This operation aimed to deceive the Germans into believing that an Allied landing would occur along the northern German coast. While the deception effort was not a complete success, it managed to divert German attention to the northern flank for the remainder of the war.

==Background==
[[File:8th Royal Lincolnshire Regiment Norfolk July 1941.jpg|thumb|alt=|Men of the 8th Battalion, [[Lincolnshire Regiment]], during an anti-invasion exercise in [[Norfolk]], 1941]]

In the early stages of the [[World War II|Second World War]] following the [[Battle of France]] in 1940, the [[United Kingdom]] was under [[Operation Sea Lion|threat of invasion]] from [[Nazi Germany|Germany]] but during the summer, the [[Battle of Britain]] dampened this threat.{{sfn|Fraser|1999|p=83}} As the year progressed, the size of the [[British Army]] increased dramatically as 140 new [[infantry]] [[battalion]]s were raised.{{sfn|Perry|1988|p=53}} In late 1940, with the possibility of a German invasion during 1941, these new battalions were formed into independent infantry [[brigade]]s that were then loaned to newly created [[British County Divisions|County Divisions]].{{sfn|Perry|1988|p=53}}{{sfn|Forty|2013|loc=County Divisions}}

The County Divisions, including the [[Norfolk County Division]], were around 10,000 men strong and assigned to defend the coast of threatened sections of the country, undertaking defensive tasks including the manning of coastal artillery.{{sfn|Perry|1988|p=53}}{{sfn|Churchill|2001|p=1321}}{{sfn|Joslen|2003|pp=108 and 114}} These divisions were largely static, lacking mobility and also divisional assets such as [[artillery]], [[Sapper|engineers]] and [[reconnaissance]] forces.{{sfn|Joslen|2003|p=108}} Using the new formations in this manner allowed the pre-war regular infantry divisions to undertake training and form an all-important reserve that could be used to counter-attack any possible German landing.{{sfn|Messenger|1994|p=61}}

On 22 June, Germany launched [[Operation Barbarossa]] the invasion of the [[Soviet Union]]; this attack all but removed the German threat to the United Kingdom. The British still had to consider the threat of an invasion, due the possibility that the Soviet Union could collapse under the German onslaught, after which Germany could easily transfer troops back to the west. With the arrival of winter in late 1941, the threat of invasion subsided. This, coupled with the production of new equipment for the British army, allowed the [[War Office]] to begin steps to better balance the army, due to the large number of infantry units formed during the preceding year and a half; as part of this reform, the County Divisions were disbanded.{{sfn|Goldstein|McKercher|2003|p=274}}{{sfn|Perry|1988|p=65}}{{sfn|Goldstein|McKercher|2003|p=274}}{{efn|The large intake of men into the army had considerably increased the infantry arm. The reforms intended to address this, with many of the newly raised battalions being &quot;converted to other arms, particularly artillery and armour&quot;.{{sfn|Perry|1988|pp=53–54}} In addition to this, historian F. W. Perry comments, there was considerable pressure &quot;to increase the armoured component [of the army] and build up [[British Commandos|raiding]] and special forces&quot;. These pressures and the re-balancing of the military, resulted in seven of the nine County Divisions being disbanded and only two being reformed as infantry divisions.{{sfn|Perry|1988|p=65}}}}

==History==
===Home defence===
During the war, the divisions of the British Army were divided between &quot;Higher Establishment&quot; and &quot;Lower Establishment&quot; formations. The former were intended for deployment overseas and combat, whereas the latter were strictly for home defence in a static role.{{sfn|Perry|1988|p=65}}{{sfn|French|2001|p=188}} On 18 November 1941, the Norfolk County Division was abolished and reformed as the 76th Infantry Division, a &quot;Lower Establishment&quot; division.{{sfn|Joslen|2003|p=99}} The division, like its predecessor, comprised the [[213th Brigade (United Kingdom)|213th]], the [[220th Brigade (United Kingdom)|220th]] and the [[222nd Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|222nd Infantry Brigades]].{{sfn|Joslen|2003|pp=99, 114}} That day, the division was assigned artillery, an [[Anti-tank warfare|anti-tank regiment]], engineers and [[signaller]]s; reconnaissance troops joined the division in January 1942.{{sfn|Joslen|2003|p=99}} The paper strength of an infantry division at this time was 17,298 men.{{sfn|Joslen|2003|pp=130–131}} [[Major General (United Kingdom)|Major-General]] [[William Maingay Ozanne]], who had commanded the Norfolk County Division since its inception, retained command of the division.{{sfn|Joslen|2003|pp=99, 114}} The 76th Division was assigned to [[II Corps (United Kingdom)|II Corps]] and maintained its previous mission of defending the Norfolk coastline.{{sfn|Joslen|2003|p=99}}{{sfn|Kemp|1963|p=253}} The [[Imperial War Museum]] comments that the division insignia, a &quot;red Norfolk wherry, under sail&quot;, underscored &quot;the association of the Division with Norfolk&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.iwm.org.uk/collections/item/object/30072644 |title=badge, formation, 76th Infantry Division |website=[[Imperial War Museum]] |accessdate=1 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the division became a training formation, the insignia was only worn by the permanent division members.{{sfn|Davis|1983|p=107}}

The division was involved in establishing the ability of the [[Abwehr]] (German military intelligence). A German-published [[order of battle]] of the British army based within the United Kingdom, dated 10 April 1942, was captured. This document included the division and had a near perfect listing of its subordinate units, with one exception. Rather than including the 1st Battalion, [[Leicestershire Regiment]], the Germans believed the 18th Battalion, [[Welch Regiment]] had already replaced it. This and similar errors led the British to understand the capability of the Germans to intercept wireless communications in the United Kingdom. In 1943, this, in part, led to the [[Operation Fortitude]] a plan to exploit the German ability and deceive their intelligence community about future Allied operations like [[Operation Overlord]].{{sfn|Hesketh|2000|pp=5–7}}

===Training formation===

[[File:Eastern Command training 1942.jpg|thumb|left|alt=|A [[Bren Gun]] team train at Eastern Command's Battle School, 1942.]]

During the winter of 1942–43, the army overhauled the training of recruits. The 76th Division, along with the [[48th (South Midland) Division|48th Infantry]] and [[77th Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|77th Infantry]] divisions, was changed from a &quot;Lower Establishment&quot; unit to a &quot;Reserve Division&quot;.{{sfn|Perry|1988|p=66}}{{sfn|Joslen|2003|pp=77, 100}} On 20 December, the division was renamed the 76th Infantry (Reserve) Division, becoming a training formation in the process.{{sfn|Joslen|2003|p=99}}{{sfn|Perry|1988|p=66}} These three divisions were supplemented by a fourth training formation, the [[80th Infantry (Reserve) Division (United Kingdom)|80th Infantry (Reserve) Division]], which was raised on 1 January 1943.{{sfn|Joslen|2003|p=103}} The 76th Infantry (Reserve) Division was assigned to [[Eastern Command (United Kingdom)|Eastern Command]], and moved to [[Norwich]].{{sfn|Hesketh|2000|pp=5–7}}{{sfn|Forty|2013|loc=Reserve Divisions}} Soldiers who had completed their corps training, were sent to these training divisions.{{sfn|French|2001|p=68}}{{efn|Having entered military service, a recruit was assigned to the [[General Service Corps]]. He would then undertake six weeks' training at a Primary Training Centre and take aptitude and intelligence tests. The recruit would then be posted to a Corps Training Centre that specialized in the arm of the service they were joining. For those who would be joining the infantry, corps training involved a further sixteen week course. For more specialized roles, such as signallers, it could be up to thirty weeks.{{sfn|French|2001|p=68}}}} The soldiers were given five weeks of additional training at the [[Section (military unit)|section]], [[platoon]] and [[Company (military unit)|company]] level, before undertaking a final three-day [[Military exercise|exercise]]. Troops would then be ready to be sent overseas to join other formations.{{sfn|French|2001|p=68}} Training was handled in this manner to relieve the &quot;Higher Establishment&quot; divisions from being milked for replacements for other units and to allow them to intensively train without the interruption of having to handle new recruits.{{sfn|Forty|2013|loc=Reserve Divisions}} For example, the 9th Battalion, [[Dorsetshire Regiment]] provided recruits to other battalions within the regiment as well as the [[Royal Norfolk Regiment]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.keepmilitarymuseum.org/history/second+world+war/the+dorsetshire+regiment/the+sixth+ninth+thirtieth+and+seventieth+battalions|title=The 6th (Home Defence), 9th, 30th and 70th (Young Soldiers) Battalions The Dorsetshire Regiment in World War Two|website=The Keep Military Museum: Home of the Regiments of Devon and Dorset|accessdate=15 May 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; During this period, command of the division changed several times. On 21 December 1943, Ozanne was replaced by Major-General [[Colin Callander]] who in turn was replaced by Major-General [[John Edward Utterson-Kelso]] on 13 March 1944.{{sfn|Joslen|2003|p=99}}

On 30 June 1944, the 76th Infantry (Reserve) Division, along with the other training divisions, had a combined total of 22,355 men. Of this number, only 1,100 were immediately available as replacements for the [[21st Army Group]].{{sfn|Hart|2007|p=52}}{{efn|The war establishment—the paper strength—of a &quot;Higher Establishment&quot; infantry division in 1944 was 18,347 men.{{sfn|Joslen|2003|pp=130–131}}}} The remaining 21,255 men were considered ineligible for service abroad, due to a variety of reasons, ranging from medical, not being considered fully fit or not yet fully trained. Over the following six months, up to 75 per cent of these men would be deployed to reinforce the 21st Army Group, following the completion of their training and having met the required fitness levels.{{sfn|Hart|2007|pp=48–51}} Stephen Hart comments that, by September, the 21st Army Group &quot;had bled [[Commander-in-Chief, Home Forces|Home Forces]] dry of draftable riflemen&quot;, due to the losses suffered during the [[Normandy Campaign]], leaving the army in Britain, with the exception of the [[52nd (Lowland) Infantry Division]], with just &quot;young lads, old men, and the unfit&quot;.{{sfn|Hart|2007|pp=49–50}} On 1 September 1944, the division was disbanded.{{sfn|Joslen|2003|p=99}} Utterson-Kelso assumed command of the [[47th (London) Infantry Division|47th Infantry (Reserve) Division]], which took over the role of the 76th Division.{{sfn|Forty|2013|loc=Reserve Divisions}}{{sfn|Joslen|2003|p=41}}

===Deception===
[[File:Ww2 map68.jpg|thumb|The front line, in North West Europe, following Operation Market Garden]]

The creation of the fictitious division arose from an actual reorganisation of British forces. During 1944, the British Army was facing a manpower crisis. The army did not have enough men to replace the losses to front line infantry. While efforts were made to address this (such as transferring men from the [[Royal Artillery]] and [[Royal Air Force]] to be retrained as infantry), the War Office began disbanding divisions to reduce the size of the army and to transfer the surplue men to other units to help keep those as close to full strength as possible.{{sfn|Messenger|1994|p=122}}{{sfn|Allport|2015|p=216}} The 76th Infantry (Reserve) Division was one of several &quot;Lower Establishment&quot; divisions in the United Kingdom, chosen to be disbanded.{{sfn|Hesketh|2000|p=246}}

[[R Force]], the Fortitude deception staff, seized upon this opportunity to retain the division as a phantom unit. A cover story was established to explain the change in the division's status. It was claimed that with the war nearing an end, several [[Army Reserve (United Kingdom)|Territorial Army]] divisions would revert to their peacetime recruiting role and release their equipment and resources to other units. For the 76th, this was the 47th Division. With the transfer of equipment, the 76th was notionally raised to the &quot;Higher Establishment&quot; and assigned to reinforce the 21st Army Group.{{sfn|Hesketh|2000|p=246}}

As a deception unit, the division was assigned to the bogus [[Operation Trolleycar]].{{sfn|Holt|2004|p=923}} Trolleycar was initially envisioned as a fictitious amphibious assault upon the coast of the [[Netherlands]], by the phantom British [[Fourth Army (United Kingdom)|Fourth Army]], to exploit the success of the authentic [[Operation Market Garden]]. When the [[Battle of Arnhem]] failed, the notional invasion plan was temporarily scrapped.{{sfn|Hesketh|2000|p=328}} Trolleycar was revived to convince the Germans that the Fourth Army would land near [[Emden]], in support of an imaginary assault by the [[First Canadian Army]], that would be launched west of [[Arnhem]] and through the Netherlands.{{sfn|Hesketh|2000|p=329}} The deception effort was kept up until 1945, being wound down in January. Despite the British ceasing their attempts to deceive the Germans about this possible landing and the Germans not believing all that had been reported to them, the Germans remained anxious about a landing along the northern coast for the remainder of the war.{{sfn|Hesketh|2000|p=335}}{{sfn|Holt|2004|p=643}}

==General officer commanding==
{{see also|General officer commanding}}
Commanders included:
{|
!Appointed
!General officer commanding
|-
|18 November 1941
|[[Major General (United Kingdom)|Major-General]] [[William Maingay Ozanne]]{{sfn|Joslen|2003|p=99}}
|-
|21 December 1943
|Major-General [[Colin Callander]]{{sfn|Joslen|2003|p=99}}
|-
|13 March 1944
|Major-General [[John Edward Utterson-Kelso]]{{sfn|Joslen|2003|p=99}}
|}

==Order of Battle==
{| class=&quot;toccolours collapsible collapsed&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; background:transparent;&quot;
!colspan= | 76th Infantry Division
|-
|colspan=&quot;2&quot; |
213th Infantry Brigade{{sfn|Joslen|2003|p=376}}
{{main |213th Brigade (United Kingdom) | l1 = 213th Infantry Brigade }}
* 13th Battalion, [[Royal Warwickshire Regiment]] (until 12 September 1942)
* 9th Battalion, [[Royal Berkshire Regiment]] (until 16 November 1943)
* 14th Battalion, [[South Staffordshire Regiment]] (until 13 December 1942)
* 7th Battalion, [[Royal Norfolk Regiment]] (between September and October 1942)
* 7th Battalion, [[North Staffordshire Regiment]] (between September and October 1942)
* 9th Battalion, [[King's Own Scottish Borderers]] (from December 1942, until December 1943)
* 11th Battalion, [[York and Lancaster Regiment]] (from December 1942, until November 1943)
* 9th Battalion, [[Seaforth Highlanders]] (from December 1942, until November 1943)
* 1st Battalion, [[Sherwood Foresters]] (from 15 November 1943, until the division was disbanded)
* 4th Battalion, [[East Lancashire Regiment]] (from 15 November 1943, until the division was disbanded)
* 7th Battalion, [[Border Regiment]] (from 15 November 1943, until the division was disbanded)

220th Infantry Brigade{{sfn|Joslen|2003|p=383}}
{{main |220th Brigade (United Kingdom) | l1 = 220th Infantry Brigade }}
* 7th Battalion, Royal Norfolk Regiment (until September 1942)
* 9th Battalion, Royal Norfolk Regiment (until December 1942)
* 9th Battalion, [[Bedfordshire and Hertfordshire Regiment]] (until September 1942)
* 1/5th Battalion, [[West Yorkshire Regiment]] (from September 1942, until January 1943)
* 6th Battalion, [[Northamptonshire Regiment]] (from September 1942, until November 1943)
* 18th Battalion, [[Welch Regiment]] (from December 1942, until November 1943)
* 6th Battalion, [[King's Own Yorkshire Light Infantry]] (from December 1942, until October 1943)
* 5th Battalion, West Yorkshire Regiment (from October 1943, until July 1944)
* 9th Battalion, [[Royal Welch Fusiliers]] (from October 1943, until July 1944)
* 2/6th Battalion, [[Lancashire Fusiliers]] (from October 1943, until July 1944)
* 6th Battalion, [[King's Own Royal Regiment]] (from November 1943, until July 1944)
* 8th Battalion, [[Suffolk Regiment]] (from July 1944, until the division disbanded)
* 9th Battalion, [[Dorsetshire Regiment]] (from August 1944, until the division disbanded)
* 6th Battalion, [[Devonshire Regiment]] (from August 1944, until the division disbanded)

222nd Infantry Brigade (brigade was disbanded on 18 November 1943){{sfn|Joslen|2003|p=385}}
{{main |222nd Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom) | l1 = 222nd Infantry Brigade }}
* 8th Battalion, [[Lincolnshire Regiment]] (until December 1942)
* 8th Battalion, [[Leicestershire Regiment]] (Battalion was renamed the 1st Battalion in July 1942, and remained with the division until December 1942.)
* 11th Battalion, [[Royal Scots Fusiliers]] (until September 1942)
* 9th Battalion, Bedfordshire and Hertfordshire Regiment (between September and October 1942)
* 4th Battalion, East Lancashire Regiment (from October 1942, until November 1943)
* 7th Battalion, Border Regiment (from December 1942, until November 1943)
* 16th Battalion, Sherwood Foresters (December 1942)
* 1st Battalion, Sherwood Foresters (from January 1943 until November 1943)

Divisional Troops{{sfn|Joslen|2003|p=99}}

* 52nd Field Regiment, [[Royal Artillery]] (until August 1942)
* 53rd Field Regiment, Royal Artillery (until June 1942)
* 167th Field Regiment, Royal Artillery (from May 1942, until January 1943)
* 173rd Field Regiment, Royal Artillery (from November 1943, until the division disbanded)
* [[1st Fife Artillery Volunteers|56th (Highland) Medium Regiment, Royal Artillery]] (from January 1943, until the division disbanded)
* 60th Heavy Regiment, Royal Artillery (from July 1943, until November 1943)
* 56th Anti Tank Regiment, Royal Artillery (until December 1941)
* 100th Anti Tank Regiment, Royal Artillery (from January 1942, until November 1942)
* 94th Anti Tank Regiment, Royal Artillery (from January 1943, until November 1943)
* 76th Infantry Divisional Engineers, [[Royal Engineers]]
** 591st Field Company (until December 1941)
** 757th Field Company (from November 1941, until February 1942)
** 556th Field Company (from December 1041, until January 1943)
** 250th Field Company (from February 1942, until August 1944)
** Divisional Field Stores Section (from December 1941, until August 1944)
* 76th Divisional Signals, [[Royal Corps of Signals]] (later known as the 76th Infantry (Reserve) Division Signal Regiment)
* 76th Independent Company, [[Reconnaissance Corps]] (from January 1942, until June 1942)
* 76th Independent Squadron, Reconnaissance Corps (from June 1942, until January 1943)
|}

==See also==
{{portal|British Army|World War II}}
* [[List of British divisions in World War II]]

==Notes==
; Footnotes
{{Notelist}}
; Citations
{{Reflist|3}}

==References==
{{Refbegin|2}}
* {{cite book |ref=harv |first=Alan|last=Allport|author1-link=Alan Allport|title=Browned Off and Bloody-minded: The British Soldier Goes to War 1939–1945|location=New Haven |publisher=[[Yale University Press]]|year=2015|isbn=978-0-300-17075-7|lastauthoramp=y}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|last=Churchill|first=Winston|author-link=Winston Churchill|editor-last=Gilbert|editor-first=Martin|editor-link=Martin Gilbert|title=The Churchill War Papers: The Ever-Widening War|volume=3|location=New York|publisher=[[W. W. Norton &amp; Company]]|year=2001|isbn=978-0-393-01959-9}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|last=Forty|first=George|title=Companion to the British Army 1939–1945|location=New York|publisher=[[The History Press|Spellmount]]|year=2013|origyear=1998|edition=ePub|isbn=978-0-750-95139-5}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|last=Fraser|first=David|author-link=David Fraser (British Army officer)|title=And We Shall Shock Them: The British Army in the Second World War|location=London|publisher=[[Orion Publishing Group|Cassell Military]] |year=1999|origyear=1983|isbn=978-0-304-35233-3}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|last=French|first=David|title=Raising Churchill's Army: The British Army and the War Against Germany 1919–1945|location=Oxford|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|year=2001|origyear=2000|isbn=978-0-199-24630-4}}
*{{cite book|ref=harv|editor-last1=Goldstein|editor-first1=Erik|editor-last2=McKercher|editor-first2=Brian|title=Power and Stability: British Foreign Policy, 1865–1965|series=Diplomacy &amp; Statecraft|location=London|publisher=[[Routledge]]|year=2003|isbn=978-0-71468-442-0}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv|first=Stephen Ashley|last=Hart|title=Colossal Cracks: Montgomery's 21st Army Group in Northwest Europe, 1944–45|location=Mechanicsburg|publisher=[[Stackpole Books]]|year=2007|origyear=2000|isbn=978-0-811-73383-0}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv|first=Roger|last=Hesketh|authorlink=Roger Fleetwood-Hesketh|title=Fortitude: The D-Day Deception Campaign|location=Woodstock|publisher=[[The Overlook Press|Overlook Hardcover]]|year=2000|isbn=978-1-585-67075-8}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv|first=Thaddeus|last=Holt|title=[[The Deceivers: Allied Military Deception in the Second World War]]|location=New York|publisher=[[Simon &amp; Schuster|Scribner]]|year=2004|isbn=978-0-743-25042-9}}
* {{Joslen-OOB}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv|first=Colonel J. C.|last=Kemp|title=The History of the Royal Scots Fusiliers, 1919–1959|publisher=Robert Maclehose|location=Glasgow|year=1963|oclc=1435011}}
* {{cite book |ref=harv |last=Messenger |first=Charles |year=1994 |series=A History of British Infantry |title=For Love of Regiment 1915–1994 |volume=2 |location=London|publisher=[[Pen and Sword Books]] |isbn=978-0-850-52422-2}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv|first=Frederick William|last=Perry|title=The Commonwealth Armies: Manpower and Organisation in Two World Wars|series=War, Armed Forces and Society|location=Manchester|publisher=[[Manchester University Press]]|year=1988|isbn=978-0-719-02595-2}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book|ref=harv|first=Brian Leigh|last=Davis|title=British Army Uniforms &amp; Insignia of World War Two|location=London|publisher=Arms and Armour Press|year=1983|isbn=978-0-853-68609-5}}
{{refend}}

{{British Army Divisions}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:76 Infantry Division}}
[[Category:Infantry divisions of the British Army in World War II]]
[[Category:Military units and formations established in 1941]]
[[Category:Military units and formations disestablished in 1944]]</text>
      <sha1>f7i2a475zok8rcj5huz3v4wjcfoskd3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
