<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Action of 28 January 1945</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>29682693</id>
    <revision>
      <id>740535384</id>
      <parentid>733059285</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-21T17:38:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* References */http&amp;rarr;https for [[Google Books]] and [[Google News]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14525">{{infobox military conflict
|conflict = Action of 28 January 1945
|partof = the [[World War II|Second World War]]
|image = [[File:HMS Diadem dock.jpg|300px|alt=Black and white photo of a World War II-era warship. The ship is painted in camouflage and is armed with several gun turrets.|HMS ''Diadem'' in 1944]]
|caption = HMS ''Diadem'' in 1944
|date = 27/28&amp;nbsp;January 1945
|place = Waters off [[Bergen]], [[Norway]]
|coordinates =
|map_type =
|latitude =
|longitude =
|map_size =
|map_caption =
|map_label =
|territory =
|result = Inconclusive
|status =
|combatant1 = {{flag|United Kingdom}}
|combatant2 = {{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
|commander1 = {{flagicon|United Kingdom|naval}} [[Frederick Dalrymple-Hamilton]]
|commander2 = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany|naval}} H.F. von Wangenheim&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany|naval}} Karl Hetz
|units1 =
|units2 =
|strength1 = 2 light cruisers
|strength2 = 3 destroyers&lt;br/&gt;Shore batteries
|casualties1 = 1 killed, 3 wounded&lt;br/&gt;2 light cruisers lightly damaged
|casualties2 = 55 killed, 24 wounded&lt;br/&gt;1 destroyer heavily damaged&lt;br/&gt;1 destroyer lightly damaged
|notes =
}}
{{Campaignbox Norwegian Campaigns (1941 - 1945)}}

The '''Action of 28&amp;nbsp;January 1945''' was an inconclusive naval battle of the [[World War II|Second World War]] fought between two British [[Royal Navy]] [[light cruiser]]s and three ''[[Kriegsmarine]]'' (German navy) [[destroyer]]s near [[Bergen]], [[Norway]]. The battle was both the last of many actions between British and German warships off Norway during the war, and the second last surface engagement to fought by the ''Kriegsmarine''. It resulted in heavy damage to one of the German destroyers and light damage to another destroyer and both British cruisers.

Shortly after midnight on the night of 27/28&amp;nbsp;January, as the three destroyers of the German 4th&amp;nbsp;Destroyer Flotilla were sailing from northern Norway to the [[Baltic Sea]], they were intercepted by the British cruisers {{HMS|Diadem|84|6}} and {{HMS|Mauritius|80|2}}. In the resulting engagement, the destroyers [[German destroyer Z31|''Z31'']] and [[German destroyer Z34|''Z34'']] were damaged by gunfire but the German flotilla outran the slower British ships and escaped. All the German warships eventually reached the Baltic, though ''Z31'' was delayed until repairs were completed in Norway.

==Background==
The ''Kriegsmarine''{{'}}s 4th&amp;nbsp;Destroyer Flotilla comprised the [[Narvik class destroyer|''Narvik''-class destroyer]]s ''Z31'', [[German destroyer Z34|''Z34'']], and ''Z38''. By January 1945, these ships had been stationed in northern Norwegian waters for three and a half years, but had only occasionally put to sea during 1944. Due to Germany's deteriorating position, the flotilla was directed in January to leave Norwegian waters and return to the Baltic. The three destroyers departed [[Tromsø]] on the 25th of the month.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ohara_254&quot;&gt;O'Hara (2004), p. 254&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Koop_112&quot;&gt;Koop (1995), p. 112&lt;/ref&gt;

The Royal Navy's [[Home Fleet]] conducted a number of attacks on German shipping travelling off the coast of Norway during January 1945. These included successful attacks by [[Motor Torpedo Boat|motor torpedo boats]] on three escorted ships between 6 and 8&amp;nbsp;January and the interception of a convoy by the [[heavy cruiser]] {{HMS|Norfolk|78|6}} and [[light cruiser]] {{HMS|Bellona|63|6}} near [[Egersund]] on the night of 11/12&amp;nbsp;January.&lt;ref name= &quot;Roskill_253&quot;&gt;Roskill (1961), p. 253&lt;/ref&gt; On 27&amp;nbsp;January, the [[escort carrier]]s {{HMS|Campania|D48|6}}, {{HMS|Nairana|D05|2}} and {{HMS|Premier|D23|2}} departed the Home Fleet's main base at [[Scapa Flow]] to conduct a raid against shipping near Vaago which was designated [[Operation Winded]]. The carriers were escorted by the heavy cruiser {{HMS|Berwick|65|6}} and six destroyers.&lt;ref name=Roskill_253/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Brown (2009), p. 31&lt;/ref&gt;

The British were alerted to the 4th&amp;nbsp;Destroyer Flotilla's movement by [[Ultra]] signals intelligence.&lt;ref name=Ohara_254/&gt; The commander of the Home Fleet, Admiral [[Henry Ruthven Moore|Henry Moore]], was informed that the destroyers had sailed on 27&amp;nbsp;January, shortly after the three carriers and their escort had put to sea. He believed that the German ships were likely to use a route between the coastal islands and the shore, as was common for the ''Kriegsmarine''. If this route was used, it would be preferable for strike aircraft of [[No. 18 Group RAF]] to attack the destroyers as Norway's inshore waters were protected by [[naval mine]]s and [[Coastal artillery|coastal batteries]]. Alternatively, the German ships could make a high-speed night passage outside of the coastal islands.&lt;ref&gt;Roskill (1961), pp. 253–254&lt;/ref&gt; In case an offshore route was used, Moore ordered Vice Admiral [[Frederick Dalrymple-Hamilton]], the commander of the 10th&amp;nbsp;Cruiser Squadron, to sail with the cruisers ''Diadem'' and ''Mauritius'' and patrol off Bergen. The Home Fleet did not have any destroyers available to accompany Dalrymple-Hamilton's force, though Moore considered but decided against cancelling the carrier operation in order to make some of these ships available.&lt;ref name=&quot;Roskill_254&quot;&gt;Roskill (1961), p. 254&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battle==
[[File:Action of 28 January 1945 map.jpg|thumb|300px|alt=Map of the Norwegian coastline near Bergen marked to show the route of the Allied and German ships during this battle as described in the text|Approximate route of the German and Allied ships during the action&lt;ref&gt;O'Hara (2004), p. 249&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Contrary to British expectations, the commander of the 4th&amp;nbsp;Destroyer Flotilla, Captain H.F. von Wangenheim, chose to take the faster route outside of the coastal islands.&lt;ref name=Ohara_254/&gt; On the evening of 27&amp;nbsp;January, the destroyers were spotted and attacked by British aircraft whilst west of [[Sognefjord]], but continued their voyage.&lt;ref name=w1&gt;Whitley (1991), p. 172&lt;/ref&gt; Contact was made between the two naval forces at 00:48&amp;nbsp;am on 28&amp;nbsp;January. At this time, the 4th&amp;nbsp;Destroyer Flotilla was proceeding south and was located about {{convert|15|mi|nmi km}} southwest of the [[Utvær]] lighthouse and {{convert|35|mi|nmi km}} northwest of Bergen. The sea was calm and visibility was excellent due to a full moon.&lt;ref name=Ohara_254/&gt; The British and German forces spotted each another simultaneously; at the time the cruisers were about {{convert|11|mi|nmi km}} west of the 4th&amp;nbsp;Destroyer Flotilla.&lt;ref&gt;O'Hara (2004), pp. 254–255&lt;/ref&gt; Upon sighting the destroyers, the British ships fired [[Shell (projectile)#Illumination|star shell]]s to illuminate the area and turned to the south on a course parallel to that of the German ships.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ohara_255&quot;&gt;O'Hara (2004), p. 255&lt;/ref&gt;

''Z31'' suffered extensive damage early in the battle. She was struck by seven {{convert|6|in|mm|abbr=on|0}} shells, which caused her to catch fire, damaged the [[hydrophone]] compartment and [[torpedo]] [[Glossary of nautical terms#T|transmitting stations]] and destroyed her forward [[gun turret]].&lt;ref name=Ohara_255/&gt; ''Z31''{{'}}s speed was not affected, but casualties were heavy, with 55 sailors killed and another 24 wounded.&lt;ref name=&quot;OHara_255-256&quot;&gt;O'Hara (2004), pp. 255–256&lt;/ref&gt; After ''Z31'' was damaged, Commander Karl Hetz on board ''Z34'' assumed command of the 4th&amp;nbsp;Destroyer Flotilla. ''Z34'' made two torpedo attacks on the British cruisers in an attempt to force them to change course, but this was not successful.&lt;ref name=Roskill_254/&gt;&lt;ref name=Ohara_255/&gt; ''Z38'' also tried to launch torpedoes, but had to break off this attack when her funnel caught fire and a [[boiler]] tube burst. ''Z34'' suffered a hit on her [[waterline]] during this period.&lt;ref name=Ohara_255/&gt;

After ''Z34'' was damaged, Hetz decided to turn to the north and attempt to outrun the British cruisers. ''Z34'' fired a third salvo of torpedoes as the flotilla made this turn, again without result, and the three ships laid [[smoke screen]]s in an attempt to conceal their position. The two cruisers also turned north to chase the German ships.&lt;ref name=Ohara_255/&gt; This led to a running battle in which ''Mauritius'' sustained a hit on her mess deck that did not cause any casualties and ''Diadem'' was struck on her boat deck by a shell six minutes later that killed one man and wounded three.&lt;ref name=w1/&gt; The German destroyers were capable of making {{convert|38|kn}} while ''Diadem'' had a maximum speed of {{convert|32|kn}} and ''Mauritius'' {{convert|31|kn}}. As a result, the German vessels gradually pulled ahead and came under the protection of shore batteries at about 2:00&amp;nbsp;am.&lt;ref name=Ohara_255/&gt; The British ships broke off the pursuit and returned to Scapa Flow after these batteries fired on them.&lt;ref name=Roskill_254/&gt;

==Aftermath==
Early in the morning of 28&amp;nbsp;January, the 4th&amp;nbsp;Destroyer Flotilla resumed its journey south and put into Bergen. ''Z31'' entered one of the town's docks to be repaired while ''Z34'' and ''Z38'' departed on the evening of 28&amp;nbsp;January. The two ships were attacked from the air the next day, but did not suffer any damage and sheltered in a fjord south of [[Stavanger]] during daylight hours. They put to sea again on the evening of 29&amp;nbsp;January and eventually reached [[Kiel]] in Germany on 1&amp;nbsp;February.&lt;ref name=Roskill_254/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Rohwer_391&quot;&gt;Rohwer (2005), p. 391&lt;/ref&gt;

At Bergen, ''Z31'' received initial repairs, which included removing the wreckage of her forward turret.&lt;ref name=Koop_112/&gt; She departed the town on 8&amp;nbsp;February bound for [[Horten]]. After arriving safely in this port she received further repairs and had her anti-aircraft armament upgraded. Her forward turret was not replaced, but a {{convert|4.1|in|mm|abbr=on}} gun was mounted instead; this was intended to be a temporary measure but remained in place for the remainder of her career.&lt;ref name=Ohara_255/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Koop (1995), pp. 112–113&lt;/ref&gt; After these repairs were completed, ''Z31'' eventually reached [[Gdynia|Gotenhafen]] on 15 March.&lt;ref name=Koop_112/&gt; The last German destroyer remaining in northern Norwegian waters, [[German destroyer Z33|''Z33'']], sailed for Germany on 5&amp;nbsp;February 1945 but ran aground while en route and suffered further damage in the Allied [[Black Friday (1945)|&quot;Black Friday&quot;]] air raid on the ninth of the month. Following repairs, she arrived at [[Świnoujście|Swinemünde]] on 2&amp;nbsp;April.&lt;ref&gt;Koop and Schmolke (1995), p. 114&lt;/ref&gt;

Both the British and German navies were dissatisfied with the results of the battle on 28 January. The British were disappointed with the action's inconclusive result, and Admiral Moore regretted his decision to not cancel the escort carrier operation so that destroyers could be attached to the cruiser force.&lt;ref name=Roskill_254/&gt; However, historians have judged that the combination of excellent visibility on the night of 27/28&amp;nbsp;January and the superior speed of the German destroyers meant that the British had no ability to force a result.&lt;ref name=Roskill_254/&gt;&lt;ref name=OHara_255-256 /&gt; In a post-war assessment, First Sea Lord Admiral [[Andrew Cunningham, 1st Viscount Cunningham of Hyndhope|Andrew Cunningham]] endorsed the tactics Dalrymple-Hamilton used during the engagement, but stated that the size of the British force was &quot;inadequate&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Cunningham (2006), p. 260&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Kriegsmarine'' was also unsatisfied with the conduct of the battle, with German naval authorities believing that the destroyers should have taken shelter in coastal waters after they were sighted by Allied aircraft on the evening of 27&amp;nbsp;January.&lt;ref name=Roskill_254/&gt;

The action of 28&amp;nbsp;January was the final battle between British and German warships in Norwegian waters during World War II.&lt;ref name=&quot;Smith_233&quot;&gt;Smith (1981), p. 233&lt;/ref&gt; It was also the second last surface action fought by the ''Kriegsmarine'', with its final engagement taking place on 18&amp;nbsp;March 1945 when a force of two [[torpedo boat]]s and a destroyer was defeated by two British destroyers in the [[Battle of the Ligurian Sea]].&lt;ref&gt;O'Hara (2004), pp. 245–247, 275&lt;/ref&gt; By this time, most of the ''Kriegsmarine''{{'}}s remaining warships were stationed in the Baltic Sea where they supported German military operations and the [[Flight and evacuation of German civilians during the end of World War II|evacuation of civilians]] until the end of the war in May.&lt;ref&gt;O'Hara (2004), pp. 257–258&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
;Citations
{{reflist|2}}

;Bibliography
* {{cite book|last=Brown|first=J.D.|title=Carrier Operations in World War II|year=2009|publisher=Naval Institute Press|location=Annapolis, Maryland|isbn=978-1-59114-108-2|editor=Hobbs, David}}
*{{cite book|last=Cunningham |first=Andrew|title=The Cunningham Papers: Selections from the Private and Official Correspondence of Admiral of the Fleet Viscount Cunningham of Hyndhope, O.M., K.T., G.C.B., D.S.O. and Two Bars|year=2006|publisher=Ashgate Publishing|isbn=0-7546-5598-9|url= https://books.google.com/books?id=MynRmONNSLcC&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s|location=Farnham, Surrey}}
*{{cite book|last=Koop|first=Gerhard|title=German Destroyers of World War II|year=1995|publisher= Greenhill Books|isbn=1-85367-540-7|author2=Schmolke, Klaus-Peter|location=London}}
*{{cite book|last=O'Hara|first=Vincent P.|title=The German Fleet at War, 1939–1945|year=2004| publisher=Naval Institute Press|isbn=1-59114-651-8|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=z85Xh21qniEC&amp;dq|location=Annapolis, Maryland}}
*{{cite book|last=Rohwer|first=Jurgen|title=Chronology of the War at Sea 1939–1945: The Naval History of World War Two|year=2005|publisher=Naval Institute Press|isbn=1-59114-119-2|location= Annapolis, Maryland}}
*{{cite book|last=Roskill|first=S.W.|title=The War at Sea 1939–1945. Volume III: The Offensive Part II|year=1961|publisher=Her Majesty's Stationery Office|location=London|oclc=464447827}}
*{{cite book|last=Smith|first=Peter Charles|title=Cruisers in Action, 1939–1945|year=1981|publisher =W. Kimber|author2=Dominy, John|isbn=0-7183-0218-4|location=London}}
*{{cite book|last=Whitley|first=M. J.|title=German Destroyers of World War Two|publisher=Naval Institute Press|year=1991|isbn=1-55750-302-8 |location=Annapolis, Maryland}}

{{Good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:19450128}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1945]]
[[Category:1945 in Norway]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom|A]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Germany]]</text>
      <sha1>gnr2pcu0yguneyqmaafnsp2efggw5th</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
