<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Al-Mu'tadid</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1091224</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750418507</id>
      <parentid>749919830</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-19T16:51:16Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cplakidas</username>
        <id>613068</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Death and legacy */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="50302">{{for|the 11th-century ruler of the [[taifa of Seville]]|Abbad II al-Mu'tadid}}
{{good article}}
{{Infobox royalty
|name         = Al-Mu'tadid bi-llah&lt;br /&gt;المعتضد بالله
|image        = Dinar of al-Mu'tadid, AH 285.jpg
|alt          = Obverse and reverse of a round gold coin with Arabic inscriptions
|caption      = [[Gold dinar]] of al-Mu'tadid, [[Anno Hegirae|AH]] 285 (AD 892/3)
|title        = 
|succession   = 16th [[Caliph]] of the [[Abbasid Caliphate]]
|reign        = 15 October 892 – 5 April 902
|predecessor  = [[al-Mu'tamid]]
|successor    = [[al-Muktafi]]
|birth_date   = ca. 854 or ca. 861
|birth_place  = 
|death_date   = 5 April 902  (aged 48 or 41)
|death_place  = [[Baghdad]]
|burial_place = [[Baghdad]]
|father       = [[al-Muwaffaq]]
|mother       = Dirar
|spouse       = Qatr al-Nada bint Khumarawayh 
|spouse-type  = Consort
|religion     = [[Sunni Islam]]
|issue        = {{plainlist|
* [[al-Muktafi]]
* [[al-Muqtadir]]
* [[al-Qahir]]
}}}}
'''Abu'l-Abbas Ahmad ibn Talha al-Muwaffaq''' (854 or 861 – 5 April 902), better known by his [[regnal name]] '''al-Mu'tadid bi-llah''' ({{lang-ar|المعتضد بالله}}, &quot;Seeking Support in God&quot;{{sfn|Bowen|1928|p=25}}) was the [[Abbasid]] [[Caliph]] in [[Baghdad]] from 892 until his death in 902.

Al-Mu'tadid was the son of [[al-Muwaffaq]], who was the regent and virtual ruler of the Abbasid state during the reign of his brother, Caliph [[al-Mu'tamid]]. As a prince, the future al-Mu'tadid served under his father in various military campaigns, most notably in the suppression of the [[Zanj Rebellion]], in which he played a major role. When al-Muwaffaq died in June 891 al-Mu'tadid succeeded him as regent. He quickly sidelined his cousin and heir-apparent [[al-Mufawwad]], and when al-Mu'tamid died in October 892, he succeeded to the throne. Like his father, al-Mu'tadid's power depended on his close relations with the army, first forged in the campaigns against the Zanj and reinforced in later expeditions which the Caliph led in person: al-Mu'tadid would prove to be the most militarily active of all Abbasid caliphs. Through his energy and ability, he succeeded in restoring to the Abbasid state some of the power and provinces it had lost during the turmoils of the previous decades.

In a series of campaigns he recovered the provinces of [[al-Jazira, Mesopotamia|Jazira]], [[Thughur]] and [[Jibal]], and effected a rapprochement with the [[Saffarids]] in the east and the [[Tulunids]] in the west that secured their—albeit largely nominal—recognition of caliphal suzerainty. These successes came at the cost of gearing the economy almost exclusively towards maintenance of the army, which resulted in the expansion and rise to power of the central fiscal bureaucracy and contributed to the Caliph's lasting reputation for avarice. Al-Mu'tadid was also renowned for his cruelty when punishing criminals, and subsequent chroniclers record his extensive and ingenious use of torture. His reign also saw the permanent move of the capital back to Baghdad, where he engaged in major building activities. A firm supporter of [[Sunni]] traditionalist orthodoxy, he nevertheless maintained good relations with the [[Alids]], and was interested in natural sciences, renewing caliphal sponsorship of scholars and scientists.

Despite his successes, al-Mu'tadid's reign was ultimately too short to effect a lasting reversal of the Caliphate's fortunes, and the revival that he spearheaded was too dependent on the presence of capable personalities at the helm of the state. The brief reign of his less able son and heir, [[al-Muktafi]], still saw some major gains, notably the annexation of the Tulunid domains, but his later successors lacked his energy, and new enemies appeared in the form of the [[Qarmatians]]. In addition, the factionalism within the bureaucracy, that had become apparent during the later years of al-Mu'tadid's reign, would debilitate the Abbasid government for decades to come, eventually leading to the subjugation of the Caliphate to a series of military strongmen and culminating in the conquest of Baghdad by the [[Buyids]] in 946.

== Early life ==
[[File:Abbasids Ninth Century.svg|thumb|right|upright=1.2|alt=Family tree, with the caliphs marked in green|Family tree of the Abbasid dynasty in the middle and late 9th century]]
Al-Mu'tadid was born Ahmad, the son of Talha, one of the sons of the Caliph [[al-Mutawakkil]] (reigned 847–861), and a [[Byzantine Greeks|Greek]] slave named Dirar. The exact date of his birth is unknown; as he is variously recorded as being thirty-eight or thirty-one years old at the time of his accession, he was born around either 854 or 861.{{sfn|Kennedy|1993|pp=759–760}}{{sfn|Zetterstéen|1987|p=777}}{{sfn|Bowen|1928|p=26}} In 861, al-Mutawakkil was murdered, beginning a period of internal turmoil, known as the &quot;[[Anarchy at Samarra]]&quot; from the site of the Caliphate's capital, which ended in 870 with the rise to the throne of Ahmad's uncle, [[al-Mu'tamid]]. Real power however had come to lie with the elite Turkish troops and with Ahmad's own father, Talha, who, as the Caliphate's main military commander, served as the chief intermediary between the caliphal government and the Turks. Assuming the honorific name [[al-Muwaffaq]] in the style of the caliphs, Talha soon became the effective ruler of the Caliphate, a position consolidated in 882 after a failed attempt by al-Mu'tamid to flee to [[Egypt in the Middle Ages|Egypt]] led to his confinement in house arrest.{{sfn|Kennedy|2001|pp=148–150}}{{sfn|Bonner|2010|pp=323–324}}

Caliphal authority in the provinces collapsed during the &quot;Anarchy at Samarra&quot;, with the result that by the 870s the central government had lost effective control over most of the Caliphate outside the metropolitan region of [[Iraq]]. In the west, Egypt had fallen under the control of [[Ahmad ibn Tulun]], who also disputed control of [[Bilad al-Sham|Syria]] with al-Muwaffaq, while [[Khurasan]] and most of the Islamic East had been taken over by the [[Saffarids]], who replaced the Abbasids' loyal client state, the [[Tahirids]]. Most of the [[Arabian peninsula]] was likewise lost to local potentates, while in [[Tabaristan]] a radical [[Zaydi]] [[Shi'a]] dynasty took power. Even in Iraq, the [[Zanj Revolt|rebellion]] of the [[Zanj]] slaves threatened Baghdad itself, and further south the [[Qarmatians]] were a nascent threat.{{sfn|Mottahedeh|1975|pp=77–78}}{{sfn|Bonner|2010|pp=313–327}}{{sfn|Kennedy|2001|p=148}} Al-Muwaffaq's regency was thus a continuous struggle to save the tottering Caliphate from collapse.{{sfn|Bonner|2010|p=314}} His attempts to recover control of Egypt and Syria from Ibn Tulun failed, with the latter even able to expand his territory and obtain recognition as a hereditary ruler,{{sfn|Kennedy|2004a|p=177}}{{sfn|Bonner|2010|p=335}} but he succeeded in preserving the core of the Caliphate in Iraq by [[Battle of Dayr al-'Aqul|repelling]] a Saffarid invasion aimed at capturing Baghdad, and by subduing the Zanj after a long struggle.{{sfn|Bonner|2010|pp=323–324}}{{sfn|Mottahedeh|1975|p=79}}

=== Campaigns against the Zanj and the Tulunids ===
[[File:Iraq Ninth Century.png|thumb|right|upright=1.2|alt=Geophysical map with regions and major cities|Map of Iraq in the 9th–10th centuries]]
It was against the Zanj that the future al-Mu'tadid—at this time usually referred to by his ''[[kunya (Arabic)|kunya]]'' of Abu'l-Abbas—would acquire his first military experience and establish the close ties with the army that would characterize his reign. Al-Muwaffaq gave his son a military upbringing from an early age, and the young prince became &quot;a keen horseman and took care to inspect both his troops and their mounts in person&quot;.{{sfn|Kennedy|1993|pp=759–760}}{{sfn|Kennedy|2001|pp=151, 156}}

Within a decade from the outbreak of the revolt in 869, the Zanj had seized most of lower Iraq, including the cities of [[Basra]] and [[Wasit]], and expanded into [[Khuzistan]] as well.{{sfn|Bonner|2010|pp=323–324}}{{sfn|Kennedy|2004a|pp=177–179}} In 879 the death of the founder of the Saffarid state, [[Ya'qub al-Saffar]], allowed the Abbasid government to fully concentrate its attention against the Zanj rebellion,{{sfn|Bonner|2010|pp=323–324}} and Abu'l-Abbas' appointment to command in December 879 at the head of 10,000 troops marks the turning point of the war.{{sfn|Kennedy|2001|pp=153–154}} In the long and hard struggle that followed, which involved amphibious operations in the [[Mesopotamian Marshes]], Abu'l-Abbas and his own military slaves (''[[ghilman|ghilmān]]'')—of which the long-serving [[Zirak al-Turki]] was the chief—played the major role: although the Abbasid armies eventually swelled with reinforcements, volunteers, and Zanj defectors, it was the few but elite ''ghilmān'' who formed the army's backbone, filling its leadership positions and bearing the brunt of the battle, often under the personal command of Abu'l-Abbas.{{sfn|Kennedy|2001|pp=151, 153–156}} After years of gradually tightening the noose around the Zanj, in August 883 the Abbasid troops stormed their capital of al-Mukhtara, putting an end to the rebellion.{{sfn|Bonner|2010|p=324}}{{sfn|Kennedy|2004a|p=179}} A detailed account of the war, written by a former Zanj rebel and preserved in the history of [[al-Tabari]], stresses the role of al-Muwaffaq and Abu'l-Abbas as the heroes who, in defence of the embattled Muslim state, suppressed the rebellion; the successful campaign would become a major tool in their propaganda effort to legitimize their ''de facto'' usurpation of the Caliph's power.{{sfn|Kennedy|2003|pp=26–35}}

Following the death of Ibn Tulun in May 884, the two caliphal generals [[Ishaq ibn Kundaj]] and [[Muhammad ibn Abi'l-Saj|Ibn Abu'l-Saj]] sought to take advantage of the situation and attacked the Tulunid domains in Syria, but their initial gains were rapidly reversed. In the spring of 885, Abu'l-Abbas was sent to take charge of the invasion. He soon succeeded in defeating the Tulunids and forcing them to retreat to [[Palestine (region)|Palestine]], but after a quarrel with Ibn Kundaj and Ibn Abu'l-Saj, the latter abandoned the campaign and withdrew their forces. In the [[Battle of Tawahin]] on 6 April, Abu'l-Abbas confronted Ibn Tulun's son and heir, [[Khumarawayh ibn Ahmad ibn Tulun|Khumarawayh]], in person. The Abbasid prince was initially victorious, forcing Khumarawayh to flee, but was in turn defeated and fled the battlefield, while much of his army was taken prisoner.{{sfn|Sobernheim|1987|p=973}}{{sfn|Bianquis|1998|pp=104–105}} After this victory the Tulunids expanded their control over the [[al-Jazira, Mesopotamia|Jazira]] and the borderlands (the [[Thughur]]) with the [[Byzantine Empire]]. A peace agreement followed in 886, whereby al-Muwaffaq was forced to recognize Khumarawayh as hereditary governor over Egypt and Syria for 30 years, in exchange for an annual tribute.{{sfn|Kennedy|2004a|p=177}}{{sfn|Bonner|2010|p=335}} Over the next couple of years, Abu'l-Abbas was involved in his father's ultimately unsuccessful attempts to wrest control of [[Fars Province|Fars]] from Saffarid control.{{sfn|Bosworth|1975|pp=119–120}}

=== Imprisonment and rise to the throne ===
During this period, relations between Abu'l-Abbas and his father deteriorated, although the reason is unclear. Already in 884, Abu'l-Abbas' ''ghilmān'' rioted in Baghdad against al-Muwaffaq's [[vizier]], [[Sa'id ibn Makhlad]], possibly over unpaid salaries.{{sfn|Kennedy|1993|pp=759–760}}{{sfn|Kennedy|2001|p=152}} Eventually, in 889, Abu'l-Abbas was arrested and put in prison on his father's orders, where he remained despite the demonstrations of the ''ghilmān'' loyal to him. He apparently remained under arrest until May 891, when al-Muwaffaq returned to Baghdad after two years spent in [[Jibal]].{{sfn|Kennedy|1993|pp=759–760}}{{sfn|Kennedy|2001|p=152}} 

Al-Muwaffaq, suffering from [[gout]],{{sfn|Bowen|1928|p=25}} was already visibly nearing his end; the vizier [[Isma'il ibn Bulbul]] and the city commander of Baghdad, Abu'l-Saqr, called al-Mu'tamid and his sons, including the heir-apparent [[al-Mufawwad]], into the city, hoping to exploit al-Muwaffaq's imminent death for their own purposes. Nevertheless the attempt to sideline Abu'l-Abbas failed due to his popularity with the soldiers and the common people. He was set free to visit his father's deathbed, and was able to immediately assume power when al-Muwaffaq died on 2 June. The Baghdad mob ransacked his opponents' houses, and Ibn Bulbul was dismissed and thrown in prison, where he died from maltreatment after a few months. Similar fates awaited any of his supporters that Abu'l-Abbas could lay his hands on.{{sfn|Bowen|1928|p=27}}{{sfn|Kennedy|2001|pp=152–153}}

Now &quot;all-powerful&quot;,{{sfn|Bowen|1928|p=27}} Abu'l-Abbas succeeded his father in all his offices, with the title of ''al-Mu'tadid bi-llah'' and a position in the line of succession after the Caliph and al-Mufawwad. Within a few months, in April 892, al-Mu'tadid had his cousin removed from the succession, and probably killed. As a result, when al-Mu'tamid died in October—possibly poisoned—al-Mu'tadid succeeded to the throne as caliph.{{sfn|Kennedy|2003|pp=26, 34}}{{sfn|Bonner|2010|p=332}}{{sfn|Bowen|1928|p=25}}

== Reign ==
Harold Bowen describes al-Mu'tadid at his accession as &quot;in appearance upright and thin; and on his head was a white mole, which, since white moles were not admired, he used to dye black. His expression was haughty. In character he was brave—a story was told of his killing a lion with only a dagger. [...] he had inherited all his father's energy, and cultivated a reputation of prompt action.&quot;{{sfn|Bowen|1928|p=26}} Like his father, al-Mu'tadid’s power rested on his close relations with the military, and it was military activities which consumed his interest, especially as he usually led his army in person on campaign. As the historian [[Michael Bonner]] comments, &quot;[t]he role of '[[Ghazi warriors|ghazī]] caliph', invented by [[Harun al-Rashid]] and enhanced by [[al-Mu'tasim]], now had its greatest performance, in al-Mu'tadid's tireless campaigning&quot;.{{sfn|Bonner|2010|p=332}}{{sfn|Kennedy|2004a|p=181}}

=== Reunification campaigns and foreign relations ===
From the start of his reign, the new Caliph set out to reverse the fragmentation of the Abbasid Caliphate,{{sfn|Kennedy|1993|pp=759–760}} a goal towards which he worked with a mixture of force and diplomacy; although an active and enthusiastic campaigner, al-Mu'tadid was also &quot;a skilful diplomat, always prepared to make compromises with those who were too powerful to defeat&quot; (Hugh Kennedy).{{sfn|Kennedy|2004a|p=181}} 

==== Relations with the Tulunids ====
This policy became immediately evident in the conciliatory attitude the new Caliph adopted towards his most powerful vassal, the Tulunids: in spring 893, al-Mu'tadid recognized and reconfirmed Khumarawayh in his office as autonomous [[emir]] over Egypt and Syria, in exchange for an annual tribute of 300,000 [[gold dinar|dinars]] and a further 200,000 dinars in arrears, as well as the return to caliphal control of the two Jaziran provinces of [[Diyar Rabi'a]] and [[Diyar Mudar]].{{sfn|Bianquis|1998|pp=105–106}} To seal the pact, Khumarawayh offered his daughter, Qatr al-Nada (&quot;Dew Drop&quot;) as bride to one of the Caliph's sons, but al-Mu'tadid chose to marry her himself. The Tulunid princess brought with her a million dinars as her dowry, a &quot;wedding gift that was considered the most sumptuous in medieval Arab history&quot; (Thierry Bianquis).{{sfn|Sobernheim|1987|p=973}}{{sfn|Bianquis|1998|p=106}} Her arrival in Baghdad was marked by the luxury and extravagance of her retinue, which contrasted starkly with the impoverished caliphal court. According to a story, after a thorough search, al-Mu'tadid's chief eunuch could only find five ornate silver-and-gold candlesticks to decorate the palace, while the princess was accompanied by 150 servants each carrying such a candlestick. Thereupon al-Mu'tadid is said to have remarked &quot;come let us go and hide ourselves, lest we be seen in our poverty&quot;.{{sfn|Sobernheim|1987|p=973}} 

Qatr al-Nada died soon after the wedding, and the murder of Khumarawayh in 896 left the Tulunid state in the unsteady hands of Khumarawayh's under-age sons. Al-Mu'tadid swiftly took advantage of this and in 897 extended his control over the border emirates of the Thughur, where, in the words of Michael Bonner, &quot;[he] assumed, after a long hiatus, the old caliphal prerogative of commanding the annual summer expedition and arranging the defence against the Byzantine Empire&quot;. In addition, to secure caliphal recognition of his position, the new Tulunid ruler [[Harun ibn Khumarawayh]] (r. 896–904) was forced into further concessions, handing back all of Syria north of [[Homs]], and increasing the annual tribute to 450,000 dinars.{{sfn|Bonner|2010|p=336}}{{sfn|Kennedy|2004a|p=181}} Over the next few years, increasing domestic turmoil in the remaining Tulunid domains, and the escalation of Qarmatian attacks, encouraged many Tulunid followers to defect to the resurgent Caliphate.{{sfn|Bonner|2010|p=336}}

==== Jazira, Transcaucasia, and the Byzantine front ====
[[File:Al-Jazira.svg|thumb|right|upright=1.2|alt=Geophysical map with regions and major cities, al-Jazira is highlighted in red|Map of the [[al-Jazira, Mesopotamia|Jazira]] (Upper [[Mesopotamia]]), with its provinces, in medieval times]]
In the Jazira the new Caliph struggled against a variety of opponents: alongside an [[Kharijite Rebellion (866–896)|almost thirty-year-old Kharijite rebellion]], there were various autonomous local magnates, chiefly the [[Banu Shayban|Shaybani]] ruler of [[Amid]] and [[Diyar Bakr]], [[Ahmad ibn Isa al-Shaybani]], and the [[Banu Taghlib|Taghlibi]] chief [[Hamdan ibn Hamdun]]. In 893, while the Kharijites were distracted by internal quarrels, al-Mu'tadid captured [[Mosul]] from the Shayban. Next, in 895 Hamdan ibn Hamdun was evicted from his strongholds, hunted down and captured. Finally, the Kharijite leader Harun ibn Abdallah himself was defeated and captured by Hamdan's son [[Husayn ibn Hamdan|Husayn]] in 896, before being sent to Baghdad, where he was [[crucifixion|crucified]]. This exploit marked the beginning of an illustrious career for Husayn ibn Hamdan in the caliphal armies, and the gradual rise of the [[Hamdanid]] family to power in the Jazira.{{sfn|Kennedy|1993|pp=759–760}}{{sfn|Kennedy|2004a|pp=181–182, 266}}{{sfn|Zetterstéen|1987|p=777}} Ahmad al-Shaybani retained Amid until his death in 898, being succeeded by his son [[Muhammad ibn Ahmad al-Shaybani|Muhammad]]. In the next year, al-Mu'tadid returned to the Jazira, ousted Muhammad from Amid, and reunified the entire province under central government control by installing his son and heir, [[Ali al-Muktafi]], as governor.{{sfn|Kennedy|1993|pp=759–760}}{{sfn|Kennedy|2004a|p=182}}

Al-Mu'tadid was unable, however, to restore effective caliphal control north of the Jazira in [[Transcaucasia]], where [[Medieval Armenia|Armenia]] and [[Adharbayjan]] remained in the hands of virtually independent local dynasties.{{sfn|Kennedy|2004a|p=182}} Ibn Abu'l-Saj, who was now the caliphal governor of Adharbayjan, proclaimed himself independent around 898, although soon he recognized again the Caliph's suzerainty during his conflicts with the Christian Armenian princes. When he died in 901, he was succeeded by his son [[Devdad ibn Muhammad|Devdad]], marking the consolidation of the semi-independent [[Sajid dynasty]] in the region.{{sfn|Madelung|1975|pp=228–229}} In 900 Ibn Abu'l-Saj was even suspected of plotting to seize the Diyar Mudar province with the co-operation of the notables of [[Tarsus (city)|Tarsus]], after which the vengeful Caliph ordered the latter arrested and the city's fleet burned.{{sfn|Zetterstéen|1987|p=777}}{{sfn|Madelung|1975|p=229}} This decision was a self-inflicted wound on the [[Arab–Byzantine wars|centuries-long war]] against Byzantium; in recent decades the Tarsians and their fleet had played a major role in the raids against the Byzantine frontier provinces.{{sfn|Treadgold|1997|pp=461–466}} While a Syrian fleet under the renegade [[Damian of Tarsus]] sacked the port of [[Demetrias]] around 900, and Arab fleets would go on to wreak havoc in the [[Aegean Sea]] over the next two decades, the Byzantines were strengthened on land by an influx of Armenian refugees, such as [[Melias]]. The Byzantines began to expand their control over the border regions, scoring victories and founding new provinces ([[theme (Byzantine district)|themes]]) in the former no-man's land between the two empires.{{sfn|Treadgold|1997|pp=466ff}}

==== The East and the Saffarids ====
In the Islamic East, the Caliph was forced to acknowledge the reality of the Saffarids' domination and established a ''[[modus vivendi]]'' with them, perhaps hoping, according to Hugh Kennedy, to harness them in a partnership analogous to that which the Tahirids had enjoyed in previous decades. Consequently, the Saffarids were recognized in their possession of Khurasan and eastern Persia as well as Fars, while the Abbasids were to exercise direct control over western Persia, namely Jibal, [[Rey, Iran|Rayy]] and [[Isfahan]].{{sfn|Kennedy|1993|pp=759–760}}{{sfn|Bonner|2010|p=336}} This policy gave the Caliph a free hand to recover the territories of the [[Dulafids]], another semi-independent local dynasty that was centred on Isfahan and [[Nihavand]]. When the Dulafid [[Ahmad ibn Abd al-Aziz ibn Abi Dulaf]] died in 893, al-Mu'tadid moved swiftly to install his son al-Muktafi as governor in Rayy, [[Qazvin]], [[Qum]] and [[Hamadan]]. The Dulafids were confined to their core region around [[Karaj]] and Isfahan, before being deposed outright in 896. Nevertheless, the Abbasid hold over these territories remained precarious, especially due to the proximity of the [[Alids of Tabaristan, Daylam and Gilan|Zaydi emirate]] in Tabaristan, and in 897 Rayy was handed over to Saffarid control.{{sfn|Bonner|2010|p=336}}{{sfn|Kennedy|2004a|pp=182–183}}

The Abbasid–Saffarid partnership in Iran was most clearly expressed in their joint effort against the general [[Rafi ibn Harthama]], who had made his base in Rayy and posed a threat to both caliphal and Saffarid interests in the region. Al-Mu'tadid sent Ahmad ibn Abd al-Aziz to seize Rayy from Rafi, who fled and made common cause with the Zaydis of Tabaristan in an effort to seize Khurasan from the Saffarids. However, with Amr mobilizing the anti-Alid sentiments of the populace against him and the expected assistance from the Zaydis failing to materialize, Rafi was defeated and killed in [[Khwarazm]] in 896. Amr, now at the pinnacle of his power, sent the defeated rebel's head to Baghdad, and in 897 the Caliph transferred control of Rayy to him.{{sfn|Bosworth|1975|p=120}} The partnership finally collapsed after Mu'tadid appointed the Saffarid ruler [[Amr ibn al-Layth]] in 898 as governor of [[Transoxiana]], which was ruled by his rivals, the [[Samanids]]. Al-Mu'tamid deliberately encouraged Amr to confront the Samanids, only for Amr to be crushingly defeated and taken prisoner by the latter in 900. The Samanid ruler, [[Isma'il ibn Ahmad]], sent him in chains to Baghdad, where he was executed in 902, after al-Mu'tadid's death. Al-Mu'tadid in turn conferred Amr's titles and governorships to Isma'il ibn Ahmad. The Caliph also moved to regain Fars and Kirman, but the Saffarid remnant under [[Tahir ibn Muhammad ibn Amr|Tahir]] proved sufficiently resilient to thwart the Abbasid attempts at capturing these two provinces for several years. It was not until 910 that the Abbasids managed to regain the coveted Fars province.{{sfn|Kennedy|1993|pp=759–760}}{{sfn|Bosworth|1975|pp=121–122}}{{sfn|Bonner|2010|pp=336–337}}

==== Fragmentation in the periphery ====
At the same time, the Caliphate faced a new threat, the Qarmatians. A radical Islamic sect founded in [[Kufa]] around 874, the Qarmatians were originally a sporadic and minor nuisance in the [[Sawad]] (Lower Iraq), but their power grew swiftly to alarming proportions after 897: under the leadership of Abu Sa'id al-Jannabi, they seized [[Bahrayn (historical region)|Bahrayn]] in 899 and in the next year defeated a caliphal army under [[al-Abbas ibn Amr al-Ghanawi]]. In the years following al-Mu'tadid's death, the Qarmatians &quot;were to prove the most dangerous enemies the Abbasids had faced since the time of the Zanj&quot; (Hugh Kennedy).{{sfn|Kennedy|1993|pp=759–760}}{{sfn|Bianquis|1998|pp=106–107}} The same period also saw more anti-Abbasid regimes established on the periphery of the Islamic world: another Zaydi dynasty [[Al-Hadi ila'l-Haqq Yahya|was established]] in [[Yemen]] in 897, and in 909 the [[Fatimids]] seized power in [[Ifriqiya]] from the Abbasid clients, the [[Aghlabids]].{{sfn|Bonner|2010|pp=327–332}}{{sfn|Bonner|2010|p=327}}

=== Domestic government ===
[[File:Abbasid Caliphate 900.png|thumb|right|upright=1.2|alt=Blank map of the Middle East, with green shaded areas for the Abbasid Caliphate, and the major regions and provinces marked|Map showing the result of al-Mu'tadid's campaigns of consolidation, ca. 900: areas under direct Abbasid control in dark green, areas under loose Abbasid suzerainty, but under autonomous governors, in light green]]
==== Fiscal policies ====
The Abbasid army, following the reforms of al-Mu'tasim, was a smaller and more professional fighting force than the caliphal armies of the past. Although it proved effective militarily, it also posed a potential danger to the stability of the Abbasid regime: drawn from Turks and other peoples from the Caliphate's periphery and the lands beyond, it was alienated from the society of the Caliphate's heartlands, with the result that the soldiers were &quot;entirely reliant on the state not just for cash but for their very survival&quot; (Hugh Kennedy). As a result, any failure by the central government to provide their pay resulted in a military uprising and a political crisis, as had been repeatedly demonstrated during the Anarchy at Samarra.{{sfn|Kennedy|2004b|pp=10–15}} Consequently, ensuring the regular payment of the army became the prime task of the state. According to Hugh Kennedy, based on a treasury document from the time of al-Mu'tadid's accession, &quot;out of the total expenditure of 7915 dinars per day, some 5121 are entirely military, 1943 in areas (like riding animals and stables) which served both military and non-military and only 851 in areas like the bureaucracy and the [[harem]] which can be described as truly civilian (though even in this case, the bureaucrats’ main purpose seems to have been to arrange the payment of the army). It seems reasonable to conclude that something over 80 per cent of recorded government expenditure was devoted to maintaining the army.&quot;{{sfn|Kennedy|2001|p=156}}

At the same time, the Caliphate's fiscal basis had shrunk dramatically after so many tax-paying provinces had been lost from the central government's control.{{sfn|Mottahedeh|1975|p=80}} The caliphal government was now increasingly reliant on the revenue of the Sawad and the other areas of lower Iraq, which were witnessing a rapid decline in agricultural productivity due to the disruption of the civil wars and neglect of the irrigation network. In the reign of Harun al-Rashid the Sawad had provided an annual revenue of 102,500,000 ''[[dirham]]s'', more than double the revenue of Egypt and three times that of Syria; by the early 10th century it was providing less than a third of that figure.{{sfn|Kennedy|2004a|p=187}}{{sfn|Kennedy|2004b|pp=11–13}} The situation was further exacerbated by the fact that in the remaining provinces, semi-autonomous governors, grandees and members of the dynasty were able to establish virtual [[latifundia]], aided by the system of ''muqāṭa'a'', a form of [[tax farming]] in exchange for a fixed tribute, which they often failed to pay.{{sfn|Kennedy|2004a|p=187}}{{sfn|Mottahedeh|1975|p=87}} To maximise their revenue from the territory remaining to them, the Abbasids increased the breadth and complexity of the central bureaucracy, dividing the provinces into smaller tax districts as well as increasing the number of the fiscal departments (''[[divan|dīwān]]s''), allowing for close oversight of both revenue collection and the activities of the officials themselves.{{sfn|Mottahedeh|1975|pp=79–80, 87}}

To combat this fiscal crisis, the Caliph would often personally devote himself to the supervision of revenue, acquiring a reputation for &quot;a spirit of economy, verging on avarice&quot; (F. Malti-Douglas); he was said to &quot;examine petty accounts that a commoner would scorn to consider&quot; (Harold Bowen).{{sfn|Bowen|1928|p=26}}{{sfn|Malti-Douglas|1999|p=327}} Fines and confiscations multiplied under his rule, with the resulting revenue, along with the income from the crown domain and even a portion of the provincial taxation, flowing to the caliphal privy purse (''bayt al-māl al-khāṣṣa''). The latter now acquired a leading role among the other fiscal departments, and it frequently held more money than the public treasury (''bayt al-māl al-ʿāmma'') itself.{{sfn|Bonner|2010|p=334}}{{sfn|Finer|1999|pp=706–707}} By the end of al-Mu'tadid's reign, the once empty privy purse would contain ten million dinars.{{sfn|Bowen|1928|p=26}} On the other hand, in a measure aimed to ease the tax burden of the farmers, in 895 the Caliph changed the start of the tax year from the [[Persian New Year]] in March to 11 June—which became known as ''Nayrūz al-Muʿtaḍid'', &quot;al-Mu'tadid's New Year&quot;—so that the land tax (''[[kharaj|kharāj]]'') was now collected after the harvest instead of before.{{sfn|Kennedy|2004a|p=181}}{{sfn|Talbi|1998|p=456 (note 313)}}

==== Rise of the bureaucracy ====
The Caliph's policies strengthened the position of the civil bureaucracy, which now reached the apogee of its influence, and especially the vizier, whom even the army came to respect as the spokesman of the caliph.{{sfn|Mottahedeh|1975|p=79}} In terms of personnel, al-Mu'tadid's reign was marked by continuity among the senior leadership of the state. [[Ubayd Allah ibn Sulayman ibn Wahb]] remained vizier from the start of the reign until his death in 901, and was succeeded by his son, [[Al-Qasim ibn Ubayd Allah|al-Qasim]], who had from the start been deputizing his father during the latter's absences from the capital. The [[freedman]] [[Abu'l-Najm Badr al-Mu'tadidi|Badr]], a veteran who had served under al-Muwaffaq and whose daughter married the Caliph's son, remained commander of the army. The fiscal departments, especially of the Sawad, were managed first by the [[Banu'l-Furat]] brothers [[Ahmad ibn al-Furat|Ahmad]] and [[Ali ibn al-Furat|Ali]], and after 899 by the [[Banu'l-Jarrah]] under [[Muhammad ibn Dawud]] and his nephew, [[Ali ibn Isa al-Jarrah|Ali ibn Isa]].{{sfn|Kennedy|2004a|pp=179–180}}{{sfn|Bonner|2010|p=333}}{{sfn|Bowen|1928|pp=28–31, 43–45}} The original administrative team was so effective and harmonious that according to the 11th-century historian [[Hilal al-Sabi'|Hilal as-Sabi]], it was said by subsequent generations that &quot;there had never been such a quartet, Caliph, Vizier, Commander, and chief of the ''diwāns'', as al-Mu'tadid, Ubayd Allah, Badr and Ahmad ibn al-Furat&quot;.{{sfn|Bowen|1928|p=44}} 

On the other hand, Michel Bonner points out that the later reign of al-Mu'tadid &quot;saw a growth of factionalism within this bureaucracy, observable also in the army and in urban civilian life&quot;.{{sfn|Bonner|2010|p=333}} The rivalry between the two bureaucratic dynasties of the Banu'l-Furat and the Banu'l-Jarrah, with their extensive networks of clients, began at this time. Although a strong caliph and vizier could restrain this rivalry, it would dominate the Abbasid government over the next decades, with the factions alternating in office and often fining and torturing their predecessors to extract money according to the well-established practice known as ''muṣādara''.{{sfn|Mottahedeh|1975|p=79}}{{sfn|Bonner|2010|pp=333–334}}{{sfn|Kennedy|2004a|p=180}} In addition, al-Qasim ibn Ubayd Allah was of an altogether different character than his father: soon after his appointment to the vizierate, al-Qasim even plotted to have al-Mu'tadid assassinated, and tried to involve Badr in his scheming. The general rejected his proposals with indignation, but al-Qasim was saved from discovery and execution by the Caliph's sudden death. The vizier then tried to dominate al-Muktafi, moved swiftly to have Badr denounced and executed, and was involved in yet more intrigues against the Banu'l-Furat.{{sfn|Bowen|1928|pp=57ff}}

==== Return of the capital to Baghdad ====
Al-Mu'tadid also completed the return of the capital from Samarra to Baghdad, which had already served as his father's main base of operations. The city's centre, however, was relocated on the eastern bank of the Tigris and further downstream from the original city, where it has remained to this day.{{sfn|Kennedy|2004a|pp=180–181}} As the 10th-century historian [[al-Mas'udi]] wrote, the Caliph's two main passions were &quot;women and building&quot; (''al-nisāʿ waʿl-banāʿ''),{{sfn|Bowen|1928|p=26}} and accordingly he engaged in major building activities in the capital: he restored and expanded the Great Mosque of [[al-Mansur]] which had fallen into disuse,{{sfn|Le Strange|1900|pp=34–36}} enlarged the Hasani palace, built the new palaces of Thurayya (&quot;[[Pleiades]]&quot;) and Firdus (&quot;Paradise&quot;), and began work on the Taj (&quot;Crown&quot;) Palace, which was completed under al-Muktafi.{{sfn|Le Strange|1900|pp=xxx, 242ff}}{{sfn|Bowen|1928|p=59}} He also took care to restore the city's irrigation network by cleaning up the silted-up [[Dujayl Canal]] and paying for it with money from those landowners who stood to profit from it.{{sfn|Kennedy|2004a|pp=180–181}}

==== Theological doctrines and promotion of science ====
In terms of doctrine, al-Mu'tadid from the outset of his reign sided firmly with [[Sunni]] traditionalist orthodoxy, forbidding theological works and abolishing the fiscal department on property in [[escheat]], which [[Hanbali]] legal opinion regarded as illegal.{{sfn|Sourdel|1970|p=132}} At the same time he also tried to maintain good relations with the Alids, to the point of seriously considering ordering the official cursing of [[Mu'awiya]], the first [[Umayyad]] caliph and author of the death of [[Ali]]; he was only dissuaded at the last moment by his advisers, who feared any unforeseen consequences such an act might have. Al-Mu'tadid also maintained good relations with the breakaway Zaydi imams of Tabaristan, but his pro-Alid stance failed to prevent the establishment of a second Zaydi state in Yemen in 901.{{sfn|Sourdel|1970|p=132}} 

Al-Mu'tadid also actively promoted the traditions of learning and science that had flourished under his early 9th-century predecessors [[al-Ma'mun]] (r. 813–832), al-Mu'tasim, and [[al-Wathiq]] (r. 842–847). Court patronage for scientific endeavours had declined under al-Mutawakkil, whose reign had marked a return to Sunni orthodoxy and did not favour scientific inquiry, while his successors had lacked the luxury to engage in intellectual pursuits. Himself &quot;keenly interested in natural sciences&quot; and able to speak Greek, al-Mu'tadid promoted the career of one of the great [[Translation Movement|translators of Greek texts]] and mathematicians of the era, [[Thabit ibn Qurra]], and of the [[grammarian]]s [[Ibn Durayd]] and [[al-Zajjaj]], who became tutor of the Caliph's children.{{sfn|Kennedy|2006|pp=243–245}} One of the leading intellectual figures of the period was al-Mu'tadid's own tutor, [[Ahmad ibn al-Tayyib al-Sarakhsi]], a pupil of the great philosopher [[al-Kindi]]. Al-Sarakhsi became a close companion of the Caliph, who appointed him to the lucrative post of market supervisor of Baghdad, but was executed in 896, after angering the Caliph. According to one account, al-Qasim ibn Ubayd Allah—who is frequently featured as the villain in anecdotes of al-Mu'tadid's court—inserted his name in a list of rebels to be executed; the Caliph signed the list, and only learned of his mistake after his old master had been executed.{{sfn|Kennedy|2006|pp=245–246}}

==== Justice and punishment under al-Mu'tadid ====
In the dispensation of justice, he was characterized by what F. Malti-Douglas describes as &quot;severity bordering on sadism&quot;. While tolerant of error and not above displays of sentimentality and tenderness, when his wrath was aroused he resorted to torture in the most ingenious ways, and had special torture chambers constructed underneath his palace. Chroniclers like al-Mas'udi and the Mamluk historian al-Safadi describe in great detail the tortures inflicted by the Caliph on prisoners, as well as his practice of making an example of them by having them publicly displayed in Baghdad. At the same time, however, they tend to justify his severity as legitimate, in service of the interests of the state. F. Malti-Douglas remarks that when al-Safadi compared al-Mu'tadid with the founder of the Abbasid state, calling him &quot;[[al-Saffah]] the Second&quot;, this was not only to emphasize his restoration of the Caliphate's fortunes, but was also a direct allusion to the meaning of al-Saffah's name, &quot;the Blood-Shedder&quot;.{{sfn|Bowen|1928|p=26}}{{sfn|Malti-Douglas|1999|pp=327–334}}

===Death and legacy===
Al-Mu'tadid died at the Hasani palace on 5 April 902, at the age of either 40 or 47. There were rumours that he had been poisoned, but it is more likely that the rigours of his campaigns, coupled with his dissolute life, severely weakened his health. During his final illness, he refused to follow the advice of his physicians, and even kicked one of them to death.{{sfn|Zetterstéen|1987|p=777}}{{sfn|Bowen|1928|p=58}} He left behind him four sons and several daughters.{{sfn|Bowen|1928|p=58}} Al-Mu'tadid was the first Abbasid caliph to be buried within the walls of Baghdad. Like his sons after him, he was buried in the former Tahirid palace in the western part of the city, which was now used by the caliphs as a secondary residence.{{sfn|Le Strange|1900|pp=120, 194–195 (note 2)}}

According to the Orientalist [[Karl Vilhelm Zetterstéen]], al-Mu'tadid &quot;had inherited his father's gifts as a ruler and was distinguished alike for his economy and his military ability&quot;, becoming &quot;one of the greatest of the Abbasids in spite of his strictness and cruelty&quot;.{{sfn|Zetterstéen|1987|p=777}} Al-Mu'tadid's capable reign is credited with having arrested the Abbasid Caliphate's decline for a while, but his successes were too dependent on the presence of an energetic ruler at the helm, and ultimately his reign &quot;was too short to reverse long-term trends and re-establish Abbasid power on a long-term basis&quot; (Hugh Kennedy).{{sfn|Kennedy|1993|pp=759–760}}

Al-Mu'tadid had taken care to prepare his son and successor, al-Muktafi, for his role by appointing him as governor in Rayy and the Jazira.{{sfn|Kennedy|1993|pp=759–760}}{{sfn|Bonner|2010|p=337}} Although al-Muktafi tried to follow his father's policies, he lacked his energy. The heavily militarized system of al-Muwaffaq and al-Mu'tadid required the Caliph to actively participate in campaigns, setting a personal example and allowing for the formation of ties of loyalty, reinforced by patronage, between the ruler and the soldiers. Al-Muktafi, on the other hand, did not &quot;in his character and comportment [...], being a sedentary figure, instil much loyalty, let alone inspiration, in the soldiers&quot; (Michael Bonner).{{sfn|Bonner|2010|pp=332, 335, 337}} The Caliphate was still able to secure major successes over the next few years, including the reincorporation of the Tulunid domains in 904 and victories over the Qarmatians, but with al-Muktafi's death in 908, the so-called &quot;Abbasid restoration&quot; passed its high-water mark, and a new period of crisis began.{{sfn|Bonner|2010|pp=337–339}}{{sfn|Kennedy|2004a|pp=184–185}}{{sfn|Sourdel|1970|pp=132–134}}

Power was now wielded by the senior bureaucrats, who installed the weak and pliable [[al-Muqtadir]] on the throne. Over the next decades, the expenditure of both the court and the army increased, while maladministration and strife between military and bureaucratic factions intensified. By 932, when al-Muqtadir was assassinated, the Caliphate was effectively bankrupt, and authority soon devolved on a series of military strongmen who competed for control of the caliph and the title of ''[[amir al-umara|amīr al-umarāʾ]]''. This process culminated in the capture of Baghdad in 946 by the [[Buyids]], who put an end to caliphal independence even in name. Thereafter the caliphs remained as symbolic figureheads, but were divested of any military or political authority or independent financial resources.{{sfn|Kennedy|2004a|pp=185–197}}{{sfn|Donner|1999|p=30}}{{sfn|Sourdel|1970|pp=134–139}}

== References ==
{{reflist|30em}}

== Sources ==
* {{cite book | chapter = Autonomous Egypt from Ibn Ṭūlūn to Kāfūr, 868–969 | first = Thierry | last = Bianquis | authorlink = | title = Cambridge History of Egypt, Volume One: Islamic Egypt, 640–1517 | publisher = Cambridge University Press | editor-last = Petry | editor-first = Carl F. | location = Cambridge | year = 1998 | isbn = 0-521-47137-0 | pages = 86–119 | chapterurl = https://books.google.com/books?id=y3FtXpB_tqMC&amp;pg=PA86#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Bonner | first = Michael | authorlink = Michael Bonner | chapter = The waning of empire, 861–945 | title = The New Cambridge History of Islam, Volume I: The Formation of the Islamic World, Sixth to Eleventh Centuries | editor-last=Robinson | editor-first=Charles F | publisher = Cambridge University Press | location=Cambridge | year = 2010 | isbn = 978-0-521-83823-8 | pages = 305–359| ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Bosworth | first = C. E. | authorlink = Clifford Edmund Bosworth | chapter = The Ṭāhirids and Ṣaffārids | title = The Cambridge History of Iran, Volume 4: From the Arab Invasion to the Saljuqs | year = 1975 | publisher = Cambridge University Press | location=Cambridge | chapterurl=https://books.google.com/books?id=hvx9jq_2L3EC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PA90#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false | editor-first = R. N. | editor-last = Frye | isbn = 0-521-20093-8| pages=90–135 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | first = Harold | last = Bowen | title = The Life and Times of ʿAlí Ibn ʿÍsà: The Good Vizier | year = 1928 | location = Cambridge | publisher = Cambridge University Press | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=TZM3AAAAIAAJ | oclc = 386849 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Donner | first = Fred M. | chapter = Muhammad and the Caliphate: Political History of the Islamic Empire up to the Mongol Conquest | pages = 1–62 | editor-first = John L. | editor-last = Esposito | title = The Oxford History of Islam | location = New York and Oxford  | publisher = Oxford University Press | year = 1999 | isbn = 0195107993 | chapterurl = https://books.google.com/books?id=imw_KFD5bsQC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PA1#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | first = Samuel Edward | last = Finer | title = The History of Government from the Earliest Times, Volume II: The Intermediate Ages | year = 1999 | location = New York and Oxford | publisher = Oxford University Press | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=AhEab85xHAMC | isbn = 0-19-820790-5 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite encyclopedia | title=al-Muʿtaḍid Bi’llāh | first = Hugh N. | last = Kennedy | authorlink=Hugh N. Kennedy | encyclopedia = The Encyclopedia of Islam, New Edition, Volume VII: Mif–Naz | publisher = BRILL | location = Leiden and New York | year = 1993 | isbn = 90-04-09419-9 | pages = 759–760 | url = http://referenceworks.brillonline.com/entries/encyclopaedia-of-islam-2/al-mutadid-billah-SIM_5640| ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | title = The Armies of the Caliphs: Military and Society in the Early Islamic State | first = Hugh N. | last = Kennedy | authorlink=Hugh N. Kennedy | publisher = Routledge | location = London and New York | year = 2001 | isbn = 0-415-25093-5 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=UIspERtZEHIC| ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | chapter = Caliphs and Their Chroniclers in the Middle Abbasid Period (Third/Ninth Century) | first = Hugh N. | last = Kennedy | authorlink=Hugh N. Kennedy | pages = 17–35 | title = Texts, Documents, and Artefacts: Islamic Studies in Honour of D.S. Richards | editor-last = Robinson | editor-first = Chase F. | location = Leiden | publisher = BRILL | year = 2003 | isbn = 90-04-12864-6 | chapterurl = https://books.google.com/books?id=axNbLoiLLgMC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PA17#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | title=The Prophet and the Age of the Caliphates: The Islamic Near East from the 6th to the 11th Century | edition = Second | last=Kennedy| first=Hugh N. | authorlink=Hugh N. Kennedy | year=2004a | publisher=Pearson Education Ltd. | location=Harlow, UK |isbn=0-582-40525-4 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=Wux0lWbxs1kC | ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal | title = The Decline and Fall of the First Muslim Empire | first = Hugh N. | last = Kennedy | authorlink=Hugh N. Kennedy | pages = 3–30 | journal = Der Islam | volume = 81 | year = 2004b | issn = 0021-1818 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Kennedy | first = Hugh N. | authorlink = Hugh N. Kennedy | title = When Baghdad Ruled the Muslim World: The Rise and Fall of Islam's Greatest Dynasty | location = Cambridge, MA | publisher = Da Capo Press | year = 2006 | isbn = 978-0-306814808 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=67fZB5YGkOQC | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | title=Baghdad During the Abbasid Caliphate from Contemporary Arabic and Persian Sources | last = Le Strange | first = Guy | url = https://archive.org/details/BaghdadDuringTheAbbasidCaliphateFromContemporaryArabicAndPersian | location = Oxford | publisher = Clarendon Press | year = 1900 | oclc =  257810905 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | title = The Cambridge History of Iran, Volume 4: From the Arab Invasion to the Saljuqs | year = 1975 | publisher = Cambridge University Press | location = Cambridge | editor-last = Frye | editor-first = R. N. | last = Madelung | first = W. | authorlink = Wilferd Madelung | chapter = The Minor Dynasties of Northern Iran | pages = 198–249 | isbn = 978-0-521-20093-6 | chapterurl = https://books.google.com/books?id=hvx9jq_2L3EC| ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal | first = Fedwa | last = Malti-Douglas | title = Texts and Tortures: The Reign of al-Mu'tadid and the Construction of Historical Meaning | journal = Arabica | volume = 46 | year = 1999 | pages = 313–336 | issn = 0570-5398 | ref=harv | doi=10.1163/157005899323288721}}
* {{cite book | last = Mottahedeh | first = Roy | authorlink = Roy Mottahedeh | chapter = The ʿAbbāsid Caliphate in Iran | title = The Cambridge History of Iran, Volume 4: From the Arab Invasion to the Saljuqs | year = 1975 | publisher = Cambridge University Press | location=Cambridge | chapterurl=https://books.google.com/books?id=hvx9jq_2L3EC | editor-first = R. N. | editor-last = Frye |pages=57–89 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite encyclopedia | title = Khumārawaih | first = Moritz | last = Sobernheim | encyclopedia = E.J. Brill's First Encyclopaedia of Islam, 1913–1936, Volume IV: 'Itk–Kwaṭṭa | editor-first = Martijn Theodoor | editor-last = Houtsma | publisher = BRILL | location = Leiden | year = 1987 | isbn = 90-04-08265-4 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=7CP7fYghBFQC&amp;pg=PA973#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false | pages = 973 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Sourdel | first = Dominique | authorlink = Dominique Sourdel | chapter = The ʿAbbasid Caliphate | pages = 104–139 | title=The Cambridge History of Islam, Volume 1A: The Central Islamic Lands from Pre-Islamic Times to the First World War | editor1-last = Holt | editor1-first = P. M. | editor2-last = Lambton | editor2-first = Ann K. S. | editor3-last = Lewis | editor3-first = Bernard | publisher = Cambridge University Press | location = Cambridge | year = 1970 | isbn = 978-0-521-21946-4 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Talbi | first = Muhammad | chapter = Everyday life in the cities of Islam | pages= 379–460 | title = The Different Aspects of Islamic Culture: The Individual and Society in Islam | editor1-first = Abdelwahab | editor1-last = Bouhdiba | editor2-first = Muhammad | editor2-last = Ma'ruf al-Dawalibi | publisher = UNESCO | location = New York | year = 1998 | isbn = 92-3-102742-5 | chapterurl = https://books.google.com/books?id=xek6yZPAQjAC&amp;pg=PA379#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false | ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Treadgold |first=Warren |authorlink=Warren Treadgold |title=A History of the Byzantine State and Society |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=nYbnr5XVbzUC |year=1997 |publisher=Stanford University Press |location=Stanford, California |isbn=0-8047-2630-2 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite encyclopedia | title = al-Muʿtaḍid Bi’llāh | last=Zetterstéen | first=K. V. | authorlink = Karl Vilhelm Zetterstéen | encyclopedia = E.J. Brill's First Encyclopaedia of Islam, 1913–1936, Volume VI: Morocco–Ruzzik | editor-first = Martijn Theodoor | editor-last = Houtsma | publisher = BRILL | location = Leiden | year = 1987 | isbn = 90-04-08265-4 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=fWNpIGNFz0IC&amp;pg=PA777#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false | page = 777 | ref=harv}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-hou|[[Abbasid dynasty]]||c. 854/861||5 April 902}}
{{s-rel|su}}
{{s-bef|before=[[al-Mu'tamid]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[List of caliphs|Caliph of Islam]]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/small&gt;[[Abbasid Caliph]]&lt;/small&gt;|years=October 892 – 5 April 902}}
{{s-aft|after=[[al-Muktafi]]}}
{{end}}
{{Abbasids}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Mu'tadid}}
[[Category:850s births]]
[[Category:902 deaths]]
[[Category:9th-century Abbasid caliphs]]
[[Category:10th-century Abbasid caliphs]]
[[Category:9th-century rulers in Asia]]
[[Category:10th-century rulers in Asia]]
[[Category:Abbasid caliphs]]
[[Category:Abbasid generals]]
[[Category:Arab people of Greek descent]]
[[Category:Baghdad under the Abbasid Caliphate]]
[[Category:Year of birth uncertain]]</text>
      <sha1>mj293x2ew6io9uy94gco9z0aclgei42</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
