<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Australian light destroyer project</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>21856295</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745590088</id>
      <parentid>740767880</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-22T01:40:29Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 1 sources and tagging 0 as dead. #IABot (v1.2.5)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="21897">{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2014}}
{{Use Australian English|date=April 2014}}
{|{{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
|Ship image=[[File:DDL from Navy News September 72.jpg|300px|An artist's impression of the light destroyer design as approved by the Government]]
|Ship caption=An artist's impression of the light destroyer design as approved by the Government in August 1972
}}
{{Infobox ship class overview
|Builders=Williamstown Naval Dockyard (planned) 
|Operators={{Navy|AUS}} (planned)
|Class before=[[Daring-class destroyer (1949)|''Daring''-class destroyer]] and early [[River-class destroyer escort]]
|Class after=[[Adelaide-class frigate|''Adelaide''-class frigate]]
|Built range=1975–1984 (planned)
|In commission range=1980 (planned)
|Total ships planned=10 originally, later 3
|Total ships completed=0
|Total ships cancelled=3
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
|Ship type=Light destroyer
|Ship displacement=4,200 tons
|Ship length={{convert|425|ft|m|1|abbr=on}}
|Ship beam={{convert|48|ft|m|1|abbr=on}}
|Ship draught=
|Ship propulsion=Two shafts each with one [[Rolls-Royce Olympus]] and one [[Rolls-Royce Tyne]] gas turbine&lt;ref name=&quot;Killen_34&quot; /&gt;
|Ship speed={{convert|30|kn}}
|Ship range=Up to {{convert|6000|mi|abbr=on}}&lt;ref&gt;Loxton (1973), p. 21&lt;/ref&gt;
|Ship complement=210
|Ship sensors=Automated combat data system&lt;ref name=&quot;Killen_34&quot; /&gt;
|Ship EW=
|Ship armament=*One [[5&quot;/54 caliber Mark 45 gun|5&quot;/54 calibre Mark 45 gun]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Killen_34&quot;&gt;Killen (1976), p. 34&lt;/ref&gt;
*Six [[Boeing Harpoon|Harpoon]] missiles&lt;ref name=&quot;Killen_34&quot; /&gt;
*Two double-barreled close-range guns
*One [[Mk 13 missile launcher]] and [[RIM-66 Standard|Standard]] anti-aircraft missiles
*Six anti-submarine torpedoes in two triple tube mounts
|Ship aircraft=Two helicopters
|Ship aircraft facilities=Hangar and stern flight deck
|Ship notes=Ship characteristics from Gillett (1988), p. 68&lt;ref name=&quot;Gillett&quot;&gt;Gillett (1988), p. 68&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
|}
The '''Australian light destroyer project''' aimed to build a [[Ship class|class]] of small [[destroyer]]s for the [[Royal Australian Navy]] (RAN). The project began in 1966 with the goal of developing simple light destroyers (DDL) to support [[patrol boat]] operations. The project was rescoped in 1969 when the Navy decided to use the ships to replace other destroyers as they retired, leading to an increase in the design's size and complexity. Concerns over the ships' cost and technological risk led the government to cancel the DDL project in 1973 on the RAN's advice, and a variant of the United States' {{Sclass|Oliver Hazard Perry|frigate|6}} was procured instead.

==Requirement==
From 1963 to 1966, RAN warships [[Military history of Australia during the Indonesia-Malaysia Confrontation|took part]] in the [[Indonesia–Malaysia confrontation|Indonesian Confrontation]]. During this period, Australian [[Minesweeper (ship)|minesweepers]] and [[frigate]]s patrolled Malaysia's coastline to counter Indonesian infiltration parties travelling in small craft. These ships also bombarded Indonesian positions in [[East Kalimantan]] near the border with Malaysia on several occasions. The RAN's experiences during this conflict led it to perceive a need for light destroyers and [[patrol boat]]s tailored to Confrontation-type tasks.&lt;ref&gt;Cooper (2006), pp. 198–200&lt;/ref&gt;

When the DDL project began in 1966, the ships' role was to support [[patrol boat]]s during anti-infiltration operations and complement the Navy's existing destroyer force. The intention was that the DDLs would be fast, simply armed and smaller than conventional destroyers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Loxton_17&quot;&gt;Loxton (1973), p. 17&lt;/ref&gt; It was also hoped that a common DDL [[Hull (watercraft)|hull]] design could be used to produce variants optimised for different roles.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cooper_200&quot;&gt;Cooper (2006), p. 200&lt;/ref&gt; The RAN and British [[Royal Navy]] (RN) held discussions in 1967 on jointly developing DDLs, but the RN withdrew from the project when the Australians insisted on arming the ships with United States-designed weapons.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gillett&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Loxton_17&quot;/&gt;

The DDL design evolved during the late 1960s. As a result of planning conducted during 1967 and 1968, it gradually became clear that the ships would replace rather than complement the Navy's three [[Daring-class destroyer (1949)|''Daring''-class destroyers]] and four early [[River-class destroyer escort]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gillett&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Loxton_17&quot;/&gt; Accordingly, it was specified in 1969 that the DDLs would be more capable and flexible than originally conceived, allowing the RAN to maintain its capabilities as the older destroyers retired. The intended roles for the DDLs' were set in 1970 by an agreement between the RAN and [[Department of Defence (Australia)|Department of Defence]], which specified that the ships were to be capable of destroying equivalent surface warships, carrying out [[Maritime Interdiction Operations|maritime interdiction]] duties, commanding groups of patrol boats and aircraft, have reasonable [[Anti-aircraft warfare|anti-aircraft]] and [[Anti-submarine warfare|anti-submarine]] capabilities and be able to provide [[naval gunfire support]] to land forces.&lt;ref name=&quot;Loxton_17&quot;/&gt;

The RAN originally intended to order up to ten DDLs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gillett&quot;/&gt; All the ships were to be built in Australia to maintain local shipbuilding capabilities, and Australian industry was to be involved to the greatest possible extent.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schaetzel_16&quot;&gt;Schaetzel (1986), p. 16&lt;/ref&gt; Production of the ships was to be evenly split between [[Cockatoo Island (New South Wales)|Cockatoo Island Dockyard]] in Sydney and [[Williamstown, Victoria|Williamstown Naval Dockyard]] in Melbourne.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jeremy_2006_p201&quot;&gt;Jeremy (2006), p. 201&lt;/ref&gt;

==Design==
The DDL design changed considerably over the life of the project. The initial specification was for a 1,000-ton escort vessel&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones_219&quot;&gt;Jones (2006), p. 219.&lt;/ref&gt; and in an early design the class was to have a single {{convert|5|in|mm|0|adj=on}} gun as its primary armament and carry a [[helicopter]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Cooper_200&quot; /&gt; When the Navy Office later prepared an initial sketch design it was for a 2,100-ton ship with a length of {{convert|335|ft|m|1}}, a beam of {{convert|40|ft|m|1}} and a {{convert|32|kn|sing=on}} maximum speed. These DDLs were to be armed with two five-inch guns and operate a single light helicopter.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jeremy_2005_p176&quot;&gt;Jeremy (2005), p. 176&lt;/ref&gt;

After preparing its initial sketch design, the Navy contracted [[Yarrow Shipbuilders|Yarrow Admiralty Research Division]] (Y-ARD) in July 1970 to complete preliminary designs for the DDLs. As an initial stage, Y-ARD was required to develop sketch designs for six different armament configurations using a common hull.&lt;ref name=&quot;Loxton_17&quot; /&gt; Requests for tender for studies on major sub-components were also issued in 1970, and these were completed by mid-1971.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jeremy_2005_p177&quot;&gt;Jeremy (2005), p. 177&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Earnshaw_90&quot; /&gt;

The RAN conducted armament effectiveness studies of each of the six DDL variants in parallel with Y-ARD's development of the designs. These studies found that including an area [[Anti-aircraft warfare|air defence]] capability and an ability to operate two helicopters greatly improved the DDL's effectiveness. As a result, these features were included in the Navy's specification for the DDL design which was issued in late 1970.&lt;ref&gt;Loxton (1973), pp. 17–19&lt;/ref&gt; By this time the design had evolved to specify a general-purpose destroyer of 4,200 tons, armed with a five-inch gun and a [[RIM-24 Tartar|Tartar]] missile launcher, and capable of operating two helicopters. The changes increased the cost of building the ships, and the number planned was reduced to three.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jeremy_2005_p177&quot; /&gt; Nevertheless, the DDL design was considered likely to result in very capable ships, with the 1972–73 edition of ''[[Jane's Fighting Ships]]'' commenting favourably.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schaetzel_16&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Janes&quot;&gt;Blackman (1972), p. 21&lt;/ref&gt;

The changes to the DDL design reflected shifting requirements and poor project management by the Navy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones_219&quot; /&gt; The development of an Australian-designed ship customised for Australian conditions caused naval officers to include requirements beyond those which were essential.&lt;ref name=&quot;Earnshaw_90&quot;&gt;Earnshaw (1999), p. 90&lt;/ref&gt; These changes were made without regard for costs, as the team tasked with developing the specifications was not also responsible for the ships' final price and delivery schedule.&lt;ref&gt;Senate Foreign Affairs, Defence and Trade Committee (2006), p. 43&lt;/ref&gt; The Navy's failure to maintain control of the design requirements and make cost-performance trade-offs may have been due to its limited experience in overseeing the design of new warships.&lt;ref name=&quot;Earnshaw_90&quot; /&gt;

==Cancellation==
Despite the changes to the design and its growing costs, construction of three DDLs was approved by the [[Liberal Party of Australia|Liberal Party]] [[McMahon Government]] in August 1972.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gillett&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Earnshaw_90&quot; /&gt; At this time, the total project cost was estimated at A$355 million; this figure included all costs associated with building three ships and operating them for ten years. The ships themselves were expected to cost approximately $210 million.&lt;ref&gt;Willis (1972), p. 26&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;DDL team to be withdrawn&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Cranston |first=Frank |url=http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article110749064 |title=DDL team to be withdrawn |newspaper=The Canberra Times|date=24 September 1973 |accessdate=9 March 2015 |page=6 |publisher=National Library of Australia}}&lt;/ref&gt; All three ships were to be built at Williamstown Dockyard, with construction of the first ship beginning in 1975, followed by the other ships at two-yearly intervals.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones_219&quot; /&gt; The initial DDL was to be commissioned in 1980, and the third in 1984.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gillett&quot; /&gt; Further DDLs may also have been ordered over time to replace the Navy's destroyers as they reached the end of their service lives.&lt;ref name=&quot;Earnshaw_89&quot;&gt;Earnshaw (1999), p. 89&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cranston Smaller ships no DDL substitute&quot; /&gt;

The DDL design was not supported by the [[Australian Labor Party]] (ALP) opposition, which believed that the ships would be too large and expensive for escort, patrol and surveillance duties.&lt;ref name=&quot;Earnshaw_91&quot;&gt;Earnshaw (1999), p. 91&lt;/ref&gt; In June 1972 ''[[The Australian Quarterly]]'' published an article by the shadow minister for Defence, [[Lance Barnard]], in which he argued that &quot;the DDL concept goes completely against trends in the development of vessels for maritime warfare&quot;, and that the high cost of the warships would mean that not enough would be purchased to meet the RAN's requirements. Barnard suggested that if the DDL project was cancelled the RAN's needs could be met at a lower cost by selecting from one of several existing foreign designs for smaller, but just as well armed, destroyers and building these ships under licence in Australia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Cranston |first=Frank |url=http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article101999423 |title=Light destroyer idea challenged |newspaper=The Canberra Times|date=16 August 1972 |accessdate=9 March 2015 |page=2 |publisher=National Library of Australia}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Barnard (1972), p. 17&lt;/ref&gt; The Minister for the Navy, [[Malcolm Mackay]], rejected Barnard's criticisms in August 1972 and stated that studies carried out by the Navy and Department of Defence had found that smaller and less heavily armed ships would not be able to fill the roles intended for the DDLs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cranston Smaller ships no DDL substitute&quot;&gt;{{cite news |last=Cranston |first=Frank |url=http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article101999695 |title=Smaller ships 'no DDL substitute'. |newspaper=The Canberra Times|date=17 August 1972 |accessdate=10 March 2015 |page=3 |publisher=National Library of Australia}}&lt;/ref&gt; Barnard became Minister for Defence following the election of the ALP [[Whitlam Government]] in December 1972, and directed in January 1973 that the DDL project be reviewed. This review considered the feasibility of the project, including its budget and timeline, as well as the suitability of comparable American, British and Dutch warships.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Cranston |first=Frank |url=http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article110702727 |title=$355m navy plan under review |newspaper=The Canberra Times|date=17 January 1973 |accessdate=9 March 2015 |page=3 |publisher=National Library of Australia}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:HMS Coventry D118.jpg|thumb|left|The British [[Type 42 destroyer|Type 42]] was one of the designs considered after the DDL project was cancelled]]

Increasing costs and concerns over the ships' design led to the cancellation of the DDL project. The Department of Defence observed that the DDL's costs were escalating and it was unable to finalise the design. The Navy also reviewed the project and found that it was unduly expensive, and a Joint Parliamentary committee concluded that a unique Australian design entailed significant technological risks.&lt;ref&gt;Senate Foreign Affairs, Defence and Trade Committee (2006), pp. 42–43&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, the Navy recommended to the Government that the DDL project be cancelled, and this took place in August 1973.&lt;ref name=&quot;Earnshaw_90&quot; /&gt; The cost of the project to the Navy had been A$1.7 million, most of which was spent on design investigations and management consultancies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.navy.gov.au/w/images/Navy_News-August-31-1973.pdf |title=Effect on the Navy |date=31 August 1973 |work=Navy News |publisher=Royal Australian Navy |page=2 |accessdate=22 March 2009 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110321020159/http://www.navy.gov.au/w/images/Navy_News-August-31-1973.pdf |archivedate=21 March 2011 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; The opposition Liberal Party opposed the decision to cancel the DDL project.&lt;ref name=&quot;Australia to buy US warships&quot; /&gt;

The DDL project's problems harmed the Australian shipbuilding industry. The cancellation of both the DDLs and another project to develop an Australian [[fast combat support ship]] design led to a perception that technical risks needed to be minimised when selecting new warships, and it was preferable to rely on proven foreign designs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jeremy_2006_p201&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Jeremy_2005_p178&quot;&gt;Jeremy (2005), p. 178&lt;/ref&gt; Australian industry was also left with a bad impression as companies involved in the project had devoted considerable resources to preparing tenders for the DDL.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schaetzel_17&quot;&gt;Schaetzel (1986), p. 17&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:USS Oliver Hazard Perry FFG-7.jpg|thumb|The United States' {{Sclass|Oliver Hazard Perry|frigate|0}} was the other option to replace the DDL project, and the design selected by the Australians.]]

Despite cancelling the DDL project, the government endorsed the RAN's requirement for new destroyer-type warships and requested a review of existing foreign designs to find a replacement.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones_220&quot;&gt;Jones (2006), p. 220&lt;/ref&gt; The process of evaluating new designs was managed by what had been the DDL project office, and in line with the government's priorities it initially focused on selecting affordable warships of a proven design for further consideration.&lt;ref name=&quot;Berlyn_13&quot;&gt;Berlyn and Hurt (1981), p. 13&lt;/ref&gt; A large number of designs were studied by the project office, and the United States' {{Sclass|Oliver Hazard Perry|frigate|6}}s and a variant of the British [[Type 42 destroyer]] armed with [[RIM-66 Standard|SM-1 surface to air missiles]] were eventually short listed for detailed evaluation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones_220&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Berlyn_14&quot;&gt;Berlyn and Hurt (1981), p. 14&lt;/ref&gt; The project team found that the Type 42 was the only design capable of meeting the Navy's requirement, and stated that the ''Oliver Hazard Perry'' class was &quot;a second rate escort that falls short of the DDL requirements on virtually every respect&quot;. Despite this, there were serious concerns over whether it would be possible to fit SM-1 missiles to the Type 42, and this led the government to approve the purchase of two ''Oliver Hazard Perry'' ships from the United States in April 1974.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones_220&quot; /&gt;

The DDL project was reviewed again when the Liberal [[Fraser Government]] came into office in late 1975. The review panel unanimously advised the new Minister for Defence [[James Killen]] that the DDL project was no longer viable as the total cost of the ships would be about $130 million higher than the ''Oliver Hazard Perry'' project, and it would take three years longer for the DDLs to be completed. Killen accepted this advice, and a firm order for two ''Oliver Hazard Perry'' frigates was placed in February 1976. A third ship was ordered in late 1977.&lt;ref name=&quot;Australia to buy US warships&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article110803483 |title=Australia to buy US warships |newspaper=The Canberra Times |location=ACT |date=19 February 1976 |accessdate=9 March 2015 |page=11 |publisher=National Library of Australia}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones_220&quot; /&gt; Six of these frigates, which were designated the {{Sclass|Adelaide|frigate|6}}, were eventually ordered, and the final two were built in Australia at Williamstown.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones_224&quot;&gt;Jones (2006), p. 224&lt;/ref&gt; The expertise of the DDL project office and the preparations which had been undertaken to manage the process of ordering and building the ships contributed to the Navy's ability to rapidly evaluate alternative designs and oversee their entry into service once an order was placed.&lt;ref&gt;Berlyn and Hurt (1981), pp. 20–21&lt;/ref&gt;
{{clear}}

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==Bibliography==
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite journal|last1=Barnard|first1=Lance|title=Destroyer Procurement and Naval Policy|journal=The Australian Quarterly|date=June 1972|volume=44|issue=2|pages=9–17}}
*{{cite journal|last=Berlyn|first=N.R.B|author2=Hurt, RCM|title=The Introduction of Guided Missile Frigates into the RAN|journal=Defence Force Journal|date=September–October 1981|issue=30|pages=11–25|url=http://www.adfjournal.adc.edu.au/UserFiles/issues/30%201981%20Sep_Oct.pdf}}
* {{cite book|editor=Blackman, Raymond V.B.|title=Jane's Fighting Ships 1972–73|publisher=Sampson, Low, Marston &amp; Co|location=London|year=1972|series=Jane's Year Books|isbn=978-0-07-032161-8}}
* {{cite book|last=Cooper|first=Alastair|title=The Royal Australian Navy. A History|editor=Stevens, David|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Melbourne|year=2006|edition=Paperback|chapter=1955–1972: The Era of Forward Defence|isbn=978-0-19-555542-4}}
* {{cite web|url=http://naa12.naa.gov.au/scripts/ItemDetail.asp?M=0&amp;B=4939393|title=New Australian Naval Destroyer proposal – Decision 1051 and 1090(ADHOC)|last=Department of Defence|year=1972|work=Cabinet Submission 14&amp;nbsp;June 1972|publisher=National Archives of Australia|accessdate=22 March 2009}}
* {{cite book|last=Earnshaw|first=Paul|title=Arming the Nation|editor=Cain, Frank|publisher=Australian Defence Studies Centre|location=Canberra|year=1999|chapter=Shaping Naval Shipbuilding in Australia|isbn=0-7317-0433-9}}
* {{cite book|last=Gillett|first=Ross|title=Australian &amp; New Zealand Warships Since 1946|publisher=Child &amp; Associates|location=Sydney|year=1988|isbn=0-86777-219-0}}
* {{cite book|last=Jeremy|first=John|title=Cockatoo Island: Sydney's Historic Dockyard|publisher=UNSW Press|location=Sydney|year=2005|isbn=0-86840-817-4|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=1ulc79wlY54C&amp;pg=PA178&amp;lpg=PA178&amp;dq=Australian+DDL+ship#PPA177,M1}}
* {{cite book|last=Jeremy|first=John|title=Navy and the Nation: The Influence of the Navy on Modern Australia|editor=Stevens, David |editor2=Reeve, John|publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin|location=Sydney|year=2006|chapter=Australian Shipbuilding and the Impact of the Second World War|isbn=1-74114-200-8|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=BGs6__kbqKIC&amp;pg=PA201&amp;lpg=PA201&amp;dq=Australian+DDL+ship}}
* {{cite book|last=Jones|first=Peter|title=The Royal Australian Navy. A History|editor=Stevens, David|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Melbourne|year=2006|edition=Paperback|chapter=1972–1983: Towards Self-Reliance|isbn=978-0-19-555542-4}}
* {{cite web|url=http://naa12.naa.gov.au/scripts/ItemDetail.asp?M=0&amp;B=7426304|title=Submission No 85 : Destroyer acquisition – Decision 240|last=Killen|first=James|year=1976|work=Cabinet Submission 6&amp;nbsp;February 1976|publisher=National Archives of Australia|accessdate=22 March 2009}}
* {{cite book|last=Loxton|first=B.H.|title=Royal Australian Navy. A Survey of Future Needs August 1972|publisher=The Parliament of the Commonwealth of Australia|location=Canberra|year=1973|series=Parliamentary Paper No. 138|chapter=Development of the DDL Concept}}
* {{cite book|author1=Senate Foreign Affairs |author2=Defence and Trade Committee |title=Blue water ships: consolidating past achievements|publisher=Commonwealth of Australia|location=Canberra|year=2006|isbn=0-642-71736-2|url=http://www.aph.gov.au/senate/committee/FADT_CTTE/completed_inquiries/2004-07/shipping/report/index.htm}}
* {{cite book|last=Schaetzel|first=Stanley S.|title=Local Development of Defence Hardware in Australia|publisher=Research School of Pacific Studies, Australian National University|location=Canberra|year=1986|series=The Strategic and Defence Studies Centre Working Paper No. 100|isbn=0-86784-845-6}}
* {{cite book|last=Willis|first=G.J.|title=Royal Australian Navy. A Survey of Future Needs August 1972|publisher=The Parliament of the Commonwealth of Australia|location=Canberra|year=1973|series=Parliamentary Paper No. 138|chapter=The DDL Project}}
{{refend}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Australian Light Destroyer Project}}
[[Category:Destroyer classes]]
[[Category:Destroyers of the Royal Australian Navy|Light Destroyer]]
[[Category:Abandoned military projects of Australia]]</text>
      <sha1>ps0f3l2o8ncy9sfoft7u50b2f90urmj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
