<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of Porton Plantation</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>24898353</id>
    <revision>
      <id>739107376</id>
      <parentid>726145143</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-12T20:26:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GreenC bot</username>
        <id>27823944</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[User:Green Cardamom/WaybackMedic 2|WaybackMedic 2]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="37882">{{good article}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Battle of Porton Plantation
| partof      = the [[Pacific War|Pacific theatre]] of [[World War II]]
| image       = [[File:4 Field Regiment firing on Porton.jpg|250px|alt=Men stand and kneel behind an artillery gun set behind a wall of logs in a jungle setting]]
| caption     = 25 pounder guns from the Australian 4th Field Regiment fire upon Japanese positions near Porton Plantation, June 1945
| date        = 8–10 June 1945&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Davidson|2005|p=vii}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
| place       = [[Bougainville Island|Bougainville]], [[Territory of New Guinea|New Guinea]]
| result      = Japanese victory
| combatant1  = {{flagicon|Australia}} Australia&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|New Zealand}} New Zealand
| combatant2  = {{flagicon|Japan}} Japan
| commander1  = John Stevenson &lt;br&gt; Joseph Kelly &lt;br&gt; Clyde Downs
| commander2  = [[Eikichi Kato]]
| units1      = [[31st/51st Battalion (Australia)|31st/51st Infantry Battalion]]
| units2      = 87th Naval Garrison Force
| strength1   = 190 infantrymen&lt;br&gt;Artillery and air support
| strength2   = 400–500 infantrymen
| casualties1 = 23 killed, 106 wounded
| casualties2 = 26 killed
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Bougainville}}
}}

The '''Battle of Porton Plantation''' (8–10 June 1945) took place near the village of [[Soraken]] on [[Bougainville Island]], in the [[Solomon Islands (archipelago)|Solomon Islands archipelago]] during [[World War II]]. Involving forces from Australia, New Zealand and Japan, the battle was part of the wider [[Bougainville campaign]], which had begun in late 1943 and lasted until the end of the war in August 1945. The battle formed part of Australian efforts to liberate the northern part of Bougainville.

The fighting occurred after a [[Company (military unit)|company]]-sized Australian force from the [[31st Battalion (Australia)|31st/51st Infantry Battalion]] made an amphibious landing north of the Porton Plantation{{#tag:ref|The Japanese name for this was &quot;Moton&quot;.&lt;ref name=Tanaka296&gt;{{harvnb|Tanaka|1980|p=296}}.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=Note}} [[Jetty|jetties]] in an attempt to outflank the Japanese positions on the [[Battle of Ratsua|Ratsua]] front, which were holding up the advance of the [[26th Battalion (Australia)|26th]] and the 31st/51st Infantry Battalions from the [[11th Brigade (Australia)|11th Brigade]]. The Australians landed unopposed and established a small perimeter, but some of their landing craft ran aground and they were unable to bring their heavy weapons and support elements ashore. Troops from the Japanese 87th Naval Garrison Force quickly surrounded the beachhead and, as their supply situation grew desperate, the Australians were forced to withdraw. In the course of their evacuation by sea another landing craft ran aground. Over the next two days several unsuccessful rescue attempts were made until eventually, in the early morning of 11 June, the last Australian survivors were picked up.

The battle was a victory for the Japanese and it proved instrumental in helping them to regain the initiative in the northern sector of Bougainville. As a result, shortly afterwards the Australian forces on Bougainville changed the focus of their operations to the southern sector of the island where they were able to advance along the coastal plain towards the main Japanese position at [[Buin, Papua New Guinea|Buin]]. Since the end of the war, there has been considerable criticism of the planning undertaken by the Australians prior to the operation, and it has been argued that the operation failed due to poor intelligence and lack of resources and was ultimately unnecessary.

==Background==

===Strategic situation===
Japanese forces had [[Invasion of Buka and Bougainville|landed on Bougainville]] in early 1942, capturing it from the small force of Australians garrisoning the island. They had subsequently developed several airbases on the island, using it to conduct operations in the northern [[Solomon Islands]] and to attack the Allied [[lines of communication]] between the United States, Australia and the Southwest Pacific Area.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Keogh|1965|p=414}}.&lt;/ref&gt; These bases also helped protect [[Rabaul]], the major Japanese garrison and naval base in Papua New Guinea, and throughout 1943, Allied planners determined that Bougainville was vital for neutralising the Japanese base around Rabaul.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Rentz|1946| p=1}}.&lt;/ref&gt; US Marines conducted an [[Landings at Cape Torokina|amphibious landing at Cape Torokina]], on the western coast of the island, north of [[Empress Augusta Bay]], in November 1943. After an initial counter-attack which had been repulsed, the US Marines had been replaced by a garrison of US Army troops who began consolidating their position around Torokina, establishing a strong perimeter. In March 1944, the Japanese launched a [[Bougainville counterattack|heavy counter-attack]], which was turned back with many casualties. After this, the situation on Bougainville became largely static, as the Japanese focused primarily on subsistence, and the US forces chose to adopt a mainly defensive posture focused on maintaining the perimeter around Torokina.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|James|2012|pp=29–30}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Shindo|2016|pp=61–63}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Map nw bougainville 1945.jpg|thumb|upright=0.9|right|North-west Bougainville.|alt=A detailed map showing the north-western coast line of an island. Several harbours are depicted, along with various locations]]

On 22 November 1944, the [[II Corps (Australia)|Australian II Corps]], consisting mainly of [[Australian Army Reserve|Militia]] troops under the command of [[Lieutenant General (Australia)|Lieutenant General]] [[Stanley Savige]], took over responsibility for Allied operations on Bougainville from the US [[XIV Corps (United States)|XIV Corps]]. Throughout November and December Australian units began relieving the Americans who were then redeployed on [[Philippines Campaign (1944–45)|subsequent operations in the Philippines]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Keogh|1965|p= 416}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Although Japanese forces on Bougainville actually numbered around 40,000 men at the time,&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Grey|2008|p=191}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Allied intelligence failed to determine this accurately, estimating that there were only about 17,500 defenders. As a result of this error, Australian planning staff believed that they were opposed by a roughly equal-sized force and the Australian corps commander, Savige, under orders from [[General (Australia)|General]] [[Thomas Blamey]], commander-in-chief of the Australian Military Forces during the war, to &quot;destroy... [Japanese]...resistance...without committing major forces&quot; and limiting casualties, consequently decided that he would pursue a limited offensive campaign to clear the Japanese from Bougainville.&lt;ref name=Johnston30&gt;{{harvnb|Johnston|2007|p= 30}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=James2016_234&gt;{{harvnb|James|2016|p=234}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The majority of the Japanese force was believed to be concentrated in the south and as a result the main effort of the Australian plan was focused upon driving towards [[Buin, Papua New Guinea|Buin]]. Supporting operations were also conducted along two other fronts. In the north, it was planned that the Japanese would be forced into the narrow [[Bonis Peninsula]] and contained there while, in the centre, the [[Battle of Pearl Ridge|seizure of Pearl Ridge]] would give the Australians control of the east–west avenues of approach, as well as affording them protection against further [[counter-attack]]s and opening the way for a drive to the east coast.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Johnston|2007|pp=30–31}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The Australian troops were largely inexperienced, but were according to historian Karl James &quot;fresh...[and] well equipped&quot;. For their part, according to James, the Japanese force on Bougainville had been &quot;...reinforced from Rabual with troops, weapons and equipment&quot; and although much of 1944 had been spent foraging and establishing food supplies on the island, there was only &quot;enough food reserves for four months&quot;.&lt;ref name=James2016_234/&gt;

The build up of Australian forces was hampered by a lack of resources, which were focused largely upon the US operations in the Philippines,&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|James|2016|p=38}}.&lt;/ref&gt; and Australian operations in Borneo, which was considered the priority, and ultimately these considerations would impact upon Australian strategy upon the island due to the limited amount of amphibious support available.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Grant|2016|p=226}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Dennis et al|1995|p=429}}.&lt;/ref&gt; After initial moves by the Australians to take over the US perimeter at Torokina and garrison the Outer Islands in September and October, in November the Australians took over officially from the Americans. Later that month, troops from the [[7th Brigade (Australia)|7th Brigade]] left the perimeter and took over from the small US forces holding outposts along the Numa Numa Trail in the centre of the island. From there, a couple of minor skirmishes followed culminating in the Battle of Pearl Ridge.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|James|2016|pp=235–236}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In late December, the [[11th Brigade (Australia)|11th Brigade]], under the command of [[Brigadier (Australia)|Brigadier]] John Stevenson, took over control of the northern sector of the island from the 7th Brigade, which was transferred to the southern sector to take part in the main offensive. Throughout January, as part of efforts to liberate the northern part of the island, the brigade advanced north along the coast from Kuraio Mission, clearing the main settlements while sending patrols inland in an effort to flush out the Japanese from the high features in an effort to draw them into fighting in the open.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Long|1963|p=122}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In mid-January the lead Australian battalion, the [[31st/51st Battalion (Australia)|31st/51st Infantry Battalion]], under the command of [[Lieutenant Colonel (Australia)|Lieutenant Colonel]] Joseph Kelly, came up against a strong Japanese position at [[Battle of Tsimba Ridge|Tsimba Ridge]]{{#tag:ref|The Japanese name for this feature was &quot;Sun Highland&quot;.&lt;ref name=Tanaka296/&gt;|group=Note}} and over the course of three weeks fought to gain control of the feature. The Australians lost 23 killed and 53 wounded while the Japanese had at least 66 men killed.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Long|1963|p=125}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Preliminary moves===

Following the fighting on Tsimba Ridge, the 31st/51st was relieved by the [[26th Battalion (Australia)|26th Infantry Battalion]], and the Australians continued to advance north towards Soraken. Over the course of several months, the 26th advanced on several axes: from Downs' Ridge they crossed the Nagam River, while on the coast another element advanced though Lalum to the Compton River. Between these two forces, another linked up with those that had crossed the Nagam, and proceeded north over the Compton towards Soraken Plantation. Elsewhere, barges were used to land forces on the Soraken Peninsula in several locations to dislocate the Japanese forces there and sever their lines of communication, while other landings took place on Saposa Island and Torokori Island.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|James|2012|p=120}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|James|2016|p=240}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In April, the 26th was relieved by the [[55th/53rd Battalion (Australia)|55th/53rd Infantry Battalion]] which advanced north to Ratsua,{{#tag:ref|The Japanese name for this was &quot;Tasui&quot;.&lt;ref name=Tanaka296/&gt;|group=Note}} from where the Australians planned to move along the Bonis Peninsula. By late May, however, casualties amongst the 55th/53rd meant that they had to be withdrawn from the line, and the 26th Infantry Battalion was moved back up to replace them, along with the 31st/51st.&lt;ref name=Maitland120121&gt;{{harvnb|Maitland|1999|pp=120–121}}.&lt;/ref&gt; At the start of June the Australians were stretched out across a {{convert|5|mi|km|adj=on}} line between Ratsua to Ruri Bay.&lt;ref name=Lawie44&gt;{{harvnb|Lawie|2001|p= 44}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Bougainville 1945.jpg|thumb|right|alt=Military officers discuss a tactical situation around a map |Australian commanders on Bougainville, May 1945]]

On 4 June, the 31st/51st Infantry Battalion began patrolling operations around Buoi Plantation. Two companies, 'B' and 'D', were committed to these operations with 'B' Company focusing upon the north-eastern part of the plantation, while 'D' Company patrolled to their east.&lt;ref name=Burla166&gt;{{harvnb|Burla| 2005|p=166}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Clashes followed over the next three days; the Australians lost one killed, and the Japanese 10.&lt;ref name=Burla166/&gt; Australian intelligence suggested that the Japanese had concentrated strongly along the approaches to the peninsula, and in order to deal with these positions it was decided that an amphibious landing would be made by a company of the 31st/51st Infantry Battalion near the [[Jetty|jetties]] around Porton Plantation, {{convert|3.1|mi|km}} to the north of Ratusa,&lt;ref name=Lawie44/&gt; to outflank them and launch an attack from the rear, while the main force&amp;nbsp;– consisting of the remainder of the 31st/51st and the 26th Infantry Battalion&amp;nbsp;– pushed north from the Ratsua front to establish a new position along a line between Porton and Chindawon.&lt;ref name=Maitland120121/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|James|2005|p=175}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|James|2012|p=127}}.&lt;/ref&gt; During the planning phase, concerns were raised by several officers about the size of the force allocated and the distance that the breakthrough force would be required to advance to link up with the force landing at the beachhead, but these were ultimately discounted.&lt;ref name=Davidson31_39&gt;{{harvnb|Davidson|2005|pp=31–39}}.&lt;/ref&gt; On the evening of 5 June, the Australian battalion commander outlined his plan and in the afternoon of the following day rehearsal landings were undertaken. Final preparations were made on the night of 6/7 June and continued throughout the next day.&lt;ref name=Burla167&gt;{{harvnb|Burla|2005|p=167}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Opposing forces===
The Australian landing force consisted of 190 men embarked on six [[Assault Landing Craft|landing craft]]. The bulk of the force was made up of [[infantry]] from 'A' Company and a [[platoon]] from 'C' Company, 31st/51st Infantry Battalion under the command of [[Captain (Australia)|Captain]] Clyde Downs. [[Artillery]] support was provided by the 11th and 12th Batteries of the [[4th Field Regiment, Royal Australian Artillery|4th Field Regiment]] and the [[2nd Mountain Battery (Australia)|2nd Mountain Battery]].&lt;ref name=Burke6&gt;{{harvnb|Burke|2006|p=6}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Other supporting units included engineers from the 16th Field Company and 42nd Assault Landing Craft Company, medical support from the 19th Field Ambulance and logistics support from the 223rd Supply Platoon.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Davidson|2005|p=172}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Although aerial reconnaissance indicated that there were strong Japanese fortifications in the area, initially no air support was allocated to the operation,&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Charlton|1983|p=56}}.&lt;/ref&gt; with requests for preliminary air strikes being denied by II Corps as they were, according to James, not &quot;considered to be suitable air targets&quot;.&lt;ref name=James191&gt;{{harvnb|James|2005|pp=129 &amp; 191}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The Japanese force in the immediate vicinity initially consisted of about 100 men from the [[Imperial Japanese Navy]]'s 87th Naval Garrison Force which had been formed from men drawn from the 211th Pioneer Unit interspersed with regular naval personnel.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Burla|2005|p=165}}.&lt;/ref&gt; However, over the course of the battle the strength of the Japanese force grew to between 400 and 500 men.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Long|1963|pp=210–215}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Burla|2005|pp=168–171}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The Japanese force was commanded by the senior naval officer at [[Buka, Papua New Guinea|Buka]], [[Captain (naval)|Captain]] [[Eikichi Kato]],&lt;ref name=Long215&gt;{{harvnb|Long|1963|p=215}}.&lt;/ref&gt; whose 87th Naval Garrison Force had taken over responsibility for the defence of the Tarlena area{{#tag:ref|The Japanese name for this area was &quot;Tarina&quot;.&lt;ref name=Tanaka296/&gt;|group=Note}} when the [[Imperial Japanese Army]]'s [[38th Independent Mixed Brigade (Imperial Japanese Army)|38th Independent Mixed Brigade]] was transferred south to the [[Numa Numa Trail|Numa Numa]] area.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Tanaka|1980|p=297}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battle==

===Initial landing and fighting around the beachhead===
At 3:57&amp;nbsp;am on 8 June the first wave of Australian troops landed on the beach in three landing craft. They came ashore unopposed and after advancing about {{convert|100|yd|m}} inland established a small perimeter around the beachhead in the tree line surrounding the plantation.&lt;ref name=Burla167/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Long|1963|pp=210–211}}.&lt;/ref&gt; A series of forward positions were then established a further {{convert|50|yd|m}} inland.&lt;ref name=Burla167/&gt; Instead of pushing his rifle platoons further inland, however, Downs decided that he would wait for the second wave to arrive. This ultimately proved critical as it allowed the Japanese commander, Kato, time to respond to the landing.&lt;ref name=James179&gt;{{harvnb|James|2005|p= 179}}.&lt;/ref&gt; As the three landing craft of the first wave withdrew, another three landing craft came in with reinforcements, heavy weapons and other support elements, however, they ran aground on a coral reef and the men aboard were forced to wade ashore. Although one of these craft was later able to float free, two of the others remained stuck. A short time later they began to take fire from Japanese machine-guns, which stopped the Australians from unloading their equipment.&lt;ref name=Maitland121&gt;{{harvnb|Maitland|1999|p=121}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Long211&gt;{{harvnb|Long|1963|p=211}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Porton jetty (AWM image P02729 008).jpg|thumb|left|An aerial photograph showing the landing beach and jetty at Porton Plantation in May 1945.|alt=An aerial photograph showing a cleared area of beach, with the words &quot;Porton jetty&quot; labelled in pencil with an arrow.]]

Lacking organic indirect fire support as all the mortars had been in the landing craft that were in the second wave,&lt;ref name=Long211/&gt; Downs established communications with the artillery, and a barrage was brought down on suspected Japanese positions by the artillery [[forward observation officer]], [[Lieutenant (Australia)|Lieutenant]] David Spark,&lt;ref name=Burke6/&gt; with the assistance of a [[Royal Australian Air Force]] (RAAF) [[CAC Boomerang|Boomerang]] that was on station overhead to provide aerial observation.&lt;ref name=James179/&gt; By dawn, Downs' company was taking sporadic fire from Japanese pill boxes, and they began patrolling forward of their perimeter to locate these positions. These patrols were unable to progress very far before they were forced back by Japanese fire, which confirmed how bad the company's position was.&lt;ref name=James180&gt;{{harvnb|James|2005|p=180}}.&lt;/ref&gt; They determined that they had landed about {{convert|270|yd|m}} north of where they had been supposed to land,&lt;ref name=Burke6/&gt; and inside what the official historian [[Gavin Long]] described as an &quot;arc of enemy trenches and pill-boxes with a radius of about 400 yards&quot;&lt;ref name=Long211/&gt; that effectively boxed them in.&lt;ref name=James180/&gt;

Throughout the day the defenders began pressing against the Australian forward positions and engaging them with mortar fire as more reinforcements were brought up.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Davidson|2005|p=66}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly after the landing, Kato was able to concentrate a force of about 100 Japanese defenders in the immediate vicinity,&lt;ref name=Long211/&gt; however, throughout the day he was able to bring in further reinforcements and by nightfall there were approximately 300 Japanese around the Australian perimeter. In order to respond, an attempt was made by the Australians to bring in reinforcements of their own and supplies by sea. Due to the low tide and heavy fire from the beach, the attempt failed, as did two subsequent attempts,&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Long|1963|p=212}}.&lt;/ref&gt; as the Japanese commander pre-empted their arrival and set up ambushes along the approaches north and south of the landing beach.&lt;ref name=James183&gt;{{harvnb|James|2005|p=183}}.&lt;/ref&gt; While the fighting was going on around Porton, beginning on 4 June, the 26th Infantry Battalion and the rest of the 31st/51st Infantry  Battalion attempted to break through to the Australian company from Ratsua. They were unable to penetrate the Japanese lines;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb |31st/51st Battalion (Kennedy and Far North Queensland Regiment) |}}&lt;/ref&gt; however, as they came up against defenders that were determined to resist because they were unable to withdraw any further along the peninsula.&lt;ref name=James192&gt;{{harvnb|James|2005|p=192}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|James|2012|p=145}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Australian evacuation efforts===
By the morning of 9 June, the supply situation for Downs' company had become critical and 11th Brigade headquarters decided that it would be best to evacuate the beach. Up until that point casualties had been relatively light with only four killed and seven wounded, but the Japanese force, which had increased overnight to between 400 and 500 men as reinforcements arrived by barges and trucks from the Buka Passage area,&lt;ref name=Lawie45&gt;{{harvnb|Lawie|2001|p=45}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|James|2005|pp=181–183}}.&lt;/ref&gt; launched a strong attack aimed at destroying the Australian force, attacking from three sides of the perimeter. In order to defend themselves the Australians called down heavy artillery fire from the [[Artillery battery|battery]] of [[Ordnance QF 25 pounder|25-pounders]] that was supporting them from its position on the Soraken peninsula.&lt;ref name=Lawie45/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Davidson|2005|p=62}}.&lt;/ref&gt; As the fighting intensified, some of the artillery shells were brought down as close as {{convert|25|yd|m}} from their own troops. Air support was also called in, with 16 RAAF Boomerangs and [[Royal New Zealand Air Force]] [[F4U Corsair|Corsairs]] attacking Japanese positions around the perimeter.&lt;ref name=Burke7&gt;{{harvnb|Burke|2006|p=7}}.&lt;/ref&gt; As a result of these attacks, the Australians were able to hold off the Japanese attacks until 4:30&amp;nbsp;pm when three [[Landing Craft Assault|assault landing craft]] arrived from Soraken to take them off the beach,&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Davidson|2005|p=86}}.&lt;/ref&gt; and ferry them out to two larger vessels that were waiting further out to sea.&lt;ref name=James184&gt;{{harvnb|James|2005|p=184}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:31st 51st Bn patrol at Porton Plantation June 1945.jpg|thumb|right|Men from the 31st/51st Infantry Battalion about to go out on patrol towards Porton Plantation from the Ratsua front, 9 June 1945.|alt=Soldiers sitting on stores boxes at a military camp surrounded by thick jungle]]

Amid a torrent of Japanese fire, the Australians broke contact and made for the landing craft, bringing the wounded out with them. The embarkation took only five minutes, but as the vessels attempted to depart two of them, overloaded with about 60 men on board, ran aground and stuck fast.&lt;ref name=Long213&gt;{{harvnb|Long|1963|p=213}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In an effort to lighten the load, several men volunteered to leave the craft, which enabled one of the vessels to float free.&lt;ref name=Burke7/&gt; The other, however, remained stuck. Coming under attack from the Japanese, some of whom waded out and attacked the men in the vessel with grenades, the casualties mounted, with a number of men, including Downs, being either killed or lost overboard and subsequently listed as missing, presumed killed.&lt;ref name=Long213/&gt;

As rations and water dwindled, unsuccessful attempts were made on 10 June to rescue the men in the stranded barge with support from artillery and aircraft. While Corsairs flew close support missions, [[Bristol Beaufort|Beaufort]] and [[North American B-25 Mitchell|Mitchell]] bombers dropped life rafts but the survivors were unable to reach them due to machine-gun fire.&lt;ref name=Lawie47&gt;{{harvnb|Lawie|2001|p=47}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Burla174&gt;{{harvnb|Burla|2005|p=174}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Further casualties occurred when, in the early morning of 11 June, a Japanese soldier managed to reach the vessel and fired upon the occupants with a machine-gun, killing two and wounding others before he was killed himself. Shortly after this a Japanese [[anti-tank gun]] fired two shells at the landing craft, destroying its stern. Further shots were prevented when Australian artillery ranged in on the gun, having been directed by Captain [[John Whitelaw (1921–2010)|John Whitelaw]],&lt;ref name=Burke7/&gt; an artillery observer on one of two landing craft that had been despatched with [[canvas]] assault boats, crewed by engineers from the 16th Field Company.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Long|1963|p=214}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Launching {{convert|150|yd|m}} from the stranded craft, three assault boats set out and over the course of two hours ferried the survivors back to the landing craft, which then set out for Soraken, arriving there at 4:30&amp;nbsp;am on 11 June.&lt;ref name=Long215/&gt; Other men swam over {{convert|5|km|mi}} through the shark-infested waters to Torokori Island,&lt;ref name=Burke7/&gt;&lt;ref name=Lawie47/&gt; while others were either rescued at sea or managed to link up with the Australians along the Ratsua front, who had been attempting to break through to them but found themselves checked {{convert|500|yd|m}} from them,&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Hughes|1993|pp=253–254}}.&lt;/ref&gt; by sneaking through the Japanese lines from the rear.&lt;ref name=Long215/&gt;&lt;ref name=James180/&gt;

==Aftermath==

===Subsequent operations===
Following the failure of the landing at Porton Plantation, the planned Australian advance into the Bonis Peninsula was called off. The Australian high command decided to refocus their efforts upon the drive towards Buin in the south and as a result the effort in the north was reduced to that of a holding action as further resources were transferred out of the sector.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Long|1963|pp=234–235}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Following the withdrawal, the 31st/51st Infantry Battalion [[Battle of Ratsua|continued fighting along the Ratsua front]] before being relieved on 28 June by the [[8th Battalion (Australia)|8th Infantry Battalion]] and withdrawing to [[Torokina]], where they remained until the end of the war.&lt;ref name=Davidson140/&gt; The [[23rd Brigade (Australia)|23rd Brigade]] under Brigadier [[Arnold Potts]] took over control of the sector, and for a period of four weeks along the Ratsua front the 8th and [[27th Battalion (Australia)|27th Infantry Battalions]] carried out patrolling operations before the Australians decided to withdraw to the Buoi Plantation in mid-July,&lt;ref name=Long253&gt;{{harvnb|Long|1963|p=235}}.&lt;/ref&gt; by which time the Japanese forces in the area, boosted by their victory at Porton, had begun to seize the initiative through the use of harassment tactics.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|James|2005|p=196}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Following this several small-scale actions continued along the front until offensive action was discontinued on 11 August 1945 as the war came to a conclusion.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Long|1963|p=237}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Analysis===
[[File:Battle of Porton wounded 12 June 1945.jpg|left|thumb|Australian wounded are evacuated during the Battle of Porton Plantation, 12 June 1945.|alt=Wounded men lie on stretchers on the deck of a landing craft covered by blankets. Others are tending the wounded.]]

Since the end of the war, the conceptual validity and strategic necessity of the Australian landing has been called into question by historians. Both James and Davidson state that several aspects of the planning undertaken by 11th Brigade staff and the 31st/51st Infantry Battalion's commander contributed to the defeat,&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|James|2005|pp=191–192}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=James144&gt;{{harvnb|James|2012|p=144}}.&lt;/ref&gt; particularly in relation to the failure of intelligence to adequately identify the risks posed by the nearby reefs, as well as the failure to adequately resource the operation, and an overestimation of the ability of neighbouring forces to breakthrough to the beachhead.&lt;ref name=&quot;Davidson31_39&quot;/&gt; Charlton also argues that the landing was hastily planned, under-resourced and inadequately supported, and that it was part of a strategically unnecessary campaign.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Davidson| 2005|pp=140–146}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Charlton57&gt;{{harvnb|Charlton|1983|p=57}}.&lt;/ref&gt; James agrees that it was under resourced, stating that the size of the assault force was &quot;too small to establish a beachhead and push inland as well&quot;, although ultimately argues that the campaign was necessary.&lt;ref name=James144/&gt; It has also been speculated that the Japanese might also have gained prior knowledge of the attack. In support of this, James outlines that in the aftermath of the fighting, Blamey visited Kelly at his headquarters around Ratsua and upon interviewing him, stated to the II Corps commander, Savige, that he felt that Kelly had erred in conducting rehearsals of the barge landings during the planning stage within view of Japanese positions, potentially warning them of the operation.&lt;ref name=James191/&gt;

The Battle of Porton Plantation ended in defeat for the Australians, as the landing was repulsed and the Japanese remained in possession of the beachhead.&lt;ref name=Davidson140&gt;{{harvnb|Davidson|2005|p=140}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Amidst a campaign where largely the Australians dominated – it was the only defeat – the battle represented a shift in momentum in the northern sector, which was in part due to the shift in resources south, a fact which continued to impact Australian operations in the sector until the end of the war.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|James|2012|p=147}}.&lt;/ref&gt; During the course of the landing and the subsequent withdrawal, the Australians suffered 23 killed or missing, presumed dead, and 106 wounded,&lt;ref name=Long215/&gt; while the Japanese lost 26 killed.&lt;ref name=KatoLong216&gt;{{harvnb|Long|1963|p=216}}.&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|Charlton provides the figure of 23 Japanese killed.&lt;ref name=Charlton57/&gt;|group=Note}} Both sides seem to have overestimated the casualties that they inflicted, with the Australians believing that they had killed between 147 and 197 Japanese,&lt;ref name=Long215/&gt; and the Japanese estimating Australian losses to have been around 60 killed and 100 wounded.&lt;ref name=KatoLong216/&gt;

===Commemoration===
After the end of hostilities, a reconnaissance party including officers from the 31st/51st Infantry Battalion returned to the area and found that the Japanese defenders had buried the Australians that had died on the beach and had constructed a memorial to them, reading: &quot;The Australian soldiers buried here died by the sea&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Davidson|2005| p=150}}.&lt;/ref&gt; For its part in the landing, the 31st/51st Infantry Battalion received the [[battle honour]] of &quot;Bonis–Porton&quot;, as did the 26th Infantry Battalion.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Maitland|1999|p=145}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Bonis–Porton|}}&lt;/ref&gt; Today, this honour is held by both the [[31st Battalion, Royal Queensland Regiment]] and the [[Far North Queensland Regiment|51st Battalion, Far North Queensland Regiment]], the successor units of the 31st/51st Infantry Battalion.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Burla|2005|p=362}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=51FNQR&gt;{{harvnb|History of 51 Far North Queensland Regiment |}}&lt;/ref&gt; The following decorations were awarded to members of the Australian forces that took part in the battle: one [[Distinguished Conduct Medal]], two [[Military Cross]]es, four [[Military Medal]]s, and three [[Mentioned in Despatches|Mentions in Despatches]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Davidson|2005|p=171}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Porton Training Depot in [[Cairns]], [[Australia]], was named after this battle.&lt;ref name=51FNQR/&gt;

==Notes==
;Footnotes
{{Reflist|group=Note}}

;Citations
{{Reflist|3}}

==References==
{{Commons category|Battle of Porton Plantation}}
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite web |title=31st/51st Battalion (Kennedy and Far North Queensland Regiment) |work=Second World War, 1939–1945 units |publisher=Australian War Memorial |date= |url= http://www.awm.gov.au/units/unit_11316.asp|accessdate=4 May 2009|ref=CITEREF31st/51st_Battalion_(Kennedy and Far North Queensland Regiment)}}
* {{cite web|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/units/event_458.asp|title=Bonis–Porton |work=Battle honours |publisher=Australian War Memorial|accessdate=29 October 2009 |ref=CITEREFBonis–Porton}}
* {{cite journal|last=Burke|first=Arthur|year=2006|title=Porton, One Beach Too Far&amp;nbsp;– Bougainville 1945|journal=Sabretache|publisher=Military Historical Society of Australia|volume=47|issue=1|pages=5–8|issn=0048-8933 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last=Burla | first=Robert | authorlink= | year=2005 | title=Crossed Boomerangs: The History of All the 31 Battalions | edition= | publisher=Australian Military Publications | location=Loftus, New South Wales | isbn=978-1-876439-67-5 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Charlton |first=Peter |title=The Unnecessary War: Island Campaigns of the South-West Pacific 1944–45 |year=1983 |publisher=Macmillan Australia |location=Crows Nest, New South Wales |isbn=0-333-35628-4 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Davidson|first=Audrey|title=Porton: A Deadly Trap|year=2005|publisher=Boolarong Press|location=Brisbane, Queensland|isbn=0-646-44766-1 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last=Dennis |first=Peter |year=1885 |title=The Oxford Companion to Australian Military History |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Melbourne |isbn=0-19-553227-9|display-authors=etal|ref=CITEREFDennis_et_al1995}}
* {{cite book |last=Grant |first=Lachlan |year=2016 |chapter=Given a Second Rate Job: Campaigns in Aitape–Wewak and New Britain, 1944–45 |title=Australia 1944–45: Victory in the Pacific |editor=Dean, Peter J. |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=Port Melbourne, Victoria | pp=213–231 |isbn=9781107083462|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Grey |first=Jeffrey|coauthors= |title=A Military History of Australia |edition=3rd |publisher=Cambridge University Press|location=Melbourne, Victoria |year=2008|series= |url= |isbn=978-0-521-69791-0 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite web|url=http://www.army.gov.au/51fnqr/history.html  |title=History of 51 Far North Queensland Regiment |publisher=Department of Defence |accessdate=23 January 2011 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20080801144220/http://www.army.gov.au/51fnqr/history.html |archivedate = 1 August 2008 |ref=CITEREFHistory_of_51_Far_North_Queensland Regiment}}
* {{cite book |last=Hughes |first=William |title=At War With the 51st Infantry Battalion and 31/51st Infantry Battalion (AIF) from 1940 to 1946 |year=1993 |publisher=Church Archivist Press |location=Brisbane, Queensland |isbn= 978-0-949122-29-2 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite thesis |degree=PhD |title=The Final Campaigns: Bougainville 1944–1945  |url=http://ro.uow.edu.au/theses/467 |last=James |first=Karl |year=2005 |publisher=School of History and Politics, University of Wollongong |oclc=225536344 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=James |first=Karl |title=The Hard Slog: Australians in the Bougainville Campaign, 1944–45 |year=2012 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=Cambridge, United Kingdom |isbn= 978-1-107-01732-0 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=James |first=Karl |year=2016 |chapter=More Than Mopping Up: Bougainville |title=Australia 1944–45: Victory in the Pacific |editor=Dean, Peter J. |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=Port Melbourne, Victoria | pp=232–251 |isbn=978-1-107-08346-2|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Johnston|first=Mark|authorlink=Mark Johnston (historian)|title=The Australian Army in World War II|year=2007|publisher=Osprey Publishing|location=Botley, Oxford|isbn=978-1-84603-123-6 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Keogh|first=Eustace|title=The South West Pacific 1941–45|year=1965|publisher=Grayflower Productions|location=Melbourne, Victoria|isbn= |oclc=7185705 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal|last=Lawie|first=Donald|year=2001|title=Ordeal at Porton|journal=Wartime: Official Magazine of the Australian War Memorial|publisher=Australian War Memorial|volume=|issue=16|pages=45–47|issn=1328-2727 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Long|first=Gavin|authorlink=Gavin Long|title=The Final Campaigns|series=Australia in the War of 1939–1945, Series 1—Army. Volume VII|year=1963|edition=1st|publisher=Australian War Memorial|location=Canberra, Australian Capital Territory |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070206/|oclc=1297619 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Maitland|first=Gordon|title=The Second World War and its Australian Army Battle Honours|year=1999|publisher=Kangaroo Press|location=East Roseville, New South Wales|isbn=0-86417-975-8 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Rentz |first=John N. |year=1946 |url=http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/USMC/USMC-M-NSols/index.html |title=Bougainville and the Northern Solomons |series=USMC Historical Monograph |publisher=Historical Branch, Headquarters, U.S. Marine Corps |location=Washington, D.C. |oclc=1313812 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Shindo |first=Hiroyuki |year=2016 |chapter=Holding on to the Finish: The Japanese Army in the South and Southwest Pacific, 1944–45 |title=Australia 1944–45: Victory in the Pacific |editor-last=Dean |editor-first=Peter J. |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=Port Melbourne, Victoria |pages=51–76 |isbn=978-1-107-08346-2 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Tanaka|first=Kengoro|title=Operations of the Imperial Japanese Armed Forces in the Papua New Guinea Theater During World War II|year=1980|publisher=Japan Papua New Guinea Goodwill Society|location=Tokyo, Japan|oclc=9206229 |ref=harv}}
{{refend}}

{{Coord|5|32|2.32|S|154|45|49.38|E|type:event|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Porton}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1945]]
[[Category:1945 in Papua New Guinea]]
[[Category:South West Pacific theatre of World War II]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Japan]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Australia]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving New Zealand]]</text>
      <sha1>am2n6ymvaglc55baf6uob9tjlkc5j0p</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
