<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of Magersfontein</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3504170</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749813217</id>
      <parentid>746655309</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-16T08:10:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lord Eastfarthing</username>
        <id>11187569</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Cleaned up using [[WP:AutoEd|AutoEd]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="49691">{{Use South African English|date=October 2013}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Battle of Magersfontein
| partof      = [[Second Boer War]]
| image       = [[File:Paul Methuen, 3rd Baron Methuen.png|93px|alt=black and white portrait of Lord Methuen]] [[File:PACronje CHM VA2863.jpg|121px|alt=black and white portrait of General P.A. Cronje]]&lt;br&gt;[[File:Andrew-gilbert-wauchope BW.jpg|106px|alt=black and white portrait of General Andrew Gilbert Wauchope]] [[File:KoosDeLaRey.jpg|106px|alt=B&amp;W Portrait of General Koos De La Rey]]
| caption     = The Commanders: &lt;br&gt;Lord Methuen, General Cronjé,&lt;br&gt;General Wauchope†, General De La Rey
| date        = 11 December 1899
| place       = [[Magersfontein]], [[British Cape Colony|Cape Colony]], [[South Africa]]
| coordinates = {{Coord|28|58|S|24|42|E|type:event_region:ZA|display=title}}
| map_type    = South Africa
| latitude    = -28.9
| longitude   = 24.8
| map_size    = 250
| map_caption = Location of Magersfontein within South Africa
| casus       =
| territory   =
| result      = Boer victory
| combatant1  = {{flagcountry|United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland}}
| combatant2  = {{flag|South African Republic}}&lt;br&gt;{{flag|Orange Free State}}
| commander1  = {{flagicon|UK}} [[Paul Sanford Methuen, 3rd Baron Methuen|Lord Methuen]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|UK}} [[Andrew Gilbert Wauchope]] [[Killed in action|†]]
| commander2  = {{flagicon|South African Republic}} [[Piet Cronje]] &lt;br&gt; {{flagicon|South African Republic}} [[Koos de la Rey]]
| strength1   = 14,964 men and 27 guns&lt;ref name=&quot;MAUR6&quot;&gt;Maurice, (1998b), Vol. 6&lt;/ref&gt;
| strength2   = 8,500 men, five guns and three machine guns&lt;ref name=Kruger130/&gt;
| casualties1 = 948 killed and wounded&lt;ref name=&quot;MAUR6&quot;/&gt;
| casualties2 = 236 killed and wounded&lt;ref name=&quot;PAK20610&quot;/&gt;
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Second Boer War}}
}}

The '''Battle of Magersfontein'''&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;Spelt incorrectly in various English texts as &quot;Majersfontein&quot;, &quot;Maaghersfontein&quot; and &quot;Maagersfontein&quot;.&lt;/ref&gt; ({{IPAc-en|ˈ|m|ɑː|x|ər|s|f|ɒ|n|t|eɪ|n}} {{respell|MAH|khərs-fon-tayn}}) was fought on 11 December 1899, at [[Magersfontein]] near [[Kimberley, Northern Cape|Kimberley]] on the borders of the [[British Cape Colony|Cape Colony]] and the independent republic of the [[Orange Free State]]. [[United Kingdom|British]] forces under Lieutenant General [[Paul Sanford Methuen, 3rd Baron Methuen|Lord Methuen]] were advancing north along the railway line from the Cape in order to relieve the [[Siege of Kimberley]], but their path was blocked at Magersfontein by a [[Boer]] force that was entrenched in the surrounding hills. The British had already fought a series of battles with the Boers, most recently at [[Battle of Modder River|Modder River]], where the advance was temporarily halted.

Lord Methuen failed to perform adequate reconnaissance in preparation for the impending battle, and was unaware that Boer ''Veggeneraal'' (Combat General) [[De la Rey]] had entrenched his forces at the foot of the hills rather than the forward slopes as was the accepted practice. This allowed the Boers to survive the initial British artillery bombardment; when the British troops failed to deploy from a compact formation during their advance, the defenders were able to inflict heavy casualties. The [[Highland Brigade (Scottish)|Highland Brigade]] suffered the worst casualties, while on the Boer side, the Scandinavian Corps was destroyed. The Boers attained a tactical victory and succeeded in holding the British in their advance on Kimberley. The battle was the second of three battles during what became known as the [[Black Week#Second Boer War|Black Week]] of the [[Second Boer War]].

Following their defeat, the British delayed at the Modder River for another two months while reinforcements were brought forward. General [[Frederick Roberts, 1st Earl Roberts|Lord Roberts]] was appointed Commander in Chief of the British forces in South Africa and moved to take personal command of this front. He subsequently lifted the Siege of Kimberley and forced Cronje to surrender at the [[Battle of Paardeberg]].
{{TOC limit|limit=2}}

==Background==
In the early days of the war in the [[British Cape Colony|Cape Colony]], the Boers surrounded and [[Siege of Kimberley|laid siege]] to the British garrisons in the towns of [[Kimberley, South Africa|Kimberley]] and [[Siege of Mafeking|Mafeking]] and destroyed the railway bridge across the [[Orange River]] at [[Hopetown]].&lt;ref&gt;German General Staff, (1998), p. 78&lt;/ref&gt; Substantial British reinforcements (an army corps under General [[Redvers Buller]]) arrived in South Africa and were dispersed to three main fronts. While Buller himself advanced from the port of [[Durban]] in [[Colony of Natal|Natal]] to relieve the besieged town of [[Siege of Ladysmith|Ladysmith]] and a smaller detachment under Lieutenant General [[William Forbes Gatacre|Gatacre]] secured the Cape Midlands, the reinforced [[1st Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|1st Division]] under Lord Methuen advanced from the [[Orange River]] to relieve Kimberley.&lt;ref name=&quot;GGS79&quot;&gt;German General Staff, (1998), p. 79&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Modder River pontoon bridge.jpg|thumb|left|[[Pontoon bridge]] built over the Modder River after the railway bridge was destroyed by retreating Boers|alt=A low bridge over twelve pontoons, with troops on the nearby bank]]
Methuen advanced along the Cape–Transvaal railway line because a lack of water and pack animals made the reliable railway an obvious choice. Also, Buller had given him orders to evacuate the civilians in Kimberley and the railway was the only means of mass transport available.&lt;ref&gt;Miller, (1996)&lt;/ref&gt; But his strategy had the disadvantage of making the direction of his approach obvious.&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller-p85&quot;&gt;Miller, (1999), p. 85&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, his army drove the Boers out of their defensive positions along the railway line at [[Battle of Belmont|Belmont]], Graspan, and the [[Battle of Modder River|Modder River]], at the cost of a thousand casualties. The British were forced to stop their advance within {{convert|16|mi|km}} of Kimberley&lt;ref name=&quot;CD150&quot;&gt;Conan Doyle, (1900), p. 150&lt;/ref&gt; at the Modder River crossing. The Boers had demolished the railway bridge when they retreated, and it had to be repaired before the army could advance any further. Methuen also needed several days for supplies and reinforcements to be brought forward, and for his extended [[Line of communication|supply line]] to be secured from sabotage.&lt;ref&gt;Maurice, (1998a), p. 308&lt;/ref&gt;  The Boers were badly shaken by their three successive defeats and also required time to recover.&lt;ref&gt;German General Staff, (1998), p. 85&lt;/ref&gt;  The delay gave them time to bring up reinforcements, to reorganise, and to improve their next line of defence at Magersfontein.&lt;ref name=&quot;CD150&quot;/&gt;

==Prelude==

===Boer defences===
After the Battle of the Modder River, the Boers initially retreated to [[Jacobsdal]], where a commando from Mafeking linked up with them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tallboy384&quot;&gt;Tallboy, p.&amp;nbsp;384&lt;/ref&gt;  The following day, Cronje moved his forces {{convert|10|mi|km}} north to Scholtz Nek and Spytfontein,&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;Location of Scholtz Nek:{{Coord|-28.911564|24.707565|display=inline|type:event_region:ZA|name=Scholtz Nek|format=dms}}.  Location of Spytfontein: {{Coord|-28.882230|24.683372|display=inline|type:event_region:ZA|name=Spytfontein|format=dms}}&lt;/ref&gt; where they began to fortify themselves in the hills that made up the last defensible position along the railway line to Kimberley.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tallboy384&quot;/&gt;  Although closer to the British camp than the Boer camp, Jacobsdal was left poorly defended, and continued to function as the Boers' supply base until 3 December.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tallboy384&quot;/&gt;

The Free State government decided to reinforce Cronje's position after the Battle of Belmont.  Between eight hundred and a thousand men of the [[Heilbron]], [[Kroonstad]] and [[Bethlehem, Free State|Bethlehem]] commandos arrived at Spytfontein from Natal, accompanied by elements of the [[Ficksburg]] and [[Ladybrand]] commandos from the [[Lesotho|Basuto]] border. Reinforcements were also brought up from the [[Bloemhof]] and [[Wolmaranstad]] commandos who were besieging Kimberley.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tallboy384&quot;/&gt;  The remainder of Cronje's force arrived from the [[Siege of Mafeking]].  Their force now numbered 8,500 fighters,&lt;ref name=Kruger130&gt;Kruger, (1960), p. 130&lt;/ref&gt; excluding camp followers and the African labourers who performed the actual work of digging the Boer entrenchments.&lt;ref name=Pakenham200&gt;Pakenham, (1979), p. 200&lt;/ref&gt;

Koos de la Rey had been absent from the army immediately after the Battle of the Modder River, having gone to Jacobsdal to bury his son Adriaan, who had been killed by a British shell during the battle. He arrived at the defensive positions on 1 December&lt;ref name=&quot;Meintjies&quot;&gt;Meintjes, p.&amp;nbsp;125&lt;/ref&gt; and surveyed the Boer lines the following day.  He found the defences lacking, and realised that Cronje's position at Spyfontein was vulnerable to long range artillery fire from the hills at Magersfontein.  He therefore recommended that they should move their defensive position forward to Magersfontein, to deny the British this opportunity.&lt;ref&gt;Maurice, (1998a), p. 305&lt;/ref&gt;  Cronje, who was the more senior officer, disagreed with him, so De la Rey telegraphed his objections to President [[Martinus Theunis Steyn]] of the Orange Free State.  After consulting with President [[Paul Kruger]] of the Transvaal, Steyn visited the front on 4 December at Kruger's suggestion.&lt;ref name=Pakenham199&gt;Pakenham, (1979), p. 199&lt;/ref&gt; Steyn also wished to settle a rift that had developed between the Transvaal and Free State Boers over the poor performance of his Free Staters in the battle on 28 November.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tallboy384&quot;/&gt;  He spent the next day touring the camps and defences, then summoned a ''krijgsraad'' ([[council of war]]).

The Boers had learnt in earlier battles that the British artillery was superior in numbers to theirs, and could pound any high ground where they placed their guns or rifle pits. At [[Siege of Ladysmith|Ladysmith]], the Boers used rocks to build defensive [[sangar (fortification)|sangars]], but the ground at Magersfontein was sandy and less rocky.&lt;ref&gt;Knight ''et al'', p. 47&lt;/ref&gt;  De la Rey recommended, contrary to common practice, that they should entrench themselves forward of the line of ''[[Monadnock|kopjes]]'',&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;Hill or ridge.&lt;/ref&gt; rather than on the facing slopes.&lt;ref&gt;Creswicke, (1900), p. 172&lt;/ref&gt;  The trenches overlooking the receding, open ground sloping down towards the British axis of advance afforded the Boers concealment and protection from fire, and permitted them to use the flat [[trajectory]] of their [[Mauser#Model 1894 and Model 1895|Mauser rifles]] to greater effect.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ralf178&quot;&gt;Ralf, (1900), p. 178&lt;/ref&gt;  Since the trenches were concealed, they could thwart the standard British tactic of advancing to within close range under cover of darkness and then storming the Boer position at daybreak.&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller134&quot;&gt;Miller, p.&amp;nbsp;134&lt;/ref&gt;  A final consequence of De la Rey's defensive layout was that the troops would not be able to retreat, as Commandant General Marthinus Prinsloo's forces had done at Modder River.&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller134&quot;/&gt;  Before leaving the front, Steyn raised the morale of the Free State ''burghers''&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;Citizen soldiers or territorial soldiers.&lt;/ref&gt; by dismissing Prinsloo, who was seen as the chief reason for the defeats in earlier battles.&lt;ref name=Kruger130/&gt;

The new defensive line occupied a wide crescent-shaped front, extending for {{convert|6|mi|km|0}} and straddling the road and the railway line that Methuen's advance depended upon. The main trench directly in front of the Magersfontein Hill was {{convert|2|mi|km}} long,&lt;ref name=&quot;Ralf178&quot;/&gt; and protected on the right flank by a single trench.  The trenches that were to protect the left flank in the direction of the river were not completed before the battle commenced.&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller133&quot;&gt;Miller, p.&amp;nbsp;133&lt;/ref&gt;  Two high wire fences complemented the natural obstacles created by the thick scrub bush. One ran north-northeast and marked the border of the Orange Free State, while a second protected the trenches in front of the Boer position.&lt;ref&gt;Maurice, (1998a), p. 306&lt;/ref&gt;

===British plan===
[[File:Magersfontein sketch.png|thumb|right|Contemporary sketch of the battlefield, looking north towards the Boer position from Modder River|alt=Sketch showing placement of guns and trenches, with hills in the background]]
Methuen believed that the Boers were occupying the crests of the line of ''kopjes'', as they had done at Belmont, but he was unable to reconnoitre the position; his mounted scouts could not roam the countryside freely on account of wire farm fences,&lt;ref&gt;Tufnell ''et al'', (1910), p. 59&lt;/ref&gt; nor could they approach any closer than {{convert|1|mi|km}} to the Boer positions without being driven off by rifle fire.&lt;ref name=Pakenham200/&gt; No serviceable maps were available; those in the possession of the British officers had been prepared for the purposes of land registration, with no consideration of military operations. Officers supplemented these maps with hasty sketches based on limited daily reconnaissance.&lt;ref name=&quot;GGS79&quot;/&gt; The poor maps and lack of reconnaissance would prove critical to the outcome of the battle.&lt;ref&gt;Miller, (1999), p. 185&lt;/ref&gt;

Ever since the victory against an Egyptian army at the [[Battle of Tel-el-Kebir]], the standard British tactic against an entrenched position was an approach march at night in close order to maintain cohesion, followed by deployment into open order within a few hundred yards of the objective and a frontal attack with the bayonet at first light. Methuen planned to bombard the Boer positions with artillery from 16:50 to 18:30 on 10 December. Following the barrage, the newly arrived [[Highland Brigade (Scottish)|Highland Brigade]] under Major General [[Andrew Gilbert Wauchope|Wauchope]] was to make a night march that would position them to launch a frontal attack on the Boers at dawn the following day.&lt;ref&gt;Creswicke, (1900), pp. 172–173&lt;/ref&gt; Wauchope had argued for a flanking attack along the Modder River, but had been unable to convince his superior.&lt;ref&gt;SAMHS, July 2003&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Battle of Magersfontein.png|left|thumb|Disposition and movement of forces|alt=Map showing the location of opposing forces]]
Methuen's orders show that his intention was to &quot;hold the enemy on the north and to deliver an attack on the southern end of Magersfontein Ridge.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mau312&quot;&gt;Maurice, (1998a), pp. 312–315&lt;/ref&gt;  The advance was to be made in three columns. The first column consisted of the Highland Brigade, the [[9th Queen's Royal Lancers|9th Lancers]], the 2nd [[King's Own Yorkshire Light Infantry]], and supporting artillery and engineer sections as well as a balloon section.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mau312&quot;/&gt; The first column was ordered to march directly on the south-western spur of the ''kopje'' and on arrival, before dawn, the 2nd [[Black Watch]] were to move east of the ''kopje'', where he believed the Boers had a strong-point. He ordered the 2nd [[Seaforth Highlanders]] to advance to the south-eastern point of the hill, and the 1st [[Argyll and Sutherland Highlanders]] to extend the line to the left. The 1st [[Highland Light Infantry]] was to advance as a reserve. All units were to advance in a mass of quarter columns, the most compact formation in the drill book: 3,500 men in 30 companies aligned in 90 files, all compressed into a column {{convert|45|yd|m}} wide and {{convert|160|yd|m}} long,&lt;ref name=&quot;PK203&quot;&gt;Pakenham, (1979), p. 203&lt;/ref&gt; with the outer sections using ropes to guide the four battalions in their night march and deployment for the dawn attack.&lt;ref name=&quot;Creswicke p. 173&quot;&gt;Creswicke, (1900), p. 173&lt;/ref&gt; The second column, on the left under Major-General Reginald Pole-Carew, consisted of a battalion from the 9th Brigade, the Naval Brigade with a [[QF 4.7 inch Gun Mk I - IV|4.7-inch naval gun]], and [[Rimington's Guides]] (a mounted infantry unit raised in [[Cape Town]]).  The third column, led by Major-General Sir [[Henry Edward Colville]], was in reserve and was composed of the [[12th Royal Lancers|12th Lancers]], the Guards Brigade, and artillery, engineer, and medical support elements.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mau312&quot;/&gt;

===Advance to attack===
[[File:Loopgrawe.JPG|thumb|right|Present-day view of the trenches looking south from the Boer position towards the British position in the distance|alt=Present-day elevated view of the open ground over which the British advanced]]
A drizzle started by mid-afternoon on 10 December and continued throughout the artillery bombardment, which was delivered by 24 field guns, four howitzers, and a 4.7-inch naval gun. In preparation for the attack, the soldiers bivouacked in the rain {{convert|3|mi|km}} from the Boer lines.&lt;ref&gt;Conan Doyle, (1900), p. 136&lt;/ref&gt; Instead of &quot;softening&quot; the Boer positions, the explosions of [[Picric acid|lyddite]] shells against the facing slopes above their trenches merely alerted the Boers to the impending attack.&lt;ref name=&quot;PK203&quot;/&gt; As midnight approached, the rain increased to a downpour and the leading elements of the Highland Brigade commenced their advance towards their objective at the southern end of Magersfontein ridge.&lt;ref name=&quot;Creswicke p. 173&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Tufnell ''et al'', (1910), p. 61&lt;/ref&gt; Wauchope had made a similar night march in his advance on [[Battle of Omdurman|Omdurman]] in 1898, but this time he was faced not by flat desert terrain and clear skies, but rather by torrential rain, rocky outcrops, and thorn scrub, which caused delays and annoyance.&lt;ref&gt;Parkenham, (1979), p. 203&lt;/ref&gt; The thunderstorm and the high iron ore content of the surrounding hills played havoc with compasses and navigation.&lt;ref name=&quot;PK203&quot;/&gt;

The brigade was advancing in quarter column as directed by Methuen's orders.  The soldiers advanced packed as closely together as possible, with each ordered to grasp his neighbour to prevent the men losing contact with each other in the darkness.&lt;ref&gt;Maurice, (1998a), p. 316&lt;/ref&gt; As first light approached, the storm abated and the Brigade was on course, but the delays put them {{convert|1000|yd|m}} from the line of hills. Wauchope's guide, [[Major Benson]] of the [[Royal Artillery]], suggested to Wauchope that it was no longer safe to continue in closed formation and that the Brigade should deploy. Wauchope replied &quot;''... I'm afraid my men will lose direction. I think we will go a little further.''&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Pakenham, (1979), p. 204&lt;/ref&gt; Still in quarter column, the Highlanders advanced further towards the unknown enemy lines, when an advancing British soldier tripped an alarm on the fence in front of the Boer trench.&lt;ref&gt;Conan Doyle, (1900), p. 154&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battle==

===Highland Brigade trapped===
[[File:Magersfonteinmodel.JPG|thumb|Relief model at the Magersfontein museum.]]
[[File:Boer Trench.jpg|thumb|The primary Boer trench at Magersfontein from which the Highlanders were fired upon|alt=Contemporary photograph looking down a Boer trench located at the foot of a hill]]
The Highlanders had advanced to within {{convert|400|yd|m}} of the Boer trenches when the Boers opened fire; the British had no time to reform from their compact quarter columns into a fighting formation.&lt;ref&gt;Maurice, (1998a), p. 318&lt;/ref&gt;  Wauchope instructed the brigade to extend its order, but in the face of such close-range Boer fire, the changing formation was thrown into disarray and confusion. [[General Wauchope]] was killed by almost the first volley, as was Lieutenant-Colonel G. L. J. Goff, the commanding officer of the Argylls.&lt;ref&gt;Maurice, (1998a), p. 319&lt;/ref&gt; The men at the head of the brigade disentangled themselves from the dead and most of them fled.&lt;ref name=&quot;CD155&quot;/&gt; Some of the Black Watch at the head of the column charged the Boer trenches; a few broke through, but as they climbed [[Magersfontein Hill]] they were engaged by their own artillery and Boer parties, including one led by General Cronje himself, who had been wandering the ''kopje'' since 01:00,&lt;ref&gt;Kruger, (1960), pp. 131–132&lt;/ref&gt; and were subsequently killed or captured. Others were shot while entangled in the wire fence in front of the trenches.&lt;ref name=&quot;PAK20610&quot;&gt;Pakenham, (1979), p. 206&lt;/ref&gt; Conan Doyle points out that 700 of the British casualties that day occurred in the first five minutes of the engagement.&lt;ref&gt;Conan Doyle, (1900), p. 144&lt;/ref&gt;

An attempt was made to outflank the trenches on the right where a number of Boers were taken prisoner, but this action was soon blocked by the redeployment of Boer elements.&lt;ref name=&quot;CD155&quot;&gt;Conan Doyle, (1900), pp. 155–157&lt;/ref&gt; After sunrise, the remnants of the four battalions of the [[Highland Brigade (United Kingdom)|Highland Brigade]] were unable to advance or retreat due to Boer rifle fire. The only movement at that time was a team led by [[Lt. Lindsay]], who managed to bring the Seaforth's [[Maxim gun|Maxim]] forward to provide a degree of [[fire support]]. Later the Lancers were able to bring their Maxim forward and into action as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;CD155&quot;/&gt; Methuen ordered all available artillery to provide fire support; the howitzers engaged at {{convert|4000|yd|m}} and the three field batteries at a range of {{convert|1|mi|m}}. The Horse Artillery advanced to the southern flank in an attempt to enfilade the trenches.&lt;ref name=&quot;CD155&quot;/&gt; With all guns engaged, including the 4.7-inch naval gun commanded by [[Captain Bearcroft RN]],&lt;ref&gt;Maurice, (1998a), p. 321&lt;/ref&gt; the Highlanders were given some respite from the Boer small-arms fire, and some men were able to withdraw.  As with the preliminary barrage of the previous evening, most of the shot was however again directed at the facing slopes of the hills rather than the Boer trenches at their foot.&lt;ref name=&quot;CD155&quot;/&gt;

===Reinforcements arrive===
As the day progressed, British reinforcements that were originally left to guard the camp near the [[Modder River]] started to arrive—first the [[Gordon Highlanders]] and later the 1st and 2nd [[Coldstream Guards]]. At the same time, Cronjé launched a fresh attack on the British southern (right) flank in an attempt to extend a salient to the left and behind the remaining Highlanders, cutting them off from the main British force. Initially the [[Seaforth Highlanders|Seaforths]] attempted to stem this attack and ran into the [[Scandinavian Corps]], which they quickly neutralised.  The Seaforths then had to regroup, which prevented them from further action to halt the Boer attempts to encircle the Highland Brigade.&lt;ref&gt;Maurice, (1998a), p. 327&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Grenadier Guards]], with five companies of the King's Own Yorkshire Light Infantry, were moved to counter the attack.  The British only showed some sign of success after the freshly arrived battalions of the Coldstream Guards were committed too.  But once the Coldstreams were committed, Methuen had engaged all of his reserves.&lt;ref name=&quot;CD155&quot;/&gt;

The remaining Highlanders, now under the command of Lieutenant Colonel James Hughes-Hallet of the Seaforths,&lt;ref name=&quot;ConanDoyle162&quot;&gt;Conan Doyle, (1900), p.&amp;nbsp;162&lt;/ref&gt; had been lying prone under a harsh summer sun for most of the day with the Boers still attempting to encircle them from the south. In the late afternoon, those who remained alive stood up and fled west towards the main body of British troops. This unexpected move left many of the field guns which had been advanced to the front line over the course of the morning exposed to the Boers.  Only a lack of initiative on the part of the Boers saved the guns from being captured.  The gap created by the hurried withdrawal of the Highland Brigade was filled by the Gordons and the Scots Guards.&lt;ref&gt;Conan Doyle, (1900), p. 159&lt;/ref&gt;

===Scandinavian volunteers===
[[File:Boer-war-volunteers from Finland&amp;Scandinavia.jpg|thumb|right|Members of the Scandinavian Volunteer Corps prior to the Battle of Magersfontein|alt=Portrait photograph of a group of men in uniform, posing with rifles and bandoliers]]
The [[Scandinavia]]n Volunteer Corps (''Skandinaviska Kåren'') was not a true corps but rather a unit the size of a company, consisting of [[Boer foreign volunteers|foreign volunteers]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Uddgren, 1924, pp. 8–19&quot;&gt;Uddgren, (1924), pp. 8–19&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref| According to Swedish combatant Erik Stålberg who was one of the few survivors of the battle from the Scandinavian corps, it consisted of 82 men. At the outbreak of war, a meeting was held in Pretoria on 12 October 1899 between members of the Scandinavian Organization in Transvaal (''Skandinaviska Organisationen i Transvaal'') and the South African Republic (ZAR) military staff with the intention of forming a Scandinavian volunteer unit to support the Boer republic against the British. The offer was accepted by the ZAR government. The military organisation issued the corps with [[7.92×57mm Mauser|Mod. 1888 Mauser rifles]] and 90 horses. Clothes suitable for use as uniforms were supplied by the Scandinavian Organization in Transvaal Committee. On the first day of recruitment, 68 Scandinavians volunteered for duty. The corps, now numbering 100 men, was ordered to the Mafeking front on 16 October 1899. They joined the forces of [[General Piet Cronje]] at Reitvlej near Mafeking on 23 October 1899, where they first saw action with the Boers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Uddgren, 1924, pp. 8–19&quot;/&gt;|group=&quot;Note&quot;}}  Approximately half of the Corps (refer to the [[#Order of battle|Order of battle]]) was ordered to hold a forward position in the gap between the high ground held by Cronje and De la Rey's forces during the night of 10–11 December. The rest of the force was entrenched in defensive positions some {{convert|1500|m|yd}} further north-east. In the early morning hours of 11&amp;nbsp;December, General Cronje ordered [[Commandant Tolly de Beer]] to abandon the outpost, but the order did not reach the Scandinavian section, which was left on its own.&lt;ref&gt;Uddgren, (1924), p. 46&lt;/ref&gt; Save for seven men, this section was destroyed while holding back the attack of the Seaforth Highlanders, who were in the process denied access between the hills and prevented from reaching the Boer guns.&lt;ref&gt;Uddgren, (1924), p. 47&lt;/ref&gt; Cronje understood the significance of this stand, and said in a subsequent letter to Kruger that &quot;next to God we can thank the Scandinavians for our victory&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Winquist, (1978), p. 171&lt;/ref&gt;

===Final retreat===
In the late afternoon, a Boer messenger bearing a white flag arrived at a Scots Guard outpost to say that the British could send ambulances to collect their wounded lying in front of the trenches at the foot of the hills. [[Royal Army Medical Corps]] and Boer medical orderlies treated the wounded until the truce was broken by fire from the British naval gun, Captain (RN) Bearcroft not having been informed of the temporary armistice. A British medical orderly was sent to the Boers with apologies, and the truce was reinstated. When the truce was officially over, G Battery RHA, the [[62nd Field Battery]], and the [[Argyll and Sutherland Highlanders]] were tasked to screen the reorganisation and withdrawal of some of the British troops.&lt;ref&gt;Maurice, (1998a), p. 330&lt;/ref&gt;

The Boer guns, which had not yet seen action that day, opened fire on the cavalry at about 17:30 and the center of the British attack began to fall back.&lt;ref&gt;Conan Doyle, (1900), p. 142&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;CD160&quot;/&gt; Men instinctively withdrew to beyond the range of the Boer guns; Methuen decided that a total withdrawal was preferable to his troops spending the night near the Boer trenches.&lt;ref name=&quot;CD160&quot;&gt;Conan Doyle, (1900), pp. 160–161&lt;/ref&gt;  Battalions and remnants of battalions retreated throughout the night and were mustered for roll call at the Modder River camp the next morning.&lt;ref&gt;Conan Doyle, (1900), p. 161&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==

===Tactical dispositions===
[[File:Magersfontein Observation Balloon.jpg|thumb|right|An [[observation balloon]] being prepared by the [[Royal Engineers]] at the Battle of Magersfontein, with the hills occupied by the Boers in the background|alt=Contemporary image of a tethered, round observation balloon being prepared for use]]
The Boers halted Methuen's advance to relieve the siege of Kimberley, defeated his superior force and inflicted heavy losses, particularly on the Highland Brigade. The British were forced to withdraw to the Modder River to regroup and to await further reinforcements.&lt;ref name=&quot;CD160&quot;/&gt;  Unlike previous occasions, where the Boers withdrew after an engagement, this time Cronje held the Magersfontein defence line,&lt;ref name=&quot;PAK20610&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Tufnell ''et al'', (1910), p. 63&lt;/ref&gt; knowing that Methuen would again be forced to continue his advance along his logistical railway &quot;lifeline&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller-p85&quot;/&gt;

===Losses===
The British lost 22&amp;nbsp;officers and 188&amp;nbsp;other ranks killed, 46&amp;nbsp;officers and 629&amp;nbsp;other ranks wounded, and one officer and 62&amp;nbsp;other ranks missing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mau329&quot;&gt;Maurice, (1998a), pp. 329–330&lt;/ref&gt; Of this, the Highland Brigade suffered losses of 747&amp;nbsp;men being killed, wounded, and missing.  Among the battalions, [[The Black Watch]] suffered the most severely, losing 303&amp;nbsp;officers and other ranks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mau329&quot; /&gt; On 12 December, when British ambulances again went forward to collect the dead and remaining wounded, they found Wauchope's body within {{convert|200|yd|m}} of Cronjé's trenches.&lt;ref name=&quot;PAK20610&quot;/&gt; The British camp at Modder River, and subsequently at Paardeberg, created ideal conditions for the spread of [[typhoid fever]].  By the time the British reached [[Bloemfontein]], an [[epidemic]] broke out amongst the troops, with 10,000–12,000 taken ill, and 1,200 deaths in the city.&lt;ref&gt;De Villiers, (1984)&lt;/ref&gt; The disease ultimately took more British lives during the war than were lost through enemy action.&lt;ref&gt;Fremont-Barnes, (2003), p.&amp;nbsp;86&lt;/ref&gt;

The animosity that the troops on the ground felt towards their leadership is captured in this contemporary poem by a soldier of the Black Watch:

{{cquote|Such was the day for our regiment,&lt;br&gt;Dread the revenge we will take.&lt;br&gt;Dearly we paid for the blunder&lt;br&gt;A drawing-room General's mistake.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Why weren't we told of the trenches?&lt;br&gt;Why weren't we told of the wire?&lt;br&gt;Why were we marched up in column,&lt;br&gt;May [[Tommy Atkins]] enquire…&lt;br&gt;''Private Smith, December 1899.''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=BxsILFdm-7IC&amp;pg=PA65|title=Worst Journeys: An Anthology of South African Travel Disasters|last=Hopkins|first=Pat|chapter=The Black Watch At Magersfontein|pages=63–66|isbn=1-77007-101-6|year=2005|publisher=Zebra}}&lt;/ref&gt;|20px}}

[[File:Skandinawiese monument magersfontein.JPG|thumb|right|Monument to the Scandinavian volunteers killed while fighting for the Boers at the battle. The memorial reads (in Swedish): &quot;They could not retreat. They could only fall. In memory of Scandinavians killed here.&quot;|alt=Photograph of two memorial crosses on stone mounds]]
Boer losses are disputed.  The official British account of the battle records 87 killed and 188 wounded,&lt;ref name=&quot;Mau329&quot;/&gt; while later accounts record a total loss of 236 men.&lt;ref name=&quot;PAK20610&quot;/&gt; As with the Boers, several different figures regarding the strength of the Scandinavian outpost exist. British sources quote 80 men&lt;ref name=&quot;ConanDoyle162&quot;/&gt; and Scandinavian sources between 49 and 52 men. Uddgren records 52 men based on identified names, consisting of 26 Swedes, 11 Danes, 7 Finns, 4 Norwegians, and 4 of unknown nationality, of whom all but five were either killed, wounded or captured.&lt;ref&gt;Uddgren, (1924), p.&amp;nbsp;86&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|  The losses of native Africans working or fighting for the two sides during the battle were not recorded. It is estimated that during the Anglo-Boer War, 100,000 black and Coloured people served with the British forces either as combatants, scouts, spies, transport and despatch riders or servants (of which, 10,000 were armed). The Boer force included an estimated 10,000 Africans, although they rarely carried weapons.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://yourarchives.nationalarchives.gov.uk/index.php?title=The_Role_of_Africans_in_the_South_African_War |title=The Role of Africans in the South African War |publisher=National Archives (UK) |accessdate=11 November 2010 }}{{dead link|date=October 2016 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;|group=&quot;Note&quot;}}

===Strategic consequences===
{{Main article|Siege of Kimberley#Relief|l1=Relief of Kimberley|Battle of Paardeberg}}
The week from 10 December to 17 December 1899 rapidly became known to troops in the field—and to politicians in Britain—as &quot;[[Black Week]]&quot;, during which the British suffered three defeats: the battles of [[Battle of Stormberg|Stormberg]] in the Cape Midlands and [[Battle of Colenso|Colenso]] in Natal, as well as the Battle of Magersfontein.&lt;ref&gt;Barbary, (1975), p. 47&lt;/ref&gt; The defeat at Magersfontein{{#tag:ref|The battle is commemorated with a [[Pipe band|pipe]] [[March (music)|march]] called &quot;The Highland Brigade at Magersfontein&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pipetunes.ca/composers.asp?pg=Details&amp;composerID=23|title=Pipetunes|author=John McLellan, Dunoon (Composer)|publisher=pipetunes.ca|accessdate=28 October 2010| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20100928102204/http://pipetunes.ca/composers.asp?pg=Details&amp;composerID=23| archivedate= 28 September 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;| group=&quot;Note&quot;}} caused much consternation in Britain, particularly in Scotland, where the losses to the Highland regiments were keenly felt. Wauchope was well known in Scotland, having stood as a Parliamentary candidate for [[Midlothian]] in the [[United Kingdom general election, 1892|general election of 1892]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Baird&quot;&gt;Baird, (1900), p. 166&lt;/ref&gt;

The reverberations of the Black Week defeats led to the hasty approval of large reinforcements being sent to South Africa, from both Britain and the Dominions. Although Cronje temporarily defeated the British and held up their advance, General [[Frederick Roberts, 1st Earl Roberts|Lord Roberts]] was appointed as overall Commander in Chief in South Africa; he took personal command on this front, and at the head of an army reinforced to 25,000 men, he relieved Kimberley on 15 February 1900. Cronje's retreating army was surrounded and forced to surrender at the [[Battle of Paardeberg]] on 27 February 1900.&lt;ref&gt;Kruger, (1960)&lt;/ref&gt;

Lord Methuen later salvaged his reputation and career through successes he achieved against [[George Henri Anne-Marie Victor de Villebois-Mareuil|George Villebois-Mareuil]] at the [[Battle of Boschoff]].&lt;ref&gt;Miller, (1999), pp. 185–186&lt;/ref&gt; However, he was the only general [[Battle of Tweebosch|captured]] by the Boers during the war.&lt;ref&gt;Pakenham, (1979), p. 583&lt;/ref&gt;

===Victoria Cross awards===
Three [[Victoria Cross]] citations were made for the action at Magersfontein:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/documentsonline/victoriacross.asp |title=Victoria Cross Registers |publisher=National Archives (UK)|accessdate= 11 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* Lieutenant [[Henry Edward Manning Douglas]]. Royal Army Medical Corps
* Corporal [[John Shaul]]. Highland Light Infantry
* Captain [[Ernest Beachcroft Beckwith Towse]]. Gordon Highlanders&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;In the UK National Archive Victoria Cross listings (See [http://www.london-gazette.co.uk/issues/27208/pages/4196 London Gazette, 6 July 1900]), the local for Captain Towse's award is incorrectly listed as ''Majesfontein'' instead of ''Magersfontein.''  The regiment and date are correct.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Gallery|align=center
| title  = The Battle of Magersfontein: 11 December 1899
| lines  = 5
| width  = 140
| height = 140
|File:Black Watch at Magersfontein.jpg|alt1=Painting of a rugged group of soldiers gathering their dead and wounded|Contemporary painting of the Black Watch at Magersfontein
||alt2=Boer Commando men dressed in mufti armed with rifles|Boer Commando in typical dress as would have been encountered at Magersfontein
|File:The Second Anglo - Boer War, South Africa 1899 - 1902 Q82943.jpg|alt3=View of a naval gun on carriage from behind as shot is being fired|A 4.7&amp;nbsp;inch Naval gun known as ''Joe Chamberlain'' firing at Magersfontein.
|File:MunitionWagon.jpg|alt4=B&amp;W photo of Boers on an ammunition wagon under a tarpaulin|Boers on an ammunition wagon
|File:Armoured train 1899-2.jpg|alt5=Inside view of British soldiers firing through gun slits from within an armoured train coach|British troops in an armoured train, as was brought forward from Modder River
|File:BL 5 inch Howitzer Second Boer War LOC LC-USZ62-48652.jpg|alt6=Alternate Text 4|British BL 5&quot; howitzer as used at Magersfontein
|File:Battle of Magersfontein USLoC.jpg|alt7=black and white image of a 5&quot; field gun being towed by horses|Contemporary British sketch of the battle
}}

==Order of battle==

===British Forces===
{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
| style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot; |'''[[1st Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|1st Infantry Division]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Maurice, 1998b, Vol. 7&quot;&gt;Maurice, (1998b), Vol. 7.&lt;/ref&gt;'''||Lieutenant-General Lord [[Paul Sanford Methuen, 3rd Baron Methuen|Paul Sanford Methuen]] &lt;small&gt;GCB, GCMG, GCVO&lt;/small&gt;
|-
| style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;|'''Division Troops'''
|-
|A Squadron, [[Life Guards (British Army)|Life Guards]]||12th Lancers (detached from the 1st Cavalry Brigade)
|-
|18th Field Battery, [[Royal Artillery]]||62nd Field Battery, Royal Artillery
|-
|65th Field Battery, Royal Artillery||[[G Battery, Royal Horse Artillery]]
|-
|11th &amp; 26th Field Companies, [[Royal Engineers]]&lt;ref name=&quot;GGS&quot;/&gt;||No 7 Field Hospital
|-
|Balloon Section, Royal Engineers||Detachment, [[Army Service Corps]]
|-
|Ammunition Column||Signals Detachment
|-
| style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;|'''Infantry Brigades'''
|-
| width = &quot;400pt&quot;|'''1st (Guards) Brigade''': Major-General [[Pole Baronets|Reginald Pole-Carew]]||width=&quot;400pt&quot;|'''9th Brigade''': Major-General [[Charles W. H. Douglas|Charles Whittingham Douglas]]
|-
|3rd Battalion, [[Grenadier Guards]]||1st Battalion [[Northumberland Fusiliers]]
|-
|1st Battalion, [[Coldstream Guards]]||1st Battalion [[Loyal North Lancashire Regiment]]
|-
|2nd Battalion, Coldstream Guards||2nd Battalion [[Northamptonshire Regiment]]
|-
|1st Battalion, [[Scots Guards]]||2nd Battalion [[King's Own Yorkshire Light Infantry]]
|-
|No 18 Bearer Company&lt;ref name=&quot;GGS&quot;/&gt;||Volunteer Bearer Company&lt;ref name=&quot;GGS&quot;/&gt;
|-
|No 18 Field Hospital&lt;ref name=GGS&gt;German General Staff (1998), Vol II, p. 238&lt;/ref&gt;||No 19 Field Hospital&lt;ref name=&quot;GGS&quot;/&gt;
|-
|No 19 Company Army Service Corps&lt;ref name=&quot;GGS&quot;/&gt;||No 20 Company Army Service Corps&lt;ref name=&quot;GGS&quot;/&gt;
|-
|}

The 3rd Highland Brigade was attached to the 1st Infantry Division from the 9th Infantry Division&lt;ref&gt;Maurice, (1998b), Vol. 8&lt;/ref&gt;
{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
| style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot; |'''3rd (Highland) Brigade'''||Major General [[Andrew Gilbert Wauchope|A.G. Wauchope]] &lt;small&gt;CB&lt;/small&gt;
|-
| width = &quot;400pt&quot;|2nd Battalion, [[Black Watch]]||width=&quot;400pt&quot;|1st Battalion, [[Highland Light Infantry]]
|-
|2nd Battalion, [[Seaforth Highlanders]]||1st Battalion, [[Argyll &amp; Sutherland Highlanders]]
|-
|No 1 Bearer Company&lt;ref name=&quot;GGS&quot;/&gt;||No 8 Field Hospital&lt;ref name=&quot;GGS&quot;/&gt;
|-
|No 14 Company, Army Service Corps&lt;ref name=&quot;GGS&quot;/&gt;||
|-
|}

The below units were deployed for communication line protection duties and as such were under command of Major-General Methuen.&lt;ref&gt;Maurice, (1998b), Vol. 5&lt;/ref&gt;
{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
| style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;|'''Communication protection duties
|-
| width = &quot;400pt&quot;|9th [[Lancers]]||width=&quot;400pt&quot;|2nd Battalion, [[Yorkshire Light Infantry]] (Two companies)
|-
|[[Rimington's Guides]]||
|-
|}

===Boer Forces===
{|class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
| style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot; |'''South Western Military Force'''||General [[Piet Cronjé]]
|-
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;|&lt;small&gt;(Figures represent strengths at time of mobilisation, actual strengths deployed at Magersfontein were lower)&lt;ref name=&quot;Maurice, 1998b, Vol. 7&quot;/&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
|-
| style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;|'''Commandos under command of General A. Cronje'''&lt;ref name=&quot;MAURMAP&quot;&gt;Maurice, (1998b), Vol 5, Map 13 and 13(a)&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|{{flagicon|Transvaal}} [[Soutpansberg|Zoutpansberg]] Commando &lt;small&gt;(1,287)&lt;/small&gt; ||{{flagicon|Transvaal}} Part of [[Potchefstroom]] Commando &lt;small&gt;(Total of 3,000)&lt;/small&gt;
|-
| width = &quot;400pt&quot;|{{flagicon|Orange Free State}} [[Fauresmith]] Commando &lt;small&gt;(1,560)&lt;/small&gt;||width=&quot;400pt&quot;|{{flagicon|Orange Free State}} [[Ladybrand]] Commando &lt;small&gt;(1,113)&lt;/small&gt;
|-
|{{flagicon|Orange Free State}} Elements of Orange Free State Burghers||{{flagicon|Transvaal}} [[Transvaalse Staatsartillerie|Transvaal State Artillery]] section. (2x [[7.7 cm FK 96]] Guns)
|-
| style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;|'''Commandos under command of General [[Piet Cronjé]]'''&lt;ref name=&quot;MAURMAP&quot;/&gt;
|-
|{{flagicon|Orange Free State}} [[Hoopstad]] Commando &lt;small&gt;(799)&lt;/small&gt;||{{flagicon|Orange Free State}} [[Kroonstad]] Commando &lt;small&gt;(2,561)&lt;/small&gt;
|-
|{{flagicon|Orange Free State}} [[Bloemhof]] Commando &lt;small&gt;(800)&lt;/small&gt;  ||{{flagicon|Orange Free State}} [[Boshof]] Commando &lt;small&gt;(1,030)&lt;/small&gt;
|-
| colspan=&quot;2&quot;|{{flagicon|Sweden|1844}} {{flagicon|Norway|1844}}  Scandinavian Volunteer Corps &lt;small&gt;(100)&lt;/small&gt;
|-
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; |{{flagicon|Transvaal}} [[Transvaalse Staatsartillerie|Transvaal State Artillery]] section. (2x [[7.7 cm FK 96]] Guns and 2x [[QF 1 pounder pom-pom]] guns)
|-
| style=&quot;background:#efefef;&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;|'''Commandos under command of General [[Koos de la Rey]]'''&lt;ref name=&quot;MAURMAP&quot;/&gt;
|-
|{{flagicon|Orange Free State}} [[Wolmaransstad]] Commando &lt;small&gt;(400)&lt;/small&gt;||{{flagicon|Transvaal}}  Part of [[Potchefstroom]] Commando
|-
|{{flagicon|Transvaal}} [[Lichtenburg, North West|Lichtenburg]] Commando &lt;small&gt;(850)&lt;/small&gt;||{{flagicon|Orange Free State}} [[Jacobsdal]] Commando &lt;small&gt;(250)&lt;/small&gt; (under command of General Albrecht)
|-
| colspan=&quot;2&quot; |{{flagicon|Transvaal}} [[Transvaalse Staatsartillerie|Transvaal State Artillery]] section. (1x [[7.7 cm FK 96]] Gun and 3x [[QF 1 pounder pom-pom]] guns)
|-
|}

==Notes==
;Footnotes
{{Reflist|group=Note}}

;Citations
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
{{Refbegin}}
* {{cite web|last=Baird|first=William|title=General Wauchope|url=https://archive.org/stream/generalwauchope00bairuoft/generalwauchope00bairuoft_djvu.txt|publisher=Oliphant, Anderson and Ferrier|year=1900|accessdate=26 October 2010}}
* {{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=EaUNAQAAIAAJ|author=Barbary, James|title=The Boer War|year=1975|publisher=Puffin Books|location=Harmondsworth|isbn=978-0-14-030697-2}}
* {{cite book|last=Conan Doyle|first=Arthur|authorlink=Arthur Conan Doyle|title=The Great Boer War|publisher=Smith, Elder &amp; Co|location=London|year=1900|edition=8th Impression|isbn=0-86977-074-8}}
* {{cite book|last=Creswicke|first=Louis|title=South Africa and the Transvaal War|publisher=T.C. &amp; E.C. Jack|location=Edinburgh|year=1900|edition=1st|volume=Volume 2: From the Commencement of the War to the Battle of Colenso, 15 Dec 1899|oclc=248490510}}
* {{cite journal|journal=South African Military History Journal|volume= 6|issue= 3|title=The Medical Aspect of the Anglo-Boer War, 1899–1902 Part ll|first=Professor J.C.|last=de Villiers|url=http://samilitaryhistory.org/vol063jc.html|date=June 1984}}
* {{cite book|title=The Boer War 1899-1902|author=Fremont-Barnes, Gregory|publisher=Osprey Publishing|location=Oxford|year=2003|isbn=1-84176-396-9|page=86}}
* {{cite book|last=German General Staff|series=The War in South Africa: October 1899 to February 1900| title=The Advance to Pretoria after Paardeberg, the Upper Tugela Campaign, etc| publisher=The Battle Press |location=Nashville |year=1998| origyear=1st. pub. 1906 (Historical section of the Great General Staff, Berlin)| isbn=0-89839-285-3| lastauthoramp=y}}
* {{cite book|title=Boer Commando: 1876–1902|last1=Knight|first1= Ian|last2=Ruggeri|first2= Raffaele|isbn=1-84176-648-8|publisher=Osprey Publishing|location=Oxford|year=2004}}
* {{cite book|title=Good-bye Dolly Grey: The Story of the Boer War|author=Kruger, Rayne|year=1960|publisher=Lippincott| oclc=220929457}}
* {{cite book|last=Maurice|first=Major-General Sir Frederick|series=History of the War in South Africa 1899–1902| title=Volume 1| publisher=Naval and Military Press |location=East Sussex |year=1998a| origyear=1st. pub. 1906| oclc=154660583| lastauthoramp=y}}
* {{cite book|last=Maurice|first=Major-General Sir Frederick|series=History of the War in South Africa 1899–1902| title=Maps: Volumes 5 – 8| publisher=Naval and Military Press |location=East Sussex |year=1998b| origyear=1st. pub. 1906| oclc=154660583| lastauthoramp=y}}
* {{cite book|last=Meintjies|first=Johannes|title=De La Rey-Lion of the West: A Biography|publisher=H. Keartland|year=1966}}
* {{cite book|title=Lord Methuen and the British Army: Failure and Redemption in South Africa|first=Stephen M.|last=Miller|year=1999|isbn=0-7146-4904-X|publisher=Routledge|location=London}}
* {{cite journal|url=http://samilitaryhistory.org/vol104sm.html|last=Miller|first=Stephen|journal=Military History Journal|volume= 10|issue= 4|title=Lord Methuen and the British Advance to the Modder River|publisher=The South African Military History Society|date=4 December 1996}}
* {{cite book|last=Pakenham|first=Thomas|title=The Boer War|publisher=Jonathan Ball|year=1979|isbn=0-86850-046-1|location=Johannesburg}}
* {{cite book |author=Ralph, Julian |publisher=Frederick A. Stokes |location=New York|year=1900 |title=Towards Pretoria; a Record of the War Between Briton and Boer, to the Relief of Kimberley|chapter=Chapter XIX: Battle of Maaghersfontein|oclc=1179791}}
* {{cite book|title=The Times History of the War in South Africa, 1899-1902|location=London|year=1902|publisher=[[The Times]]|last=Tallboy|first=G.P.}}
* {{cite book|url=http://www.gutenberg.org/files/15699/15699-h/15699-h.htm|title=A Handbook of the Boer War With General Map of South Africa and 18 Sketch Maps and Plans|author=Tufnell, Wyndham Frederick|location=London; Aldershot|year=1910|publisher=Gale &amp; Polden|oclc=504434575}}
* {{cite book|last=Uddgren|first=H.E.|title=Hjältarna vid Magersfontein|publisher=Uddevalla |year=1924|oclc=105930561|language=Swedish|location=Stockholm}}
* {{cite book|last=Winquist|first=Alan H|publisher=A. A. Balkema|year=1978|isbn=0-86961-096-1|title=Scandinavians and South Africa: Their Impact on the Cultural, Social and Economic Development of Pre-1902 South Africa|location=Cape Town}}
* {{cite journal|url=http://samilitaryhistory.org/3/03julnl.html|date=July 2003|journal=South African Military History Society (SAMHS)|title=Newsletter}}
{{Refend}}

==Further reading==
{{Refbegin}}
* {{cite journal|last=Barbour|first=Fiona|title=Who was Magersfontein's 'Young Unknown Scottish Bugler'?|journal=The South African Military History Society – Military History Journal |date=December 1979|volume= 4|issue= 6|url=http://rapidttp.co.za/milhist/vol046fb.html}}
* {{cite book|title=Geskiedenis van die Tweede Vryheidsoorlog (History of the Second War of Liberation)|author=Breytenbach, JH|publisher=Protea|isbn=978-0-7970-2160-0|year=1983}}
* {{cite book|last=Cowan|first=Paul|title=Scottish Military Disasters|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Yx4OAQAAMAAJ|isbn=1-903238-96-X|publisher=New Wilson Publishing|year=2008}}
* {{cite book|title=Disease and Empire: The Health of European Troops in the Conquest of Africa|first=Philip D.|last=Curtin|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=1998|isbn=0-521-59835-4}}
* {{cite book|title=The Life of Major-General Wauchope|last=Douglas|first=George|publisher=Kessinger Publishing|year=2006|isbn=1-4286-0456-1|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=9fcPrpGHfK4C}}
* {{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=C6YNAQAAIAAJ|title=The Battle of Magersfontein, 11th December, 1899|author=Duxbury, George Reginald|publisher=[[McGregor Museum]]|year=1997|origyear=1977|isbn=0-620-21125-3|location=Kimberley}}
* {{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=AGhzAAAAMAAJ|title=The War Diary of Burgher Jack Lane, 16 November 1899 to 27 February 1900|publisher=Van Riebeeck Society|year=2001|isbn=0-9584112-8-X|author=Lane, Jack}}
* {{cite book|title=Field Sanitation|author=MacDonald, Ronald St. John|publisher=Frowde, Hodder and Stoughton|location=London|year=1918|oclc=287182259}}
* {{cite book|title=The Siege of Kimberley and the Battle of Magersfontein|publisher=Ravan Press|year=2001|last=Robbins|first=David|isbn=0-86975-532-3}}
* {{cite journal|date=June 2001|title=The Wartime Correspondence of Jeannot Weinberg|publisher=The South African Military History Society|volume= 12|issue= 1|journal=Military History Journal|last=Saks|first=David}}
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Battle of Magersfontein}}
* {{cite web|url=http://britishbattles.com/great-boer-war/magersfontein.htm|title=The Battle of Magersfontein|publisher=BritishBattles.com}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2010}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Magersfontein, Battle Of}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1899]]
[[Category:1899 in the Cape Colony]]
[[Category:Battles of the Second Boer War]]
[[Category:Battles involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Kimberley, Northern Cape]]
[[Category:Karoo]]</text>
      <sha1>po98f0rck3z2xl0sunpewqrc59eobo0</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
