<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of the Bowling Alley</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>28057568</id>
    <revision>
      <id>747221920</id>
      <parentid>736698861</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-01T04:16:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Gorthian</username>
        <id>15179295</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Disambiguating links to [[Riverside, New Jersey]] (link changed to [[Riverside Township, New Jersey]]) using [[User:Qwertyytrewqqwerty/DisamAssist|DisamAssist]].</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="44194">{{good article}}
{{Coord|36|04|N|128|32|E|region:KR_type:city(2,500,000)|display=title}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict   = Battle of the Bowling Alley
| partof     = the [[Battle of Pusan Perimeter]]
| image      = [[File:Tank Action in the Bowling Alley.jpg|300px|alt=A tank advances into a valley]]
| caption    = US tanks advance into the Bowling Alley on August 21.
| date       = August 12–25, 1950
| place      = Gasan, [[Chilgok]], [[South Korea]]
| result     = United Nations victory
| combatant1 = 
{{flag|United Nations}}
*{{flag|South Korea|1948|size=23px}}
*{{Flag|United States|1912}}
| combatant2 = {{Flag|North Korea}}
| commander1 = {{Flagicon|South Korea|1948|size=23px}} [[Paik Sun Yup]]&lt;br&gt;{{Flagicon|US|1912}} [[John H. Michaelis]]&lt;br&gt;{{Flagicon|US|1912}} [[Paul L. Freeman, Jr.]]
| commander2 = Choi Yong Chin&lt;br&gt;Hong Rim&lt;br&gt;Paik Son Choi
| units1     = {{Flagicon|South Korea|1948|size=23px}} [[1st Infantry Division (South Korea)|1st Division]]
*11th Regiment
*12th Regiment
*13th Regiment
*10th Regiment
{{Flagicon|United States|1912}} [[23rd Infantry Regiment (United States)|23rd Infantry Regiment]]
{{Flagicon|United States|1912}} [[27th Infantry Regiment (United States)|27th Infantry Regiment]]
| units2      = [[13th Division (North Korea)|13th Division]]&lt;br&gt;[[1st Division (North Korea)|1st Division]]&lt;br&gt;[[NK 15th Division|15th Division]]
| strength1   = {{flagicon|South Korea|1948|size=23px}}: 7,500&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|USA|1912}}: ~5,000
| strength2   = 16,000&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple255&quot;/&gt;
| casualties1 = {{flagicon|South Korea|1948|size=23px}}: 2,300 killed&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|USA|1912}}: 8 killed, 70 wounded
| casualties2 = 5,690 killed&lt;br&gt;13 [[T-34]] tanks&lt;br&gt;6 [[SU-76]]s&lt;ref name=&quot;Mil10221&quot;/&gt;
| campaignbox = 
{{Campaignbox Korean War}}
{{Campaignbox Pusan Perimeter}}
}}
In the '''Battle of the Bowling Alley ''' (August 12–25, 1950), [[United Nations]] (UN) forces defeated [[Democratic People's Republic of Korea|North Korean]] forces early in the [[Korean War]] near the city of [[Taegu]], [[South Korea]].  The battle took place in a narrow valley, dubbed the &quot;Bowling Alley&quot;, which was north of Taegu. It followed a week of fighting between the [[Korean People's Army]] (KPA) [[13th Division (North Korea)|13th Division]] and the [[Republic of Korea Army]]'s (ROK) [[1st Infantry Division (South Korea)|1st Division]] along the latter's last defensible line in the hills north of the city. Reinforcements, including the [[US Army]]'s [[27th Infantry Regiment (United States)|27th]] and [[23rd Infantry Regiment (United States)|23rd Infantry Regiment]]s were committed to bolster the South Koreans' defenses. This battle and several others were smaller engagements of the [[Battle of Pusan Perimeter]].

For another week, North Korean divisions launched all the troops they had in massed attacks against the ROK and US lines. Their attacks, which usually occurred at night and were supported by armor and artillery, advanced with infantry and tanks in close support of one another. Each North Korean attack ran into well-established UN lines, where US tanks, mines and entrenched infantry were positioned to counter them. Strikes by US aircraft ravaged the attacking North Koreans. The fighting was fierce with many casualties on both sides, particularly where the North and South Koreans fought one another. The repeated attacks eventually broke and pushed back the North Korean forces. They continued their push against the Pusan Perimeter until they were outflanked in the [[Battle of Inchon]].

==Background==
===Outbreak of war===
[[File:Task Force Smith.jpg|thumb|240px|alt=Soldiers carrying their bags off of a train in a Korean train station|Task Force Smith arrives in South Korea.]]
Following the invasion of the South Korea by North Korea on June 25, 1950, the UN voted to use force to defend South Korea. The United States, a member of the UN, simultaneously committed ground forces to the Korean peninsula with the goal of pushing back the North Korean invasion and preventing South Korea from collapsing. But US forces in the [[Far East]] had been steadily decreasing since the end of [[World War II]], five years earlier, and at the time the closest force was the [[24th Infantry Division (United States)|24th Infantry Division]], headquartered in Japan. The division was understrength, and most of its equipment was antiquated due to reductions in military spending. Nevertheless, the 24th was ordered to South Korea.&lt;ref name=&quot;Var3&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Varhola|2000|p=3}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The 24th Infantry Division was the first US unit sent into Korea with the mission to take the initial &quot;shock&quot; of North Korean advances, delaying much larger North Korean units to buy time to allow reinforcements to arrive.&lt;ref name=Alexander52&gt;{{harvnb|Alexander|2003|p=52}}&lt;/ref&gt; The division fought for several weeks while the [[1st Cavalry Division (United States)|1st Cavalry]], [[7th Infantry Division (United States)|7th Infantry]] and [[25th Infantry Division (United States)|25th Infantry]] Divisions and [[Eighth United States Army]] supporting units were arriving.&lt;ref name=Alexander52/&gt; Advance elements of the 24th were badly defeated in the [[Battle of Osan]] on July 5, the first encounter between American and North Korean forces.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Catchpole|2001|p=15}}&lt;/ref&gt; For the first month after the defeat at Osan, the 24th Infantry Division was repeatedly defeated and forced south by superior North Korean numbers and equipment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Var4&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Varhola|2000|p=4}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Alex90&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Alexander|2003|p=90}}&lt;/ref&gt; The regiments of the division were systematically pushed south in engagements around [[Battle of Chochiwon|Chochiwon]], [[Battle of Chonan|Chonan]], and [[Battle of Pyongtaek|Pyongtaek]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Var4&quot;/&gt; The 24th was finally annihilated in the [[Battle of Taejon]], but was able to delay the North Korean forces until July 20.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alex105&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Alexander|2003|p=105}}&lt;/ref&gt; By that time, the Eighth Army's force of combat troops were roughly equal to North Korean forces attacking the region, with new UN units arriving every day.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fehr103&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Fehrenbach|2001|p=103}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===North Korean advance===
[[File:Pusan Perimeter.jpg|thumb|300px|Tactical map of the Pusan Perimeter in August 1950. The fight at P'ohang-dong occurred between North and South Korean forces on the northeastern line.|alt=A map of a perimeter on the southeastern tip of a land mass]]
After the fight at Taejon, UN forces were pushed back repeatedly before finally halting the North Korean advance in a series of engagements in the southern section of the country. Forces of the 3rd Battalion, [[29th Infantry Regiment (United States)|29th Infantry]], newly arrived in the country, were wiped out at [[Hadong]] in a [[Hadong Ambush|coordinated ambush]] by North Korean forces on July 27, opening a pass to the Pusan area from the west.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple221&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Appleman|1998|p=221}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Alexander|2003|p=114}}&lt;/ref&gt; Soon after, North Korean forces took [[Chinju]], east of Hadong, pushing back the US [[19th Infantry Regiment (United States)|19th Infantry Regiment]] and leaving routes to Pusan open to direct North Korean attacks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Catch24&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Catchpole|2001|p=24}}&lt;/ref&gt; The UN formations were subsequently able to defeat the North Koreans in the [[Battle of the Notch]] on August 2, halting their advance from the west. Suffering mounting losses, the KPA force withdrew for several days to re-equip and receive reinforcements. This granted both sides a reprieve to prepare for the attack on the Pusan Perimeter.&lt;ref name=&quot;Catchpole 2001 25&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Catchpole|2001|p=25}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Appleman|1998|p=247}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Taegu===
Meanwhile, the Eighth Army commander [[Lieutenant General (United States)|Lieutenant General]] [[Walton Walker]] had established [[Taegu]] as his headquarters.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fehr135&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Fehrenbach|2001|p=135}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the center of the Pusan Perimeter line, Taegu stood at the entrance to the [[Naktong River]] valley, an area where North Korean forces could advance in large numbers in close support. The natural barriers provided by the Naktong River to the south and the mountainous terrain to the north converged around Taegu, a transportation hub and the last major South Korean city aside from Pusan itself to remain in UN hands.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Appleman|1998|p=335}}&lt;/ref&gt; From south to north, the city was defended by the US 1st Cavalry Division, the ROK 1st Division and the [[6th Infantry Division (South Korea)|6th Division]], which were under the command of [[ROK II Corps]]. The 1st Cavalry Division was spread out along a long line on the Naktong River to the south, with its [[5th Cavalry Regiment (United States)|5th Cavalry]] and [[8th Cavalry Regiment (United States)|8th Cavalry]] regiments holding a {{convert|24000|m|sp=us|adj=on}} line along the river south of Waegwan, facing west. The [[7th Cavalry Regiment (United States)|7th Cavalry]] held position to the east in reserve, along with artillery forces, ready to reinforce anywhere a North Korean crossing could be attempted. The ROK 1st Division held a northwest-facing line in the mountains immediately north of the city while the ROK 6th Division held position to the east, guarding the narrow valley holding the Kunwi road into the Pusan Perimeter area.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple337&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Appleman|1998|p=337}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Five North Korean divisions amassed around Taegu to oppose the UN forces in the city. From south to north, the [[10th Division (North Korea)|10th]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple253&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Appleman|1998|p=253}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[3rd Division (North Korea)|3rd]], [[15th Division (North Korea)|15th]], 13th,&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple254&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Appleman|1998|p=254}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[1st Division (North Korea)|1st North Korean Division]]s occupied a wide line encircling Taegu from Tuksong-dong and around [[Waegwan]] to Kunwi.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leckie112&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Leckie|1996|p=112}}&lt;/ref&gt; The North Korean army planned to use the natural corridor of the Naktong River valley from [[Sangju]] to Taegu as its main axis of attack for the next push south, so the KPA divisions all eventually moved through this valley, crossing the Naktong at different areas along the low ground.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Appleman|1998|p=336}}&lt;/ref&gt; Elements of the [[NK 105th Armored Division]] also supported the attack.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple337&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Catch31&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Catchpole|2001|p=31}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Prelude==
===US forces assemble===
During mid-August, the US 27th Infantry Regiment was mopping up North Korean resistance from the southern part of the [[Battle of Naktong Bulge|Naktong Bulge]] area to counter a North Korean attack there. The regiment, temporarily attached to the US 24th Infantry Division, was recalled by the Eighth Army when a new North Korean threat formed to the north of Taegu, alarming Walker. Acting on the threat, Walker relieved the regiment from the 24th Infantry Division on August 14 and the next day ordered it northward to [[Kyongsan]] as a [[military reserve|reserve force]]. Arriving at Kyongsan on August 16, [[Colonel (US)|Colonel]] [[John H. Michaelis]], 27th Infantry's commander, was ordered to reconnoiter routes east, north, northwest, and west of Kyongsan and counter any North Korean attacks from these directions. During the day, two North Korean [[T-34]] tanks came through the ROK 1st Division lines {{convert|12|mi}} north of Taegu at [[Tabu-dong]], but South Korean [[Bazooka#Korean War|3.5-inch bazooka]] teams knocked out both of them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple353&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Appleman|1998|p=353}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ROK 1st Division, also in the area, was ordered to assemble in the hills around the road and wait for reinforcements or make a [[last stand]] if needed to prevent the North Koreans from coming any closer to Taegu. To its east was the ROK 6th Division and to its west was the Naktong River.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mil10220&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Millett|2010|p=220}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Maj. Gen. Paik Sun Yup.jpg|thumb|left|alt=An Asian man in a military uniform in an outdoor setting|ROK [[Brigadier General]] [[Paik Sun Yup]].]]
At 12:00 the next day, August 17, Eighth Army ordered the 27th Infantry to move its headquarters and a reinforced [[battalion]] &quot;without delay&quot; to a point across the [[Kumho River]] {{convert|3|mi}} north of Taegu on the road from Tabu-dong to Sangju &quot;to secure Taegu from enemy penetration&quot; from that direction.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mil2000464&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Millett|2000|p=464}}&lt;/ref&gt; South Korean sources reported a North Korean regiment, led by six T-34 tanks, had entered the village of Kumhwa, {{convert|2|mi}} north of Tabu-dong.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple353&quot;/&gt; The 1st Battalion, 27th Infantry, a [[platoon]] of the Heavy Mortar Company, and most of the 8th Field Artillery Battalion moved north to [[Ch'ilgok]] where the ROK 1st Division command post was located.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mil2000464&quot;/&gt; By nightfall, the entire 27th Regiment was north of Taegu on the Tabu-dong road, reinforced by C [[Company (military)|Company]], 73rd Tank Battalion.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple353&quot;/&gt; US Army commanders also ordered the 37th Field Artillery Battalion to move from the area around [[Kyongju]] and [[P'ohang-dong]], where a [[Battle of P'ohang-dong|heavy battle]] had been in progress for days, for attachment to the US 27th Infantry Regiment in order to reinforce the 8th Field Artillery Battalion above Taegu. It arrived there the next day.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mil2000464&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple354&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Appleman|1998|p=354}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the front, ROK 1st Division commander [[Brigadier General]] [[Paik Sun-yup]] assumed senior command of the 27th Infantry and the other US units, to the chagrin of Michaelis.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mil10221&quot;/&gt;

===North Korean forces assemble===
In its engagements during the Perimeter battle, the KPA 13th Division, with 9,500 men,&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple255&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Appleman|1998|p=255}}&lt;/ref&gt; had forced South Korean troops into the Tabu-dong corridor and started advancing on Taegu.&lt;ref name=&quot;Paik36&quot;/&gt; This division had battled the ROK 11th and 12th Regiments in the [[Yuhak-san]] area for a week before it broke through to the corridor on August 17.&lt;ref name=&quot;Paik34&quot;/&gt; A regimental commander of the division said later it suffered 1,500 casualties in the process. On August 18, the 13th Division was concentrated mostly west of the road just north of Tabu-dong.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple354&quot;/&gt;

To the west of the KPA 13th Division, the KPA 15th Division with 5,000 men&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple255&quot;/&gt; was also deployed on Yuhak-san.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mil2000466&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Millett|2000|p=466}}&lt;/ref&gt; It, too, had begun battling the ROK 1st Division, but thus far only in minor engagements. The North Korean High Command then ordered the KPA 15th Division to move from its position northwest of Tabu-dong eastward, to the [[Yongch'on]] front, where the KPA [[8th Division (North Korea)|8th Division]] had tried and failed to advance to the Taegu lateral corridor. The KPA 15th Division left the Yuhak-san area on August 20. Meanwhile, the KPA 1st Division, to the east of the 13th, advanced to the Kunwi area, {{convert|25|mi}} north of Taegu. The North Korean command ordered it to proceed to the Tabu-dong area and maneuver astride the 13th Division for the attack on Taegu down the Tabu-dong corridor. At the same time, the North Koreans received their only substantial tank reinforcements during the Pusan Perimeter fighting.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mil2000464&quot;/&gt; On August 15, the KPA [[105th Armored Division (North Korea)|105th Armored Division]] received 21 new T-34 tanks and 200 troop replacements, which it distributed to the divisions attacking Taegu. The tank regiment with the KPA 13th Division reportedly had 14 T-34 tanks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mil10221&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple354&quot;/&gt;

On August 18, the KPA 13th Division was astride the Sangju–Taegu road just above Tabu-dong and only {{convert|13|mi}} from Taegu. The Eighth Army ordered the 27th Infantry Regiment to attack north along the road to counter the threat.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mil10221&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Millett|2010|p=221}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, two regiments of the ROK 1st Division were to attack along high ground on either side of the road.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mil2000464&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple354&quot;/&gt; The plan called for a limited-objective attack to restore the ROK 1st Division lines in the vicinity of [[Sokchok]], a village {{convert|4|mi}} north of Tabu-dong. [[M26 Pershing]] tanks of C Company, 73rd Tank Battalion, and two batteries of the 37th Field Artillery Battalion were to support the 27th Infantry in the attack.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple355&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Appleman|1998|p=355}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Terrain===
{{wide image|The Bowling Alley.jpg|600px|alt=A long, narrow valley|The Bowling Alley, 1950}}
In front of the 27th Infantry position, the [[Populus|poplar]]-lined Taegu–Sangju road ran northward in the narrow mountain valley. A stream on the west closely paralleled the road, which was nearly straight on a north-south axis through the 27th Infantry position and for some distance northward. This stretch of the road later became known as the &quot;Bowling Alley.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple356&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Appleman|1998|p=356}}&lt;/ref&gt; About {{convert|1|mi}} in front of the 27th Infantry position the road forked at a small village called [[Ch'onp'yong-dong]]; the western prong was the main Sangju road, the eastern one was the road to [[Kunwi]]. At the road fork, the Sangju road bends to the northwest in a long curve. The village of Sinjumak lay on this curve a short distance north of the fork. Hills protected it against direct fire from the 27th Infantry position. It was there that the North Korean tanks remained hidden during the daytime.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple356&quot;/&gt;

Rising from the valley on the west side was the Yuhak-san mountain range which swept up to a height of {{convert|2700|ft}}. On the east, a similar mountain range rose to a height of {{convert|2,400|ft}}, culminating {{convert|2.5|mi}} southward in a mountain called [[Ka-san]], more than {{convert|2,900|ft}} high at its walled summit. The Kunwi and Sangju roads from the northeast and northwest entered the natural and easy corridor between Yuhak-san and Ka-san at Ch'onp'yong-dong, leading into the Taegu basin. The battles in the Bowling Alley occurred south of this road junction.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple356&quot;/&gt;

==Battle==
===Deadlock===
The ROK 1st Infantry Division, with 7,500 men&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Paik|1992|p=28}}&lt;/ref&gt; had held the line around the Bowling Alley since August 12.&lt;ref name=&quot;Paik34&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Paik|1992|p=34}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Bowling Alley area was selected because of its advantageous high ground which provided natural barriers to funnel North Korean troops into smaller fronts where South Korean defenses could attack them from the high ground in concealed positions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Paik35&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Paik|1992|p=35}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the meantime, the KPA 3rd, 13th, and 15th Divisions were advancing south and preparing to close on Taegu.&lt;ref name=&quot;Paik36&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Paik|1992|p=36}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Alex144&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Alexander|2003|p=144}}&lt;/ref&gt; The KPA 13th Division converged on the Tabu-dong corridor and a vicious melee ensued between the North and South Korean troops, with ROK 1st Division's 11th, 12th, and 13th regiments committed against the KPA 13th Division's 19th, 21st and 23rd regiments.&lt;ref name=&quot;Paik39&quot;/&gt; The fight became a [[Attrition warfare|battle of attrition]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Paik37&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Paik|1992|p=37}}&lt;/ref&gt; As the two sides closed on one another, the battle took a brutal turn by August 15 as supplies ran low and units were locked in close quarters combat with little ammunition for the weapons. Fighting across the entire front became [[hand-to-hand]] combat and [[grenade]] fights at close range. The two divisions were so evenly matched that neither could make any appreciable gains for days of fighting and huge numbers of casualties.&lt;ref name=&quot;Paik38&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Paik|1992|p=38}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The bloody fighting obliged Paik to call for emergency reinforcements to hold the line. The Eighth Army responded immediately by sending the US 27th Infantry&lt;ref name=&quot;Alex145&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Alexander|2003|p=145}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as the ROK 10th Regiment from the ROK 8th Division to reinforce the ROK 1st Division's three regiments. [[US Air Force]] aircraft also conducted a [[Battle of Taegu#Carpet bombing|carpet bombing campaign]] against the advancing North Korean positions to undetermined effect.&lt;ref name=&quot;Paik39&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Paik|1992|p=39}}&lt;/ref&gt; Around that time the KPA 15th Division, which had been supporting the KPA 13th Division, withdrew from the front to attack elsewhere, leaving the ROK 1st Division, with the US 27th Infantry, and the KPA 13th Division as principal opponents in the conflict that followed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alex145&quot;/&gt;

===US infantry advance===
As the 27th Infantry's trucks rolled northward from Tabu-dong and approached their [[Line of Departure]], the men inside could see the North Koreans and South Koreans fighting on the ridges overlooking the road. The infantry dismounted and deployed an attacking line, with the 1st Battalion on the left of the road and the 2nd Battalion on the right. With US tanks leading the infantry on the road, the two battalions crossed the line at 13:00. The tanks opened fire against the mountain [[escarpments]] to aid the South Korean infantry engaged there. The US infantry on either side of the road swept the lower hills, as the tanks on the road paced their advance with the infantry. A North Korean outpost line in the valley withdrew and there was almost no North Korean opposition during the first hour of the US advance. North Korean outpost lines were {{convert|2.5|mi}} in front of their main positions. The 27th Infantry had reached a point about {{convert|2|mi}} north of Tabu-dong when Michaelis was informed that neither of the ROK regiments on the high ground flanking the valley road had been able to advance.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alex145&quot;/&gt; He was ordered to halt and form a perimeter defense with both battalions astride the road.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple355&quot;/&gt;

The two battalions of the 27th Infantry went into a perimeter defense just north of the village of Soi-ri.&lt;ref name=&quot;Paik40&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Paik|1992|p=40}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 1st Battalion, on the left of the road, took a position with C Company on high ground in front, and with A Company on a ridge behind it. On their right, B Company was placed parallel to A Company, and carried the line across the stream and the narrow valley to the road. There the 2nd Battalion took up the defense line with E Company on the road and F Company on its right, while G Company held a ridge behind F Company. Thus, the two battalions presented a four-company front, with one company holding a [[refused flank]] position on either side. A platoon of tanks took positions on the front line, two tanks on the road and two in the stream bed, with four more tanks in reserve. The artillery went into firing positions behind the force. Six bazooka teams took up positions in front of the infantry positions along the road and in the stream bed. At the same time, the ROK 1st Division remained in control of the high ground on either side of the 27th Infantry positions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple355&quot;/&gt;

=== August 18 attack ===
The first of seven successive North Korean night attacks struck the 27th Infantry defensive perimeter shortly after dark that night, August 18.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mil10221&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Paik41&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Paik|1992|p=41}}&lt;/ref&gt; North Korean mortars and artillery fired a heavy preparation for the general attack for several hours.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alex145&quot;/&gt; Two T-34 tanks and an [[SU-76]] [[self-propelled gun]] moved out of the village of Sinjumak {{convert|2|mi}} in front of the 27th Infantry lines. Infantry followed them, some in trucks and others on foot. The lead tank moved slowly and without firing, apparently observing, while the second one and the SU-76 fired repeatedly into F Company's position. As the tanks drew near, a 3.5-inch bazooka team from F Company destroyed the second one in the line.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple356&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Alex145&quot;/&gt;

Bazooka teams also hit the lead tank, causing its crew to abandon it. Fire from the 8th Field Artillery Battalion knocked out the self-propelled gun, destroyed two trucks, and killed or wounded an estimated 100 North Korean troops at the point of the advance. US [[First Lieutenant]] [[Lewis Millett]], an artillery [[forward observer]] and later a [[Medal of Honor]] winner after he transferred to the infantry, directed this artillery fire on the North Koreans, even as a T-34 tank approached within {{convert|50|ft}} of his position.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple357&quot;/&gt; Three more North Korean tanks had come down the road but, on realizing that the Americans had effective anti-tank weapons, they switched on their running lights and retreated north without engaging the UN troops.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alex146&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Alexander|2003|p=146}}&lt;/ref&gt; Around 00:30 on August 19 the first North Korean attack had stalled and they withdrew. North Korean troops made a second effort, much weaker than the first, around 02:30, but artillery and mortar fire dispersed them before they reached the UN lines.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple357&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Appleman|1998|p=357}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Over the course of the next week, the US troops were able to discern the North Koreans' system of attack and use it to their advantage. The North Koreans used a system of flares to signal various actions and coordinate them. It quickly became apparent to the defending Americans that green flares were used to signal an attack on a given area. So the 27th Infantry obtained its own green flares and then, after the North Korean attack had begun, fired them over its main defensive positions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple357&quot;/&gt; This confused the attacking forces and often drew them to the points of greatest US strength where they suffered massive casualties from defensive machine-gun crossfire.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alex146&quot;/&gt; The US troops also began using land mines in front of their positions to stall the North Koreans. The mines stopped the tanks and the infantry tried to remove them. When this happened, US troops fired flares to illuminate the scene and pre-registered artillery and mortar fire blasted the immobilized North Koreans. This tactic was effective in inflicting further significant casualties.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple357&quot;/&gt;

=== Stalemate ===
On the morning of August 19, the ROK 11th and 13th Regiments launched counterattacks along the ridges with some gains, however the fight continued to produce heavy casualties for both sides.&lt;ref name=&quot;Paik41&quot;/&gt; Walker ordered another reserve unit, a battalion of the ROK 10th Regiment, to the Taegu front to close a gap between the ROK 1st and 6th Divisions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple358&quot;/&gt; Later in the day, Walker also ordered the US 23rd Infantry Regiment, under command of Colonel [[Paul L. Freeman, Jr.]], to move up and establish a defense perimeter around the 8th and 37th Field Artillery Battalions at their positions {{convert|8|mi}} north of Taegu, to protect them from North Korean attack.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mil2000465&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Millett|2000|p=465}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was the only occasion during the war that two US regiments were assigned to a South Korean command.&lt;ref name=&quot;Paik42&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Paik|1992|p=42}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 3rd Battalion, 23rd Infantry took up a defensive position around the artillery while the 2nd Battalion occupied a defensive position on the road behind the 27th Infantry. The next day the two battalions exchanged places.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple358&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Appleman|1998|p=358}}&lt;/ref&gt; South Korean troops, suffering losses from the fighting, began recruiting students and civilians from nearby villages to fight.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mil2000465&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Waegwan Tanks.jpg|thumb|250px|alt=A pair of heavily damaged tanks destroyed in a ditch|Destroyed North Korean T-34 tanks, 1950.]]
There was little fighting on the ground during the day on August 20. However, US aircraft attacked North Korean positions around Taegu repeatedly during the day, often in close proximity to American ground forces. As night fell, North Korean troops launched a second attack, firing a barrage of 120–mm. mortar shells into the 27th Infantry's Heavy Weapons Company area at 17:00; several of their tanks also began advancing down the corridor. The US troops responded with artillery and mortar fire, hitting the North Korean column and its accompanying infantry. Waiting Americans held their small arms and machine gun fire until the North Koreans were within {{convert|200|ft}} of their positions. The combined fire of all the US weapons repulsed this attack.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple358&quot;/&gt;

The next morning, August 21, a US patrol of two platoons of infantry and M26 Pershing tanks went up the road toward the North Korean positions. [[White flag]]s had appeared in front of the American line, and civilians in the area said many North Koreans wanted to surrender. The US patrol's mission was to investigate this situation and to form an estimate of North Koreans losses. The patrol advanced about {{convert|1|mi}}, engaging small North Korean groups and receiving some artillery fire. On its way it destroyed five disabled North Korean tanks with [[thermite]] grenades. The patrol also found a 37&amp;nbsp;mm anti-tank gun, two SU-76 self-propelled guns, and a 120&amp;nbsp;mm mortar among the destroyed North Korean equipment, as well as recognizing a large number of North Korean dead. At the point of farthest advance, the patrol found and destroyed an abandoned T-34 tank in a village schoolhouse courtyard.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple359&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Appleman|1998|p=359}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== August 21 attack ===
That evening, the 27th Infantry placed two belts of antipersonnel mines and [[trip flare]]s across the road and stream bed {{convert|250|ft}} and {{convert|150|ft}} in front of its positions in the valley. After dusk, the North Koreans began shelling the general area of the 27th Infantry positions until just before midnight.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple359&quot;/&gt; ROK troops had planned to mount an attack, but it became apparent that the North Koreans would hit first.&lt;ref name=&quot;Paik43&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Paik|1992|p=43}}&lt;/ref&gt; Then the KPA 13th Division launched a major attack against the entire UN front in and around the valley.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mil2000467&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Millett|2000|p=467}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nine US tanks supported the infantry troops in the valley. Because it was on higher ground and positioned in front of all the other American units, C Company on the left of the road usually was the first to detect an approaching attack. That evening the C Company commander telephoned the regimental headquarters that he could hear tanks. When the artillery fired an illuminating shell he was able to count 19 North Korean vehicles in the attacking column on the road. The tanks and self-propelled guns approached the American positions, firing rapidly. Most of their shells landed in the rear areas. North Korean infantry moved forward on both sides of the road. Simultaneously, other North Korean units attacked the ROK troops on the high ridges flanking the valley.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple359&quot;/&gt;

American artillery and mortar fire bombarded the North Koreans, trying to separate the tanks from the infantry.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mil2000467&quot;/&gt; US machine gun fire opened on the KPA infantry only after they had entered the mine field and were at close range. The US Pershing tanks in the front line held their fire until the North Korean tanks came very close. One of the American tanks knocked out the lead North Korean tank and a bazooka team from F Company knocked out a towed gun, the third vehicle in column. The trapped second tank was disabled by bazooka fire and abandoned by its crew.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple359&quot;/&gt; It was during this fight that the battle received its name. The US troops at the battle noted the tank shells being fired up and down the valley in the dark looked &quot;like bowling balls.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Paik42&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mil2000467&quot;/&gt;

Artillery and 90&amp;nbsp;mm tank fire destroyed seven more North Korean T-34 tanks, three more SU-76 towed guns, and several trucks and personnel carriers. This night battle, which was at times very intense, lasted about five hours. The US B Battery, 8th Field Artillery Battalion alone fired 1,661 105&amp;nbsp;mm rounds, the 4.2-inch mortar platoon fired 902 rounds, the 81&amp;nbsp;mm mortar platoon fired 1,200 rounds, and F Company, 27th Infantry fired 385 60&amp;nbsp;mm mortar rounds. The North Korean column was completely destroyed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple359&quot;/&gt; US patrols after daylight estimated the North Koreans had suffered 1,300 casualties in the fight.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alex146&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mil2000467&quot;/&gt; Eleven prisoners captured by the patrol said the action had decimated their units and that the division was only at 25 percent strength.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple359&quot;/&gt;

=== North Korean flanking moves ===
During the night battle, North Korean forces infiltrated along the high ridge line around the east flank of the 27th Infantry and appeared the next day at about 12:00 {{convert|6|mi}} in the rear of that regiment and only {{convert|9|mi}} from Taegu. This force was a regiment of the KPA 1st Division and was 1,500 men strong. The regiment had just arrived from the Kunwi area to join in the battle for Taegu.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alex147&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Alexander|2003|p=147}}&lt;/ref&gt; It began ambushing supply lines to the American forces in the valley.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple360&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Appleman|1998|p=360}}&lt;/ref&gt; One of the regiment's companies attacked the ROK 1st Division's headquarters with intent to capture Paik, but was repulsed by the ROK 10th Regiment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Paik41&quot;/&gt;

About this time, Michaelis sent an urgent message to Eighth Army saying that the ROK troops on his left had given way and that &quot;those people are not fighting.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple360&quot;/&gt; One of the battalions of the ROK 11th Regiment had been driven back and was retreating in disarray.&lt;ref name=&quot;Paik43&quot;/&gt; Prisoners told him that about 1,000 North Koreans were on his west flank. He asked for an air strike. Had these South Korean troops been driven from this high ground, the perimeter position of the 27th Infantry Regiment would have been untenable. Paik bitterly resented Michaelis' charge that his men were not fighting, and in the argument, Eighth Army [[Korean Military Advisory Group]] advisers visited each ROK unit to ensure they were remaining in position.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple360&quot;/&gt; Paik personally rallied the ROK 11th Regiment for a charge back into its positions, impressing Michaelis.&lt;ref name=&quot;Paik44&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Paik|1992|p=44}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later, Michaelis apologized to Paik though their relationship for the remainder of the battle remained strained.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mil10221&quot;/&gt;

On the afternoon of August 22, 2nd Battalion, 23rd Infantry, guarding the support artillery behind the 27th Infantry, came under attack by the KPA 1st Division troops that had passed around the forward positions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alex147&quot;/&gt; Freeman reported to Eighth Army at 16:40 that the North Koreans had shelled the rear battery of the 37th Field Artillery Battalion, that North Korean infantry were between the US 27th and US 23rd Regiments on the road, and that other North Korean groups had passed around the east side of his forward battalion. An intense artillery barrage began falling on the headquarters area of the 8th Field Artillery Battalion at 16:05, and 25 minutes later two direct hits destroyed the [[fire direction center]], killing four officers and two non-commissioned officers. The individual batteries quickly took over control of the battalion fires and continued to support the infantry, while the battalion [[Headquarters and Headquarters Company]] withdrew under fire.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple361&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Appleman|1998|p=361}}&lt;/ref&gt;

UN aircraft launched air strikes on the North Korean-held ridge east of the road and on the valley beyond.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mil10221&quot;/&gt; That night, Walker released control of the 23rd Infantry, less the 1st Battalion, to the US 1st Cavalry Division with orders for it to clear the North Koreans from the road and the commanding ground overlooking the [[main supply route]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Alex147&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple361&quot;/&gt;

About 10:00, [[Lieutenant Colonel]] Chong Pong Uk, commanding the artillery regiment supporting the KPA 13th Division, walked up alone to a ROK 1st Division position {{convert|3|mi|km}} north of Tabu-dong and defected.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mil10221&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple361&quot;/&gt; Chong, the highest ranking North Korean prisoner of war thus far in the war, gave precise information on the location of his artillery.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mil2000467&quot;/&gt; According to him, there were seven 122&amp;nbsp;mm howitzers and thirteen 76&amp;nbsp;mm guns emplaced and camouflaged in an orchard {{convert|4.5|mi}} north of Tabu-dong, in a little valley on the north side of Yuhak-san. Upon receiving this information, Eighth Army immediately prepared to destroy the North Korean weapons. Fighter-bombers attacked the orchard site with [[napalm]], and US artillery took the location under fire.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mil2000467&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple361&quot;/&gt; Chong was eventually commissioned in South Korea's armed forces.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mil10221&quot;/&gt;

=== Final moves ===
During the night of August 22–23, the North Koreans launched a weak attack against the 27th Infantry, which was quickly repulsed. Just before 12:00 on August 23, however, a violent action occurred some distance behind the front line when about 100 North Korean soldiers, undetected, succeeded in reaching the positions of K Company, 27th Infantry and of the 1st Platoon, C Company, 65th Engineer Combat Battalion. They overran parts of these positions before being driven off and suffering 50 killed. Meanwhile, as ordered by Walker, the 2nd Battalion, 23rd Infantry, after repelling several North Korean night attacks, counterattacked at dawn and seized the high ground overlooking the road at the artillery positions. At the same time the 3rd Battalion started an all-day attack that swept a stretch of high ground east of the road. This action largely cleared the North Koreans from the area behind and on the flanks of the 27th Infantry. At 13:35, Michaelis reported from the Bowling Alley to Eighth Army that the KPA 13th Division had blown the road to his front, had mined it, and was withdrawing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple362&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Appleman|1998|p=362}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mil2000468&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Millett|2000|p=468}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The next day, August 24, the 23rd Infantry continued clearing the rear areas and by night it estimated that there were fewer than 200 North Koreans behind the forward positions. The Bowling Alley front was quiet during the day. Shortly after midnight on August 24 the North Koreans launched what had by now become their regular nightly attack down the Bowling Alley. This attack was in an estimated two-company strength supported by a few tanks. The 27th Infantry broke up the attack and two more North Korean tanks were destroyed by the supporting artillery fire. This was the last night the 27th Infantry Regiment spent in the Bowling Alley.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alex147&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple362&quot;/&gt;

With the North Koreans turned back north of Taegu, Walker issued orders for the 27th Infantry to leave the Bowling Alley and return to the 25th Division in the [[Masan]] area.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mil2000469&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Millett|2000|p=469}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ROK 1st Division was to assume responsibility for the Bowling Alley, but the 23rd Infantry was to remain north of Taegu in its support. ROK relief of the 27th Infantry began at 18:00, 25 August, and continued throughout the night until completed at 03:45 August 26. Survivors of the 1st Regiment, KPA 1st Division, joined the rest of that division in the mountains east of the Taegu–Sangju road near the walled summit of Ka-san. Prisoners reported that the 1st Regiment was down to about 400 men and had lost all its 120&amp;nbsp;mm mortars, 76&amp;nbsp;mm howitzers, and antitank guns as a result of its action on the east flank of the KPA 13th Division at the Bowling Alley.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple363&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Appleman|1998|p=363}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Aftermath ==
The confirmed North Korean losses from August 18 to 25 included 13 T-34 tanks, five SU-76 self-propelled guns, and 23 trucks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Apple362&quot;/&gt; The KPA 13th Division's troops suffered heavy casualties during the fight, with an estimated 3,000 killed, wounded and captured. The division withdrew to rebuild.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mil10221&quot;/&gt; The North Koreans' total casualties from August 12 to 25 were 5,690 killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Paik45&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Paik|1992|p=45}}&lt;/ref&gt;

US losses during the battle were extremely light; unusual for fighting at a time in which other UN offensive forces were paying a heavy price when making similar pushes against the North Korean troops.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ecker29&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Ecker|2004|p=29}}&lt;/ref&gt; The US infantry forces suffered only five killed and 54 wounded in the 27th Infantry, plus three killed and 16 wounded in the 23rd Infantry. This brought the total American casualty count to 8 dead, 70 wounded.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ecker30&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Ecker|2004|p=30}}&lt;/ref&gt; South Korean troops suffered much more heavily during the fight. An estimated 2,300 South Korean men were killed in the fighting; 2,244 enlisted men and 56 officers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Paik45&quot;/&gt; However, these losses were not crippling, as volunteers poured in from the surrounding countryside to fight for the South Korean Army.&lt;ref name=&quot;Paik46&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Paik|1992|p=46}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
=== Citations ===
{{reflist|3}}

=== Sources ===
{{Portal|United States Army}}
{{Refbegin}}
*{{citation|first=Bevin |last=Alexander |authorlink=Bevin Alexander |title=Korea: The First War we Lost |publisher=[[Hippocrene Books]] |year=2003 |isbn=978-0-7818-1019-7 |location=[[New York, New York]]}}
*{{citation|last=Appleman |first=Roy E. | url = http://www.history.army.mil/books/korea/20-2-1/toc.htm |title=South to the Naktong, North to the Yalu: United States Army in the Korean War |year=1998 |publisher=[[Department of the Army]] |isbn=978-0-16-001918-0 |location=[[Washington, D.C.]]}}
*{{citation|first=Brian |last=Catchpole |title=The Korean War |year=2001 |publisher=[[Robinson Publishing]] |isbn=978-1-84119-413-4 |location=[[London, United Kingdom]]}}
*{{citation|last=Ecker |first=Richard E. |title=Battles of the Korean War: A Chronology, with Unit-by-Unit United States Casualty Figures &amp; Medal of Honor Citations |publisher=[[McFarland &amp; Company]] |year=2004 |isbn=978-0-7864-1980-7 |location=[[Jefferson, North Carolina]]}}
*{{citation|first=T.R. |last=Fehrenbach |authorlink=T. R. Fehrenbach |title=This Kind of War: The Classic Korean War History – Fiftieth Anniversary Edition |publisher=Potomac Books Inc. |year=2001 |isbn=978-1-57488-334-3|location=Washington, D.C.}}
*{{citation|first=Robert |last=Leckie |title=Conflict: The History Of The Korean War, 1950–1953 |year=1996 |publisher=[[Da Capo Press]] |isbn=978-0-306-80716-9 |location=[[Mason City, Iowa]]}}
*{{citation|last=Millett |first=Allan R. |title=The Korean War, Volume 1 |year=2000 |publisher=[[University of Nebraska]] Press |isbn=978-0-8032-7794-6|location=[[Lincoln, Nebraska]]}}
*{{citation|first=Allan R. |last=Millett |title=The War for Korea, 1950–1951: They Came from the North |publisher=University Press of Kansas |year=2010 |isbn= 978-0-7006-1709-8|location=[[Lawrence, Kansas]]}}
*{{citation|last=Paik |first=Sun Yup |authorlink=Paik Sun-yup |title=From Pusan to Panmunjom |year=1992 |location=[[Riverside Township, New Jersey|Riverside, New Jersey]] |publisher=Brassey Inc. |isbn=0-02-881002-3}}
*{{citation|first=Michael J. |last=Varhola |authorlink=Michael J. Varhola |title=Fire and Ice: The Korean War, 1950–1953 |publisher=[[Da Capo Press]] |year=2000 |isbn=978-1-882810-44-4|location=[[Mason City, Iowa]]}}
{{Refend}}

;Attribution
{{ACMH|article = South to the Naktong, North to the Yalu: United States Army in the Korean War |url = http://www.history.army.mil/books/korea/20-2-1/toc.htm}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bowling Alley, Battle Of}}
[[Category:Battle of Pusan Perimeter]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1950]]
[[Category:1950 in Korea]]
[[Category:Battles of the Korean War]]
[[Category:Battles involving North Korea]]
[[Category:Battles involving South Korea]]
[[Category:Battles of the Korean War involving the United States]]
[[Category:North Gyeongsang Province]]
[[Category:Metaphors referring to sport]]</text>
      <sha1>34bwqna9zawxmzztb2gue6i97bio92o</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
