<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of Bonchurch</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>10476132</id>
    <revision>
      <id>746617017</id>
      <parentid>738565857</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-28T13:46:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 1 sources and tagging 0 as dead. #IABot (v1.2.6)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14339">{{Use British English|date=March 2012}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| partof      = the [[French invasion of the Isle of Wight (1545)|French invasion of the Isle of Wight]] during the [[Italian War of 1542–1546]].
| image       = [[File:Monks Bay Battle of Bonchurch.jpg]]
| caption     = Monks Bay in 2008. French troops advanced from the bay before they reached St. Boniface Down, the location where the fighting took place.
| conflict    = Battle of Bonchurch
| date        = July, 1545
| place       = [[Bonchurch]], [[The Isle of Wight]], England
| coordinates = {{Coord|50|36|12.46|N|1|11|55.43|W|display=inline,title}}
| result      = English victory&lt;ref name=False&gt;{{Citation|title=False Prophets |url=http://web.ukonline.co.uk/lordcornell/iwhr/plaq.htm |accessdate=2 January 2008 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20041205155722/http://web.ukonline.co.uk/lordcornell/iwhr/plaq.htm |archivedate=5 December 2004 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonchurch A-Z&quot;&gt;Goodwin, ''Bonchurch from A-Z'', 7.&lt;/ref&gt;
| combatant1  = [[File:Pavillon royal de la France.png|22px]] [[Early Modern France|France]]
| combatant2  = [[File:Flag of England.svg|22px]] [[Kingdom of England|England]]
| commander1  = [[File:Pavillon royal de la France.png|22px]] [[Le Seigneur de Tais]]&lt;ref name=False/&gt;&lt;ref name=Lastinvasion&gt;{{Citation|title=The Last Invasion of the Isle of Wight |url=http://www.iwbeacon.com/The-Last-Invasion-of-the-Isle-of-Wight-The-Battle-of-Portsmouth.aspx |accessdate=14 February 2008 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110713070925/http://www.iwbeacon.com/The-Last-Invasion-of-the-Isle-of-Wight-The-Battle-of-Portsmouth.aspx |archivedate=13 July 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
| commander2  = [[File:Flag of England.svg|22px]] [[Robert Fyssher]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonchurch A-Z&quot;/&gt;
| strength1   = Approx 500 soldiers&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonchurch A-Z&quot;/&gt;
| strength2   = 300&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonchurch A-Z&quot;/&gt;-2800&lt;ref name=Lastinvasion/&gt; militiamen
| casualties1 = Unknown
| casualties2 = Unknown
}}
{{Campaignbox Italian War of 1542-1546}}

The '''Battle of Bonchurch''' took place sometime in late July 1545 at [[Bonchurch]] on the [[Isle of Wight]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonchurch A-Z&quot;/&gt; No source of information states a specific date, although it could have happened on 21 July.&lt;ref name=Lastinvasion/&gt;  The battle was a part of the wider [[Italian War of 1542–1546]], and took place during the [[French invasion of the Isle of Wight (1545)|1545 French invasion of the Isle of Wight]].  Several landings were made by the French during the invasion of the Isle of Wight, including the one at Bonchurch.&lt;ref name=Lastinvasion/&gt; The two combatants were the [[Kingdom of England]] and the [[Kingdom of France]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonchurch A-Z&quot;/&gt; England won the battle, and the French advance across the Isle of Wight was halted.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonchurch A-Z&quot;/&gt;

The battle was fought between French regular soldiers, and English militiamen.&lt;ref name=Lastinvasion/&gt; The number of French soldiers involved is believed to be around 500.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonchurch A-Z&quot;/&gt;  The number of English militiamen is uncertain, with one source of information stating  300, and another stating 2800.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonchurch A-Z&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Lastinvasion/&gt;  English forces at the battle are understood to have been commanded by Captain [[Robert Fyssher]], whilst French forces engaged were commanded by [[Le Seigneur de Tais]].&lt;ref name=False/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonchurch A-Z&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lastinvasion&quot;/&gt;
The battle was one of several that were fought between the English and the French on the Isle of Wight.&lt;ref name=Lastinvasion/&gt;  The majority of sources of information regarding the battle state that the English won,&lt;ref name=&quot;False&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonchurch A-Z&quot;/&gt; although one source of information states that the French were victorious.&lt;ref name=Lastinvasion/&gt;  The battle was fought because it was part of the French attempt to cause enough damage to the Isle of Wight to force the English ships standing off the coast of England to leave their defensive positions and attack in conditions favourable to the French.&lt;ref name=Lastinvasion/&gt; The landing at Bonchurch was one of several made by the French on the Isle of Wight, with others taking place at [[Sandown]], [[Bembridge]] and [[St Helens, Isle of Wight|St Helens]].&lt;ref name=Lastinvasion/&gt;

==Background==
{{Main|Italian War of 1542-1546|French invasion of the Isle of Wight (1545)|Battle of the Solent}}

The [[Italian War of 1542-1546]] occurred because the disputes between the [[Holy Roman Emperor]] [[Charles V, Holy Roman Emperor|Charles V]] and [[Francis I of France]] had not been settled by the [[Italian War of 1535-1538]], and those disputes resulted in a war between France, aided by the [[Ottoman Empire]] and [[United Duchies of Jülich-Cleves-Berg|Jülich-Cleves-Berg]], and the [[Holy Roman Empire]], aided by the [[Kingdom of England]], Spain, [[Saxony]], and [[Brandenburg]]. After two years of fighting Charles V, and [[Henry VIII of England|Henry VIII]] of the Kingdom of England, invaded France. In September 1544, English forces captured [[Boulogne-sur-Mer|Boulogne]]. France attempted to re-capture the city by force, but failed. Peace talks to end the fighting between England and France did not yield any positive results, partly because Henry VIII refused to consider returning Boulogne.&lt;ref&gt;[[Robert Knecht]], ''Renaissance Warrior'', 501; Scarisbrick, ''Henry VIII'', 397–398.&lt;/ref&gt; As a result of the failure of diplomacy to get back Boulogne for France, Francis I decided to invade England, hoping that Henry VIII would return Boulogne to France in return for French forces leaving England. Thirty thousand French troops and a fleet of some 400 vessels were assembled.&lt;ref&gt;Knecht, ''Renaissance Warrior'', 502; Phillips, &quot;Testing the 'Mystery'&quot;, 50–51.&lt;/ref&gt; The fleet left [[Le Havre]], in France, on 16 July.

On 18 July, the hostile engagement of French and English ships by the English coast marked the beginning of the [[Battle of the Solent]]. On that day, the outnumbered English ships withdrew.&lt;ref name=Lastinvasion/&gt; The English hoped to lure the French ships into the shallows and narrow channels of the Spithead, but the French wanted to attack the English in the more open waters of the eastern Spithead where the English ships could be encircled and annihilated.&lt;ref name=Lastinvasion/&gt; To entice the English ships to abandon their defensive position, and engage the numerically greater French ships, the French decided to invade the Isle of Wight, burning buildings and crops.&lt;ref name=Lastinvasion/&gt; France hoped that the residents of the Isle of Wight would support them, and rebel against England, and that the Isle of Wight could be used a base to challenge the English.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|title=Mary Rose Dossier disaster |url=http://www.thenewscentre.co.uk/rose/disaster.htm |accessdate=2 January 2007 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060513221510/http://www.thenewscentre.co.uk:80/rose/disaster.htm |archivedate=13 May 2006 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; French troops landed on the Isle of Wight, on 21 July.  England would oppose this invasion of the Isle of Wight.

The [[Hundred Years War]] had resulted in the society which existed on the Isle of Wight being very militarised.  Every male adult was obligated to fight when needed, and they participated in regular military training. The Captain of the Isle of Wight, Sir [[Richard Worsley]] of [[Appuldurcombe House]], is considered to have been a “capable and energetic commander”.  He was assisted by Sir [[Edward Bellingham]], an officer in the regular English army, along with a headquarters staff.  The English militiamen were equipped with &quot;long [[pike (weapon)|pike]]s topped with a bill hook, and daggers, knives and clubs for close fighting&quot;, as well as the [[Welsh longbow]].  The French soldiers were equipped with firearms, and steel blades.  The militiamen had the advantage of superior morale, speed and agility.&lt;ref name=Lastinvasion/&gt;

The plan for the advance of the French soldiers at Bonchurch may have been to burn [[Wroxall, Isle of Wight|Wroxall]] and [[Appuldurcombe]], capture and consolidate a position on the heights of [[St. Boniface Down]], and then move towards [[Sandown]] to link up with a French landing there.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonchurch A-Z&quot;/&gt;  The area around Bonchurch became important in its own right because [[Dunnose Point]], near Bonchurch, offered a safe anchorage for French ships.&lt;ref name=Lastinvasion/&gt; There were also sources of fresh water nearby that could be used by the soldiers and sailors of the fleet.&lt;ref name=Lastinvasion/&gt;

==Prelude==
French troops were landed at three locations on the coast of the Isle of Wight, and the total number of French soldiers who were landed was 2000.&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation |title=Isle of Wight Heritage |url=http://www.greenislandtourism.org/heritage.htm |accessdate=18 October 2007 |format=  – &lt;sup&gt;[http://scholar.google.co.uk/scholar?hl=en&amp;lr=&amp;q=intitle%3AIsle+of+Wight+Heritage&amp;as_publication=&amp;as_ylo=&amp;as_yhi=&amp;btnG=Search Scholar search]&lt;/sup&gt;|archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20070506202312/http://www.greenislandtourism.org/heritage.htm |archivedate = 6 May 2007|deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bonchurch was one of the three places where French troops landed, and the number of soldiers who landed at Bonchurch is believed to be around 500.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonchurch A-Z&quot;/&gt; The landing was unopposed and the French forces began to advance inland, up steep thickly wooded slopes.&lt;ref name=Lastinvasion/&gt; The Isle of Wight [[militia]], however, learnt about the French invasion very quickly. 300 soldiers of the militia, under the command of Captain [[Robert Fyssher]], were waiting at [[St. Boniface Down]] for the French to advance from [[Monks Bay]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonchurch A-Z&quot;/&gt;

==Battle==
Reports of the fighting are confused,&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonchurch A-Z&quot;/&gt; and therefore no fully comprehensive account of the battle has been agreed upon. However, the battle could have taken place at dawn (the day of the battle is unknown), and lasted until midday.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonchurch A-Z&quot;/&gt; Some records of the battle say that some women of the Isle of Wight participated in the battle by shooting arrows at the French.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonchurch A-Z&quot;/&gt;

===Did the French win the battle?===
One source of information states that the French won the battle at Bonchurch. This source says that the English forces opposing the French were not local militiamen, but militiamen from [[Hampshire]].  The English forces took up a defensive position, a fact which is agreed upon by another account of the fighting, and were flanked by cliffs and screened by woods. According to this account, the number of English troops was 2,800.  The first French attack was repelled but [[Le Seigneur de Tais]], commander of the French forces involved in the battle, rallied his troops.  A second French attack against the English forces was launched, with the French forces arranged into the 'array' fighting formation.  The account concludes its description of the fighting by saying that, after heavy casualties were sustained by both sides, the English line broke and the militia routed as a result of the second attack by the French.  The account also states that Captain [[Robert Fyssher]], which another source of information states commanded the English forces during the battle, is reported to have shouted out, as the militia routed, offering £100 for anyone who could bring him a horse, because he was too fat to run.  A quote by Sir [[John Oglander]] is recorded, which reads that “but none could be had even for a kingdom”.  The captain was never heard from again, and the account states that he was either killed, or captured and then buried at sea.&lt;ref name=Lastinvasion/&gt;

==Aftermath==
The casualties for both sides were heavy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonchurch A-Z&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Lastinvasion/&gt; The battle resulted in the French invasion of the Isle of Wight being stopped.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonchurch A-Z&quot;/&gt; Another skirmish took place at Bonchurch several days after the battle, when English forces engaged with French men who had disembarked from French ships retreating from Portsmouth looking for water.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonchurch A-Z&quot;/&gt; A senior French commander, [[Chevalier D'Aux]], was killed as a result of the engagement.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bonchurch A-Z&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Lastinvasion/&gt;  The English victory at Bonchurch only had a marginal impact on the course of the [[Italian War of 1542-1546]], because the battle only involved a very small number of men relative to the numbers of men that were engaged throughout the entirety of the war. The fact that it only had a marginal impact is also because, if the French had captured the Isle of Wight, it is unlikely that that capture would have drastically affected the course of the war, because there were more significant territories that were being contested. The Isle of Wight could have been used to support French operations against England had it been captured; [[Claude d'Annebault]], commander of the French armada, recorded that “having it [the Isle of Wight] under our control, we [the French] could then dominate Portsmouth... and so put the enemy to extraordinary expense in maintaining a standing army and navy to contain us.”&lt;ref name=Lastinvasion/&gt; Although some sources do state that the victory at Bonchurch was responsible for the French withdrawal from the Isle of Wight, the source of information which states that the French won the battle says that fighting at [[Bembridge]] was what drove the French from the island.&lt;ref name=Lastinvasion/&gt;

==Sources==
{{Refbegin}}
* Goodwin, John. ''Bonchurch from A-Z''. Bonchurch: The Bonchurch Trading Company, 1992. ISBN 1-873009-00-3
* Knecht, Robert J. ''Renaissance Warrior and Patron: The Reign of Francis I''. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1994. ISBN 0-521-57885-X.
* Scarisbrick, J. J. ''Henry VIII''. London: The Folio Society, 2004.
{{Refend}}

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}
{{Good article}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2012}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bonchurch, Battle Of 1545}}
[[Category:1545 in England]]
[[Category:1545 in France]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1545]]
[[Category:Battles involving England]]
[[Category:Battles involving France]]
[[Category:Battles of the Italian Wars]]
[[Category:Military history of the Isle of Wight]]
[[Category:16th century in Hampshire]]</text>
      <sha1>tg82gkgtb5hsmbci12by3fgi0pe0jek</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
