<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of Marengo</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>157671</id>
    <revision>
      <id>728595903</id>
      <parentid>728595179</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-07-06T10:46:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Anadessma</username>
        <id>1911284</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Propaganda */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="42114">{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Battle of Marengo
|partof=the [[War of the Second Coalition]] and the [[French Revolutionary Wars]]
|image=[[Image:Lejeune - Bataille de Marengo.jpg|300px|alt=Scene of the battle in which Napoleon, followed by some generals, advances on horseback from the left towards the centre of the image. Behind him, a regiment confronts in line the head of the Austrian pursuit column, while Desaix is being mortally wounded at the head of his men. Further to the right, General Zach is captured by some cavalrymen and General Saint-Julien tries to escape the same fate. In the background General Kellermann conducts his famous cavalry charge in the flank of the Austrians. Behind all the action lies the village of Spinetta, in front of the Apennines.]]
|caption=[[Louis-François Lejeune]]: The Battle of Marengo
|date=14 June 1800
|place=[[Spinetta Marengo]], [[Province of Alessandria|Alessandria]], [[Piedmont]], present-day [[Italy]]
|coordinates={{Coord|44|53|N|8|41|E|region:IT_type:event_scale:50000|display=inline,title}}
|result=Decisive French victory&lt;ref name=&quot;BrauerWright1990&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=Brauer|author2=William E. Wright|title=Austria in the Age of the French Revolution: 1789–1815|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=rFrOFBqeg1YC&amp;pg=PA34|accessdate=21 April 2013|date=1 December 1990|publisher=Berghahn Books|isbn=978-1-57181-374-9|page=34}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AfflerbachStrachan2012&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=Holger Afflerbach|author2=Hew Strachan|title=How Fighting Ends: A History of Surrender|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=gh6VIodYxNMC&amp;pg=PA215|accessdate=17 April 2013|date=26 July 2012|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-969362-7|page=215}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|combatant1={{flagicon|France}} [[French First Republic|French Republic]]
|combatant2={{flagicon|Habsburg Monarchy}} [[Habsburg Monarchy|Austria]]
|commander1=[[Napoleon I of France|Napoleon Bonaparte]]&lt;br&gt;[[Louis Desaix]]{{KIA}}
|commander2=[[Michael von Melas]]&lt;br&gt;[[Peter Karl Ott von Batorkez|Peter Ott]]
|strength1=24,000 &lt;br&gt;24 guns &lt;ref name=&quot;Benoit117&quot;&gt;Benoît, p. 117&lt;/ref&gt;
|strength2=31,000 &lt;br&gt;100 guns
           
|casualties1=1,100 killed&lt;br&gt;3,600 wounded&lt;br&gt;900 missing or captured&lt;ref name=&quot;Benoit122&quot;&gt;Benoît, p. 122&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;'''Total: 5,600'''&lt;ref&gt;Chandler, David G.. ''The Campaigns of Napoleon'', New York, 1966, ISBN 0-02-523660-1, p. 296, gives: 25% total casualties.&lt;/ref&gt;
|casualties2= 6,000 dead or wounded&lt;br&gt;8,000 captured&lt;br&gt;40 guns captured&lt;br&gt;15 colours captured&lt;ref name=&quot;Benoit122&quot;/&gt;&lt;br&gt;'''Total: 14,000'''&lt;ref&gt;Chandler, David G.. ''The Campaigns of Napoleon'', New York, 1966, ISBN 0-02-523660-1, p. 296, gives: 15 colours, 40 guns, 8,000 captured and 6,000 killed. Asprey, Robert. ''The Rise of Napoleon Bonaparte'', Basic Books, 2001, ISBN 0-465-04881-1, p. 387, gives: 6,000 killed or wounded and another 6,000 captured; 15 flags, 40 cannon.&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
{{Campaignbox Second Coalition}}
{{Campaignbox French Revolutionary Wars:Italy}}

The '''Battle of Marengo'''  was fought on 14 June 1800 between [[French First Republic|French]] forces under [[Napoleon Bonaparte]] and [[Austrian Empire|Austrian]] forces near the city of [[Alessandria]], in [[Piedmont]], [[Italy]].   Near the end of the day, the French overcame General [[Michael von Melas]]'s surprise attack, driving the Austrians out of Italy, and enhancing Napoleon's political position in [[Paris]] as [[First Consul]] of France in the wake of his [[18 Brumaire|coup d’état]] the previous November.&lt;ref&gt;Hollins, ''Encyclopedia'', pp. 605–606&lt;/ref&gt;

Surprised by the Austrian advance toward [[Genoa]] in mid-April 1800, Bonaparte had hastily led his army over the [[Alps]] in mid-May and reached [[Milan]] on 2 June. After cutting Melas’s line of communications by crossing the [[Po (river)|river Po]] and defeating ''[[Feldmarschallleutnant]]'' (FML) [[Peter Karl Ott von Bátorkéz]] at [[Battle of Montebello (1800)|Montebello]] on 9 June, the French closed in on the Austrian army, which had massed in [[Alessandria]]. Deceived by a local double agent, Bonaparte dispatched large forces to the north and south, but the Austrians launched a surprise attack on 14 June against the main French army under General [[Louis Alexandre Berthier]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollins606&quot;&gt;Hollins, ''Encyclopedia'', p. 606&lt;/ref&gt;

Initially, their two assaults across the Fontanone stream near [[Spinetta Marengo|Marengo]] village were repelled, and General [[Jean Lannes]] reinforced the French right. Bonaparte realised the true position and issued orders at 11:00 am to recall the detachment under ''[[Général de Division]]'' (GdD) [[Louis Desaix]], while moving his reserve forward. On the Austrian left, Ott’s column had taken Castel Ceriolo, and its advance guard moved south to attack Lannes’s flank. Melas renewed the main assault and the Austrians broke the central French position. By 2:30 pm the French were withdrawing and Austrian [[dragoon]]s seized the Marengo farm.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollins606&quot;/&gt; Bonaparte had by then arrived with the reserve, but Berthier’s troops began to fall back on the main vine belts. Knowing Desaix was approaching, Bonaparte was anxious about a column of Ott’s soldiers marching from the north, so he deployed his [[Imperial Guard (Napoleon I)#History|Consular Guard]] infantry to delay it. The French then withdrew steadily eastward toward San Giuliano Vecchio as the Austrians formed a column to follow them in line with Ott’s advance in the northern sector.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollins606&quot;/&gt;

Desaix’s arrival around 5:30 pm stabilised the French position as the [[9th Light Infantry Regiment]] delayed the Austrian advance down the main road and the rest of the army re-formed north of Cascina Grossa. As the pursuing Austrian troops arrived, a mix of musketry and artillery fire concealed the surprise attack of ''[[Brigadier General|Général de Brigade]]'' (GdB) [[François Étienne de Kellermann]]’s cavalry, which threw the Austrian pursuit into disordered flight back into Alessandria, with about 14,000 killed, wounded, or captured. The French casualties were considerably fewer, but included Desaix. The whole French line chased after the Austrians to seal ''une victoire politique'' (a political victory) that secured Bonaparte’s grip on power after the coup. It would be followed by a propaganda campaign, which sought to rewrite the story of the battle three times during Napoleon’s rule.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollins606&quot;/&gt;

==Background==
[[File:David - Napoleon crossing the Alps - Malmaison1.jpg|thumb|''[[Napoleon Crossing the Alps]]'' by [[Jacques-Louis David]]|alt=Napoleon on a rearing white horse pointing his men to continue their advance through a mountain pass.]]
The Battle of Marengo was the victory that sealed the success of Bonaparte's [[Italian campaigns of the French Revolutionary Wars#Second Coalition (1799–1800)|Italian campaign of 1800]] and is best understood in the context of that campaign. By a daring crossing of the Alps&lt;ref&gt;Shosenberg, p. 63&lt;/ref&gt; with his Army of the Reserve (officially commanded by [[Louis Alexandre Berthier]]) in mid-May 1800 almost before the passes were open, Bonaparte (who crossed on a mule) had threatened Melas's lines of communications in northern Italy. The French army then seized [[Milan]] on 2 June, followed by [[Pavia]], [[Piacenza]] and [[Stradella, Lombardy]], cutting the main Austrian supply route eastward along the south bank of the [[Po river]]. Bonaparte hoped that Melas's preoccupation with the [[Siege of Genoa (1800)|Siege of Genoa]], held by General [[André Masséna]], would prevent the Austrians from responding to his offensive. However, Genoa surrendered on 4 June, freeing a large number of Austrians for operations against the French.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollins606&quot;/&gt;

On 9 June, General [[Jean Lannes]] beat [[Feldmarschallleutnant]] [[Peter Karl Ott von Batorkez|Peter Ott]] in the [[Battle of Montebello (1800)|Battle of Montebello]]. This caused Bonaparte to become overconfident. He became convinced that Melas would not attack, and further, that the Austrian was about to retreat. As other French forces closed from the west and south, the Austrian commander had withdrawn most of his troops from their positions near [[Nice]] and [[Genoa]] to [[Alessandria]] on the main [[Turin]]-[[Mantua]] road.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollins606&quot;/&gt;

===Austrian plans and preliminary French moves===
The Austrians planned to fight their way out eastward but—using a local double agent, usually known by his cover of François Toli—attempted to deceive Bonaparte into thinking they would try to march north, cross the Po, and head for Milan, joined by the remaining troops marching up from Genoa. The spy would advise Bonaparte to march via [[Sale, Piedmont|Sale]] on the northern side of the plain, so that he could be engaged by the Austrian left wing; meanwhile the main force would move through [[Spinetta Marengo|Marengo]] village in the centre, turn north, and fall into the French left flank. Ott arrived from Montebello of 13 June in a war council. The senior generals of the Austrian army strongly approved this plan, as the alternative would have meant that the Austrian army would have had to retreat along the river Po and leave [[Piedmont]] to the enemy without a fight. Nonetheless, by abandoning the San Giuliano plain, where the superior Austrian cavalry could have given him an edge, Melas probably made a serious mistake.&lt;ref&gt;Pigeard, p. 521&lt;/ref&gt;

Bonaparte knew that Ott had no way out from Alessandria, but he had no idea of Melas's position. Following his meeting with the spy and fearing that the Austrian general might try to escape, Bonaparte spread his army out in a wide net by sending [[Louis Desaix]] with [[Divisional General]] [[Jean Boudet]]'s division (6,000 men) south to [[Novi Ligure]] and Divisional General [[Jean François Cornu de La Poype]] (3,500 men) north on the other bank of the Po. Further north, from [[Vercelli]] to [[Lake Maggiore]], were stationed the divisions of Antoine de Béthencourt and [[Joseph Chabran]] and, further to the rear, north of [[Piacenza]], [[Jean Thomas Guillaume Lorge]]'s division.&lt;ref name=&quot;Benoit117&quot;/&gt; Bonaparte's view was confirmed when General [[Claude Victor-Perrin]], supported by Divisional General [[Joachim Murat]]’s cavalry, swiftly evicted FML [[Andreas O'Reilly von Ballinlough]]’s Austrian brigade from Marengo village that afternoon. Victor then deployed divisional generals [[Gaspard Amédée Gardanne]] and [[Jacques-Antoine de Chambarlhac de Laubespin]]'s divisions along the Fontanone stream. Austrian headquarters debated building a bridge to the north to outflank the French, but the lack of pontoons and time forced the Austrians to cross the [[Bormida (river)|river Bormida]] and then launch a single, direct assault across the Fontanone bridge.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollins606&quot;/&gt;

==Prelude==
===Battlefield===
[[File:I-AL-Torre Garofoli.JPG|thumb|Torre Garofoli, Napoleon's headquarters before the battle|alt=Small building with a courtyard surrounded by brick walls and a bell tower in the background.]]
The battle took place to the east of Alessandria, on a plain crossed by a river forming meanders, the Bormida, over which the Austrians installed a bridgehead. On the plain were spread numerous hamlets and farms which represented strategic points. The three main sites of the battle formed a triangle, with Marengo in the west, Castel Ceriolo in the north, and San Giuliano Vecchio in the east. A small stream, the Fontanone, passed between Marengo and the Bormida. The First Consul had established his headquarters at Torre Garofoli, which was further to the east. This headquarters nowadays visitable is situated in the street: &quot;Strada Comunale Cerca&quot; coordinates N44°53'37.01'' E 8°48'14.12''&lt;ref name=&quot;Benoit117&quot;/&gt;

===Forces===
{{details|Marengo Order of Battle}}
The 30,000 Austrians and their 100 guns were opposed by 22,000 French and their 15 guns. Meanwhile, after the arrival of Desaix, 6,000 men would reinforce Bonaparte's army.&lt;ref name=&quot;Benoit117&quot;/&gt;

The 1799 campaign had exhausted the Austrian army in Italy, casualties and disease reducing some regiments to 300 men. The largest component of the army was in [[Piedmont]] and the neighbouring Po
valley; only a few units were moved to winter quarters in better-supplied areas. Long distances from the home bases, from which the regiments drew reinforcements, meant that troop transports had to endure miserable conditions, so only about 15 per cent reached the field army. The army of March 1800 was scarcely larger than at the conclusion of the 1799 campaign.&lt;ref&gt;Hollins, ''The Battle of Marengo 1800'', p. 16&lt;/ref&gt; Equipment and uniforms were improved and updated. Although a simpler uniform, with a [[leather]] helmet and smaller calibre [[musket]]s, was introduced, little had reached the field armies by 1800. Efforts were made to standardise equipment, but many units used a variety of musket and sabre patterns.&lt;ref&gt;Hollins, ''The Battle of Marengo 1800'', p. 15&lt;/ref&gt; Melas split his army into three corps facing the Bormida, in front of Alessandria. In the north Ott commanded [[Friedrich Heinrich von Gottesheim]]'s advance guard plus [[Joseph von Schellenberg]] and [[Ludwig von Vogelsang]]'s divisions. In the south was Feldmarschallleutnant [[Andreas O'Reilly von Ballinlough]]'s division. Melas himself took control of the centre, with the divisions of [[Karl Joseph Hadik von Futak]], [[Konrad Valentin von Kaim]], [[Ferdinand Johann von Morzin]] and [[Anton von Elsnitz]].&lt;ref&gt;Benoît, pp. 117–118&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1799 the 36,000 French troops in Italy were in a desperate state similar to that at the end of 1795. Supplies of all sorts were inadequate, discipline was breaking down, desertion was increasing, and on a few occasions, whole formations marched to the rear in search of food. The
survivors would be of limited combat value. In establishing the Army of the Reserve in France, Bonaparte's first move was to overhaul the supply system to provide the troops with regular food and decent uniforms. Lacking the large superiority in infantry and artillery enjoyed in many
Republican campaigns, the core of Bonaparte's reserve was 30,000 men, mostly from the [[Batavian Republic]], who had been used under [[Guillaume Marie Anne Brune]] to crush the rebellion in the [[Vendée]]. Additional veteran troops came from the remains of the former [[Army of England]].&lt;ref&gt;Hollins, ''The Battle of Marengo 1800'', p. 17&lt;/ref&gt; The new mililary doctrine emphasised the offensive, mobility and the bayonet, over linear firepower.&lt;ref&gt;Hollins, ''The Battle of Marengo 1800'', p. 18&lt;/ref&gt; In front of the Austrian army were stationed, in and to the south of Marengo, the corps of Victor ([[Jacques-Antoine de Chambarlhac de Laubespin]] and [[Gaspard Amédée Gardanne]]'s divisions), supported on the left by [[François Étienne de Kellermann]]'s cavalry and, further to the northeast, by the corps of Lannes ([[François Watrin]]'s division, Mainoni's brigade) together with two cavalry brigades. To the east of Castel Ceriolo took position [[Jean-Charles Monnier]]'s division, supported by the Guard, which formed the reserve. Victor was the one who would bear the brunt of the Austrian attack.&lt;ref&gt;Benoît, p. 118&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battle==
===Austrian attack===
[[File:Von Melas.jpg|thumb|left|[[Michael von Melas]] led the centre of the army during the attack, but he mistakenly believed that the battle was over before the arrival of Desaix.|alt=Half-length portrait of General Melas dressed in a white Austrian general's uniform with a decoration on his chest. Melas has white hair and keeps his right hand on his belt and his left one on a table, while looking to the right.]]
The Austrian troops advanced from Alessandria eastwards across the Bormida river by two bridges [[debouch]]ing in a narrow bend of the river (the river being not easily crossed elsewhere). Poor Austrian staff work prevented any rapid development of their attack and the entire army had to file through a narrow bridgehead.&lt;ref&gt;Arnold, p. 146&lt;/ref&gt; The movement began about 6 am with the first shots fired around 8 am, but the attack was not fully developed until 9 am.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollins606&quot;/&gt;

The 1,200-man Austrian advance guard, under [[Colonel]] (''Oberst'') [[Johann Maria Philipp Frimont]] and a division of 3,300 men under FML O'Reilly, pushed the French outposts back and deployed to become the Austrian right wing, driving the enemy from Pedrabona farm, then
heading south to tackle the French at La Stortiglione farm.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollins606&quot;/&gt; The Austrian centre (about 18,000 under Melas) advanced towards Marengo until halted by GdD Gardanne's French infantry deployed in front of the Fontanone stream.&lt;ref&gt;Arnold, p. 149&lt;/ref&gt; On the Austrian left, 7,500 men under FML [[Peter Karl Ott von Batorkez|Peter Ott]] waited for the road to clear before heading for the village of Castel Ceriolo well to the north of the French positions. This move threatened either an envelopment of the French right, or a further advance to cut the French line of communication with Milan.&lt;ref&gt;Benoît, p. 119&lt;/ref&gt;

Gardanne's men gave a good account of themselves, holding up the Austrian deployment for a considerable time. When Gardanne's division was exhausted, Victor pulled it back behind the Fontanone and committed his second division under GdD Chambarlhac (this officer soon lost his nerve and fled). The French held Marengo village and the line of the Fontanone until about noon, with both flanks in the air. First, at 8 am, Melas hurled FML [[Karl Joseph Hadik von Futak]]'s division (four battalions) at Victor's defenses, supported by Frimont’s advance guard battery along the stream.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollins606&quot;/&gt; Forced into a funnel by the bad ground and Fontanone stream, Hadik’s attack came under fire from two sides and failed, with Hadik being killed. The Austrian commander then committed FML [[Konrad Valentin von Kaim]]'s division but this attack was also thwarted by 11 am. Finally, as the French position was reinforced by [[François Étienne de Kellermann]]'s cavalry and [[Jean Lannes]]'s formation was on the way, FML [[Ferdinand Johann von Morzin]]'s elite [[grenadier]] division was sent in to attack Marengo village.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollins607&quot;&gt;Hollins, ''Encyclopedia'', p. 607&lt;/ref&gt; Melas also committed a serious tactical blunder, detaching ''[[Generalmajor]]'' (GM) Nimptsch's brigade of 2,300 [[hussar]]s and two artillery batteries back over the Bormida bridge to block the corps of General [[Louis Gabriel Suchet]], which was mistakenly reported around 9 am from [[Acqui Terme]] to be approaching Alessandria from the south.&lt;ref&gt;Arnold, p. 151&lt;/ref&gt; Besides delaying the crossing of the Austrian left wing, this also meant that, being 30 kilometers away, Nimptsch's brigade would play no part in the battle.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollins607&quot;/&gt;

====Stalemate in the centre around Marengo====
[[File:Kellermann, Francois Etienne.jpg|thumb|[[François Étienne de Kellermann]] played an important role during the battle.|alt=Painted portrait of Kellermann while wearing his French blue general uniform with yellow epaulettes, a red sash, and high collar. His hair and eyes are brown and he gazes to the left of the viewer. Kellermann wears three decorations on his chest.]]
It took Bonaparte (5 kilometers away from Marengo) until about 10 am to recognize that the Austrian activity was not a diversionary attack to cover the anticipated retreat by Melas.  His subordinates had brought their troops up in support of Victor's corps. Lannes's corps had deployed on the crucial right flank. GM [[Friedrich Joseph Anton von Bellegarde]]’s part of Kaim’s division had crossed the Fontanone north of Marengo and occupied La Barbotta farm. Lannes directed Watrin’s infantry to drive Bellegarde back. They briefly crossed the Fontanone before Austrian reserve guns drove the French back. Kellermann's heavy cavalry brigade and the 8th Dragoons took up a covering position on the left, smashing an attempt by GM Giovanni Pilatti's light dragoon brigade which attempted to cross the steep-sided Fontanone at its southern end to envelop Victor's flank.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollins607&quot;/&gt; On the right, [[Brigadier General|GdB]] Pierre Champeaux was killed trying to stop the progress of Ott's column. A small part of the 6ème Légère (6th Light Infantry Regiment) occupied Castel Ceriolo to the north, but soon Ott's lead units took it around 11:30 am and began putting pressure on the French right flank. Ott could not see any sign of the expected main French advance from Sale (to the northeast), so he sent GM [[Friedrich Heinrich von Gottesheim]]’s reinforced advance guard to outflank Lannes north of Marengo.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollins607&quot;/&gt; By 11 am Bonaparte was on the battlefield. He sent urgent recalls to his recently detached forces and summoned up his last reserves. As they came up, GdD [[Jean-Charles Monnier]]'s division and the [[Imperial Guard (Napoleon I)#History|Consular Guard]] were committed to extend and shore up the French right, rather than to try to hold Marengo where Victor's men were running short of ammunition.&lt;ref&gt;Arnold, p. 158&lt;/ref&gt;

====Austrian breakout across the Fontanone====
Toward 12:30 pm Lannes moved the rest of his force to face Gottesheim in a hook shape, while Kaim attacked again, but this time against Victor’s wings. A ''Laufbrücke'' (small bridge) was thrown over the Fontanone and supported by reserve artillery. GM [[Christoph von Latterman]]’s grenadiers crossed to engage [[Olivier Macoux Rivaud de la Raffinière]]’s two demibrigades defending Marengo village, while Bellegarde and Frimont’s four squadrons split Watrin off. Although Rivaud retook the village, O’Reilly had taken Stortiglione by 2:00 pm, and in the north, Ott prepared to send FML [[Joseph von Schellenberg]]’s column to support Gottesheim. After securing the Fontanone bridge, Pilatti’s cavalry crossed but were again charged and defeated by Kellermann. However, Victor could no longer hold his positions and withdrew southeast to the main vine belt ([[Vitis|grape vines]] slung among [[mulberry]] trees), Lannes mirroring the move. The Marengo farm garrison was abandoned and at around 2:30 pm Melas led two cavalry squadrons to capture them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollins607&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Johann Maria Philipp Frimont.png|thumb|left|[[Johann Maria Philipp Frimont|Johann Frimont]]'s troops destroyed the Consular Guard infantry.|alt=Black and white half-length portrait of General Frimont wearing a full hussar-style dress. His black strands of hair conceal his early baldness. He looks to the left of the viewer and keeps his right hand on a table and his left one on the hip, covered by the pelisse. He has multiple decorations on his chest.]]
At about 2:00 pm the French attacked Castel Ceriolo and delayed the advance of Schellenberg’s column by attacking its tail.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollins607&quot;/&gt; Aided by Frimont, Ott defeated Monnier and forced two-thirds of his command to retreat to the northeast. About the same time, Marengo had fallen to the Austrians, forcing Napoleon's men into a general retreat.&lt;ref&gt;Arnold, p. 162&lt;/ref&gt; As Austrian troops crossed the Fontanone, their guns bombarded the French infantry in the vines. In a bid to further delay Schellenberg’s advance, Bonaparte committed his main Guard battalion and its artillery, which moved to flank the column. After driving off Austrian [[dragoon]]s with the aid of GdB Champeaux’s remaining cavalry (under [[Joachim Murat]]), they engaged the head of the column. After a 15-minute firefight around 4:00 pm the Guard were surprised and destroyed by Frimont’s cavalry.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollins607&quot;/&gt;

The French fell back c. 3&amp;nbsp;km and attempted to regroup to hold the village of San Giuliano. With the French outnumbered and driven from their best defensive position, the battle was as good as won by the Austrians. Melas, who was slightly wounded, and 71, handed over command to his chief-of-staff, General [[Anton von Zach]], and Kaim. The Austrian centre formed into a massive pursuit column in order to chase the French off the battlefield, with the advance guard commanded by GM [[Franz Xaver Saint-Julien]]. The column formed up around Spinetta, southeast of Marengo, and advanced down the New Road. However, delays in the flanks led to the Austrian army forming a crescent shape with a thinly stretched central sector.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollins607&quot;/&gt; On the Austrian right wing, O'Reilly wasted time hunting down a 300-man French detachment led by Achille Dampierre (which was finally captured) and moved southeast. This took his troops out of supporting distance from the Austrian main body.&lt;ref&gt;Arnold, p. 160&lt;/ref&gt; On the Austrian left, Ott hesitated to press hard against the French because GdB Jean Rivaud's small brigade of French cavalry hovered to the north.&lt;ref&gt;Arnold, p. 173&lt;/ref&gt;

===French counter-attack===
[[Image:Battle of Marengo map.jpg|thumb|300px|Situation at the beginning of the French counter-attack|alt=Black and white map of the battle, featuring Castel Ceriolo in the top-left corner and San Giuliano in the lower-right centre. French troops are positioned to the left of San Giuliano and extend until to the right of Castel Ceriolo. The Austrian pursuit column advances from the left towards San Giuliano, but is blocked by the arrival of Desaix and Kellermann's charge.]]
However, Desaix, in charge of the force Bonaparte had detached southwards, had hastened his advance and reached a small road junction north of Cascina Grossa (3 kilometers west of San Giuliano).&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollins607&quot;/&gt; Shortly before 5:00 pm, he reported to Bonaparte in person with the news that his force (6,000 men and 9 guns of Boudet's division) was not far behind. The story goes that, asked by Bonaparte what he thought of the situation, Desaix replied: &quot;This battle is completely lost. However, there is time to win another.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Chandler, p. 269&lt;/ref&gt;

The French were fast to bring up and deploy the fresh troops in front of San Giuliano, and the Austrians were slow to mount their attack. Boudet and the 9ème Légère ([[9th Light Infantry Regiment]]) were quickly moved on to the exit from the main vine belt, where they surprised the head of Saint-Julien’s column. As the Austrian infantry deployed on the south side of the road, the 9ème Légère conducted a steady withdrawal for 30 minutes back to Desaix’s position. There he had placed GdB Louis Charles de Guénand’s brigade on the north side while most of the remaining French army (Monnier and Lannes) were forming up north from there. The Austrians deployed three artillery batteries on the north side of the road supported by a dragoon regiment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollins607&quot;/&gt; GdB [[Auguste de Marmont]] massed the remaining French cannon against the Austrians as they advanced. Boudet's division advanced in line of brigades against the head of the Austrian column, defeating Saint-Julien's leading Austrian brigade. Zach brought forward GM Latterman's grenadier brigade in line and renewed the attack. Faced with a crisis, Napoleon sent Desaix forward again and ordered a cavalry charge requested by Desaix. The 9ème Légère halted to face the main Austrian advance and Marmont's guns blasted the Austrians with grapeshot at close range.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollins607&quot;/&gt; Further back, an Austrian ammunition limber exploded. In the temporary heightening of confusion, Lattermann's formation was charged on its left flank by Kellermann's heavy cavalry (ca. 400 men) and disintegrated. At the decisive moment of the battle, Desaix was shot from his horse.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollins607&quot;/&gt; Zach and at least 2,000 of his men were taken prisoners.&lt;ref&gt;Arnold, pp. 177–180&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Broc.jpg|thumb|left|250px|Napoleon is presented the body of Desaix|alt=Oil painting featuring Napoleon in the foreground being presented by a soldier the body of Desaix. Desaix is wearing a white shirt and his chest is exposed to show the wound. Numerous and curious bystanders surround the scene.]]
Murat and Kellermann immediately pounced on the supporting Liechtenstein Dragoons who were too slow to respond and routed them as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollins607&quot;/&gt; The fleeing Austrian horsemen crashed into the ranks of Pilatti's rattled troopers and carried them away. As the mob of terrified cavalry stampeded past them, the exhausted Austrian infantry of the main body lost heart, provoking a wild rush to the rear. The gun teams fled, pursued by French cavalry, while their whole infantry line advanced westward.&lt;ref&gt;Hollins, ''Encyclopedia'', pp. 607–608&lt;/ref&gt; The second grenadier brigade under GM [[Karl Philippi von Weidenfeld]] and some unpanicked cavalry delayed Boudet’s advance long enough for O’Reilly’s cavalry to return, and together with Frimont, they mounted a last defense around Marengo village as night fell, allowing the Austrian centre to reach safety behind the Bormida.&lt;ref&gt;Arnold, pp. 180–181&lt;/ref&gt; Ott with the Austrian left failed to intervene and found his retreat through Castel Ceriolo blocked by French troops advancing northwest from the centre, but managed to fight his way back to the Bormida bridgehead.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollins608&quot;&gt;Hollins, ''Encyclopedia'', p. 608&lt;/ref&gt;

The Austrians fell back into Alessandria, having lost about half the forces they had committed. The Austrians had lost heavily in the 12 hours of fighting: 15 colours, 40 guns, almost 8,000 taken prisoner, and 6,500 dead or wounded.&lt;ref&gt;Fremont-Barnes, Gregory. ''The French Revolutionary Wars'', Routledge: New Edition, 2001, ISBN 978-1-57958-365-1, p.56, gives 6,000 casualties and 8,000 prisoners , 40 guns. Similarly, Chandler and Asprey.&lt;/ref&gt; French casualties (killed and wounded) were on the order of 4,700 and 900 missing or captured, but they retained the battlefield and the strategic initiative.&lt;ref name=&quot;Benoit122&quot;/&gt; Desaix's body was found among the slain.&lt;ref&gt;Benoît, p. 137&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
Bonaparte needed to depart for [[Paris]] urgently and the next morning sent Berthier on a surprise visit to Austrian headquarters.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollins608&quot;/&gt; Within 24 hours of the battle, Melas entered into negotiations (the [[s:Convention of Alessandria|Convention of Alessandria]]) which led to the Austrians evacuating northwestern Italy west of the [[Ticino river]], and suspending military operations in Italy.

Bonaparte's position as [[First Consul]] was strengthened by the successful outcome of the battle and the preceding campaign.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollins608&quot;/&gt; After this victory, Napoleon could breathe a sigh of relief. The generals who had been hostile to him could see that his luck had not abandoned him. Thus, he had surpassed [[Barthélemy Louis Joseph Schérer|Schérer]], [[Barthélemy Catherine Joubert|Joubert]], [[Jean Étienne Championnet|Championnet]], and even [[Jean Victor Marie Moreau|Moreau]], none of whom had been able to inflict a decisive blow on the Coalition. Moreau's victory at [[Battle of Hohenlinden|Hohenlinden]], which was the one that in reality had put an end to the war, was minimised by Bonaparte who, from then on, would pose as a saviour of the fatherland, and even of the Republic. He rejected offers from [[Louis XVIII of France|Louis XVIII]], who had considered the [[French Consulate|Consulate]] to be a mere transition towards the restoration of the king. Thanks to the victory at Marengo, Napoleon could finally set about [[Napoleon I#Reforms|reforming France according to his own vision]].&lt;ref&gt;Benoît, pp. 124–125&lt;/ref&gt;

===Propaganda===
[[File:Rue de Marengo, Paris.JPG|thumb|''Rue de Marengo'' in [[Paris]] is named to commemorate the battle.|alt=Blue street sign with green edges. It says in white: &quot;1er Arrt&quot; and below &quot;RUE DE MARENGO&quot;.]]
A last-gasp victory in reality, Marengo was mythologised in an army bulletin and three increasingly glamourised &quot;Official Reports&quot; during Bonaparte's reign. Tales were invented about the Guard and the 72ème demibrigade, which had been under his direct control throughout.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hollins608&quot;/&gt;

General [[François Étienne de Kellermann|François Kellermann]] distinguished himself at Marengo. Melas, trapped in Alessandria with his hopes of breaking through to the east shattered, sent the same evening to [[Vienna]] a message in which he explained that the &quot;charge of Kellermann had broken the soldiers and this sudden and terrible change of fortunes finished by smashing the courage of the troops. The disorder of the cavalry which had disorganised our infantry precipitated its retreat.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Benoit123&quot;&gt;Benoît, p. 123&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, Murat was writing to Berthier: &quot;I especially have to tell you about Kellermann; through a powerful charge he managed to tilt the balance in our favour.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Benoit123&quot;/&gt; However, in the ''Bulletin de l'armée'' issued the following day, Napoleon sought to counterbalance Kellermann's charge with [[Jean-Baptiste Bessières]]'s: &quot;The ''[[chef de brigade]]'' Bessières, in front of the reckless grenadiers of the guard, executed a charge with as much activity as valour and penetrated the line of the enemy cavalry; this resulted in the entire rout of the army.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Benoît, p. 124&lt;/ref&gt;

Another piece of work which attempted to justify the retreat maneuver and to present it as a highly strategic calculation was Berthier's ''Relation de la bataille de Marengo'', published in 1804. Berthier suggests that time had to be given to Desaix and Boudet's division to occupy their positions: &quot;The enemy general misinterpreted this maneuver and thought the army was in full retreat, while in reality it was only executing a movement of conversion.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Benoit123&quot;/&gt; However, it is known that Desaix's arrival, while definitely expected, was not certain before the retreat. The bulletin explains that Desaix's forces were waiting in reserve with artillery pieces, which in reality was false, because they arrived late in the battle. Several participants to the fighting reveal the precarious condition of the army throughout the day, including Marmont in his Memoirs, Captain Coignet: &quot;We were retreating in good order but all ready to start running at the earliest sign of danger&quot;, Captain Gervais: &quot;In this battle, we were many times on the verge of being defeated. The enemy cavalry, on a terrain favourable to this arm, charged us repeatedly. We were often obliged to concentrate and even to retreat&quot;, and General Thévenet: &quot;There is no doubt that a part of the French army was repelled up to the [[Scrivia]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Benoît, pp. 123–124&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
===Marengo museum===
The Museum of Marengo &quot;Museo della Battaglia di Marengo&quot; is located in Via della Barbotta, Spinetta Marengo, Alessandria. This is exactly the place where most of the fights between the French and Austrian armies took place. It is a part of Villa Delavo, with the park of the museum surrounding the village of Marengo.

===Remembrance===
[[File:I-AL-Marengo3.JPG|thumb|The column at Marengo|alt=A five feet high column with an eagle on top]]
Napoleon sought to ensure that his victory would not be forgotten, so, besides the propaganda campaign, he entrusted General Chasseloup with the construction of a pyramid on the site of the battle. On 5 May 1805, a ceremony took place on the field of Marengo. Napoleon, dressed in the uniform he wore on 14 June 1800, together with Empress [[Joséphine de Beauharnais|Joséphine]] seated on a throne placed under a tent, oversaw a military parade. Then, Chasseloup gave Napoleon the founding stone, on which was inscribed: &quot;Napoleon, Emperor of the French and King of Italy, to the ''[[manes]]'' of the defenders of the fatherland who perished on the day of Marengo.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Benoit138&quot;&gt;Benoît, p. 138&lt;/ref&gt; This pyramid was actually part of a very ambitious project meant to glorify Bonaparte's conquests in Italy. The field of Marengo was supposed to become the site of a &quot;city of Victories&quot; whose boulevards, named after Italian battles, would converge to the pyramid. In the event, the project was abandoned in 1815 and the stones recovered by the peasants. The column erected in 1801 was also removed, only to be restored in 1922.&lt;ref name=&quot;Benoit138&quot;/&gt;

Napoleon ordered that several ships of the [[French Navy]] be named Marengo, including ''[[French ship Sceptre (1780)|Sceptre (1780)]]'', ''[[French ship Jean-Jacques Rousseau (1795)|Jean-Jacques Rousseau (1795)]]'', ''[[French ship Ville de Paris (1851)|Ville de Paris (1851)]]'' and ''[[French ship Marengo (1810)|Marengo (1810)]]''. In 1802, the [[Marengo department]] was named in the honour of the battle.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last = Vosgien|first = Lyon et Paris|title = Les départements de l'Empire Français en 1809|url=http://www.1789-1815.com/depts_1809.htm#marengo|accessdate = 13 September 2010| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20100921071419/http://www.1789-1815.com/depts_1809.htm| archivedate= 21 September 2010 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, Napoleon's mount throughout the battle was named [[Marengo (horse)|Marengo]] and further carried the Emperor in the [[Battle of Austerlitz]], [[Battle of Jena-Auerstedt]], [[Battle of Wagram]], and [[Battle of Waterloo]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last = Hamilton|first = Jill|title = MARENGO, the Myth of Napoleon's Horse|url=http://www.jill-hamilton.com/pdf/marengo-the-myth-of-napoleons-horse.pdf|accessdate = 13 September 2010}} p. 32&lt;/ref&gt;

After Bonaparte's fall, [[Marengo County, Alabama|Marengo County]], Alabama, first settled by Napoleonic refugees with their [[Vine and Olive Colony]], was named in honour of this battle. Since then, numerous settlements were named Marengo in Canada and the United States (see [[Marengo (disambiguation)#Places|places named Marengo]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title=Alabama Counties: Marengo County|work=&quot;Alabama Department of Archives and History&quot;|url=http://www.archives.state.al.us/counties/marengo.html|accessdate=13 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Presently, a museum of the battle exists on the outskirts of Alessandria. Re-enactments are also organised every year to commemorate the event.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last = Hicks|first = Peter|title = Marengo Museum: opening weekend|url=http://www.napoleon.org/en/reading_room/articles/files/477077.asp|accessdate = 13 September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Cultural references===
Puccini's opera ''[[Tosca]]'' is set in Rome three days after the battle of Marengo, which is how long it took for the news of Napoleon's victory to reach Rome. The conflict between Papists and Republicans is an important part of the plot.  [[Chicken Marengo]] is named for this battle; either Napoleon ate its first preparation after his victory or a restaurant chef named the dish in Napoleon's honor. Author [[Robert Penn Warren]], in his 1946 work [[All the King's Men]], has protagonist Willie Stark lecture his son that his erratic behavior will result in his suspension from the state university's football team, of which he is the star quarterback, saying &quot;I don't care if you are Napoleon at Marengo, I'll see you never get your hands on a football again.&quot;

{{clear}}

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
*{{Cite book|last=Arnold|first= James R.|title=Marengo &amp; Hohenlinden: Napoleon's Rise to Power|publisher=Pen &amp; Sword|year=2005}} ISBN 1-84415-279-0
*{{Cite book|last=Asprey|first= Robert|title=The Rise of Napoleon Bonaparte|publisher=Basic Books|year=2001}} ISBN 0-465-04881-1
*{{cite book|last=Benoît|first=Jérémie|title=Marengo: Une victoire politique|publisher=Réunion des Musées Nationaux|year=2000|language=fr}} ISBN 2-7118-4010-7
*{{Cite book|last=Chandler|first=David|title=Dictionary of the Napoleonic Wars|publisher=Macmillan|year=1979}} ISBN 0-02-523670-9
*{{Cite book|last=Chandler|first=David|title=Campaigns of Napoleon|publisher=Scribner|year=1966}} ISBN 0-02-523660-1
*{{Cite book|last=Hollins|first=David|title=The Battle of Marengo 1800|publisher=Osprey Publishing|year=2000}} ISBN 1-84176-117-6
*{{Cite book|last=Hollins|first=David|title=&quot;Battle of Marengo&quot; in The Encyclopedia of the French Revolutionary and Napoleonic War|publisher=ABC-CLIO|year=2006}} ISBN 1-85109-646-9
*{{Cite book|last=Fremont-Barnes|first=Gregory|title=The French Revolutionary Wars|publisher=Routledge; New edition|year=2001}} ISBN 978-1-57958-365-1
* {{cite book|last=Pigeard|first=Alain|title=Dictionnaire des batailles de Napoléon|publisher=Tallandier, Bibliothèque Napoléonienne|year=2004|language=fr}} ISBN 2-84734-073-4
*{{Cite journal|title=To Marengo, Battle of 1800|last= Shosenberg|first=James|journal=Military History|date=June 2000|volume=17|issue=II}}

==External links==
{{wikisource|Convention of Alessandria}}
{{Commons category|Battle of Marengo}}
* [http://www.wtj.com/articles/marengo/ The Battle of Marengo – A Bicentennial Review] ''An overview of the battle, including short summaries for beginning students and detailed analysis for more serious readers.''
* [http://www.napolun.com/mirror/web2.airmail.net/napoleon/Marengo_battle.htm Defeat of Bonaparte's Guard at Marengo, 1800.]
* [http://www.napoleonic-literature.com/Book_13/Notebook_3.htm Battle of Marengo in the memoirs of Captain Coignet] ''
* [http://www.simmonsgames.com/research/authors/Cugnac/ArmeeReserve/index.html Gaspar Cugnac, Campaign of the Army of the Reserve in 1800 ] ''French scans and OCR complete, English translation for vol 1 only, use French version for the battle proper.''
* [http://www.simmonsgames.com/research/authors/Berthier/RelationMarengo/index.html Alex. Berthier, Relation of the Battle of Marengo]
* {{it icon}} [http://www.marengomuseum.it/ Marengo Museum]

{{French Revolution navbox}}
{{Use British English|date=November 2010}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Marengo, Battle of}}
[[Category:Battles of the French Revolutionary Wars]]
[[Category:Battles of the War of the Second Coalition]]
[[Category:Battles involving Austria]]
[[Category:Battles involving France]]
[[Category:Military history of Italy]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1800]]
[[Category:1800 in Italy]]
[[Category:1800 in Austria]]
[[Category:1800 in France]]</text>
      <sha1>14ll47f1a3vo1pyjuv5ia3aujmbf4pj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
