<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of Ostrach</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>24495975</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749401363</id>
      <parentid>746663678</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-14T03:39:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GreenC bot</username>
        <id>27823944</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>1 archive template merged to {{[[template:webarchive|webarchive]]}} ([[User:Green_Cardamom/Webarchive_template_merge|WAM]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="37716">{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2011}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Battle of Ostrach
| partof      = the [[War of the Second Coalition]]
| image       = [[File:Archduke Charles at Battle of Ostrach.JPG|270px]]
| caption     = Archduke Charles and his staff at the Battle of Ostrach
| date        = 20–21&amp;nbsp;March 1799 
| place       = [[Ostrach]], [[Salem Abbey]] (Germany)
| result      = French Retreat
| combatant1  = {{flagicon|Habsburg Monarchy}} [[Habsburg Monarchy|Habsburg Austria]] 
| combatant2  = [[File:Flag of France.svg|22px|link=]] [[French First Republic]]
| commander1  = [[Archduke Charles, Duke of Teschen|Archduke Charles]]
| commander2  = [[Jean Baptiste Jourdan]]
| strength1   = 52,000  
| strength2   = 28,000  
| casualties1 = 2,113 (4%) 
| casualties2 = 2,257 (8%) 
| notes       = Digby Smith. ''Napoleonic Wars Databook: Actions and Losses in Personnel, Colours, Standards and Artillery, 1792–1815''. Mechanicsburg PA: Stackpole, 1998, ISBN 1-85367-276-9, p. 147
| campaignbox = 
{{Campaignbox Second Coalition}}
{{Second Coalition in southwest Germany}}
}}
The '''Battle of Ostrach''', also called the '''Battle by Ostrach''', occurred on 20–21&amp;nbsp;March 1799. It was the first battle of the [[War of the Second Coalition]]. The battle resulted in the victory of the Austrian forces, under the command of [[Archduke Charles, Duke of Teschen|Archduke Charles]], over the French forces, commanded by [[Jean Baptiste Jourdan]].

The battle occurred during [[Holy Week]], 1799, amid rain and dense fog. Initially, the French were able to take, and hold, [[Ostrach]] and the nearby hamlet of [[Hoßkirch]] plus several strategic points on the Ostrach marsh. As the engagement began, Habsburg numerical superiority overwhelmed French defenses. By evening, the French left wing was flanked and Jourdan's men retreated from Ostrach to the [[Pfullendorf]] heights. On the next morning, as Jourdan considered a counter-attack, the weather broke, and he could look down on the Austrian battle array. The numbers and dispositions of the Austrians convinced him that any attack would be useless, and that he could not hope to maintain his position in the heights. As he withdrew, a portion of his right flank was cut off from the main force.

Although casualties appeared even on both sides, the Austrians had a significantly larger fighting force, both on the field at Ostrach, and stretched along a line between [[Lake Constance]] and [[Ulm]]. French casualties amounted to eight percent of the force and Austrian, approximately four percent. The French withdrew to [[Engen, Germany|Engen]] and [[Stockach]], where a few days later the armies engaged again, this time with greater losses on both sides, and an [[Battle of Stockach (1799)|Austrian victory]].

==Background==
{{main|French Revolutionary Wars}}
Initially, the rulers of Europe, such as [[Joseph II, Holy Roman Emperor]], viewed the revolution in France as an event between the French king and his subjects, and not something in which they should interfere. As the rhetoric grew more strident, however, the other monarchies started to view events with alarm. In 1790, [[Leopold II, Holy Roman Emperor|Leopold]] succeeded his brother Joseph as emperor and by 1791, he considered the situation surrounding his sister, [[Marie Antoinette]], and her children, with greater and greater alarm. In August 1791, in consultation with French émigré nobles and [[Frederick William II of Prussia|Frederick William II]] of Prussia, he issued the [[Declaration of Pilnitz]], in which they declared the interest of the monarchs of Europe as one with the interests of Louis and his family. They threatened ambiguous, but quite serious, consequences if anything should happen to the royal family.&lt;ref&gt;Timothy Blanning. ''The French Revolutionary Wars'', New York: Oxford University Press, pp. 41–59.&lt;/ref&gt;

The French Republican position became increasingly difficult. Compounding problems in international relations, French émigrés continued to agitate for support of a counter-revolution abroad. Chief among them were the [[Louis Joseph de Bourbon, prince de Condé|Prince Condé]], his son, the [[Louis Henry II, Prince of Conde|Duke de Bourbon]], and his grandson, the [[Louis-Antoine-Henri de Bourbon-Condé, duc d'Enghien|Duke d'Enghien]]. From their base in [[Koblenz]], immediately over the French border, they sought direct support for military intervention from the royal houses of Europe, and raised an army.&lt;ref&gt;Blanning, pp. 44–59.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 20 April 1792, the [[French National Convention]] declared war on Austria. In this [[War of the First Coalition]] (1792–1798), France ranged itself against most of the European states sharing land or water borders with her, plus Portugal and the Ottoman Empire. Although the Coalition forces achieved several victories at [[Battle of Verdun (1792)|Verdun]], [[Battle of Kaiserslautern|Kaiserslautern]], [[Battle of Neerwinden (1793)|Neerwinden]], [[Battle of Mainz|Mainz]], [[Battle of Amberg|Amberg]] and [[Battle of Würzburg|Würzburg]], the efforts of [[Napoleon Bonaparte]] in northern [[Italian campaigns of the French Revolutionary Wars|Italy]] pushed Austrian forces back and resulted in the negotiation of the [[Peace of Leoben]] (17 April 1797) and the subsequent [[Treaty of Campo Formio]] (October 1797).&lt;ref&gt;Blanning, pp. 41–59.&lt;/ref&gt;

The treaty called for meetings between the involved parties to work out the exact territorial and remunerative details, to be convened at [[Second Congress of Rastatt|Rastatt]]. The French demand for more territory than originally agreed upon stalled negotiations. Despite their agreement at Campo Formio and the ongoing meetings at Rastatt, the two primary combatants of the First Coalition, France and Austria, were highly suspicious of the other's motives. Several diplomatic incidents undermined the agreement. The Austrians were reluctant to cede the designated territories and the Rastatt delegates could not, or would not, orchestrate the transfer of agreed upon territories to compensate the German princes for their losses. [[Ferdinand I of the Two Sicilies|Ferdinand of Naples]] refused to pay tribute to France, followed by the Neapolitan rebellion, invasion by France, and the subsequent establishment of the [[Parthenopaean Republic]]. Republican uprising in the Swiss cantons, encouraged by the French Republic with military support, led to the establishment of the [[Helvetic Republic]].&lt;ref&gt;Blanning, pp. 230–232.&lt;/ref&gt;

Other factors contributed to the rising tensions as well. On his way to [[Napoleon's invasion of Egypt|Egypt]] in 1798, [[Napoleon]] had stopped on the [[Malta#History|Island of Malta]] and forcibly removed the [[Knights Hospitaller|Hospitallers]] from their possessions. This angered [[Paul I of Russia|Paul, Tsar of Russia]], who was the honorary head of the Order. The [[French Directory]], furthermore, was convinced that the Austrians were conniving to start another war. Indeed, the weaker the French Republic seemed, the more seriously the Austrians, the Neapolitans, the Russians and the English actually discussed this possibility.&lt;ref&gt;John Gallagher. ''Napoleon's enfant terrible: General Dominique Vandamme,'' Tulsa: University of Oklahoma Press, 2008, ISBN 978-0-8061-3875-6 p. 70.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Ostrach --&gt;{{coord|47|57|N|9|23|E|display=title}}

==Prelude==
[[Archduke Charles, Duke of Teschen|Archduke Charles of Austria]] had taken command of the army in late January. Although he was unhappy with the strategy set forward by his brother, the Holy Roman Emperor [[Francis II, Holy Roman Emperor|Francis II]], he had acquiesced to the less ambitious plan to which Francis and the [[Aulic council]] had agreed: Austria would fight a defensive war and would maintain a continuous defensive line from the Danube to northern Italy. The archduke had stationed himself at [[Friedberg, Bavaria|Friedberg]] for the winter, {{convert|4.7|mi|0}} east-south-east of [[Augsburg]]. The army was already settled into cantonments in the environs of Augsburg, extending south along the Lech river.&lt;ref&gt;Blanning, p. 232; Gunther E. Rothenberg. ''Napoleon’s great adversaries: Archduke Charles and the Austrian Army 1792–1914''. Stroud, (Gloucester): Spellmount, 2007, p. 74; Ramsey Weston Phipps. ''The Armies of the First French Republic'', volume 5: The armies of the Rhine in Switzerland, Holland, Italy, Egypt and the coup d'etat of Brumaire, 1797–1799, Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1939, pp. 49–50.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!--  {{coord|48|22|0|N|10|54|0|E|display=inline}} --&gt;

As winter broke in 1799, on 1&amp;nbsp;March, General [[Jean Baptiste Jourdan]] and his army of 25,000,&lt;ref&gt;John Young, D.D. ''A History of the Commencement, Progress, and Termination of the Late War between Great Britain and France which continued from the first day of February 1793 to the first of October 1801'', in two volumes. Edinburg: Turnbull, 1802, vol. 2, p. 220.&lt;/ref&gt;  the so-called [[Army of the Danube]], crossed the [[Rhine]] at [[Kehl]]&lt;!-- {{coord|48|34|0|N|7|49|0|E|display=inline}} --&gt;. Instructed to block the Austrians from access to the Swiss alpine passes, the Army of the Danube would ostensibly isolate the armies of the Coalition in Germany from allies in northern Italy, and prevent them from assisting one another; furthermore, if the French held the interior passes in Switzerland, they could use the routes to move their own forces between the two theaters. The Army of the Danube, meeting little resistance, advanced through the [[Black Forest]] in three columns, through the Höllental (Hölle valley), via [[Oberkirch (Baden)|Oberkirch]], and [[Freudenstadt]], and a fourth column advanced along the north shore of the Rhine.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blanning, p. 232&quot;&gt;Blanning, p. 232.&lt;/ref&gt; Although Jourdan might have been better advised to establish a position on the eastern slope of the mountains, he did not.&lt;ref&gt;Rothenberg, pp. 49–50.&lt;/ref&gt; Instead, he pushed across the Danube plain and took up position between [[Rottweil]] &lt;!-- {{coord|48|10|N|8|37|E|display=inline}} --&gt;and [[Tuttlingen]]&lt;!-- {{coord|47|59|6|N|8|49|24|E|display=inline}} --&gt;, and eventually pushing toward the [[Free imperial city|imperial city]] of [[Pfullendorf]] in Upper [[Swabia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Blanning, p. 232&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Stockach.png|thumb|upright=1.8|alt=A map of southwestern Germany, where troops wintered in the east and west, on the banks of two rivers; the troops converged at a point in the center.|French troops wintered in France and crossed the Rhine, moving toward Ostrach in March 1799; Austrian troops wintered in Bavaria, crossed the Lech, and approached Ostrach from the east.]]

News of the French advance across the Rhine took three days to reach Charles at Augsburg. The Austrian ''Vorhut'' (advance guard), 17,000&amp;nbsp;men under the command of Field marshal [[Friedrich Joseph, Count of Nauendorf]], crossed the [[Lech (river)|Lech]] in three columns, the first at [[Babenhausen]], marching in the direction of [[Biberach, Baden|Biberach]], the second, and strongest, at [[Memmingen]], marching in the direction of Waldsee, and the third at [[Leutkirch]], heading in the direction of [[Ravensburg]]. The main force of 53,000&amp;nbsp;men, under the command of the Archduke, crossed the Lech by [[Augsburg]], [[Landsberg am Lech|Landsberg]] and [[Schongau, Bavaria|Schongau]], and six battalions of 6,600&amp;nbsp;men crossed the Danube at [[Ulm]]. An additional force of 13,000&amp;nbsp;troops under the command of Lieutenant Field Marshal [[Anton Graf Sztáray von Nagy-Mihaly|Anton Sztáray]] marched toward Neumarkt in the direction of [[Rednitz]].&lt;ref&gt;Smith, p. 147.&lt;/ref&gt;  Eventually, 10,000&amp;nbsp;men under the command of General [[Friedrich Freiherr von Hotze]] marched north from Feldkirch in Switzerland, but they did not arrive in time to participate at either the battle at Ostrach, or for the subsequent battle at [[Battle of Stockach (1799)|Stockach]].&lt;ref&gt;David Hollins, ''Austrian Commanders of the Napoleonic Wars, 1792–1815''. London, Osprey, 2004, pp. 18–19.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Locale===
Ostrach was a small village, with a population of 300. The village belonged to the Cistercian [[Imperial Abbey of Salem]],&lt;!--  {{coord|47|46|34|N|9|16|46|E|display=inline}}, --&gt; an influential and wealthy ecclesiastical territory on [[Lake Constance]]. The village was largely dedicated to farming, although a stretch of the imperial post road connected it and Pfullendorf. A wide, flat plain, marshy in places, stretched between the base of the Pfullendorf heights and the village; low lying hills ringed the valley, which was creased by a small stream from which the village takes its name.&lt;ref&gt;Jean-Baptiste Jourdan. ''A Memoir of the operations of the army of the Danube under the command of General Jourdan, taken from the manuscripts of that officer'', London: Debrett, 1799, p. 164.&lt;/ref&gt; Ostrach itself lies almost at the northern end of this plain, but slightly south of the Danube itself. The two armies faced each other across this small and, at that time of that year, very soggy valley.&lt;ref&gt;Young, p. 228.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Dispositions===
By 7 March, the first Austrian soldiers arrived in Ostrach.&lt;ref&gt;Blanning, p. 232; {{de icon}} Ruth Broda. ''&quot;Schlacht von Ostrach:“ jährt sich zum 210. Mal {{dash}} Feier am Wochenende. Wie ein Dorf zum Kriegsschauplatz wurde''. In: ''Südkurier'' vom 13. Mai 2009&lt;/ref&gt; The French advance guard arrived by the 9th, under command of General [[François Joseph Lefebvre]]; in the forward line, the 25th Demi-brigade and Light Infantry positioned themselves between Ostrach and Hoßkirch; Lefebvre also had three battalions each of the 53rd and 67th Demi-Brigades of light infantry, twenty squadrons of hussars, chasseurs, and dragoons, and field artillery pieces.&lt;ref&gt;Smith, p. 147; Jourdan, pp. 140–144; Broda, ''Südkurier''.&lt;/ref&gt; By 12 March, the village and the surrounding farms were filled with [[Lancers]] (''Ulanen'') and [[Hussars]] (''Hussaren'') and by the 17th, the Austrian advance guard had established forward posts at [[Buchau]], [[Altshausen]] and [[Bad Waldsee|Waldsee]].&lt;ref&gt;Broda. ''Südkurier''.&lt;/ref&gt;  The remainder of Charles' army, at this point nearly 110,000&amp;nbsp;strong, had established itself along a line from Ulm to Lake Constance.&lt;ref&gt;Phipps, pp. 49–50; Young, p. 227.&lt;/ref&gt;

By 18 March, Jourdan had formed his headquarters at Pfullendorf&lt;!--  {{coord|47|55|N|9|15|E|display=inline}} --&gt;, on the heights above Ostrach. In front of him stood the largest part of his cavalry and half of his infantry. The center, including the 4th Regiment of Hussars, the 1st of [[Chasseurs à Cheval]], and two squadrons of the 17th Dragoons, lay behind Ostrach, under command of General Klein. Jourdan distributed them in three columns, the strongest on the post road by [[Bad Saulgau|Saulgau]], another on the road in the direction of Altshausen, and a third at the hamlet of Friedberg.&lt;ref&gt;Phipps, pp. 49–50; Young, p. 227–228.&lt;/ref&gt;

The flank of Lefebvre's division, with 7,000&amp;nbsp;men, commanded by [[Laurent de Gouvion Saint-Cyr|Laurent Saint-Cyr]] extended to the Danube; by the time skirmishing began, Vandamme was still in the environs of Stuttgart, with 3,000&amp;nbsp;men, looking in vain for Austrian forces that might be stationed there, and he played no part in the battle.&lt;ref&gt;John Gallagher. ''Napoleon's enfant terrible: General Dominique Vandamme''. Tulsa: University of Oklahoma Press, 2008, ISBN 978-0-8061-3875-6, p. 76-77.&lt;/ref&gt;  The far right, under command of Ferino, angled south from Pfullendorf to Lake Constance, or the [[Bodensee]]. The cavalry reserve of 3,000&amp;nbsp;under General [[Jean-Joseph Ange d'Hautpoul]] included a battalion of the 53rd Demi-Brigade, and waited in close column in the environs of Pfullendorf.&lt;ref&gt;Young, pp. 220–228; Jourdan, p. 140–144&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battle==
Jourdan considered his position superior to the Austrian's, protected as he was by the marshy plain between his positions and the Austrian front, and he thought he had another three days to consolidate his positions. His forces occupied Hoßkirch, and a couple of other points he considered strategic: the causeway (post road) that passed Saulgau (today Bad Saulgau), the village of [[Altshausen]]&lt;!--  {{coord|47|56|N|9|32|E|display=inline}} --&gt; {{convert|11|km|0|sp=us}} east, and the hamlet of [[Friedberg (Bad Saulgau)|Friedberg]]&lt;!--  {{coord|48|0|N|9|25|E|display=inline}} --&gt;,&lt;ref&gt;Phipps, pp. 49–50; Young, p. 227-228.&lt;/ref&gt;  {{convert|5|km|0|sp=us}} to the north-north-east of Ostrach. These positions created a perimeter around Ostrach. He was unaware that the Archduke had arrived by forced marches from Augsburg to the vicinity of Ostrach; Jourdan thought the main force of Charles' army was still at least three days' march away.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jourdan, p. 178&quot;&gt;Jourdan, p. 178.&lt;/ref&gt;  By the middle of Holy Week in 1799, more than a third of Charles' army, 48,000&amp;nbsp;mixed troops, was positioned in a formation parallel to Jourdan's, and his 72,000&amp;nbsp;remaining troops were arrayed with the left wing at [[Kempten]], the center near [[Memmingen]]&lt;!--  {{coord|47|59|16|N|10|10|52|E}} --&gt;, and the right flank extended to Ulm.&lt;ref name=&quot;Phipps pp. 49&quot;&gt;Phipps, pp. 49–50; Young, pp. 220–228.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Skirmishing ===
As the armies assembled in their positions, the flanks and forward outposts encountered one another in several skirmishes; indeed, they had been skirmishing for seven days, until 19&amp;nbsp;March, when the outposts of both armies nearly overlapped.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cust166&quot;&gt;Edward Cust (Sir). ''Annals of the wars of the eighteenth century, compiled from the most authentic histories of the period''. London: Mitchell's military library, 1857–1860, p. 166.&lt;/ref&gt; On the right wing, General Ferino's men encountered an Austrian column of volunteer infantry and some light cavalry from one of the border Hussar regiments, and took 70&amp;nbsp;and 80&amp;nbsp;prisoners, respectively, including several officers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Phipps pp. 49&quot;/&gt; All of this happened without the Austrians knowing that there was an official declaration of war. On the 20&amp;nbsp;March, a French emissary arrived at camp of Prince [[Karl Philipp, Prince of Schwarzenberg|Schwarzenberg]], a major general commanding a brigade of the advanced guard. The emissary asked if he possessed a declaration of war from Vienna, and upon being informed that Schwarzenberg had received no such declaration, informed him that the [[Treaty of Campo Formio|armistice]] established at [[Campo Formio]] was ended, and there existed between France and Austria a state of war. General Jourdan reportedly began a general attack when the emissary left,&lt;ref&gt;From the Hamburgh Mail. &quot;Private Correspondence&quot;, Hamburgh, 2&amp;nbsp;March 1799, reported in ''The Times'', 8&amp;nbsp;April 1799, pg. 3; col A.&lt;/ref&gt; although other sources do not bear out the scale of the attack.&lt;ref&gt;Phipps, pp. 49–50.&lt;/ref&gt; 
[[File:Ostrachbattlelocale.svg|thumb|left|upright=1.75|alt=Map shows the primary town of Ostrach, with several nearby villages which the French and Austrian forces skirmished.|Ostrach and the nearby villages.]]

Initially, the strength of the French advance guard pushed the most forward of the Austrian right to Saulgau and [[Ratzenreute]]&lt;!-- {{coord|47|57|N|9|28|E|display=inline}} --&gt;, {{convert|6.2|km|0|sp=us}} east of Ostrach, backing the Austrian main army against the [[Schussen]] river.&lt;ref&gt;Jourdan, p. 146.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Jean Victor Tharreau]]'s mixed brigade of infantry, light infantry and cavalry encountered the Austrians at Barendorf, and forced them to give up the ground; immediately, Charles sent reinforcements, and the Austrians regained what they had lost.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cust166&quot;/&gt;

At the center of the French line, at Hoßkirch, {{convert|3|km|0|sp=us}} east-south-east of Ostrach, General Lefebvre's column attacked the Austrians in an action that lasted most of the day. The Austrian line included several seasoned Grenzer (border) regiments, the ''Vecsy'' Hussars, and some lancers; although Lefebvre's initial assault caused confusion in the Austrian ranks, the Lancers counter-attacked with ferocity and, joined by the Grenzers and the Hussars, pursued the French along the Ostrach river valley, and cut up four squadrons of the 8th Regiment of ''Chasseurs à Cheval''.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Private Correspondence&quot;, ''The Times'', 8&amp;nbsp;April 1799.&lt;/ref&gt; Lefebvre's column was forced out of the hamlet by the Austrians, who had four battalions, 1200&amp;nbsp;horse, and six cannons.&lt;ref&gt;Phipps, pp. 49–50; Jourdan, pp. 145–149.&lt;/ref&gt; After bringing up additional reinforcements—several light artillery, ''Chasseurs à Cheval'', Hussars, and the 17th Regiment of Dragoons, Lefebvre was able to take the village again. By 0500&amp;nbsp;of 21&amp;nbsp;March, however, he sent word to Jourdan that he was being attacked on all posts by the Austrians, and they must soon expect a general engagement.&lt;ref&gt;Jourdan, pp. 144–145.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== General engagement ===
Charles had divided his force into columns, and at close to 1000, the Austrians attacked in force, with simultaneous assaults upon multiple positions. With Nauendorf's advance force moved with 11&amp;nbsp;battalions and 20&amp;nbsp;squadrons on Saint Cyr's position .&lt;ref&gt;Cust, p. 166.&lt;/ref&gt; Following behind with the main force of the right column, Fürstenberg had little difficulty pushing the French out of Davidsweiler and advanced on Ruppersweiler an Einhard&lt;!-- {{coord|47|59|N|9|21|E|display=inline}}  --&gt; {{convert|5|km|0|sp=us}} to the northwest. His force pressured elements of Saint Cyr's thinly manned line, and the entire line fell back slowly, to maintain contact with its flanks. [[Maximilian, Count of Merveldt]]'s force, attacking on Saint Cyr's far left flank, continued to pressure the line, which started to crumble.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cust166&quot;/&gt;  Further south, [[Olivier, Count of Wallis]] took a column of 18&amp;nbsp;battalions and 42&amp;nbsp;squadrons and attacked the Adjutant General [[François-Xavier Octavie Fontaine]]'s French line at [[Riedhausen]], between Ostrach and Ferino's column at [[Salem, Baden-Württemberg|Salem]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Cust166&quot;/&gt; In the maneuvering, the cross-fire trapped French forces; at Riedhausen, unable to take cover, they were cut down from both sides.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jourdan, p. 160&quot;&gt;Jourdan, p. 160.&lt;/ref&gt;

Charles himself took a main column along the high road, a causeway that passed by Saulgau,&lt;ref&gt;[[Thomas Graham, 1st Baron Lynedoch]]. ''The History of the campaign of 1796 in Germany and Italy.'' London, 1797. p. 70.&lt;/ref&gt; to attack Lefebvre on points between Hoßkirch and Ostrach.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cust166&quot;/&gt; In this deployment of his force, Charles sought to dislodge the center of the French line from its position in Ostrach, separating the wings from the main body of force and overcoming both separately.&lt;ref&gt;Graham, p. 69.&lt;/ref&gt;

The convergence of the two columns on the French at Ostrach demonstrated the advantage of the superiority of Austrian numbers. From every angle, the Austrians threatened to overwhelm the French. Jourdan wrote that his men disappeared under a cloud of red coats.&lt;ref&gt;Although the Habsburg Infantry wore white coats, some grenadier and hussar units wore red. Jourdan himself says that the coats were red, and an English source confirms this. Jourdan, p. 145. ''Times'', 5&amp;nbsp;April 1799.&lt;/ref&gt; Battalion after battalion of Austrians threw themselves against the French defenses.&lt;ref&gt;Jourdan, pp. 145–146.&lt;/ref&gt; By late morning, Charles' troops pushed the French out of Hoßkirch, and into Ostrach, which the French nearly lost until Jourdan sent reinforcements. The fighting remained fierce until about 1600, when the French pulled back toward Pfullendorf,&lt;ref name=&quot;Jourdan, p. 160&quot;/&gt; encouraged by Austrian cavalry. Once out of Ostrach, and established on the road at and around Pfullendorf, the French formed a new perimeter, reinforced by reserves of Soulham, and enjoyed the benefit of altitude from which they could fire down upon the attacking Austrians. Despite the punishing musket fire, Charles' strategy worked. The far right wing (Ferino's force), which had not been attacked yet, fell back to Salem Abbey, to maintain communication with the French center.&lt;ref&gt;Graham, pp. 67–68.&lt;/ref&gt;

At the Pfullendorf heights, the fight began anew. Charles sent two strong columns of eight battalions each across the Ostrach stream. The French poured fire on the Austrians, who took heavy losses, but did not give up the ground. In the night, Fürstenberg broke through the French line to Einhard, flanking Jourdan's main force and cutting off Saint Cyr. Further south, Wallis threatened to do the same to Fontaine and Ferino.&lt;ref&gt;Cust, p. 166; Sir Archibald Alison. ''A History of Europe from the Commencement of the French Revolution in 1789&amp;nbsp;to the Restoration of the Bourbons''. New York: A.S. Barnes, 1850, p. 115; Phipps, pp. 49–50.&lt;/ref&gt; As darkness fell, so ended the first day of fighting.&lt;ref name=&quot;Graham, p. 68&quot;&gt;Graham, p. 68.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Withdrawal ===
As Jourdan was deciding whether or not to attempt another foray, the fog lifted and revealed the scene below him. He wrote later, 
:&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;... [W]e discovered an immense line of cavalry and infantry. It may be said, without exaggeration, that the troops which engaged our advanced guard amounted to twenty-five thousand men. I now perceived the absolute impossibility of making any further resistance against such a superior force, as well as the danger that threatened the division, from the advantage which the enemy had gained on the left. I therefore ordered General Soult to fall back with the division to the post before Pfulendorf [sic].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Jourdan, p. 159.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
He was wrong; the Austrians engaged with the French advance guard numbered closer to 50,000, and constituted the main body of Charles' army, not its advance guard.&lt;ref&gt;Phipps, pp. 78–79; Young, pp. 229–231.&lt;/ref&gt; In the night, Charles also had moved additional troops to renew the attack on the Pfullendorf heights at daybreak.&lt;ref name=&quot;Graham, p. 68&quot;/&gt;

On 21&amp;nbsp;March, at 2200, Jourdan ordered the wounded to be transported to [[Schaffhausen]] in Switzerland, via Stockach. The main army then began its own retreat in the early morning of 22&amp;nbsp;March. The reserve division of d'Hautpoul left first, and pulled back via Stockach to [[Emmingen-Liptingen|Emmingen ob Egg]]. According to Jourdan, the retreat occurred in perfect order, and was supported in particular by a company of sappers, who blew up the bridges in the face of enemy fire, and then fought like grenadiers.&lt;ref&gt;Jourdan, pp. 159–60.&lt;/ref&gt; The Austrians outflanked Saint Cyr's forces on the right flank and General Ferino, at the southern-most point, retreated to Salem, to maintain the line with the remainder of the French force.&lt;ref&gt;Phipps, pp. 49–50; Jourdan, p. 178.&lt;/ref&gt;  When the first division pulled back to [[Bodman-Ludwigshafen|Bodman]], on the northern tip of the Überlingen-finger of Lake Constance, a portion of the force was encircled and cut off by the 2nd Lancers of [[Karl Philipp Fürst zu Schwarzenberg|Karl Philipp, Prince Schwarzenberg's]] brigade, and more than 500&amp;nbsp;were taken prisoner.&lt;ref&gt;{{de icon}} Roland Kessinger, '&quot;Die Schlacht von Stockach am 25. März 1799&quot;. ''Zeitschrift für Militärgeschichte.'' Salzburg: Öst. Milizverlag, 1997–. [2006], p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt;

Other sources are less sanguine in their assessment of Jourdan's retreat. Jourdan's forces, especially his left flank, were severely pressed; the French line collapsed upon itself at both ends as the soldiers fell back. A dispatch to Paris, later reported in the ''Times'', claimed that the French intent had been betrayed to the Austrians by a deserter,&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Engagements Between The Grand Armies Of The Archduke and General Jourdan.&quot; ''The Times'', Friday, 5&amp;nbsp;April 1799; pg. 2; col A.&lt;/ref&gt; but there is some evidence that this was Jourdan's mendacious attempt to explain the apparent surprise with which the Austrians attacked.&lt;ref&gt;Graham, p. 72.&lt;/ref&gt;  A British report claimed that the French commander had two horses shot from under him,&lt;ref&gt;''Times'', 5&amp;nbsp;April 1799.&lt;/ref&gt; but Jourdan himself reported that only one horse was shot, and he was thrown, stunned, to the ground.&lt;ref&gt;Jourdan, p. 161; Cust, p. 166.&lt;/ref&gt;  Lefebvre received a musket ball in the wrist&lt;ref&gt;''The Times'' 5&amp;nbsp;April 1799. Other sources report he lost his arm: See &quot;Private Correspondence&quot;, ''The Times'', 8&amp;nbsp;April 1799, pg. 3; col A.&lt;/ref&gt; and had to be carried from the field; command of his division was given to the rising star [[Jean-de-Dieu Soult]]. Furthermore, a sizable portion—sources are not clear on how many—of the French right wing (Ferino's force) had been cut off from its main force, and made prisoner. Finally, General [[Friedrich Freiherr von Hotze]] was quickly making his way north with 10,000&amp;nbsp;men from [[Feldkirch, Vorarlberg|Feldkirch]] and prepared to attack Jourdan's army from the south.&lt;ref&gt;Phipps, pp. 49–50; Young, pp. 229–231.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
Eventually, Jourdan withdrew first to [[Messkirch]] (sometimes spelled Mößkirch or Meßkirch), and when that city was no longer defensible, fell back to [[Stockach]], and then again [[Engen]], but he wrote that the armies had been well-matched; French valor, he wrote, overcame servitude.&lt;ref&gt;Phipps, pp. 49–50 Young, p. 228; Jourdan, p. 178.&lt;/ref&gt;  His men had taken many Austrian prisoners, and he knew also that many Austrians lay dead or wounded on the field of battle. His army itself had losses, but their valor in death matched the ambitious tyranny of the Austrians: Charles had driven his army hard, he wrote, and the Austrians would not pursue the gallant, liberty-loving French; Charles' failure to pursue the French affirmed Jourdan's perception that his had not been a defeat followed by retreat, but rather a strategic withdrawal.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jourdan, p. 178&quot;/&gt; Jourdan probably did not know that Charles had been ordered to maintain a continuous and orderly defensive line with troops to the south.&lt;ref name=&quot;Blanning, p. 232&quot;/&gt;

Jourdan's own assessment did not match that of his superiors in Paris, who recognized that the loss of twelve percent of the fighting force, versus less than four percent for the adversary, did not amount to a draw.&lt;ref&gt;Phipps, pp. 49–50 Young, p. 230.&lt;/ref&gt;  Furthermore, this first attempt to cut the Austrians off from access to the upper Rhine and Lake Constance had not succeeded.&lt;ref&gt;Phipps, pp. 49–50; Young, p. 231.&lt;/ref&gt;  There were other considerations, primarily that Jourdan simply did not have enough men to fight not only this battle but the subsequent ones as well.&lt;ref&gt;Adolphe Thiers. ''The history of the French revolution''. New York: Appleton, 1854, v. 4, p. 370.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Ostrachbattlemonument.jpg|thumb|alt=The Ostrach battle monument is a small, square building, raised from the ground about .5 meter, 8 meters high. A 3&amp;nbsp;meter dome, topped with a simple cross, caps the monument. It is of marble, with a simple double door.|Located at {{coord|47|57|19.9|N|9|23|18|E|display=inline}} The architect of the monument was the [[Hohenzollern]] state conservator, [[Wilhelm Friedrich Laur]].]]

For his own part, the Archduke did not push his troops to pursue and capture the enemy, or even harass their retreat. Charles' slow pursuit might have been due to his own disgruntlement with Vienna's overarching defensive strategy and the undoubted difficulty of the battle itself, conducted with troops wearied by a forced march of {{convert|30|mi|km|0|sp=us}}, fighting in rain, fog, and on normally boggy terrain made more soggy by the heavy spring rains and snow melt. Regardless, he more than made up for these shortcomings within the week.&lt;ref&gt;Blanning, pp. 232, 264; Phipps, pp. 49–50.&lt;/ref&gt;  Five days after Jourdan's departure from Ostrach and Pfullendorf, the French and Austrian armies continued the fight at [[Battle of Stockach (1799)|Stockach]]. This time, the decision could not be argued: The Army of the Danube could not hold the territory and withdrew into the Black Forest.&lt;ref&gt;Blanning, p. 264.&lt;/ref&gt;

The battle at Ostrach had been difficult, as Jourdan pointed out, due largely to the dense fog and terrible weather that hampered his observation of his enemy's movements, yet the same fog that blinded him to the Austrian movements did not seem to hamper Charles.&lt;ref&gt;Phipps, pp. 49–50; Young, pp. 228–230.&lt;/ref&gt;  The fog and rainy weather did play a role, however. On a local level, in the damp night of the 20th, which was ''Gründonnerstag,'' (German: Green Thursday, or [[Maundy Thursday]]), the Danube overflowed, backing up into the Ostrach, and causing it to burst its own banks. The flood trapped 300&amp;nbsp;civilians between the two armies intent on destruction; suspecting what was to come, Ostrachers huddled in their cellars, and hoped for the best and gasping for breath as the battle thundered overhead. Amazingly, none were killed, although they spent Easter Sunday caring for the wounded, and helping to bury the 4,000&amp;nbsp;or so soldiers who died in the battle.&lt;ref&gt;{{de icon}} Broda, ''Südkurier''.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battle monument==
Prior to 1903, a simple wooden cross commemorated the battle site, located on the so-called Buchbuhl, a hill overlooking the village, and the plains to the southeast, where much of the fighting occurred. In 1903, a monument was erected to honor the battle. In 1945, when French troops arrived in the region, they closed the monument; the local pastor encouraged them to reopen it, calling it a chapel.&lt;ref&gt;{{de icon}} Edwin Ernst Weber. [http://www.ostrach.de/geschichte/buchbuehldenkmal.htm  ''Ostrach 1799 – die Schlacht, der Ort, das Gedenken''] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070822224853/http://www.ostrach.de/geschichte/buchbuehldenkmal.htm |date=22 August 2007 }}, [http://www.ostrach.de/default.htm Gemeinde Ostrach, BW, DE website]. Accessed 24&amp;nbsp;October 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Sources==

===Notes and citations===
{{Reflist|2}}

===Books and journals===
* Alison, Sir Archibald. '' A History of Europe from the Commencement of the French Revolution in 1789 to the Restoration of the Bourbons''. New York: A.S. Barnes, 1850.
* Blanning, Timothy. ''The French Revolutionary Wars''. New York: Oxford University Press, 1996. ISBN 0-340-56911-5.
* Gallagher, John.  ''Napoleon's enfant terrible: General Dominique Vandamme''. Tulsa: University of Oklahoma Press, 2008, ISBN 978-0-8061-3875-6.
* Cust, Edward (Sir). ''Annals of the wars of the eighteenth century, compiled from the most authentic histories of the period''. London: Mitchell's military library, 1857–1860. 
* [[Thomas Graham, 1st Baron Lynedoch|Graham, Thomas, Baron Lynedoch]].(?) ''The History of the campaign of 1796 in Germany and Italy.'' London, 1797.
* Hollins, David. ''Austrian Commanders of the Napoleonic Wars, 1792–1815''. London: Osprey, 2004.
* Jourdan, Jean-Baptiste,  ''A Memoir of the operations of the army of the Danube under the command of General Jourdan, taken from the manuscripts of that officer,'' London: Debrett, 1799.
* {{de icon}} Kessinger, Roland.  '&quot;Die Schlacht von Stockach am 25. März 1799&quot;. ''Zeitschrift für Militärgeschichte.''  Salzburg: Öst. Milizverlag, 1997–. [2006].
* Phipps, Ramsey Weston.  ''The Armies of the First French Republic'', volume 5: The armies of the Rhine in Switzerland, Holland, Italy, Egypt and the coup d'etat of Brumaire, 1797–1799, Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1939.
*{{cite book |authorlink=Gunther E. Rothenberg |first=Gunther E. |last=Rothenberg |title=Napoleon’s great adversaries: Archduke Charles and the Austrian Army 1792–1914 |location=[[Stroud, Gloucestershire]] |publisher=[[Spellmount]] |year=2007 |isbn=978-1-86227-383-2}}
*{{cite book |authorlink=Digby Smith |last=Smith |first=Digby
 |title=The Greenhill Napoleonic Wars Data Book: Actions and Losses in Personnel, Colours, Standards and Artillery, 1792–1815 |location=Greenhill, Pennsylvania |publisher=[[Stackpole Books]] |year=1998 |isbn=1-85367-276-9}}* Thiers, Adolphe. '' The history of the French revolution,'' New York, Appleton, 1854, v. 4.
* {{de icon}} Weber, Edwin Ernst. [https://web.archive.org/web/20070822224853/http://www.ostrach.de:80/geschichte/buchbuehldenkmal.htm  ''Ostrach 1799 – die Schlacht, der Ort, das Gedenken''], [http://www.ostrach.de/default.htm Gemeinde Ostrach website]. Accessed 24 October 2009.
* Young, John, D.D., ''A History of the Commencement, Progress, and Termination of the Late War between Great Britain and France which continued from the first day of February 1793 to the first of October 1801''. Volume 2. Edinburg: Turnbull, 1802.

===Newspapers===
*&quot;Engagements Between The Grand Armies Of The Archduke and General Jourdan.&quot; ''The Times'', Friday, 5 April 1799; pg. 2; col A.
* Excerpted from the Hamburgh Mail. &quot;Private Correspondence&quot;, Hamburgh, 2 March 1799, reported in ''The Times'', 8 April 1799, pg. 3; col A.
* {{de icon}} Broda, Ruth. &quot;Schlacht von Ostrach:“ jährt sich zum 210. Mal – Feier am Wochenende. Wie ein Dorf zum Kriegsschauplatz wurde. In: ''Südkurier'' vom 13. Mai 2009.

{{commonscat|Battle of Ostrach}}

{{good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Ostrach}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1799]]
[[Category:1799 in Germany]]
[[Category:French Revolutionary Wars]]
[[Category:Campaigns of the French Revolutionary Wars by year]]
[[Category:Battles involving France]]
[[Category:Battles involving Austria]]
[[Category:Battles of the French Revolutionary Wars]]
[[Category:War of the Second Coalition]]
[[Category:Battles of the War of the Second Coalition]]</text>
      <sha1>m25mpax589fc5vyzn1zd724unilnnwl</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
