<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Bijeljina massacre</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>27459570</id>
    <revision>
      <id>741392961</id>
      <parentid>739758293</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-27T06:25:11Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* References */http&amp;rarr;https for [[Google Books]] and [[Google News]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="64179">{{good article}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2013}}
{{Infobox civilian attack
| title= Bijeljina massacre
| partof = the [[Bosnian War]]
| image_size = 300
| image = Ron Haviv - Massacre in Bijeljina.jpg
| alt = Dying woman kicked
| caption = [[Ron Haviv]]'s image showing a member of the [[Serb Volunteer Guard]] kicking a dying Bosniak woman
| location = [[Bijeljina]], [[Bosnia and Herzegovina]]
| coordinates = {{coord|44|45|N|19|13|E|display=inline,title}}
| target = [[Bosniaks]]
| date = 1–2 April 1992
| time =
| timezone = 
| type = Mass killings
| fatalities = 48–78
| injuries =
| perps = [[Serb Volunteer Guard]], Mirko's [[Chetniks]]
| motive = Establishment of homogenous Serb territory{{sfn|Human Rights Watch|May 2000|pp=2, 16, 33}}
}}

The '''Bijeljina massacre''' involved the killing of between 48 and 78 civilians by [[Serbs|Serb]] [[paramilitary]] groups in [[Bijeljina]] on 1–2 April 1992 during the [[Bosnian War]]. The majority of those killed were [[Bosniaks]] (or Bosnian Muslims). Members of other ethnicities were also killed, such as Serbs deemed disloyal by the local authorities. The killing was committed by a local paramilitary group known as Mirko's [[Chetniks]] and by the [[Serb Volunteer Guard]] (SDG, also known as Arkan's Tigers), a [[Republic of Serbia (1990-2006)|Serbia]]-based [[paramilitary]] group led by [[Željko Ražnatović]] (aka Arkan). The SDG were under the command of the [[Yugoslav People's Army]] (JNA), which was controlled by [[President of Serbia|Serbian President]] [[Slobodan Milošević]].

In September 1991, [[Bosnian Serbs]] proclaimed a [[Serbian Autonomous Oblast]] with Bijeljina as its capital. In March 1992, the [[Bosnia and Herzegovina independence referendum, 1992|Bosnian referendum on independence]] was passed with overwhelming support from Bosniaks and [[Bosnian Croats]], although Bosnian Serbs either boycotted it or were prevented from voting by Bosnian Serb authorities. A poorly organized, local Bosniak [[Patriotic League (Bosnia and Herzegovina)|Patriotic League]] paramilitary group had been established in response to the Bosnian Serb proclamation. On 31 March, the Patriotic League in Bijeljina was provoked into fighting by local Serbs and the SDG. On 1–2 April, the SDG and the JNA took over Bijeljina with little resistance; murders, rapes, house searches, and pillaging followed. These actions were described as [[genocide|genocidal]] by the historian Professor Eric D. Weitz of the [[City College of New York]]. Professor [[Michael Sells]] of the [[University of Chicago]] concluded that they were carried out to erase the cultural history of the Bosniak people of Bijeljina.

Around 3 April, Serb forces removed the bodies of those massacred in anticipation of the arrival of a Bosnian government delegation tasked with investigating what had transpired. A number of sources put the figure of civilians killed in the hundreds or possibly a thousand, but the [[International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia]] (ICTY) and the Serbian War Crimes Prosecutor's Office were only able to verify between 48 and 78 deaths. Post-war investigations have documented the deaths of a little over 250 civilian of all ethnicities in the Bijeljina municipality during the course of the war. After the massacre, a campaign of mass [[ethnic cleansing]] of non-Serbs was carried out, all mosques were demolished, and nine detention camps were established. Many deaths in Bijeljina were not officially listed as civilian war victims and their death certificates claim they &quot;died of natural causes.&quot;

{{As of|2014|December}}, local courts had not prosecuted anyone for the killings, and no members of the SDG had been prosecuted for any crimes the unit carried out in Bijeljina or elsewhere in [[Croatia]] or Bosnia and Herzegovina. Milošević was indicted by the ICTY and charged with carrying out a genocidal campaign that included Bijeljina and other locations, but died during the trial. [[Republika Srpska]] leaders [[Biljana Plavšić]] and [[Momčilo Krajišnik]] were convicted for the deportations and forcible transfers in the ethnic cleansing that followed the massacre. [[Radovan Karadžić]], the former [[President of Republika Srpska]], is currently on trial for the massacre and other crimes against humanity committed in Bijeljina. At the end of the war, fewer than 2,700 Bosniaks still lived in the municipality from a pre-war population of 30,000. The Serbs of Bijeljina celebrate 1 April as &quot;City Defense Day&quot;, and a street in the city has been named after the SDG.

==Background==
{{Location map | Bosnia and Herzegovina
| width      = 250
| float      = right
| caption    = Location of the town of Bijeljina in Bosnia and Herzegovina.
| alt        = Map locating the town of Bijeljina
| lat_deg = 44.75
| lon_deg = 19.216667
}}
According to the 1991 census, the municipality of [[Bijeljina]] had approximately 97,000 inhabitants. The demographic proportions were approximately 59% [[Bosnian Serbs]], 31% [[Bosniaks]] and 10% belonged to other ethnicities.{{sfn|Human Rights Watch|May 2000|p=11}} The town of Bijeljina itself had 36,414 inhabitants, 19,024 of whom were Bosniaks (or 52% of the town's population), while the [[Serbs]] were the second largest ethnic group in the town.&lt;ref name=census/&gt;

During 1990, a group of Serb [[Yugoslav People's Army]] (JNA) officers and experts from the JNA's Psychological Operations Department had developed the [[RAM Plan]]{{sfn|Allen|1996|p=56}} with the intent of organizing Serbs outside of [[Serbia]], consolidating control of the [[Serbian Democratic Party (Bosnia and Herzegovina)|Serbian Democratic Party]] (SDS), and preparing arms and ammunition.{{sfn|Judah|2000|p=170}} In 1990 and 1991, Serbs in [[Socialist Republic of Croatia|Croatia]] and [[Socialist Republic of Bosnia and Herzegovina|Bosnia and Herzegovina]] had proclaimed a number of [[Serbian Autonomous Oblasts]] with the intent of later unifying them into a homogeneous Serb territory.{{sfn|Lukic|Lynch|1996|p=203}}{{sfn|Bugajski|1995|p=15}} As early as September or October 1990, the JNA began arming Bosnian Serbs and organizing them into militias.{{sfn|Ramet|2006|p=414}} That same year, the JNA disarmed the [[Territorial Defense Force of the Republic of Bosnia and Herzegovina]] (TORBiH).{{sfn|Central Intelligence Agency|2002|p=135}} By March 1991, the JNA had distributed an estimated 51,900 firearms to Serb [[paramilitary|paramilitaries]] and 23,298 firearms to the SDS.{{sfn|Ramet|2006|p=414}} Throughout 1991 and early 1992, the SDS heavily [[Serbianisation|Serbianized]] the police force in order to increase Serb political control.{{sfn|Central Intelligence Agency|2002|p=135}} In September 1991, Bijeljina was established by the Bosnian Serbs as the capital of the [[SAO North-Eastern Bosnia|Serbian Autonomous Oblast of Northern Bosnia]], later renamed in November as the Serbian Autonomous Oblast of [[Semberija]], renamed again in December as the &quot;Serbian Autonomous Oblast of Semberija and [[Majevica]]&quot;.{{sfn|Thomas|2006|p=9}} In response, local Bosniaks established the paramilitary [[Patriotic League (Bosnia and Herzegovina)|Patriotic League of Bosnia and Herzegovina]], shortened to the Patriotic League.{{sfn|Human Rights Watch|May 2000|p=12}}

In January 1992, the SDS assembly proclaimed the &quot;Republic of the Serbian People of Bosnia and Herzegovina&quot; and [[Radovan Karadžić]], its soon-to-be president, announced that a &quot;unified Bosnia and Herzegovina no longer exists&quot;.{{sfn|Toal|Dahlman|2011|p=110}} In March, the [[Bosnia and Herzegovina independence referendum, 1992|Bosnian referendum on independence]] passed with overwhelming support from Bosniaks and [[Bosnian Croats]], having been boycotted by most Bosnian Serbs.{{sfn|Human Rights Watch|May 2000|p=12}} The SDS, claiming that independence would result in the Serbs becoming &quot;a national minority in an Islamic state&quot;,{{sfn|Toal|Dahlman|2011|p=110}} had used armed irregular units to block the delivery of ballot boxes, and dropped leaflets encouraging the boycott.{{sfn|Gow|2003|p=173}} Despite this, thousands of Serbs in larger cities did participate in the referendum and voted for independence,{{sfn|Velikonja|2003|p=238}} and several violent incidents were triggered across Bosnia and Herzegovina.{{sfn|Human Rights Watch|May 2000|p=12}} According to historian [[Noel Malcolm]] the &quot;steps taken by Karadžić and his party – [declaring Serb] &quot;Autonomous Regions&quot;, the arming of the Serb population, minor local incidents, non-stop propaganda, the request for federal army &quot;protection&quot; – matched exactly what had been done in Croatia. Few observers could doubt that a single plan was in operation.&quot;{{sfn|Lukic|Lynch|1996|p=204}} Bijeljina was strategically significant because of its location, which enabled the easy movement of military personnel, weaponry, and goods into [[Posavina]] and the [[Bosnian Krajina]] where Serb forces were gathered.{{sfn|Human Rights Watch|May 2000|p=15}}

==Provocation, takeover, and massacre==
[[Željko Ražnatović]] (&quot;Arkan&quot;), leader of the [[Serb Volunteer Guard]] (SDG), spent a month in Bijeljina devising battle plans prior to the attack.{{sfn|United Nations Security Council|28 December 1994}} On 30 March 1992, [[Blagoje Adžić]], Bosnian Serb chief-of-staff of the JNA, announced that the army was &quot;ready to protect Serbs from open aggression&quot;.{{sfn|Goldstein|1999|p=242}} Fighting broke out in Bijeljina on 1 April, after local Serbs and SDG personnel threw grenades into shops,{{sfn|Gow|2003|p=128}} including a Bosniak-owned cafe,{{sfn|United Nations Security Council|28 December 1994}} provoking the poorly organized Patriotic League into an armed conflict.{{sfn|Central Intelligence Agency|2002|p=135}}{{sfn|Toal|Dahlman|2011|p=113}}{{sfn|Calic|2012|p=125}} About a thousand{{sfn|United Nations Security Council|28 December 1994}}{{sfn|Toal|Dahlman|2011|p=113}} SDG members and Mirko's [[Chetniks]],{{sfn|International Crisis Group|2 November 2000|pp=10–13}} a paramilitary formation commanded by [[Mirko Blagojević]], were involved and captured important structures in the town.{{sfn|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|27 September 2006|p=113}} According to journalist and political analyst Miloš Vasić, Bijeljina was defended by 35 or 38 Bosnian policemen.{{sfn|Amanpour|1 June 1997}} According to the [[International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia]] (ICTY), Bijeljina was the &quot;first municipality of Bosnia and Herzegovina to be taken over by the Bosnian Serbs in 1992&quot;.{{sfn|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|27 September 2006|p=113}} Despite the pro-Serb activities of the JNA during the [[Croatian War of Independence]], the Chairman of the [[Presidency of Bosnia and Herzegovina]], [[Alija Izetbegović]] apparently believed that the JNA would act differently in Bosnia and Herzegovina, and asked the JNA to defend Bijeljina against the SDG.{{sfn|Kumar|1999|p=40}}

On 1–2 April 1992, the town was surrounded by JNA forces,{{sfn|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|27 September 2006|p=113}} ostensibly to keep the peace.{{sfn|Central Intelligence Agency|2002|p=135}} According to [[Human Rights Watch]] (HRW), Serb paramilitaries wearing balaclavas took up positions around the city, including sniper positions in windows on the top floor of buildings.{{sfn|Human Rights Watch|August 1992}} Meeting little resistance,{{sfn|Amnesty International|21 December 1994|p=5}} the SDG, under JNA command{{sfn|Magaš|Žanić|2001|p=182}} and reporting directly to Serbian President [[Slobodan Milošević]],{{sfn|Ramet|2006|p=427}} swiftly captured Bijeljina.{{sfn|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|27 September 2006|p=113}} Artillery units shelled the town in coordination with the street fighting.{{sfn|Gow|2003|p=129}} According to photojournalist [[Ron Haviv]], Serb forces struck first, with several busloads of soldiers arriving in the city, seizing the radio station, and forcing local Serbs to reveal the identities of the city's non-Serb residents.{{sfn|Keane|2003}} The [[Panthers (paramilitary)|Panthers]], a paramilitary group led by [[Ljubiša Savić]] (&quot;Mauzer&quot;), who was a founder of the SDS,{{sfn|BBC|8 June 2000}} also participated in the assault or arrived shortly after.{{sfn|Human Rights Watch|May 2000|pp=11–12}} Together with the SDG, they began a campaign of violence against local Bosniaks and some of the Serb population, committing several rapes and murders, and searching residents' houses and pillaging their property.{{sfn|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|27 September 2006|p=117}} Subsequently, Bosnian President Izetbegović tasked the JNA with occupying Bijeljina and stopping the violence.{{sfn|Magaš|Žanić|2001|p=182}} At Karadžić's trial, the former Mayor of Bijeljina Cvijetin Simić, testified that the only real fighting that took place in the town on 1–2 April happened around the city hospital, where the most fatalities occurred.{{sfn|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|Radovan Karadžić transcript|p=35702}}

As the fighting progressed, the SDS and the Bosnian Serbs created the [[Ministry of Interior of Republika Srpska]] (MUP RS), an independent Serb police force.{{sfn|Central Intelligence Agency|2002|p=135}} According to HRW, a pattern of violence, fueled by &quot;the strive to create a [[Greater Serbia]]&quot;,{{sfn|Human Rights Watch|May 2000|pp=2, 16, 33}} developed in Bijeljina that was later repeated in other municipalities in north-eastern Bosnia and Herzegovina by similar paramilitary groups from [[Republic of Serbia (1990-2006)|Serbia]].{{sfn|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|27 September 2006|p=113}} This pattern was described by the [[United Nations]] Commission of Experts in the following terms:{{sfn|Human Rights Watch|May 2000|p=16}}

{{quote|First, Bosnian Serb paramilitary forces, often with the assistance of the JNA, seize control of the area. In many cases, Serbian residents are told to leave the area before the violence begins. The homes of non-Serb residents are targeted for destruction and cultural and religious monuments, especially churches and mosques, are destroyed. Second, the area falls under the control of paramilitary forces who terrorize the non-Serb residents with random killings, rapes, and looting. Third, the seized area is administered by local Serb authorities, often in conjunction with paramilitary groups. During this phase, non-Serb residents are detained, beaten, and sometimes transferred to prison camps where further abuse, including mass killings, have occurred. Non-Serb residents are often fired from their jobs and their property is confiscated. Many have been forced to sign documents relinquishing their rights to their homes before being deported to other areas of the country.}}

The exact number killed in the takeover is unknown.{{sfn|Human Rights Watch|May 2000|p=14}} Several sources put the figure anywhere between several dozen and a thousand.{{sfn|Goldstein|1999|p=242}}{{sfn|Magaš|Žanić|2001|p=182}}{{sfn|Human Rights Watch|May 2000|p=14}}{{sfn|Malcolm|1994|p=236}}{{sfn|Off|2010|p=69}}{{sfn|Karabegović|4 April 2012}} According to the ICTY, at least 48 civilians were killed of which 45 were non-Serbs. Around 3 April, a local policeman was ordered to guard a hearse which was picking up bodies from the streets and houses of the town.{{sfn|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|27 September 2006|p=114}} The killings were [[eliticidal]] with the aim of erasing cultural history{{sfn|Sells|1996|p=26}} and included &quot;political leaders, businessmen, and other prominent Bosniaks&quot;,{{sfn|Human Rights Watch|May 2000|p=14}} but also included women and children.{{sfn|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|27 September 2006|p=114}} A number of Serbs who had attempted to stop the massacre were also killed.{{sfn|Weitz|2003|p=215}} An investigation by the ICTY later stated that the victims had been shot &quot;in the chest, mouth, temple, or back of the head, some at close range&quot; and that none had been wearing military uniforms.{{sfn|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|27 September 2006|p=114}} According to the historian Professor Eric D. Weitz of the [[City College of New York]], the killing of Bosniaks in Bijeljina was a genocidal act.{{sfn|Weitz|2003|p=215}} The acts against civilians in Bijeljina and those carried out by the JNA and special forces that followed were an attempt to intimidate and sidetrack the Bosnian government and general public from pursuing independence.{{sfn|Bećirević|2014|pp=88–89}}

Haviv, who had been invited by Arkan to take photographs, witnessed the killings and one of his pictures, which depicted an SDG member kicking a dying Bosniak woman, was later published in the international media prompting Arkan to put out a death warrant for Haviv.{{sfn|BBC|24 May 2001}}{{sfn|Kifner|24 January 2001}} Meanwhile, the Serbian state-owned [[Radio Belgrade]] network reported that Bijeljina had been &quot;liberated&quot; with the help of &quot;members of the Serbian National Guard of Semberija and Majevica, in cooperation with Serbian volunteers, Arkan's men, and the Serbian 'radicals'&quot;.{{sfn|United Nations Security Council|28 December 1994}}

==Bosnian delegation investigation and response==
Serb forces ordered the removal of the bodies of those killed, in anticipation of a delegation of high-ranking Bosnian officials due to arrive on 4 April. The delegation included [[Biljana Plavšić]], a Serb representative of the [[Presidency of Bosnia and Herzegovina|Presidency]]; [[Fikret Abdić]], a Bosniak representative; the Croat Minister of Defense, [[Jerko Doko]]; and the chief-of-staff of the JNA 2nd Military District, General [[Dobrašin Praščević]].{{sfn|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|27 September 2006|p=115}} They were sent by Izetbegović for the purpose of investigating the alleged atrocities.{{sfn|Silber|Little|1997|p=225}} On the same day, the JNA moved into Bijeljina, but the violence continued.{{sfn|Kumar|1999|p=40}} On 4 April, the SDG established themselves in the local headquarters of the SDS. Local police, who were engaged in arresting the town's [[Party of Democratic Action]] (SDA) presidency, joined them for several days, as did members of the [[White Eagles (paramilitary)|White Eagles]] paramilitary group and local [[Territorial Defense Forces (Yugoslavia)|Territorial Defense]] (TO) members.{{sfn|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|27 September 2006|p=114}} Serb flags were mounted on two mosques in Bijeljina,{{sfn|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|27 September 2006|pp=113–114}} and checkpoints and roadblocks were established, preventing journalists and European monitors from entering. The delegation visited the crisis staff and a military barracks where they were made aware of the situation.{{sfn|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|27 September 2006|p=114}}

During the visit, Plavšić requested that Arkan transfer control of Bijeljina to the JNA. Arkan refused, citing unfinished business, and said he would target [[Bosanski Brod]] next. Plavšić consequently withdrew her request and commended Arkan for &quot;protecting&quot; Bijeljina's Serbs from the Bosniaks.{{sfn|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|27 September 2006|p=115}} She called him a &quot;Serb hero&amp;nbsp;... who was prepared to give his life for his people&quot;, adding that &quot;we need such people&quot;.{{sfn|Velikonja|2003|p=247}} She then thanked and kissed Arkan in public to which the local members of the SDS responded with &quot;shouts of approval&quot;.{{sfn|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|27 September 2006|p=115}} In a conversation with [[Cedric Thornberry]], a [[United Nations Protection Force]] (UNPROFOR) representative, she described Bijeljina as a &quot;liberated&quot; town.{{sfn|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|27 September 2006|p=115}} Abdić was initially turned back at gunpoint,{{sfn|Malcolm|1994|p=236}} but was later able to enter.{{sfn|Silber|Little|1997|p=225}} He was then kept in custody by Arkan until Plavšić arrived to release him.{{sfn|Ramet|2006|pp=427–428}} &quot;Bijeljina was practically empty,&quot; he recalled. &quot;I met with the local authorities, they told me what had happened, but there wasn't a single Muslim there, so we couldn't discuss the problem as a whole. Muslims didn't answer our appeal. They were too scared to come out, and specially scared to talk about it at all.&quot;{{sfn|Silber|Little|1997|p=225}} General [[Sava Janković]], commander of the JNA's 17th Corps, reported that:{{sfn|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|27 September 2006|pp=329–330}}

{{quote|A big influence of the SDS and Arkan's propaganda is felt in the 38th [Partisan Division] and the 17th [Mixed Artillery Regiment], because of which some [conscripts] have left their units with arms.&amp;nbsp;... The situation in the territory is extremely complex. The town of Bijeljina is controlled by the SDS and Arkan's men, who do not even allow our anti-tank unit to reach certain positions in the town. There are about 3,000 refugees in the barracks and the Cooperative Hall area in [[Patkovača]]. A team from the BH Presidency led by Fikret Abdić, Biljana Plavšić, the chief-of-staff of the 2nd Military District and the commander of the 17th Corps, has been in Bijeljina barracks since 1200 hours.}}

&quot;In the following days,&quot; he predicted, &quot;further deterioration of the entire security and political situation is expected. There is a threat that interethnic conflicts in Posavina and Semberija might spread to other parts of the zone of responsibility&amp;nbsp;... Direct armed provocations by SDA, HDZ &lt;nowiki&gt;[&lt;/nowiki&gt;[[Croatian Democratic Union of Bosnia and Herzegovina|Croatian Democratic Union]]&lt;nowiki&gt;]&lt;/nowiki&gt;, and SDS paramilitary units against commands and units are also possible, as well as attacks by them on military warehouses and isolated facilities.&quot;{{sfn|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|27 September 2006|pp=329–330}} On the same day, Bosnian Defense Minister [[Ejup Ganić]] and Croat members of the coalition government urged Izetbegović to mobilize the TORBiH{{sfn|Kumar|1999|p=40}} due to the inability of the JNA to stop the violence.{{sfn|Central Intelligence Agency|2002|p=135}} Izetbegović described the images coming out of Bijeljina as &quot;unbelievable&quot;. &quot;I thought it was a photomontage,&quot; he explained. &quot;I couldn't believe my eyes. I couldn't believe it was possible.&quot;{{sfn|Silber|Little|1997|p=224}} He described the takeover as &quot;criminal&quot;, and said he considered the JNA responsible for Bijeljina's fall because it &quot;passively stood by and watched what was happening&quot;.{{sfn|Sudetic|5 April 1992}} Izetbegović mobilized the Territorial Defense later that day so as to &quot;enable people to defend themselves&amp;nbsp;... from future Bijeljinas&quot;. The Serb members of the Bosnian Presidency, Plavšić and [[Nikola Koljević]], denounced the mobilization as illegal and resigned.{{sfn|Central Intelligence Agency|2002|p=135}} On 8 April, Izetbegović announced a &quot;state of imminent war danger&quot;.{{sfn|Calic|2012|p=125}} The JNA rejected requests from the Bosnian Presidency to return the TORBiH's weapons that they had confiscated in 1990.{{sfn|Central Intelligence Agency|2002|p=135}} Karadžić and the Bosnian Serb leadership used Izetbegović's mobilization order as a pretext to independence and mobilized their Municipal Crisis Headquarters, reserve police units, and TO forces.{{sfn|Central Intelligence Agency|2002|p=136}}

==Ethnic cleansing, mosque destruction, and detainment==
The SDG stayed in Bijeljina until at least May 1992.{{sfn|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|27 September 2006|p=115}} General [[Manojlo Milovanović]], chief-of-staff of the [[Army of Republika Srpska]] (VRS), commented on Arkan's activities in Bijeljina and [[Zvornik]] in April and May 1992: &quot;The return of Serb voluntary units from the Republika Srpska and [[Republika Srpska Krajina]] was characterized by long formations consisting of both personnel carriers and tanks and a great number of trucks. This was a clear sign of looting.&quot;{{sfn|Bećirević|2014|p=90}} The ICTY concluded that Serb forces killed a minimum of 52 people, mostly Bosniaks, between April and September 1992 in the Bijeljina municipality.{{sfn|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|27 September 2006|pp=117–118}} In April, an &quot;organized campaign&quot; had begun to remove the Bosniak population of Bijeljina.{{sfn|Sudetic|18 July 1994}} The SDS in Bijeljina put forth a plan and proposed that a Bosniak family be killed &quot;on each side of town to create an atmosphere of fear&quot;.{{sfn|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|27 September 2006|pp=117–118}} On 23 September 1992, the SDG and Mirko's Chetniks handed over control of Bijeljina to the SDS{{sfn|United Nations Security Council|28 December 1994}} and the plan was carried out by Duško Malović's special police unit.{{sfn|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|27 September 2006|pp=117–118}} On 24 and 25 September, in the village of [[Bukreš]], 22 people including seven children were removed from their homes and taken to the village of [[Balatun]] where they were killed and thrown into the [[Drina]] river.{{sfn|Musli|24 September 2011}} It is suspected that they were killed by members of the Special Unit of the MUP RS under the supervision of local police and the [[State Security Administration|former State Security]].{{sfn|Musli|26 September 2012}}{{sfn|Karabegović|4 April 2012}} All were under the direct command of [[Mićo Stanišić]] the then Minister of MUP RS.{{sfn|Musli|26 September 2012}} Mass [[ethnic cleansing]] was committed and nine detention camps were established following the massacre.{{sfn|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|27 September 2006|pp=117–118}} All seven mosques in Bijeljina were destroyed.{{sfn|Human Rights Watch|May 2000|p=4}} They were systematically destroyed using explosives under the supervision of police and experts, and after their collapse the remains were removed with military construction equipment.{{sfn|Musli|13 March 2013}} Trees were planted where they once stood.{{sfn|United Nations Security Council|28 December 1994}}

A &quot;State Commission for the Free transfer of the Civilian Population&quot;{{sfn|Totten|Bartrop|2008|p=410}} or &quot;Commission for the Exchange of Population&quot; was created and headed by Vojkan Đurković, a [[Major (military)|Major]] in the SDG,{{sfn|Human Rights Watch|May 2000|p=28}} and included Mauzer's Panthers.{{sfn|Amnesty International|21 December 1994|pp=6–7}} Its purpose was to completely expel all non-Serbs from Bijeljina.{{sfn|Totten|Bartrop|2008|p=410}} Đurković claimed that the Bosniaks had left voluntarily and said Bijeljina was &quot;sacred Serbian land&quot;.{{sfn|United Nations Security Council|28 December 1994}} According to him &quot;after a time, the [Bosnian Serb] People's Deputies, Milan Teslić and Vojo Kuprešanin, expanded the Commission in the name of the [Serb Democratic Party] Deputies Club, and later the Commission was approved by the Parliament of the Serbian Republic [of Bosnia and Herzegovina].&quot;{{sfn|Cigar|Williams|2002|p=53}} He explained that &quot;travel [expulsion] was undertaken in the following manner: the State Commission for the Free Transfer of the Civilian Population had as its duty to inform the State Security Service of the Serbian Republic [of Bosnia and Herzegovina] (Republika Srpska) of that travel. The latter, by fax, would then pass that on to that ministry in the Republic of Serbia which has jurisdiction. The transit [on to [[Hungary]]] would occur in broad daylight, at noon.&quot;{{sfn|Cigar|Williams|2002|p=133}} Expulsions continued into 1994,&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Sudetic|18 July 1994}}; {{Harvnb|Sudetic|30 August 1994}}; {{Harvnb|Sudetic|3 September 1994}}; {{Harvnb|Sudetic|5 September 1994}}; {{Harvnb|Sudetic|20 September 1994}}&lt;/ref&gt; and in July a &quot;systematic program&quot; was implemented with the goal of &quot;expelling the remaining Bosniaks and extorting property and money from them&quot;.{{sfn|Amnesty International|21 December 1994|p=3}} Đurković was promoted by Arkan to [[Lieutenant Colonel]] in 1995.{{sfn|Cigar|Williams|2002|p=53}} Mauzer's Panthers later became a special unit of the VRS.{{sfn|Human Rights Watch|May 2000|p=34}} Mauzer was killed in 2000.{{sfn|BBC|8 June 2000}}

==War crimes prosecution==
{{Quote box|width=246px|align=right|quote=&quot;We live with the former war criminals, we see them every day in the streets.&quot;|source=Branko Todorović, President of the [[Helsinki Committee for Human Rights]] in Bijeljina{{sfn|Little|17 September 2008}}}}

Bosnian courts have not filed any war crimes indictments for the massacre. In 2008, [[Branko Todorović]], the President of the [[Helsinki Committee for Human Rights]] in Bijeljina, criticized the &quot;lethargic&quot; and &quot;unacceptable behavior&quot; of the Republika Srpska judiciary.{{sfn|Husejnovic|8 November 2008}} However, since 2003, the prosecution of war crimes has mostly been under the jurisdiction of the Court of Bosnia and Herzegovina.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.oscebih.org/Default.aspx?id=70&amp;lang=EN |title=Accountability for War Crimes |author=&lt;!--Staff writer--&gt; |date= |website=oscebih.org |publisher=OSCE Mission to Bosnia and Herzegovina |access-date=12 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2000, the [[International Crisis Group]] named three individuals from Bijeljina as &quot;potentially indictable for war crimes&quot;:
* Mirko Blagojević: who is alleged to have led Mirko's Chetniks, which took part in the attack and in the ethnic cleansing of Bijeljina.{{sfn|International Crisis Group|2 November 2000|pp=10–13}} He served as the head of the [[Serbian Radical Party]] (SRS) in Bijeljina{{sfn|Little|17 September 2008}} and is now a lawyer.{{sfn|Musli|2 April 2012}}
* Vojkan Đurković: who is suspected of forcing Bosniak civilians &quot;to hand over all their money, valuables and documents, and to sign away their property&quot;. He is also reported to have worked with the Panthers and other groups in the &quot;forcible expulsion of the civilian population&quot;.{{sfn|International Crisis Group|2 November 2000|pp=10–13}} He was arrested in November 2005, but released from police custody less than a month later.{{sfn|B92|27 October 2011}}
* Jovan Aćimović: who is alleged to have played a major role in the last initiative to remove Bosniaks from Bijeljina shortly prior to the signing of the [[Dayton Agreement]] in November 1995.{{sfn|International Crisis Group|2 November 2000|pp=10–13}} He reportedly continued to evict Bosniaks from their houses during peace time. He later became a member of the police in [[Ugljevik]].{{sfn|Human Rights Watch|May 2000|p=36}}

In 1997, the ICTY secretly indicted Arkan for war crimes carried out in [[Sanski Most]] in 1995, but not for those in Bijeljina.{{sfn|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|23 September 1997}} In January 2000, he was killed in a Belgrade hotel lobby by masked gunmen, and did not face trial.{{sfn|Erlanger|16 January 2000}} In 1999, Milošević was indicted for carrying out a [[Genocide|genocidal]] campaign that included Bijeljina and other locations in Bosnia and Herzegovina, among other charges, but he died mid-trial in March 2006.{{sfn|Armatta|2010|pp=285, 470}} In February 2000, Plavšić and [[Momčilo Krajišnik]], the speaker of the [[National Assembly of Republika Srpska]], were indicted for the same genocidal campaign in Bosnia and Herzegovina, among other charges.{{sfn|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|Momčilo Krajišnik CIS|p=1}}{{sfn|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|Biljana Plavšić CIS|p=1}} On 2 October 2002, Plavšić pleaded guilty to persecuting the non-Serb populations in 37 municipalities in Bosnia and Herzegovina, including Bijeljina. This plea was entered under an agreement that involved the prosecution moving to dismiss the remaining charges. She was subsequently sentenced to 11 years imprisonment.{{sfn|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|Biljana Plavšić CIS|p=1}} On 27 September 2006, Krajišnik was found guilty on a five counts of [[crimes against humanity]], including the same count as Plavšić regarding the persecution of non-Serb populations in municipalities including Bijeljina, but he was found not guilty of genocide. In 2009, he was handed a twenty-year prison sentence.{{sfn|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|Momčilo Krajišnik CIS|p=1}} After serving two-thirds of her sentence, Plavšić was released in October 2009.{{sfn|Traynor|27 October 2009}} Krajišnik was released in August 2013, having served two-thirds of his sentence (including time spent in custody).{{sfn|Fox News|30 August 2013}}

In 2010, the Serbian War Crimes Prosecutor's Office investigated [[Borislav Pelević]], a former SDG member and a member of the [[National Assembly (Serbia)|Serbian National Assembly]]. The investigation was ultimately dropped due to lack of evidence.{{sfn|Ristic|2 October 2012}} In 2012, former SDG member Srđan Golubović was arrested in [[Belgrade]] at the request of the Prosecutor's Office. Golubović was charged with an indictment listing the names of 78 victims. [[Clint Williamson]], the lead prosecutor, said that other members of the SDG could not be identified because their faces had been covered with masks.{{sfn|Ristic|2 October 2012}} As of October 2014,{{sfn|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|Radovan Karadžić CIS|p=5}} [[closing argument]]s had been concluded in the trial of Karadžić, the former [[President of Republika Srpska]], for the massacre,{{sfn|Irwin|22 March 2013}} and other crimes against humanity committed in Bijeljina, among other areas, as well as for the [[Srebrenica massacre|genocide at Srebrenica]].{{sfn|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|Radovan Karadžić CIS|p=1}} The ICTY is expected to deliver judgment in Karadžić's case in the first quarter of 2016.{{sfn|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|Cases summary}}

{{As of|2014|December}} no member of the SDG has been prosecuted for the murders, rapes, or looting committed in Bijeljina,{{sfn|Al Jazeera|9 December 2014}} or any of the crimes allegedly committed by the unit elsewhere in Croatia or Bosnia and Herzegovina.{{sfn|Dzidic||Ristic|Domanovic|Collaku|Milekic|8 December 2014}}

==Aftermath==
The [[Research and Documentation Center in Sarajevo]] has recorded a total of 1,078 fatalities in the Bijeljina municipality during the war, including approximately 250 civilians of all ethnicities.{{sfn|Prometej|27 February 2013}} Many deaths in Bijeljina were not officially listed as civilian war victims and their death certificates claim they &quot;died of natural causes.&quot;{{sfn|Musli|16 September 2013}} After the war ended, less than 2,700 people of the pre-war Bosniak population of over 30,000 still lived in the municipality of Bijeljina (the town itself had 19,000 Bosniak inhabitants&lt;ref name=census&gt;{{citation| title=1991 Population Census in Bosnia and Herzegovina: Ethnic Composition of the Population| publisher=Institute for Statistics of Bosnia and Herzegovina| url=http://www.fzs.ba/Dem/Popis/nacionalni%20sastav%20stanovnistva%20po%20naseljenim%20mjestima%20bilten%20234.pdf#page=17| page=17}}&lt;/ref&gt;). Many faced difficulties in returning to their homes including discrimination from the police, being unable to receive an identification card, or reconnect their phone lines. Local authorities prevented the Islamic community from reconstructing a mosque and, for a while, did not allow them to have their own local meeting place. Meaningful Bosniak participation in the politics and administration of the municipality was also blocked.{{sfn|Human Rights Watch|May 2000|pp=3, 37}} As of 2012, 5,000 Bosniaks have returned to Bijeljina.{{sfn|Karabegović|4 April 2012}}

In 2007, the Bijeljina [[truth commission]] was created with a four-year mandate. It held two public hearings in 2008, but by March 2009, although it was not formally disbanded, the commission was effectively dissolved when the majority of its members resigned. A number of factors have been cited as contributing to its failure, such as the inclusion of the commander of the [[Batković concentration camp]] in its delegation, its limited legal standing, disputes over the commission's scope, and poor funding.{{sfn|International Center for Transitional Justice|8 September 2009|p=3}}

Local Serbs celebrate 1 April as &quot;City Defense Day&quot;,{{sfn|Dnevni Avaz|2 April 2012}}{{dead link|date=January 2016}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.infobijeljina.com/2980_Proslava-dana-odbrane-grada.html |title=Proslava dana odbrane grada|trans-title=Celebration of the City Defense Day |author=&lt;!--Staff writer--&gt; |date=31 March 2015 |website=InfoBijeljina.com |access-date=6 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a street in the town is presently named after the Serbian Volunteer Guard.{{sfn|Pazarac|8 August 2010}}{{sfn|Karabegović|4 April 2012}} In 2012, the Bijeljina municipal veterans organization, municipal officials, and city leaders marked the occasion stating that &quot;on this day the Serbian people of Semberija were organized to defend against and prevent a new [[Jasenovac concentration camp|Jasenovac]] and notorious [[13th Waffen Mountain Division of the SS Handschar (1st Croatian)|13th Handschar division]].&quot;{{sfn|Musli|2 April 2012}}

== See also ==
* [[List of massacres in Bosnia and Herzegovina]]
* [[Serbian war crimes in the Yugoslav Wars]]

==Footnotes==
{{Research help|Gen}}
{{reflist|4}}

==References==

;Books and journals
{{Refbegin|2}}
* {{cite book
  | last = Allen
  | first = Beverly
  | title = Rape Warfare: The Hidden Genocide in Bosnia-Herzegovina and Croatia
  | publisher = University of Minnesota Press
  | location = Ithaca
  | year = 1996
  | isbn = 978-0-8014-4158-5
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=0GS9e-iq73kC
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Armatta
  | first = Judith
  | title = Twilight of Impunity: The War Crimes Trial of Slobodan Milosevic
  | publisher = Duke University Press
  | location = Durham
  | year = 2010
  | isbn = 978-0-8223-9179-1
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=pXygFoqg-G0C
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | author = [[Central Intelligence Agency]]
  | title = Balkan Battlegrounds: A Military History of the Yugoslav Conflict, 1990–1995
  | publisher = Office of Russian and European Analysis, Central Intelligence Agency
  | volume = 1
  | location = Washington, D.C.
  | year = 2002
  | ref = {{harvid|Central Intelligence Agency|2002}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Bećirević
  | first = Edina
  | year = 2014
  | title = Genocide on the Drina River
  | publisher = Yale University Press
  | location = New Haven and London
  | isbn = 978-0-300-19258-2
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=N0X4AwAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Bugajski
  | first = Janusz
  | author-link = Janusz Bugajski
  | title = Ethnic Politics in Eastern Europe: A Guide to Nationality Policies, Organizations and Parties
  | publisher = M. E. Sharpe
  | location = Armonk
  | year = 1995
  | isbn = 978-1-56324-283-0
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=m_AcqFSfvzAC&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Calic
  | first = Marie–Janine
  | chapter = Ethnic Cleansing and War Crimes, 1991–1995
  | year = 2012
  | title = Confronting the Yugoslav Controversies: A Scholars' Initiative
  | edition = 2nd
  | editor1-last = Ingrao
  | editor1-first = Charles
  | editor2-last = Emmert
  | editor2-first = Thomas A.
  | pages = 109–127
  | publisher = Purdue University Press
  | location = West Lafayette
  | isbn = 978-1-55753-617-4
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=IDMhDgCJCe0C&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Cigar
  | first1 = Norman L.
  | last2 = Williams
  | first2 = Paul
  | title = Indictment at the Hague: The Milosevic Regime and Crimes of the Balkan Wars
  | year = 2002
  | publisher = New York University Press
  | isbn = 978-0-8147-1626-7
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=vIMUCgAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Goldstein
  | first = Ivo
  | author-link = Ivo Goldstein
  | title = Croatia: A History
  | publisher = C. Hurst &amp; Co.
  | location = London
  | year = 1999
  | isbn = 978-1-85065-525-1
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=pSxJdE4MYo4C&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Gow
  | first = James
  | year = 2003
  | title = The Serbian Project and its Adversaries: A Strategy of War Crimes
  | publisher = C. Hurst &amp; Co.
  | location = London
  | isbn = 978-1-85065-646-3
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=FTw3lEqi2-oC&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Judah
  | first = Tim
  | authorlink = Tim Judah
  | year = 2000
  | title = The Serbs: History, Myth and the Destruction of Yugoslavia
  | publisher = Yale University Press
  | location = New Haven
  | isbn = 978-0-300-08507-5
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=B4YbP0fPcMYC&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Kumar
  | first = Radha
  | authorlink = Radha Kumar
  | year = 1999
  | title = Divide and Fall?: Bosnia in the Annals of Partition
  | publisher = Verso
  | location = London and New York
  | isbn = 978-1-85984-183-9
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=wHEXb81jRMcC&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Lukic
  | first1 = Rénéo
  | last2 = Lynch
  | first2 = Allen
  | title = Europe From the Balkans to the Urals: The Disintegration of Yugoslavia and the Soviet Union
  | year = 1996
  | publisher = Oxford University Press
  | isbn = 978-0-19-829200-5
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=WPhhLfp8huIC&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Magaš
  | first1 = Branka
  | last2 = Žanić
  | first2 = Ivo
  | year = 2001
  | title = The War in Croatia and Bosnia-Herzegovina 1991–1995
  | publisher = Frank Cass
  | location = London
  | isbn = 978-0-7146-8201-3
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=9NljlSh2vpIC&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Malcolm
  | first = Noel
  | authorlink = Noel Malcolm
  | year = 1994
  | title = Bosnia: A Short History
  | publisher = New York University Press
  | location = New York
  | isbn = 978-0-8147-5520-4
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=Cvk6oMf9R7AC&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Off
  | first = Carol
  | year = 2010
  | title = The Ghosts of Medak Pocket: The Story of Canada's Secret War
  | publisher = Random House
  | location = New York
  | isbn = 978-0-307-37078-5
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=NYGxSqwgUccC&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Ramet
  | first = Sabrina P.
  | year = 2006
  | title = The Three Yugoslavias: State-Building and Legitimation, 1918–2005
  | publisher = Indiana University Press
  | location = Bloomington
  | isbn = 978-0-253-34656-8
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=FTw3lEqi2-oC&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Sells
  | first = Michael
  | author-link = Michael Sells
  | chapter = Religion, History, and Genocide in Bosnia-Herzegovina
  | year = 1996
  | title = Religion and Justice in the War Over Bosnia
  | editor1-last = Davis
  | editor1-first = G. Scott
  | pages = 23–44
  | publisher = Psychology Press
  | location = New York
  | isbn = 978-0-415-91520-5
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=EPFM7fChJ4EC&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Silber
  | first1 = Laura
  | authorlink1 = Laura Silber
  | last2 = Little
  | first2 = Allan
  | authorlink2 = Allan Little
  | year = 1997
  | title = Yugoslavia: Death of a Nation
  | publisher = Penguin Books
  | location = New York
  | isbn = 978-0-14-026263-6
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite journal
  | last = Subotić
  | first = Jelena
  | title = The Cruelty of False Remorse: Biljana Plavšić at the Hague
  | journal = Southeastern Europe
  | publisher = BRILL
  | year = 2012
  | volume = 36
  | number = 1
  | pages = 39–59
  | url = http://www.academia.edu/2578509/The_Cruelty_of_False_Remorse_Biljana_Plavsic_at_The_Hague
  | doi = 10.1163/187633312X617011
  | issn = 0094-4467
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Thomas
  | first = Nigel
  | year = 2006
  | title = The Yugoslav Wars (2): Bosnia, Kosovo, and Macedonia, 1992–2001
  | publisher = Osprey Publishing
  | location = New York
  | isbn = 978-1-84176-964-6
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=a7cOQ9Nch2AC&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Toal
  | first1 = Gerard
  | last2 = Dahlman
  | first2 = Carl T.
  | title = Bosnia Remade: Ethnic Cleansing and Its Reversal
  | publisher = Oxford University Press
  | location = New York
  | year = 2011
  | isbn = 978-0-19-973036-0
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=Q1TrvGxJeasC&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Totten
  | first1 = Samuel
  | last2 = Bartrop
  | first2 = Paul R.
  | title = Dictionary of Genocide
  | year = 2008
  | publisher = ABC-CLIO
  | volume = II
  | isbn = 978-0-313-34642-2
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=7c2LHlpdMfAC&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{Cite book
  | last = Velikonja
  | first = Mitja
  | year = 2003
  | title = Religious Separation and Political Intolerance in Bosnia-Herzegovina
  | publisher = Texas A&amp;M University Press
  | location = College Station
  | isbn = 978-1-58544-226-3
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=Rf8P-7ExoKYC&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Weitz
  | first = Eric D.
  | year = 2003
  | title = A Century of Genocide: Utopias of Race and Nation
  | publisher = Princeton University Press
  | location = Princeton
  | isbn = 978-0-691-00913-1
  | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=af3gJaNj3ZEC&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | ref = harv
  }}
{{Refend}}

;News articles
{{Refbegin|2}}
* {{cite AV media
 | last = Amanpour
 | first = Christiane
 | date = 1 June 1997
 | title = Arkan: Part 2 - From Bijeljina to Infamy
 | medium = Documentary
 | publisher = [[CNN]]
 | quote = I mean, to take Bijeljina was nothing actually. Bijeljina was defended by something like 35 or 38 Bosnian police officers. Bijeljina was an undefended city.
 | url = http://www2.scc.rutgers.edu/serbiandigest/296/t296-8.htm
 | ref = {{harvid|Amanpour|1 June 1997}}
}}
* {{cite news
  | title = Arkan's Balkan 'Tigers' escape accountability
  | newspaper = Al Jazeera
  | date = 9 December 2014
  | url = http://www.aljazeera.com/humanrights/2014/12/arkan-balkan-tigers-escape-accountability-2014127122222470909.html
  | ref = {{harvid|Al Jazeera|9 December 2014}}
  }}
* {{cite news
  | title = Biljana Plavsic: Serbian Iron Lady
  | newspaper = BBC
  | date = 27 February 2003
  | url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/1108604.stm
  | ref = {{harvid|BBC|27 February 2003}}
  }}
* {{cite news
  | title = Bosnian Serbs welcome released war criminal Momcilo Krajisnik home as a hero
  | publisher = Fox News
  | date = 30 August 2013
  | url = http://www.foxnews.com/world/2013/08/30/bosnian-serbs-welcome-released-war-criminal-momcilo-krajisnik-home-as-hero/
  | ref = {{harvid|Fox News|30 August 2013}}
  }}
* {{cite news
  | last1 = Dzidic
  | first1 = Denis
  | last2 = Ristic
  | first2 = Marija
  | last3 = Domanovic
  | first3 = Milka
  | last4 = Collaku
  | first4 = Petrit
  | last5 = Milekic
  | first5 = Sven
  | title =Arkan's Paramilitaries: Tigers Who Escaped Justice
  | newspaper = Balkan Insight
  | date = 8 December 2014
  | url = http://www.balkaninsight.com/en/article/arkan-s-paramilitaries-tigers-who-escaped-justice
  | ref = {{harvid|Dzidic||Ristic|Domanovic|Collaku|Milekic|8 December 2014}}
  }}
* {{cite news
  | last = Erlanger
  | first = Steve
  | title = Suspect in Serbian War Crimes Murdered by Masked Gunmen
  | newspaper = The New York Times
  | date = 16 January 2000
  | url = http://www.nytimes.com/2000/01/16/world/suspect-in-serbian-war-crimes-murdered-by-masked-gunmen.html?ref=zeljkoraznatovic
  | ref = {{harvid|Erlanger|16 January 2000}}
  }}
* {{cite news
  | title = Former Bosnian Serb Commander Killed
  | newspaper = BBC
  | date = 8 June 2000
  | url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/782457.stm
  | ref = {{harvid|BBC|8 June 2000}}
  }}
* {{cite news
  | last = Husejnovic
  | first = Merima
  | title = Bijeljina's Strange Silence Over War Crimes
  | newspaper = Balkan Investigative Reporting Network
  | date = 8 November 2008
  | url = http://www.bosnia.org.uk/news/news_body.cfm?newsid=2511
  | ref = {{harvid|Husejnovic|8 November 2008}}
  }}
* {{cite news
  | last = Rachel
  | first = Irwin
  | title = Karadzic Witness Pressed on Serb &quot;Tigers&quot;
  | date = 22 March 2013
  | newspaper = Institute for War &amp; Peace Reporting
  | url = http://iwpr.net/report-news/karadzic-witness-pressed-serb-tigers
  | ref = {{harvid|Irwin|22 March 2013}}
  }}
* {{cite news
  | last = Karabegović
  | first = Dženana
  | title = Sjećanje na zločine u Bijeljini
  | trans_title = Remembering the Crimes Committed in Bijeljina
  | newspaper = Radio Free Europe / Radio Liberty
  | language = Serbo-Croatian
  | date = 4 April 2012
  | url = http://www.slobodnaevropa.org/content/sjecanje_na_zlocine_u_bijeljini/24537462.html
  | ref = {{harvid|Karabegović|4 April 2012}}
  }}
* {{cite AV media
  | last = Keane
  | first = David
  | year = 2003
  | title = Arkan: Baby-faced Psycho
  | medium = Documentary
  | publisher = [[History (U.S. TV channel)|The History Channel]]
  | isbn = 978-0-7670-6417-0
  | ref = {{harvid|Keane|2003}}
  }}
* {{cite news
  | last = Kifner
  | first = John
  | authorlink = John Kifner
  | date = 24 January 2001
  | title = A Pictorial Guide to Hell; Stark Images Trace the Balkans' Descent and a Photographer's Determination
  | newspaper = The New York Times
  | url = http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/24/books/pictorial-guide-hell-stark-images-trace-balkans-descent-photographer-s.html
  | ref = {{harvid|Kifner|24 January 2001}}
  }}
* {{cite news
  | title = Ko uzima deo Cecine kuće?
  | trans_title = Who's Taking a Piece of Ceca's House?
  | date = 27 October 2011
  | newspaper = B92
  | language = Serbo-Croatian
  | url = http://www.b92.net/info/vesti/index.php?yyyy=2011&amp;mm=10&amp;dd=27&amp;nav_category=16&amp;nav_id=552854
  | ref = {{harvid|B92|27 October 2011}}
  }}
* {{cite news
  | last = Little
  | first = Allan
  | title = Karadzic's broken Bosnia remains
  | newspaper = BBC
  | date = 17 September 2008
  | url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/7621649.stm
  | ref = {{harvid|Little|17 September 2008}}
  }}
* {{cite news
  | last = Musli
  | first = Emir
  | title = Zločin bez kazne
  | trans_title = Crime Without Punishment
  | newspaper = Deutsche Welle
  | language = Serbo-Croatian
  | date = 24 September 2011
  | url = http://www.dw.de/zlo%C4%8Din-bez-kazne/a-15413852-0
  | ref = {{harvid|Musli|24 September 2011}}
  }}
* {{cite news
  | last = Musli
  | first = Emir
  | title = Odbrana ili zločin?
  | trans_title = Defense or Crime?
  | newspaper = Deutsche Welle
  | language = Serbo-Croatian
  | date = 2 April 2012
  | url = http://www.dw.de/odbrana-ili-zločin/a-15853579
  | ref = {{harvid|Musli|2 April 2012}}
  }}
* {{cite news
  | last = Musli
  | first = Emir
  | title = Nekažnjeni zločin u Bijeljini
  | trans_title = Unpunished Crimes in Bijeljina
  | newspaper = Deutsche Welle
  | language = Serbo-Croatian
  | date = 26 September 2012
  | url = http://www.dw.com/bs/neka%C5%BEnjeni-zlo%C4%8Din-u-bijeljini/a-16262532
  | ref = {{harvid|Musli|26 September 2012}}
  }}
* {{cite news
  | last = Musli
  | first = Emir
  | title = Dvadeset godina od rušenja bijeljinskih džamija
  | trans_title = Twenty Years Since the Destruction of Bijeljina's Mosques
  | newspaper = Deutsche Welle
  | language = Serbo-Croatian
  | date = 13 March 2013
  | url = http://www.dw.de/dvadeset-godina-od-rušenja-bijeljinskih-džamija/a-16667134
  | ref = {{harvid|Musli|13 March 2013}}
  }}
* {{cite news
  | last = Musli
  | first = Emir
  | title = Ubijeni prirodnom smrću
  | trans_title = The Dead of Natural Causes
  | newspaper = Deutsche Welle
  | language = Serbo-Croatian
  | date = 16 September 2013
  | url = http://www.dw.com/bs/ubijeni-prirodnom-smr%C4%87u/a-17090522
  | ref = {{harvid|Musli|16 September 2013}}
  }}
* {{cite news
  | last = Pazarac
  | first = Sadik
  | title = Kako su se mijenjali nazivi ulica u Bijeljini
  | trans_title = How the Names of Streets Have Changed in Bijeljina
  | newspaper = Radio Free Europe / Radio Liberty
  | language = Serbo-Croatian
  | date = 8 August 2010
  | url = http://www.slobodnaevropa.org/content/kako_su_se_mijenjali_nazivi_ulica_u_bijeljini/2137582.html
  | ref = {{harvid|Pazarac|8 August 2010}}
  }}
* {{cite news
  | newspaper = Prometej
  | title = Pojedinačan popis broja ratnih žrtava u svim općinama BiH
  | trans_title = Detailed Census of War Fatalities in All Municipalities of Bosnia and Herzegovina
  | language = Serbo-Croatian
  | date = 27 February 2013
  | url = http://www.prometej.ba/clanak/drustvo-i-znanost/pojedinacan-popis-broja-ratnih-zrtava-u-svim-opcinama-bih-997
  | ref = {{harvid|Prometej|27 February 2013}}
  }}
* {{cite news
  | last = Ristic
  | first = Marija
  | title = Belgrade DJ Investigated For War Crimes
  | newspaper = Balkan Insight
  | date = 2 October 2012
  | url = http://www.balkaninsight.com/en/article/belgrade-dj-investigated-for-war-crimes
  | ref = {{harvid|Ristic|2 October 2012}}
  }}
* {{cite news
  | title = Sjećanje na početak aprila 1992. godine: Bijeljina slavi zločine
  | trans_title = Remembering the Beginning of April 1992: Bijeljina Celebrates Crimes
  | publisher = Dnevni Avaz
  | language = Serbo-Croatian
  | date = 2 April 2012
  | url = http://www.avaz.ba/vijesti/teme/88069-sjecanje-na-pocetak-aprila-1992-godine-bijeljina-slavi-zlocine.html
  | ref = {{harvid|Dnevni Avaz|2 April 2012}}
  }}
* {{cite news
  | last = Sudetic
  | first = Chuck
  | authorlink = Chuck Sudetic
  | title = Bosnia Calls Up Guard and Reserve
  | newspaper = The New York Times
  | date = 5 April 1992
  | url = http://www.nytimes.com/1992/04/05/world/bosnia-calls-up-guard-and-reserve.html?pagewanted=all
  | ref = {{harvid|Sudetic|5 April 1992}}
  }}
* {{cite news
  | last = Sudetic
  | first = Chuck
  | title = More 'Ethnic Cleansing' by Serbs Is Reported in Bosnia
  | newspaper = The New York Times
  | date = 18 July 1994
  | url = http://www.nytimes.com/1994/07/18/world/more-ethnic-cleansing-by-serbs-is-reported-in-bosnia.html?pagewanted=all
  | ref = {{harvid|Sudetic|18 July 1994}}
  }}
* {{cite news
  | last = Sudetic
  | first = Chuck
  | title = Serb Gang Expels 566 Muslims From Their Homes in Bosnia
  | newspaper = The New York Times
  | date = 3 September 1994
  | url = http://www.nytimes.com/1994/09/03/world/serb-gang-expels-566-muslims-from-their-homes-in-bosnia.html?pagewanted=all
  | ref = {{harvid|Sudetic|3 September 1994}}
  }}
* {{cite news
  | last = Sudetic
  | first = Chuck
  | title = Serbs Drive 800 More Muslims From Homes
  | newspaper = The New York Times
  | date = 5 September 1994
  | url = http://www.nytimes.com/1994/09/05/world/serbs-drive-800-more-muslims-from-homes.html?pagewanted=all
  | ref = {{harvid|Sudetic|5 September 1994}}
  }}
* {{cite news
  | last = Sudetic
  | first = Chuck
  | title = Serbs Step Up Violence Against Bosnian Muslim Civilians
  | newspaper = The New York Times
  | date = 20 September 1994
  | url = http://www.nytimes.com/1994/09/20/world/serbs-step-up-violence-against-bosnian-muslim-civilians.html?pagewanted=all
  | ref = {{harvid|Sudetic|20 September 1994}}
  }}
* {{cite news
  | last = Sudetic
  | first = Chuck
  | title = Bosnian Serbs Force More Than 2,000 Muslims to Leave Their Homes
  | newspaper = The New York Times
  | date = 30 August 1994
  | url = http://www.nytimes.com/1994/08/30/world/bosnian-serbs-force-more-than-2000-muslims-to-leave-their-homes.html?pagewanted=all
  | ref = {{harvid|Sudetic|30 August 1994}}
  }}
* {{cite news
  | last = Traynor
  | first = Ian
  | title = Leading Bosnian Serb war criminal released from Swedish prison
  | newspaper = The Guardian
  | date = 27 October 2009
  | url = http://www.theguardian.com/world/2009/oct/27/bosnian-serb-war-criminal-freed
  | ref = {{harvid|Traynor|27 October 2009}}
  }}
* {{cite news
  | title = Witness to Balkans bloodshed
  | date = 24 May 2001
  | newspaper = BBC
  | url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/1347218.stm
  | ref = {{harvid|BBC|24 May 2001}}
  }}
{{Refend}}

;International, governmental, and NGO sources
{{Refbegin|2}}
* {{cite web
  | title = Biljana Plavšić – Case Information Sheet
  | id = IT-00-39 &amp; 40/1
  | publisher = International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia
  | url = http://www.icty.org/x/cases/plavsic/cis/en/cis_plavsic.pdf
  | ref = {{harvid|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|Biljana Plavšić CIS}}
  }}
* {{cite report
  | title = Bosnia-Herzegovina: Living for the Day – Forced Expulsions from Bijeljina and Janja
  | id = EUR 63/022/1994
  | publisher = Amnesty International
  | date = 21 December 1994
  | url = https://www.amnesty.org/download/Documents/184000/eur630221994en.pdf
  | ref = {{harvid|Amnesty International|21 December 1994}}
  }}
* {{cite report
  | title = Bosnia and Herzegovina: Submission to the Universal Periodic Review of the UN Human Rights Council
  | publisher = International Center for Transitional Justice
  | date = 8 September 2009
  | url = http://ictj.org/sites/default/files/ICTJ-FormerYugoslavia-Bosnia-Review-2009-English.pdf
  | ref = {{harvid|International Center for Transitional Justice|8 September 2009}}
  }}
* {{cite report
  | title = Final Report of the United Nations Commission of Experts Established Pursuant to Security Council Resolution 780 (1992)
  | id = S/1994/674/Add.2
  | url = http://www.ess.uwe.ac.uk/comexpert/anx/III-A.htm#IV.A.3
  | publisher = United Nations Security Council
  | date = 28 December 1994
  | ref = {{harvid|United Nations Security Council|28 December 1994}}
  }}
* {{cite web
  | title = Momčilo Krajišnik – Case Information Sheet
  | id = IT-00-39
  | publisher = International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia
  | url = http://www.icty.org/x/cases/krajisnik/cis/en/cis_krajisnik_en.pdf
  | ref = {{harvid|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|Momčilo Krajišnik CIS}}
  }}
* {{cite web
  | title = Prosecutor v. Momčilo Krajišnik (Trial Judgment)
  | id = IT-00-39-T
  | publisher = International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia (ICTY)
  | date = 27 September 2006
  | url = http://www.icty.org/x/cases/krajisnik/tjug/en/kra-jud060927e.pdf
  | ref = {{harvid|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|27 September 2006}}
  }}
* {{cite web
  | title = Trial of Radovan Karadžić – Transcript
  | id = 130320IT
  | publisher = International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia
  | url = http://icty.org/x/cases/karadzic/trans/en/130320IT.htm
  | ref = {{harvid|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|Radovan Karadžić transcript}}
  }}
* {{cite web
  | title = Prosecutor v. Željko Ražnatović (Initial Indictment)
  | id = IT-97-27
  | publisher = International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia
  | date = 23 September 1997
  | url = http://www.icty.org/x/cases/zeljko_raznjatovic/ind/en/ark-ii970930e.pdf
  | ref = {{harvid|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|23 September 1997}}
  }}
* {{cite web
  | title = Radovan Karadžić – Case Information Sheet
  | id = IT-95-5/18
  | publisher = International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia
  | url = http://www.icty.org/x/cases/karadzic/cis/en/cis_karadzic_en.pdf
  | ref = {{harvid|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|Radovan Karadžić CIS}}
  }}
* {{cite web
  | title = The Cases
  | publisher = International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia
  | url = http://www.icty.org/action/cases/4
  | access-date = 4 May 2015
  | ref = {{harvid|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|Cases summary}}
  }}
* {{cite web
  | title = Trial of Radovan Karadžić – Transcript
  | id = 130320IT
  | publisher = International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia
  | url = http://icty.org/x/cases/karadzic/trans/en/130320IT.htm
  | ref = {{harvid|International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia|Radovan Karadžić transcript}}
  }}
* {{cite report
  | title = Unfinished Business: Return of Displaced Persons and Other Human Rights Issues in Bijeljina
  | publisher = Human Rights Watch
  | date = May 2000
  | volume = 12
  | issue = 7
  | url = http://www.hrw.org/reports/2000/bosnia/BOSN005.pdf
  | ref = {{harvid|Human Rights Watch|May 2000}}
  }}
* {{cite report
  | title = War Crimes in Bosnia-Hercegovina
  | publisher = Human Rights Watch
  | date = August 1992
  | url = http://www.hrw.org/reports/2000/bosnia/BOSN005.pdf
  | ref = {{harvid|Human Rights Watch|August 1992}}
  }}
* {{cite report
  | title = War Criminals in Bosnia's Republika Srpska: Who Are the People in Your Neighbourhood?
  | number = 103
  | publisher = International Crisis Group
  | date = 2 November 2000
  | url = http://www.crisisgroup.org/~/media/Files/europe/Bosnia%2039.pdf
  | ref = {{harvid|International Crisis Group|2 November 2000}}
  }}
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Refbegin}}
* {{cite web
  | title = Bijeljina: The Righteous Man
  | series = Bosnia and Hercegovina: Twenty Years Later
  | publisher = Institute for War and Peace Reporting
  | date = 24 April 2012
  | url = http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qIe0Ew5iJo0&amp;list=PL3DFB71DBFDDAB945&amp;index=3
  }}
* {{cite web
  | title = Clouds Over Bijeljina
  | series = Bosnia and Hercegovina: Twenty Years Later
  | publisher = Institute for War and Peace Reporting
  | date = 24 April 2012
  | url = http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aIh3zgP_Y10&amp;list=PL3DFB71DBFDDAB945&amp;index=2
  }}
* {{cite news
  | last = Feinstein
  | first = Anthony
  | title = Capturing A War Crime
  | newspaper = The Globe and Mail
  | date = 21 June 2015
  | url = http://www.theglobeandmail.com/news/national/capturing-a-war-crime/article25016202/
  }}
* {{cite journal
  | last = Hadzic
  | first = Hasan
  | title = Bijeljina: A Bastion of Apartheid
  | journal = Bosnia Report
  | publisher = Bosnian Institute
  |date=July 2003
  | number = 32–34
  | url = http://www.bosnia.org.uk/bosrep/report_format.cfm?articleID=935&amp;reportid=157
  }}
* {{cite web
  | last = Haviv
  | first = Ron
  | title = Preventing Genocide – Gallery – Eyewitness Testimony – Ron Haviv
  | publisher = United States Holocaust Memorial Museum
  | url = http://www.ushmm.org/confront-genocide/cases/bosnia-herzegovina/bosnia-video-gallery/eyewitness-testimony-ron-haviv
  }}
* {{cite web
  | last = Toal
  | first = Gerard
  | date = 3 April 2012
  | title = The Bosnian War, 20 years on&amp;nbsp;... 
  | publisher = Oxford University Press Blog
  | url = http://blog.oup.com/2012/04/the-bosnian-war-20-years-on/
  }}
{{Refend}}

{{Bosnian War}}
{{Yugoslav wars}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bijeljina massacre}}
[[Category:1992 in Bosnia and Herzegovina]]
[[Category:Mass murder in 1992]]
[[Category:Massacres in the Bosnian War]]
[[Category:Serbian war crimes in the Bosnian War]]
[[Category:Bosnian genocide]]
[[Category:Eliticides]]
[[Category:History of Republika Srpska]]</text>
      <sha1>3xd3ukmpp28nz13akv4d9kz53aes1u6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
