<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Bombardment of Papeete</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>20167416</id>
    <revision>
      <id>744277148</id>
      <parentid>686175110</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-14T06:57:09Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* References */http&amp;rarr;https for [[Google Books]] and [[Google News]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18329">{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2012}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict = Bombardment of Papeete
| partof   = [[Asian and Pacific theatre of World War I]]
| image    = [[File:M 54 8 Papeete bombardée.jpg|300px|alt=Ruined bombed out buildings near a church in Papeete after the bombardment.]]
| caption  = Buildings in the city of Papeete destroyed by German shore bombardment.
| date     = 22 September 1914
| place    = off [[Papeete]], [[French Polynesia]], [[Pacific Ocean]]
| result   = German victory
*French ships sunk
*Coal piles not captured, destroyed by the French&lt;ref name=&quot;Halpern 89&quot;&gt;Halpern, p. 89&lt;/ref&gt;
| combatant1  = {{flagcountry|French Third Republic}}
| combatant2  = {{flag|German Empire}}
| commander1  = {{flagicon|France|naval}} Maxime Destremau
| commander2  = {{flagicon|German Empire|naval}} [[Maximilian von Spee]]
| strength1   = '''Land:'''&lt;br/&gt;160 [[infantry]]&lt;br/&gt;2 [[shore battery|shore batteries]]&lt;br/&gt;'''Sea:'''&lt;br/&gt;1 [[gunboat]]&lt;br/&gt;1 [[cargo ship|freighter]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Gudmundsson 2&quot;&gt;Gudmundsson, p. 2&lt;/ref&gt;
| strength2   = 2 [[armored cruiser]]s&lt;ref name=&quot;Corbett 312&quot;&gt;Corbett, p. 312&lt;/ref&gt;
| casualties1 = 1 gunboat sunk&lt;br/&gt;1 freighter sunk&lt;br/&gt;Papeete severely damaged&lt;ref name=&quot;Forestry 558&quot;/&gt;
| casualties2 = none&lt;ref name=&quot;Forestry 558&quot;/&gt;
| casualties3 = '''Civilian casualties:'''&lt;br/&gt;2 killed&lt;ref name=&quot;Forestry 558&quot;&gt;American Forestry, p. 558&lt;/ref&gt;
| notes       =
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Command of the Oceans 1914-1915}}
}}
[[File:SpeeMap.jpg|thumb|240px|right|''Scharnhost''{{'}}s and ''Gneisenau''{{'}}s path across the Pacific.|alt=Map of depicting various pacific islands and the dates at which Spee arrived at them.]]

The '''Bombardment of Papeete''' occurred in [[French Polynesia]] when [[German Empire|German]] warships attacked on 22 September 1914, during [[World War I]]. The German [[armoured cruiser]]s {{SMS|Scharnhorst||6}} and {{SMS|Gneisenau||2}} entered the port of [[Papeete]] on the island of [[Tahiti]] and sank the [[French Third Republic|French]] gunboat {{Ship|French gunboat|Zélée||2}} and freighter ''Walkure'' before bombarding the town's fortifications. French [[Coastal artillery|shore batteries]] and a gunboat resisted the German intrusion, but were greatly outgunned. The main German objective was to seize the coal piles stored on the island, but these were destroyed by the French at the start of the action.

The German vessels were largely undamaged but the French lost their [[gunboat]]. Several of Papeete's buildings were destroyed and the town's economy was severely disrupted. The main strategic consequence of the engagement was the disclosure of the cruisers' positions to the [[British Admiralty]], which led to the [[Battle of Coronel]] where the entire [[German East Asia Squadron]] defeated a [[Royal Navy]] squadron. The depletion of ''Scharnhorst''{{'}}s and ''Gneisenau''{{'}}s ammunition at Papeete also contributed to their subsequent destruction at the [[Battle of the Falklands]].

==Background==
Word of war reached Admiral [[Maximilian von Spee]]—of the German East Asia Squadron—while at [[Pohnpei|Ponape]] (17 July – 6 August). He concentrated the majority of his squadron at [[Pagan Island]] in the nearby Mariana Islands, and then steamed off into the Pacific with the [[Scharnhorst class armored cruiser|''Scharnhorst''-class]] [[armored cruiser]]s {{SMS|Scharnhorst||6}} and {{SMS|Gneisenau||2}}, the [[Königsberg class cruiser (1905)|''Königsberg''-class]] [[light cruiser]] {{SMS|Nürnberg|1906|6}}, the [[auxiliary cruiser]] SMS ''Titania'', and several [[Collier (ship type)|collier]]s at his disposal. ''Nürnberg'' and ''Titania'' were sent to gather intelligence at [[Hawaii]] and [[Fanning Raid|raid the cable station at Fanning Island]].&lt;ref&gt;Halpern, p. 88&lt;/ref&gt; Von Spee then learned that Australian and New Zealand forces had [[Occupation of German Samoa|captured German Samoa]], and he sailed off in his flagship ''Scharnhorst''—along with her [[sister ship]] ''Gneisenau''—to engage what Allied forces they could find there. Failing to catch the [[Samoa Expeditionary Force]] at [[Apia]] and having seen no action at all since leaving Pagan Island, the men of Admiral von Spee's armored cruisers were eager to meet the enemy in battle.&lt;ref&gt;Strachan, p. 472&lt;/ref&gt;

Von Spee decided to raid [[Papeete]] in [[Tahiti]] on his way to rendezvous with the rest of his squadron at [[Easter Island]]. The French held over {{convert|5000|t|ST|lk=on|abbr=on}} of high-quality [[Cardiff coal]] at the port, and von Spee hoped to seize the coal piles to replenish his squadron's supply. Additionally, von Spee aimed at destroying what allied shipping he could find in the harbour, and thought the raid might help raise his men's morale. Von Spee intended to coal at [[Suwarrow Atoll]] before sailing to Papeete, but was prevented by foul weather.&lt;ref name=&quot;Corbett 312&quot;/&gt; Instead, von Spee decided to take ''Scharnhorst'' and ''Gneisenau'' and attempt to resupply at [[Bora Bora]] while ''Nürnberg'' and ''Titania'' were dispatched to [[Nukuhiva]] to guard the fleet's colliers. The German admiral intended to keep his vessels' identities secret by disguising them as French ships, flying French flags, and only allowing French- and English-speaking members of his crew contact with the Frenchmen present there.&lt;ref name=&quot;Halpern 89&quot;/&gt; Von Spee managed to replenish his food stores using gold seized by ''Titania'' and ''Nürnberg'' during their raid of Fanning, and was able to discover the strength of the French military in the region as well as the exact size and positions of the coal piles at Papeete.&lt;ref&gt;Hough, p. 47&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Jose 558&quot;&gt;Jose, p. 558&lt;/ref&gt;

The French had no heavy defenses at Papeete but had been warned that von Spee's squadron might raid Tahiti and that a German squadron had been sighted off Samoa. Although Papeete was the capital of the [[French Settlements in Oceania]], by 1914 it had become a colonial backwater, lacking a [[radio|wireless station]] and having a garrison of only 25 colonial infantry and 20 [[Gendarmerie|gendarme]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jose 558&quot;/&gt; In order to bolster the town's defenses, [[Lieutenant]] Maxime Destremau—commander of the old wooden gunboat {{Ship|French gunboat|Zélée||2}} and the ranking officer at Papeete—had his ship's {{convert|100|mm|in|abbr=on}} stern gun and all of her {{convert|65|mm|in|abbr=on}} and {{convert|37|mm|in|abbr=on}} guns removed from his vessel and placed ashore to be used in place of Papeete's antiquated [[Coastal artillery|land batteries]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Halpern 89&quot;/&gt; Several [[Ford Motor Company|Ford]] trucks were turned into impromptu [[Armored car (military)|armored car]]s by mounting them with ''Zélée''{{'}}s 37-mm guns and 160 sailors and marines drilled in preparation to repel any German attempt at landing.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gudmundsson 2&quot;/&gt; ''Zélée'' retained only her 100-mm bow gun and 10 men under the ship's second in command.&lt;ref name=&quot;Destremau&quot;&gt;{{Cite press release | title = Defending Tahiti – September 1914 | language= French | publisher = Noëlle Destremau | date = 9 March 1999 | url = http://www.alafrontiere.fr/NOELLE/ND/abaNoelle%20Destremau.html | accessdate = 8 February 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to the gunboat and harbor fortifications, the French also had at Papeete the unarmed German [[Cargo ship|freighter]] ''Walkure'', which had been captured by ''Zélée'' at the start of the war.&lt;ref&gt;American Forestry, p. 559&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the French preparations, the two German cruisers were more than a match for the forces Destremau commanded at Papeete. Both ''Scharnhorst'' and ''Gneisenau'' heavily outgunned ''Zélée'', each being armed with eight {{convert|210|mm|in|abbr=on}} guns, six {{convert|150|mm|in|abbr=on}} guns, eighteen {{convert|88|mm|in|abbr=on}} guns, and four torpedo tubes. Von Spee's forces also outnumbered the French with over 1,500 sailors aboard their vessels, more than enough to form a landing party and overwhelm the forces Destremau had to oppose them.&lt;ref&gt;Gröner, p. 52&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battle==
[[File:Gws scharnhorst 01.jpg|thumb|right|One of the turrets of ''Scharnhorst''{{'s}} main battery.|alt=Picture of large caliber guns on a German armored cruiser.]]
[[File:Capitaine Destremeau et son etat major a Papeete en 1914.jpg|thumb|Captain Maxime Destremau (center) and his staff in Papeete in 1914.]]

At 07:00 on 22 September 1914, the French sighted two unidentified cruisers approaching the harbor of Papeete. The alarm was raised, the harbor's signal beacons destroyed, and three [[warning shot]]s were fired by the French batteries to signal the approaching cruisers that they must identify themselves.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jose 558&quot;/&gt; The cruisers replied with a shot of their own and raised the [[Ensign|German colors]], signaling the town to [[Surrender (military)|surrender]]. The French refused the German demands, and von Spee's vessels began to shell the shore batteries and town from a distance of {{convert|6000|m|yd|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref&gt;American Forestry, p. 553&lt;/ref&gt; The land batteries and the gunboat in the harbor returned fire, but scored no hits on the armored cruisers. Having difficulty in discovering the exact position of the French batteries, the German cruisers soon turned their attention to the French shipping in the harbor.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hough 48&quot;&gt;Hough, p. 48&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jose, p. 559&lt;/ref&gt;

The French commander—Destremau—had ordered the coal piles burned at the start of the action and now smoke began billowing over the town. ''Zélée'' and ''Walkure'' were sighted and fired upon by the Germans. The French had begun to [[Scuttling|scuttle]] their vessels when the action had begun, but both were still afloat when ''Scharnhorst'' and ''Gneisenau'' began firing upon them and finished the two ships off. By now, most of the Papeete's inhabitants had fled and the town had caught fire from the German shelling, with two [[City block|block]]s of Papeete set alight.&lt;ref name=&quot;Forestry 554&quot;&gt;American Forestry, p. 554&lt;/ref&gt; With the coal piles destroyed and the threat of [[naval mine|mine]]s in the harbor, von Spee saw no meaningful purpose in making a landing.&lt;ref&gt;Gudmundsson, p. 3&lt;/ref&gt; Accordingly, the German admiral withdrew his ships from Papeete's harbor by 11:00.&lt;ref name=&quot;Forestry 554&quot;/&gt; After leaving Papeete, the ships steamed out towards [[Nuku Hiva]] to meet ''Nürnberg'', ''Titania'', and colliers waiting there.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hough 48&quot;/&gt;

==Aftermath==
[[File:PapeeteDestroyed.jpg|thumb|240px|right|Some of the damage done to the town of Papeete after it was bombarded by the Germans.]]
[[File:WalkureSunk.jpg|thumb|Picture of a battle damaged freighter half-sunk in shallow water]]

By the time von Spee withdrew his ships, large portions of the town had been destroyed. Two entire blocks of Papeete had burnt to the ground before the fires were finally put out. A [[copra]] store, a market, and several other buildings and residences were among those destroyed by the shellfire and resulting inferno. While the majority of Papeete's civilians fled to the interior of the island as soon as the fighting began, a Japanese civilian and a [[Tahitians|Polynesian]] boy were both killed by German shellfire. Although the two French vessels in the harbor had been sunk, there were no military casualties on either side and the German vessels took no damage. Overall, the bombardment was estimated in 1915 to have caused over 2&amp;nbsp;million [[French franc|franc]]s' worth of property damage, some of which was recouped through the seizure of a German store on the island.&lt;ref name=&quot;Forestry 558&quot;/&gt; In addition to the seizure of their property, several local Germans were [[internment|interned]] and forced to repair the damage von Spee's squadron had caused. Perhaps the most lasting effect of the bombardment on the French was the dramatic fall of copra prices in the region, as local suppliers had previously sold a majority of their produce to German merchants in the area who were now interned.&lt;ref&gt;Davis, p. 1&lt;/ref&gt; Further havoc and distress spread throughout the island 18 days after von Spee's squadron had left, when rumors started to spread that a second German bombardment was about to begin.&lt;ref name=&quot;Forestry 558&quot;/&gt;

After withdrawing, ''Scharnhorst'' and ''Gneisenau'' rendezvoused with ''Nürnberg'' and ''Titania'' at Nuku Hiva, where they resupplied and their crews took [[shore leave]] before moving on to meet the rest of the squadron at Easter Island.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hough 48&quot;/&gt; Although the Germans had destroyed the shipping at Papeete and wreaked havoc in the town, they had been denied their primary objective of seizing the French coal piles and replenishing their own stocks. Von Spee's raid allowed the British Admiralty to receive word on his position and heading, allowing them to inform Rear Admiral [[Christopher Cradock]] of the German intentions thus leading to the [[Battle of Coronel]].&lt;ref&gt;Hough, p. 71&lt;/ref&gt; Another effect was the reduction of ammunition available to the two German cruisers. The hundreds of shells fired by von Spee's ships at Papeete were irreplaceable. The depletion of ammunition as a result of the action at Papeete contributed to the German East Asia Squadron's failure to adequately defend itself at the [[Battle of the Falkland Islands]] against British [[battlecruiser]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Freeman, p. 274&lt;/ref&gt; Lieutenant Destremau was chastised by his misinformed superior officer for his actions during the defense of Papeete and for the loss of the gunboat ''Zélée''. He was summoned back to Toulon under arrest to be court-martialled, but died of illness in 1915 before the trial. In 1918, Destremau was finally recognized for his actions at Papeete and was posthumously awarded the ''[[Légion d'honneur]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Destremau&quot;/&gt;

==Citations==
{{reflist|2}}

==References==
*{{Cite journal | last = | first = | authorlink = | coauthors = | title = Bombardment of Papeete | journal = American Forestry | volume = XXI | issue = | pages = | publisher = The American Forestry Association | location = Washington, D.C. | year = 1915 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=Ex0CAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA553&amp;dq=bombardment+of+papeete&amp;lr=#v=onepage&amp;q=bombardment%20of%20papeete&amp;f=false | accessdate = 21 November 2009 }}
* {{cite book |series=History of the Great War based on Official Documents |title=Naval Operations |volume=I |first=J. S. |last=Corbett |authorlink=Julian Corbett |year=2009 |orig-year=1938 |publisher=Longmans, Green |edition=2nd reprinted Imperial War Museum and N &amp; M Press |location=London |url=https://archive.org/details/navaloperations01corb |accessdate=29 April 2015 |isbn=1-84342-489-4}}
*{{Cite journal | last = Davis | first = W. M. | authorlink = | coauthors = | title = The Reef-Encircled Islands of the Pacific | journal = The Journal of Geography | volume = XVII | issue = | pages = | publisher = The Post Publishing Co. | location = Appleton, Wisconsin | year = 1918 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=ILmfAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA1&amp;dq=bombardment+papeete#v=onepage&amp;q=bombardment%20papeete&amp;f=false | accessdate = 22 November 2009 }}
*{{Cite journal | last = Freeman | first = Lewis R. | authorlink = Lewis R. Freeman | coauthors = | title = The Story of the ''Cornwall'' | journal = The Worlds Work | volume = XXXVI | issue = | pages = | publisher = Doubleday, Page &amp; Company | location = New York | year = 1918 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=faLNAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA374&amp;dq=bombardment+of+papeete&amp;lr=#v=onepage&amp;q=bombardment%20of%20papeete&amp;f=false | accessdate = 21 November 2009 }}
*{{cite book | last = Gröner | first = Erich | authorlink = | coauthors = | title = German Warships 1815–1945 Volume One: Major Surface Vessels | publisher = Naval Institute Press | year = 1990 | location = Annapolis | isbn = 0-87021-790-9 }}
*{{cite book | last = Gudmundsson | first = Bruce I. | authorlink = | coauthors = | title = On Armor | publisher = Praeger Publishers | year = 2004 | location = Westport, CT | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=uSivaTC7tSgC&amp;pg=PA2&amp;dq=Destremau+zelee#v=onepage&amp;q=Destremau%20zelee&amp;f=false | isbn = 0-275-95019-0 }}
*{{cite book | last = Halpern | first = Paul G. | authorlink = Paul Halpern | coauthors = | title = A Naval History of World War I | publisher = US Naval Institute Press | year = 1995 | location = Annapolis, MD | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=Sc71ej2XGDcC&amp;pg=PA311&amp;dq=tenth+flotilla+arabis&amp;lr=&amp;cd=2#v=snippet&amp;q=papeete&amp;f=false | isbn = 1-55750-352-4 }}
*{{cite book | last = Hough | first = Richard | authorlink = Richard Hough | coauthors = | title = Falklands 1914: The Pursuit of Admiral Von Spee | publisher = Periscope Publishing | year = 2003 | location = Penzance, Cornwall | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=ARLc4b8ff88C&amp;pg=PA48  | isbn = 1-904381-12-X }}
*{{cite book | last = Jose | first = Arthur | authorlink = Arthur W. Jose | coauthors = | series = Official History of Australia in the War of 1914–1918 |title=The Royal Australian Navy, 1914–1918 |volume=IX | publisher = Angus &amp; Robertson | year = 1941 |edition=9th | location = Sydney | pages = | url = http://www.awm.gov.au/histories/first_world_war/volume.asp?levelID=67895 | doi = | id = | isbn = }}
*{{cite book | last = Strachan | first = Hew | authorlink = Hew Strachan | title = The First World War: To Arms | publisher = Oxford University Press | year = 2001 | location = New York | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=zv8Zrrt6vqgC&amp;pg=PA472&amp;dq=bombardment+papeete&amp;lr=#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false | isbn =0-19-820877-4}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite book | last = Gasse | first = Michel | authorlink = | coauthors = | title = Tahiti 1914 – Le vent de guerre | language = French | publisher = A la frontière (maison d'édition) | year = 2009 | location = Lardy, France | pages = 352 | url = | doi = | id = | isbn = 978-2-918665-00-7}}

{{Coord|17|32|S|149|34|W|type:event|display=title}}
{{Portal|World War I}}

{{good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Papeete, Bombardment of}}
[[Category:1914 in France]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1914]]
[[Category:History of French Polynesia]]
[[Category:1914 in French Polynesia]]
[[Category:Naval battles of the Asian and Pacific Theatre (World War I)]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War I involving France]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War I involving Germany]]</text>
      <sha1>0bj0kkki72apt7df2ew4xjpdy5tzyx2</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
