<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Borodino-class battlecruiser</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4674998</id>
    <revision>
      <id>732838125</id>
      <parentid>714120232</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-03T15:39:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Italia2006</username>
        <id>11898625</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="27027">{{about|the Borodino-class battlecruisers|the earlier pre-dreadnought battleships|Borodino-class battleship}}
{|{{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
|Ship image=[[File:NEP5224Izmail.JPG|300px]]
|Ship caption=Plan and right elevation drawings of the ''Borodino'' class
}}
{{Infobox ship class overview
|Name=''Borodino'' (''Izmail'')
|Builders=
|Operators={{navy|Russia}}
|Class before=''None''
|Class after={{Sclass-|Kronshtadt|battlecruiser|4}}
|Cost=
|Built range=1912–17
|Total ships planned=4
|Total ships cancelled=4
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
|Hide header=
|Header caption=
|Ship type=[[Battlecruiser]]
|Ship displacement=*{{convert|32500|LT|t|0|lk=in}} standard
*{{convert|36646|LT|t|0}} full load
|Ship length= {{convert|223.85|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
|Ship beam={{convert|30.5|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
|Ship draught={{convert|8.81|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
|Ship propulsion=4 shafts, 4 [[steam turbine]]s
|Ship power=*{{convert|66000|shp|lk=in|abbr=on}}
*25 triangular [[Yarrow]] [[water-tube boiler]]s
|Ship speed= {{convert|26.5|kn|lk=in}}
|Ship complement=1,174
|Ship armament=*4 × 3 – {{convert|14|in|mm|adj=on|0}} guns
*24 × 1 – [[130 mm/55 B7 Pattern 1913|{{convert|130|mm|adj=on|sp=us}} Pattern 1913 guns]]
*4 × 1 – {{convert|2.5|in|mm|adj=on}} AA guns
*6 × {{convert|17.7|in|adj=on|0}} [[torpedo tube]]s
|Ship armour=*[[Belt armor|Waterline belt]]: {{convert|125|-|237.5|mm|in|abbr=on}}
*[[Barbette]]s: {{convert|147.5|-|247.5|mm|in|abbr=on}}
*[[Conning tower]]: {{convert|300|-|400|mm|in|1|abbr=on}}
*[[gun turret|Turrets]]: {{convert|300|mm|in|abbr=on|1}}
*[[Deck (ship)|Deck]]s: {{convert|37.5|-|75|mm|in|abbr=on}}
*[[Bulkhead (partition)|Bulkhead]]s: {{convert|75|-|300|mm|in|1|abbr=on}}
|Ship notes=
}}
|}

The '''''Borodino''-class battlecruisers''' ({{lang-ru|Линейные крейсера типа «Измаил»}}) were a group of four [[battlecruisers]] ordered by the [[Imperial Russian Navy]] before [[World War I]]. Also referred to as the '''''Izmail'' class''', they were laid down in December 1912&lt;ref group=Note&gt;All dates used in this article are [[Old Style and New Style dates|New Style]] (Gregorian).&lt;/ref&gt; at [[Saint Petersburg]] for service with the [[Baltic Fleet]]. Construction of the ships was delayed as many domestic factories were overloaded with orders and some components had to be ordered from abroad. The start of World War I slowed their construction still further as the imported components were often not delivered and domestic production was diverted into areas more immediately useful for the war effort.

Three of the four ships were launched in 1915 and the fourth in 1916. Work on the [[gun turret]]s lagged, and it became evident that Russian industry would not be able to complete the ships during the war. The [[Russian Revolution (1917)|Russian Revolution]] of 1917 put a stop to their construction, which was never resumed. Although some consideration was given to finishing the hulls that were nearest to completion, they were all eventually sold for scrap by the [[Soviet Union]]. The [[Soviet Navy]] proposed in 1925 to convert ''Izmail'', the ship closest to completion, to an [[aircraft carrier]], but the plan was cancelled after political maneuvering by the [[Red Army]] led to funding not being available.

==Design and development==
After the end of the [[Russo-Japanese War]] of 1905, the Russian Naval General Staff decided that it needed a squadron of fast &quot;[[armoured cruiser]]s&quot;{{refn|The ''Borodino''-class ships were formally known as armoured cruisers until an order of 29 July 1915, when they were redesignated as battlecruisers (''{{lang-ru|lineinyi kreiser}}'').&lt;ref name=m4/&gt;|group=Note}}&lt;ref name=m4&gt;McLaughlin, p. 244&lt;/ref&gt; that could use their speed to engage the leader of an enemy's [[battle line]], much as [[Tōgō Heihachirō|Admiral Tōgō]] had done against the Russian fleet during the [[Battle of Tsushima]]. Initially the Naval General Staff wanted a ship with high speed ({{convert|28|knots|lk=in|disp=or}}), {{convert|12|in|0|adj=on}} guns, and limited protection (a [[Belt armor|waterline belt]] of {{convert|190|mm|in|1|abbr=on|disp=or}}); the [[Emperor]] approved construction of four such ships on 5 May 1911, but the [[Duma]] session ended before the proposal could be voted on. Preliminary bids for the ships were solicited from private builders, but the bids proved to be very high,&lt;ref name=m4/&gt; leading to a reconsideration of the requirements. A new specification was issued on 1 July 1911 by the Naval General Staff for a ship with a speed of only {{convert|26.5|knots}} and with armour increased to {{convert|254|mm|in|0|abbr=on}}. Armaments were increased to nine {{convert|14|in|mm|0|adj=on}} guns in three non-[[Superfire|superfiring]] triple-[[gun turret]]s,&lt;ref&gt;McLaughlin, p. 245&lt;/ref&gt; based on a false rumor that the Germans were increasing the caliber of their guns.&lt;ref&gt;Gardiner and Gray, p. 304&lt;/ref&gt; The Russian Navy believed that widely separating the main gun [[magazine (artillery)|magazine]]s improved the survivability of the ship, and that under a superfiring arrangement, [[muzzle blast]] would hurt the sailors manning the [[gun sight]]s in the lower turrets through the open [[Glossary of nautical terms#S|sighting hoods]] on the turret roofs.

The Naval Ministry solicited new bids on 8 September from 23 shipbuilders, domestic and foreign, but only seven responded, even after the deadline was extended by a month. A number of designs were rejected for not meeting the revised criteria. In the meantime, the Artillery Section of the Main Administration of Shipbuilding had decided that it preferred a four-turret design, and new bids were solicited in May 1912 from the leading contenders from the first round of bidding.&lt;ref name=watts65/&gt; The eventual winner was a design by the [[Admiralty Shipyard|Admiralty Works]] in [[Saint Petersburg]], which had the extra turret added to a new hull section inserted into the original three-turret design.&lt;ref name=m56&gt;McLaughlin, pp. 245–46&lt;/ref&gt;

The Duma approved construction in May 1912, before the design was finalised, and allocated 45.5 million [[ruble]]s for each ship. However, the increase in armaments and consequential increase in the size of the ships raised their estimated cost by seven million rubles each, and some money was diverted from the budget for the {{sclass|Svetlana|cruiser}}s. Orders were placed on 18 September 1912 for a pair of ships each from the [[New Admiralty Shipyard]] and the [[Baltic Shipyard|Baltic Works]]. The first pair was to be ready for trials on 14 July 1916 and the second pair on 14 September 1916.&lt;ref name=watts65&gt;Watts, p. 65&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McLaughlin, p. 247&lt;/ref&gt;

Full-scale armour trials revealed serious weaknesses in the proposed protection scheme. The trials employed the obsolete [[ironclad]] {{ship|Russian battleship|Chesma|1886|2}}, modified with armour protection identical to that used by the {{sclass|Gangut|battleship}}s then under construction. The [[deck (ship)|deck]] and turret roof armour proved to be too thin, and the structure supporting the side armour was not strong enough to withstand the shock of impact from heavy shells.&lt;ref name=m47/&gt;

The design of the ''Borodino''-class ships was modified as a consequence, which slowed their construction. Deck armour was reinforced with extra plates, the turret roofs were increased to a thickness of {{convert|150|mm|in|1|abbr=on}}, and the side and roof of the [[conning tower]] were increased by {{convert|100|mm|in|1|abbr=on}} and {{convert|125|mm|in|1|abbr=on}} respectively. To compensate for the additional weight, the rear conning tower was removed entirely and the thickness of the main belt was reduced by {{convert|4.5|mm|in|abbr=on}}. [[Mortise and tenon]] joints were introduced between the armour plates along their vertical edges to better distribute the shock of a shell impact and to lessen the stress on the supporting hull structure. The launching of the first pair of ships was postponed by six months because of these changes, plus delays imposed by the large number of ship orders already in hand.&lt;ref group=Note&gt;The shipyards were overloaded with orders and simply lacked the capacity to maintain the original construction schedule.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=m47&gt;McLaughlin, pp. 247–48&lt;/ref&gt;

The outbreak of the First World War in 1914 caused further delays as a number of components had been ordered from foreign manufacturers. As an example, the gun turrets rested on {{convert|8|in|mm|0|adj=on}} [[Bearing (mechanical)|roller bearings]] made in Germany, but attempts to order replacements from the United Kingdom and Sweden proved futile, as no company was willing and able to make the bearings. Components for the turbines of ''Navarin'' and ''Izmail''&lt;ref name=watts65/&gt; that had been ordered from [[AG Vulcan Stettin|AG Vulcan]] in Germany were seized by the German government at the beginning of the war and used in the construction of the two {{sclass|Brummer|cruiser}}s.&lt;ref&gt;McLaughlin, pp. 248–249, 253&lt;/ref&gt;

===General characteristics===
The ''Borodino''-class ships were {{convert|223.85|m|ftin}} long [[length overall|overall]]. They had a [[beam (nautical)|beam]] of {{convert|30.5|m|ftin}} and a [[draft (ship)|draught]] of {{convert|8.81|m|ftin}} at full load. The ships [[displacement (ship)|displaced]] {{convert|32500|LT|t|lk=in}} normally, and {{convert|36646|LT|t}} at ([[Full-load displacement|full load]]).&lt;ref name=taras39&gt;Taras, p. 39&lt;/ref&gt; High-tensile steel was used throughout the hull with [[Carbon steel#Mild and low carbon steel|mild steel]] used only in areas that did not contribute to structural strength. The hull was subdivided into 25 transverse watertight [[bulkhead (partition)|bulkhead]]s and the engine room was divided by a longitudinal bulkhead. The [[double bottom]] had a height of {{convert|1.275|m|ftin}}, while the vitals of the ship were protected by a triple bottom that added an extra {{convert|875|mm}} of depth. The design called for a [[freeboard (nautical)|freeboard]] of {{convert|8.89|m|ftin}} forward, {{convert|6.24|m|ftin}} amidships and {{convert|6.49|m|ftin}} aft. The ships were fitted with three Frahm [[Glossary of nautical terms#A|anti-rolling tanks]] on each side.&lt;ref&gt;McLaughlin, pp. 243, 249, 251&lt;/ref&gt;

===Propulsion===
Two sets of [[steam turbine]]s were ordered on 22 April 1913 from the Franco-Russian Works in Saint Petersburg for the Admiralty-built ships; the Baltic Works built its own turbines and one pair for ''Navarin'' was ordered by the [[AG Vulcan Stettin]] in Germany, with some components ordered from abroad. The wing propeller shafts were powered by high-pressure impulse-reaction turbines, and the inboard shafts were powered by low-pressure reaction-type turbines. They produced a total of {{convert|66000|shp|kW|lk=in}} and were designed to be overloaded to {{convert|90000|shp|kW|abbr=on}}. The turbines were powered by 25 triangular [[Yarrow boiler]]s with a working pressure of {{convert|17|kg/cm2|kPa psi|0|abbr=on|lk=on}}. The forward boilers were grouped into three compartments with three oil-fired boilers in each compartment. The rear boilers were split into four compartments with each containing four coal-fired boilers fitted with oil sprayers. Maximum speed was estimated at 26.5 knots, although forcing the machinery would increase it to {{convert|28.5|knots}}. Coal capacity was {{convert|1974|LT|t}} and [[fuel oil]] capacity was {{convert|1904|LT|t}}, which gave an estimated range of {{convert|2280|nmi|-1}} at full speed.&lt;ref name=watts65/&gt;&lt;ref name=taras39/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McLaughlin, pp. 244, 253–54&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''Borodino''-class ships had six [[turbo generator]]s and two [[diesel generator]]s, each rated at {{convert|320|kW|lk=in}}. These were divided among four compartments on the platform deck, two forward and two aft of the machinery. The generators powered a complex electrical system that combined [[alternating current]] for most equipment with [[direct current]] for heavy-load machinery such as the turret motors.&lt;ref&gt;McLaughlin, pp. 254, 332&lt;/ref&gt;

===Armament===
The main armament consisted of four electrically powered turrets, which were never built. The turrets were designed to elevate and traverse at a rate of 3° per second. Each would have had three 52-[[caliber (artillery)|calibre]] {{convert|356|mm|in|adj=on|0}} Model 1913 guns. The guns could be depressed to −5° and elevated to +25°. They could be loaded at any angle between −5° and +15°; the expected rate of fire was three rounds per minute. At full load, 80 rounds per gun could be carried. The guns fired {{convert|747.6|kg|adj=on}} projectiles at a [[muzzle velocity]] of {{convert|731.5|m/s|ft/s|abbr=on}}; this provided a maximum range of {{convert|23240|m|yd}}.&lt;ref name=taras39/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McLaughlin, pp. 251–52&lt;/ref&gt;

The secondary armament consisted of twenty-four 55-calibre [[130 mm/55 B7 Pattern 1913|130 mm Pattern 1913 guns]] mounted in [[casemate]]s. A pair of casemates were situated on each side, below the three rear turrets; near the forward turret were six additional casemates, two of which were directly above the middle pair. This positioning reflected the Naval General Staff's prediction of the most likely direction of attack by [[torpedo boat]]s.&lt;ref name=taras39/&gt;&lt;ref name=m2&gt;McLaughlin, p. 252&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[anti-aircraft warfare|anti-aircraft]] armament was intended to be four 38-caliber {{convert|64|mm|in|adj=on}} [[anti-aircraft gun]]s fitted on the upper deck with 220 rounds stored per gun.&lt;ref name=m2/&gt; Four {{convert|75|mm|in|adj=on}} guns were to be mounted in pairs on the main turret roofs for [[sub-caliber training]] with the main guns. Six underwater {{convert|450|mm|in|adj=on}} [[torpedo tube]]s were fitted, three on each [[broadside]]; they were provided with a total of eighteen torpedoes.&lt;ref name=taras39/&gt;&lt;ref name=m2/&gt;

===Fire control===
The fore and aft main gun turrets were given a {{convert|6|m|ftin|adj=on|sp=us}} [[rangefinder]], and there was another {{convert|5|m|ftin|adj=on}} unit on top of the conning tower.&lt;ref name=m2/&gt; These would provide data for the Geisler [[Fire-control system#Naval fire control|central artillery post]] computer, which would then transmit commands to the gun crew.&lt;ref&gt;Friedman, pp. 273–75&lt;/ref&gt; The mechanical fire-control computer would have been either a [[Arthur Pollen|Pollen Argo]] range clock, which had been bought in 1913, or a domestically designed Erikson system.&lt;ref name=m2/&gt;

===Protection===
The trials with the ''Chesma'' greatly affected the armour protection design of the ''Borodino''-class ships. The [[Krupp cemented armour|Krupp cemented-armour]] plates were sized to match the frames to provide support for their joints, and they were locked together with mortise-and-tenon joints to better distribute the shock of a shell's impact. The {{convert|237.5|mm|in}} [[Belt armour|waterline belt]] covered the middle {{convert|151.2|m|ftin}} of the ship. It had a total height of {{convert|5.015|m|ftin}}, {{convert|3.375|m|ftin}} of which was above the design [[waterline]] and {{convert|1.64|m|ftin}} below. It was backed by 75&amp;nbsp;millimeters of wood to make a better fit between the hull and the armour. The remaining portion of the waterline was protected by {{convert|125|mm|in|adj=on}} plates backed by {{convert|50|mm}} of wood. The upper belt was {{convert|100|mm}} thick and had a height of {{convert|2.89|m}}. It thinned to 75&amp;nbsp;mm forward of the casemates all the way to the bow. The rear portion of the forecastle deck was protected by an upward extension of the upper belt in the area of the forward [[barbette]]s and the upper casemates. The upper casemates themselves were protected from axial fire by 100&amp;nbsp;mm transverse bulkheads. Behind the side armour was an inboard longitudinal splinter bulkhead that was {{convert|50|mm}} thick between the middle and lower decks. This decreased to {{convert|25|mm}} between the middle and upper decks. The bulkhead sloped away from the edge of the lower deck to the lower edge of the armour belt with a total thickness of 75&amp;nbsp;mm. The slope was one 50&amp;nbsp;mm plate of [[Krupp armour|Krupp non-cemented armour]] (KNC) on a 25&amp;nbsp;mm nickel-steel plate. The forward end of the [[armoured citadel]] was protected separately and the transverse bulkhead was therefore only 75&amp;nbsp;mm thick. The rear bulkhead had no other protection and was {{convert|300|mm|1}} thick between the middle and lower decks, decreasing to 75&amp;nbsp;mm at the level of the armour belt.&lt;ref name=m2/&gt;

The main gun turrets had sides 300&amp;nbsp;mm thick with 150&amp;nbsp;mm roofs. The gun ports were protected by 50&amp;nbsp;mm plates, and 25&amp;nbsp;mm bulkheads separated each gun. The barbettes were {{convert|247.5|mm|abbr=on}} thick, decreasing to {{convert|147.5|mm}} when behind other armour. They were shaped like truncated cones which matched the trajectories of descending shells and thus lessened their protective value. The conning tower was {{convert|400|mm|1}} thick, reduced to 300&amp;nbsp;mm below the upper deck. The [[funnel (ship)|funnel]] uptakes were protected by 50&amp;nbsp;mm of armour. The upper [[deck (ship)|deck]] was {{convert|37.5|mm}} thick while the middle deck consisted of {{convert|40|mm|adj=on}} plates of KNC on 25&amp;nbsp;mm of nickel-steel over the armoured citadel. Underwater protection was minimal: there was only a {{convert|10|mm|adj=on}} watertight bulkhead behind the upward extension of the double bottom, and even this was thinner as the hull narrowed towards the end turrets.&lt;ref&gt;McLaughlin, pp. 252–53&lt;/ref&gt;

==Construction==
All four ships were officially laid down on 19 December 1912, but work did not begin until March–April 1913. After a progress review on 4 June 1914, [[Ship naming and launching|launching]]{{refn|A ship's hull needs to be merely watertight and strong enough to hold together before it can be launched. Generally the major structural work is completed before launching, but the machinery and main armament may or may not be installed before the ship is launched.|group=Note}} of the first pair of ships was delayed until October 1914. When World War I began, the hull of ''Izmail'', the most advanced ship, was judged 43&amp;nbsp;percent complete, with the others lagging considerably behind. The war caused more delays, including problems obtaining imported components, and the ships were competing for scarce resources with other production deemed necessary for the war. Three of the four ships were launched in 1915, but it was clear that Russian industry would not be able to complete them during the war, mostly because the turrets were seriously delayed. They were reclassified as 2nd rank projects by the Main Administration of Shipbuilding in 1916.&lt;ref&gt;McLaughlin, pp. 248–49&lt;/ref&gt;

A number of plans were made for the post-war completion of the ships, including modifying the turrets to load at a fixed angle of +4° to reduce the weight and complexity of the loading equipment. Another intended change was to lengthen the funnels by {{convert|2|m}} to minimise smoke interference with the [[bridge (nautical)|bridge]], as this had been noted as a problem on the ''Gangut''-class dreadnoughts. There were suggestions to improve the machinery with geared turbines, [[Turbo-electric transmission|turbo-electric drive]], or [[Hermann Föttinger|Föttinger's]] hydraulic transmission, but these were more theoretical than practical.&lt;ref name=m9&gt;McLaughlin, p. 249&lt;/ref&gt;

After the [[February Revolution]], the condition of the ships was assessed on 28 April 1917. The ship that was furthest along was the ''Ismail'': her hull, engines, and boilers were around 65% complete, and her armour was 36% complete. Her turrets, however, were not expected to be completed until 1919. The Congress of Shipyard Workers decided to continue work on the ''Izmail'' in mid-1917, but only to provide jobs. The [[Russian Provisional Government|Provisional Government]] halted all work on ''Borodino'', ''Kinburn'', and ''Navarin'' on 24 October 1917, and the Soviet Supreme Naval College ordered work on ''Izmail'' halted on 14 December 1917.&lt;ref name=m9/&gt;

After the end of the [[Russian Civil War]] the victorious [[Bolshevik]]s considered finishing ''Izmail'', and possibly ''Borodino'', to their original design. It would have taken at least two years to build all of ''Izmail''{{'}}s turrets, even if enough guns had been available. Ten had been delivered by [[Vickers Limited|Vickers]] before the Revolution and one gun had been completed domestically in 1912, but the prospects that more guns could be purchased from Vickers or that the Soviets could make more were not promising, given the state of their heavy industry in the wake of the Civil War. Another problem was the complicated electrical system; it could not be completed under current conditions, and at least twenty months would be required to replace it with a simpler system.&lt;ref&gt;McLaughlin, p. 332&lt;/ref&gt;

The Soviets considered finishing ''Kinburn'' and ''Navarin'' to a modified design that featured {{convert|16|in|adj=on}} guns; a two-gun turret weighed slightly less than a triple 14-inch gun turret. Four proposals were made with various changes to the turrets' armour scheme, but none were accepted, not least because the prospects of actually acquiring such guns were minimal. Domestic industry was not capable of building such large guns and they were not able to purchase the guns from any foreign company. Other ideas were examined for the three less complete ships. These included converting the hulls to cargo ships, passenger liners, or {{convert|22000|LT|t|adj=on}} oil [[barge]]s, but most of the ideas were rejected as the hulls were thought to be too large and unwieldy for the proposed alternative uses. None of the proposals was accepted, and all three of the less complete ships were sold to a German company for [[ship breaking|scrap]] on 21 August 1923 to raise much-needed cash for the government.&lt;ref name=taras39/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McLaughlin, pp. 332–35&lt;/ref&gt;

The Operational Administration of the [[Soviet Navy]] worked out the requirements in May 1925 for a conversion that would have made ''Izmail'' into an [[aircraft carrier]] with a top speed of {{convert|27|kn}} and a capacity of fifty aircraft. She would have been armed with eight {{convert|183|mm|adj=on}} guns and her armour reduced to a maximum of {{convert|76|mm}}. This proposal was approved by [[Alexey Rykov]], Chairman of the [[Council of the People's Commissars]] on 6 July 1925. The plan was cancelled on 16 March 1926 after the [[Red Army]] managed to gain control of a commission appointed to review the needs of the Navy, and the Army was strongly opposed to spending additional money on naval projects.&lt;ref&gt;McLaughlin, pp. 335–36&lt;/ref&gt; She was scrapped beginning in 1931 in Leningrad.&lt;ref name=taras39/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Breyer, p. 114&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Watts, p. 66&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ships==
The ships were named after battles fought by the Russian Empire:
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! rowspan=2 align=&quot;center&quot; | Name
! rowspan=2 align=&quot;center&quot; | Namesake&lt;ref&gt;Silverstone, pp. 373, 377, 379&lt;/ref&gt;
! rowspan=2 align=&quot;center&quot; | Builder&lt;ref name=taras39/&gt;
! rowspan=2 align=&quot;center&quot; | Laid down&lt;ref name=m43&gt;McLaughlin, p. 243&lt;/ref&gt;
! rowspan=2 align=&quot;center&quot; | Launched&lt;ref name=m43/&gt;
! rowspan=2 align=&quot;center&quot; | Fate
! colspan=&quot;4&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; | Status on 28 April 1917&lt;ref name=&quot;m9&quot;/&gt;
|-
! align=&quot;center&quot; | Hull
! align=&quot;center&quot; | Armour  	
! align=&quot;center&quot; | Engines  	
! align=&quot;center&quot; | Boilers
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | ''Izmail'' (Измаил)  	  	  	 	  	 	  	
| align=&quot;center&quot; | [[Siege of Izmail]]
| align=&quot;center&quot; | Baltic
| align=&quot;center&quot; rowspan=4 | 19 December 1912
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 22 June 1915
| align=&quot;center&quot; | scrapped 1931&lt;ref name=taras39/&gt;
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 65%
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 36%
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 66%
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 66%
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | ''Borodino'' (Бородино)  	  	  	 	  	 	  	
| align=&quot;center&quot; | [[Battle of Borodino]]
| align=&quot;center&quot; | Admiralty
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 31 July 1915
| align=&quot;center&quot;  rowspan=3| sold for scrap 21 August 1923&lt;ref&gt;McLaughlin, pp. 335-36&lt;/ref&gt;
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 57%
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 13%
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 40%
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 38.4%
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | ''Kinburn'' (Кинбурн) 	  	  	 	  	 	  	
| align=&quot;center&quot; | [[Battle of Kinburn (1787)|Battle of Kinburn]]
| align=&quot;center&quot; | Baltic
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 30 October 1915
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 52%
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 5%
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 22%
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 7.2%
|-
| align=&quot;center&quot; | ''Navarin'' (Наварин)  	  	  	 	  	 	  	
| align=&quot;center&quot; | [[Battle of Navarino]]
| align=&quot;center&quot; | Admiralty
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 9 November 1916
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 50%
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 2%
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 26.5%
| align=&quot;center&quot; | 12.5%
|}

==Notes==
{{Portal|Battleships}}
{{Reflist|group=Note}}

==References==
{{Research help|Mil}}
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Bibliography==
* {{cite book|last=Breyer|first=Siegfried|title=Soviet Warship Development|publisher=Conway Maritime Press|location=London|year=1992|volume=Volume I: 1917–1937|isbn=0-85177-604-3}}
* {{cite book|last=Friedman|first=Norman|title=Naval Firepower: Battleship Guns and Gunnery in the Dreadnought Era|publisher=Naval Institute Press|location=Annapolis, Maryland|year=2008|isbn=978-1-59114-555-4}}
* {{cite book |editor1-last=Gardiner|editor1-first=Robert|editor2-last=Gray|editor2-first=Randal|title=Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships: 1906–1922|year=1984|location=Annapolis, Maryland|publisher=Naval Institute Press|isbn=0-85177-245-5}}
* {{cite book|last=McLaughlin|first=Stephen|title=Russian &amp; Soviet Battleships|publisher=Naval Institute Press|location=Annapolis, Maryland|year=2003|isbn=1-55750-481-4}}
*{{cite book|last=Silverstone|first=Paul H.|title=Directory of the World's Capital Ships|year=1984|publisher=Hippocrene Books|location=New York|isbn=0-88254-979-0}}
* {{cite book
  | last = Taras
  | first = Alexander
  | year = 2000
  | script-title=ru:Корабли Российского императорского флота 1892–1917 гг.
  | trans_title = Ships of the Imperial Russian Navy 1892–1917
  | location = Minsk
  | publisher = Kharvest
  | series = Library of Military History
  | language = Russian
  | isbn = 985-433-888-6
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Watts
  | first = Anthony
  | year = 1990
  | title = The Imperial Russian Navy
  | publisher = Arms and Armour Press
  | location = London
  | isbn = 0-85368-912-1
  }}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Izmail class battlecruiser}}
*[http://www.battleships-cruisers.co.uk/borodino_class1.htm#Borodino Battleships-cruisers site]
*[http://ship.bsu.by/main.asp?id=101808 Russian navy site] {{ru icon}}

{{Borodino class battlecruiser}}
{{WWIRussianShips}}
{{good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Borodino Class Battlecruiser}}
[[Category:Battlecruiser classes]]
[[Category:Borodino-class battlecruisers| ]]
[[Category:World War I battlecruisers of Russia| ]]
[[Category:Proposed ships]]</text>
      <sha1>01nvatp3xulpcgcb88xw0pi6fab4izd</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
