<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>British Army during World War I</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>19466336</id>
    <revision>
      <id>751147609</id>
      <parentid>748544550</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-23T17:54:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>217.123.235.137</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Organization */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="141823">{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2014}}
{{EngvarB|date=April 2014}}
{{British Army}}
{{Timeline of the British Army}}
The '''British Army during World War I''' fought the largest and most costly war in its [[History of the British Army|long history]].&lt;ref&gt;Bourne (2001), pp. 118–119&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike the [[French Army in World War I|French]] and [[German Army (German Empire)|German Armies]], the [[British Army]] was made up exclusively of volunteers—as opposed to [[conscription|conscripts]]—at the beginning of the conflict.&lt;ref&gt;Chappell (2003), p. 4&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, the British Army was considerably smaller than its French and German counterparts.&lt;ref&gt;Chappell (2003), p. 3&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Wiltshire Regiment Thiepval 7 August 1916.jpg|thumb|right|Men of the [[Wiltshire Regiment]] attacking near [[Thiepval]], 7 August 1916, during the [[Battle of the Somme]]. Photo taken by [[Ernest Brooks (photographer)|Ernest Brooks]].]]

During [[World War I]], there were three distinct British Armies. The &quot;first&quot; army was the small volunteer force of 40 soldiers, over half of which were posted overseas to garrison the [[British Empire]]. This total included the [[Standing army|Regular Army]] and reservists in the [[Territorial Force]] (TF). Together, they formed the [[British Expeditionary Force (World War I)|British Expeditionary Force]] (BEF), which was formed for service in France and became known as the [[Old Contemptibles]]. The 'second' army was [[Kitchener's Army]], formed from the volunteers in 1914–1915 destined to go into action at the [[Battle of the Somme]]. The 'third' was formed after the introduction of [[conscription in the United Kingdom|conscription]] in January 1916, and by the end of 1918, the British Army had reached its maximum strength of 4,000,000 men and could field over 70 [[Division (military)|division]]s. The vast majority of the British Army fought in the main [[Theater (warfare)|theatre of war]] on the [[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]] in [[France]] and [[Belgium]] against the [[German Empire]]. Some units were engaged in Italy and [[Salonika]] against [[Austria-Hungary]] and the [[Bulgarian Army]], while other units fought in the [[Middle Eastern theatre of World War I|Middle East]], Africa and [[Mesopotamian campaign|Mesopotamia]]—mainly against the [[Ottoman Empire]]—and one battalion fought alongside the [[Imperial Japanese Army|Japanese Army]] in [[China]] during the [[Siege of Tsingtao]].

The war also posed problems for the army commanders, given that, prior to 1914, the largest formation any serving General in the BEF had commanded on operations was a division. The expansion of the British Army saw some officers promoted from [[brigade]] to [[corps]] commander in less than a year. Army commanders also had to cope with the new tactics and weapons that were developed. With the move from manoeuvre to [[trench warfare]], both the infantry and the artillery had to learn how to work together. During an offensive, and when in defence, they learned how to [[combined arms|combine forces]] to defend the front line. Later in the war, when the [[Machine Gun Corps]] and the [[Royal Tank Regiment|Tank Corps]] were added to the [[order of battle]], they were also included in the new tactical doctrine.

The men at the front had to struggle with supply problems&amp;ndash;there was a shortage of food; and disease was rife in the damp, rat-infested conditions. Along with enemy action, many soldiers had to contend with new diseases: [[trench foot]], [[trench fever]] and [[nephritis|trench nephritis]]. When the [[Armistice of 11 November 1918|war ended in November 1918]], British Army casualties, as the result of enemy action and disease, were recorded as 673,375 [[Killed in action|killed]] and [[Missing in action|missing]], with another 1,643,469 [[Wounded in action|wounded]]. The rush to demobilise at the end of the conflict substantially decreased the strength of the British Army, from its peak strength of 4,000,000 men in 1918 to 370,000 men by 1920.

==Organization==
The British Army during World War I could trace its organisation to the increasing demands of imperial expansion. The framework was the voluntary system of recruitment and the [[regimental]] system, which had been defined by the [[Cardwell Reforms|Cardwell]] and [[Childers Reforms]] of the late 19th century. The British Army had been prepared and primarily called upon for [[British Empire|Empire]] matters and the ensuing [[colonial wars]].&lt;ref name=ch212/&gt; In the last years of the 19th century, the Army was involved in a major conflict, the [[Second Boer War]] (1899–1902), which highlighted shortcomings in its tactics, leadership and administration. The 1904 [[Esher Report]] recommended radical reform, such as the creation of an Army Council, a General Staff, the abolition of the office of Commander-in-Chief of the Forces, and the creation of a [[Chief of the General Staff (United Kingdom)|Chief of the General Staff]].&lt;ref&gt;Cassidy (2006), p. 78&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Haldane Reforms]] of 1907 formally created an [[Expeditionary warfare|Expeditionary Force]] of seven [[Division (military)|division]]s (one cavalry, six infantry), reorganised the volunteers into a new [[Territorial Force]] of fourteen [[cavalry]] [[brigade]]s and fourteen [[infantry]] divisions, and changed the old [[Militia (United Kingdom)|militia]] into the Special Reserve to reinforce the expeditionary force.&lt;ref&gt;Cassidy (2006), p. 79&lt;/ref&gt;

At the outbreak of the war in August 1914, the British regular army was a small professional force. It consisted of 247,432 regular troops organised in four regiments of [[Brigade of Guards|Guards]] ([[Grenadier Guards|Grenadier]], with 3 [[Battalion]]s; [[Coldstream Guards|Coldstream]], with 3 Battalions; [[Scots Guards|Scots]], with 2 Battalions; [[Irish Guards|Irish]] with 1 Battalion),&lt;ref name= &quot;MarkC&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last1=Conrad|first1=Mark|title=THE BRITISH ARMY, 1914|url=http://marksrussianmilitaryhistory.info/BRIT14.html|website=THE BRITISH ARMY, 1914|accessdate=7 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; 68 regiments of the line and the Rifle Brigade (despite its name, this was an infantry regiment)&lt;!--Chris Baker's 'The long, long trail' site includes the Rifle Brigade in its list of 69 Line Infantry Regiments, but it was taken out of the line in 1816 as an honour. Mark Conrad's site mentions 73 infantry regiments, including the 4 of Guards and the Rifle Brigade--&gt;, 31 cavalry regiments, artillery and other support arms.&lt;ref name= tr504&gt;Tucker &amp; Roberts (2005), p. 504&lt;/ref&gt; Most of the line infantry regiments had two regular battalions, one of which served at home and provided drafts and replacements to the other which was stationed overseas, while also being prepared to be part of the Expeditionary Force - the [[Royal Fusiliers]], [[Worcestershire Regiment]], [[Middlesex Regiment]], [[King's Royal Rifle Corps]] and the [[Rifle Brigade (Prince Consort's Own)]] had four regular battalions, two of which served overseas. Almost half of the regular army (74 of the 157 infantry battalions and 12 of the 31 cavalry regiments), was stationed overseas in garrisons throughout the British Empire.&lt;ref name=tr504/&gt; The [[Royal Flying Corps]] was part of the British Army until 1918. At the outbreak of the war, it consisted of 84 aircraft.&lt;ref name=tr504/&gt;

The regular army was supported by the [[Territorial Force]], and by reservists. In August 1914, there were three forms of reserves. The Army Reserve of retired soldiers was 145,350 strong. They were paid 3&amp;nbsp;[[Shilling]]s and 6&amp;nbsp;pence a week (17.5&amp;nbsp;[[pence]]) worth about £70 per week in 2013 terms, and had to attend 12 training days per year.&lt;ref name=reserve&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=28 May 2009|title=Reserves and reservists|first=Chris|last=Baker|url=http://www.1914-1918.net/reserve.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Special Reserve had another 64,000 men and was a form of part-time soldiering, similar to the Territorial Force. A Special Reservist had an initial six months full-time training and was paid the same as a regular soldier during this period; they had three or four weeks training per year thereafter.&lt;ref name=reserve/&gt; The National Reserve had some 215,000 men, who were on a register that was maintained by Territorial Force County Associations; these men had military experience, but no other reserve obligation.&lt;ref name=tr504/&gt;&lt;ref name=reserve/&gt;

The regulars and reserves—at least on paper—totalled a mobilised force of almost 700,000 men, although only 150,000 men were immediately available to be formed into the [[British Expeditionary Force (World War I)|British Expeditionary Force]] (BEF) that was sent to the continent. This consisted of six infantry divisions and one of cavalry.&lt;ref name=tr504/&gt; By contrast, the [[French Army in World War I|French Army]] in 1914 mobilised 1,650,000 troops and 62 infantry divisions, while the [[German Army (German Empire)|German Army]] mobilised 1,850,000 troops and 87 infantry divisions.&lt;ref&gt;Addington (1984), p. 92&lt;/ref&gt;

Britain, therefore, began the war with six regular and 14 reserve infantry divisions. During the war, a further six regular, 14 Territorial, 36 [[Kitchener's Army]] and six other divisions, including the [[63rd (Royal Naval) Division|Naval Division]] from the [[Royal Navy]] were formed.&lt;ref&gt;Tucker &amp; Roberts (2005), p. 505&lt;/ref&gt;

{{see also|List of British divisions in World War I}}

In 1914, each British infantry division consisted of three infantry brigades, each of four battalions, with two machine guns per battalion, (24 in the division). They also had three field [[artillery]] brigades with fifty-four [[Ordnance QF 18 pounder|18-pounder gun]]s, one field [[howitzer]] brigade with eighteen [[QF 4.5 inch Howitzer|{{convert|4.5|in|mm|abbr=on}} howitzer]]s, one heavy artillery battery with four [[BL 60 pounder gun|60-pounder gun]]s, two [[Royal Engineers|engineer]] field companies, one [[Royal Signals|royal engineer signals]] company&lt;!--Royal Corps of Signals was formed in 1920 --&gt;, one cavalry squadron, one cyclist company, three field ambulances, four [[Royal Army Service Corps|Army Service Corps]] horse-drawn transport companies and divisional headquarters support detachments.&lt;ref&gt;Tucker &amp; Roberts (2005), p. 810&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=messenger&gt;Messenger (2005), pp. 25–26&lt;/ref&gt;

The single cavalry division assigned to the BEF in 1914 consisted of 15 cavalry regiments in five brigades. They were armed with rifles, unlike their French and German counterparts, who were only armed with the shorter range [[carbine]]. The cavalry division also had a high allocation of artillery compared to foreign cavalry divisions, with 24 [[Ordnance QF 13 pounder|13-pounder gun]]s organised into two brigades and two machine guns for each regiment. When dismounted, the cavalry division was the equivalent of two weakened infantry brigades with less artillery than the infantry division.&lt;ref name=&quot;ba198&quot; /&gt; By 1916, there were five cavalry divisions, each of three brigades, serving in France, the [[1st Cavalry Division (United Kingdom)|1st]], [[2nd Cavalry Division (United Kingdom)|2nd]], [[3rd Cavalry Division (United Kingdom)|3rd]] divisions in the [[Cavalry Corps (United Kingdom)|Cavalry Corps]] and the [[1st Indian Cavalry Division|1st]] and [[2nd Indian Cavalry Division]]s in the [[Indian Cavalry Corps]], each brigade in the Indian cavalry corps contained a British cavalry regiment.&lt;ref&gt;Gudmundsson &amp; Anderson (2007), p.29&lt;/ref&gt;

Over the course of the war, the composition of the infantry division gradually changed, and there was an increased emphasis on providing the infantry divisions with [[Organic (military)|organic fire support]]. By 1918, a British division consisted of three infantry brigades, each of three battalions. Each of these battalions had 36 [[Lewis machine gun]]s, making a total of 324 such weapons in the division. Additionally, there was a divisional machine gun battalion, equipped with 64 [[Vickers machine gun]]s in four companies of 16 guns. Each brigade in the division also had a mortar battery with eight [[Stokes Mortar]]s.&lt;ref name=tr504/&gt; The artillery also changed the composition of its batteries. At the start of the war, there were three batteries with six guns per brigade; they then moved to four batteries with four guns per brigade, and finally in 1917, to four batteries with six guns per brigade to economise on battery commanders.&lt;ref name=messenger/&gt; In this way, the army would change drastically over the course of the war, reacting to the various developments, from the mobile war fought in the opening weeks to the static trench warfare of 1916 and 1917. The cavalry of the BEF represented 9.28% of the army; by July 1918, it would only represent 1.65%. The infantry would decrease from 64.64% in 1914 to 51.25% of the army in 1918, while the Royal Engineers would increase from 5.91% to 11.24% in 1918.&lt;ref name=ch212&gt;Chandler (2003), p. 212&lt;/ref&gt;

==British Expeditionary Force==
{{main article|British Expeditionary Force (World War I)|British Expeditionary Force order of battle (1914)|British infantry brigades of the First World War|British cavalry during the First World War}}
[[File:British recruits August 1914 Q53234.jpg|thumb|August 1914: London volunteers await their pay at [[St. Martin-in-the-Fields]]]]

Under the terms of the [[Entente Cordiale]], the British Army's role in a European war was to embark soldiers of the British Expeditionary Force (BEF), which consisted of six infantry divisions and five cavalry brigades that were arranged into two [[Army corps]]: [[I Corps (United Kingdom)|I Corps]], under the command of [[Douglas Haig]], and [[II Corps (United Kingdom)|II Corps]], under the command of [[Horace Smith-Dorrien]].&lt;ref name=ch211&gt;Chandler (2003), p. 211&lt;/ref&gt; At the outset of the conflict, the [[British Indian Army]] was called upon for assistance; in August 1914, 20 percent of the 9,610 British officers initially sent to France were from the Indian army, while 16 percent of the 76,450 [[Other ranks (UK)|other ranks]] came from the British Indian Army.&lt;ref name=ch211/&gt;

German Emperor [[Wilhelm II of Germany|Kaiser Wilhelm]]—who was famously dismissive of the BEF—issued an order on 19 August 1914 to &quot;exterminate...the treacherous English and walk over [[John French, 1st Earl of Ypres|General French's]] contemptible little army&quot;. Hence, in later years, the survivors of the regular army dubbed themselves &quot;The Old Contemptibles&quot;. By the end of 1914 (after the battles of [[Battle of Mons|Mons]], [[Battle of Le Cateau|Le Cateau]], [[First Battle of the Aisne|the Aisne]] and [[First Battle of Ypres|Ypres]]), the old regular British Army had been virtually wiped out; although it managed to stop the German advance.&lt;ref name=ch211/&gt;

In October 1914, the [[7th Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|7th Division]] arrived in France, forming the basis of the [[III Corps (United Kingdom)|British III Corps]]; the cavalry had grown into its own corps of three divisions.&lt;ref name=tr504/&gt; By December 1914, the BEF had expanded, fielding five army corps divided between the [[British 1st Army|First]] and the [[British 2nd Army|Second Armies]].&lt;ref&gt;Chappell (2003), p. 7&lt;/ref&gt; As the Regular Army's strength declined, the numbers were made up— first by the Territorial Force, then by the volunteers of [[Horatio Kitchener, 1st Earl Kitchener|Field Marshal Kitchener's]], [[Kitchener's Army|New Army]].&lt;ref name=tr504/&gt; By the end of August 1914, he had raised six new divisions; by March 1915, the number of divisions had increased to 29.&lt;ref name=tr504/&gt; The Territorial Force was also expanded, raising second and third battalions and forming eight new divisions, which supplemented its peacetime strength of 14 divisions.&lt;ref name=tr504/&gt; The [[British 3rd Army|Third Army]] was formed in July 1915 and with the influx of troops from Kitchener's volunteers and further reorganisation, the [[British 4th Army|Fourth Army]] and the [[Reserve Army (United Kingdom)|Reserve Army]], which became the [[British 5th Army|Fifth Army]] were formed in 1916.&lt;ref name=tr504/&gt;

==Recruitment and conscription==
{{main article|Recruitment to the British Army during World War I}}

In August 1914, 300,000 men had signed up to fight, and another 450,000 had joined-up by the end of September.&lt;ref&gt;Chandler, (2001) p. 11&lt;/ref&gt; Recruitment remained fairly steady through 1914 and early 1915, but it fell dramatically during the later years, especially after the Somme campaign, which resulted in 360,000 casualties.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=6 June 2009|title=Battle of the Somme|publisher=New Zealand History online|url=http://www.nzhistory.net.nz/war/the-battle-of-the-somme/overview}}&lt;/ref&gt; A prominent feature of the early months of volunteering was the formation of [[Pals battalion]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=6 June 2009|title=The Pals Battalions in World War One|publisher=BBC History|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/british/britain_wwone/pals_01.shtml}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many of these pals who had lived and worked together, joined up and trained together and were allocated to the same units. The policy of drawing recruits from amongst the local population ensured that, when the Pals battalions suffered casualties, whole towns, villages, neighbourhoods and communities back in Britain were to suffer disproportionate losses. With the introduction of conscription in January 1916, no further Pals battalions were raised.&lt;ref name=tr504/&gt; [[Conscription in the United Kingdom|Conscription]] for single men was introduced in January 1916. Four months later, in May 1916, it was extended to all men aged 18 to 41.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| accessdate=13 May 2009|title=Britain and World War One, 1901–1918|last=Strachen|first=Hugh Professer |publisher=BBC History|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/british/britain_wwone/overview_britain_ww1_07.shtml}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ''[[Military Service Act (United Kingdom)|Military Service Act March 1916]]'' specified that men from the ages of 18 to 41 were liable to be called up for service in the army, unless they were married (or widowed with children), or served in one of a number of [[reserved occupation]]s, which were usually industrial but which also included clergymen and teachers. This legislation did not apply to Ireland, despite its then status as part of the United Kingdom (but see [[Conscription Crisis of 1918]]). By January 1916, when conscription was introduced, 2.6 million men had volunteered for service, a further 2.3 million were conscripted before the end of the war; by the end of 1918, the army had reached its peak strength of four million men.&lt;ref name=tr504/&gt;

Women also volunteered and served in a non-combatant role; by the end of the war, 80,000 had enlisted.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=2 June 2009|title=Woman combatants|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/british/britain_wwone/women_combatants_01.shtml|publisher=BBC History}}&lt;/ref&gt; They mostly served as nurses in the [[Queen Alexandra's Imperial Military Nursing Service]] (QAIMNS), the [[First Aid Nursing Yeomanry]] (FANY), the [[Voluntary Aid Detachment]] (VAD); and from 1917, in the Army when the [[Queen Mary's Army Auxiliary Corps]] (WAAC), was founded.&lt;ref name=waac&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=3 June 2009|publisher=National Archives|title=Women's Auxiliary Army Corps|url= http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/documentsonline/waac.asp}}&lt;/ref&gt; The WAAC was divided into four sections: cookery; mechanical; clerical and miscellaneous. Most stayed on the Home Front, but around 9,000 served in France.&lt;ref name=waac/&gt;

==Commanders==
[[File:Douglas Haig.jpg|thumb|Field Marshal [[Douglas Haig, 1st Earl Haig]].]]

In 1914, no serving British officer of the [[British Expeditionary Force (World War I)|British Expeditionary Force]] (BEF) had controlled a formation larger than a division on active operations.&lt;ref&gt;Gardner (2003), p. 1&lt;/ref&gt; The first Commander in Chief of the BEF appointed in August 1914 was [[Field Marshal (United Kingdom)|Field Marshal]] [[John French, 1st Earl of Ypres|John French]].&lt;ref name=ps289-290/&gt; His last active command had been the cavalry division in the Second Boer War.&lt;ref name=ps289-290/&gt;

The commander of the [[I Corps (United Kingdom)|British I Corps]] in 1914 was [[Douglas Haig, 1st Earl Haig|Douglas Haig]]. French had remarked in 1912 that Haig would be better suited to a position on the staff than a field command.&lt;ref&gt;Gardner (2003), p. 11&lt;/ref&gt; Like French, Haig was a cavalryman. His last active command had been during the Second Boer War, first as a senior staff officer in the cavalry division, then commanding a brigade-sized group of columns.&lt;ref&gt;Gardner (2003), p. 10&lt;/ref&gt; The first commander of the [[II Corps (United Kingdom)|British II Corps]] was Lieutenant General [[James Grierson]], a noted tactician who died of a heart attack soon after arriving in France.&lt;ref name=LiddellHart33&gt;Liddell Hart (1933), p. 33&lt;/ref&gt; French wished to appoint Lieutenant General [[Herbert Plumer, 1st Viscount Plumer|Herbert Plumer]] in his place, but against French's wishes, Kitchener instead appointed Lieutenant General [[Horace Smith-Dorrien]], who had begun his military career in the [[Zulu War]] in 1879 and was one of only five officers to survive the [[battle of Isandlwana]].&lt;ref&gt;Tucker &amp; Roberts (2005), p. 1096&lt;/ref&gt; He had built a formidable reputation as an infantry commander during the [[Sudan Campaign]] and the Second Boer War.&lt;ref&gt;Gardner (2003), p. 13&lt;/ref&gt; After the Second Boer War, he was responsible for a number of reforms, notably forcing an increase in dismounted training for the cavalry. This was met with hostility by French (as a cavalryman). By 1914, French's dislike for Smith-Dorrien was well known within the army.&lt;ref name=gard14&gt;Gardner (2003), p. 14&lt;/ref&gt;

After the failed offensive at the [[Battle of Loos]] in 1915, French was replaced as commander of the BEF by Haig, who remained in command for the rest of the war. He became most famous for his role as its commander during the [[Battle of the Somme (1916)|battle of the Somme]], the [[battle of Passchendaele]], and the [[Hundred Days Offensive]], the series of victories leading to the German surrender in 1918.&lt;ref name=gg69/&gt; Haig was succeeded in command of the [[British First Army|First Army]] by General [[Charles Carmichael Monro]], who in turn was succeeded by General [[Henry Horne, 1st Baron Horne|Henry Horne]] in September 1916, the only officer with an artillery background to command a British army during the war.&lt;ref&gt;Blaxland (1968), p. 14&lt;/ref&gt;

General Plumer was eventually appointed to command II Corps in December 1914, and succeeded Smith-Dorrien in command of the [[British Second Army|Second Army]] in 1915.&lt;ref name=plumb&gt;Keegan &amp; Wheatcroft (1996), p. 141&lt;/ref&gt; He had commanded a mounted infantry detachment in the Second Boer war, where he started to build his reputation. He held command of the Ypres salient for three years and gained an overwhelming victory over the German Army at the [[Battle of Messines (1917)|battle of Messines]] in 1917. Plumer is generally recognised as one of the most effective of the senior British commanders on the Western Front.&lt;ref name=plumb/&gt;
[[File:BEF commanders and chiefs of staff 1918.jpg|left|thumb|300px|Sir Douglas Haig with his army commanders and their chiefs of staff, November 1918. Front row, left to right: [[Herbert Plumer, 1st Viscount Plumer|Herbert Plumer]], Haig, [[Henry Rawlinson, 1st Baron Rawlinson|Rawlinson]]. Middle row, left to right: [[Julian Byng, 1st Viscount Byng of Vimy|Byng]], [[William Birdwood, 1st Baron Birdwood|Birdwood]], [[Henry Horne, 1st Baron Horne|Horne]]. Back row, left to right: Lawrence, Kavanagh, [[Brudenell White|White]], Percy, [[Louis Vaughan|Vaughan]], [[Archibald Montgomery-Massingberd|Montgomery]], Anderson.]]

In 1914, General [[Edmund Allenby, 1st Viscount Allenby|Edmund Allenby]] was commander of the Cavalry Division and later the Cavalry Corps in the BEF. His leadership was noted during the [[retreat from Mons]] and the [[first battle of Ypres]].&lt;ref&gt;Page (2003), p. 13&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Olson &amp; Shadle (1996), p. 30&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Johnstone (2005), p. 203&lt;/ref&gt; After commanding an infantry corps, he was appointed to command the [[British 3rd Army|Third Army]] on the western front. He had previously served in the Zulu War, the Sudan campaign, and the Second Boer war. In 1917, he was given command of the [[Egyptian Expeditionary Force]], where he oversaw the conquest of [[Palestine (region)|Palestine]] and [[Syria]] in 1917 and 1918.&lt;ref name=jones480&gt;Jones (1986), p. 480&lt;/ref&gt; Allenby replaced [[Archibald Murray]], who had been the Chief of Staff of the British Expeditionary Force in France in 1914.&lt;ref name=LiddellHart33/&gt;

Allenby was replaced as Third Army commander by General [[Julian Byng, 1st Viscount Byng of Vimy|Julian Byng]], who began the war as commander of the [[3rd Cavalry Division (United Kingdom)|3rd Cavalry Division]]. After performing well during the First Battle of Ypres, he succeeded Allenby in command of the Cavalry Corps. He was sent to the [[Dardanelles]] in August 1915, to command the [[IX Corps (United Kingdom)|British IX Corps]]. He planned the highly successful evacuation of 105,000 Allied troops and the majority of the equipment of the [[Mediterranean Expeditionary Force]] (MEF). The withdrawal was successfully completed in January 1916, without the loss of a single man.&lt;ref name= pbg/&gt; Byng had already returned to the western front, where he was given command of the [[Canadian Corps]]. His most notable battle was the [[Battle of Vimy Ridge]] in April 1917, which was carried out by the Canadian Corps with British support.&lt;ref name=pbg/&gt;

General [[Henry Rawlinson, 1st Baron Rawlinson|Henry Rawlinson]] served on Kitchener's staff during the advance on [[Battle of Omdurman|Omdurman]], in 1898, and served with distinction in the Second Boer War, where he earned a reputation as one of the most able British commanders.&lt;ref name= tu166&gt;Tucker (2001), p. 166&lt;/ref&gt; Rawlinson took command of the [[IV Corps (United Kingdom)|British IV Corps]] in 1914 and then command of the [[British Fourth Army|Fourth Army]] in 1916, as the plans for the Allied offensive on the [[Somme (department)|Somme]] were being developed.&lt;ref name=tu166/&gt; During the war, Rawlinson was noted for his willingness to use innovative [[military tactics|tactics]], which he employed during the [[Battle of Amiens (1918)|battle of Amiens]], where he combined attacks by tanks with artillery.&lt;ref&gt;Keegan &amp; Wheatcroft (1996), p. 148&lt;/ref&gt;

General [[Hubert Gough]] commanded a mounted infantry regiment with distinction during the [[relief of Ladysmith]], but his command was destroyed while attacking a larger Boer force in 1901.&lt;ref&gt;Tucker (2001), p. 799&lt;/ref&gt; When he joined the BEF, he was in command of the 3rd Cavalry Brigade, and was promoted from a brigade to a corps command in less than a year. He was given command of the [[2nd Cavalry Division (United Kingdom)|2nd Cavalry Division]] in September 1914, the [[7th Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|7th Division]] in April 1915, and the British I Corps in July 1915. He commanded I Corps during the [[battle of Loos]].&lt;ref name=tr800&gt;Tucker &amp; Roberts (2005), p. 800&lt;/ref&gt; In May 1916, he was appointed commander of the Fifth Army, which suffered heavy losses at the battle of Passchendaele.&lt;ref name=tr800/&gt; The collapse of the Fifth Army was widely viewed as the reason for the German breakthrough in the [[Spring Offensive]], and Gough was dismissed as its commander in March 1918,&lt;ref name=tr800/&gt; being succeeded by General [[William Birdwood, 1st Baron Birdwood|William Birdwood]] for the last months of the war. Birdwood had previously commanded the [[Australian Corps]], an appointment requiring a combination of tact and tactical flair.&lt;ref&gt;Blaxland (1968), p. 143&lt;/ref&gt;

On the [[Macedonian front (World War I)|Macedonian front]], General [[George Milne, 1st Baron Milne|George Milne]] commanded the [[British Salonika Army]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Page210&quot;&gt;Heathcote (1999), p. 210&lt;/ref&gt; and General [[Ian Standish Monteith Hamilton|Ian Hamilton]] commanded the ill-fated MEF during the [[Gallipoli Campaign]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=26 May 2009|title=Sir Ian Hamilton |publisher=Encyclopaedia Britannica|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/253407/Sir-Ian-Hamilton}}&lt;/ref&gt; He had previously seen service in the [[First Boer War]], the Sudan campaign, and the Second Boer War.&lt;ref&gt;Wrigley (2002), p. 204&lt;/ref&gt;

Back in Britain, [[Chief of the Imperial General Staff]] (CIGS), effectively the professional commander of the British Army, was General [[James Wolfe-Murray|James Murray]], who retained that post during the early years of the war.&lt;ref&gt;Moorhead (2002), p. 33&lt;/ref&gt; He was replaced as CIGS in 1916 by General [[William Robertson (British Army officer)|William Robertson]].&lt;ref&gt;Woodhead (1998), p. 6&lt;/ref&gt; A strong supporter of Haig, Robertson was replaced in 1918, by General [[Sir Henry Wilson, 1st Baronet|Henry Hughes Wilson]].&lt;ref&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue=30559|supp=yes| startpage=2867|date=5 March 1918|accessdate=28 January 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Officer selection===
[[File:General Officers of World War I by John Singer Sargent.jpg|thumb|300px|''[[General Officers of World War I]]'', painting by [[John Singer Sargent]] (1922).]]

In August 1914, there were 28,060 officers in the British Army, of which 12,738 were regular officers, the rest were in the reserves.&lt;ref&gt;Sheffield (2000), pp. 29–30&lt;/ref&gt; The number of officers in the army had increased to 164,255 by November 1918. These were survivors among the 247,061 officers who had been granted a commission during the war.&lt;ref&gt;Sheffield (2000), p. 30&lt;/ref&gt;

Most pre-war officers came from families with military connections, the [[gentry]] or the [[peerage]]; a [[Public school (UK)|public school]] education was almost essential.&lt;ref&gt;Sheffield (2000), p. 2&lt;/ref&gt; In 1913, about 2% of regular officers had been promoted from the ranks.&lt;ref&gt;Sheffield (2000), pp. 3–4&lt;/ref&gt; The officer corps, during the war, consisted of regular officers from the peacetime army, officers who had been granted permanent commissions during the war, officers who had been granted temporary commissions for the duration of the war, territorial army officers commissioned during peacetime, officers commissioned from the ranks of the pre-war regular and territorial army and temporary officers commissioned from the ranks for the duration of the war alone.&lt;ref name=shef29&gt;Sheffield (2000), p. 29&lt;/ref&gt;

In September 1914, Lord Kitchener announced that he was looking for volunteers and regular NCOs to provide officers for the expanding army.&lt;ref name=shef29/&gt; Most of the volunteers came from the middle class, with the largest group from commercial and clerical occupations (27%), followed by teachers and students (18%) and professional men (15%).&lt;ref&gt;Sheffield (2000), p. 31&lt;/ref&gt; In March 1915, it was discovered that 12,290 men serving in the ranks had been members of a university or public school [[Officers' Training Corps]] (OTC). Most applied for and were granted commissions, while others who did not apply were also commissioned.&lt;ref&gt;Sheffield (2000), p. 37&lt;/ref&gt; Direct commissioning largely ceased early in 1916, from then most new officers had served in the ranks first, even if in a unit of potential officers.&lt;ref&gt;Holmes 2004, p. 580&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sheffield (2000), p. 38&lt;/ref&gt;

Once a candidate was selected as an officer, promotion could be rapid. A. S. Smeltzer was commissioned as a [[Second Lieutenant]] in 1915, after serving in the Regular Army for 15 years. He rose in rank, and by the Spring of 1917 had been promoted to [[Lieutenant Colonel]] and was commanding officer of the 6th Battalion, [[The Buffs]] (Royal East Kent Regiment).&lt;ref&gt;Connelly (2006), p. 21&lt;/ref&gt;

Along with rapid promotion, the war also noticeably lowered the age of battalion commanding officers. In 1914, they were aged over 50, while the average age for a battalion commanding officer in the BEF between 1917 and 1918 was 28.&lt;ref&gt;Connelly (2006), p. 22&lt;/ref&gt; By this stage, it was official policy that men over 35 were no longer eligible to command battalions.&lt;ref&gt;Blaxland (1968), p. 7&lt;/ref&gt; This trend was reflected amongst the junior officers. [[Anthony Eden]] was the [[Adjutant]] of a battalion when aged 18, and served as the [[Brigade Major]] in the [[66th (2nd East Lancashire) Division|198th Brigade]] while still only aged 20.&lt;ref&gt;Robbins (2005), p. 43&lt;/ref&gt;

The war also provided opportunities for advancement onto the General Staff, especially in the early days, when many former senior officers were recalled from retirement. Some of these were found wanting, due to their advanced age, their unwillingness to serve, or a lack of competence and fitness; most were sent back into retirement before the first year of the war was over, leaving a gap that had to be filled by lower-ranking officers.&lt;ref name=pbg&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=7 June 2009| publisher=Western Front Association|title=Prominent British Generals|url= http://www.westernfrontassociation.com/great-war-on-land/the-generals/947-british-generals-fortunes-the-great-war.html?showall=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Criticism of the quality of staff work in the Crimean War and the Second Boer War had led to sweeping changes under Haldane. The [[Staff College, Camberley]] was greatly expanded and Lord Kitchener established another [[Command and Staff College|staff college at Quetta]] for Indian Army officers in 1904. Nonetheless, when war broke out in August 1914, there were barely enough graduates to staff the BEF. Four-month-long staff courses were introduced, and filled with regimental officers who, upon completing their training, were posted to various headquarters. As a result, staff work was again poor, until training and experience slowly remedied the situation. In 1918, staff officers who had been trained exclusively for static trench warfare were forced to adapt to the demands of semi-open warfare.&lt;ref&gt;Marshall-Cornwall (1977), pp. 9–15&lt;/ref&gt;

During the course of the war, 78 British and [[Dominion]] officers of the rank of [[Brigadier General|Brigadier-General]] and above were killed or died during active service, while another 146 were wounded, gassed, or captured.&lt;ref&gt;Davies and Maddocks (1995), p. 22&lt;/ref&gt;

==Doctrine==
British official historian Brigadier [[James Edward Edmonds]], in 1925, recorded that &quot;The British Army of 1914 was the best trained, best equipped and best organized British Army ever sent to war&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Edmunds (1925), pp. 10–11&lt;/ref&gt; This was in part due to the [[Haldane reforms]], and the Army itself recognising the need for change and training. Training began with individual training in winter, followed by squadron, company or battery training in spring; regimental, battalion and brigade training in summer; and division or inter-divisional exercises and army manoeuvres in late summer and autumn.&lt;ref name=bs47&gt;Beckett &amp; Simpson (1985), p. 47&lt;/ref&gt; The common doctrine of headquarters at all levels was outlined in the ''Field Service Pocket Book'', which Haig had introduced while serving as Director of Staff Studies at the War Office in 1906.

The Second Boer War had alerted the army to the dangers posed by fire zones that were covered by long-range, [[Magazine (firearms)|magazine-fed rifles]].&lt;ref name=bs47/&gt; In the place of volley firing and [[frontal attack]]s, there was a greater emphasis on advancing in extended order, the use of available cover, the use of artillery to support the attack, flank and converging attacks and fire and movement.&lt;ref name=bs47/&gt; The Army expected units to advance as far as possible in a firing line without opening fire, both to conceal their positions and conserve ammunition, then to attack in successive waves, closing with the enemy decisively.&lt;ref name=bs47/&gt;

The cavalry practised reconnaissance and fighting dismounted more regularly, and in January 1910, the decision was made at the General Staff Conference that dismounted cavalry should be taught infantry tactics in attack and defence.&lt;ref&gt;Badsey (2007), P. 227&lt;/ref&gt; They were the only cavalry from a major European power trained for both the mounted cavalry charge and dismounted action, and equipped with the same rifles as the infantry, rather than short-range [[carbines]].&lt;ref name= ba198&gt;Badsey (2008), p. 198&lt;/ref&gt; The cavalry were also issued with [[entrenching tool]]s prior to the outbreak of war, as a result of experience gained during the Second Boer War.&lt;ref name=&quot;ba198&quot;/&gt;

The infantry's marksmanship, and fire and movement techniques, had been inspired by Boer tactics and was established as formal doctrine by Colonel [[Sir Charles Monro, 1st Baronet|Charles Monro]] when he was in charge of the School of Musketry at [[Shorncliffe Army Camp|Shorncliffe]]. In 1914, British rifle fire was so effective that there were some reports to the effect that the Germans believed they were facing huge numbers of machine guns.&lt;ref&gt;Rankin (2008), pp.55–&lt;/ref&gt; The Army concentrated on rifle practice, with days spent on the ranges dedicated to improving marksmanship and obtaining a rate of fire of 15 effective rounds a minute at {{convert|300|yd|m|abbr=on}}; one sergeant set a record of 38 rounds into a {{convert|12|in|mm|abbr=on}} target set at {{convert|300|yd|m|abbr=on}} in 30 seconds.&lt;ref name=js124&gt;Jarymowycz &amp; Starry (2008), p. 124&lt;/ref&gt; In their 1914 skill-at-arms meeting, the 1st Battalion [[Black Watch]] recorded 184 marksmen, 263 first-class shots, 89-second-class shots and four third-class shots, at ranges from {{convert|300|-|600|yd|m|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref&gt;Beckett &amp; Simpson (1985), p. 56&lt;/ref&gt; The infantry also practised squad and section attacks and fire from cover, often without orders from officers or [[Non-commissioned officer|NCOs]], so that soldiers would be able to act on their own initiative.&lt;ref name=bs48&gt;Beckett &amp; Simpson (1985), p. 48&lt;/ref&gt; In the last exercise before the war, it was noted that the ''infantry made wonderful use of ground, advances in short rushes and always at the double and almost invariably fires from a prone position''.&lt;ref name=bs48/&gt;

===Weapons===
{{main article|British Army uniform and equipment in World War I}}

The British Army was armed with the [[Lee–Enfield|Short Magazine Lee–Enfield Mk III]] (SMLE Mk III), which featured a bolt-action and large [[Magazine (firearm)|magazine]] capacity that enabled a trained rifleman to fire 20–30 aimed rounds a minute.&lt;ref name=&quot;js124&quot;/&gt; World War I accounts tell of British troops repelling German attackers, who subsequently reported that they had encountered machine guns, when in fact, it was simply a group of trained riflemen armed with SMLEs.&lt;ref&gt;Skennerton (1988), p. 159&lt;/ref&gt; The heavy [[Vickers machine gun]] proved itself to be the most reliable weapon on the battlefield, with some of its feats of endurance entering military mythology.&lt;ref name=hogg/&gt; One account tells of the action by the 100th Company of the Machine Gun Corps at [[High Wood]] on 24 August 1916. This company had 10 Vickers guns; it was ordered to give sustained covering fire for 12 hours onto a selected area {{convert|2000|yd|m|abbr=on}} away, to prevent German troops forming up there for a counterattack while a British attack was in progress. Two companies of infantry were allocated as ammunition, rations and water carriers for the gunners. Two men worked a belt–filling machine non–stop for 12 hours, keeping up a supply of 250-round belts. They used 100 new barrels and all of the water—including the men's drinking water and the contents of the [[latrine]] buckets—to keep the guns cool. In that 12-hour period, the 10 guns fired just short of one million rounds between them. One team is reported to have fired 120,000. At the close of the operation, it is alleged that every gun was working perfectly and that not one had broken down during the whole period.&lt;ref name=hogg&gt;Hogg (1971), p. 62&lt;/ref&gt;

The lighter [[Lewis gun]] was adopted for land and aircraft use in October 1915.&lt;ref&gt;Skennerton (1988), p. 6&lt;/ref&gt; The Lewis gun had the advantage of being about 80% faster to build than the Vickers, and far more portable.&lt;ref&gt;Hogg (1971), p. 27&lt;/ref&gt; By the end of World War I, over 50,000 Lewis Guns had been produced; they were nearly ubiquitous on the Western Front, outnumbering the Vickers gun by a ratio of about 3:1.&lt;ref&gt;Ford (2005), p. 71&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Stokes Mortar]] was rapidly developed when it became clear that some type of weapon was needed to provide artillery-like fire support to the infantry.&lt;ref name=canfield/&gt; The weapon was fully man-transportable yet also capable of firing reasonably powerful shells at targets beyond the range of rifle grenades.&lt;ref name=canfield&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=28 May 2009|first=Bruce|last= Canfield|title=U.S. Infantry Weapons of the First World War|url=http://www.worldwar1.com/dbc/smortar.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Finally, the [[Mark I (tank)|Mark I tank]]—a British invention—was seen as the solution to the stalemate of trench warfare.&lt;ref name=&quot;bbctank&quot;/&gt; The Mark I had a range of {{convert|23|mi|km|abbr=on}} without refuelling, and a speed of {{convert|3|mph|km/h|abbr=on}}; it first saw service on the Somme in September 1916.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Prof Richard |last=Holmes |accessdate=27 May 2009 |title=Battle of the Somme |publisher=Imperial War Museum |url=http://www.iwm.org.uk/server/show/nav.2184 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090630074159/http://www.iwm.org.uk:80/server/show/nav.2184 |archivedate=30 June 2009 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;bu53&quot;/&gt;

===Infantry tactics===
[[File:British infantry Morval 25 September 1916.jpg|thumb|British infantry advancing in support during the [[battle of Morval]], 25 September 1916, part of the battle of the Somme]]

After the &quot;race to the sea&quot;, [[manoeuvre warfare]] gave way to [[trench warfare]], a development for which the British Army had not prepared. Expecting an offensive mobile war, the Army had not instructed the troops in defensive tactics and had failed to obtain stocks of [[barbed wire]], [[hand grenades]], or [[Mortar (weapon)|trench mortars]].&lt;ref name=gg63&gt;Griffiths &amp; Griess (2003), p. 63&lt;/ref&gt; In the early years of trench warfare, the normal infantry attack formation was based on the battalion, which comprised four [[Company (military unit)|companies]] that were each made up of four [[platoon]]s.&lt;ref name=tu57&gt;Tucker, Matysek Wood &amp; Murphy (2005), p. 357&lt;/ref&gt; The battalion would form 10 waves with {{convert|100|yd|m|abbr=on}} between each, while each company formed two waves of two platoons. The first six waves were the fighting elements from three of the battalions' companies, the seventh contained the battalion headquarters; the remaining company formed the eighth and ninth waves, which were expected to carry equipment forward, the tenth wave contained the stretcher bearers and medics.&lt;ref name=tu57/&gt; The formation was expected to move forward at a rate of {{convert|100|yd|m|abbr=on}} every two minutes, even though each man carried his rifle, [[bayonet]], gas mask, ammunition, two [[hand grenades]], [[wire cutters]], a spade, two empty [[sandbag]]s and [[Flare (pyrotechnic)|flares]].&lt;ref name=tu57/&gt; The carrying platoons, in addition to the above, also carried extra ammunition, barbed wire and construction materials to effect repairs to captured lines and fortifications.&lt;ref name=tu57/&gt;

By 1918, experience had led to a change in tactics; the infantry no longer advanced in rigid lines, but formed a series of flexible waves.&lt;ref name=bu49&gt;Bull (2002), p. 49&lt;/ref&gt; They would move covertly, under the cover of darkness, and occupy shell holes or other cover near the German line. [[Skirmishers]] formed the first wave and followed the creeping barrage into the German front line to hunt out points of resistance. The second or main wave followed in platoons or sections in single file. The third was formed from small groups of reinforcements, the fourth wave was expected to defend the captured territory.&lt;ref name=bu49/&gt; All waves were expected to take advantage of the ground during the advance.&lt;ref name=bu49/&gt; (see below for when operating with tanks)

Each platoon now had a Lewis gun section and a section that specialised in throwing hand-grenades (then known as bombs), each section was compelled to provide two scouts to carry out reconnaissance duties.&lt;ref name=bu50/&gt; Each platoon was expected to provide mutual fire support in the attack they were to advance, without halting; but [[Leapfrogging (infantry)|leap frogging]] was accepted, with the lead platoon taking an objective and the following platoons passing through them and onto the next objective, while the Lewis gunners provided fire support.&lt;ref name=bu50/&gt; Grenades were used for clearing trenches and dugouts, each battalion carried forward two trench mortars to provide fire support.&lt;ref name=bu50&gt;Bull (2002), pp. 50–51&lt;/ref&gt;

===Tank tactics===
The tank was designed to break the deadlock of trench warfare.&lt;ref name=bbctank&gt;{{cite web| accessdate=26 May 2009|title=Mark 1 Tank|publisher=BBC History|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/worldwars/wwone/nonflash_tank.shtml|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071014050900/http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/worldwars/wwone/nonflash_tank.shtml|archivedate=14 October 2007| deadurl=yes}}&lt;/ref&gt; In their first use on the Somme, they were placed under command of the infantry and ordered to attack their given targets in groups or pairs. They were also assigned small groups of troops, who served as an escort while providing close defence against enemy attacks.&lt;ref name=bu53/&gt; Only nine tanks reached the German lines to engage machine gun emplacements and troop concentrations. On the way, 14 broke down or were ditched, another 10 were damaged by enemy fire.&lt;ref name=bu53/&gt;

In 1917, during the [[Battle of Cambrai (1917)|battle of Cambrai]], the [[Royal Tank Regiment|Tank Corps]] adopted new tactics. Three tanks working together would advance in a triangle formation, with the two rear tanks providing cover for an infantry platoon.&lt;ref name=bu53&gt;Bull (2004), p. 53&lt;/ref&gt; The tanks were to create gaps in the barbed wire for the accompanying infantry to pass through, then use their armament to suppress the German strong points.&lt;ref&gt;Tucker &amp; Roberts (2005), p. 251&lt;/ref&gt; The effectiveness of tank–infantry co-operation was demonstrated during the battle, when Major General [[George Montague Harper]] of the [[51st (Highland) Division (World War I)|51st (Highland) Division]] refused to co-operate with the tanks, a decision that compelled them to move forward without any infantry support; the result was the destruction of more than 12 tanks by German artillery sighted behind bunkers.&lt;ref&gt;Tucker &amp; Roberts (2005), p. 252&lt;/ref&gt;

The situation had changed again by 1918, when tank attacks would have one tank every 100 or {{convert|200|yd|m|abbr=on}}, with a tank company of 12–16 tanks per objective. One [[Section (military unit)|section]] of each company would be out in front, with the remainder of the company following behind and each tank providing protection for an infantry platoon, who were instructed to advance, making use of available cover and supported by machine gun fire.&lt;ref name=bu56&gt;Bull (2002), p. 56&lt;/ref&gt; When the tanks came across an enemy strong point, they would engage the defenders, forcing them into shelter and leaving them to the devices of the following infantry.&lt;ref name=bu56/&gt;

===Artillery tactics===
[[File:British 39th Siege Battery RGA Somme 1916.jpg|left|thumb|[[BL 8 inch Howitzer Mk 1 - 5|{{convert|8|in|mm|abbr=on|0}} howitzer]]s of the 39th Siege Battery, [[Royal Garrison Artillery]] conducting a shoot in the Fricourt-Mametz valley, August 1916, during the battle of the Somme.]]

Prior to the war, the artillery worked independently and was taught to support the infantry to ensure a successful attack.&lt;ref name=bs47/&gt; In 1914, the heaviest artillery gun was the 60-pounder, four in each heavy battery. The [[Royal Horse Artillery]] employed the 13-pounder, while the [[Royal Field Artillery]] used the 18-pounder gun. By 1918, the situation had changed; the artillery were the dominant force on the battlefield. Between 1914 and 1918, the Royal Field Artillery had increased from 45 field brigades to 173 field brigades,&lt;ref&gt;Gudmundsson (2005), p. 55&lt;/ref&gt; while the heavy and siege artillery of the [[Royal Garrison Artillery]] had increased from 32 heavy and six siege batteries to 117 heavy and 401 siege batteries.&lt;ref&gt;Clark &amp; Delf (2004), p. 7&lt;/ref&gt;

With this increase in the number of batteries of heavier guns, the armies needed to find a more efficient method of moving the heavier guns around. (It was proving difficult to find the number of [[draught horse]]s required.) The [[War office]] ordered over 1,000 [[Holt tractor|Holts caterpillar tractors]], which transformed the mobility of the siege artillery.&lt;ref&gt;Clark &amp; Delf (2004), p. 8&lt;/ref&gt; The army also mounted a variety of surplus naval guns on various railway platforms to provide mobile long-range heavy artillery on the Western Front.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first= Chris|last=Baker|title=The Siege Batteries of the Royal Garrison Artillery|accessdate=11 June 2009| url=http://www.1914-1918.net/siege-battery-index.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Until 1914, artillery generally fired over [[open sights]] at visible targets, the largest unit accustomed to firing at a single target was the artillery regiment or brigade.&lt;ref name=h13/&gt; One innovation brought about by the adoption of trench warfare was the [[Barrage (artillery)|barrage]]—a term first used in the [[battle of Neuve Chapelle]] in 1915.&lt;ref name=h13&gt;Hogg (1971), p. 13&lt;/ref&gt; Trench warfare had created the need for [[indirect fire]], with the use of observers, more sophisticated artillery fire plans, and an increasingly scientific approach to gunnery, where artillerymen had to use increasingly complicated calculations to lay the guns. Individual guns were aimed so that their fall of shot was coordinated with others to form a pattern; in the case of a barrage, the pattern was a line.&lt;ref name=h13/&gt;

The [[creeping barrage]] was a barrage that lifted in small increments, perhaps {{convert|50|yd}}, so that it moved forward slowly, keeping pace with the infantry,&lt;ref name=h2526&gt;Hogg (1971), pp. 25–26&lt;/ref&gt; who were trained to follow close behind the moving wall of their own fire, often as close as {{convert|55|yd|m|abbr=on}}; infantry commanders were encouraged to keep their troops as close to the barrage as possible, even at the risk of casualties from [[friendly fire]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Tucker 2001, p. 356&quot;&gt;Tucker (2001), p. 356&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hogg (1971), p. 21&lt;/ref&gt; A creeping barrage could maintain the element of surprise, with guns opening fire only shortly before the assault troops moved off. It was useful when enemy positions had not been thoroughly reconnoitred, as it did not depend on identifying individual targets in advance.&lt;ref name=murphy&gt;{{cite web|last= Murphy|first=W E|title=2nd New Zealand Divisional Artillery|publisher=New Zealand Historical Publications Branch, Wellington|year=1966|page=403|url=http://www.nzetc.org/tm/scholarly/tei-WH2Arti-c12-1.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; The idea behind the creeping barrage was that the infantry should reach the enemy positions before the defenders had time to recover, emerge from shelters, and man their positions.&lt;ref name=murphy/&gt; On the first day of the [[battle of the Somme]], the barrage outpaced the infantry, allowing the defenders to recover and emerge from their [[Dugout (shelter)|dugout]]s, with disastrous results for the attackers.&lt;ref name=h26&gt;Hogg (1971), p. 26&lt;/ref&gt; The creeping barrage demonstrated its effectiveness a year later, in 1917, during the [[Battle of Arras (1917)|battle of Arras]].&lt;ref&gt;Nicholls (2005), pp. 53–54&lt;/ref&gt; A weakness of the creeping barrage was that the infantry was subordinated to the artillery schedule, while the infantry commanders had less control over the tactical situation and were therefore in danger of forgetting how to manoeuvre their troops around the battlefield.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tucker 2001, p. 356&quot;/&gt; The importance of the barrage was such that traditional infantry tactics, including a reliance on the infantry's own firepower to support its movement forward, was sometimes forgotten.&lt;ref&gt;Griffith (1996), p. 67&lt;/ref&gt;

Once the infantry had reached the German trenches, the artillery shifted from the creeping barrage to the [[Box barrage#Standing and box barrages|standing barrage]], a static barrage that would protect the infantry from counter-attack while they consolidated the position. A variant was the [[Box barrage#Standing and box barrages|box barrage]], in which three or four barrages formed a box—or more often three sides of a box—around a position to isolate and prevent reinforcements being brought up into the front line. This was normally used to protect [[Trench raiding|trench raids]],&lt;ref&gt;Connelly (2006), p. 85&lt;/ref&gt; although it could also be used offensively against a German unit. Another type of barrage was the [[SOS]] barrage, fired in response to a German counterattack. An SOS barrage could be brought down by firing a [[Flare (pyrotechnic)|flare]] signal of a pre arranged colour, as a German barrage tended to cut the telephone lines. A pre-registered barrage would then descend on No Man's Land.&lt;ref&gt;Griffith (1996), pp. 41–44&lt;/ref&gt;

With the introduction of the tank the artillery was no longer required to aid the infantry by destroying obstacles and machine gun positions. Instead, the artillery assisted by neutralising the German artillery with [[Counter battery fire]].&lt;ref&gt;Bailey (1989), p. 142&lt;/ref&gt; British Army researchers under Lieutenant [[William Lawrence Bragg]] developed [[sound ranging]], a method of determining the location of hostile artillery from the sound of its guns firing.&lt;ref&gt;Bragg (1971), pp. 31–40&lt;/ref&gt; A Counter Battery Staff Officer (CBSO) was appointed at each corps to co-ordinate the counter battery effort, collating reports from sound ranging and Royal Flying Corps observers.&lt;ref&gt;Griffith (1996), pp. 152–153&lt;/ref&gt; By the end of the war, it was realised that the important effect of the barrage was to demoralise and suppress the enemy, rather than physical destruction; a short, intense bombardment immediately followed by an infantry assault was more effective than the weeks of grinding bombardment used in 1916.&lt;ref name=h26/&gt;

===Communications===
The [[Royal Engineers]] Signal Service, formed in 1912, was given responsibility for communications that included signal [[Despatch rider|dispatch]], [[telegraph]], telephone and later [[wireless]] communications, from army headquarters to brigade and down to battery level for the artillery.&lt;ref name=sig/&gt; For most of the war, the Army's primary methods of communication were signal dispatch (employing runners, messengers on horseback, dogs, and [[carrier pigeon]]s), visual signalling, telegraph, and telephone.&lt;ref name=sig/&gt; At the start of the war, the Army had a small number of wireless sets, which in addition to being heavy and unreliable, operated on [[longwave]]. In 1915, trench wireless sets were introduced, but the transmissions were easily intercepted by the listening Germans.&lt;ref name=sig/&gt;

Civilian telephones were used at the outset of the war, but they were found to be unreliable in the damp, muddy conditions that prevailed. Consequently, the [[field telephone]] was designed; a device that operated with its own [[Telephone switchboard|switchboard]]. Apart from voice communication, it featured a buzzer unit with a [[Morse code]] key, so that it could be used to send and receive coded messages. This facility proved useful when, in the midst of bombardment, exploding shells drowned out voice communication. The telephones were connected by lines that sustained continual damage as a result of shell fire and the movement of troops. The lines were generally buried, with redundant lines set in place to compensate for breakages.&lt;ref name=sig/&gt;

The primary types of visual signalling were [[Flag semaphore|Semaphore flags]], lamps and flags, lamps and lights, and the [[heliograph]]. In open warfare, visual signalling (employing signal flags and the heliograph) was the norm. A competent signaller could transmit 12 words a minute with signal flags (during daylight) and signal lights (at night). Signal lights, which were secured in a wooden case, employed a battery-operated Morse code key.&lt;ref name=sig/&gt; These signalling techniques had certain disadvantages, however. In trench warfare, operators using these methods were forced to expose themselves to enemy fire; while messages sent to the rear by signal lights could not be seen by enemy forces, replies to such messages were readily spotted, and operators were, once again, exposed to enemy fire.&lt;ref name=sig/&gt;

During the war, the Army also trained animals for use in the trenches. Dogs carried messages; horses, mules and dogs were used to lay telephone and telegraph cables.&lt;ref name=sig/&gt; Carrier pigeons, who transported messages back from the front line, were also carried in tanks so that they could deliver messages during an attack.&lt;ref name=sig/&gt; Over 20,000 pigeons and 370 handlers were used during the war, and at times, they were the sole means of communication.&lt;ref name=sig&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=30 May 2009 |title=Royal Engineer Signal Service |publisher=Mod Army |url=http://www2.armynet.mod.uk/museums/royalsignals/displays/first_world_war/index.htm |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090829221337/http://www2.armynet.mod.uk/museums/royalsignals/displays/first_world_war/index.htm |archivedate=29 August 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Royal Flying Corps===
{{main article|Royal Flying Corps|List of aircraft of the Royal Flying Corps}}
[[File:Royal Flying Corps poster.jpg|thumb|[[Royal Flying Corps]] World War I recruiting poster]]

At the start of the war, the Royal Flying Corps (RFC) in the Field, commanded by [[David Henderson (British Army officer)|Sir David Henderson]] consisted of five squadrons—one [[observation balloon]] squadron (RFC No 1 Squadron) and four aeroplane squadrons (Nos 2, 3, 4 and 5). These units were first used for aerial spotting on 13 September 1914, but only became efficient when they perfected the use of [[Wireless|wireless communication]] at [[Aubers Ridge]] on 9 May 1915. [[Aerial photography]] was attempted during 1914, but again, it only became effective the following year. In August 1915, General [[Hugh Trenchard, 1st Viscount Trenchard|Hugh Trenchard]] replaced Henderson. The British use of air power evolved during the war, from a reconnaissance force to a fighting force that attempted to gain command of the air above the trenches and carry out bombing raids on targets behind the line.&lt;ref name=mm54&gt;Millett &amp; Murray (1988), p. 54&lt;/ref&gt; The early aircraft of the RFC were inferior to their German rivals; in April 1917, (known as [[Bloody April]]), the RFC lost over 300 aircrew and 245 aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;Franks &amp; Van Wyngarden (2007), p. 36&lt;/ref&gt; Not until late 1917, with the introduction of the [[Sopwith Camel]] and the [[Royal Aircraft Factory S.E.5|S.E.5]], were they able to compete successfully for control of the air.&lt;ref name=mm54/&gt;

On 17 August 1917, General [[Jan Smuts]] presented a report to the War Council concerning the future of [[Aerial warfare|air power]]. Given its potential for the 'devastation of enemy lands and the destruction of industrial targets and centres of population on a vast scale'. He recommended a new air service be formed that would be on a level with the Army and Royal Navy. The formation of the new service, however, would make use of the under-utilised men and machines of the [[Royal Naval Air Service]] (RNAS), as well as ending the inter-service rivalries that at times had adversely affected aircraft procurement. On 1 April 1918, the RFC and the RNAS were amalgamated to form a new service, the [[Royal Air Force]] (RAF). The RAF was under the control of the equally new [[Air Ministry]]. By 1918, photographic images could be taken from {{convert|15000|ft|m|abbr=on}} and interpreted by over 3,000 personnel. Planes did not carry [[parachute]]s until 1918, though they had been available since before the war.&lt;ref name= &quot;beckett254&quot;&gt;Beckett &amp; Simpson (1985), p. 254&lt;/ref&gt; After starting with some 2,073 personnel in 1914, the RAF had 4,000 [[Military aircraft|combat aircraft]] and 114,000 personnel by the beginning of 1919.

===Corps of Royal Engineers===
On 1 August 1914, the Royal Engineers consisted of 25,000 officers and men in the regular army and reserves; by the same date in 1917, it had grown to a total of 250,000.&lt;ref name=reng&gt;{{cite web| accessdate=14 June 2009|title=Royal Engineers|first=Chris|last=Baker|url=http://www.1914-1918.net/cre.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1914, when the BEF arrived in France, there were two Engineer field companies attached to each infantry division, which was increased to three companies by September 1914.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=13 June 2009|first=Chris|last=Baker|title=The Field Companies RE|url=http://www.1914-1918.net/re.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; Each division also had a Signals company, which was responsible for communications between Corps, Division and Brigade headquarters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| accessdate=14 June 2009|first=Chris|last=Baker|title=Signals Company RE|url=http://www.1914-1918.net/whatfieldcoy.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Royal Engineer tunnelling companies]] were formed in response to the German blowing of 10 small mines in December 1914, at [[Givenchy]].&lt;ref name=retun/&gt; The first British mine was detonated at [[Battle of Hill 60 (Western Front)|Hill 60]] on 17 February 1915. Mining was used increasingly during the [[Battle of Aubers Ridge]] in May 1915, and the [[battle of Loos]] in September 1915. In July 1916, on the first day of the battle of the Somme, what became known as the [[Lochnagar Crater]] was created by a mine at [[La Boisselle]].&lt;ref name=retun&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=14 June 2009 |first=Chris |last=Baker |title=The Tunnelling Companies RE |url=http://www.1914-1918.net/tunnelcoyre.htm |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150510184955/http://www.1914-1918.net/tunnelcoyre.htm |archivedate=10 May 2015 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Twenty-one companies were eventually formed and were employed digging subways, cable trenches, [[Sapping]], dugouts as well as offensive or defensive mining.&lt;ref name=retun/&gt; At the end of the war, Engineers were directly responsible for maintaining buildings and designing the infantry front-line fortifications and artillery positions, the telephones, wireless and other signalling equipment, railways, roads, water supply, bridges and transport. They also operated the railways and inland waterways.&lt;ref name=reng/&gt;

===Machine Gun Corps===
In September 1915, the [[Machine Gun Corps]] (MGC) was formed to provide heavy machine-gun teams after a proposal was made to the War Office for the formation of a single specialist machine-gun company for each infantry brigade—a goal to be achieved by withdrawing guns and gun teams from the battalions.&lt;ref name=mcg&gt;{{cite web|first=Chris|last=Baker|accessdate=13 June 2009|title=The Machine Gun Corps of 1914–1918|url=http://www.1914-1918.net/mgc.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; Created in October 1915, the MGC consisted of infantry machine-gun companies, cavalry machine-gun squadrons and motor machine-gun batteries.&lt;ref name=mcg/&gt; In the trenches, the Corps' guns were deployed with an interlocking field of fire and proved to be a devastating defensive weapon against attacking infantry.&lt;ref name=mcg/&gt; They were also used in an indirect fire support role, in which they fired over the heads&lt;ref name=mcg/&gt; and from the flanks&lt;ref&gt;Connelly (2006), p. 66&lt;/ref&gt; of the advancing infantry and behind the German trenches to stop reinforcements and supplies from getting to the front.&lt;ref name=mcg/&gt;

===Tank Corps===
The [[Royal Tank Regiment|Tank Corps]] was formed as the ''Heavy Section Machine Gun Corps'' in 1916.&lt;ref&gt;Hofmann (2006), p. 53&lt;/ref&gt; Tanks were used for the first time in action in the battle of the Somme on 15 September 1916. The intention being that they would crush the barbed wire for the infantry, then cross the trenches and exploit any breakthrough behind the German lines.&lt;ref&gt;Hoffmann (2006), pp. 53–54&lt;/ref&gt; In November 1916, they were renamed the Heavy Branch MGC and in June 1917, the Tank Corps.&lt;ref&gt;Swinton (1972), p. 178&lt;/ref&gt;

Originally formed in Companies of the Heavy Branch MGC, designated A, B, C and D; each company of four sections had six tanks, three male and three female versions (artillery or machine guns), with one tank held as a company reserve.&lt;ref name=tankc&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=13 June 2009|title=The Tank Corps of 1914–1918|first=Chris|last=Baker|url=http://www.1914-1918.net/tanks.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; In November 1916, each company was reformed as a battalion of three companies, with plans to increase the Corps to 20 battalions, each Tank Battalion had a complement of 32 officers and 374 men.&lt;ref name=tankc/&gt;

Tanks were primarily used on the Western Front. The first offensive of the war in which tanks were used ''en masse'' was the [[Battle of Cambrai (1917)|battle of Cambrai]] in 1917; 476 tanks started the attack, and the German front collapsed. At midday the British had advanced five miles behind the German line.&lt;ref&gt;Tucker &amp; Roberts (2005), p. 407&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Battle of Amiens (1918)|battle of Amiens]] in 1918 saw the value of the tank being appreciated; 10 heavy and two light battalions of 414 tanks were included in the assault. 342 [[Mark V tank|Mark Vs]] and 72 [[Medium Mark A Whippet|Whippets]] were backed up by a further 120 tanks designed to carry forward supplies for the armour and infantry. By the end of the first day of the attack, they had penetrated the German line by {{convert|6|-|8|mi|km|abbr=on}}, 16,000 prisoners were taken.&lt;ref&gt;Griffiths &amp; Griess (2003), p. 155&lt;/ref&gt; In September 1918, the British Army was the most mechanised army in the world. Some 22,000 men had served in the Tank Corps by the end of the war.&lt;ref&gt;Bond 2009, p. 5.&lt;/ref&gt;

A detachment of eight obsolescent Mark I tanks was sent to Southern Palestine in early 1917 and saw action against Turkish forces there.&lt;ref&gt;Humble 1977, p. 29&lt;/ref&gt;

===Army Service Corps===
The [[Army Service Corps]] (ASC) operated the transport system to deliver men, ammunition and matériel to the front. From 12,000 men at the start of the war, the Corps increased in size to over 300,000 by November 1918.&lt;ref name=asc/&gt; In addition they had under command Indian, Egyptian, Chinese ([[Chinese Labour Corps]]) and other native labourers, carriers and stores men.&lt;ref name= asc/&gt; They provided horsed and mechanical transport companies, the [[Army Remount Service]] and ASC Labour companies.&lt;ref name=asc/&gt; In August 1914, they delivered {{convert|4500000|lb|kg|abbr=on}} of bread to the front which increased to {{convert|90000000|lb|kg|abbr=on}} by November 1918.&lt;ref name=asc&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=11 June 2009|first=Chris|last=Baker|title=Army Service Corps of 1914–1918|url=http://www.1914-1918.net/asc.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Royal Army Medical Corps===
The [[Royal Army Medical Corps]] (RAMC) supplied the doctors, casualty evacuation, field ambulances and hospitals for the army.&lt;ref name=ramc&gt;{{cite web|first=Chris|last=Baker| accessdate=11 June 2009|title=Royal Army Medical Corps of 1914–1918|url=http://www.1914-1918.net/ramc.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Corps was assisted in its work by voluntary help from the [[British Red Cross]], [[St John's Ambulance]] and the [[Friends Ambulance Unit]].&lt;ref name=ramc/&gt;

The only person to be awarded the [[Victoria Cross]] twice during the war was a doctor in the RAMC, [[Captain (British Army and Royal Marines)|Captain]] [[Noel Godfrey Chavasse]], [[Victoria Cross|VC and Bar]], [[Military Cross|MC]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=26 May 2009|publisher=Oxford Mail|title= A lesson in history|url=http://archive.oxfordmail.net/2006/6/15/97731.html}} {{Dead link|date=April 2012|bot=H3llBot}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While not strictly a member of the RAMC, stretcher bearer [[Lance Corporal]] [[William Harold Coltman]] VC, [[Distinguished Conduct Medal|DCM]] [[Medal bar|&amp; Bar]], [[Military Medal|MM]] [[Medal bar|&amp; Bar]], was the most decorated [[Other ranks (UK)|other rank]] of the war.&lt;ref&gt;Holmes (2005), p. 471&lt;/ref&gt;

==Life in the trenches==
{{main article|Trench warfare}}
[[File:Trench construction diagram 1914.png|thumb|right|Trench construction diagram, from a 1914 British infantry manual]]

By the end of 1914, the war on the Western Front had reached stalemate and the trench lines extended from the Belgian coast to the Swiss frontier.&lt;ref name=trench/&gt; By September 1915, the length of the British front line stretched some {{convert|70|mi|km|abbr=on}}. Soldiers were in the front or reserve line trenches for about eight days at a time, before being relieved.&lt;ref name=trench&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=27 May 2009 |title=Trench Warfare |publisher=Imperial War Museum |url=http://www.iwm.org.uk/server/show/nav.2178 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090629103135/http://www.iwm.org.uk:80/server/show/nav.2178 |archivedate=29 June 2009 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

There were three trenches in a typical front line sector; the fire trench, the support trench and the reserve trench, all joined by communication trenches.&lt;ref name=miller/&gt; The trenches varied in depth, but they were usually about four or five feet deep, or in areas with a high [[water table]] a wall of sandbags would be built to allow the defenders to stand upright, fire trenches were provided with a fire step, so the occupants could return fire during an attack (see diagram).&lt;ref name=miller/&gt; Ideally, the bottom of the trench was lined with [[duckboards]] to prevent men from sinking into the mud and dugouts were cut into the walls, these gave shelter from the elements and shrapnel, although in the British Army dugouts were usually reserved for the officers and senior NCOs.&lt;ref name=miller/&gt; The men were then expected to sleep wherever they could and in wet weather they lived under groundsheets or in tents at the bottom of the trench on the duckboards.&lt;ref name= miller&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=27 May 2009|title=Of Lice and Men|first=Doctor M G|last=Miller|url= http://www.gwpda.org/medical/liceand.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At the front, soldiers were in constant danger from artillery shells, mortar bombs and bullets and as the war progressed they also faced aerial attack.&lt;ref name=glasgow/&gt; Some sectors of the front saw little activity throughout the war, making life comparatively easy. Other sectors were in a perpetual state of violent activity. However, quiet sectors still amassed daily casualties through [[sniper]]s, artillery fire and disease. The harsh conditions, where trenches were often wet and muddy and the constant company of lice and rats which fed on unburied bodies, often carried disease.&lt;ref name=trench/&gt; Many troops suffered from [[trench foot]], [[trench fever]] and [[Nephritis|trench nephritis]]. They could also contract [[frostbite]] in the winter months and heat exhaustion in the summer. The men were frequently wet and extremely muddy, or dry and exceedingly dusty.&lt;ref name=trench/&gt;&lt;ref name=glasgow&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=27 May 2009|title=Trench Warfare|publisher=Glasgow Digital Library|url=http://gdl.cdlr.strath.ac.uk/springburn/springwar/springwar07.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; Food could not usually be cooked in the front line trenches as any smoke would draw enemy fire, hot food had to be carried along communication trenches in clumsy &quot;hayboxes&quot;, sometimes arriving late or not at all.

===Daily routine===
[[File:Cheshire Regiment trench Somme 1916.jpg|thumb|left|A sentry of the [[Cheshire Regiment]] in 1916. Note the four men sleeping in the trench]]

Daily routine of life in the trenches began with the morning 'stand-to'. An hour before dawn everyone was roused and ordered to man their positions to guard against a dawn raid by the Germans.&lt;ref name=routine&gt;{{cite web|title=Life in the trenches – Passchendaele'|url= http://www.nzhistory.net.nz/war/new-zealanders-in-belgium/a-soldiers-lot|publisher=New Zealand Ministry for Culture and Heritage|accessdate=27 May 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; With stand-to over, it was time for the men to have breakfast and perform ablutions. Once complete, the NCOs would assign daily chores, before the men attended to the cleaning of rifles and equipment, filling sandbags, repairing trenches or digging latrines.&lt;ref name=routine/&gt; Once the daily tasks had been completed the men who were off-duty would find a place to sleep.&lt;ref name=routine/&gt; Due to the constant bombardments and the sheer effort of trying to stay alive, [[sleep deprivation]] was common. Soldiers also had to take it in turns to be on sentry duty, watching for enemy movements.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|accessdate= 27 May 2009|title=Life in the Trenches of World War One|publisher=BBC h2g2|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/dna/h2g2/A21605979}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Each side's front line was constantly under observation by snipers and lookouts during daylight; movement was therefore restricted until after the dusk stand-to and night had fallen.&lt;ref name=routine/&gt; Under the cover of darkness, troops attended to vital maintenance and resupply, with rations and water being brought to the front line, fresh units swapped places with troops moving to the rear for rest and recuperation.&lt;ref name=routine/&gt; [[Trench raiding]] was also carried out and construction parties formed to repair trenches and fortifications, while wiring parties were sent out to repair or renew the [[barbed wire]] in [[no man's land]].&lt;ref name=routine/&gt; An hour before dawn, everyone would stand-to once more.&lt;ref name=routine/&gt;

===Moving into the front line===
A set procedure was used by a division that was moving into the front line. Once they had been informed that they were moving forward, the brigadiers and battalion commanders would be taken to the forward areas to reconnoitre the sections of the front that were to be occupied by their troops.&lt;ref name=movetrench/&gt; Meanwhile, the battalion transport officers would be taken to the headquarters of the division that they were relieving to observe the methods used for drawing rations and ammunition, and the manner in which they were supplied to the troops at the front. Detachments from the divisional artillery group would move forward and were attached to the artillery batteries of the division they were relieving.&lt;ref name=movetrench/&gt; Five days later, the infantry battalions that were destined for the front line sent forward their specialists from the Lewis gun teams, and the grenade officer, the machine gun officer, the four company commanders, and some of the signallers to take over the trench stores and settle into the trench routine before the battalions moved in.&lt;ref name=movetrench/&gt; Overnight, the battalions would move into the line, and the artillery would take over the guns that were already in position, leaving theirs behind to be taken over by the batteries that had been relieved.&lt;ref name=movetrench&gt;{{cite web|accessdate= 29 May 2009|title=The move to the front|publisher=Australian War Memorial|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/cms_images/histories/4/chapters/04.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Discipline==

===Legal authority===
The Army was ultimately under political authority. Since the Glorious Revolution of 1688 the Crown has not technically been permitted a standing army in the United Kingdom–it derives its existence from the Army Act, passed by Parliament each year (every five years since the late 1950s). The House of Commons took these responsibilities seriously: a letter from Haig clarifying the position on shell-shock had to be read out in the House of Commons on 14 March 1918.&lt;ref&gt;Bond &amp; Cave 2009, p. 208&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Corrigan 2002, p. 216&lt;/ref&gt; Most disciplinary regulations in World War One derived from the 1881 Army Act, although some offences were more severely dealt with on active service, e.g. in principle looting or wilful disobedience carried the death penalty.&lt;ref&gt;Corrigan 2002, p. 219&lt;/ref&gt;

===Lesser offences===
Lesser offences were dealt with by commanding officers.&lt;ref&gt;Corrigan 2002, p. 222&lt;/ref&gt; For petty offences, a company commander could have men fined or confined to barracks for fatigue duty&lt;ref&gt;Holmes 2004, p. 557&lt;/ref&gt; A battalion Commanding Officer could give detention, order up to 28 days Field Punishment, or demote corporals to the ranks (officers and senior NCOs were dealt with by court martial other than for very trivial offences).&lt;ref name=&quot;Holmes 2004, p. 558&quot;&gt;Holmes 2004, p. 558&lt;/ref&gt; Enlisted men could also lose leave or seniority.&lt;ref&gt;Corrigan 2002, p. 217-9&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Field punishment]] (FP) had replaced flogging (abolished at home in 1868 and on active service in 1881, although still used in military prisons until 1907). FP No.1 (in which the man was shackled to fixed object, e.g. a large wheel) was awarded to 60,210 cases, equivalent to one man in 50 (although in practice there were many repeat offenders).&lt;ref name=&quot;Holmes 2004, p. 558&quot;/&gt; FP No.1 could be very unpleasant depending on the weather, was abhorred by some as barbaric, and in some units was ritualised (e.g. by locking a man in a shed and throwing the handcuffs in with him); there were also cases of Australian troops releasing British troops whom they found tied up, although in other units it was regarded as a necessary sanction for serious offences.&lt;ref&gt;Holmes 2004, p. 560&lt;/ref&gt; FP No.2 meant that a man was shackled but not fixed in place.&lt;ref&gt;Corrigan 2002, p. 225&lt;/ref&gt;

Striking an inferior was an offence but it was not uncommon in some units for officers to turn a blind eye to NCOs keeping discipline by violence, or even to do so themselves.&lt;ref&gt;Holmes 2004, p. 555&lt;/ref&gt;

===Courts martial===
Men who committed serious offences were tried by Field General Court Martial, sometimes resulting in execution. Despite &quot;assertions&quot; that these were &quot;kangaroo courts&quot; (e.g. in the book &quot;Shot at Dawn&quot; which says that men &quot;did not receive even the rudiments of a just hearing&quot;) the release of records in 1990-4 showed this to be untrue.&lt;ref&gt;Bond &amp; Cave 2009, p. 217&lt;/ref&gt; They in fact had strict rules of procedure and a duty to uncover the facts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Holmes 2004, p. 563&quot;&gt;Holmes 2004, p. 563.&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike a General Court Martial in peacetime, there was no legally qualified Judge-Advocate to advise the court, but from the start of 1916 a &quot;Court Martial Officer&quot; – usually an officer with legal experience in civilian life&amp;nbsp;– was often present to do so.&lt;ref&gt;Holmes 2004, p. 561.&lt;/ref&gt;

The accused was entitled to object to the composition of the panel (e.g. if one of the officers was connected with the case or enjoyed a poor relationship with the accused) and to present his case, defended by an officer (a &quot;Prisoner's Friend&quot;) if he chose, although &quot;Prisoners Friends&quot; became more common as the war went on.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bond &amp; Cave 2009, p. 201&quot;&gt;Bond &amp; Cave 2009, p. 201&lt;/ref&gt; The officer who convened a court martial could not sit on it, and the most junior officer voted first (to lessen the chance of his deferring to a superior's opinion).&lt;ref&gt;Holmes 2004, p. 561&lt;/ref&gt; However, the courts were explicitly intended to be &quot;speedy&quot; and were sometimes encouraged by higher authority to make an example of certain offences, and in practice the leniency of the court and the ability of the accused to defend himself varied widely.&lt;ref name=&quot;Holmes 2004, p. 563&quot;/&gt; Some pleaded guilty or chose not to present a defence or call witnesses, and in most cases the offence was &quot;so blatant that little defence could be put forward&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Bond &amp; Cave 2009, p. 203, 216&lt;/ref&gt;

Eighty-nine per cent of courts martial returned a guilty verdict,&lt;ref&gt;Corrigan 2002, p. 225.&lt;/ref&gt; the vast majority of cases being for offences such as Absence Without Leave (the most common offence), drunkenness and insubordination. Terms of imprisonment were often suspended, to discourage soldiers from committing an offence to escape the front lines, but also to give a convicted man a chance to earn a reprieve for good conduct.&lt;ref name=&quot;Holmes 2004, p. 565&quot;&gt;Holmes 2004, p. 565&lt;/ref&gt;

Of the 252 officers tried, 76 per cent were found guilty, the most common offence (52 per cent of cases) being drunkenness. Although three officers were executed, an officer was most likely to receive a severe reprimand (60 per cent of cases&amp;nbsp;– a severe blow to his career) or be cashiered (30 per cent of cases&amp;nbsp;– stripped of his commission, which brought total social disgrace and barred him from any employment under the Crown, even working for the local council&amp;nbsp;– but a cashiered officer could still be conscripted as a private to a different unit).&lt;ref&gt;Corrigan 2002, p. 226&lt;/ref&gt;

===Executions===
A death sentence had to be passed unanimously, and confirmed in writing by various officers as the verdict passed up the chain of command. A man's battalion and brigade commander tended to comment on his own record, but senior generals tended to be more concerned with the type of offence and the state of discipline in that unit.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bond &amp; Cave 2009, p. 202&quot;&gt;Bond &amp; Cave 2009, p. 202&lt;/ref&gt; The Judge Advocate General at GHQ also checked the records for irregularities,&lt;ref name=&quot;Bond &amp; Cave 2009, p. 201&quot;/&gt; before final confirmation (or otherwise) by the Commander-in-Chief of the relevant theatre.&lt;ref name=&quot;Corrigan 2002, p. 232&quot;&gt;Corrigan 2002, p. 232&lt;/ref&gt;

Of the 3,080 men sentenced to death,&lt;ref&gt;Corrigan 2002, p. 229&lt;/ref&gt; 346 men were actually executed, the vast majority of these (266) for desertion, the next largest reasons for execution being murder (37 — these men would probably have been hanged under civilian law at the time) and cowardice (18).&lt;ref name=&quot;Corrigan 2002, p. 230&quot;&gt;Corrigan 2002, p. 230&lt;/ref&gt; Convictions for mutiny were rare — only one man was shot for the Etaples disturbances in 1917.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bond &amp; Cave 2009, p. 202&quot;/&gt; Of the men shot, 91 were already under a previous suspended sentence, and nine under two sentences. Of the 91, 40 were already under a suspended death sentence, 38 of them for desertion, and one man had already been &quot;sentenced to death&quot; twice for desertion.&lt;ref&gt;Bond &amp; Cave 2009, p. 199&lt;/ref&gt;

It was felt at the time that, precisely because most soldiers in combat were afraid, an example needed to be made of men who deserted.&lt;ref&gt;Corrigan 2002, p. 236&lt;/ref&gt; Front line soldiers also sometimes felt that those who left their mates &quot;in the lurch&quot; by deserting &quot;deserved to be shot&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Holmes 2004, p. 559&quot;&gt;Holmes 2004, p. 559&lt;/ref&gt; One historian writes that there is &quot;virtually no evidence&quot; that soldiers thought the death penalty unjust,&lt;ref&gt;Bond &amp; Cave 2009, p. 216&lt;/ref&gt; although another writes that some soldiers deplored the death penalty, while most thought it justified.&lt;ref name=&quot;Holmes 2004, p. 559&quot;/&gt; Desertion normally meant an absence of 21 days or other evidence to indicate intent of not returning, e.g. wearing civilian clothes or failing to report for a key deployment. Those executed were normally not boys&amp;nbsp;– the average age was in the mid-twenties and 40 percent had been in serious trouble before. Thirty percent were regulars or reservists, 40 percent were Kitchener volunteers, 19 percent were Irish, Canadian or New Zealand volunteers, but only nine percent were conscripts, suggesting indulgence to the conscripts, many of them under 21, who made up the bulk of the army by late in the war. Only executed men's records survive, so it is hard to comment on the reasons why men were reprieved,&lt;ref&gt;Bond &amp; Cave 2009, p. 196&lt;/ref&gt; but it has been suggested that the policy of commuting 90 percent of death sentences may well have been deliberate mercy in the application of military law designed for a small regular army recruited from the rougher elements of society.&lt;ref&gt;Bond &amp; Cave 2009, p. 200, 204&lt;/ref&gt; Only 7,361 of the 38,630 desertions were in the field. Most were away from the front line — 14 of the executed deserters were arrested in the United Kingdom — and many deserters had never served in the front line at all.&lt;ref&gt;Bond &amp; Cave 2009, p. 206&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bond &amp; Cave 2009, p. 199, 201, p206&lt;/ref&gt;

In the latter part of the war, executed men's families were usually told white lies by the authorities; their families received pensions and were buried in the same graves as other dead soldiers.&lt;ref&gt;Bond &amp; Cave 2009, p. 214&lt;/ref&gt;

Death for desertion was abolished in 1930 over objections in the [[House of Lords]] from Lords Allenby and Plumer, two of the most distinguished British commanders of World War One; calls for its restoration in World War Two were vetoed on political grounds.&lt;ref&gt;Bond &amp; Cave 2009, p. 212&lt;/ref&gt;

By contrast, of 393 men sentenced to death for falling asleep on sentry duty in all theatres in World War I, only two were executed (sentries were usually posted in pairs to keep one another awake; these two, who served in [[Mesopotamian campaign|Mesopotamia]], were made an example of because they were found sitting asleep together, suggesting that they had colluded).&lt;ref name=&quot;Corrigan 2002, p. 232&quot;/&gt;

Australians made up seven percent of the British Expeditionary Force but 25 percent of deserters, while an Australian was nine times more likely to be imprisoned than a British soldier. Haig asked for permission to shoot Australians, but their government refused.&lt;ref name=&quot;Corrigan 2002, p. 230&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bond &amp; Cave 2009, p. 210&lt;/ref&gt;

British discipline of the First World War was not especially severe compared to most other armies of the time (e.g. the Russians and Italians). The French admitted to only 133 executions and the Germans 48, but these figures may not be reliable as both armies had problems with discipline.&lt;ref&gt;Bond &amp; Cave 2009, p. 209-10&lt;/ref&gt;

===Shell shock and pardons===
At the time [[Posttraumatic stress disorder]] (known as &quot;[[shell shock]]&quot; because it was initially wrongly thought to be caused by concussion damage to the membranes of the brain) was beginning to be recognised and was admissible in defence – it was classified as a war injury, although there were concerns that soldiers accused of offences tried falsely to claim shell shock as a defence.&lt;ref&gt;Corrigan 2002, p. 233-5&lt;/ref&gt; One historian writes that &quot;in no case was a soldier whom the medical staff certified as suffering from shell shock actually executed&quot;, that &quot;there appear to have been very few cases where men who alleged shell shock, but whose claim was denied, were actually executed&quot;, and that the suggestions of modern campaigners that most of the executed men suffered from shell shock are &quot;palpably untrue&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Corrigan 2002, p. 235&lt;/ref&gt; However, another historian has pointed out that there was a great deal of chance in whether a soldier's claim of shell-shock would be taken seriously, and gives examples of soldiers being given cursory medical examinations or none;&lt;ref name=&quot;Holmes 2004, p. 565&quot;/&gt; specific references to shell-shock are uncommon, and records usually refer to dizziness, &quot;queer turns&quot;, bad nerves etc.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bond &amp; Cave 2009, p. 202&quot;/&gt; Such trauma was still poorly understood at that time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Shot for cowardice, desertion and insubordination&amp;nbsp;– or murdered for shell shock? | url=http://www.bullyonline.org/stress/ww1.htm|publisher=UK National Workplace Advisory Line|accessdate=1 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There were enquiries in 1919, 1922, 1925 and 1938, which examined documents now lost and witnesses now dead.&lt;ref&gt;Bond &amp; Cave 2009, p. 218&lt;/ref&gt; The books &quot;For the Sake of Example&quot; (1983) by Babington and &quot;Shot at Dawn&quot; (1989) by Sykes &amp; Putkowski were openly intended to start a campaign for pardons. This campaign was rejected in February 1993 because there was no evidence of procedural error (i.e. they had been correctly convicted according to the law at the time) and it was felt not right to impose modern values on to the past.&lt;ref&gt;Bond &amp; Cave 2009, p. 197&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Holmes 2004, p. 569&lt;/ref&gt; The case was rejected again in 1998 after a detailed two-year review, which found &quot;no white cases, very many black cases and a handful of grey cases&quot; in which medical evidence was ignored or not called.&lt;ref&gt;Bond &amp; Cave 2009, p. 198, 204&lt;/ref&gt; The decisions were reversed by the Government in 2006 and all men given pardons and recognised as victims of World War I. However, their sentences were not overturned as it was impossible after this length of time to re-examine the evidence in every case.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=18 February 2012|publisher=UK Gov|title=Legislation|url=http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2006/52/section/359}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Other discipline===
It has been pointed out that we have only anecdotal accounts, but no figures, for men who were shot on the spot by officers and NCOs for &quot;cowardice in the face of the enemy&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Holmes 2004, p. 570&lt;/ref&gt;

There were over 13,000 Royal Military Police (“redcaps”). They were unpopular, at a time when the police were often unpopular with young men from big cities. Besides policing, a large part of their job was maintaining discipline on the march and keeping roads running smoothly, and collecting stragglers from a battle. During the March 1918 retreat 25,000 stragglers were rounded up and sent back to fighting units. Royal Military Police also fought on occasion if headquarters areas were threatened by an enemy advance. Although soldiers sometimes told lurid tales of men who refused to fight being shot by Military Police, no reliable first-hand accounts exist of this happening.&lt;ref&gt;Holmes 2004, p. 570-1&lt;/ref&gt;

There were occasional examples of men making unwanted homosexual advances, homosexuality being then criminal under both military and civil law, to escape the front lines, but prosecutions for this crime were rare, and there is also evidence of men turning a blind eye to homosexual relationships.&lt;ref&gt;Holmes 2004, p. 599&lt;/ref&gt;

===Positive motivation===
Men were also motivated by positive means. New medals were instituted: the Military Cross was created in December 1914 for warrant officers and officers up to captain, the Military Medal for enlisted men in March 1916 (although to the regret of some men, it did not carry a cash bounty like the Distinguished Conduct Medal). The Order of the British Empire (of which the MBE is one grade) was instituted in 1917. By 1918, medals for bravery were often awarded within a week to ensure that the man lived long enough to receive it.&lt;ref&gt;Holmes 2004, p. 583-4&lt;/ref&gt;

Race meetings, concert parties (including drag acts&amp;nbsp;– good drag queens were in great demand), trips to the seaside and football matches were organised to keep men entertained.&lt;ref&gt;Holmes 2004, p. 602-4&lt;/ref&gt; There were various unofficial publications, including the “Wipers Times”&amp;nbsp;– these give an insight into the views of ordinary soldiers and junior officers. Overt patriotism was rare, and politicians such as (Prime Minister) Asquith and Ramsay MacDonald (an opponent of the war, later Labour Prime Minister) were satirised.&lt;ref&gt;Holmes 2004, p. 607&lt;/ref&gt;

==Western Front==
{{main article|Western Front (World War I)}}

Under the command of [[Field marshal (United Kingdom)|Field Marshal]] [[John French, 1st Earl of Ypres|Sir John French]],&lt;ref name=ps289-290&gt;Pearce &amp; Stewart (2002), pp. 289–290&lt;/ref&gt; the British Expeditionary Force (BEF) began to deploy to France within days of the [[declaration of war]].&lt;ref name=ps289/&gt; The first encounter with the Germans came at [[Battle of Mons|Mons]] on 23 August 1914,&lt;ref name=ps289&gt;Pearce &amp; Stewart (2002), p. 289&lt;/ref&gt; after which the Allies began the [[Great Retreat]], the BEF was involved in the [[Battle of Le Cateau]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=90 years of remembrance|publisher=BBC|accessdate=26 May 2009|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/remembrance/timeline/index.shtml}}&lt;/ref&gt; The BEF had a small role in halting the German advance at the [[First Battle of the Marne]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Battle of the Marne: 6–10&amp;nbsp;September 1914|publisher=BBC History|accessdate=26 May 2009|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/worldwars/wwone/battle_marne.shtml}}&lt;/ref&gt; before participating in the [[First Battle of the Aisne|Aisne counter-offensive]], in September which was followed by a period known as the &quot;[[Race to the Sea]]&quot; during which the BEF redeployed to [[Flanders]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video|people=Liulevicius, Vejas Gabriel|date=2006|title=World War I: The &quot;Great War&quot;|medium=DVD|publisher=The Teaching Company|location=[[University of Tennessee]]|time= disk 1, lecture 6|isbn=1-59803-153-8|quote=This name, the &quot;Race to the Sea,&quot; which has stuck, nonetheless is actually something of a misnomer; because it was not so much a race to the sea as a succession of attempts to turn the flank of the other side, until ultimately, without a decision the front simply reached the English Channel and the North Sea.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For the BEF, 1914 ended with &quot;[[First Battle of Ypres|First Ypres]]&quot; which marked the beginning of a long struggle for the [[Ypres Salient]].&lt;ref name=rickard/&gt; British casualties in the fighting between 14 October and 30 November were 58,155 (7,960 dead, 29,562 wounded and 17,873 missing). It is often said that the pre-war professional army died at the First Battle of Ypres.&lt;ref name=rickard/&gt; The British Army had arrived in France with some 84,000 [[infantry]]men. By the end of the battle, the BEF had suffered 86,237 casualties, mostly to the infantry.&lt;ref name=rickard&gt;{{cite web|last=Rickard|first=J|year=2007|title=First battle of Ypres, 19&amp;nbsp;October–22&amp;nbsp;November 1914|url=http://www.historyofwar.org/articles/battles_ypres1.html|accessdate=27 May 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:British infantry advancing at Loos 25 September 1915.jpg|thumb|right|British infantry of the [[London Rifle Brigade]] advancing through gas during the [[Battle of Loos]], 25 September 1915.]]

[[Trench warfare]] prevailed in 1915, and the BEF—as the junior partner on the Western Front—fought a series of small battles, at times coordinated with the larger French offensives, like the [[Battle of Neuve Chapelle]] which is always associated with the [[Shell Crisis of 1915|shell crisis]], the [[Battle of Aubers Ridge]], the [[Battle of Festubert]] in May and the [[Winter operations 1914&amp;ndash;1915|Battle of Givenchy]] in June.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=27 May 2009|title=Battle of Nuve Chapelle|first=Chris| last=Baker|url=http://www.1914-1918.net/bat9.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=27 May 2009|title =Battle of Aubers|first=Chris|last=Baker|url=http://www.1914-1918.net/bat11.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=27 May 2009|title=Battle of Givenchy|author=Chris Baker|url=http://www.1914-1918.net/bat11A.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 22 April 1915, the [[German Army (German Empire)|German Army]] launched the [[Second Battle of Ypres]], employing [[Chemical warfare|poison gas]] for the first time on the Western Front and capturing much of the high ground that ringed the salient.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=27 May 2009|title=2nd Battle of Ypres| first=Chris|last=Baker|url=http://www.1914-1918.net/bat10.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt; By September 1915, the BEF had grown in size with the first of the [[Kitchener's Army|Kitchener's New Army]] divisions entering the line, and as part of the [[Third Battle of Artois]],&lt;ref&gt;Tucker &amp; Roberts (2005), p. 230&lt;/ref&gt; the BEF launched a major attack, the [[Battle of Loos]], utilising its own newly developed chemical weapons for the first time.&lt;ref&gt;Frothingham (1920), p. 118&lt;/ref&gt; The resulting failure marked the end for Field Marshal French. On 19 December 1915, [[General (United Kingdom)|General]] [[Douglas Haig, 1st Earl Haig|Sir Douglas Haig]] replaced him as [[Commander-in-chief|Commander-in-Chief]] (C-in-C) of the BEF.&lt;ref name=gg69&gt;Griffiths &amp; Greiss (2003), p. 69&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:British wounded Bernafay Wood 19 July 1916.jpg|thumb|left|British wounded of the [[Royal Berkshire Regiment]] returning from fighting on [[Battle of Bazentin Ridge|Bazentin Ridge]], July 1916. Photo by [[Ernest Brooks (photographer)|Ernest Brooks]].]]

For the British Army, the year of 1916 was dominated by the [[Battle of the Somme]] which started disastrously on 1 July. The [[first day on the Somme]] remains the bloodiest day in the [[history of the British Army]], with 19,240 British soldiers killed and 38,470 wounded or missing, all for little or no gain.&lt;ref name=1stdaysomme&gt;{{cite web|first=Professor Richard |last=Holmes |accessdate=27 May 2009 |title=Battle of the Somme |publisher=Imperial War Museum |url=http://www.iwm.org.uk/server/show/nav.2182 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090630074144/http://www.iwm.org.uk:80/server/show/nav.2182 |archivedate=30 June 2009 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; The only real success was in the south where, using imaginative tactics and helped by the French, the New Army [[18th (Eastern) Division|18th]] and [[30th Division (United Kingdom)|30th Division]]s took all their objectives, including [[Montauban]], and the Regular [[7th Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|7th Division]] captured [[Mametz, Somme|Mametz]].&lt;ref name=1stdaysomme/&gt; At [[Thiepval]], the [[36th (Ulster) Division]] seized the [[Capture of Schwaben Redoubt|Schwaben Redoubt]] but was forced to withdraw because of lack of progress elsewhere.&lt;ref name=1stdaysomme/&gt; There followed four-and-a-half months of [[Attrition warfare|attrition]] during which the [[Fourth Army (United Kingdom)|Fourth Army]] of General [[Henry Rawlinson, 1st Baron Rawlinson|Henry Rawlinson]] and the [[Fifth Army (United Kingdom)|Fifth Army]] of General [[Hubert Gough]] advanced an average of {{convert|5|mi|km}} at a cost of 420,000 casualties.&lt;ref&gt;Sheffield (2007), p. 151&lt;/ref&gt;

In February 1917, the German Army began to withdraw to the [[Hindenburg Line]] and it was these formidable defences that elements of the BEF assaulted in the [[Battle of Arras (1917)|Battle of Arras]] in April. For this battle, the [[Prime Minister of the United Kingdom|Prime Minister]]—[[David Lloyd George]]—had placed Haig and the BEF under the orders of new French C-in-C ([[Robert Nivelle]]), who planned a [[Nivelle Offensive|major offensive]] in [[Champagne (province)|Champagne]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Ashworth 55&quot;&gt;Ashworth (2000), pp. 55–56&lt;/ref&gt; When the battle officially ended on 16 May, British troops had made significant advances, but had been unable to achieve a major breakthrough at any point.&lt;ref name= &quot;Ashworth 55&quot;/&gt; Having failed to deliver a breakthrough, Haig now embarked on his favoured plan to launch an offensive in [[Flanders]]. In a successful preliminary operation, General Herbert Plumer's Second Army seized the [[Battle of Messines (1917)|Messines ridge]] south of Ypres.&lt;ref&gt;Wolff (2001), p. 102&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Battle of Passchendaele]] (also known as the Third Battle of Ypres), which began on 31 July 1917, was one of the harshest ordeals endured by British and [[Dominion]] troops during the war, with the battlefield reduced to a quagmire. It was not until 6 November that Passchendaele ridge was captured, by which time the BEF had sustained around 310,000 casualties.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=27 May 2009|title= Battle of Passchendaele|publisher=BBC History|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/worldwars/wwone/battle_passchendaele.shtml}}&lt;/ref&gt; The year of 1917, for the British Army, ended with the [[Battle of Cambrai (1917)|Battle of Cambrai]] which demonstrated the potential of tanks operating ''en masse''. The [[Third Army (United Kingdom)|Third Army]] commander—General [[Julian Byng, 1st Viscount Byng of Vimy|Julian Byng]]—planned an ambitious breakthrough and achieved an unprecedented advanced of {{convert|5|mi|km}} on the first day but lacked the reserves to either continue or consolidate. A German [[counter-offensive]] succeeded in recapturing most of the lost ground.&lt;ref&gt;Turner &amp; Dennis (2007), pp. 35–65&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Machineguncorps2.jpg|thumb|right|British [[machine gun]]ners of the [[Machine Gun Corps]] fire on German aircraft near [[Arras]], France, April 1917.]]

The final year of the war—1918—started with disaster and ended in triumph. On 21 March 1918, [[General of the Infantry (Germany)|General]] [[Erich Ludendorff]], Chief of the [[German General Staff]], launched the [[Spring Offensive]], which was intended to defeat the Allies on the Western Front before the strength of the [[American Expeditionary Forces|American Expeditionary Force]] (AEF) could become overwhelming. The main weight of the first blow—[[Operation Michael|Operation ''Michael'']]—fell on General Gough' s Fifth Army which was forced to retreat. In response to the crisis facing the Allies, French ''[[Generalissimo]]'' [[Ferdinand Foch]] was made Supreme Commander of the Allied forces on the Western Front, placing the BEF under his strategic direction. The next German attack came south of Ypres in the [[Battle of the Lys (1918)|Battle of the Lys river]] and here too the BEF fell back. Field Marshal Haig issued his famous Order of the Day, &quot;With our backs to the wall and believing in the justice of our cause, each one of us must fight on to the end.&quot; A third major German offensive, falling mainly on the [[French Army in World War I|French]], was finally [[Third Battle of the Aisne|halted on the Marne]] in June.&lt;ref&gt;[[New York Times]], 13 April 1918&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Keegan (1998), p. 403&lt;/ref&gt; On 8 August, General Rawlinson's Fourth Army launched the [[Battle of Amiens (1918)|Battle of Amiens]] which marked the start of the [[Hundred Days Offensive]], the final Allied offensive on the Western Front. Over the following weeks, all five armies of the BEF went on the offensive from the Somme to Flanders.&lt;ref&gt;Langley (2008), pp. 5–75&lt;/ref&gt; Fighting continued right up until the [[Armistice of 11 November 1918|Armistice with Germany]] came into effect at 11:00 am on 11 November 1918.&lt;ref&gt;Mallam (2003), p. 1889&lt;/ref&gt;

In the final offensives, the BEF had captured 188,700 prisoners and 2,840 guns which was only 7,800 prisoners and 935 guns less than those taken by the [[French Army in World War I|French]], [[Belgian Land Component|Belgian]] and [[American Expeditionary Forces|American]] armies combined.&lt;ref name=lions&gt;{{cite web| accessdate=7 June 2009|title=Lions led by Donkeys|publisher=BBC News Special Report|url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/special_report/1998/10/98/world_war_i/197586.stm|date=5 November 1998}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Other campaigns==

===Ireland===
{{main article|Easter Rising}}

The Easter Rising was a [[rebellion]] staged in Ireland during [[Easter Week]], 1916. It was mounted by [[Irish republicans]] with the aims of ending British rule in Ireland and establishing an [[Irish Republic]]. Organised by the Military Council of the [[Irish Republican Brotherhood]], the rising lasted from 24–30 April 1916.&lt;ref name=bbcirish/&gt; Members of the [[Irish Volunteers]], joined by the smaller [[Irish Citizen Army]], along with 200 members of [[Cumann na mBan]], seized key locations in [[Dublin]] and proclaimed an [[Irish Republic]] independent of Britain.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=6 June 2009|title=The Proclamation|publisher=BBC History|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/british/easterrising/insurrection/in04.shtml}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Army reinforcements were moved into Dublin and, by 28 April, the 1,600 rebels were facing 18 to 20,000 soldiers,&lt;ref name=bbcirish/&gt; the rising was suppressed after seven days of fighting, its leaders were [[court martial]]led and executed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=6 June 2009|title=Ireland and World War One|publisher=BBC History|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/british/britain_wwone/ireland_wwone_04.shtml|first=Professor Keith|last=Jeffery}}&lt;/ref&gt; Easter Rising casualties were 450 killed, 2,614 wounded, and nine missing, almost all in Dublin. The only significant action elsewhere was at [[Ashbourne, County Meath|Ashbourne]], {{convert|10|mi|km|abbr=on}} north of Dublin. Military casualties were 116 dead, 368 wounded and 9 missing. The Irish and Dublin police forces had 16 killed and 29 wounded, 254 non-combatant civilians died.&lt;ref name=bbcirish&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=6 June 2009|title=Easter Rising|publisher=BBC History|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/british/easterrising/insurrection/in03.shtml}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Salonika===
{{main article|Balkans Campaign (World War I)}}
[[File:2.75inchMountainGunKamberliSalonikaFrontJune1918.jpg|thumb|Men of the 4th (Highland) Mountain Brigade with a [[2.75 inch Mountain Gun|{{convert|2.75|in|mm|0|abbr=on}} mountain gun]], Salonika]]

A new front was opened in [[Salonika]] at the request of the Greek government, intending to support Serbian forces and oppose [[Bulgaria]]. The first troops of the [[British Salonika Army]], arrived in Salonika in October 1916, too late to prevent the Serbian Army from retreating into Albania and Greece. French, British and Russian troops arrived in Salonika between 1916 and 1917 and became known as the [[Allied Army of the Orient]] or ''Allied Army of the East'', under the overall command of French General [[Maurice Sarrail]].&lt;ref&gt;Tucker &amp; Roberts (2005), p. 423&lt;/ref&gt;

With the objective of destroying the Bulgarian Army, the French and British launched a new offensive in April 1917, without any significant success. A stalemate ensued without any movement by either side; the front became known as ''Europe's biggest internment camp for the Allies'' by the Germans.&lt;ref name=otherfronts&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=27 May 2009|title=Other Fronts|publisher= Western Front Association|first=Doctor David|last=Payne|url=http://www.westernfrontassociation.com/great-war-on-land/battlefields/323-cam-other-front.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; This situation lasted until 18 September 1918, when the British and Greek Armies, under the command of General George Milne attacked in the [[Dojran Lake|Lake Doiran]] Sector.&lt;ref name=otherfronts/&gt; The Bulgarian Army—now in retreat—signed an [[armistice]] on 30 September 1918.&lt;ref name=otherfronts/&gt;

===Italy===
{{main article|Italian Campaign (World War I)}}

Italy joined the war on the Allies' side on 5 May 1915, declaring war on [[Austria-Hungary]] on 23 May 1915 and on Germany on 28 August 1916. The British Army's involvement in the Italian campaign did not start until late 1917, when troops were sent to help prevent a defeat on the Italian front. On 24 October 1917 in the [[battle of Caporetto]] the Second Italian Army collapsed and the Italians were forced to retreat to the [[Piave River]], where they could be reinforced with five British and six French Divisions from the Western Front, complete with supporting arms and commanded by General [[Herbert Plumer]]. The reinforced Italians successfully managed to halt the Austro-Hungarian advance at the [[battle of the Piave river]]. During the Allied counter-attack in October 1918, the Austro-Hungarian Army collapsed after taking heavy losses at the [[battle of Vittorio Veneto]]. An armistice was signed shortly afterwards on 3 November 1918.&lt;ref name= otherfronts/&gt;

===China===
[[File:BritishTroopsArriveTsingtao1914.jpg|thumb|British troops arrive at Tsingtao 1914]]

In 1914, the British Army was involved in what became known as the [[Siege of Tsingtao]] when the 2nd Battalion [[South Wales Borderers]] landed in China in support of Japanese forces in the capture of the German port of [[Qingdao|Tsingtao]].&lt;ref&gt;Willmott &amp; Kindersley, p. 91&lt;/ref&gt; The British were part of a 23,000-strong task force which included a mixed British–Indian Brigade of 1,500 troops and the battleship {{HMS|Triumph|1903|6}}. A bombardment of the port started on 31 October 1914, and by 7 November, the Japanese 18th Division, 29th Infantry Brigade and the British–Indian Brigade, had stormed and captured the garrison and its 4,000 troops.&lt;ref name=otherfronts/&gt;

===East Africa===
{{main article|East African Campaign (World War I)}}

1914 also witnessed the commencement of the [[East African Campaign (World War I)|East African Campaign]] against [[Paul Erich von Lettow-Vorbeck|von Lettow-Vorbeck]]'s elusive German and African [[askari]] forces. Most British operations in Africa were carried out by African askari units such as the [[King's African Rifles]] (KAR), [[Union of South Africa|South African]] or [[British Indian Army|Indian Army]] units. The British force was led, in turn, by General Horace Smith-Dorrien, South African General Jan Smuts, and British General [[Reginald Hoskins|Arthur Reginald Hoskins]].&lt;ref name=otherfronts/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=27 May 2009 |title=Centre for First World War Studies |publisher=University of Birmingham |url=http://www.firstworldwar.bham.ac.uk/donkey/hoskins.htm |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20061014050843/http://www.firstworldwar.bham.ac.uk/donkey/hoskins.htm |archivedate=14 October 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The force was composed of units of the KAR and the [[9th (Secunderabad) Division|27th Bangalore Brigade]] from the British Indian Army, with the 2nd Battalion, [[Loyal Regiment (North Lancashire)]] under command. The German forces of von Lettow-Vorbeck's Schutztruppe remained undefeated and surrendered on 25 November 1918, 14 days after the Armistice in Europe.&lt;ref name=otherfronts/&gt;

The casualty rate amongst British and Empire troops, excluding the Africans, was 6,000 dead and 3,000 wounded. More troops died from diseases than from enemy action, and illness accounted for 70% of the total casualties.&lt;ref name=otherfronts/&gt;

===Gallipoli===
{{main article|Gallipoli Campaign|Landing at Anzac Cove|Landing at Cape Helles}}
[[File:V Beach Helles Gallipoli.jpg|thumb|left|V Beach, Helles [[Gallipoli]].]]

Turkey had entered the war on the German side on 31 October 1914. One of its first acts was to close the [[Dardanelles]] Straits to the Allies.&lt;ref name=otherfronts/&gt; In April 1915, following the failure of the Royal Navy's attempt to capture the Dardanelles, British and [[ANZAC]] forces landed on the Gallipoli peninsula, under the command of General Ian Hamilton.&lt;ref name= otherfronts/&gt; The main British attacks were the [[First Battle of Krithia|first]], [[Second Battle of Krithia|second]] and [[Third Battle of Krithia|third battles of Krithia]]. These were a series of attacks against the Turkish defences aimed at capturing the original objectives of 25 April 1915. They all failed to achieve their objectives.&lt;ref&gt;Haythornthwaite (1991), pp. 52–64&lt;/ref&gt; In August, another landing was made at [[Landing at Suvla Bay|Suvla Bay]]. The Suvla landing was reinforced by the arrival of the [[British 10th (Irish) Division|10th Division]] from Kitchener's [[Kitchener's Army|New Army]], [[British 53rd Division|53rd]], [[British 54th Division|54th]] first-line Territorial divisions and the dismounted [[yeomanry]] of the [[2nd Mounted Division]].&lt;ref name=otherfronts/&gt; The [[British 29th Division|29th Division]] was also moved from Helles to Suvla for one more push. The final British attempt to resuscitate the offensive came on 21 August, with attacks at [[Scimitar Hill (battle)|Scimitar Hill]] and [[Battle of Hill 60 (Gallipoli)|Hill 60]]. Control of these hills would have united the Anzac and Suvla fronts, but neither battle achieved success. When fighting at Hill 60 ceased on 29 August, the battle for the Sari Bair heights, and indeed, the battle for the peninsula, was effectively over; by January 1916, the [[Allies of World War I|Allies]] had withdrawn.&lt;ref name=otherfronts/&gt;

Estimates of casualties vary enormously, but of the around 480,000 Allied troops involved in the campaign, 180,000 were wounded and 44,000 died, 20,000 of the dead being British.&lt;ref name= otherfronts/&gt;

===Mesopotamia===
{{main article|Mesopotamian campaign}}
[[File:Maude in Baghdad.jpg|thumb|March 1917, British troops entering [[Baghdad]].]]

The British force fighting in [[Mesopotamia]] was principally drawn from the British Indian Army, with only one solely British formation, the [[13th (Western) Division]]. Its objective was to secure the [[Royal Navy]]'s oil supply from [[Persia]]. On 7 November 1914, the British Indian force—led by General Sir [[John Nixon (Indian Army officer)|John Nixon]]—invaded Mesopotamia, and on 23 November, entered [[Basrah]].&lt;ref name=otherfronts/&gt; After this initial invasion, there followed a disastrous and humiliating defeat for the British by the Turks at the [[Siege of Kut-al-Amara]] from 7 December 1915 – 29 April 1916, when the entire garrison of 13,000 British and Indian troops surrendered.&lt;ref name=otherfronts/&gt; The British reorganised and raised the number of available troops to 250,000.&lt;ref name=otherfronts/&gt; The British eventually regained momentum upon General [[Frederick Stanley Maude]] becoming commander, and a new offensive began in December 1916. On 24 February 1917, Kut-al-Amara fell to the joint British and Indian force, and [[Baghdad]] was captured in March 1917.&lt;ref name=otherfronts/&gt; A week after the capture of Baghdad, General Maude issued the [[Proclamation of Baghdad]], which contained the famous line, &quot;our armies do not come into your cities and lands as conquerors or enemies, but as liberators&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The proclamation of Baghdad|publisher=Harpers Magazine|accessdate=27 May 2009|url=http://www.harpers.org/archive/2003/05/007959}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lieutenant General Sir [[William Marshall (British Army officer)|William Marshall]] succeeded Maude following the latter's death from cholera on 18 November 1917. He continued with the ''River War'' until October 1918, when the British captured the [[Mosul]] oil fields, a development that led to the collapse of the Turkish forces. The [[Armistice of Mudros]] with Turkey was signed on 30 October 1918. During the campaign, 100,000 British and Indian casualties were caused. Of these, 53,000 died, with 13,000 of the dead succumbing to disease.&lt;ref name=otherfronts/&gt;

===Sinai and Palestine===
{{main article|Sinai and Palestine Campaign}}
[[File:Allenby enters Jerusalem 1917.jpg|thumb|left|General [[Edmund Allenby]], enters [[Jerusalem]] on foot out of respect for the Holy City, 31 December 1917]]

The Sinai and Palestine Campaign was fuelled by criticism of the policy of a static defence of the [[Suez canal]], which employed six infantry divisions and five mounted brigades.&lt;ref&gt;Tucker &amp; Roberts (2005), p. 1091&lt;/ref&gt; After the repulse of the Turkish [[First Suez Offensive]], nine divisions were sent to the Western Front and one to Mesopotamia.&lt;ref&gt;MacMunn and Falls (1928), p. 98&lt;/ref&gt;

The British Army in the Sinai and Palestine subsequently included the [[British 10th Division|10th]], [[British 42nd Division|42nd]], [[52nd (Lowland) Infantry Division|52nd]], [[53rd (Welsh) Infantry Division|53rd]], [[British 54th Division|54th]], [[British 60th Division|60th]], [[74th (Yeomanry) Division|74th]] and [[British 75th Division|75th]] divisions. British yeomanry formed part of the [[ANZAC Mounted Division]], [[Australian Mounted Division]] and [[Yeomanry Mounted Division]]s. With the [[Imperial Camel Corps]] Brigade, mounted troops formed the Desert Column. The whole force—known as the Egyptian Expeditionary Force (EEF)—was under the command of General Sir [[Archibald Murray]] in [[Cairo]].&lt;ref&gt;MacMunn and Falls (1928), pp. 356–358&lt;/ref&gt;

Murray made steady progress against the Turkish forces, which were defeated in the battles of [[battle of Romani|Romani]], [[battle of Magdhaba|Magdhaba]] and [[battle of Rafa|Rafa]]. However, he was repulsed at the [[First Battle of Gaza|first]] and [[second battle of Gaza]] in 1917.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|accessdate=26 May 2009|title=The First Battle of Gaza|publisher=New Zealand Electronic Test Center|url=http://www.nzetc.org/tm/scholarly/tei-WH1-Came-t1-body-d9.html}}&lt;/ref&gt; The defeat in the Second Battle of Gaza prompted the [[War Office]] to change the command of the EEF, and on 28 June 1917, Murray was replaced by General Sir Edmund Allenby, who reinvigorated the campaign.&lt;ref&gt;MacMunn and Falls (1928), p. 368&lt;/ref&gt;

Allenby reorganised his forces along more conventional lines. The EEF now included the [[Desert Mounted Corps]], under [[Lieutenant General (Australia)|Lieutenant General]] Sir [[Harry Chauvel]]; [[XX Corps (United Kingdom)|XX Corps]] under Lieutenant General Sir [[Philip Chetwode, 1st Baron Chetwode|Phillip Chetwode]] and [[XXI Corps (United Kingdom)|XXI Corps]] under Lieutenant General [[Edward Bulfin]].&lt;ref&gt;Falls (1930), p. 16&lt;/ref&gt; In October 1917, they defeated the Turkish forces in the [[third battle of Gaza]] and the [[Battle of Mughar Ridge]], which succeeded in causing the [[Ottoman Empire|Ottoman]] Seventh and Eighth Armies to withdraw towards [[Jerusalem]] and [[Haifa]] respectively. This led to the [[Battle of Jerusalem (1917)|capture of Jerusalem]] in December 1917.&lt;ref name=otherfronts/&gt;

In February and April 1918, Australian mounted troops took part in two raids east across the Jordan River near Es Salt, a village in Palestine {{convert|14|mi|km|abbr=on}} west of [[Amman]]. Although these raids were unsuccessful, they encouraged Turkish commanders to believe that the main British effort would be launched across the Jordan, when in fact it would be launched along the coastal plain.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=AWM Battle Information: Es Salt Raid|publisher=Australian War Memorial| date=|url=http://google.com/search?q=cache:eIG4d80BOeMJ:www.awm.gov.au/units/event_27.asp+es+salt+raid+1918&amp;cd=1&amp;hl=en&amp;ct=clnk&amp;gl=au&amp;client=firefox-a|accessdate=3 May 2009}} {{dead link|date=June 2010|bot=DASHBot}}&lt;/ref&gt; The EEF was greatly weakened at this time by the crisis in France, which led to the despatch of the 52nd and 74th Divisions to the Western Front, the breaking up of the Yeomanry Mounted Division, and the replacement of most of the British infantry in four of the remaining divisions with Indian troops.&lt;ref&gt;Falls (1930), pp. 413–421&lt;/ref&gt; In September 1918, Allenby's forces won the decisive [[Battle of Megiddo (1918)|Megiddo Offensive]], which precipitated the [[Armistice of Mudros]] with the Ottoman Empire, which was signed on 31 October 1918.&lt;ref&gt;Karsh (2001), p. 327&lt;/ref&gt;

Total Allied casualties in the Sinai and Palestine campaign were 60,000 of which 20,000 were killed. Some 15,000 of the dead were British.&lt;ref name=otherfronts/&gt;

===Persia===
{{main article|Caucasus Campaign}}

Following the [[Russian Revolution (1917)|abdication of the Russian Tsar]] in 1917, the [[Caucasus Campaign|Caucasus Front]] collapsed, leaving Central Asia—and beyond it India—open to the Turkish Army. The [[War Office]] responded with a plan to send a force of hand-picked British officers and NCOs to organise any remaining Russian forces or civilians who were ready to fight the [[Ottoman Empire|Turkish forces]]. This force became known as [[Dunsterforce]] after its commander, [[Major-General (United Kingdom)|Major General]] [[Lionel Charles Dunsterville]], the inspiration for the titular character of [[Rudyard Kipling]]'s novel [[Stalky &amp; Co.]]. It arrived in [[Baku]] in August 1918. It was hoped that Dunsterforce could raise an army from the Christian [[Georgia (country)|Georgian]], Armenian and [[Assyrian/Chaldean/Syriac people|Assyrian]] people who had supported the [[Russian Empire|Russians]] and had historically feared the Turks. While Dunsterforce had some success the task proved beyond its ability.&lt;ref&gt;Bean (1937), pp. 728–731&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fighting the Senussi Arabs===
{{main article|Senussi Campaign}}

In late November 1915, in response to the growing threat from a pro-Turkish Islamic Arab sect known as the [[Senussi]], a composite British body known as the 'Western Frontier Force' was sent into the [[Libyan Desert]] to [[Mersa Matruh]], under the command of British Indian Army officer Major General Alexander Wallace. A series of sharp battles against the Arabs ensued at Um Rakhum, Gebel Medwa, and Halazin during December and January. The Western Desert Force, now under Major General [[William Peyton]], re-occupied [[Sidi Barrani]] and [[Sallum]] in February and March 1916. Shipwrecked British seamen from HMT ''Moorina'' and HMS ''Tara'', who had been held at Bir Hakeim, were rescued by a contingent of [[Armored car (military)|armoured car]]s led by the [[Hugh Grosvenor, 2nd Duke of Westminster|Duke of Westminster]].&lt;ref&gt;Bean (1929), pp. 959–964&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
{{further information|History of the British Army#Inter-War period (1919–1939)}}

The British Army during [[World War I]] was the largest military force that Britain had put into the field up to that point.&lt;ref name=tr816&gt;Tucker &amp; Roberts (2006), p. 816&lt;/ref&gt; On the [[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]], the [[British Expeditionary Force (World War I)|British Expeditionary Force]] ended the war as the strongest fighting force, more experienced than the [[American Expeditionary Forces|United States Army]] and its morale was in better shape than the [[French Army in World War I|French Army]].&lt;ref name=tr816/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;By November 1918, the U.S. Army, with ration strength of 2 million men, exceeded the BEF both in size and percentage of the front occupied.(Stevenson 2011 p 245, 249, 269) BEF ration strength peaked at 1.9 million at the start of September 1918 (after the redeployment of troops from Palestine and Italy after the German [[Spring Offensive]]s), but had dropped to 1.86 million at the war’s end. Following the extension of the British line early in 1918, the BEF occupied 24.8% of the front in March, but after the deployment of U.S. troops this dropped to 17.3% in July and remained at 17.6% in November. The U.S. sector was 3.7% of the front in March, 11.7% in July and 20.9% in November. The French sector was 66.6% in March and July, but had dropped to 55.3% in November, freeing up French reserves for an offensive into Lorraine, which was cancelled because of the [[Armistice of 11 November 1918|armistice]].(Boff 2012 pp40-2) Many of an Army’s ration strength were labourers and logistical personnel, and just over half were combat troops (of whom a decreasing proportion were infantry as the war progressed). By the end of the war, the BEF “field strength”, at 1.202m, still fractionally exceeded the U.S. (1.175m), but was still less than the French 1.554m (French field strength was down from a peak of over 2.2m in July 1916).(Watson 2008, p157)&lt;/ref&gt;

The cost of victory, however, was high. The official &quot;final and corrected&quot; casualty figures for the British Army—including the [[Territorial Force]]—were issued on 10 March 1921. The losses for the period between 4 August 1914 and 30 September 1919 included 573,507 &quot;[[killed in action]], died from wounds and died of other causes&quot; and 254,176 [[Missing in action|missing]] (minus 154,308 released [[Prisoner of war|prisoners of war]]), for a net total of 673,375 dead and missing. Casualty figures also indicated that there were 1,643,469 [[Wounded in action|wounded]].&lt;ref&gt;The Army Council (1921), pp. 62–72&lt;/ref&gt;

For some, the fighting did not end in 1918. The British Army dispatched troops to Russia during the [[Allied intervention in the Russian Civil War]], which was followed by the [[Anglo-Irish War]] in January 1919 and the [[Third Anglo-Afghan War]] in May 1919.&lt;ref&gt;Barthorp (2002), p. 152&lt;/ref&gt; The Third Afghan War was followed by the [[1920 conflict between British forces and Somaliland dervishes]]. Those not involved in fighting or occupation duties were demobilised. The demobilisation of 4,000,000 men that followed the end of the war had, within a year, reduced the British Army to 800,000 men; by November 1920, two years after the signing of the [[Armistice of 11 November 1918|Armistice]], this figure had fallen to 370,000 men.&lt;ref&gt;Jeffery (1984), p. 13&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Ten Year Rule]] was introduced in August 1919, which stipulated that the [[British Armed Forces]] should draft their estimates &quot;on the assumption that the [[British Empire]] would not be engaged in any great war during the next ten years&quot;. In 1928, [[Winston Churchill]], as [[Chancellor of the Exchequer]], successfully urged the Cabinet to make the rule self-perpetuating and hence it was in force unless specifically countermanded.&lt;ref&gt;Kennedy (1976), pp. 273–296&lt;/ref&gt; There were cuts in defence spending as a result of this rule, falling from £766 million in 1919–1920, to £189 million in 1921–1922, and to £102 million in 1932.&lt;ref&gt;Kennedy (1976), p. 231&lt;/ref&gt;

The British Army tried to learn the lessons of the First World War, and adopt them into its pre-war doctrine.&lt;ref&gt;French (2000), pp. 14–15&lt;/ref&gt; In the 1920s, and much of the 1930s, the General Staff tried to establish a small, mechanised, professional army and formed the [[Experimental Mechanized Force]] but, with the lack of any identified threat, its main function reverted to [[garrison]] duties around the British Empire.&lt;ref&gt;French (2000), p. 15&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{reflist|3}}

==Further reading==
{{portal|World War I}}
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite book|last=Addington|first=Larry H|year=1984|title=The Patterns of War Since the Eighteenth Century|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|isbn=0-7099-0561-0}}
*{{cite book|last=Army Council|title=General Annual Report of the British Army 1912–1919. Parliamentary Paper 1921, XX, Cmd.1193|year=1921|publisher=Parliament United Kingdom}}
*{{cite book|last=Ashworth|first=Tony|title=Trench Warfare 1914–1918|year=2000|publisher=Macmillan Press, London|isbn=0-330-48068-5}}
*{{cite book|last=Badsey|first=Stephen|year=2008|title=Doctrine and Reform in the British Cavalry 1880–1918|publisher=Ashgate Publishing|isbn=0-7546-6467-8}}
*{{cite book|last=Bailey|first=Jonathan B A|year=1989|title=Field Artillery and Firepower|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|isbn=0-85066-811-5}}
*{{cite book|last=Barthorp|first=Michael|title=Afghan Wars and the North-West Frontier 1839–1947| year=2002|publisher=Cassell|location=London|language=|isbn=0-304-36294-8}}
*{{cite book | last=Bean| first=C.E.W.| authorlink = Charles Bean | year=1929 | title=The AIF in France: 1916 | edition=12th| series=Official History of Australia in the War of 1914–1918 |volume= Volume III |publisher=Australian War Memorial| location=Canberra | url=http://www.awm.gov.au/histories/first_world_war/volume.asp?levelID=67889 | accessdate=10 May 2009 }}
*{{cite book | last = Bean | first = C.E.W. | authorlink = Charles Bean| year = 1937 | url = http://www.awm.gov.au/histories/chapter.asp?volume=6 | title = The Australian Imperial Force in France December 1917 – May 1918 | format = PDF | series = Official History of Australia in the War of 1914–1918|volume=Volume V| publisher= [[Australian War Memorial]] | location = [[Canberra]] }}
*{{cite book|last=Beckett|first=Ian Frederick William|last2=Simpson|first2=Keith|title=A Nation in Arms: A Social Study of the British Army in the First World War|publisher=Manchester University Press ND|year=1985|isbn=0-7190-1737-8}}
*{{cite book|last=Bickford Smith|first=Vivian|last2=Van Heyningen|first2=E|last3=Worden|first3= Nigel|year=1999|publisher=New Africa Books|title=Cape Town in the Twentieth Century: An Illustrated Social History|isbn=0-86486-384-5}}
*{{cite book|last=Blaxland|first=Gregory|title=Amiens 1918|publisher=Star Book|year=1968|isbn= 0-352-30833-8}}
*{{cite book|last=Boff|first=Jonathan|title=Winning and Losing on the Western Front|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=2012|isbn= 978-1-107-44902-2}}
*{{cite book|last1=Bond|first1=Brian|last2=Cave|first2=Nigel|title=Haig – A Reappraisal 70 Years On|publisher=Pen &amp; Sword|origyear=1998|year=2009|isbn=978-1-84415-887-4}}
* Bond, Brian, et al., ''Look To Your Front: Studies in the First World War'' (1999) 11 chapters by experts on noncombat aspects of First World War army
*{{cite book|last=Bourne|first=J M|year=2001|publisher=Routledge|isbn=0-415-14179-6|title=Who's who in World War One}}
*{{cite book|last=Bragg|first=William|authorlink=William Lawrence Bragg|title=Sound Ranging|work= Artillery Survey in the First World War|location=Elstree|publisher=Field Survey Association|year= 1971|pages=31–40|isbn=0-9501743-0-0}}
*{{cite book|last=Bromley|first=Ian|title=Bromley: A Midlands Family History—And the Search for the Leicestershire Origin|year=2006|publisher=Troubador Publishing|isbn=1-905237-95-2}}
*{{cite book|last=Bull|first=Stephen|title=World War I Trench Warfare: 1914–16|publisher=Osprey Publishing|year=2002|isbn = 1-84176-198-2}}
*{{cite book|last=Bull|first=Stephen|year=2004|publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group|title= Encyclopedia of Military Technology and Innovation|isbn=1-57356-557-1}}
* Carver, Michael. ''Seven Ages of the British Army'' (1984) Covers 1900 to 1918
*{{cite book|last=Cassidy|first=Robert M|title=Counterinsurgency and the Global War on Terror: Military Culture and Irregular War|year=2006|publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group|isbn=0-275-98990-9}}
*{{cite book|last=Chandler|first=David|authorlink=David G. Chandler|title=The Oxford History of the British Army|year=2003|publisher=Oxford paperbacks|isbn=0-19-280311-5}}
*{{cite book|last=Chandler|first=Malcolm|year=2001|title=The Home Front, 1914–18|publisher= Heinemann|isbn=0-435-32729-1}}
*{{cite book|last=Chappell|first=Mike|title=The British Army in World War I: The Western Front 1914–16|publisher=Osprey Publishing|year=2003|isbn=1-84176-399-3}}
*{{cite book|last=Clark|first=Dale|last2=Delf|first2=Brian|title=British Artillery 1914–19: Field Army Artillery|publisher=Osprey Publishing|year=2004|isbn=1-84176-688-7}}
*{{cite book|last=Connelly|first=Mark|year=2006|title=Steady the Buffs!: A Regiment, a Region, and the Great War|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=0-19-927860-1}}
*{{cite book|last=Corrigan|first=Gordon|title=Mud, Blood &amp; Poppycock|publisher=Cassell|year=2002|isbn=0-304-36659-5}}
*{{cite book|last1=Davies|first1=Frank|last2=Maddocks|first2=Graham|title=Bloody Red Tabs: General Officer Casualties of the Great War, 1914–1918|publisher=Leo Cooper|year=1995|isbn=0-85052-463-6}}
*{{cite book|last=Ensor|first=(Sir) Robert|authorlink=Robert Ensor|title=England: 1870–1914. (The Oxford History of England, Volume XIV)|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Oxford|year=1936| isbn=0-19-821705-6|edition=Revised, 1980}}
*{{cite book|last=Falls|first=Cyril Bentham|authorlink=Cyril Falls|title=Military Operations – Egypt and Palestine: Vol II. From June 1917 to the end of the War|series=[[History of the Great War]]|publisher=HMSO|year=1930|location=London|oclc=314227387}}
*{{cite book |last=Ford |first=Roger |year=2005 |title=The World's Great Machine Guns from 1860 to the Present Day |location=London (UK) |isbn=1-84509-161-2 |publisher=Amber Books}}
*{{cite book|last=Franks|first=Norman L|last2=Van Wyngarden|first2=Greg|year=2007|title=Albatros Aces of World War I|publisher=Osprey Publishing|isbn=1-84603-179-6}}
*{{cite book|last=French|first=David|year=2000|title=Raising Churchill's Army: The British Army and the War against Germany, 1919–1945|publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=0-19-820641-0}}
*{{cite book |last=Ford |first=Roger |year=2005 |title=The World's Great Machine Guns from 1860 to the Present Day |publisher=Amber Books |location=London|isbn=1-84509-161-2}}&lt;!--|publisher=Silverdale Books - shown as 2nd publisher of the book! A quick search linked the isbn with Amber, so this seems to be the incorrect one--&gt;
*{{cite book|first=Thomas|last=Frothingham|title=A Guide to the Military History of the World War, 1914–1918|publisher=Little, Brown|year=1920|oclc=949616}} Digitized 21 November 2007
*{{cite book|last=Gardner|first=Nikolas|year=2003|title=Trial By Fire: Command and the British Expeditionary Force in 1914|publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group|isbn=0-313-32473-5}}
*{{cite book|last=Griffith|first=Paddy|title=Battle Tactics of the Western Front: British Army's Art of Attack, 1916–18|publisher=Yale|year=1996|isbn=0-300-06663-5}}
*{{cite book|last=Griffiths|first=William|last2=Griess|first2=Thomas|year=2003|title=The Great War|publisher=Square One Publishers|isbn=0-7570-0158-0}}
*{{cite book|last=Gudmundsson|first=Bruce|year=2005|publisher=Osprey Publishing|title=The British Expeditionary Force 1914–15|isbn=1-84176-902-9}}
*{{cite book|last=Gudmundsson|first=Bruce I|last2=Anderson|first2=Duncan|year=2007|title=The British Army on the Western Front 1916|publisher=Osprey Publishing|isbn=1-84603-111-7}}
*{{cite book|last=Haythornthwaite|first=Philip J|year=1991|publisher=Osprey Publishing|title= Gallipoli, 1915: frontal assault on Turkey|isbn=1-85532-111-4}}
*{{cite book|last=Heathcote|first=T A|year=1999|title=The British Field Marshals 1736–1997| publisher=Pen &amp; Sword Books|isbn=0-85052-696-5}}
*{{cite book|last=Hofmann|first=George F|title=Through Mobility We Conquer: The Mechanization of U.S. Cavalry|publisher=University Press of Kentucky|year=2006|isbn=0-8131-2403-4}}
*{{cite book|last=Hogg|first=Ian V|authorlink=Ian V. Hogg|year=1971|isbn=0-356-03745-2|title=Barrage: the Guns in Action|publisher=Macdonald}}
*{{cite book|last=Hogg|first=Ian|authorlink=Ian V. Hogg|last2=Thurston|year=1972|title=British Artillery Weapons &amp; Ammunition 1914–1918|publisher=Ian Alle|location=London|isbn=0-7110-0381-5|first2=L F}}
*{{cite book|last=Holmes|first=Richard|title=Tommy: The British Soldier on the Western Front, 1914–1918|authorlink=Richard Holmes (military historian)|publisher=HarperCollins|year=2004|isbn=0-00-713751-6}}
*{{cite book|last=Humble|first=Richarg|title=Tanks|year=1977|publisher=Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson|location=London|isbn=978-0-29777-312-2}}
*{{cite book|last=Jarymowycz|first=Roman|last2=Starry|first2=Donn|title=Cavalry from Hoof to Track| year=2008|publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group|isbn=0-275-98726-4}}
*{{cite book|last=Jones|first=Archer|year=1996|publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group|title=Elements of Military Strategy: An Historical Approach|isbn=0-275-95526-5}}
*{{cite book|last=Johnstone|first=Charles H L |year=2005|title=Famous Generals of the Great War Who Led the United States and Her Allies to a Glorious Victory|publisher=Kessinger Publishing|isbn= 1-4179-0769-X}}
*{{cite book|last=Karsh|first=Efraim|title = Empires of the Sand: The Struggle for Mastery in the Middle East|publisher=Harvard University Press|year=2001|isbn=0-674-00541-4}}
*{{cite book|last=Keegan|first=John|authorlink=John Keegan|title=The First World War|publisher= Vintage Books|year=1998|isbn=0-375-70045-5}}
*{{cite book|last=Keegan|first=John|authorlink=John Keegan|last2=Wheatcroft|first2=Andrew|year=1996 |publisher=Routledge|title=Who's Who in Military History: from 1453 to the present day|isbn= 0-415-12722-X}}
*{{cite book|last=Kennedy|first=Paul|year=1976|title=The Rise and Fall of British Naval Mastery| publisher=University of Michigan|isbn=0-684-14609-6}}
*{{cite book|last=Langley|first=Andrew|title=The Hundred Days Offensive: The Allies' Push to Win World War I|publisher=Compass Point Books|year=2008|isbn=0-7565-3858-0}}
*{{cite book|last=Liddell Hart|first=Basil|title=History of the First World War|publisher=Pan|year= 1930|isbn=0-330-23354-8}}
*{{cite book|last=MacMunn|first=George|last2=Falls|first2=Cyril|authorlink2=Cyril Falls|title= Military Operations – Egypt and Palestine Vol I. From the outbreak of war with Germany to June 1917 |series=[[History of the Great War]]|publisher=HMSO|year=1928|location=London }}
*{{cite book|last=Malam|first=John|year=2003|title=The World War I Armistice: 11&amp;nbsp;November 1918| publisher=Cherrytree Books|isbn=1-84234-200-2}}
*{{cite journal|first=General Sir James|last=Marshall-Cornwall|authorlink=James Marshall-Cornwall|title=Staff Officer 1914–1918|journal=War Monthly|issue=42|publisher=[[Marshall Cavendish]]|location=London|year=1977}}
*{{cite book|last=Maze|first=Robert J|year=2002|title=Howdah to High Power: A Century of Breechloading Service Pistols (1867–1967)|publisher=Excalibur Publications|location=Tucson, Arizona |isbn=1-880677-17-2}}
*{{cite book|last=Messenger|first=Charles|year=2005|title=Call to Arms: The British Army, 1914–18 |publisher=Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson|location=London|isbn=0-297-84695-7}}
*{{cite book|last=Millett|first=Allen Reed|last2=Murray|first2=Williamson|year=1988|title=Military Effectiveness: The First World War|publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin|location=London|isbn=0-04-445053-2|oclc= 220072268}}
*{{cite book|last=Moorhead|first=Alan|year=2002|publisher=Harper Collins|title=Gallipoli|isbn= 0-06-093708-4}}
*{{cite book|last=Nicholls|first=Jonathon|title=Cheerful Sacrifice: The Battle of Arras 1917| publisher=Pen and Sword Books|year=2005|isbn=1-84415-326-6}}
*{{cite book|last=Olsen|first=James Stuart|last2=Shadle|first2=Robert|title=Historical Dictionary of the British Empire|year=1996|publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group|isbn=0-313-29366-X}}
*{{cite book|last=Page|first=Melvin Eugene|year=2003|title=Colonialism: An International, Social, Cultural, and Political Encyclopedia|isbn=1-57607-335-1|publisher=ABC-Clio|location=Santa Barbara, California}}
*{{cite book|first=Malcolm|last=Pearce|first2=Geoffrey|last2=Stewart|title=British Political History, 1867–2001: Democracy and Decline|year=2002|publisher=Routledge|isbn=0-415-26869-9}}
*{{cite book|last=Rankin|first=Nicholas|authorlink=Nicholas Rankin|title=Churchill's Wizards| publisher=Faber and Faber|year=2008|isbn=978-0-571-22195-0}}
*{{cite book|last=Robbins|first=Simon|year=2005|title=British Generalship on the Western Front 1914–18: Defeat into Victory|publisher=Routledge|isbn=0-415-35006-9}}
*{{cite book|last=Searle|first=G R|year=2005|title=A New England?: Peace and War 1886–1918| publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=0-19-928440-7}}
*{{cite book|last=Sheffield|first=Gary|authorlink=Gary Sheffield (historian)|title=War on the Western Front: In the Trenches of World War I|publisher=Osprey Publishing|year=2007|location=|isbn= 1-84603-210-5}}
*{{cite book|last=Sheffield|first=G D|authorlink=Gary Sheffield (historian)|year=2000|publisher= Palgrave Macmillan|title=Leadership in the Trenches: Officer-man Relations, Morale and Discipline in the British Army in the Era of the First World War|isbn=0-312-22640-3}}
*{{cite book|last=Skennerton|first=Ian|year=1988|title=British Small Arms of World War 2|publisher= Ian Skennerton|location=Margate QLD (Australia)|isbn=0-949749-09-5}}
*{{cite book|last=Smith|first=Joseph E.|year=1973|title=Small Arms of the World (10th Revised Edition)|publisher=Stackpole Books|location=Harrisburg, Pennsylvania|isbn=0-88365-155-6}}
*{{cite book|last=Stevenson|first=David|title=With Our Backs to the Wall|publisher=Penguin|year=2011|isbn= 978-0-141-02079-2 }}
*{{cite book|last=Swinton|first=Ernest Dunlop|authorlink=Ernest Dunlop Swinton|title=Twenty Years After; The Battlefields of 1914–18: Then and Now|publisher=G. Newnes|year=1936}} Digitized 10 June 2008
*{{cite book|last=Sumner|first=Ian|last2=Konstan|first2=Angus|last3=Chappell|first3=Mike|title=The Indian Army 1914–1947|year=2001|publisher=Osprey Publishing|isbn=1-84176-196-6}}
*{{cite book|last=Taylor|first=A. J. P.|authorlink=A. J. P. Taylor|title=English History 1914–1945 (The Oxford History of England)|year=2001|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=USA|isbn= 0-19-280140-6}}
*{{cite book|last1=Tucker|first1=Spencer|last2=Roberts|first2=Priscilla Mary|title=World War I: Encyclopedia|year=2005|publisher=ABC-CLIO|isbn=1-85109-420-2}}
*{{cite book|last=Tucker|first=Stephen|year=2001|publisher=Routledge|title=Who's Who in Twentieth Century Warfare|isbn=0-415-23497-2}}
*{{cite book|last=Tucker|first=Spencer|title=The European Powers in the First World War: An Encyclopedia|last2=Matysek Wood|first2=Laura|last3=Murphy|first3=Justin D|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|year=1999|isbn=0-8153-3351-X}}
*{{cite book|last=Turner|first=Alexander|last2=Dennis|first2=Peter|title=Cambrai 1917: The Birth of Armoured Warfare|publisher=Osprey Publishing|year=2007|isbn=1-84603-147-8}}
*{{cite book|author=War Office|title=History of the Ministry of Munitions, 1922. Volume XI, Part I Trench Warfare Supplies|publisher=Facsimile reprint by Imperial War Museum and Naval &amp; Military Press|year=2008|isbn=1-84734-885-8}}
*{{cite book|title=First World War|first=H P|last=Willmott|first2=Dorling|last2=Kindersley|year= 2008|publisher=Dorling Kindersley|isbn=1-4053-2986-6}}
*{{cite book|last=Watson|first=Alexander|title=Enduring the Great War|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=2008|isbn= 978-0-521-12308-2 }}
* Winter, Denis. ''Death's Men: Soldiers of the Great War'' (1978)
*{{cite book|last=Wrigley|first=Chris|year=2002|title=Winston Churchill: A Biographical Companion| publisher=ABC CLIO|isbn=0-87436-990-8}}
*{{cite book|last=Wolff|first=Leon|title=In Flanders Fields, Passchendaele 1917|publisher=Penguin| year=2001|isbn=0-14-139079-4}}
*{{cite book|last=Woodhead|first=David R|year=1998|title=Field Marshal Sir William Robertson: Chief of the Imperial General Staff in the Great War|publisher=Greenwood Publishing|isbn=0-275-95422-6}}
*{{cite book|last=Zabecki|first=David|title=The German 1918 Offensives: A Case Study of The Operational Level of War|publisher=Routledge|year=2006|isbn=0-415-35600-8}}
*{{cite book|last=Zuehlke|first=Mark|year=2006|publisher=Douglas &amp; McIntyre|title=Canadian Military Atlas: Four Centuries of Conflict from New France to Kosovo|isbn=1-55365-209-6}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|British Army in World War I}}

{{British Cavalry Regiments World War I}}
{{British Infantry Regiments World War I}}
{{GreatWarBritishWeapons}}
{{World War I}}

{{good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:British Army During World War I}}
[[Category:United Kingdom in World War I]]
[[Category:British Army in World War I]]
[[Category:British Empire in World War I]]
[[Category:Military units and formations of the United Kingdom in World War I| ]]</text>
      <sha1>h2ym3nypwjksghr9w5gynkg9p7u6do7</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
