<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Casimir Pulaski</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>85768</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749861036</id>
      <parentid>747157072</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-16T15:25:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 3 sources and tagging 0 as dead. #IABot (v1.2.7.1)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="56952">{{about|the Polish military leader|places and things named after him|Commemoration of Casimir Pulaski|other uses of &quot;Pulaski&quot;|Pulaski (disambiguation)}}
{{good article}}

{{Use mdy dates|date=June 2016}}

{{Infobox military person
| name =Casimir Pulaski
| native_name = Kazimierz Pułaski
| image = Kazimierz Pułaski.PNG
| image_size = 225px
| caption = A painting of Casimir Pulaski, by [[Jan Styka]].
| birth_date = {{birth date|1747|03|04}}{{Ref|a|a}}
| birth_place = [[Winiary, Warka|Winiary]], [[Polish–Lithuanian Commonwealth|Poland]] 
| death_date = {{death date and age|1779|10|11|1745|03|06}}
| death_place = [[Savannah, Georgia]], United States
| placeofburial = [[Squares of Savannah, Georgia|Monterey Square]], Savannah
| placeofburial_label =
| allegiance = [[Polish–Lithuanian Commonwealth]]&lt;br /&gt;United States
| serviceyears=1762–1779
| unit=[[Pulaski's Legion]]
| battles=[[War of the Bar Confederation]], [[American Revolutionary War]] ([[Siege of Savannah]])
| rank = U.S. [[brigadier general (United States)|Brigadier General]]
| branch = [[Military of the Polish–Lithuanian Commonwealth|Army of the Polish–Lithuanian Commonwealth]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Continental Army]]
| signature = Kazimierz Pułaski Signature.svg
}}

&lt;!-- Pulaski was not a count. Please do not add count to his name. See note b for details--&gt;'''Kazimierz Michał Władysław Wiktor Pułaski''' of [[Ślepowron coat of arms|Ślepowron]] ({{IPA-pol|kaˈʑimʲɛʂ puˈwaskʲi|-|Pl-Kazimierz_Pułaski.ogg}}; {{lang-en|'''Casimir Pulaski'''}}; March 6, 1745&lt;ref name=&quot;fm&quot;&gt;[[#Makarewicz|Makarewicz, 1998]]&lt;/ref&gt; {{spaced ndash}} October 11, 1779) was a [[szlachta|Polish nobleman]]{{Ref|b|b}}, soldier and military commander who has been called with his [[Hungarians|Hungarian]] friend [[Michael Kovats|Michael Kovats de Fabriczy]] &quot;the fathers of the American [[cavalry]]&quot;.

Born in [[Winiary, Warka|Winiary]] and following in his father's footsteps, he became interested in politics at an early age and soon became involved in the military and the revolutionary affairs in Poland (the [[Polish–Lithuanian Commonwealth]]). Pulaski was one of the leading military commanders for the [[Bar Confederation]] and fought against Russian domination of the Commonwealth. When this uprising failed, he was driven into exile. Following a recommendation by [[Benjamin Franklin]], Pulaski immigrated to North America to help in the cause of the [[American Revolutionary War]]. He distinguished himself throughout the revolution, most notably when he saved the life of [[George Washington]]. Pulaski became a [[General officer|general]] in the [[Continental Army]], created the [[Pulaski Cavalry Legion]] and reformed the American cavalry as a whole. At the [[Siege of Savannah|Battle of Savannah]], while leading a daring charge against British forces, he was gravely wounded, and died shortly thereafter.

Pulaski has been remembered as a hero who fought for independence and freedom both in Poland and in the United States. Numerous places and events are named in his honor, and he is commemorated by many works of art. Pulaski is one of only eight people to be awarded [[Honorary citizen of the United States|honorary United States citizenship]]. He never married and had no descendants. Despite his fame, there have been uncertainties and controversies surrounding both his place and date of birth and burial.

== Personal life ==

[[File:POL COA Ślepowron.svg|thumb|upright|left|alt=Ślepowron coat of arms|[[Ślepowron coat of arms|Ślepowron coat-of-arms]]]]

Pulaski was born on March 4, 1747, in the [[manor house]] of the [[Pułaski family]] in [[Winiary, Warka|Winiary]], Poland.&lt;ref name=&quot;fm&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=booklet&gt;[[#DOB|Poles in America Foundation, 2012]]&lt;/ref&gt;{{Ref|a|a}} Casimir was the second eldest son of [[Marianna Zielińska]] and [[Józef Pułaski]], who was an ''[[advocatus]]'' at the [[Crown Tribunal]], the [[Starost]] of [[Warka]], and one of the town's most notable inhabitants. He was a brother of [[Franciszek Ksawery Pułaski]] and [[Antoni Pułaski]]. His family bore the [[Ślepowron coat of arms|Ślepowron]] [[coat of arms]].&lt;ref name=&quot;psb386&quot;&gt;[[#Szczygielski86|Szczygielski, 1986]], p. 386&lt;/ref&gt; The Pułaski family was [[Roman Catholic]]&lt;ref&gt;[[#Griffin1907|Griffin, 1907]], p. 4&lt;/ref&gt; and early in his youth, Casimir Pulaski attended an elite college run by [[Theatines]], a male [[Catholic religious order|religious order of the Catholic Church]] in Warsaw, but did not finish his education.&lt;ref name=&quot;psb386&quot;/&gt;

There is some circumstantial evidence that Pulaski was a [[Freemason]]. When [[Gilbert du Motier, Marquis de Lafayette]] laid the cornerstone of the monument erected in Pulaski's honor in Savannah in 1824, a full Masonic ceremony took place with Richard T. Turner, High Priest of the Georgia chapter, conducting the ceremony. Other sources claim Pulaski was a member of the Masonic Army Lodge in Maryland. A Masonic Lodge in Chicago is named ''Casimir Pulaski Lodge, No.1167'' and a brochure issued by them claims he obtained the degree of Master Mason on June 19, 1779, and was buried with full Masonic honors. To date no surviving documents of Pulaski's actual membership have been found.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Denslow|Denslow, 2004]], p. 370&lt;/ref&gt;

{{clear}}

== Military career ==

[[File:ChelmonskiJozef.1875.KazimierzPulaskiPodCzestochowa.jpg|thumb|284px|alt=A painting by Józef Chełmoński depicting Pulaski at Częstochowa|Pulaski at Częstochowa&lt;br&gt;an 1875 painting by [[Józef Chełmoński]]]]
In 1762, Pulaski started his military career as a [[Page (occupation)|page]] of [[Carl Christian Joseph of Saxony, Duke of Courland]] and vassal of the Polish king. He spent six months at the ducal court in [[Jelgava|Mitau]], during which the court was interned in the palaces by the Russian forces occupying the area. He then returned to Warsaw, and his father gave him the village of [[Zezulińce]] in [[Podolia|Podole]]; from that time Pulaski used the title of Starost of Zezulińce.&lt;ref name=&quot;psb386&quot;/&gt;

=== Bar Confederation ===

With his family, he took part in the 1764 election of the new Polish monarch, [[Stanisław August of Poland|Stanisław II August]]. In December 1767, Pulaski and his father became involved with the [[Bar Confederation]], which saw King Stanisław as a Russian puppet and sought to curtail Russian [[hegemony]] over the [[Polish–Lithuanian Commonwealth|Commonwealth]]. The confederation was actively opposed by the Russian forces stationed in Poland. Pulaski recruited a unit and on February 29, 1768, signed the act of the confederation, thus declaring himself an official supporter of the movement. On March 6, he received the rank of a ''[[pułkownik]]'' and commanded a ''[[choragiew]]'' of [[Polish cavalry|cavalry]]. In March and April he agitated among the Polish military, successfully convincing some forces to join the Confederates. He fought his first battle on April 20 near [[Pohorełe]]; it was a victory, as was another on April 23 near [[Starokostiantyniv]]. An engagement at [[Kaczanówka]] on April 28 resulted in a defeat. In early May he garrisoned [[Chmielnik]], but was forced to retreat when allied reinforcements were defeated.&lt;ref name=&quot;psb386&quot;/&gt; He retreated to a monastery in [[Berdyczów]], which he defended during a siege by royalist forces for over two weeks until June 16. Eventually he was forced to surrender and was taken captive by the Russians. On June 28, he was released in exchange for a pledge that he would not again take up arms with the Confederates, and that he would lobby the Confederates to end hostilities. However, Pulaski considered the pledge to be non-binding, and made a public declaration to that effect upon reaching a camp of the Confederates at the end of July. Agreeing to the pledge in the first place weakened his authority and popularity among the Confederates, and his own father considered whether or not he should be [[court-martial]]ed; some heated debates followed and Pulaski was reinstated to active duty only in early September.&lt;ref name=&quot;psb387&quot;&gt;[[#Szczygielski86|Szczygielski 1986]], p. 387&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1769, Pulaski's unit was again besieged by numerically superior forces, this time in the old fortress of [[Okopy Świętej Trójcy]], which has served as his base of operations since December the previous year. However, after a staunch defense, he was able to break the Russian siege. On April 7, he was made the ''[[regimentarz]]'' of the [[Kraków Voivodeship (14th century&amp;nbsp;– 1795)|Kraków Voivodeship]].&lt;ref name=&quot;psb387&quot;/&gt; In May and June he operated near [[Przemyśl]], but failed to take the town. Criticized by some of his fellow Confederates, Pulaski departed to [[Grand Duchy of Lithuania|Lithuania]] with his allies and a force of about 600 men on June 3.&lt;ref name=&quot;psb387&quot;/&gt; There, Pulaski attempted to incite a larger revolt against Russia; despite no decisive military successes, he was able to assemble a 4,000-strong army and deliver it back to a Confederate staging point. This excursion received international notice and gained him a reputation as the most effective military leader in the Bar Confederation. Next, he moved with his unit towards [[Zamość]] and after some skirmishes was defeated at the [[Battle of Włodawa]] on September 15. He spent the rest of the year rebuilding his unit in the region of [[Podkarpacie]].&lt;ref name=&quot;psb388&quot;&gt;[[#Szczygielski86|Szczygielski 1986]], p. 388&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Bar Confederation 1768-1772.PNG|thumb|284px|alt=Map showing area of the Bar Confederation conflict|Map of the Bar Confederation conflict]]

In February 1770, Pulaski moved near [[Nowy Targ]], and in March, helped to subdue the mutiny of [[Józef Bierzyński]]. Based in [[Izby]], he subsequently operated in southern [[Lesser Poland]] and on May 13 his force was defeated at the [[Battle of Dęborzyn]]. Around June 9–10 in [[Prešov]], in a conference with other Confederate leaders, he met [[Joseph II, Holy Roman Emperor]], who complimented Pulaski on his actions. On July 3–4, Pulaski's camp was captured by [[Johann von Drewitz]], and he was forced to retreat into Austria. Early in August he met with the French emissary, [[Charles François Dumouriez]]. He disregarded an order to take [[Lanckoronna]] and instead cooperated with [[Michał Walewski]] in a raid on [[Kraków]] on the night of August 31.&lt;ref name=&quot;psb388&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;psb389&quot;&gt;[[#Szczygielski86|Szczygielski, 1986]], p. 389&lt;/ref&gt; He then departed for [[Częstochowa]]. On September 10, along with Walewski, he used subterfuge to take control of the [[Jasna Góra monastery]]. On September 18 he met [[Franciszka Corvin-Krasińska|Franciszka z Krasińskich]], an aristocrat from the [[Krasiński family]] and the wife of [[Charles of Saxony, Duke of Courland]]; he impressed her and she would become one of his protectors. Around September 22–24 Walewski was made the commandant of Jasna Góra, which slighted Pulaski. Nonetheless he continued as the ''de facto'' commander of Confederate troops stationed in and around Jasna Góra. Between September 10, 1770, and January 14, 1771, Pulaski, Walewski and [[Józef Zaremba]] commanded the Polish forces during the [[Siege of Jasna Góra (Bar Confederation)|siege of Jasna Góra]] monastery. They successfully defended against Drewitz in a series of engagements, the largest one on November 11, followed by a siege from December 31 to January 14. The defense of Jasna Góra further enhanced his reputation among the Confederates and abroad.&lt;ref name=&quot;psb389&quot;/&gt; A popular Confederate song taunting Drewitz included lyrics about Pulaski and Jasna Góra.&lt;ref name=&quot;Maciejewski1976&quot;&gt;[[#Maciejewski|Maciejewski, 1976]], p. 381&lt;/ref&gt; Pulaski intended to pursue Drewitz, but a growing discord between him and Zaremba prevented this from becoming a real option.&lt;ref name=&quot;psb389&quot;/&gt;
[[File:Kazimierz Pułaski at Częstochowa's walls.PNG|thumb|224px|left|alt=Painting by Juliusz Kossak depicting Pulaski at [[Częstochowa]]'s walls in 1770|Pulaski at [[Częstochowa]]'s walls in 1770 – [[Juliusz Kossak]].]]
In February 1771, Pulaski operated around [[Lublin]]; on February 25 he was victorious at [[Tarłów]] and on the night of February 28 and March 1, his forces besieged [[Kraśnik]]. In March that year he became one of the members of the Confederates' War Council. Dumouriez, who became a military adviser to the Confederates, at the time described him as &quot;spontaneous, more proud than ambitious, friend of the prince of Courland, enemy of the [[Potocki family]], brave and honest&quot; as well as popular among other commanders. This was due to his refusal to follow orders and adhere to discipline. [[Jędrzej Kitowicz]] who met him as well around that time described him as short and thin, pacing and speaking quickly, and uninterested in women or drinking. Furthermore, he enjoyed fighting against the Russians above everything else, and was daring to the extent he forgot about his safety in battles, resulting in his many failures on the battlefield.&lt;ref name=&quot;psb389&quot;/&gt;

In May 1771, Pulaski advanced on Zamość, refusing to coordinate an operation with Dumouriez against [[Alexander Suvorov]]; without Pulaski's support, the Confederates were defeated at the [[Battle of Lanckorona]]. Pulaski's forces were victorious at the [[Battle of Majdany]], and briefly besieged Zamość, but it was relieved by Suvorov. He retreated, suffering major losses, towards Częstochowa. On July 27, pressured by Franciszka z Krasińskich, he declared he would from then on strictly adhere to orders from the Confederacy that he had previously habitually disregarded. In October his responsibilities in the War Council were increased, and the same month he became involved with the plan to kidnap King Poniatowski.&lt;ref name=&quot;psb390&quot;/&gt; Pulaski was initially opposed to this plan but later supported it on the condition that the king would not be harmed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Storozynski2010-23&quot;&gt;[[#AlexStorozynski|Storozynski, 2010]], p. 23&lt;/ref&gt; The attempt failed, weakening the international reputation of the Confederates, and when Pulaski's involvement with the attempted kidnapping became known, the Austrians expelled him from their territories.&lt;ref name=&quot;psb390&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stone2001-272&quot;&gt;[[#Stone|Stone, 2001]], p. 272&lt;/ref&gt; He spent the following winter and spring in Częstochowa, during which time several of his followers were defeated, captured or killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;psb390&quot;&gt;[[#Szczygielski86|Szczygielski, 1986]], p. 390&lt;/ref&gt;

On May 31, 1772, Pulaski, increasingly distanced from other leaders of the Confederation, left the Jasna Góra monastery and went to [[Silesia]] in Prussia.&lt;ref name=&quot;psb390&quot;/&gt; In the meantime, the Bar Confederation was defeated, with most fighting ending around the summer.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stone2001-272&quot;/&gt; Overall, Pulaski was seen as one of the most famous and accomplished Confederate leaders. &quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;psb388&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;psb389&quot;/&gt; At the same time, he often acted independently, disobeying orders from Confederate command, and among his detractors (which included Dumouriez) had a reputation of a &quot;loose cannon&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;psb389&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;psb390&quot;/&gt;

Leaving Prussia, Pulaski sought refuge in France, where he unsuccessfully attempted to join the [[French Army]]. In 1773, his opponents in Poland accused him of attempted [[regicide]], and proceedings began at the [[Sejm Court]] on June 7.&lt;ref name=&quot;psb390&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;psb391&quot;&gt;[[#Szczygielski86|Szczygielski, 1986]], p. 391&lt;/ref&gt;

Poniatowski himself warned Pulaski to stay away from Poland, or risk death.&lt;ref name=&quot;psb390&quot;/&gt; The court verdict, declared ''[[trial in absentia|in absentia]]'' in July, stripped Pulaski of &quot;all dignity and honors&quot;, demanded that his possessions be confiscated, and sentenced him to death. He attempted to recreate a Confederate force in the [[Ottoman Empire]] during the [[Russo-Turkish War (1768–1774)|Russo-Turkish War]], but before he could make any progress, the Turks were defeated, and he barely escaped by sea to [[Marseilles]], France. He found himself in debt and unable to find an army that would enlist him. He spent the year of 1775 in France, imprisoned at times for debts, until his allies gathered enough funds to arrange for his release. Around that time, due to the efforts of his friend [[Claude-Carloman de Rulhière]], he was recruited by the [[Gilbert du Motier, marquis de La Fayette|Marquis de Lafayette]] and [[Benjamin Franklin]] (whom he met in spring 1777) for service in the [[American Revolutionary War]].&lt;ref name=&quot;psb391&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Pulaski Day&quot;/&gt;

=== In the United States ===

[[File:Kazimierz Pułaski pod Częstochową.PNG|thumb|alt=1883 painting by Juliusz Kossak depicting Pulaski on horse back| Pulaski in [[Juliusz Kossak]] painting 1883]]

==== Northern front ====

Franklin was impressed by Pulaski, and wrote of him: &quot;Count{{Ref|b|b}} Pulaski of Poland, an officer famous throughout Europe for his bravery and conduct in defence of the liberties of his country against the three great invading powers of Russia, Austria and Prussia&amp;nbsp;... may be highly useful to our service.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Storozynski2010-55-56&quot;&gt;[[#AlexStorozynski|Storozynski, 2010]], p. 56&lt;/ref&gt; He subsequently recommended that General [[George Washington]] accept Pulaski as a volunteer in the [[American cavalry|Continental Army cavalry]] and said that Pulaski &quot;was renowned throughout Europe for the courage and bravery he displayed in defense of his country's freedom.&quot;&lt;ref name=cong&gt;{{USPL|111|94}} U.S. Government Printing Office&lt;/ref&gt; Pulaski departed France from [[Nantes]] in June, and arrived in [[Marblehead, Massachusetts]], near [[Boston]], on July 23, 1777.&lt;ref name=&quot;psb392&quot;&gt;[[#Szczygielski86|Szczygielski, 1986]], p. 392&lt;/ref&gt; After his arrival, Pulaski wrote to Washington, &quot;I came here, where freedom is being defended, to serve it, and to live or die for it.&quot;&lt;ref name = cong /&gt;

On August 20, he met Washington in his headquarters in [[Neshaminy Falls]], outside [[Philadelphia]].&lt;ref name = &quot;psb392&quot; /&gt; He showed off riding stunts, and argued for the superiority of cavalry over infantry.&lt;ref name=&quot;Storozynski2010-55-56&quot;/&gt;  Because Washington was unable to grant him an officer rank, Pulaski spent the next few months traveling between Washington and the [[US Congress]] in Philadelphia, awaiting his appointment.&lt;ref name = &quot;psb392&quot;/&gt; His first military engagement against the British occurred before he received it, on September 11, 1777, at the [[Battle of Brandywine]].&lt;ref name=&quot;psb392&quot;/&gt; When the [[Continental Army]] troops began to yield, he reconnoitered with Washington's bodyguard of about 30 men, and reported that the enemy were endeavoring to cut off the line of retreat.&lt;ref name=&quot;Storozynski2010-55-56&quot;/&gt; Washington ordered him to collect, as many as possible, the scattered troops who came his way, and employ them according to his discretion to secure the retreat of the army.&lt;ref name=appletons133&gt;[[#appleton133|Appletons Cyclopaedia of American Biography: Pickering-Sumter, 1898]], p. 133&lt;/ref&gt; His subsequent charge averted a disastrous defeat of the Continental Army cavalry,&lt;ref name=&quot;Storozynski2010-55-56&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;psb392&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kazimierz Pulaski Citizenship&quot;&gt;[[#Mission|Kazimierz Pulaski Granted U.S. Citizenship Posthumously, 2009]]&lt;/ref&gt; earning him fame in America&lt;ref name= &quot;Storozynski2010-57&quot; /&gt; and saved the life of George Washington.&lt;ref&gt;111th Congress Public Law 94&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, on September 15, 1777, on the orders of Congress, Washington made Pulaski a [[brigadier general (United States)|brigadier general]] in the Continental Army cavalry.&lt;ref name= cong /&gt; At that point, the cavalry was only a few hundred men strong organized into four regiments. These men were scattered among numerous infantry formations, and used primarily for scouting duties. Pulaski immediately began work on reforming the cavalry, and wrote the first regulations for the formation.&lt;ref name=&quot;psb392&quot; /&gt;

On September 16, while on patrol west of Philadelphia, Pulaski spotted significant British forces moving toward the Continental position. Upon being informed by Pulaski, Washington prepared for a battle, but the encounter [[Battle of the Clouds|was interrupted by a major storm]] before either side was organized.&lt;ref name= &quot;SokolKissane1992&quot;&gt;[[#Sokol1992|Sokol, 1992]], pp. 31-36&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;McGuire 31-36&quot;&gt;[[#McGuire|McGuire, 2006]], pp.31-36&lt;/ref&gt; On October 4, Pulaski took part in the [[Battle of Germantown]]. He spent the winter of 1777 to 1778 with most of the army at [[Valley Forge]]. Pulaski argued that the military operations should continue through the winter, but this idea was rejected by the general staff. In turn, he focused on reorganizing the cavalry force, mostly stationed in [[Trenton, New Jersey|Trenton]].&lt;ref name= &quot;psb392&quot; /&gt; While at Trenton his assistance was requested by General [[Anthony Wayne]], whom Washington had dispatched on a foraging expedition into southern New Jersey. Wayne was in danger of encountering a much larger British force sent to oppose his movements. Pulaski and 50 cavalry rode south to [[Burlington, New Jersey|Burlington]], where they skirmished with British sentries on February 28. After this minor encounter the British commander, Lieutenant Colonel Thomas Stirling, was apparently convinced that he was facing a much larger force than expected, and prepared to withdraw his troops across the Delaware River into Pennsylvania at Cooper's Ferry (present-day [[Gloucester City, New Jersey|Gloucester City]]). Pulaski and Wayne joined forces to attack Stirling's position on February 29 while he awaited suitable weather conditions to cross.&lt;ref name= &quot;Nelson 73-74&quot;/&gt; In the resulting skirmish (which only involved a few hundred men out of the larger forces on either side), Pulaski's horse was shot out from under him and a few of his cavalry were wounded.&lt;ref name=&quot;Griffin 50-54&quot;&gt;[[#Griffin1907|Griffin, 1907]], pp. 50-54&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Anthony Wayne.jpg|thumb|right|180px|alt=Engraving of Anthony Wayne|&lt;center&gt;[[Anthony Wayne]]&lt;/center&gt;commended Pulaski for his heroic actions in New Jersey]]
American officers serving under Pulaski had difficulty taking orders from a foreigner who could scarcely speak English and whose ideas of discipline and tactics differed enormously from those to which they were accustomed. This resulted in friction between the Americans and Pulaski and his fellow Polish officers.&lt;ref name=appletons133 /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kajencki2005-47&quot;&gt;[[#Kajencki2005|Kajencki, 2005]], p. 47&lt;/ref&gt; There was also discontent in the unit over delays in pay,&lt;ref name=&quot;psb392&quot;/&gt; and Pulaski's imperious personality was a regular source of discontent among his peers, superiors, and subordinates.&lt;ref name=&quot;presidential&quot;/&gt; Pulaski was also unhappy that his suggestion to create a [[lancer]] unit was denied.&lt;ref name=&quot;psb392&quot;/&gt; Despite a commendation from Wayne, these circumstances prompted Pulaski to resign his general command in March 1778, and return to Valley Forge.&lt;ref name = &quot;psb392&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=appletons133 /&gt;

Pulaski went to [[Yorktown, Virginia|Yorktown]], where he met with General [[Horatio Gates]] and suggested the creation of a new unit. At Gates' recommendation, Congress confirmed his previous appointment to the rank of a brigadier general, with a special title of &quot;Commander of the Horse&quot;, and authorized the formation of a corps of 68 lancers and 200 light infantry.&lt;ref name=&quot;Storozynski2010-55-56&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;psb392&quot;/&gt; This corps, which became known as the [[Pulaski Cavalry Legion]], was recruited mainly in [[Baltimore, Maryland|Baltimore]], where it was headquartered.&lt;ref name=&quot;psb392&quot;/&gt; [[Henry Wadsworth Longfellow]] would later commemorate in verse the consecration of the Legion's banner.&lt;ref name=&quot;America1943&quot;/&gt; By August 1778, it numbered about 330 men, both Americans and foreigners. General [[Charles Lee (general)|Charles Lee]] commented on the high standards of the Legion's training.&lt;ref name=&quot;psb392&quot;/&gt; The &quot;father of the American cavalry&quot; demanded much of his men and trained them in tested cavalry tactics. He used his own personal finances when money from Congress was scarce, in order to assure his forces of the finest equipment and personal safety.&lt;ref name=&quot;In Quest of a Cultural Identity: An Inquiry for the Polish Community&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Storozynski2010-60&quot;/&gt; However, later that year a controversy arose related to the Legion's finances, and its requisitions from the local populace.&lt;ref name=&quot;psb392&quot;/&gt; His troubles with the auditors continued until his death; Pulaski complained that he received inadequate funds, was obstructed by locals and officials, and that he was forced to spend his own money. He was not cleared of these charges until after his death.&lt;ref name=&quot;psb393&quot;/&gt;

In the autumn Pulaski was ordered to [[Little Egg Harbor]], where in the engagement on October 15, known as [[The Affair at Little Egg Harbor]], the legion suffered heavy losses.&lt;ref name=&quot;psb392&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;StrykerJersey1894&quot;&gt;[[#Stryker|Stryker, 1894]], p. 16&lt;/ref&gt; During the following winter Pulaski was stationed at [[Minisink, New York|Minisink]], at that time in [[New Jersey]].&lt;ref name=&quot;psb393&quot;/&gt; Ordered to take part in a punitive [[Sullivan Expedition]] against the [[Iroquois people|Iroquois]], he was dissatisfied with this command, and intended to leave the service and return to Europe, but instead asked to be reassigned to the Southern front.&lt;ref name=&quot;psb392&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;psb393&quot;/&gt; On February 2, 1779 Washington instead ordered him to [[South Carolina]].&lt;ref name=&quot;psb393&quot;/&gt;

==== Southern front ====

Pulaski arrived in [[Charleston, South Carolina|Charleston]] on May 8, 1779, finding the city [[Siege of Charleston|in crisis]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Wilson 107-108&quot;&gt;[[#Wilson2005|Wilson, 2005]], pp. 107-108&lt;/ref&gt; General [[Benjamin Lincoln]], commander of the southern army, had led most of the army toward [[Augusta, Georgia]], in a bid to recapture [[Savannah, Georgia|Savannah]], which had been [[Capture of Savannah|captured by the British]] in late 1778.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wilson 101-102&quot;&gt;[[#Wilson2005|Wilson, 2005]], pp. 101-102&lt;/ref&gt; The British commander, Brigadier General [[Augustine Prevost]], responded to Lincoln's move by launching a raiding expedition from Savannah across the [[Savannah River]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Wilson 103&quot;&gt;[[#Wilson2005|Wilson, 2005]], p. 103&lt;/ref&gt; The South Carolina militia fell back before the British advance, and Prevost's force followed them all the way to Charleston. Pulaski arrived just as military leaders were establishing the city's defenses.&lt;ref name=&quot;Russell 106&quot;&gt;[[#Russell|Russell, 2000]], p. 106&lt;/ref&gt; When the British advanced on May 11, Pulaski's Legion engaged forward elements of the British force, and was badly mauled in the encounter. The Legion infantry, numbering only about 60 men before the skirmish, was virtually wiped out, and Pulaski was forced to retreat to the safety of the city's guns.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wilson 108&quot;&gt;[[#Wilson2005|Wilson, 2005]], p. 108&lt;/ref&gt; Although some historians credit this action with Prevost's decision to withdraw back toward Savannah the next day (despite ongoing negotiations of a possible surrender of Charleston), that decision is more likely based on news Prevost received that Lincoln's larger force was returning to Charleston to face him, and that Prevost's troops had gone further than he had originally intended. One early historian criticized Pulaski's actions during that engagement as &quot;ill-judged, ill-conducted, disgraceful and disastrous&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Griffin 95&quot;&gt;[[#Griffin1907|Griffin, 1907]], p. 95&lt;/ref&gt;  The episode was of minor strategic consequence and did little to enhance the reputation of Pulaski's unit.&lt;ref name=&quot;Russell 107&quot;&gt;[[#Russell|Russell, 2000]], p. 107&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Death of Pulaski.jpg|thumb|Pulaski mortally wounded by grape shot while leading cavalry charge]]
Although Pulaski frequently suffered from [[malaria]] while stationed in Charleston, he remained in active service. At the beginning of September Lincoln prepared to launch an attempt to retake Savannah with French assistance. Pulaski was ordered to Augusta, where he was to join forces with General [[Lachlan McIntosh]].&lt;ref name=appletons133/&gt; Their combined forces were to serve as the forward elements of Lincoln's army.&lt;ref name=&quot;The history of Georgia: Revolutionary epoch&quot;&gt;[[#Colcock1883|Colcock, 1883]], p. 378&lt;/ref&gt; Pulaski captured a British outpost near [[Ogeechee River]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Kajencki2005-93&quot;&gt;[[#Kajencki2005|Kajencki, 2005]], p. 93&lt;/ref&gt; His units then acted as an advance guard for the allied French units under Admiral [[Charles Hector, comte d'Estaing]].&lt;ref name=&quot;psb393&quot;/&gt; He rendered great services during the [[siege of Savannah]], and in the assault of October 9 commanded the whole cavalry, both French and American.&lt;ref name=appletons133/&gt;

=== Death and burial ===
While attempting to rally fleeing French forces during a cavalry charge, Pulaski was mortally wounded by [[grapeshot]].&lt;ref name=&quot;psb393&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Storozynski2010-91&quot;/&gt; The reported grapeshot is on display today at the [[Georgia Historical Society]] in Savannah; The [[Charleston Museum]] also has a grapeshot reported to be from Pulaski's wound.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kajencki2001-163&quot;&gt;[[#Kajencki2005|Kajencki, 2005]], p. 163&lt;/ref&gt; A wounded Pulaski was carried from the field of battle and taken aboard the South Carolina merchant [[brigantine|brig]] [[privateer]] Wasp under the command of Captain Samuel Bulfinch,&lt;ref&gt;[[#WASP|WASP, 2011]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Pinkowski|Pinkwoski, 1997]]&lt;/ref&gt; where he died two days later, having never regained consciousness.&lt;ref name=cong/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;psb393&quot;/&gt; His death, perceived by [[Patriot (American Revolution)|American Patriot]] supporters as heroic, further boosted his reputation in America.&lt;ref name=&quot;Storozynski2010-91&quot;&gt;[[#AlexStorozynski|Storozynski, 2010]], p. 91&lt;/ref&gt;

The historical accounts for Pulaski's time and place of burial vary considerably. According to several contemporary accounts there were witnesses, including Pulaski's [[aide-de-camp]], that Pulaski received a symbolic burial in Charleston on October 21,&lt;ref name=&quot;psb393&quot;/&gt; sometime after he was [[burial at sea|buried at sea]].&lt;ref name=&quot;pcpdf&quot;&gt;[[#film|American Council for Polish Culture]]&lt;/ref&gt; Other witnesses, including Captain Samuel Bulfinch of the ''Wasp'' however, claimed that the wounded Pulaski was actually later removed from the ship and taken to the Greenwich [[plantations in the American South|plantation]] in the town of [[Thunderbolt, Georgia|Thunderbolt]], near Savannah, where he died and was buried.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Baptism|Polish American Journal, 1996]]&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 1825, during his [[Visit of the Marquis de Lafayette to the United States|grand tour]] of the United States, Lafayette personally laid the cornerstone for the [[Casimir Pulaski Monument in Savannah]], Georgia.&lt;ref name=cong/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Szymański301&quot;&gt;[[#Szymański|Szymański, 1979]], p. 301&lt;/ref&gt; Remains at [[Squares of Savannah, Georgia|Monterey Square]] in that city, alleged to be Pulaski's, were exhumed in 1996 and examined in a forensic study. The eight-year examination, including DNA analysis, ended inconclusively, although the skeleton is consistent with Pulaski's age and occupation.  A healed wound on the skull's forehead is consistent with historical records of an injury Pulaski sustained in battle, as is a bone defect on the left cheekbone, believed to have been caused by a benign tumor.&lt;ref name=&quot;burial2&quot;&gt;[[#Mystery|The Pulaski Mystery, 2008]]&lt;/ref&gt; The remains were reinterred with [[military funeral|military honors]] in 2005.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pulaski's Grand Burial in Savannah&quot;/&gt;

== Tributes and commemoration ==

[[File:Kazimierz Pulaski museum statue.jpg|thumb|left|upright=0.8|alt=Photo of Pulaski Statue at the Kazimierz Pułaski Museum in Poland|Statue of Pulaski at the Kazimierz Pułaski Museum in [[Warka]], Poland.]]
[[File:General Pulaski 1931 Issue-2c.jpg|thumb|right|upright=0.8|alt=Image of Pulaski U.S. commemorative postage stamp|&lt;center&gt;General Casimir Pulaski&lt;br&gt; [[Postage stamps and postal history of the United States|United States postage stamp]].&lt;br&gt;Issue of 1931, 2c &lt;/center&gt;]]
{{main article|Commemoration of Casimir Pulaski}}
The United States has long commemorated Pulaski's contributions to the American Revolutionary War, and already on October 29, 1779, the [[United States Congress]] passed a resolution that a monument should be dedicated to him, but the [[Casimir Pulaski Monument in Savannah|first monument to him]] was not built until 1854. A bust of Pulaski was added to a collection of other busts of American heroes at [[United States Capitol]] in 1867. On May 11, 1910, [[US President]] [[William Taft]] revealed a Congress-sponsored [[General Casimir Pulaski (statue)|General Casimir Pulaski statue]].&lt;ref name=&quot;psb393&quot;/&gt; In 1929, Congress passed another resolution, this one recognizing October 11 of each year as &quot;[[General Pulaski Memorial Day]]&quot;, with a large parade held annually on [[Fifth Avenue]] in New York City.&lt;ref name=&quot;cong&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;psb393&quot;/&gt; Separately, a [[Casimir Pulaski Day]] is celebrated in [[Illinois]] and some other places on the first Monday of each March.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pulaski Day&quot;/&gt; After a previous attempt failed,&lt;ref name=&quot;sjres&quot;/&gt; Congress passed a joint resolution conferring [[Honorary citizen of the United States|honorary U.S. citizenship]] on Pulaski in 2009, sending it to President [[Barack Obama]] for approval.&lt;ref name=&quot;cong&quot;/&gt; He duly signed it on November 6, 2009, making Pulaski the seventh person so honored.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Mann|Seattle Times, Nov 10, 2009]]&lt;/ref&gt;

In Poland, in 1793 Pulaski's relative, Antoni Pułaski, obtained a cancellation of his brother's sentence from 1773. He has been mentioned in the literary works of numerous Polish authors, including [[Adam Mickiewicz]], [[Juliusz Słowacki]] and [[Józef Ignacy Kraszewski]]. [[Adolf Nowaczyński]] wrote a drama &quot;Pułaski w Ameryce&quot; (Pulaski in America) in 1917.&lt;ref name=&quot;psb393&quot;/&gt; A museum dedicated to Pulaski, the [[Kazimierz Pułaski Museum]], opened in Warka in 1967.&lt;ref name=&quot;Muzeum imienia Kazimierza Pułaskiego w Warce&quot;/&gt;

Throughout Poland and the United States, people have celebrated anniversaries of Pulaski's birth and death, and there exist numerous objects of art such as paintings and statues of him.&lt;ref name=&quot;psb393&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;psb394&quot;/&gt; In 1879, to commemorate the 100th anniversary of his death, [[Henri Schoeller]] composed &quot;[[A Pulaski March]]&quot;. Twenty years earlier, [[Eduard Sobolewski]] composed his opera, &quot;Mohega&quot;, about the last days of Pulaski's life. Commemorative medals and stamps of Pulaski have been issued. Several towns and [[Pulaski County (disambiguation)|counties]] in United States are named after him, as are numerous streets, parks and structures, such as the [[Pulaski Bridge]] or the [[Pulaski Skyway]]. There is also a number of educational, academic, and [[Polish-American]] institutions named after him.&lt;ref name=&quot;psb393&quot;/&gt; A US Navy submarine, {{USS|Casimir Pulaski|SSBN-633|6}}, has been named for him, as was a 19th-century [[United States Revenue Cutter Service]] [[Cutter (boat)|cutter]].&lt;ref name=&quot;uscg&quot;&gt;[[#coastguard|U.S. Coast Guard, Pulaski, 1825]]&lt;/ref&gt; A Polish frigate, [[ORP Generał Kazimierz Pułaski|ORP ''Generał Kazimierz Pułaski'']], is also named after Pulaski.&lt;ref name=&quot;Marynarka Wojenna&quot;/&gt; [[Fort Pulaski National Monument|Fort Pulaski]], active during the [[American Civil War]], is named in honor of Casimir Pulaski.&lt;ref name=&quot;Casimir Pulaski&amp;nbsp;– Fort Pulaski National Monument&quot;/&gt;  A statue commemorating Pulaski titled [[General Casimir Pulaski]] stands at the eastern end of [[Freedom Plaza]] in Washington, D.C. There is an equestrian statue of Pulaski in [[Roger Williams Park]] in [[Providence, Rhode Island]].  A statue by [[Granville W. Carter]] depicting  Pulaski on a rearing horse signaling a
forward charge with a sword in his right hand is erected in [[Hartford, Connecticut]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ctgov&quot; /&gt;

Polish historian [[Władysław Konopczyński]], who wrote a monograph on Pulaski in 1931, noted that he was one of the most accomplished Polish people, grouping him with other Polish military heroes such as [[Tadeusz Kościuszko]], [[Stanisław Żółkiewski]], [[Stefan Czarniecki]], and Prince [[Józef Poniatowski]].&lt;ref name=&quot;psb394&quot;/&gt;

&quot;The Mysterious Stranger&quot;, a 1959 episode of the [[American Broadcasting Company|ABC]]/[[Warner Brothers]] [[Western (genre)|western]] [[television series]] ''[[Sugarfoot]]'', features [[Adam West]] as Frederick Pulaski, a declared descendant of the Casimir Pulaski. However, Pulaski never married or had direct heirs. In the story line, Frederick Pulaski is a concert pianist who defends oppressed Polish miners in a western town. Series character Tom &quot;Sugarfoot Brewster ([[Will Hutchins]]), befriends Pulaski in a legal hearing and reconciles him with the young woman to whom both are smitten, Kathy O'Hara ([[Sue Randall]]), who is also studying to be a concert pianist. [[Karl Swenson]] appears in this episode as Kathy's wealthy [[Ireland|Irish]] father, Dennis O'Hara.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0712919/|title=&quot;The Mysterious Stranger&quot;, February 17, 1959|publisher=[[Internet Movie Data Base]]|accessdate=December 28, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== In popular culture==

In the Season 3 episode of ''[[The West Wing]]'' entitled &quot;[[Stirred]]&quot;, Pulaski is mentioned, and [[US President]] [[Jed Bartlett]] describes him as &quot;a [[Poles|Polish]] [[Brigadier General]] who vanquished the [[Russia]]n ''and [[Prussian]]'' military, then came to the colonies and commanded our cavalry during the [[American Revolution]]&quot;.

There is a statue of Pulaski in the fictional town of [[Stars Hollow]] from the TV series ''[[Gilmore Girls]]''.

Singer-songwriter [[Sufjan Stevens]] wrote a song entitled &quot;Casimir Pulaski Day&quot; on his ''[[Illinois (Sufjan Stevens album)|Illinois]]'' album.

== See also ==
{{Portal|Biography|Poland|Georgia (U.S. state)|United States Army|American Revolutionary War}}
* [[Johann de Kalb]], a Bavarian-born French officer who served as a general in the Continental Army
* [[Michael Kovats]], a Hungarian officer in the Continental Army cavalry
* [[Tadeusz Kościuszko]], a fellow Polish officer who served in the Continental Army
* [[Charles Lee (general)|Charles Lee]], a British officer who served as a major general in both the Polish and Continental armies
* [[Gilbert du Motier, Marquis de Lafayette]], a French officer who served as a major general in the Continental Army
* [[Friedrich Wilhelm von Steuben]], a Prussian officer who served as a general in the Continental Army

== Notes ==
{{Note|a|a}} Older sources have cited varying dates and places of birth of Pulaski. The suggested alternative dates have been March 4, 1746 or 1747, and the alternative place of birth, [[Pułaski family]] manor at [[Winiary, Warka|Winiary]].&lt;ref name=&quot;fm&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=booklet/&gt; Modern sources agree that Pulaski was born on March 6, 1745, in the now-nonexistent Pulaski manor house, located near the present address 53 Nowy Świat St. near Warecka St. in Warsaw.&lt;ref name=&quot;fm&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=booklet/&gt;

{{Note|b|b}} Some sources refer to Pulaski as a &quot;[[count]]&quot;. This is likely an artifact of some well-publicized American letters and statements in which he is titled as such, in particular, Benjamin Franklin's letter of 1777. Americans of that era had a habit of giving such grandiose titles to all European nobles, to resemble the titles of famous European allies of the nascent American state such as [[Marquis de Lafayette]] or [[Baron von Steuben]]. In reality, Pulaski was never a count, simply an untitled member of the [[Polish nobility]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Pastusiak1977&quot;&gt;[[#Pastusiak|Pastusiak, 1977]], p. 47&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last1=Hammack|first1=Bill|title=Pulaski and the Siege of Savanna|journal=Outdoors in Georgia|date=1976|publisher=Georgia Department of Natural Resources|url=https://archive.org/details/outdoorsingeorgi7607geor}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pulaski never used this title himself.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Przegląd historyczny|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=i1QfAQAAIAAJ|year=1910|publisher=Państwowe Wydawn. Naukowe|page=241|language=Polish}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist|2|refs=

&lt;ref name=&quot;America1943&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Polish Institute of Arts and Sciences in America|title=Bulletin of the Polish Institute of Arts and Sciences in America|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ljUoAQAAMAAJ|accessdate=September 21, 2012|year=1943|publisher=Polish Institute of Arts and Sciences in America|page=451}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Casimir Pulaski&amp;nbsp;– Fort Pulaski National Monument&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nps.gov/fopu/historyculture/casimir-pulaski.htm |title=Casimir Pulaski&amp;nbsp;– Fort Pulaski National Monument |publisher=Nps.gov |accessdate=June 5, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Marynarka Wojenna&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mw.mil.pl/index.php?akcja=oliver |title=Marynarka Wojenna |language=pl |publisher=Mw.mil.pl |accessdate=June 5, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Nelson 73-74&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Nelson|first=Paul David|title=Anthony Wayne: Soldier of the Early Republic|publisher=Indiana University Press|year=1985|location=Bloomington, Indiana|isbn=978-0-253-30751-4|oclc=11518827|pages=73–74}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;psb393&quot;&gt;Szczygielski 1986, p. 393.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;psb394&quot;&gt;Szczygielski 1986, p. 394.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pulaski Day&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://castle.eiu.edu/~insight/pulaski/pulaski.htm |title=Pulaski Day |publisher=Castle.eiu.edu |accessdate=June 5, 2012 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120722013614/http://castle.eiu.edu/~insight/pulaski/pulaski.htm |archivedate=July 22, 2012 |df=mdy }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Pulaski's Grand Burial in Savannah&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.poles.org/Sav_2005/Sav_05.html |title=Pulaski's Grand Burial in Savannah |publisher=Poles.org |accessdate=June 6, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Storozynski2010-57&quot;&gt;Storozynsky 2010, [https://books.google.com/books?id=wVqnlTbsdXcC&amp;pg=PT56 p. 57].&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Storozynski2010-60&quot;&gt;Storozynsky 2010, [https://books.google.com/books?id=wVqnlTbsdXcC&amp;pg=PT60 p. 60].&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;In Quest of a Cultural Identity: An Inquiry for the Polish Community&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=Seidner |first=Stanley S. |year=1976 |title=In Quest of a Cultural Identity: An Inquiry for the Polish Community |publisher=IUME, Teachers College, Columbia University |location=New York |url=http://www.eric.ed.gov/ERICWebPortal/search/detailmini.jsp?_nfpb=true&amp;_&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchValue_0=ED167674&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchType_0=no&amp;accno=ED167674 |accessdate=October 14, 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Muzeum imienia Kazimierza Pułaskiego w Warce&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.muzeumpulaski.pl |title=Muzeum imienia Kazimierza Pułaskiego w Warce |publisher=Muzeum imienia Kazimierza Pułaskiego w Warce|accessdate=May 15, 2012|language=Polish}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;presidential&quot;&gt;Presidential Studies Quarterly Vol. XXIV No. 4 Fall 1994, pp.&amp;nbsp;876–77&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;sjres&quot;&gt;{{USBill|110|sjres|5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;ctgov&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ct.gov/ctva/lib/ctva/digital/hartford_war_memorials_list.pdf|title=Hartford War Memorials}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

==Bibliography==
{{refbegin|2}}
*{{cite book |last=Pastusiak |first=Longin |title=Kościuszko, Pułaski i inni: o udziale Polaków w osadnictwie amerykańskim i w walce o niepodległość Stanów Zjednoczonych|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3MMCAAAAMAAJ|year=1977|publisher=Krajowa Agencja Wydawnicza|page=47|language=Polish |ref=Pastusiak}}
*{{cite book|author=Polish Institute of Arts and Sciences in America|title=Bulletin of the Polish Institute of Arts and Sciences in America|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ljUoAQAAMAAJ|accessdate=September 21, 2012|year=1943|publisher=Polish Institute of Arts and Sciences in America|page=451 |ref=Bulletin1943}}
*{{cite web|url=http://www.poles.org/L_Kaz/E_Kaz.html |title=The Pulaski Mystery |publisher=Poles.org |date=April 18, 2008 |accessdate=June 6, 2012 |ref=Mystery}}
*{{cite web|url=http://www.nps.gov/fopu/historyculture/casimir-pulaski.htm |title=Casimir Pulaski&amp;nbsp;– Fort Pulaski National Monument |publisher=Nps.gov |accessdate=June 5, 2012}}
*{{cite book |first=William R. |last=Denslow |title=10,000 Famous Freemasons V3, K to P, Volume 3 |year=2004 |publisher=&lt;br&gt;Kessinger Publishing, prepared by the Missouri Lodge of Research |isbn=978-1-4179-7579-2 |ref=Denslow}}, [https://books.google.com/books?id=D-cCeOEXGyoC&amp;dq=Casimir+Pulaski&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s Url]
*{{cite book |last=Maciejewski |first=Janusz |title=Literatura barska|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=FgxhAAAAMAAJ|accessdate=June 5, 2012|year=1976|publisher=Zakład Narodowy im. Ossolińskich|language=Polish |ref=Maciejewski}}
*{{cite web|url=http://www.mw.mil.pl/index.php?akcja=oliver |title=Marynarka Wojenna |language=pl |publisher=Mw.mil.pl |accessdate=June 5, 2012}}
*{{cite book|last=Nelson|first=Paul David|title=Anthony Wayne: Soldier of the Early Republic|publisher=Indiana University Press|year=1985|location=Bloomington, Indiana|isbn=978-0-253-30751-4|oclc=11518827|pages=73–74}}
*{{cite web|url=http://www.polishcultureacpc.org/Pulaski/Pulaski.pdf|title=Casimir Pulaski Polish and American Hero. Project of documentary film by Jolanta Kessler-Chojecka.|publisher=American Council for Polish Culture|accessdate=June 4, 2012 |ref=film}}
*{{Cite book |last=Szczygielski |first=Wacław |chapter=''Pułaski Kazimierz''|title=Polski Słownik Biograficzny, Tom XXIX|publisher=Zakład Narodowy Imenia Ossolińskich I Wydawnictwo Polskieh Akademii Nauk|year=1986|isbn=83-04-00148-9|page=386|language=Polish |ref=Szczygielski86}}
*{{cite web|url=http://castle.eiu.edu/~insight/pulaski/pulaski.htm |title=Pulaski Day |publisher=Castle.eiu.edu |accessdate=June 5, 2012 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120722013614/http://castle.eiu.edu/~insight/pulaski/pulaski.htm |archivedate=July 22, 2012 |df=mdy }}
*{{cite web|url=http://www.poles.org/Sav_2005/Sav_05.html |title=Pulaski's Grand Burial in Savannah |publisher=Poles.org |accessdate=June 6, 2012}}
*{{cite book |author1=Stanley S. Sokol|author2=Sharon F. Mrotek Kissane|author3=Alfred L. Abramowicz|title=The Polish Biographical Dictionary: Profiles of Nearly 900 Poles Who Have Made Lasting Contributions to World Civilization |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=IGOhdT-w1eIC&amp;pg=PA327 |accessdate=September 21, 2012 |date=January 1, 1992 |publisher=Bolchazy-Carducci Publishers |isbn=978-0-86516-245-7 |ref=Sokol1992}}
*{{cite book |last=Stone |first=Daniel |title=The Polish-Lithuanian State, 1386–1795|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=LFgB_l4SdHAC&amp;pg=PA272|accessdate=June 5, 2012|year=2001|publisher=University of Washington Press|isbn=978-0-295-98093-5 |ref=Stone}}
*{{cite book |last=Storozynski |first=Alex |title=The Peasant Prince: Thaddeus Kosciuszko and the Age of Revolution|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=wVqnlTbsdXcC&amp;pg=PT23|accessdate=June 5, 2012|date=August 3, 2010|publisher=Macmillan|isbn=978-0-312-62594-8|page=23 |ref=AlexStorozynski}}
*{{cite book|last=Griffin|first=Martin |title=Catholics and the American Revolution |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3rUTAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA95&amp;f=false |publisher=self-published, 385 pages |year=1907|location=Ridley Park, Pennsylvania |ref=Griffin1907}}
*{{cite book|last=McGuire|first=Thomas|title=Battle of Paoli|pages=31–36|publisher=Stackpole Books|year=2006|isbn=978-0-8117-3337-3|location=Mechanicsburg, Pennsylvania |ref=McGuire}}
*{{cite book|last=Russell| first=David Lee|title=The American Revolution in the Southern Colonies | publisher=McFarland| year=2000| isbn=978-0-7864-0783-5 |location=Jefferson, North Carolina| oclc=248087936|page=106 |ref=Russell}}
*{{cite book|last= Russell| first=David Lee|title=The American Revolution in the Southern Colonies | publisher=McFarland| year=2000| isbn=978-0-7864-0783-5 |location=Jefferson, North Carolina| oclc=248087936|page=107}}
*{{cite book|title=The Southern Strategy: Britain's Conquest of South Carolina and Georgia, 1775–1780|first=David K |last=Wilson |publisher=University of South Carolina Press|year=2005|isbn=1-57003-573-3|location=Columbia, South Carolina|oclc=232001108|pages=101–102 |ref=Wilson2005}}
*{{cite book |first=Leszek |last=Szymański |title=Kazimierz Pulaski in America: A Monograph, 1777–1779 |publisher=Contra Publishers |year=1979 |ref=Szymański}}
*{{cite book|title=The Southern Strategy: Britain's Conquest of South Carolina and Georgia, 1775–1780|first=David K |last=Wilson|publisher=University of South Carolina Press|year=2005|isbn=1-57003-573-3|location=Columbia, South Carolina|oclc=232001108|page=103}}
*{{cite book|title=The Southern Strategy: Britain's Conquest of South Carolina and Georgia, 1775–1780|first=David K|last=Wilson|publisher=University of South Carolina Press|year=2005|isbn=1-57003-573-3|location=Columbia, South Carolina|oclc=232001108|pages=107–108}}
*{{cite book|title=The Southern Strategy: Britain's Conquest of South Carolina and Georgia, 1775–1780|first=David K|last=Wilson|publisher=University of South Carolina Press|year=2005|isbn=1-57003-573-3|location=Columbia, South Carolina|oclc=232001108|page=108}}
*{{Cite book |last=Jones |first=Charles Colcock |title=The history of Georgia: Revolutionary epoch|year=1883 |volume=2 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=MxESGlpQikQC&amp;pg=PA378 |publisher=Houghton, Mifflin and Co., 540 pages|accessdate=May 17, 2012 |ref=Colcock1883}}
*{{cite book |title=Pulaski, CasimirPublisher=Appletons' Cyclopaedia of American Biography: Pickering-Sumter |year=1898 |first1=James Grant |last1=Wilson  |first2=John |last2=Fiske |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZbBAAQAAMAAJ&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s |ref=appleton133}}
*{{cite web|url=http://www.poles.org/B_day_12/PulaskiBooklet3.pdf|title=Casimir Pulaski Birthday Commemoration. The Real Date of Casimir Pulaski's Birth|publisher=Poles in America Foundation|date=March 6, 2012 |accessdate=May 17, 2012 |ref=DOB}}
*{{cite web |last=Pinkowski |first=Edward |url=http://www.polamjournal.com/Library/APHistory/buried/buried.html |title=General Pulaski's Age. Baptism Record Verifies Historian's Hunch | publisher=Polish American Journal |date=February 1996 |accessdate=May 15, 2012 |ref=Baptism}}
*{{USPL|111|94}} Proclaiming Casimir Pulaski to be an honorary citizen of the United States.
*{{Cite journal |last=Makarewicz |first=Father Stanislaw |others=translated by Peter Obst and Alexandra Medvec |title=The Four Birth Records of Kazimierz Pulaski |url=http://www.poles.org/birth.html |accessdate=March 4, 2009 |publisher=The Catholic University of Lublin (KUL) |year=1998 |periodical=Archiwa, Biblioteki i Muzea Koscielne |volume=70 |ref=Makarewicz}}
*{{cite journal |last=Seidner |first=Stanley S. |year=1976 |title=In Quest of a Cultural Identity: An Inquiry for the Polish Community |publisher=IUME, Teachers College, Columbia University |location=New York |url=http://www.eric.ed.gov/ERICWebPortal/search/detailmini.jsp?_nfpb=true&amp;_&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchValue_0=ED167674&amp;ERICExtSearch_SearchType_0=no&amp;accno=ED167674 |accessdate=October 14, 2009 }}
*{{cite web |title=Kazimierz Pulaski Granted U.S. Citizenship Posthumously (11 March 2009)&amp;nbsp;– U.S. Diplomatic Mission to Warsaw, Poland |url=http://poland.usembassy.gov/embassy-events/embassy-events-2009/kazimierz-pulaski-granted-u.s.-citizenship-posthumously-11-march-2009 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100529093423/http://poland.usembassy.gov/embassy-events/embassy-events-2009/kazimierz-pulaski-granted-u.s.-citizenship-posthumously-11-march-2009 |archivedate=May 29, 2010 |publisher=U. S. Department of State | date = March 11, 2009 |accessdate=May 16, 2012 |ref=Mission}}
*{{cite web|url=http://www.muzeumpulaski.pl |title=Muzeum imienia Kazimierza Pułaskiego w Warce |publisher=Muzeum imienia Kazimierza Pułaskiego w Warce|accessdate=May 15, 2012|language=Polish}}
*Presidential Studies Quarterly Vol. XXIV No. 4 Fall 1994, pp.&amp;nbsp;876–77
*{{cite news | last = Mann | first = William C. | url = | title = Revolutionary War hero becomes honorary US citizen | date = November 10, 2009 |publisher=The Seattle Times | accessdate = May 15, 2012 |ref=Mann}}
*{{cite book|author1=William Scudder Stryker|author2=Society of the Cincinnati in the State of New Jersey|title=The affair at Egg Harbor, New Jersey, October 15, 1778|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=JQIrAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA16|accessdate=May 17, 2012|year=1894|publisher=Naar, Day &amp; Naar |ref=Stryker}}
*{{cite web|url=http://www.uscg.mil/history/webcutters/Pulaski_1825.pdf |title=Pulaski, 1825; U.S. Coast Guard| publisher=U. S. Coast Guard Historian's Office |accessdate= May 15, 2012 |ref=coastguard}}
*{{cite web|url=http://www.ct.gov/ctva/lib/ctva/digital/hartford_war_memorials_list.pdf|title=Hartford War Memorials}}
* {{cite book |first=Annmarie Francis |last=Kajencki |title=Count Casimir Pulaski: From Poland to America, A Hero's Fight for Liberty |publisher=The Rosen Publishing Group |year=2005 |location=New York |isbn=978-1-4042-2646-3 |ref=Kajencki2005}} [https://books.google.com/books?id=MKfKuDDM0doC&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s Url]
*{{cite web |title=WASP |url=http://www.awiatsea.com/Privateers/W/Wasp%20South%20Carolina%20Brig%20%5bBulfinch%20Ferrer%5d.html |publisher=American War of Independence – At Sea|accessdate=April 16, 2011 |ref=WASP}}
*{{cite web |title=General Pulaski's Body |first=Edward |last=Pinkowski |year=1997 |url=http://www.poles.org/p_body.html |publisher=Pulaski Museum in Warka, Poland |ref=Pinkowski}}
{{refend}}

== Further reading ==
*{{cite book |title=Sepulture of Major General Nathanael Greene : and of Brig. Gen. Count Casimir Pulaski |last=Jones |first=Charles Colcock |year=1885 |url=https://archive.org/details/sepultureofmajor00jonerich}}
* {{cite book |title=Hero on Horseback: The Story of Casimir Pulaski |last=Collins |first=David R. |year=1997 |page=32 |publisher=Pelican Publishing |location=Los Angeles|isbn=978-1-4556-0570-5}} [https://books.google.com/books?id=Z4r7SZeVjpMC&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s Url]
* {{cite book |first=Robert Joseph |last=Kerner |title=Brigadier General Casimir Pulaski, A Hero of the American Revolution |publisher=Slavonic Alliance of California|location=San Francisco |year=1936 |oclc=30632693}} [https://books.google.com/books?id=tzJCAAAAIAAJ&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s Url]
* {{cite book |title= Casimir Pulaski|last= Konopczynski|first= Wladyslaw |authorlink= Wladyslaw Konopczynski|author2=translated by Irena Makarewicz |series=Archives and museum|volume= 11|year= 1947|publisher= Annals of the Polish Roman Catholic Union|location= |oclc= 459864667|page= 64}}
* {{cite book |editor-last=Stefaniak |editor-first=Iwona |title=40 lat Muzeum im. Kazimierza Pułaskiego w Warce: bohater, historia i perspektywy rozwoju: materiały z polsko-amerykańskiego sympozjum w Warce-Winiarach, 13–16 października 2007|trans_title=Forty Years of the Casimir Pulaski Museum in Warka: The Hero, History and Perspectives for Development: Papers from the Polish-American Symposium in Warka-Winiary, October 13–16, 2007 |year=2007 |publisher=Casimir Pulaski Museum in Warka |location=Warka |isbn=978-83-925551-5-5 |oclc=212815661 |page=347}}

== External links ==
{{Wikisource|Casimir Pulaski}}
{{commons category|Kazimierz Pułaski}}
* [http://www.poles.org/PulaskiBio.html A Chronology of Casimir Pulaski's Life 1745–1779]
* [http://www.poles.org/Lenkiewicz.html One More Funeral of Kazimierz Pulaski 221 Years After his Death]
* [http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/12561a.htm Biography from ''Catholic Encyclopedia'']
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20100901023219/http://castle.eiu.edu:80/~insight/pulaski/pulaski.htm Casimir Pulaski Day], the Office of Civil Rights and Diversity at [[Eastern Illinois University]]. Leszek Szymański, ''Casimir Pulaski: A Hero of the American Revolution'', E207.P8 S97 1994.
* {{Find a Grave|1632}}
* {{cite web |url= http://www.muzeumpulaski.pl/html/kazimierz_pu3aski.html|title= KAZIMIERZ PUŁASKI |publisher= Muzeum im. Kazimierza Pułaskiego w Warce |language= Polish |trans_title=Casimir Pulaski biography on Casimir Pulaski's Museum in Warka, Poland |accessdate= September 9, 2010 }}
* [http://www.pulaski.pl Casimir Pulaski Foundation]
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Pulaski, Casimir}}
[[Category:1745 births]]
[[Category:1779 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Warsaw]]
[[Category:Pułaski family]]
[[Category:Bar confederates]]
[[Category:Continental Army generals]]
[[Category:Polish emigrants to the United States]]
[[Category:Polish generals in other armies]]
[[Category:Polish people of the American Revolution]]
[[Category:People sentenced to death in absentia]]
[[Category:Military personnel killed in the American Revolutionary War]]
[[Category:Burials in Georgia (U.S. state)]]
[[Category:American Revolution]]
[[Category:People of the American Revolution]]</text>
      <sha1>7eowge0r8try7aosc5exow3qm7hil1k</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
