<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Collins-class submarine</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>810758</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750390178</id>
      <parentid>741435589</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-19T12:31:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Toby6250</username>
        <id>27949080</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="115395">{{Use British English|date=January 2013}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2013}}
{|{{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
|Ship image=[[File:HMAS Rankin 2007.jpg|300px|alt=A large submarine travelling on the surface of the ocean.]]
|Ship caption={{HMAS|Rankin|SSG 78|6}}, sixth submarine of the ''Collins'' class, underway in 2006
}}
{{Infobox ship class overview
|Builders=[[Australian Submarine Corporation]]
|Operators={{navy|AUS}}
|Class before=[[Oberon-class submarine|''Oberon'' class]]
|Class after=[[Collins-class submarine replacement project|''Collins''-class submarine replacement project]] (Planned)
|Built range=14 February 1990 – 18 March 2003
|In commission range=27 July 1996 – present
|Total ships completed=6
|Total ships active=6
|Total ships laid up=
|Total ships lost=
|Total ships retired=
|Total ships preserved=
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
|Ship type=Diesel-electric submarine
|Ship displacement=*{{convert|3100|t|LT}} (surfaced)
*{{convert|3407|t|LT}} (submerged)
|Ship length={{convert|77.42|m|ft|abbr=on}}
|Ship beam={{convert|7.8|m|ft|abbr=on}}
|Ship draught={{convert|7|m|ft|abbr=on}} at waterline
|Ship power=3 × Garden Island-Hedemora HV V18b/15Ub (VB210) 18-cylinder diesel motors, 3 × [[Jeumont-Schneider]] generators (1,400&amp;nbsp;kW, 440-volt DC)
|Ship propulsion=*Main: 1 × [[Jeumont-Schneider]] DC motor ({{convert|7200|hp|abbr=on|disp=or}}), driving 1 × seven-bladed, {{convert|4.22|m|ft|adj=on|abbr=on}} diameter skewback propeller
*Emergency: 1 × MacTaggart Scott DM 43006 retractable hydraulic motor
|Ship speed=*{{convert|10|kn}} surfaced and snorkel depth
*{{convert|20|kn|abbr=on}} submerged
|Ship range=*{{convert|11500|nmi}} at {{convert|10|kn}} surfaced
*{{convert|9000|nmi|abbr=on}} at {{convert|10|kn|abbr=on}} snorkel
*{{convert|480|nmi|abbr=on}} at {{convert|4|kn|abbr=on}} submerged
|Ship endurance=70 days
|Ship test depth=Over {{convert|180|m|ft|abbr=on}} – actual depth classified
|Ship complement=*Originally 42 (plus up to 12 trainees)
*Increased to 58 in 2009
|Ship sensors=*Sonar:
*Thomson Sintra Scylla bow and distributed sonar arrays
*Thales SHORT-TAS towed sonar array
*Thales intercept array
*Radar:
*Kelvin Hughes Type 1007 surface search radar
*Periscopes:
*Thales CK043 search periscope
*Thales CH093 attack periscope
*'''Combat system:'''
*Modified Raytheon CCS Mk2 (AN/BYG-1)
|Ship EW=*Condor  CS-5600 ESM
*2 × SSE decoys
|Ship armament=*6 × {{convert|21|in|mm|adj=on}} bow torpedo tubes
*'''Payload:''' 22 torpedoes, mix of:
*Mark 48 Mod 7 CBASS torpedoes
*UGM-84C Sub-Harpoon anti-ship missiles
*'''Or:''' 44 Stonefish Mark III mines
|Ship notes=
}}
|}
The '''''Collins'' class''' of six Australian-built [[Diesel-electric transmission|diesel-electric]] [[submarine]]s is operated by the [[Royal Australian Navy]] (RAN). The ''Collins'' class takes its name from Australian Vice Admiral [[John Augustine Collins]]; all six submarines are named after significant RAN personnel who distinguished themselves in action during {{nowrap|World War II}}. The boats were the first submarines to be constructed in Australia, prompting widespread improvements in Australian industry.

Planning for a new design to replace the RAN's [[Oberon-class submarine|''Oberon''-class]] submarines began in the late 1970s and early 1980s. Proposals were received from seven companies; two were selected for a funded study to determine the winning design, which was announced in mid-1987. The submarines,  enlarged versions of Swedish shipbuilder [[Kockums]]' [[Västergötland-class submarine|''Västergötland'' class]] and originally referred to as the Type 471, were constructed between 1990 and 2003 in South Australia by the [[Australian Submarine Corporation]] (ASC).

The submarines have been the subject of incidents and technical problems since the design phase, including accusations of foul play and bias during the design selection, improper handling of design changes during construction, major capability deficiencies in the first submarines, and ongoing technical problems throughout the early life of the class. These problems have been compounded by the inability of the RAN to retain sufficient personnel to operate the submarines—by 2008, only three could be manned, and between 2009 and 2012, on average two or fewer were fully operational. The resulting negative press has led to a poor public perception of the ''Collins'' class.

The ''Collins'' class is expected to remain in service until the 2020s. Planning for [[Collins-class submarine replacement project|a replacement class]] of up to 12 vessels commenced in 2007. The new boats are predicted to enter service from 2025, and be active until the 2070s. On 26 April 2016 it was announced that the ''Collins'' class will be replaced by 12 [[French Barracuda-class submarine#Conventional variant|Shortfin Barracuda]] submarines designed by French firm [[DCNS (company)|DCNS]] and to be built in Australia at a projected cost of A$50 billion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.abc.net.au/news/2016-04-26/pm-announces-france-has-won-submarine-contract/7357462|title=PM announces France has won submarine contract|publisher=ABC News|date=26 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Development and design==
The proposal for a new type of submarine to replace the ''Oberon'' class of diesel-electric submarines began in July 1978, when the RAN director of submarine policy prepared a paper detailing the need to start considering a replacement for the ageing ''Oberon''s.&lt;ref name=YW26&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 26&lt;/ref&gt; The paper also raised the suggestion that the majority of the submarines be constructed in Australia and that the number of submarines be increased beyond the six ''Oberon''s.&lt;ref name=YW26/&gt; Building the submarines in Australia was initially met with reactions predicting an impossible task because of the poor state of the Australian shipbuilding industry, and Australian industry in general, although campaigning by several figures in Australian industry who thought it could be done came to the attention of those spearheading the project to design the ''Oberon''-class replacement, and led to the view that it was both possible and feasible.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 37–43&lt;/ref&gt; The campaign to build submarines in Australia was also met with support from the [[Australian Labor Party]] and several trade unions.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 44&lt;/ref&gt;

The proposal was accepted by the defence operational requirements committee in August 1978, and the project was given the procurement designation of SEA 1114.&lt;ref name=YW26/&gt; Approval for the development phase of the project was given in the 1981–82 [[Government of Australia|federal]] budget.&lt;ref name=WoolnerChange3&gt;Woolner, ''Procuring Change'', p. 3&lt;/ref&gt; The RAN had four main requirements: that the submarines were tailored to operating conditions in the [[Australasia]]n region, that they be equipped with a combat system advanced enough to promote a long service life, that appropriate and sustainable infrastructure be established in Australia to construct the boats, then provide maintenance and technical support for their operational lifespan, and that the submarines were capable of peacetime and emergency operations in addition to their hunter-killer role.&lt;ref name=Jonesopp240&gt;Jones, in ''The Royal Australian Navy'', opp. p. 240&lt;/ref&gt; Ten submarines were envisioned, a number which was revised to between four and eight boats by the start of 1983, and later settled on the acquisition of six submarines, with the option to order two more.&lt;ref name=WoolnerChange3/&gt;&lt;ref name=Jones243&gt;Jones, in ''The Royal Australian Navy'', p. 243&lt;/ref&gt;

===Requests for tenders===
The development of the submarine commenced in May 1983, when the government released a [[request for tender]] and approached seven of the world's nine diesel-electric submarine manufacturers for submissions.&lt;ref name=WoolnerChange4&gt;Woolner, ''Procuring Change'', p. 4&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=YW59&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 59&lt;/ref&gt; The submissions would be narrowed down to two based on the provided information, with these undergoing a funded study to determine the winning design.&lt;ref name=YW59/&gt; Tendering companies had to demonstrate how Australian industries would be incorporated into the project, and that they were willing to establish an Australia-based consortium to construct the submarines.&lt;ref name=YW59/&gt; All seven companies responded by the end of the year: the combined submissions totalling four tonnes (9,000&amp;nbsp;lb) of paper.&lt;ref&gt;Woolner, ''Procuring Change'', pp. 4–5&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Jones244&gt;Jones, in ''The Royal Australian Navy'', p. 244&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[DCNS (company)|Directions Techniques Des Constructions Naval]] of France originally supplied a design modified from the [[Agosta-class submarine|''Agosta'' class]], but the submission review board did not view this favourably, as the submarine was of the same vintage as the ''Oberon''s.&lt;ref name=WoolnerChange5&gt;Woolner, ''Procuring Change'', p. 5&lt;/ref&gt; Their submission was altered to a conventionally powered version of the [[Rubis-class submarine|''Rubis''-class nuclear submarine]].&lt;ref name=WoolnerChange5/&gt;
* The German companies [[Ingenieur Kontor Lübeck]] (IKL) and [[Howaldtswerke-Deutsche Werft]] (HDW) collaborated to offer an enlarged version of the [[Type 209 submarine]], designated the Type 2000.&lt;ref name=WoolnerChange6/&gt; Submarines based on the Type 209 design had been exported to several nations, but were not operated by the German Navy.&lt;ref name=WoolnerChange6&gt;Woolner, ''Procuring Change'', p. 6&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Nordseewerke|Thyssen Nordseewerke]], another German company, offered their [[TR-1700-class submarine]].&lt;ref name=WoolnerChange6/&gt; Like the Type 209, the TR-1700 was an export-only submarine design.&lt;ref name=WoolnerChange6/&gt;
* [[Cantieri Navali Riuniti]] of Italy proposed a design based on their [[Sauro-class submarine|''Sauro''-class submarine]], scaled up by 25%.&lt;ref name=WoolnerChange6/&gt; The age of the early 1970s design was a concern, and the proposal was withdrawn early in the process.&lt;ref&gt;Woolner, ''Procuring Change'', pp. 6, 8&lt;/ref&gt;
* The Dutch partnership of [[United Shipbuilder Bureaux]] and [[Rotterdamsche Droogdok Maatschappij]] submitted the [[Walrus-class submarine|''Walrus'' class]].&lt;ref name=WoolnerChange6/&gt; Their offer was identical to that constructed for the [[Royal Netherlands Navy]], minus the Dutch combat system.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 67&lt;/ref&gt;
* Swedish shipbuilder [[Kockums]] submitted the Type 471&amp;nbsp;design, an enlarged version of the [[Västergötland-class submarine|''Västergötland''-class submarine]] operated by the [[Swedish Navy]].&lt;ref name=WoolnerChange7&gt;Woolner, ''Procuring Change'', p. 7&lt;/ref&gt;
* The United Kingdom company [[Vickers Shipbuilding &amp; Engineering]] offered a design referred to as the Type 2400, that later became the [[Upholder/Victoria-class submarine|''Upholder'' class]].&lt;ref name=WoolnerChange8&gt;Woolner, ''Procuring Change'', p. 8&lt;/ref&gt;
The review board concluded that the IKL/HDW Type&amp;nbsp;2000 was the best design offered, the ''Walrus'' class was rated as 'fair', while Kockums' and Vickers' proposals were considered 'marginal' contenders.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 62–8&lt;/ref&gt; However, none of the tenders completely matched the desired RAN specifications, and the two proposals selected would have to be redesigned during the funded study.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 67–8&lt;/ref&gt;

The combat data system was procured separately to the submarine design; 14 companies were identified as capable of providing what the RAN wanted, from which eight were approached in January 1983 with a separate request for tender.&lt;ref name=WoolnerChange4/&gt;&lt;ref name=YW59/&gt; Five responded: a consortium led by [[Rockwell International]] of the United States, [[Plessey]] of the United Kingdom, [[Signaal]] of the Netherlands, [[Sintra Alcatel]] of France, and a collaboration between the German [[Atlas Elektronik|Krupp Atlas Elektronik]] and the British [[Ferranti]].&lt;ref name=YW68&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 68&lt;/ref&gt; Each tender was required to offer a system with a [[distributed architecture]], despite the absence of an accepted definition for '[[distributed computing]]' at that time, and had to show the cost of programming the software in [[Ada (programming language)|Ada]], although they could offer additional cost breakdowns for other programming languages.&lt;ref name=YW68/&gt;

===Funded studies===
By May 1985, three months behind schedule, the review board narrowed the tenders down to two contenders in each group: IKL/HDW and Kockums for the submarine, Rockwell and Signaal for the combat system.&lt;ref name=WoolnerChange9&gt;Woolner, ''Procuring Change'', p. 9&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Walrus'' and Type 2400&amp;nbsp;submarine designs were considered to be too expensive to manufacture because of inefficient building practices, while the combat data system tenders had been narrowed down by unjustified development risk in the Plessey and Krupp/Ferranti proposals, and the dual problems in the Sintra Alcatel tender of excessive power usage and incompatibility with the proposed American weapons system.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 68–71&lt;/ref&gt; On 9 May, the Australian cabinet approved the selections for the funded studies and decided that six submarines would be built, with the option for two more, all in Australia.&lt;ref name=YW74.5&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 74–5&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Rss archer.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Aerial photograph of a submarine removed from the water in a dock, flags and banners decorate the submarine.|RSS ''Archer'', a [[Västergötland class submarine|''Västergötland''-class submarine]] of the Republic of Singapore Navy: The ''Västergötland'' design was enlarged to create Kockums' Type 471&amp;nbsp;proposal.]]

The companies were granted funding for project definition studies, from which the final selections would be made.&lt;ref name=GrazebrookDU/&gt; Liaison teams were sent to each of the four companies to observe the development of the concepts presented in the initial proposals.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 90–1&lt;/ref&gt; As part of this process, the two submarine designers were required to establish a consortium with at least 50% Australian ownership: IKL/HDW joined with [[Eglo Engineering]] to form [[Australian Marine Systems]], while Kockums (which had originally planned to work with Eglo) became part of a joint venture with the Australian branch of [[Chicago Bridge &amp; Iron]], [[Wormald International]], and the [[Australian Industry Development Corporation]] to create the [[Australian Submarine Corporation]].&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 76–80&lt;/ref&gt;

During the study, various accusations of foul play by or unsuitability of both submarine designers were made by Australian politicians and the media.&lt;ref name=YW82.3&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 82–3&lt;/ref&gt; These included claims that the similar [[Left-wing politics|left-wing political leanings]] of the [[Australian Labor Party]] (ALP) and the [[Swedish Social Democratic Party]], both in power at the time, would lead to a pro-Kockums bias, investigations into perceived coaching of IDL/HDW representatives in the questions to be asked at an ALP Caucus briefing session on the project, and public emphasis on security incidents in both Sweden and West Germany.&lt;ref name=YW82.3/&gt; These incidents either lacked supporting evidence or were proven false, and were the result of the [[Liberal Party of Australia|Liberal Party]] attempting to discredit the Labor government, or pro-British politicians and organisations who believed both submarines were inferior to the Vickers Type 2400&amp;nbsp;offering.&lt;ref name=YW82.3/&gt;

The [[Dibb Report]] on the state of the Australian Defence Force was released in March 1986; it included advice that if the submarine project cost increased too much, the boats' capabilities should be scaled back to save money.&lt;ref name=YW97&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 97&lt;/ref&gt; Around the same time, [[Treasurer of Australia|Federal Treasurer]] [[Paul Keating]] began efforts to tighten [[fiscal policy]] and cut government spending across all portfolios.&lt;ref name=YW97/&gt; Consequently, despite his enthusiastic support for the project as a means to improve Australia's defence and industrial capabilities, [[Minister for Defence (Australia)|Minister for Defence]] [[Kim Beazley]] advised the project heads that he would not be able to secure Cabinet approval for construction of the submarines if the predicted cost &quot;started with a 4 [A$4 billion]&quot;.&lt;ref name=YW97/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jones, in ''The Royal Australian Navy'', pp. 243–4&lt;/ref&gt;

===Evaluation and final selection===
The four tenders resulting from the study were submitted during October and November 1986.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 100&lt;/ref&gt; Although the IKL/HDW design was rated highest during the initial inspection, the evaluation team found that the German proposal was less attractive than previously thought.&lt;ref name=YW102.6&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 102–6&lt;/ref&gt; Although IKL/HDW claimed that their boat could meet the RAN's performance requirements, the evaluators concluded from the information provided that doing so would require the deactivation of all non-essential and some essential systems.&lt;ref name=YW102.6/&gt; Conversely, Kockums' proposal conceded that they did not meet the requirements, although evaluators found that the figures failed by only narrow margins, and believed that these were conservative.&lt;ref name=YW102.6/&gt; The evaluation team recalculated the capability statistics for both submarines to a common baseline, portraying the predicted Australian operating conditions, which generally saw Kockums' figures revised upwards, and those from IKL/HDW downwards.&lt;ref name=YW102.6/&gt; This resulted in growing support for the Type&amp;nbsp;471 bid, and outcries from the IKL and HDW groups, who questioned the validity of the recalculations and if the Australian evaluators had the experience to do this correctly.&lt;ref name=YW102.6/&gt;

[[File:ROKS Lee Sunsin (SS 068) arrives at Naval Station Pearl Harbor.jpg|thumb|left|alt=A submarine travelling on the water's surface near to shore, with trees and mountains in the background.|ROKS ''Lee Sunsin'', a South Korean submarine based on the IKL/HDW [[Type 209 submarine|Type 209]] design. The Type 209 unsuccessfully competed against the Kockums Type 471 for selection as the basis of the ''Collins'' class]]
Analysis of the two combat system proposals saw Signaal fall out of favour with the tender reviewers.&lt;ref name=YW99.107.8&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 99, 107–8&lt;/ref&gt; This was primarily attributed to a cost-reducing re-design late in the process: the changes were not fully documented because of time constraints.&lt;ref name=YW99.107.8/&gt; Supporting documentation was further criticised by the reviewers for being vaguely worded and not using [[milspec]] terminology and standards.&lt;ref name=YW99.107.8/&gt; In addition, the system proposed by Rockwell appeared to have greater performance capabilities, and would be cheaper to implement.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 180&lt;/ref&gt;

On 18 May 1987, the Australian Cabinet approved the final design: Kockums' Type&amp;nbsp;471 submarine, fitted with the Rockwell system.&lt;ref name=Jones244/&gt; The contract for construction of six submarines was signed on 3 June and valued at A$3.9 billion in 1986 prices, with allowances for inflation and the changing value of the Australian dollar.&lt;ref name=WoolnerChange13&gt;Woolner, ''Procuring Change'', p. 13&lt;/ref&gt; The submarine acquisition project was at the time the most expensive project ever undertaken by the [[Australian Defence Force]], but was unseated from this title by the [[Anzac-class frigate|''Anzac''-class frigate project]] a few years later.&lt;ref&gt;Jones, in ''The Royal Australian Navy'', p. 245&lt;/ref&gt;

==Construction==
The Australian Submarine Corporation construction facility was established on previously undeveloped land on the bank of the [[Port River]], at [[Osborne, South Australia]].&lt;ref name=Jones244/&gt; Work on the site began on 29 June 1987, and it was opened in November 1989.&lt;ref name=Jones244/&gt;&lt;ref name=YW127&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 127&lt;/ref&gt; South Australia was selected as the site of the construction facility based on the proposed location of the facility and promises by the State Government to help minimise any problems caused by workers unions.&lt;ref name=YW87.8.128&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 87–8, 128&lt;/ref&gt; The state's bid was aided by careful promotion to both Kockums and IKL/HDW during early in the project, and problems with the other states' proposals: [[Tasmania]] and [[Western Australia]] lacked the necessary industrial base, [[New South Wales]] could not decide on the location of the construction facility, [[Victoria (Australia)|Victoria's]] proposed site was poorly sited, and building in [[Liberal Party of Australia|Liberal]]-led [[Queensland]] would have been politically unwise for the project when [[Australian Labor Party|Labor]] was in power both federally and in all other states.&lt;ref name=YW87.8.128/&gt;

[[File:Australian Submarine Corporation building.jpg|thumb|left|alt=A long, wide building on the shore of a river, with the letters &quot;ASC&quot; on the visible faces.|The Australian Submarine Corporation construction facility, where the six submarines were assembled]]
Each submarine was constructed in six sections, each consisting of several sub-sections.&lt;ref name=YW147&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 147&lt;/ref&gt; One of the main criteria of the project was that Australian industries contribute to at least 60% of the work; by the conclusion of the project 70% of the construction and 45% of the software preparation had been completed by Australian-owned companies.&lt;ref name=GrazebrookDU&gt;Grazebrook, ''Collins class comes up Down Under''&lt;/ref&gt; Work was sub-contracted out to 426&amp;nbsp;companies across twelve countries, plus numerous sub-sub-contractors.&lt;ref name=YW127/&gt; In many cases, components for the first submarine were constructed by companies outside Australia, while those for the following five boats were replicated by an Australian-owned partner or subsidiary.&lt;ref name=YW142.4/&gt; The project prompted major increases in quality control standards across Australian industries: in 1980, only 35&amp;nbsp;Australian companies possessed the appropriate quality control certifications for Defence projects, but by 1998 this had increased to over 1,500.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 48&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the acquisition project organisers originally planned for the first submarine to be constructed overseas, the Cabinet decided as part of the project's approval that all six submarines would be built in Australia; the increases in construction time and cost from not building the lead ship in the winning designer's home shipyard was considered to be offset by the additional experience provided to Australian industries.&lt;ref&gt;Woolner, ''Procuring Change'', pp. 4, 9&lt;/ref&gt; Even so, two sections of the first submarine were constructed by Kockums' shipyard in [[Malmo, Sweden]].&lt;ref name=YW142.4&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 142–4&lt;/ref&gt;

By the end of 1990, Chicago Bridge &amp; Iron and Wormald International had both sold their shares in ASC.&lt;ref name=YW181.4&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 181–4&lt;/ref&gt; The shares were bought up by Kockums and the Australian Industry Development Corporation, with some of Kockums' shares then sold to [[James Hardie Industries]] to maintain an Australian majority ownership of the company.&lt;ref name=YW181.4/&gt; On 5 April 2000, the shares in ASC held by Kockums were bought out and the company was [[nationalised]], despite a trend at the time to [[privatise]] government-owned companies.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 312&lt;/ref&gt; At the end of 2003, a contract to maintain the ''Collins'' class worth $3.5&amp;nbsp;billion over 25&amp;nbsp;years was awarded to ASC.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 315&lt;/ref&gt;

As of April 1996, the option to order the seventh and eighth submarines was still under consideration, but was looked on unfavourably by the Department of Defence at the time, as the additional cost would require the diversion of funding from the [[Australian Army]] and [[Royal Australian Air Force]], resulting in an imbalance in the capabilities of the Australian Defence Force.&lt;ref name=GrazebrookCross/&gt; The option was cancelled outright by late 2001.&lt;ref&gt;Woolner, ''Getting in Early'', p. 16&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- Source does not specify when the two submarines were cancelled --&gt;

===Entry into service===
[[File:HMAS Collins ASC.png|thumb|upright|alt=A submarine emerging from a large building. The submarine is decorated with flags, and the name &quot;COLLINS&quot; is painted across the front. There are a number of people around the base of the submarine.|Launching of HMAS ''Collins'', lead boat and namesake of the class, on 28 August 1993]]
The first submarine, {{HMAS|Collins|SSG 73|6}}, was laid down in February 1990.&lt;ref name=Jonesopp240/&gt; ''Collins''{{'}} launch was originally planned for 1994, but was later set for 28 August 1993.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 187–8&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=JDW070893/&gt; Although launched on schedule, she was not complete: the design of the submarine had not been finalised, important internal pipes and fittings were not installed, the components of the combat system had yet to be delivered, and some hull sections were actually sheets of timber painted black so the submarine would appear complete in photographs of the launching ceremony.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 188–9, 193&lt;/ref&gt; Within weeks of the launch, ''Collins'' was removed from the water, and it was not until June 1994 that the submarine was completed.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 193&lt;/ref&gt; Progress on the other five submarines was delayed by the extra effort required to meet ''Collins''{{'}} launching date and the subsequent work to complete her.&lt;ref name=YW188/&gt; ''Collins'' was not commissioned into the RAN until 27 July 1996; eighteen months behind schedule, because of several delays and problems, most relating to the provision and installation of the combat data system software.&lt;ref name=Jonesopp240/&gt;&lt;ref name=Lok/&gt; ''Collins'' was not approved for operational deployments until 2000.&lt;ref name=Wertheim19&gt;Wertheim (ed.), ''Combat Fleets of the World'', p. 19&lt;/ref&gt;

The other five submarines were scheduled for completion at 12-month intervals.&lt;ref name=YW188&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 188&lt;/ref&gt; However, the series of defects and problems encountered during [[sea trial]]s of the submarines (particularly ''Collins'') resulted in the repeated diversion of resources from those still under construction, adding to delays.&lt;ref name=YW215&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 215&lt;/ref&gt; Consequently, delivery of the submarines ran significantly behind schedule; submarines were presented to the RAN between 21&amp;nbsp;and 41&amp;nbsp;months late, and the entire class was not cleared for full operational service until March 2004, a year after the last boat was commissioned.&lt;ref name=YuleWool348&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 348&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=SPGmedia/&gt; These delays forced the RAN to keep several ''Oberon''-class submarines and the submarine base [[HMAS Platypus (naval base)|HMAS ''Platypus'']] in service beyond their planned decommissioning dates.&lt;ref&gt;Jones, in ''The Royal Australian Navy'', pp. 276–7&lt;/ref&gt;

===McIntosh-Prescott Report and Fast Track program===&lt;!-- This section heading is used as a redirect anchor for [[McIntosh-Prescott Report]], and is linked directly from several articles --&gt;
Following his appointment as [[Minister for Defence (Australia)|Minister for Defence]] following the [[Australian federal election, 1998|1998 federal election]], [[John Moore (Australian politician)|John Moore]]  decided that the only way to solve the various problems of the ''Collins'' class was for an independent report to be prepared on them.&lt;ref name=YW274.81&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 274–81&lt;/ref&gt; He appointed Malcolm McIntosh, chief executive of the [[CSIRO]] and an unofficial advisor to Moore, and John Prescott, a former [[Broken Hill Proprietary Company|BHP]] director, to investigate the project, uncover the problems with the submarines, and suggest ways of solving them.&lt;ref name=YW274.81/&gt;

The ''Report to the Minister for Defence on the Collins class submarine and related matters'' (commonly referred to as the ''McIntosh-Prescott Report'') was compiled in ten weeks, and released on 1 June 1999.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 278, 280–1&lt;/ref&gt; This report concluded that the ''Collins'' class was incapable of performing at the required level for military operations.&lt;ref name=YW281.2&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 281–2&lt;/ref&gt; Although the report highlighted several elements of the submarine design that performed to or beyond expectations, and acknowledged that many of the publicised problems had been or were in the process of being fixed, it presented the propulsion system, combat system, and excessive noise as ongoing problems across the class.&lt;ref name=YW281.2/&gt; After identifying the combat system as the central problem, McIntosh and Prescott recommended that it be scrapped entirely and replaced with a system based on commercially available equipment and software.&lt;ref name=YW281.2/&gt; They also claimed that these problems were caused by poor design and manufacture; inappropriate design requirements; deficiencies in the structure of the contract, particularly with regards to modifying the contract to meet changing requirements; and problems between the various parties involved in the construction of the submarines, with a lack of overall direction and conflicts of interest causing avoidable hostility and uncooperativeness.&lt;ref name=YW281.2/&gt; Despite the report being promoted by the government as 'ground-breaking', many people involved with the ''Collins''-class project later claimed that large sections of the report could have been copied from reports previously submitted by the RAN or ASC.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 282–3&lt;/ref&gt;

The report, along with the planned December 2000 decommissioning of the final ''Oberon''-class submarine, {{HMAS|Otama||2}}, prompted the establishment of an A$1&amp;nbsp;billion program to bring the fourth and fifth submarines ({{HMAS|Dechaineux|SSG 76|2}} and {{HMAS|Sheean|SSG 77|2}}) up to operational standards, then retrofit the modifications to the other boats.&lt;ref name=YW288.9&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 288–9&lt;/ref&gt; Referred to as the &quot;fast track&quot; or &quot;get well&quot; program, the program also included solving the problems preventing various parties from cooperating fully, and improving the negative media coverage and public perception of the class by responding to criticism and providing more information to reporters.&lt;ref name=YW288.9/&gt;

===Submarines in class===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
!Name&lt;ref name=RANclass&gt;''Collins Class'', Royal Australian Navy&lt;/ref&gt;
!Pennant&lt;ref name=RANclass/&gt;
!Laid down&lt;ref name=Wertheim18&gt;Wertheirm (ed.), ''Combat Fleets of the World'', p. 18&lt;/ref&gt;
!Launched&lt;ref name=Wertheim18/&gt;
!Delivered&lt;ref name=YuleWool348/&gt;
!Commissioned&lt;ref name=RANclass/&gt;
!Namesake&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 317, 340&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|{{HMAS|Collins|SSG 73|2}}
|SSG 73
|14 February 1990
|28 August 1993
|15 July 1996&lt;br /&gt;(18 months late)
|27 July 1996
|[[Vice admiral|Vice Admiral]] [[John Augustine Collins|Sir John Collins KBE, CB]]
|-
|{{HMAS|Farncomb|SSG 74|2}}
|SSG 74
|1 March 1991
|15 December 1995
|15 December 1997&lt;br /&gt;(22 months late)
|31 January 1998
|[[Rear admiral|Rear Admiral]] [[Harold Bruce Farncomb|Harold Farncomb CB, DSO, MVO]]
|-
|{{HMAS|Waller|SSG 75|2}}
|SSG 75
|19 March 1992
|14 March 1997
|30 April 1999&lt;br /&gt;(27 months late)
|10 July 1999
|[[Captain (naval)|Captain]] [[Hector Waller|Hector Waller DSO and Bar]]
|-
|{{HMAS|Dechaineux|SSG 76|2}}
|SSG 76
|4 March 1993
|12 March 1998
|21 July 2000&lt;br /&gt;(31 months late)
|23 February 2001
|[[Captain (naval)|Captain]] [[Emile Dechaineux|Emile Dechaineux DSC]]
|-
|{{HMAS|Sheean|SSG 77|2}}
|SSG 77
|17 February 1994
|1 May 1999
|25 August 2000&lt;br /&gt;(21 months late)
|23 February 2001
|[[Ordinary seaman (rating)|Ordinary Seaman]] [[Teddy Sheean|Edward Sheean]]
|-
|{{HMAS|Rankin|SSG 78|2}}
|SSG 78
|12 May 1995
|26 November 2001
|18 March 2003&lt;br /&gt;(41 months late)
|29 March 2003
|[[Lieutenant commander|Lieutenant Commander]] [[Robert William Rankin|Robert Rankin]]
|-
|}

==Problems during construction and trials==
The ''Collins''-class submarines experienced a wide range of problems during their construction and early service life. Many of these were attributed to the submarines being a new, untested design, and were successfully addressed as they were discovered.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 217–8&lt;/ref&gt; Most systems and features worked with few or no problems, while the boats' maximum speed, manoeuvrability, and low-speed submerged endurance were found to exceed specifications.&lt;ref name=YW217&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 217&lt;/ref&gt; The ship control system, which during development had been marked as a major potential problem, functioned beyond positive expectation: for example, the autopilot (which aboard ''Collins'' was nicknamed 'Sven') was found to be better at maintaining depth during [[Submarine snorkel|snorting]] than most helmsmen.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 217, 220&lt;/ref&gt;

However, problems with the combat system, excessive noise, and engine breakdowns were recurring and appeared across the entire class.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 220&lt;/ref&gt; These and other shortcomings were often made harder to solve by disagreements between Kockums, ASC, Rockwell, the RAN, and the Australian Government over the nature of problems, their causes, and who was responsible for solving them.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 323&lt;/ref&gt; Media reporting of the problems during the mid-1990s was often negative and exaggerated, creating poor public perception.&lt;ref name=YW221&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 221&lt;/ref&gt; This was aided by politicians, who used the shortcomings to politically attack the Labor Party and Kim Beazley, particularly after Labor was defeated by the [[Coalition (Australia)|Liberal-National Coalition]] in the [[Australian federal election, 1996|1996 federal election]], and Beazley became [[Leader of the Opposition (Australia)|Leader of the Opposition]].&lt;ref name=Kelton103.4&gt;Kelton, ''More than an ally?'', pp. 103–4&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=YW266&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 266&lt;/ref&gt; During the mid-1990s, it was recommended on several occasions that the submarine project be abandoned, and the completed submarines and incomplete hulls be broken up for scrap.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 266, 288&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the ''McIntosh-Prescott Report'', which indicated the long-term faults with the class that still required solving, successful efforts were made to bring the submarines to operational standard.&lt;ref name=&quot;YW288.9&quot; /&gt; As part of this, a public relations plan was implemented to provide up-to-date information on the submarines to the media, to improve the public perception of the class by providing factual information on the status of the project and responding to queries and incidents.&lt;ref name=YW289&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 289&lt;/ref&gt; This same period saw the dispelling of the idea, widely held within the RAN, that the ''Collins''-class boats would be like any other vessel previously ordered by the RAN: in service with another navy, well tested, and with all the problems solved before they entered Australian hands.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 209, 267&lt;/ref&gt; The RAN began to realise that as the parent navy for the class, they had a greater responsibility than normal in ensuring that the boats were at an operational standard.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 209, 267–9&lt;/ref&gt;

===Welding of ''Collins''===
During assembly of ''Collins''{{'}} [[Bow (ship)|bow]] section in Sweden, multiple defects in the hull welding were discovered.&lt;ref name=YW144.6&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 144–6&lt;/ref&gt; Different reasons were given by different parties for the problems: the [[Alloy steel|steel alloy]] used for the hull required different welding techniques to those normally used by Kockums; the Swedish navy always requested partial penetration welds for their submarines, while the RAN wanted full penetration welding, but had not made this clear; delays in delivering the steel plates to Kockums resulted in rushed work and a resulting drop in quality.&lt;ref name=YW144.6/&gt; Kockums engineers proposed that the section be kept in Sweden for repairs, but to minimise delays it was accepted as-is, with repairs attempted at ASC during full assembly of the first boat.&lt;ref name=YW144.6/&gt;

However, when ''Collins'' returned to the ASC facility in April 2001 for a year-long maintenance docking, multiple welding defects were found in the bow and escape tower sections of the submarine (the two sections constructed by Kockums), while almost no problems were found in the welding of the four Australian-built sections.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 316–7&lt;/ref&gt; Repairing these welds quadrupled the time ''Collins'' spent in dock.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 317&lt;/ref&gt;

===Noise signature===
The noise made by the submarines, which compromised their ability to stay hidden, was another major problem with the design.&lt;ref name=YW137.9&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 137–9&lt;/ref&gt; In the original requisition, the RAN guidelines for the noise signature of the new submarines were vague; for example, asking that they be &quot;twice as quiet&quot; as the ''Oberon''s.&lt;ref name=YW226&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 226&lt;/ref&gt; Expectations and operational requirements also changed between the 1987 contract signing and when the submarines began operating in the late 1990s.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 226–7&lt;/ref&gt; The major element of the noise signature for the ''Oberon'' class was machinery noise transmitted through the hull; this was successfully avoided during construction of the ''Collins'' class by mounting machinery on platforms isolated from the hull.&lt;ref name=YW226/&gt;

Noise testing during 1996 and 1997 found that the hydrodynamic noise signature—the noise made by a submarine passing through the water—was excessive, particularly at high speed.&lt;ref name=YW227.9&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 227–9&lt;/ref&gt; The shape of the hull was the main cause: although a scale model of the design had been tested during the funded study and was found to have a minimal signature, the hull shape was changed after the contract was signed, primarily by a {{convert|2|m|ft|adj=on}} lengthening of the submarine and a redesign of the bow dome to accommodate the larger-than-expected main sonar and reduce its blind spot (the [[baffles (submarine)|baffles]]).&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 137–9, 227&lt;/ref&gt; The design had not been retested, as who would pay for this could not be agreed on.&lt;ref name=YW137.9/&gt; Propeller [[cavitation]], caused by [[Fluid dynamics|water flow]] over control surfaces onto the propeller at certain speeds, was the other main noisemaker.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 229&lt;/ref&gt; Cavitation had not been a problem with earlier Swedish submarine designs or during early testing of the Type 471 design, but the propeller had to be redesigned late in the process to provide more power, and like the redesigned hull, was not retested.&lt;ref name=YW230&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 230&lt;/ref&gt; During the years 2000, an unusual meeting took place with a next door neighbor (Francis 'Frank' Smith)of the then HMAS Stirling Naval Base commander. He was an Aircraft Maintenance Engineer (originally trained at Government Aircraft Factories Fisherman's bend) who had been aware of the fluid dynamics issues of the Collins class for some time, purely by interest and observation on television. After a lengthy discussion, he was invited to discuss and demonstrate where possible, his observations at the Stirling Naval Base with Navy and DSTO staff who were there at that time as part of an investigative group. He showed on a white board, the aerofoil issue with the Dorsal - Sail conning tower structure showing that the Cord ratio (Length to Width) was too short and that severe turbulence / cavitation would be generated by such a design. This was demonstrated again on the white board using Aircraft aerofoil wing shapes as a basis for the discussion. That the turbulence / cavitation generated would, by natural rearward flow, move down the rear upper surface deck of the hull and be drawn into the propeller. He was also able to demonstrate that the design of the bow section would not pass a flow test for generated turbulence / cavitation, with the change in shape from circular bow section to long hull, being ill conceived. He made several recommendations during the lecture that would be cost effective and possible. 1) To lengthen and taper the dorsal fin and create a more streamlined integration of the Dorsal to Flat upper Hull deck section. and 2) To 'fill in' the hollow section of hull aft of the bow curvature. Both these could be achieved with Carbon Fibre or Fibreglass covers as no load bearing strength would be required. Subsequent studies by the [[Defence Science and Technology Organisation|Defence Science and Technology Organization]] showed that the submarine's hull shape, particularly the redesigned sonar dome, the [[Fin (submarine)|fin]], and the rear of the submarine, focused the displaced water into two turbulent streams; when the seven propeller blades hit these streams, the propeller's vibration was increased, causing cavitation.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 236–8&lt;/ref&gt; These problems were fixed by modifying the casing of the submarine with fiberglass fairings.&lt;ref name=YW238&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 238&lt;/ref&gt;

===Propulsion system===
During trials of the first submarines, the propulsion system was found to be prone to failure for a variety of reasons.&lt;ref name=YW222&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 222&lt;/ref&gt; Most failures were attributed to the fifteen-tank diesel fuel system: the tanks were designed to fill with salt water as they were emptied to maintain [[neutral buoyancy]], but water would regularly enter the engines due to a combination of poor design, [[gravity separation]] of the fuel and water being insufficient, and operator error resulting from poor training.&lt;ref name=YW222/&gt; Problems were also caused by bacterial contamination of the diesel fuel, which, along with the salt water, would cause the fuel pumps to rust and other components to seize.&lt;ref name=YW222.4&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 222–4&lt;/ref&gt; The fuel-related issues were solved by installing [[coalescer]]s, improving training and operational procedures, and adding [[biocide]]s to the fuel.&lt;ref name=YW222.4/&gt;

Propeller shaft seals were a significant problem on ''Collins'' and ''Farncomb''.&lt;ref name=YW233&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 233&lt;/ref&gt; Although designed to allow for a leak of {{convert|10|L}} per hour, during trials it was found that the seals would regularly misalign and allow hundreds of litres per hour into the boat—during one deep diving test the flow rate was measured at approximately {{convert|1000|L}} a minute.&lt;ref name=YW233/&gt; ASC claimed that solving these problems could be done by manually adjusting the seals as the submarine dived and rose, but this would have required a sailor dedicated solely to that task, affecting efforts to minimise the required number of personnel.&lt;ref name=YW233/&gt; It was found that the problem could be temporarily alleviated by running the propeller in reverse for 100&amp;nbsp;revolutions, pulling the seal back into alignment, although a permanent solution could initially not be found, as ASC refused to accept responsibility for the problem, and the original manufacturer of the seals had closed down.&lt;ref name=YW233/&gt; New suppliers were found, with modified seals fitted to the first two submarines in late 1996, before completely re-designed seals were fitted to the boats in late 1997, solving the problem.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 233–4&lt;/ref&gt;

The propellers themselves were also found to be poorly manufactured, having been shaped by hand, with at least one cast at the wrong [[Blade pitch|pitch]].&lt;ref name=YW230.1.8.9&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 230–1, 238–9&lt;/ref&gt; This was rectified by using a five-axis [[milling machine]] for future shaping work and replacing the miscast propeller.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 230–1&lt;/ref&gt; The material used for the propellers was also found to be weaker than expected, developing [[Fatigue (material)|fatigue]] cracks after only a few years of use.&lt;ref name=YW230.1.8.9/&gt; Instead of going to Kockums, which had started to go into decline after the end of the Cold War, the submarine project office sent the propeller to the [[United States Navy]] for redesigning.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 263&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the Americans fixing the problems with the propeller design, resulting in significant performance improvements, the Swedish company was dissatisfied with the Australian actions; the dispatch of the propellers was one of the points of contention in the company's legal action in the mid-2000s against the Australian government over ownership of the [[intellectual property]] rights to the submarine's design.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 264, 315–17&lt;/ref&gt;

Other propulsion problems included excessive motor vibrations at certain speeds which damaged various components (which was attributed to the removal of a [[flywheel]] and to corrosion caused by the fuel problems), and excessive fuel consumption in ''Collins'' at high speed (found to be caused by manufacturing problems with the turbines and turbochargers).&lt;ref name=YW224.55&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 224–5&lt;/ref&gt; The propulsion system was also found to be a secondary source of noise: poor design of the exhaust [[muffler]]s, weight-saving measures in the generator mountings, and an incorrect voltage supply to the battery compartment exhaust fans were noise-creating factors found and eliminated during studies by the Defence Science and Technology Organisation.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 239–40&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 2010, the Department of Defence revealed that the generators in five of the submarines were flawed and had to be replaced.&lt;ref name=OakesMarch2010&gt;Oakes, ''This time it's the generators''&lt;/ref&gt; The three Australian-made generators aboard each of the five submarines (the generators aboard ''Collins'' were French-built, and exhibited no defects) are to be replaced in the submarines as they come in for their next [[#Maintenance|maintenance docking]].&lt;ref name=OakesMarch2010/&gt;

===Periscopes and masts===&lt;!-- This section heading is linked to from within the article --&gt;
The periscopes had two problems, the first of which was shared with the other masts.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 231–2&lt;/ref&gt; They were not streamlined; raising a periscope while moving would create enough [[drag (physics)|drag]] and [[turbulence]] to shake the entire submarine.&lt;ref name=YW231&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 231&lt;/ref&gt; As with many elements of the submarine, there were disagreements as to who was responsible for the problem.&lt;ref name=YW231/&gt; It was solved by modifying the masts to redirect the water flow around them (for example, a spiral wrap was fixed around the head of each periscope).&lt;ref name=YW232&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 232&lt;/ref&gt;

The periscopes also had problems with their optics: periscope users reported difficulty in refocusing after changing magnification, duplication of images, and bands across the field of vision.&lt;ref name=YW232/&gt; These problems were attributed to RAN demands that the optical view be the first exposed when a periscope was raised above the water, instead of placing the infrared sensor and single-pulse radar at the head as on other submarines, requiring the optical path to be routed around these components.&lt;ref name=YW232/&gt; The periscopes were gradually improved, and were no longer a problem by the time the fast track submarines entered service.&lt;ref name=Wertheim19/&gt;

===Combat system===
Despite the public focus on the various physical issues with the boats, the major problem with the submarines was the development of the Rockwell combat system.&lt;ref name=YW153.4&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 153–4&lt;/ref&gt; The problems had started during the funded study, when [[Singer Librascope]] and [[Thomson CSF]], who were partnering with Rockwell to develop the combat system, refused to release their intellectual property or their software code for Rockwell to sell.&lt;ref name=YW98&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 98&lt;/ref&gt; It was proposed that Computer Sciences of Australia, a division of [[Computer Sciences Corporation]] and a minor partner in the consortium, take over the role of writing the software for the combat system, although this meant that Singer Librascope, which had prior experience in creating submarine combat systems, was reduced to a minor role in the project.&lt;ref name=YW98/&gt; Other major problems with the system, to which most of the later difficulties were attributed, were that the original concept was beyond the technology of the day, and that the system architecture required by the RAN was both overly ambitious and flawed.&lt;ref name=YW153.4/&gt; This was compounded by the rate of advancement in computer technology: equipment had to be designed from scratch and custom manufactured at the start of the project, but by the time these were installed, they were obsolete compared to commercially available hardware and software.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 155–6&lt;/ref&gt;

Australian Submarine Corporation was made responsible for the delivery of the Rockwell combat system, but had little ability to enforce this.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 156&lt;/ref&gt; Rockwell was contracted to deliver the combat system by 9 September 1993, but was unlikely to do so.&lt;ref name=YW199.200&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 199–200&lt;/ref&gt; ASC's management board voted to issue a default notice to Rockwell as the American company had defaulted on the contract, but was ordered by the Department of Defence to retract the default notice and accept gradual delivery of partially completed versions of the combat system—referred to as 'releases' and 'drops'—until the complete system had been delivered.&lt;ref name=YW199.200/&gt; [[Sea trial]]s of ''Collins'' were unable to commence until Release 1.5 of the combat system software was delivered; because of ongoing delays in the provision of the software, the early phases of the trials were completed using stand-alone equipment&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 212, 244–5&lt;/ref&gt; By March 1994, the combat system had become the major area of concern for the submarine project: assembly of the system was almost nine months behind schedule, and at least 20% of the software had not been compiled.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 245&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Rockwell signs 'Kilo' system deal'', Jane's Defence Weekly&lt;/ref&gt; The combat system continued to be a problem during the next few years, with progressive drops offering little improvements in performance over the previous version, and the completion date of Release 2—the designation for the full contractual realisation of the combat system software—was continually postponed.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 245–8&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1996, Rockwell sold its military and aerospace division, including responsibility for the ''Collins'' combat system, to [[Boeing]].&lt;ref name=YW250.1&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 250–1&lt;/ref&gt; Boeing attempted to produce a workable combat system, but believed that this could only be done if the changes in technology were accounted for in a contract alteration, which the RAN and the Australian Government initially refused to do.&lt;ref name=YW250.1/&gt; Boeing then requested assistance from [[Raytheon]], and after further negotiations with the Government resulted in a reduction of the system capabilities, the companies were able to stabilise the system and deliver Release 2.0 at the end of 1999.&lt;ref name=YW260&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 260&lt;/ref&gt; Boeing sold its naval systems division to Raytheon in May 2000, making the latter company solely responsible for completion of the combat system.&lt;ref name=YW260/&gt; After this, the submarine project began investigating ideas for a new combat system.&lt;ref name=YW292&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 292&lt;/ref&gt; Because there was not enough time to evaluate the replacement system to include it in the [[Collins-class submarine#McIntosh-Prescott Report and Fast Track program|&quot;fast track&quot; program]], ''Dechaineux'' and ''Sheean'' were fitted with the old Rockwell combat system, which was enhanced by the addition of sub-systems developed during the early 1980s for the ''Oberon''-class mid-life upgrade and [[commercial off-the-shelf]] components.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 292–4&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Woolner, ''Getting in Early'', p. 28&lt;/ref&gt; Even with the enhanced system, it was believed that the capabilities of the fast track ''Collins'' boats was at best equivalent to the ''Oberon''s.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 294&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Collins class training facility.jpg|thumb|alt=Men sitting at computer terminals with other men and a woman standing behind them|U.S. Secretary of the Navy [[Donald C. Winter]] observing the Collins Weapon System Trainer Facility at HMAS ''Stirling'' in August 2007]]

[[Lockheed Martin]], [[Thales Group|Thales]], [[STN Atlas]], and Raytheon were approached to provide tenders to design and assemble a new combat system for the submarines, with all four submitting proposals during early 2000.&lt;ref name=YW300.1&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 300–1&lt;/ref&gt; In May 2000, after the [[Defence Science and Technology Organisation]] tested operational versions of the proposed combat software packages, the Lockheed and Thales tenders were eliminated, despite the Thales proposal being rated better than Raytheon's.&lt;ref name=YW300.1/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kelton, ''More than an ally?'', p. 117&lt;/ref&gt; After indepth testing of the remaining systems and observations of the systems in action, the German STN Atlas ISUS 90-55 aboard an Israeli [[Dolphin-class submarine|''Dolphin''-class submarine]] and the American Raytheon CCS Mk2 aboard a USN [[Los Angeles-class submarine|''Los Angeles''-class submarine]], it was decided that the STN Atlas system was the best for the class.&lt;ref name=YW300.1/&gt; However, political pressure from both the United States and Australia, questions about the security problems and possible leaks involved with a European combat system linked to American weapons, and desires to increase the [[Australia – United States relations|political and military ties between Australia and the United States]] resulted in the cancellation of the tender program in July 2001 and the decision to enter a joint development program with the United States, with a formal agreement signed on 10 September 2001 at the Pentagon.&lt;ref&gt;Woolner, ''Getting in Early'', p. iii&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 301–7&lt;/ref&gt;

The second combat system development program proceeded with far fewer problems, and took the tactical and fire control components from the CCS Mk2 system, and the sonar interface component from the fast track program.&lt;ref name=YW307.8&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 307–8&lt;/ref&gt; This system is the same as the AN/BYG-1 system which was fitted to United States Navy submarines during the 2000s.&lt;ref&gt;Mack, ''The U.S. Navy and Royal Australian Navy Relationship. A Partnership to Educate''&lt;/ref&gt; The new combat system was installed on ''Waller'' in 2006, and was to be fitted to the other five ''Collins''-class submarines (in the order of ''Dechaineux'', ''Collins'', ''Farncomb'', ''Sheean'', then ''Rankin'') by 2010,&lt;ref&gt;Elliott, ''Replacement Combat System for the Collins Class Soon to be Operational!'', pp. 44–8&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 309&lt;/ref&gt; but delays in the [[Collins-class submarine#Maintenance|maintenance cycle]] combined with the manning and mechanical problems during the late 2000s have pushed this date back to 2014.{{citation needed|date=June 2011}}

===Budget===
Several newspaper articles and commentators have incorrectly claimed that the project ran significantly over the contract cost.&lt;ref name=YW324&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 324&lt;/ref&gt; As of the launch of the first submarine, the project cost had increased from A$3.892 billion in 1986 dollars to A$4.989 billion in 1993 dollars, which corresponded to the rate of [[inflation]] during that period.&lt;ref name=YW187&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 187&lt;/ref&gt; By 2006, A$5.071 billion had been spent to build the submarines (excluding the fast track program); after taking inflation into account, the project had run less than A$40 million over contract.&lt;ref name=YW325.48&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 325, 348&lt;/ref&gt;

Of the A$1.17 billion allocated to the fast track program, only A$143 million was required to fix problems where the submarines did not correspond with the original contract: the rest was used to update components that were technologically obsolete and make changes to the submarines beyond the contract specifications.&lt;ref name=YW324/&gt; When the fast track program is factored in, the ''Collins'' class cost just under 20% more than the inflation-adjusted contract value; a smaller increase than other contemporary defence projects.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 325&lt;/ref&gt;

==Characteristics==
[[File:John Collins 28AWM P00444 093 29.jpg|thumb|upright|alt=Half-length portrait of a middle-aged man in a naval officer's uniform|Captain (later Vice Admiral Sir) [[John Augustine Collins]], namesake of the ''Collins'' class]]
The ''Collins'' class is an enlarged version of the Kockums ''Västergötland'' class submarine.&lt;ref name=WoolnerChange7/&gt; The design was referred to as the Type 471 Submarine until it was decided to name the lead boat, HMAS ''Collins'', after RAN Vice Admiral Sir John Augustine Collins.&lt;ref name=YW147/&gt; The names of the six submarines was first announced during ''Collins''{{'}} laying down ceremony: ''Collins'', ''Farncomb'', ''Waller'', ''Dechaineux'', ''Sheean'', and ''Rankin''; all named after Australian naval personnel who distinguished themselves during World War II.&lt;ref name=YW147/&gt; The Collins-class submarines are classified by the RAN as SSGs, or guided missile carrying submarines,&lt;ref name=RANclass/&gt; although some defence industry websites refer to the boats as hunter-killer submarines, or SSKs.&lt;ref name=SPGmedia&gt;''SSK Collins Class (Type 471) Attack Submarine'', naval-technology.com&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=DID15nov&gt;''Australia's Collins Class Subs'', Defense Industry Daily&lt;/ref&gt;

At {{convert|77.8|m|ft}} in length, with a beam of {{convert|7.8|m|ft}} and a waterline depth of {{convert|7|m|ft}}, the six boats were the largest conventionally powered submarines in the world at the time of their commissioning.&lt;ref name=Jones244/&gt;&lt;ref name=Jane12p27&gt;Saunders (ed.), ''IHS Jane's Fighting Ships 2012–2013'', p. 27&lt;/ref&gt; The submarines are single-hulled, and have two continuous decks.&lt;ref name=GrazebrookDU/&gt; Each boat displaces {{convert|3100|t|LT}} when surfaced, and {{convert|3407|t|LT}} when submerged.&lt;ref name=Jane12p27/&gt; The depth that the submarines can dive to is classified: most sources claim that the diving depth is in excess of {{convert|180|m|ft}},&lt;ref name=Wertheim19/&gt;&lt;ref name=Grazebrook&gt;Grazebrook, ''RAN prepares for Collins class''&lt;/ref&gt; although some give the maximum depth as over {{convert|300|m|ft}}.&lt;ref&gt;Woolner, ''Getting in Early'', p. 21&lt;/ref&gt; Following the near-loss of ''Dechaineux'' in 2003 when a seawater hose burst during a deep dive, the diving depth was reduced.&lt;ref name=subdepth/&gt;

The hull is constructed from a high-tensile [[micro-alloy steel]], developed by Swedish steel manufacturer [[SSAB]], and improved by BHP of Australia, which was lighter and easier to weld than the [[HY-80]] or HY-100 [[Alloy steel|nickel-alloy steel]] used in contemporary submarine construction projects, while providing better results in [[explosion bulge test]]ing.&lt;ref name=YW165.74&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 165–74&lt;/ref&gt; The submarines are covered in a skin of [[anechoic tile]]s to minimise detection by sonar: ''Collins'' was retrofitted with the tiles after the standard sonar signature of the submarine had been established, while the other five boats were covered during construction.&lt;ref name=JDW070893&gt;''‘Built in Australia’ Collins rolls out'', Jane's Defence Weekly&lt;/ref&gt; These tiles were developed by the Australian DSTO: as the United States and United Kingdom would not share their information on the tiles used on their nuclear submarines, Australian researchers had to develop the tiles from scratch.&lt;ref name=JDW070893/&gt;&lt;ref name=YW177.80&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 177–80&lt;/ref&gt; The tiles were moulded in the shape of the hull, and are secured by a commercial adhesive normally used to fix [[cat's eye (road)|cat's eyes]] to road surfaces: although British and American submarines are often seen with missing tiles, as of March 2007, none have been lost from a ''Collins''-class boat.&lt;ref name=YW177.80/&gt;

===Armament===
The ''Collins'' class submarines are armed with six {{convert|21|in|mm|adj=on}} torpedo tubes, and carry a standard payload of 22 torpedoes.&lt;ref name=Wertheim18/&gt; Originally, the payload was a mixture of Gould [[Mark 48 torpedo|Mark 48 Mod 4]] torpedoes and [[Boeing Harpoon|UGM-84C Sub-Harpoon]] anti-ship missiles; previously carried by the ''Oberon''-class boats.&lt;ref name=SPGmedia/&gt;&lt;ref name=Grazebrook/&gt; In 2006, the Mark&amp;nbsp;48 torpedoes were upgraded to the Mod&amp;nbsp;7 Common Broadband Advanced Sonar System (CBASS) version, which was jointly developed with the United States Navy.&lt;ref&gt;''Heavyweight Torpedo – Mark 48'', United States Navy Fact File&lt;/ref&gt; ''Waller'' was the first vessel of either navy to fire an armed Mod&amp;nbsp;7, sinking the decommissioned [[Spruance-class destroyer|''Spruance''-class]] destroyer {{USS|Fletcher|DD-992|6}} on 16 July 2008, during [[RIMPAC|RIMPAC&amp;nbsp;08]].&lt;ref&gt;McPhedran, ''Torpedoed – Collins Class submarine sinks US ship''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Haney, ''WashingtonWatch''&lt;/ref&gt; Some or all of the torpedo payload can be replaced with up to 44&amp;nbsp;[[Stonefish (mine)|Stonefish Mark III]] mines.&lt;ref name=SPGmedia/&gt;

During the construction phase, consideration was given to acquiring submarine-launchable [[BGM-109 Tomahawk|Tomahawk cruise missiles]]; giving the boats the capability to attack land targets after minor modifications.&lt;ref name=GrazebrookCross&gt;Grazebrook, ''Australia's Navy at the Southern Crossroads''&lt;/ref&gt; Plans to acquire Tomahawk or similar land-attack missiles remained under consideration until 2009, when the ''[[Defending Australia in the Asia Pacific Century: Force 2030]]'' white paper was released; stating that land-attack missiles will instead be incorporated into the armament of the ''Collins''-class replacement.&lt;ref name=AWship24/&gt;

The ''Collins''-class boats are also capable of supporting special forces teams.&lt;ref name=Fowler&gt;Fowler, ''Are leaky Collins class subs all washed up?''&lt;/ref&gt; In 2005, ''Collins'' was fitted with various modifications to support special forces, including exterior shelters for inflatable boats.&lt;ref name=Muir&gt;Muir, ''Pacific 2008: RAN submarines: present and future capabilities''&lt;/ref&gt; ''Dechaineux'' was modified in 2006.&lt;ref name=Muir/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gordon, ''Pimp my ride. The return of Big 'D&lt;nowiki&gt;'&lt;/nowiki&gt;'', p. 15&lt;/ref&gt; This allows for the dispatch of special forces teams whilst submerged.&lt;ref&gt;Patrick, ''Submarines and Special Forces'', p. 37.&lt;/ref&gt; Although the other submarines were originally slated to receive the hatches during their [[#Maintenance|full cycle docking]], the 2012 edition of ''[[Jane's Fighting Ships]]'' indicates that only two submarines have been modified for increased special forces capabilities.&lt;ref name=Jane12p27/&gt;
 
===Propulsion===
Each submarine is equipped with three Garden Island-[[Hedemora Diesel|Hedemora]] HV V18b/15Ub (VB210) 18-cylinder diesel engines, which are each connected to a 1,400&amp;nbsp;kW, 440-volt DC [[Jeumont-Schneider]] generator.&lt;ref name=SPGmedia/&gt;&lt;ref name=Wertheim18/&gt; The combined electrical generation capability of each submarine is 4.2 megawatts.&lt;ref&gt;Woolner, ''Getting in Early'', p. 20&lt;/ref&gt; The Hedemora diesels were chosen because of modular construction, which made servicing easier; they could be installed three across in the available space, while other contenders required at least two banks of two; and they had [[turbocharger]]s driven by the exhaust gas.&lt;ref name=&quot;YW224.55&quot; /&gt; Fifteen fuel tanks are located throughout the submarine: they must be used in specific sequences to preserve the submarine's buoyancy and trim.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 133&lt;/ref&gt;

Electricity is stored in four lead-acid battery packs, totalling 400 tonnes, assembled by Pacific Marine Batteries, a joint venture between [[VARTA]] of Germany and Pacific Dunlop of Australia.&lt;ref name=GrazebrookDU/&gt;&lt;ref name=YW127/&gt; These supply a single Jeumont Schneider DC motor, which provides 7,200 [[shaft horsepower]] to a seven-bladed, {{convert|4.22|m|ft|adj=on}} diameter [[skewback propeller]].&lt;ref name=GrazebrookDU/&gt;&lt;ref name=Wertheim18/&gt; The propeller design is classified Top Secret, and must be covered before a ''Collins''-class submarine can be removed from the water for maintenance.&lt;ref&gt;Davidson &amp; Allibone, ''Beneath Southern Seas'', p. 150&lt;/ref&gt; Emergency propulsion is provided by a MacTaggart Scott DM 43006 retractable hydraulic motor.&lt;ref name=SPGmedia/&gt; The aft control surfaces are mounted on an X-shaped structure, giving the boats the ability to outmanoeuvre most warship and submarine classes.&lt;ref name=WoolnerChange13/&gt;

[[File:HMAS Rankin at periscope depth.jpg|thumb|right|alt=Aerial view of a submarine just below the water's surface. The body of the submarine is distorted, and only the wake from three upright projections can be seen clearly.|''Rankin'' underway at snorkel or periscope depth during RIMPAC 04]]
The ''Collins'' class has a speed of {{convert|10|kn}} when surfaced and at snorkel depth, and can reach {{convert|20|kn}} underwater.&lt;ref name=Jane12p27/&gt; When travelling at {{convert|10|kn}}, the submarines have a range of {{convert|11500|nmi}} along the surface, or {{convert|9000|nmi}} at snorkel depth.&lt;ref name=Jane12p27/&gt; When fully submerged, a ''Collins''-class submarine can travel {{convert|480|nmi}} at {{convert|4|kn}}.&lt;ref name=Jane12p27/&gt; Each boat has an endurance of 70 days.&lt;ref name=Wertheim18/&gt;

[[Nuclear submarine|Nuclear propulsion]] was ruled out at an early stage of the project, because supporting nuclear submarines without a [[Nuclear power in Australia|nuclear power industry in Australia]] and [[Anti-nuclear movement in Australia|public opposition]] to such infrastructure would be extremely difficult.&lt;ref name=Skinner30&gt;Skinner, ''NCSM: The Collins class submarine'', p. 30&lt;/ref&gt; [[Air-independent propulsion]] (AIP) was also considered for the class, and the submarines were designed to be retrofitted with an AIP system.&lt;ref name=Wertheim19/&gt; The AIP plan was cancelled in July 1996, after it was demonstrated during sea trials that during constant operations, the boat's [[submarine snorkel|snorkel]] was exposed for only a few minutes in a 24-hour period; officials from ASC claimed that any ''Collins''-class submarine spotted while snorting would be because the boat was &quot;dead unlucky&quot;.&lt;ref name=Lok&gt;Lok, ''Australia rethinks AIP for Collins class boats''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Wertheim19/&gt; Installation of AIP was not believed to provide enough of an improvement on this to justify the predicted A$100 million cost.&lt;ref name=Lok/&gt;

===Sensors and systems===
The main sonar array is a Thomson Sintra Scylla active/passive bow sonar, linked to a passive intercept and ranging array distributed along the flanks of the submarine; three panels on each side.&lt;ref name=Jonesopp240/&gt;&lt;ref name=Jane12p27/&gt; ''Collins'' and ''Farncomb'' were originally fitted with Thales Karriwarra passive towed sonar arrays, while the other four boats could be fitted with the Karriwarra or Thales' Namara array.&lt;ref name=Wertheim18/&gt; These were later replaced across the class with the Thales SHOR-TAS towed passive array, deployed through the horizontal 'pipe' at the stern.&lt;ref name=Wertheim19/&gt;&lt;ref name=Jane12p27/&gt; When surfaced or at periscope depth, the ''Collins''-class boats can use a [[Kelvin Hughes]] Type 1007 surface search radar, which is situated in a retractable mast on the [[fin (submarine)|fin]].&lt;ref name=Jonesopp240/&gt;&lt;ref name=Jane12p27/&gt;

[[File:HMAS Sheean conning tower 2002.gif|thumb|alt=Close-up of the submarine's fin. Two naval officers, a small flag, and the periscope mast are on top of the fin.|The fin and conning tower of ''Sheean''. The CH093 attack periscope mast is extended, and one of the panels for the distributed sonar array can be seen at the bottom right of the image.]]
Each submarine is fitted with a CK043 search periscope and CH093 attack periscope.&lt;ref name=SPGmedia/&gt; The periscopes were manufactured by Pilkington Optronics (now [[Thales Optronics]]), and experienced several problems early in the submarines' service lives.&lt;ref name=SPGmedia/&gt;

The hardware for the original combat system was based around the [[Motorola 68000 family]] of processors.&lt;ref&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 155&lt;/ref&gt; The replacement combat system consists of the tactical and fire control components from the Raytheon CCS Mk2 system, combined with the sonar interfaces developed for the improved combat system used aboard ''Sheean'' and ''Dechaineux''.&lt;ref name=YW307.8/&gt; Countermeasures include a Condor CS-5600 [[Electronic Surveillance Measures|ESM]] intercept and warning unit, and two SSE decoys.&lt;ref name=Jane12p27/&gt; The boats are fitted with a Marconi SDG-1802 [[degaussing]] system, and a receive-only [[Link 11]] combat information exchange datalink.&lt;ref name=Wertheim19/&gt; In October 2006, [[Sagem Défense Sécurité]] was selected to fit the ''Collins'' class with SIGMA 40XP gyrolaser inertial navigation systems.&lt;ref name=SPGmedia/&gt;

===Ship's company===
Originally, the standard complement of each submarine was six officers and thirty-six sailors, with facilities to carry an additional twelve personnel (usually trainees).&lt;ref name=GrazebrookDU/&gt;&lt;ref name=Wertheim18/&gt; This number was minimised by the RAN during design, which insisted that functions be automated where possible; the RAN also requiring that each sailor have his own rack and did not need to '[[hot bunking|hot bunk]]'.&lt;ref&gt;Davidson &amp; Allibone, ''Beneath Southern Seas'', pp. 117, 141&lt;/ref&gt; It was originally intended that multiple ship's companies be established per submarine, and that these be rotated to maximise the submarines' time at sea without adversely affecting personnel, but difficulties in maintaining submariner numbers made this plan unworkable.&lt;ref name=GrazebrookDU/&gt; Enlisted submariners are accommodated in six-bunk cabins.&lt;ref name=Oakes160611&gt;Oakes, ''Sea change: mixed bunks on subs''&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:HMAS Waller 2008.jpg|thumb|left|alt=A submarine with people wearing white uniforms standing on the outer hull|Members of HMAS ''Waller''{{'}}s complement working on the boat as she enters Pearl Harbor in 2008]]

In May 1997, two groups of six female sailors were posted to ''Collins'' and ''Farncomb'' to test the feasibility of mixed-sex submarine companies.&lt;ref name=Jones283&gt;Jones, in ''The Royal Australian Navy'', p. 283&lt;/ref&gt; Following the trial's success, eleven female sailors and one female officer commenced submarine training in 1998.&lt;ref name=Brower33&gt;Brower, ''The Enemy [Below]... The Brass Above'', p. 33&lt;/ref&gt; Officers and senior enlisted submariners slept in mixed accommodation, but junior enlisted submariners could only be deployed in groups of six: one of the enlisted cabins was set aside, and all six bunks in the cabin had to be filled.&lt;ref name=Oakes160611/&gt; Mixed accommodation for all female submariners was approved in June 2011, in order to increase posting opportunities and help make up shortfalls in submarine complements.&lt;ref name=Oakes160611/&gt;

During the late 1990s, a combination of low recruitment and retention rates across the RAN resulted in the number of trained submariners falling below 40% of that required.&lt;ref name=Jones284&gt;Jones, in ''The Royal Australian Navy'', p. 284&lt;/ref&gt; As an attempt to retain submariners, the RAN offered a one-off A$35,000 bonus in 1999.&lt;ref name=Jones284/&gt; Other measures introduced around the same time included priority transfer of volunteers for submarine training and rotating submariners between sea and shore assignments to relieve them from continual sea service and prevent [[burnout (psychology)|burnout]].&lt;ref name=YW291&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 291&lt;/ref&gt; A year later, these measures had increased submariner numbers to 55% of requirements.&lt;ref name=YW291/&gt;

However, the problem with submarine crewing continued; by 2008 the RAN could only provide complete companies for three of the six submarines.&lt;ref name=Blenkin&gt;Blenkin, ''Navy unveils plan to boost submariner numbers''&lt;/ref&gt; A review by Rear Admiral [[Rowan Moffitt]] during 2008 (the ''Submarine Workforce Sustainability Review'' or ''Moffitt Report'') found that poor leadership and a culture of &quot;mission achievement at almost any cost&quot; resulted in submariners who were regularly stressed and fatigued from working for up to 22 hours in a stretch, under conditions worse than those experienced by the [[Australian Special Air Service Regiment|Special Air Service]] during the [[Operation Slipper|Afghanistan conflict]].&lt;ref name=Blenkin/&gt;&lt;ref name=Pearlman&gt;Pearlman, ''Subs at risk of catastrophic accident''&lt;/ref&gt; Submariners were also found to have lower morale and job satisfaction levels than any other position in the RAN, with these factors combining to cause a high rate of personnel burnout, while resignations meant that the average experience level in those remaining decreased.&lt;ref name=AWship24&gt;''Future Force'', Australian Warship, p. 24&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Blenkin/&gt; The report, publicly released in April 2009, made 29 recommendations to improve conditions and stabilise or increase submariner numbers; all of which the RAN agreed to adopt.&lt;ref name=McPhedranCrew&gt;McPhedran, ''Australia's submarine fleet sinking, says RAN chief''&lt;/ref&gt; These measures included increasing each boat's complement to 58 to spread workload (a practice successfully employed aboard ''Farncomb'' since December 2008), reducing the length of patrols and increasing shore leave, paying bonuses for submariners who remain in the submarine service for at least eighteen months, and providing internet access aboard the submarines.&lt;ref name=Blenkin/&gt;&lt;ref name=Pearlman/&gt;&lt;ref name=McPhedranCrew/&gt; A dedicated recruiting program was also suggested, promoting the submarine service as an elite unit, and targeting RAN personnel aboard surface ships, former submariners whose civilian jobs may have been affected by the [[Financial crisis of 2007–2010|global financial crisis]], and submariners in foreign navies.&lt;ref name=Blenkin/&gt;&lt;ref name=McPhedranCrew/&gt; The program was successful; by June 2010, three expanded ship's companies were active, while a fourth was undergoing training.&lt;ref name=OakesMay10&gt;Oakes, ''Navy fears being left high and dry by resources boom''&lt;/ref&gt; By December 2012, the fourth company was active, and was preparing to bring a submarine out of deep maintenance in 2013.&lt;ref name=&quot;NN-06-12-12&quot;&gt;{{cite news |title=This year in review |last=Berry |first=Paul |date=6 December 2012 |work=Navy News |publisher=Directorate of Defence News |pages=6–7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Maintenance===&lt;!-- This section heading is linked to from within the article --&gt;
The ''Collins''-class submarines return to the ASC facility in South Australia for maintenance and upgrades on four occasions during every six years of operation.&lt;ref name=DA177&gt;Davidson &amp; Allibone, ''Beneath Southern Seas'', p. 177&lt;/ref&gt; These occur approximately every eighteen months: the first and third are ten-week-long 'intermediate dockings', and the second, or 'mid-cycle docking', lasts sixteen weeks.&lt;ref name=DA177/&gt; At the end of six years, each boat comes in for her 'full cycle docking', which involves completely refurbishing the submarine.&lt;ref name=DA177/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Woolner, ''Getting in Early'', p. ii&lt;/ref&gt; During these dockings, the submarines are fitted with any enhancements or new technologies as part of the Collins Continuous Improvement Program (part of Defence procurement project SEA 1439).&lt;ref name=Muir/&gt;

[[File:Collins at Dock - ASC.JPG|thumb|left|alt=A submarine next to a dock, which is occupied by several cranes and other mechanical equipment|A ''Collins''-class submarine alongside at ASC in 2008]]
The six ''Collins''-class submarines are the most expensive items in the Australian Defence Force inventory.&lt;ref name=YW327/&gt; The annual cost of operating and maintaining the class was estimated at A$100 million in 2000, and at A$322 million in 2008.&lt;ref name=YW327&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', p. 327&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Coleman&gt;Coleman, ''More problems with Collins class submarines&lt;/ref&gt;

There have been concerns about the capability of ASC to handle the maintenance of the submarines.&lt;ref name=Walters09&gt;Walters, ''Engine problems cripple Collins-class submarines''&lt;/ref&gt; Defence officials believe that the full cycle docking (which was intended to take a year per submarine, but as of 2009 was averaging three years) could be handled more efficiently.&lt;ref name=DA177/&gt;&lt;ref name=Walters09/&gt;

==Operations and deployments==
The entire class is based at {{HMAS|Stirling}}, also known as Fleet Base West, which is located on [[Garden Island (Western Australia)|Garden Island]], off the coast of Western Australia.&lt;ref&gt;Jones, in ''The Royal Australian Navy'', p. 250&lt;/ref&gt; The decision to locate all six submarines at ''Stirling'' was prompted by the lack of suitable long-term facilities on the east coast of Australia (although individual submarines can use [[Fleet Base East]] in Sydney Harbour as a forward staging facility), and the proximity to Australian offshore interests, including most of the nation's [[States and territories of Australia|external territories]], the oil and natural gas resources of the [[North West Shelf Venture|North West Shelf]], and the Indian Ocean [[sea lines of communication]], through which the majority of Australia's seaborne trade passes.&lt;ref&gt;Kelton, ''More than an ally?'', p. 111&lt;/ref&gt; The submarines' primary missions are patrolling the waters of Australia and nearby nations, and gathering intelligence through the interception of electronic communications by foreign nations and the deployment/retrieval of special forces operatives.&lt;ref name=Fowler/&gt;
[[File:HMAS Sheean 01 gnangarra.jpg|thumb|left|alt=A submarine next to a dock, with navy personnel and civilians standing on the outer hull. Parts of another submarine and two warships can be seen in the background.|HMAS ''Sheean'' (left) and ''Collins'' (right) at the 2006 HMAS ''Stirling'' open day]]

===Operational history===
HMAS ''Waller'' reportedly operated in support of the [[International Force for East Timor]] (INTERFET) in 1999.&lt;ref name=WoolnerEarly1.2&gt;Woolner, ''Getting in Early'', pp. 1–2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McDonald, ''Into Dili's darkness''&lt;/ref&gt; Although not assigned to INTERFET, the submarine acted as a deterrent against the possible deployment of one of Indonesia's submarines, and may have covertly landed [[Clearance Diving Team (RAN)|clearance divers]] in advance of the INTERFET fleet's arrival.&lt;ref name=WoolnerEarly1.2/&gt;

[[File:Abraham-Lincoln-battlegroup.jpg|thumb|alt=Aerial photograph of twenty-one ships, including an aircraft carrier, sailing in close formation.|The {{USS|Abraham Lincoln|CVN-72|2}} [[Carrier battle group|battle group]] during RIMPAC 2000. ''Waller'' operated with this force during late May 2000, becoming the first Australian submarine to be integrated into a carrier battle group.]]
During several multinational exercises and wargames, the ''Collins'' class has demonstrated its effectiveness in the hunter-killer role by successfully attacking both surface warships and other submarines.&lt;ref name=Thompson26.8&gt;Thompson, ''Lessons not learned'', pp. 26–8&lt;/ref&gt; In late May 2000, ''Waller'' became the first Australian submarine to operate as a fully integrated component of a USN [[carrier battle group]] during wargames.&lt;ref name=YW295.6&gt;Yule &amp; Woolner, ''The Collins Class Submarine Story'', pp. 295–6&lt;/ref&gt; ''Waller''{{'}}s role was to search for and engage opposing submarines hunting the aircraft carrier {{USS|Abraham Lincoln|CVN-72|6}}, a role in which she performed better than expected.&lt;ref name=YW295.6/&gt; A few days later, as part of the multinational exercise [[RIMPAC]] 2000, ''Waller'' was assigned to act as an 'enemy' submarine, and was reported to have successfully engaged two USN nuclear submarines before almost coming into attacking range of ''Abraham Lincoln''.&lt;ref name=WoolEarly22&gt;Woolner, ''Getting in Early'', p. 22&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Thompson28/&gt; ''Waller'' performed similarly during the [[Operation Tandem Thrust]] wargames in 2001, when she 'sank' two USN amphibious assault ships in waters just over {{convert|70|m|ft}} deep, although the submarine was 'destroyed' herself later in the exercise.&lt;ref name=WoolEarly22/&gt;&lt;ref name=Thompson28&gt;Thompson, ''Lessons not learned'', p. 28&lt;/ref&gt; ''Waller''{{'}}s second feat was repeated by ''Sheean'' during RIMPAC 02, when the boat was able to penetrate the air and surface anti-submarine screens of an eight-ship amphibious task force, then successfully carry out simulated attacks on both the amphibious assault ship {{USS|Tarawa|LHA-1|6}} and the dock landing ship {{USS|Rushmore|LSD-47|6}}.&lt;ref name=Thompson28/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Field, ''Prawns, roo end RIMPAC 2002 at Pearl Harbor''&lt;/ref&gt;

Later that year, during two weeks of combat trials in August, ''Sheean'' demonstrated that the class was comparable in the underwater warfare role to the [[Los Angeles-class submarine|''Los Angeles''-class]] nuclear-powered attack submarine {{USS|Olympia|SSN-717|6}}.&lt;ref name=Thompson28/&gt;&lt;ref name=Nicholson&gt;Nicholson, ''Collins sub shines in US war game''&lt;/ref&gt; The two submarines traded roles during the exercise and were equally successful in the attacking role, despite ''Olympia'' being larger, more powerful, and armed with more advanced torpedoes.&lt;ref name=Nicholson/&gt; In 2003, a ''Collins''-class boat&lt;!-- Source does not specify which --&gt; carried out successful attacks on two USN nuclear submarines and an aircraft carrier during a multinational exercise.&lt;ref&gt;Thompson, ''Lessons not learned'', p. 26&lt;/ref&gt; The repeated successes of the class in wargames and multinational exercises earned the ''Collins'' class praise from foreign military officers for being &quot;a very capable and quiet submarine&quot;,&lt;ref name=Thompson26.8/&gt; and recognition of the boats as a clear example of the threat posed to navies by modern diesel submarines.&lt;ref&gt;Sherman, ''Aussie Collins-Class Sub &quot;Sinks&quot; US boat&lt;/ref&gt;

On 12 February 2003, ''Dechaineux'' was operating near her maximum safe diving depth off the coast of Western Australia when a seawater hose burst.&lt;ref name=subdepth&gt;Australian Associated Press, ''Navy forced to reduce subs' diving depth''&lt;/ref&gt; The high-pressure seawater flooded the lower engine room before the hose was sealed off: it was estimated that if the inflow had continued for another twenty seconds, the weight of the water would have prevented ''Dechaineux'' from returning to the surface.&lt;ref name=subdepth/&gt; The RAN recalled the ''Collins''-class submarines to base after the incident; after engineers were unable to determine any flaws in the pipes that could have caused the incident, the maximum safe diving depth of the class was reduced.&lt;ref name=subdepth/&gt;
[[File:2009 SH Fleet Entry 056 crop.jpg|thumb|right|alt=A submarine sitting in calm water, in front of a large warship, and with numerous tall buildings in the background. White-uniformed personnel are standing on the decks of both vessels.|''Farncomb'' and the amphibious transport ship {{HMAS|Kanimbla|L 51|6}} anchored in Sydney Harbour following a ceremonial fleet entry in March 2009]]

On 10 June 2005, ''Rankin'' became the first submarine since {{HMAS|Orion||2}} in 1987 to receive the [[Gloucester Cup]], an award presented to the RAN vessel with the greatest overall efficiency during the previous year.&lt;ref name=DA204&gt;Davidson &amp; Allibone, ''Beneath Southern Seas'', p. 204&lt;/ref&gt; The award was subsequently presented to ''Sheean'' in 2006, and again to ''Rankin'' in 2008.&lt;ref&gt;Jeffrey, ''Presentation of the 2007 Gloucester Cup to HMAS Rankin'', [speech]&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2008 and 2009, personnel shortages reduced the number of submarines able to be deployed to three; the maintenance cycles of ''Sheean'', ''Rankin'', and ''Dechaineux'', and problems with ''Collins'' and ''Waller'' further reducing this to one, ''Farncomb'', in mid-2009.&lt;ref name=Blenkin/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McPhedran, ''Only one submarine left to defend Australia''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Oakes2sub&gt;Oakes, ''Two subs out of action for 9 years''&lt;/ref&gt; ''Farncomb'' was docked for repair after a generator malfunction in February 2010, by which point ''Collins'' and ''Waller'' were active (the former on limited duties because of defects), and ''Dechaineux'' was slated to re-enter service by May 2010.&lt;ref name=Oakes2sub/&gt; Workforce shortages and malfunctions on other submarines during the preceding two years impacted heavily on the maintenance of ''Sheean'' and ''Rankin'', with RAN and ASC officials predicting that they will not be active until 2012 and 2013, respectively.&lt;ref name=Oakes2sub/&gt; In June 2011, ''[[The Australian]]'' newspaper claimed despite two submarines (''Waller'' and ''Dechaineux'') designated as operational, neither was in sailable condition.&lt;ref&gt;Stewart, ''Not a single submarine seaworthy''&lt;/ref&gt; The initial findings from the Coles Review revealed significant, systemic problems with the submarines and noted the need for their management to be reformed.&lt;ref name=&quot;rrsf&quot;&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.abc.net.au/news/2011-12-13/review-reveals-serious-flaws-with-collins-subs/3729558 |title=Review reveals 'serious flaws' with Collins subs |accessdate=13 December 2011 |date=13 December 2011 |work=ABC News |publisher=Australian Broadcasting Corporation}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 2014 statement by Vice Admiral [[Ray Griggs (admiral)|Ray Griggs]] indicated that up to four submarines had been operational on most occasions since 2012.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://news.navy.gov.au/en/Jan2014/Fleet/798 |title=Inaccurate reporting of Navy capability |last=Griggs |first=Ray |authorlink=Ray Griggs (admiral) |date=21 January 2014 |work=Navy Daily |publisher=Royal Australian Navy |accessdate=23 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Replacement==
{{Main|Collins-class submarine replacement project}}
The submarines originally had a predicted operational life of around 30 years, with ''Collins'' to decommission around 2025.&lt;ref name=Coleman/&gt;&lt;ref name=Stewart/&gt; The Submarine Institute of Australia released a report in July 2007 arguing that planning for the next generation of Australian submarines had to begin soon.&lt;ref name=Stewart&gt;Stewart, ''Defence to reach new depths''&lt;/ref&gt; In December 2007, shortly after the [[Australian federal election, 2007|2007 federal election]], the Australian government announced that planning for a ''Collins''-class replacement (procurement project SEA 1000) had commenced.&lt;ref name=Stewart/&gt; The 2009 ''Defending Australia in the Asia Pacific Century: Force 2030'' white paper confirmed the replacement project, and announced that the submarine fleet would be increased to twelve vessels to sustain submarine operations in any conflict, and counter the growing potency of Asian-Pacific naval forces.&lt;ref name=AWship24/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Department of Defence, ''Defending Australia in the Asia Pacific Century'', pp. 38, 64, 70–1&lt;/ref&gt;

The 2009 white paper outlined the replacement submarine as a 4,000-ton vessel fitted with land-attack cruise missiles in addition to torpedoes and anti-ship missiles, capable of launching and recovering covert operatives while submerged, and carrying surveillance and intelligence-gathering equipment.&lt;ref name=AWship24/&gt;&lt;ref name=36bil&gt;Nicholson, ''Sub fleet carries $36b price tag: experts''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Department of Defence, ''Defending Australia in the Asia Pacific Century'', p. 81&lt;/ref&gt; The project initially had four options: a [[Military-Off-The-Shelf]] (MOTS) design without modification, a MOTS design modified for Australian conditions, an evolution of an existing submarine, or a newly designed submarine.&lt;ref name=KerrSea1000&gt;Kerr, ''Sea 1000''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Depts3/&gt; Nuclear propulsion was ruled out because of the lack of [[Nuclear power in Australia|nuclear infrastructure]] and public opposition to nuclear technology.&lt;ref name=KerrSea1000/&gt;&lt;ref name=KerrTestWater&gt;Kerr, ''Australia tests the water for its largest-ever defence procurement challenge''&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=ABCNuke&gt;ABC News, ''New subs unlikely to go nuclear: ADA''&lt;/ref&gt; Designs initially considered for purchase or modification included the Spanish [[S-80-class submarine|S-80 class]], the French-designed [[Scorpène-class submarine|''Scorpène'' class]], the German-designed [[Type 214 submarine|Type 214]], and Japan's [[Sōryū-class submarine|''Sōryū'' class]], along with an evolution of the ''Collins''.&lt;ref name=KerrSea1000/&gt;

There were long delays in organising the replacement project. Originally, preliminary designs were to be established for selection by 2013, with detailed design work completed by 2016.&lt;ref name=KerrSea1000/&gt; However, meetings to clarify concepts and intended capabilities did not occur until March 2012, and initial design phase funding was not approved until May 2012, pushing construction start out to 2017.&lt;ref name=KerrSea1000/&gt;&lt;ref name=Depts3&gt;Offices of the Prime Minister, Minister for Defence, and Minister for Defence Materiel, ''Next stage of future submarine project announced''&lt;/ref&gt; By November 2014, initial capabilities still had not been decided on, with recommendations to be made across 2015.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.janes.com/article/45759/submarine-chief-canberra-to-get-recommendations-in-next-12-months |title=Submarine chief: Canberra to get recommendations in next 12 months |last=Kerr |first=Julian |date=13 November 2014 |work=IHS Jane's Navy International |accessdate=3 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The best case prediction for seeing the first new submarine enter service, made in 2012, was &quot;after 2030&quot;, with the lack of decision making partly attributed to politicians fearing being held responsible for a repeat of the issues surrounding the ''Collins'' class.&lt;ref name=KerrSea1000/&gt;&lt;ref name=HamishSnow&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.smh.com.au/national/submarines-no-longer-all-at-sea-20120708-21pk3.html |title=Submarines no longer all at sea |last=McDonald |first=Hamish |author2=Snow, Deborah  |date=9 July 2012 |work=The Sydney Morning Herald |accessdate=3 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Throughout 2014, there was increasing speculation that the ''Sōryū'' class (or a derivative) was the most likely candidate for the replacement.&lt;ref name=KerrAnalysis&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.janes.com/article/44933/analysis-european-yards-face-soryu-shaped-hurdle-to-replacing-collins-class |title=Analysis: European yards face Soryu-shaped hurdle to replacing Collins class |last=Kerr |first=Julian |date=22 October 2014 |work=IHS Jane's Navy International |accessdate=3 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Taylor&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.wsj.com/articles/japan-gains-edge-in-australia-submarine-deal-1417503055 |title=Japan Gains Edge in Australia Submarine Deal |last=Taylor |first=Rob |date=2 December 2014 |work=The Wall Street Journal |accessdate=5 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=NicholsonChoice&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.theaustralian.com.au/news/features/choice-of-navys-new-submarine-is-a-20bn-guessing-game/story-e6frg6z6-1227127446112 |title=Choice of navy’s new submarine is a $20bn guessing game |last=Nicholson |first=Brendan |date=19 November 2014 |work=The Australian |accessdate=5 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Defence technology sharing deals between Japan and Australia, along with the loosening of Japanese defence export restrictions, were seen as preliminary steps towards such a deal.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Wallace |first=Rick |url=http://www.theaustralian.com.au/national-affairs/defence/japan-tech-deal-could-help-power-our-subs/story-e6frg8yo-1226482149198 |title=Japan tech deal could help power our subs |newspaper=The Australian |date=27 September 2012 |accessdate=24 January 2014 |format=behind paywall}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.usni.org/2014/07/07/japan-australia-cooperate-new-submarine-design |title=Japan and Australia to Cooperate on New Submarine Design |last1=LaGrone |first1=Sam |date=7 July 2014 |website=news.usni.org |publisher=U.S. Naval Institute |accessdate=8 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://thediplomat.com/2014/07/australia-and-japan-to-ink-submarine-deal/ |title=Australia and Japan to Ink Submarine Deal |last1=Keck |first1=Zachary |date=8 July 2014 |website=thediplomat.com |publisher=The Diplomat |accessdate=8 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The close personal relationship between the then-Australian Prime Minister [[Tony Abbott]] and Japanese Prime Minister [[Shinzō Abe]] was also cited as a factor in the likeliness of such a deal.&lt;ref name=KerrAnalysis/&gt;&lt;ref name=Hardy&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.janes.com/article/44931/after-collins-australia-s-submarine-replacement-programme |title=After Collins: Australia's submarine replacement programme |last=Hardy |first=James |date=23 October 2014 |work=IHS Jane's Navy International |accessdate=3 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=NicholsonWallace&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.theaustralian.com.au/national-affairs/defence/homebuilt-submarines-deemed-too-expensive-too-risky/story-e6frg8yo-1227052023555 |title=Home-built submarines deemed too expensive, too risky |last=Nicholson |first=Brendan |author2=Wallace, Rick  |date=9 September 2014 |work=The Australian |accessdate=3 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; In response to the rumours of the Japanese deal, unsolicited proposals were made by [[ThyssenKrupp Marine Systems]] (its [[Type 216 submarine]] concept), [[Saab Group|Saab]]  (an enlarged version of the [[A26 submarine]]), and [[Thales Group|Thales]] and [[DCNS (company)|DCNS]] (a diesel-electric variant of the [[French Barracuda-class submarine|''Barracuda''-class submarine]]).&lt;ref name=KerrAnalysis/&gt;&lt;ref name=Taylor/&gt;&lt;ref name=Wroe&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.smh.com.au/federal-politics/political-news/australianmade-submarines-substantially-cheaper-than-government-suggests-20141120-11qimc.html |title=Australian-made submarines substantially cheaper than government suggests |last=Wroe |first=David |date=20 November 2014 |work=The Sydney Morning Herald |accessdate=3 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In January 2015, a three-way &quot;competitive evaluation process&quot; between the Japanese proposal, ThyssenKrupp's plan, and the Thales-DCNS offer was announced.&lt;ref name=ABC20Feb15&gt;Australian Broadcasting Corporation, ''Submarine program: Japan, France, Germany to compete for build process; Government promises hundreds of local jobs''&lt;/ref&gt; A 2012 study of the ''Collins'' class concluded that the submarines' lifespan could be extended by one maintenance cycle (seven years) to cover any capability gap, with lead submarine ''Collins'' to be retired in the early 2030s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |author=Department of Defence |title=Defence White Paper 2013 |publisher=Commonwealth of Australia |date=3 May 2013 |isbn=978-0-9874958-0-8 |oclc= |page=83}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 26 April 2016, Prime Minister [[Malcolm Turnbull]] announced the Shortfin Barracuda by French firm DCNS as the winner.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.abc.net.au/news/2016-04-26/pm-announces-france-has-won-submarine-contract/7357462|title=PM announces France has won submarine contract|publisher=ABC News|date=26 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Citations==
{{Reflist|3}}

==References==
;Books
*{{cite book |last=Davidson |first=Jon |author2=Allibone, Tom |title=Beneath Southern Seas |publisher=University of Western Australia Press |location=Crawley, WA |year=2005 |isbn=1-920694-62-5 |oclc=69242056}}
*{{cite book |author=Department of Defence |title=[[Defending Australia in the Asia Pacific Century: Force 2030]] |publisher=Commonwealth of Australia |date=2 May 2009 |isbn=978-0-642-29702-0 |oclc=426475923}}
*{{cite book |last=Jones |first=Peter |editor=Stevens, David |title=The Royal Australian Navy |series=The Australian Centenary History of Defence |volume=III |year=2001 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=South Melbourne, VIC |isbn=0-19-555542-2 |oclc=50418095 |chapter=A Period of Change and Uncertainty}}
*{{cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Sdw9aVeNdwkC |title=More than an ally?: contemporary Australia-US relations |last=Kelton |first=Maryanne |year=2008 |publisher=Ashgate |location=Aldershot, Hampshire |isbn=0-7546-7367-7 |oclc=181424108}}
*{{cite book |title=IHS Jane's Fighting Ships 2012–2013 |editor=Saunders, Stephen |publisher=IHS Jane's |location=Coulsdon |year=2012 |series=[[Jane's Fighting Ships]] |isbn=9780710630087 |oclc=793688752}}
*{{cite book| last=Thompson |first=Roger |title=Lessons not learned: the U.S. Navy's status quo culture |publisher=Naval Institute Press |location=Annapolis, MD |year=2007 |isbn=978-1-59114-865-4 |oclc=76901958 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Tqj9ZP8FsJEC}}
*{{cite book |title=The Naval Institute Guide to Combat Fleets of the World: Their Ships, Aircraft, and Systems |editor=Wertheim, Eric |publisher=Naval Institute Press |location=Annapolis, MD |year=2007 |edition=15th |isbn=978-1-59114-955-2 |oclc=140283156 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=TJunjRvplU4C}}
*{{cite book |last=Yule |first=Peter |author2=Woolner, Derek |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=qZ-WlswoHFwC |title=The Collins Class Submarine Story: Steel, Spies and Spin |year=2008 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=Port Melbourne, VIC |isbn=978-0-521-86894-5 |oclc=213111359}}

;Journal articles
*{{cite journal |title=Future Force: Australia's 21st century navy |journal=Australian Warship |issue=50 |pages=24–31}}
*{{cite journal |last=Brower |first=J. Michael |title=The Enemy [Below]... The Brass Above |journal=U.S. Naval Institute Proceedings |publisher=United States Naval Institute |volume=126 |issue=6 |page=33 |issn=0041-798X}}
*{{cite news |url=http://www.defenseindustrydaily.com/australias-collins-class-subs-submariners-on-track-for-upgrades-01488/ |title=Australia's Collins Class Subs, Submariners on Track for Upgrades |date=15 November 2008 |publisher=Defense Industry Daily |accessdate=15 April 2009}}
*{{cite journal |last=Elliott |first=Rob |date=March 2006 |title=Replacement Combat System for the Collins Class Soon to be Operational! |journal=Navy Engineering Bulletin |issue=10 |pages=44–48 |url=http://www.navy.gov.au/sites/default/files/documents/Navy_Engineering_Bulletin_March_2006.pdf |accessdate=23 May 2009 |oclc=223159268 &lt;!-- ISSN listed inside publication is not a valid ISSN --&gt;}}
*{{cite journal |last=Grazebrook |first=A.W. |date=1 December 1995 |title=RAN prepares for Collins class |journal=Jane's Navy International |publisher=Jane's Information Group |volume=100 |issue=6}}
*{{cite journal |last=Grazebrook |first=A.W. |date=1 April 1996 |title=Australia's Navy at the Southern Crossroads |journal=Jane's Navy International |publisher=Jane's Information Group |volume=101 |issue=3}}
*{{cite journal |last=Grazebrook |first=A.W. |date=1 January 1998 |title=Collins class comes up Down Under |journal=Jane's Navy International |publisher=Jane's Information Group |volume=103 |issue=1}}
*{{cite journal| last=Gordon |first= Lindsay |year=2009 |title=Pimp my ride. The return of Big 'D' |journal=The Trade |publisher=Royal Australian Navy |issue=July 2009 |url=http://www.navy.gov.au/w/images/The_Trade_Ed1_2009.pdf}}
*{{cite journal |last=Haney |first=Cecil |year=2008 |title=WashingtonWatch |journal=Undersea Warfare |issue=38 |url=http://www.navy.mil/navydata/cno/n87/usw/usw_summer_08/washington.html |accessdate=18 May 2009}}
*{{cite journal |date=7 August 1993 |title='Built in Australia' Collins rolls out |journal=Jane's Defence Weekly |publisher=Jane's Information Group |volume=20 |issue=6}}
*{{cite journal |date=9 April 1994 |title=Rockwell signs 'Kilo' system deal |journal=Jane's Defence Weekly |volume=21 |issue=14}}
*{{cite journal|last=Kerr |first=Julian |date=12 January 2012 |title=Wave of the future |journal=Jane's Defence Weekly |publisher=Jane's Information Group}}
*{{cite journal|last=Kerr |first=Julian |date=13 April 2012 |title=Sea 1000: Australia's Future Submarine is slow to surface |journal=Jane's Navy International |publisher=Jane's Information Group}}
*{{cite journal |last=Lok |first=Joris Janssen |date=17 July 1996 |title=Australia rethinks AIP for Collins class boats |journal=Jane's Defence Weekly |publisher=Jane's Information Group |volume=026 |issue=3}}
*{{cite journal |last=Mack |first=Stephen |year=2007 |title=The U.S. Navy and Royal Australian Navy Relationship. A Partnership to Educate |journal=Undersea Warfare |publisher=Chief of Naval Operations Submarine Warfare Division|location=Washington, DC |volume=9 |issue=4 |url=http://www.navy.mil/navydata/cno/n87/usw/summer_07/summer_07/royal.html}}
*{{cite journal |last=Muir |first=Tom |year=2007 |title=Pacific 2008: RAN submarines: present and future capabilities |journal=Australian Defence Magazine |issue=7 Dec/Jan 8 |url=http://www.australiandefence.com.au/F9074B80-F806-11DD-8DFE0050568C22C9}}
*{{cite journal |last=Patrick |first=Rex|date=September 2014 |title=Submarines and Special Forces |url=http://apdr.realviewtechnologies.com/default.aspx?iid=101338&amp;startpage=page0000020#folio=36 |journal=Asia Pacific Defence Reporter |publisher=Venura Media Asia-Pacific  |volume=40 |issue=7 |pages=36–40 |issn=1446-6880}}
*{{cite journal|last=Scott |first=Richard |date=14 January 2010 |title=Horns of a dilemma: Project SEA 1000 seeks to balance technology and risk |journal=International Defence Review |publisher=Jane's Information Group}}
*{{cite journal |last=Sherman |first=Kenneth B. |date=December 2003 |title=Aussie Collins-Class Sub &quot;Sinks&quot; US Boat |journal=The Journal of Electronic Defence |volume=26 |issue=12 |pages=24 |issn=0192-429X}}
*{{cite journal |last=Skinner |first=Christopher |date=September 2008 |title=NCSM: The Collins class submarine: national benefits and costs |journal=Journal of the Australian Naval Institute |issue=129 |pages=28–34 |issn=1833-6531}}
*{{cite journal |last=Woolner |first=Derek |date=18 September 2001 |title=Getting in Early: Lessons of the Collins Submarine Program for Improved Oversight of Defence Procurement |journal=Research Paper |publisher=Department of the Parliamentary Library |location=Canberra |volume=2001–02 |issue=3 |url=http://www.aph.gov.au/binaries/library/pubs/rp/2001-02/02rp03.pdf |accessdate=23 January 2015 |issn=1328-7478}}
*{{cite journal |last=Woolner |first=Derek |date=18 September 2001 |title=Procuring Change: How Kockums was Selected for the Collins Class Submarine |journal=Research Paper |publisher=Department of the Parliamentary Library |location=Canberra |volume=2001–02 |issue=4 |url=http://www.aph.gov.au/binaries/library/pubs/rp/2001-02/02rp04.pdf |accessdate=23 January 2015 |issn=1328-7478}}

;Newspaper articles
*{{cite news |url=http://www.abc.net.au/news/2015-02-20/japan-france-germany-to-compete-for-submarine-build/6159834 |title=Submarine program: Japan, France, Germany to compete for build process; Government promises hundreds of local jobs |work=ABC News |publisher=Australian Broadcasting Corporation |date=20 February 2015 |accessdate=21 February 2015}}
*{{cite news |url=http://www.theage.com.au/news/National/Navy-forced-to-reduce-subs-diving-depth/2005/07/23/1121539174654.html |title=Navy forced to reduce subs' diving depth |author=Australian Associated Press |date=23 July 2005 |work=The Age |accessdate=19 April 2009}}
*{{cite news |title=Navy unveils plan to boost submariner numbers |last=Blenkin |first=Max |date=8 April 2009|work=AAP General News Wire |publisher=Australian Associated Press}}
*{{cite news |title=New subs unlikely to go nuclear: ADA |url=http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2007/12/26/2127332.htm |work=ABC News |publisher=Australian Broadcasting Corporation |date=16 December 2007 |accessdate=3 June 2012}}
*{{cite news |last=Coleman |first=Matt |url=http://www.abc.net.au/pm/stories/s125474.htm |title=More problems with Collins class submarines |work=PM |publisher=ABC Radio |format=Transcript |date=10 May 2000 |accessdate=19 August 2009}}
*{{cite news |last=Field |first=Nick |url=http://www.defence.gov.au/news/navynews/editions/4518/topstories/story15.htm |title=Prawns, roo end RIMPAC 2002 at Pearl Harbor |work=Navy News |publisher=Directorate of Defence Newspapers |date=12 September 2002 |accessdate=21 April 2009}}
*{{cite news |url=http://www.abc.net.au/7.30/content/2003/s792830.htm |title=Are leaky Collins class subs all washed up? |last=Fowler |first=Andrew |date=25 February 2003 |work=The 7:30 Report |publisher=Australian Broadcasting Corporation |accessdate=2 September 2009}}
*{{cite news |url=http://150.theage.com.au/view_bestofarticle.asp?intid=1739&amp;inttype=1&amp;straction=update |title=Into Dili's darkness |last=McDonald |first=Hamish |date=18 September 1999 |work=The Age |accessdate=30 August 2009}}
*{{cite news |url=http://www.news.com.au/news/torpedoed-collins-class-sub-sinks-us-ship/story-fna7dq6e-1111117009709 |title=Torpedoed – Collins Class submarine sinks US ship |last=McPhedran |first=Ian |date=25 July 2008 |work=The Advertiser |accessdate=26 December 2015}}
*{{cite news |url=http://www.news.com.au/couriermail/story/0,23739,25311438-5001021,00.html |title=Australia's submarine fleet sinking, says RAN chief |last=McPhedran |first=Ian |date=9 April 2009 |work=Daily Telegraph |accessdate=15 September 2009}}
*{{cite news |url=http://www.news.com.au/story/0,27574,25515669-421,00.html |title=Only one submarine left to defend Australia |last=McPhedran |first=Ian |date=21 May 2009 |work=The Advertiser |accessdate=28 May 2009}}
*{{cite news |url=http://www.theaustralian.com.au/news/new-subs-to-be-built-in-adelaide-whatever-the-pick/story-e6frg8yo-1225824141618 |title=New subs to be built in Adelaide whatever the pick |last=Nicholson |first=Brendan |date=28 January 2010 |work=The Australian |accessdate=29 January 2010}}
*{{cite news |last=Nicholson |first=Brendan |url=http://www.theage.com.au/articles/2002/10/12/1034222635806.html |title=Collins sub shines in US war game |work=The Age |date=13 October 2002 |accessdate=20 April 2009}}
*{{cite news |last=Nicholson |first=Brendan |url=http://www.smh.com.au/national/sub-fleet-carries-36b-price-tag-experts-20091029-hnqj.html |title=Sub fleet carries $36b price tag: experts |work=The Sydney Morning Herald |date=30 October 2009 |accessdate=30 October 2009}}
*{{cite news|url=http://www.smh.com.au/national/sea-change-mixed-bunks-on-subs-20110615-1g40o.html |title=Sea change: mixed bunks on subs |last=Oakes |first=Dan |date=16 June 2011 |work=The Sydney Morning Herald |accessdate=16 June 2011}}
*{{cite news |url=http://www.theage.com.au/national/two-subs-out-of-action-for-9-years-20100210-nsgh.html |title=Two subs out of action for 9 years |last=Oakes |first=Dan |date=11 February 2010 |work=The Age |accessdate=12 February 2010}}
*{{cite news |url=http://www.smh.com.au/national/this-time-its-the-generators-defence-reveals-latest-battle-with-navys-underwater-lemons-20100330-rbla.html |title=This time it's the generators: Defence reveals latest battle with navy's underwater lemons |last=Oakes |first=Dan |date=31 March 2010 |work=The Sydney Morning Herald |accessdate=17 August 2010}}
*{{cite news |url=http://www.theaustralian.com.au/news/nation/navy-fears-being-left-high-and-dry-by-resources-boom/story-e6frg6nf-1225864746895 |title=Navy fears being left high and dry by resources boom |last=Oakes |first=Dan |date=11 May 2010 |work=The Australian |accessdate=17 August 2010}}
*{{cite news|url=http://www.theaustralian.news.com.au/story/0,25197,25430228-31477,00.html |title=Labor reneges on submarine promise to builder ASC |last1=Owen |first1=Michael |last2=Akerman |first2=Pia |date=5 May 2009 |work=The Australian |accessdate=5 May 2009}}
*{{cite news |url=http://www.smh.com.au/national/subs-at-risk-of-catastrophic-accident-20090408-a0vt.html |title=Subs at risk of catastrophic accident |last=Pearlman |first=Jonathan |date=9 April 2009 |work=Sydney Morning Herald |accessdate=15 September 2009}}
*{{cite news |first=Cameron |last=Stewart |title=Defence to reach new depths |url=http://www.theaustralian.news.com.au/story/0,25197,22981343-31477,00.html |work=The Australian |date=29 December 2007 |accessdate=25 April 2009}}
*{{cite news |url=http://www.theaustralian.com.au/national-affairs/not-a-single-submarine-seaworthy/story-fn59niix-1226072631716 |title=Not a single submarine seaworthy |last=Stewart |first=Cameron |date=10 June 2011 |work=The Australian |accessdate=11 June 2011}}
*{{cite news |url=http://www.theaustralian.news.com.au/story/0,25197,26239359-601,00.html |title=Engine problems cripple Collins-class submarines |last=Walters |first=Patrick |date=21 October 2009 |work=The Australian |accessdate=23 October 2009}}

;Websites and other media
*{{cite web |url=http://www.navy.gov.au/Collins_Class |title=Collins Class |publisher=Royal Australian Navy |accessdate=20 April 2009}}
*{{cite web |url=http://www.navy.mil/navydata/fact_display.asp?cid=2100&amp;tid=950&amp;ct=2 |title=Heavyweight Torpedo – Mark 48 |date=17 January 2009 |work=United States Navy Fact File |publisher=United States Navy |accessdate=22 April 2009}}
*{{cite speech |title=Presentation of the 2007 Gloucester Cup to HMAS Rankin |first=Michael |last=Jeffery |authorlink=Michael Jeffery |date=8 April 2008 |location=HMAS ''Stirling'', WA |url=http://www.gg.gov.au/governorgeneral/speech.php?id=407 |accessdate=26 May 2009}}
*{{cite web |url=http://www.naval-technology.com/projects/collins/ |title=SSK Collins Class (Type 471) Attack Submarine |work=Industry Projects, naval-technology.com |publisher=SPG Media |accessdate=20 April 2009}}
*{{cite press release |title=Next stage of future submarine project announced |publisher=Offices of the Prime Minister, Minister for Defence, and Minister for Defence Materiel |date=3 May 2012 |url=http://www.minister.defence.gov.au/2012/05/03/prime-minister-minister-for-defence-minister-for-defence-materiel-joint-media-release-next-stage-of-future-submarine-project-announced/ |accessdate=3 June 2012}}

==External links==
{{commons|Collins class submarines}}
*[http://www.navy.gov.au/media-room/multimedia/virtual-fleet Virtual Fleet] – Virtual tour of RAN warships, including the ''Collins'' class submarine.
*[http://www.navy.gov.au/fleet/ships-boats-craft/submarines/submarine-names Submarine Names] – RAN webpage providing histories of the six personnel the submarines are named after.
;Reviews and reports
*[http://www.minister.defence.gov.au/1999/collins.html Report to the Minister for Defence on the Collins class submarine and related matters] – the 1999 report by McIntosh and Prescott on the state of the ''Collins'' class project.
*[http://www.submarineinstitute.com/userfiles/File/07REP2150_Conclusions%20Regarding%20a%20Future%20Submarine%20Capability%20for%20Australia_1_04_07.pdf A brief on the issues arising from consideration of the requirements for a future submarine capability for Australia] – the 2007 report by the Submarine Institute of Australia which prompted the commencement of the ''Collins'' class replacement project.
*[http://www.navy.gov.au/media-room/publications/submarine-workforce-sustainability-review Submarine Workforce Sustainability Review] – declassified text of the 2008 review by Moffitt on providing ship's complements for the ''Collins'' class submarines.

{{Australian submarines}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Collins Class Submarine}}
[[Category:Collins-class submarines| ]]
[[Category:Submarine classes]]</text>
      <sha1>5wz2a99bhk3prsf7r0ujo5skei8dtpv</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
