<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Convoy Faith</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>27935788</id>
    <revision>
      <id>739617025</id>
      <parentid>729273756</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-15T20:11:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mr Stephen</username>
        <id>863017</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Notes */clean up, dashes in year ranges, ISBN format using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="21403">{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2013}}
{{good article}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Convoy Faith
| partof      = the [[Battle of the Atlantic]], [[World War II]]
| image       = [[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-619-2663-06, Flugzeug Focke-Wulf FW 200 &quot;Condor&quot;.jpg|300px|alt=A black and white photo of the belly of a four engined monoplane in flight|A Fw 200 C-4 Condor in 1942. Aircraft of this model attacked Convoy Faith.]]
| caption     = A Fw 200 C-4 Condor in 1942. Aircraft of this model attacked Convoy Faith.
| date        = 8–12&amp;nbsp;July 1943
| place       = Atlantic Ocean, about {{convert|480|km|mi}} west of [[Portugal]]
| result      = German victory
| status      =
| combatant1  = {{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
| combatant2  = {{flag|United Kingdom}}&lt;br&gt;{{flag|Canada|1921}}&lt;br&gt;{{flag|United States|1912}}
| commander1  =
| commander2  = {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} W.G. Busk-Wood
| strength1   = First attack: three aircraft&lt;br&gt;Second attack: two aircraft
| strength2   = Two troopships, one transport&lt;br&gt;Two destroyers, two frigates, two flying boats
| casualties1 = One wounded&lt;br&gt;One aircraft damaged
| casualties2 = 115 killed&lt;br&gt;Two troopships sunk&lt;br&gt;one storeship damaged
| notes       =
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Atlantic Campaign}}
}}
'''Convoy Faith''' was a small, fast [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] [[convoy]] of [[World War II]]. It suffered heavy casualties when attacked by [[Nazi Germany|German]] [[Focke-Wulf Fw 200|Focke-Wulf Fw&amp;nbsp;200 Condor]] long-range bombers while en route from Britain to West Africa in July 1943. The convoy comprised two large [[troopship]]s and a [[cargo ship|freighter]], later joined by two [[destroyer]]s and two [[frigate]]s as escorts at various dates after it sailed on 7&amp;nbsp;July 1943. The two troopships, [[SS California (1923)|SS ''California'']] and [[SS Duchess of York (1928)|SS ''Duchess of York'']], both former [[Ocean liner|liner]]s, were carrying military personnel to West Africa, where locally recruited troops were to be embarked as reinforcements for the Allied forces in Burma and the Middle East. The freighter [[MV Port Fairy|MV ''Port Fairy'']], carrying ammunition, was ultimately bound for Australia and New Zealand via the [[Panama canal]].

On the evening of 11&amp;nbsp;July, four days after sailing, Convoy Faith was attacked by three Condors. Both troopships were severely damaged and subsequently sunk by torpedoes from the escorts; over 100 of the personnel aboard the two ships were killed. The freighter escaped unscathed, but was damaged in a second air attack on 12&amp;nbsp;July en route to [[Casablanca]]. The loss of the two troopships delayed the movement of a [[Division (military)|division]] of West African soldiers to India until four replacements arrived.

The British military was surprised by the attack on Convoy Faith, as it had been believed that the Condors no longer posed a serious threat. In response, the convoy route between Britain and Africa was moved to the west. The German Condor force attempted to repeat its success against Convoy Faith by carrying out similar attacks on other convoys, but sustained heavy losses from Allied anti-aircraft guns and aircraft.

==Background==

From August 1940 to June 1941, the German [[Luftwaffe]] (air force) unit [[Kampfgeschwader 40|III./KG 40]], which was based at [[Bordeaux–Mérignac Airport]] in southern France and equipped with Focke-Wulf Fw&amp;nbsp;200 Condors, attacked Allied shipping travelling in the Atlantic. The unit made a number of successful attacks on convoys and individual ships traveling in the [[Western Approaches]] as well as on the route between Britain and [[Gibraltar]]. In response, the Allies increased the anti-aircraft armament carried by many merchant ships, and began to deploy [[CAM ship]]s and [[escort carrier]]s to provide fighter protection for convoys. During the last six months of 1941 these improved defences inflicted heavy losses on the Condor force, and it ceased attacking shipping in early 1942.&lt;ref&gt;Forczyk (2010), pp. 44–59&lt;/ref&gt; In 1942, III./KG&amp;nbsp;40 mainly operated in the reconnaissance role and reported targets for [[U-boat]]s to attack. A small number of attacks were made on ships travelling between Britain and Gibraltar from May onwards, but these cost the unit eight Condors destroyed in action and seven in accidents for no sinkings. As a result of the Condor's vulnerability to Allied defences, the commander of the Luftwaffe's Atlantic anti-shipping force ([[Fliegerführer Atlantik]]) recommended in December that the aircraft be withdrawn from service.&lt;ref&gt;Forczyk (2010), pp. 60–61&lt;/ref&gt;

The British military conducted regular convoys to transfer personnel from the United Kingdom to the Middle East and India from mid-1940 until late 1943. This convoy route was assigned the code [[List of World War II convoys#Indian Ocean Convoys|&quot;WS&quot;]], which was widely believed to be an abbreviation for &quot;Winston Special&quot; in honor of Prime Minister [[Winston Churchill]]. The WS convoys typically comprised several large [[ocean liner]]s which had been converted to [[troopships]] protected by a strong force of warships. As the Mediterranean Sea was a war zone, the convoys normally traveled from the [[River Clyde|Clyde]] in Scotland to the Middle East or South Asia via the [[Cape of Good Hope]] at the southern tip of Africa. En route, the ships typically stopped at [[Freetown]] in West Africa to refuel and embark water, and again at either [[Cape Town]] or [[Durban]] in South Africa.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hague_35&quot;&gt;Hague (2000), p. 35&lt;/ref&gt; German aircraft, submarines and surface ships attacked the WS convoys on occasion.&lt;ref&gt;Munro (2006), pp. xii–xiii&lt;/ref&gt;

==Prelude==
Despite its poor performance during most of 1942, III./KG 40's ability to attack Allied shipping was improved late in the year. During the last months of 1942 the unit received 18 C-4 variants of the Fw&amp;nbsp;200 which were fitted with the [[Lotfernrohr 7|Lotfe&amp;nbsp;7D]] bombsight. This sight reduced the Condors' vulnerability to anti-aircraft fire by allowing them to bomb targets from medium altitudes; previously they had only been able to attack accurately from low levels. Several of the unit's Condors were also fitted with surface search radar, which improved their ability to locate Allied ships.&lt;ref name=&quot;Forczyk_62&quot;&gt;Forczyk (2010), p. 62&lt;/ref&gt; In early 1943 it was decided to use these aircraft to renew attacks on convoys travelling to Gibraltar in an attempt to disrupt the Allied buildup in the Mediterranean during the [[Tunisia Campaign]]. These attacks began in early March and were conducted off Portugal between [[Lisbon]] and [[Cape St Vincent]]; this area was beyond the range of Allied fighter aircraft based in Gibraltar, and few escort carriers were available to protect convoys. III./KG 40 sank five merchant ships and damaged another two between March and the start of July, for the loss of at least five Condors. In response, the British began to use [[de Havilland Mosquito]] fighters to patrol the [[Bay of Biscay]], deployed four additional [[Squadron (aviation)|squadron]]s of patrol aircraft to Gibraltar, and embarked [[signals intelligence]] teams on board warships in the Bay of Biscay to monitor KG&amp;nbsp;40's radio communications.&lt;ref&gt;Forczyk (2010), pp. 62–64&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:HMS California WWII IWM FL 7404.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Black and white photo of a large boat with a single funnel at sea|''California'' during her service as an AMC during the first years of the war]]
[[File:SS Duchess of York.jpg|thumb|left|SS ''Duchess of York'']]
In February 1943 the British Government decided to transfer the recently raised [[81st (West Africa) Division]] from West Africa to India to take part in the [[Burma Campaign]]. This unit required much more shipping space than other British divisions, as its fighting units were supported by thousands of [[Porter (carrier)|porters]]. To facilitate the division's movement, additional troopships were assigned to the regular WS convoys.&lt;ref&gt;Munro (2006), p. 395&lt;/ref&gt; The 81st&amp;nbsp;Division's advance parties departed Freetown with Convoys WS&amp;nbsp;29 and WS&amp;nbsp;30 in April and May, and the [[6th (West Africa) Brigade]] embarked on ships of Convoy WS&amp;nbsp;31 at [[Lagos]] between 2 and 10&amp;nbsp;July.&lt;ref&gt;Munro (2006), pp. 398, 406, 411&lt;/ref&gt; It was planned to transport the division's two remaining brigades in convoys WS&amp;nbsp;32 and WS&amp;nbsp;33.&lt;ref name=&quot;Munro_414&quot;&gt;Munro (2006), p. 414&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[5th (West Africa) Brigade]] was the second of the 81st Division's brigades to be shipped from West Africa.&lt;ref&gt;Munro (2006), p. 421&lt;/ref&gt; The brigade comprised 12,000 personnel and was scheduled to depart with Convoy WS&amp;nbsp;32 on 31 July. The liners ''[[RMS Britannic (1929)|Britannic]]'', ''[[SS Largs Bay|Largs Bay]]'' and ''[[SS Tamaroa|Tamaroa]]'' were available in Freetown to carry 8,528 of these men, and it was decided to sail the troopship [[SS California (1923)|SS ''California'']] directly from the Clyde to provide the remaining berths.&lt;ref name=&quot;Munro_415&quot;&gt;Munro (2006), p. 415&lt;/ref&gt;

''California'' was a liner that had spent the first years of the war as an [[Armed merchantman|armed merchant cruiser]] before being converted to a troopship. She had previously carried troops to [[Bombay]] in India as part of convoys WS&amp;nbsp;22 and 26. She returned to the Clyde from Gibraltar on 4&amp;nbsp;June as part of Convoy MFK&amp;nbsp;15 and spent the next month docked in [[Glasgow]] undergoing repairs. Once this work was complete, ''California'' began to embark 470 personnel bound for West Africa on 4&amp;nbsp;July. She was to be accompanied on this voyage by [[SS Duchess of York (1928)|SS ''Duchess of York'']], which had been tasked with carrying 600 [[Royal Air Force]] personnel and civilians to West Africa, but had missed an earlier convoy owing to electrical problems. Like ''California'', ''Duchess of York'' was a pre-war liner which had been converted to a troopship. Prior to the ships' departure it was decided to use ''Duchess of York'' to transport elements of the 5th&amp;nbsp;(West Africa) Brigade to Bombay after the ships arrived at Freetown, while ''California'' would instead carry other West African personnel to the Middle East.&lt;ref name=Munro_415 /&gt;

==Attack==
[[File:Convoy Faith route July 1943.png|thumb|alt=A map of the West Atlantic coastline of Europe from northern Britain to Morocco. The route taken by Convoy Faith as described in the article is marked in by a red line. The approximate location of the attack on the night of 11/12 July 1943 is marked with a yellow dot.|Convoy Faith's approximate route until the night of 11/12&amp;nbsp;July&lt;ref&gt;Munro (2006), p. 481&lt;/ref&gt;]]

''California'' and ''Duchess of York'' sailed from [[Greenock]] on the afternoon of 7&amp;nbsp;July. They spent the night at anchor in the Clyde; shortly after getting underway early the next day they were joined by the storeship MV ''Port Fairy'', bound for Australia and New Zealand via West Africa and the [[Panama Canal]]. The master of the ''Duchess of York'', Captain W.G. Busk-Wood, probably served as the [[Convoy Commodore]]. Busk-Wood had been the master of the liner [[RMS Empress of France (1928)|SS ''Duchess of Bedford'']] prior to the war, and remained in command of this ship until November 1942 when he transferred to the ''Duchess of York''. He also held the rank of [[Commander (Royal Navy)|commander]] in the [[Royal Naval Reserve]]. The merchant ships were escorted by the destroyer {{HMS|Douglas}} and frigate {{HMS|Moyola}} from 9&amp;nbsp;July, and the Canadian destroyer {{HMCS|Iroquois|G89|6}} joined the convoy the next day.&lt;ref name=Munro_415 /&gt; While ''Iroquois''{{'}} commanding officer, Commander W.B.L Holms, was the most senior officer present, he chose to not assume command of the convoy as his destroyer would not remain with the troopships for their entire journey.&lt;ref name=&quot;Douglas_154&quot;&gt;Douglas et al. (2007), p. 154&lt;/ref&gt; The route taken by Convoy Faith was similar to that of other recent convoys sailing between Britain and Africa. While the strength of the escort force was much smaller than that assigned to the regular convoys, it was believed that submarines posed the main threat and that three warships would provide adequate protection.&lt;ref name=Munro_415 /&gt;

Convoy Faith was detected by a German Condor at 8:00&amp;nbsp;pm on 11&amp;nbsp;July while about {{convert|480|km|mi}} off the Portuguese coast.&lt;ref name=Munro_415 /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Forczyk_64&quot;&gt;Forczyk (2010), p. 64&lt;/ref&gt; This aircraft circled near the ships, broadcasting a homing signal. Two other Condors joined the first aircraft at about 9:00&amp;nbsp;pm, and they commenced their attack on the convoy shortly thereafter.&lt;ref name=&quot;Douglas_155&quot;&gt;Douglas et al. (2007), p. 155&lt;/ref&gt; At this time, Convoy Faith was deployed in a formation intended to protect the ships from submarines. The two troopships and ''Port Fairy'' were sailing line abreast (''Duchess of York'' was the westernmost of the three ships, ''California'' was in the centre and ''Port Fairy'' at the east of this group), ''Iroquois'' was located {{convert|3000|yd|m}} ahead and the two other escorts were on each flank of the troopships. Busk-Wood had maintained this formation after the first Condor was spotted in the belief that the aircraft would call in submarines rather than conduct an attack.&lt;ref name=Douglas_155 /&gt;

The three Condors made their attack from an altitude  of about {{convert|15000|ft|m}}.&lt;ref name=Munro_415 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Forczyk_64 /&gt; Despite heavy anti-aircraft fire from the escorts, ''California'' was badly damaged by a near miss from the first plane to attack, and was hit by two bombs dropped by the second attacker. The damage caused by these bombs flooded one of the ship's holds and set her on fire. ''California''{{'}}s passengers were evacuated on board lifeboats while the crew tried to save the ship. This proved unsuccessful, however, and they abandoned ship later that night. ''Duchess of York'' also came under attack; several bombs hit the centre of the ship and set her on fire. This fire could not be brought under control, and she too was abandoned, at 10:40&amp;nbsp;pm on 11&amp;nbsp;July.&lt;ref name=&quot;Munro_416&quot;&gt;Munro (2006), p. 416&lt;/ref&gt; ''Port Fairy'' was also straddled by two near misses, but did not suffer significant damage.&lt;ref name=Douglas_155 /&gt; Both troopships were subsequently torpedoed and sunk by their escorts, the ''Duchess of York'' by ''Douglas'', for fear their blazing hulks would attract German submarines to the area.&lt;ref name=Munro_416 /&gt;

While there are differing accounts of the casualties on board the two troopships, the official figures state that 89 people were killed on board ''Duchess of York'' and 26 on board ''California''.&lt;ref name=Munro_416 /&gt; The survivors were rescued by the two destroyers and ''Moyola'', including 660 by ''Iroquois'' alone.&lt;ref name=Munro_416 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Coombs (2008), pp. 221–222&lt;/ref&gt; They were subsequently taken to [[Casablanca]] in North Africa by the warships, from where the seamen returned to Britain and military personnel continued to West Africa on board the troopship [[SS Nea Hellas|SS ''Nea Hellas'']].&lt;ref name=Munro_416 /&gt;

[[File:HMS Swale K217.jpg|thumb|left|HMS ''Swale'']]
The frigate {{HMS|Swale|K217|6}}, despatched from [[Gibraltar]] to make a scheduled rendezvous, sighted the convoy under attack at 10:10&amp;nbsp;pm, and was herself attacked by Condors, the bombs falling 20 yards astern. After conducting an [[anti-submarine|A/S]] sweep around the convoy, ''Swale'' was ordered to detach and escort ''Port Fairy'' to Casablanca. At 6:45&amp;nbsp;pm the following day, ''Swale'' rescued eight survivors from a [[Consolidated PBY Catalina|PBY Catalina]], but within an hour the two ships were again attacked by Condors returning from a reconnaissance mission. Despite the intervention of two [[United States Navy]] Catalinas sent to their aid, a bomb hit ''Port Fairy'' on her starboard quarter, starting a fire next to the magazine and disabling her steering. The Catalinas eventually drove off the Condors with machine gun fire; one of the German aircrew was seriously wounded in this engagement.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ragnarsson_65&quot;&gt;Ragnarsson (2006), p. 65&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Forczyk_65&quot;&gt;Forczyk (2010), p. 65&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=C_in_C /&gt;   At 10:05&amp;nbsp;pm ''Swale'' came alongside ''Port Fairy'' to aid the extinction of the fire with her hoses. With ''Port Fairy'' in danger of exploding, 64 survivors from the two troopships and 8 passengers were transferred to ''Swale''. The blaze was eventually extinguished at 00:41&amp;nbsp;am, and both ships continued the remaining 500 [[nautical miles|nm]] to Casablanca without further incident, ''Port Fairy'' steering by her engines. ''Port Fairy'' did not suffer any casualties in the attack and was repaired on arrival at Casablanca.&lt;ref name=Forczyk_65 /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;C_in_C&quot;&gt;C in C, Western Approaches. ''HMS Swale: Report of Proceedings while escorting SS Duchess of York, California, &amp; Port Fairy, 11–14 July 1943.'' ADM 199 / 1032. The National Archives, Kew, London&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
The losses suffered by Convoy Faith shocked the British military, as it had been believed that the Condor force no longer posed a significant threat.&lt;ref name=Forczyk_65 /&gt; The decision to use a route which was similar to that used by previous convoys despite Convoy Faith's small escort made it an attractive target.&lt;ref name=&quot;Munro_417&quot;&gt;Munro (2006), p. 417&lt;/ref&gt; In his assessment of the action Admiral [[Charles Forbes (Royal Navy officer)|Charles Forbes]], the [[Commander-in-Chief, Plymouth]] strongly criticised the troopships for not taking evasive action during the attack. He also criticised the captain of ''Iroquois'' for not assuming command of the convoy. However, the Canadian [[official history]] argues that &quot;it is doubtful whether Holms would have acted differently under the circumstances&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Douglas_158&quot;&gt;Douglas et al. (2007), p. 158&lt;/ref&gt; In order to prevent a repetition of the attack, the convoy routes between Britain and West Africa were moved further to the west so that they were almost at the limit of the Condors' range.&lt;ref&gt;Munro (2006), pp. 419–420&lt;/ref&gt;

The loss of ''California'' and ''Duchess of York'' represented a heavy blow to the Allies' already heavily committed fleet of large troopships. ''Duchess of York''{{'}}s intended role was filled by ''Nea Hellas'' after she disembarked Convoy Faith's survivors at Freetown. ''Nea Hellas'' embarked the Gold Coast elements of the 5th&amp;nbsp;(West Africa) Brigade at [[Sekondi-Takoradi|Takoradi]] from 2&amp;nbsp;August while ''Britannic'', ''Tamaroa'' and ''Largs Bay'' loaded the remainder of the unit at other West African ports. Convoy WS&amp;nbsp;32 sailed from Freetown on 5&amp;nbsp;August, and ''Nea Hellas'' joined it at sea two days later. The liner was left behind at [[Durban]] owing to a mechanical fault, but eventually disembarked its soldiers at Bombay in late September after sailing there as part of Convoy CM&amp;nbsp;45. The West African personnel which were to be transported to the Middle East on board ''California'' were embarked on Convoy WS&amp;nbsp;33 in September and arrived at their destination in early November.&lt;ref&gt;Munro (2006), pp. 419–425&lt;/ref&gt;

The Germans attempted to build on their success against Convoy Faith by carrying out further medium-altitude attacks on convoys. III./KG 40 sank another four ships between July and September 1943, but suffered heavy losses from Allied aircraft and anti-aircraft guns. From October, [[Heinkel He 177|Heinkel He&amp;nbsp;177]]s largely took over the Condors' anti-shipping role, and the last Condor sorties were made over the Atlantic in early 1944.&lt;ref&gt;Forczyk (2010), pp. 65–70&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
;Citations
{{Reflist|2}}

;Bibliography
* {{Cite book|last=Coombs|first=Howard|title=The Insubordinate and the Noncompliant: Case Studies of Canadian Mutiny and Disobedience, 1920 to Present|year=2008|publisher=Dundurn Press|isbn=978-1-55002-764-8|location=Toronto}}
*{{cite book|last=Douglas|first=W.A.B.|title=A Blue Water Navy : The Official Operational History of the Royal Canadian Navy in the Second World War, 1943–1945. Volume II, Part 2|year=2007|publisher=Vanwell Publlishing|location=St. Catherine's, Canada|isbn=1-55125-069-1|display-authors=etal}} 
* {{Cite book|last=Forczyk|first=Robert|title=Fw 200 Condor vs Atlantic Convoy. 1943–43|year=2010|publisher=Osprey Publishing|isbn=978-1-84603-917-1|location=Oxford}}
* {{cite book|last=Hague|first=Arnold|title=The Allied Convoy System 1939–1945 : Its Organization, Defence and Operation|year=2000|publisher=Vanwell Publishing|location=St. Catharines, Canada|isbn=1-55125-033-0}}
* {{Cite book|last=Munro|first=Archie|title=The Winston Specials: Troopships Via the Cape 1940–1943|year=2006|publisher=Maritime Books|isbn=978-1-904459-20-0|location=Liskeard, United Kingdom}}
*{{Cite book|last=Ragnarsson|first=R.|title=US Navy PBY Catalina Units of the Atlantic War|year=2006|publisher=Osprey Publishing|isbn=1-84176-910-X|location=Oxford}}

[[Category:North Atlantic convoys of World War II|Faith]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Canada]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving the United States]]
[[Category:1943 in military history]]</text>
      <sha1>pf7otsi2laa0nrje9xi7j9wgd7iqrws</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
