<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>De Havilland Comet</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>182728</id>
    <revision>
      <id>751050678</id>
      <parentid>744371453</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-23T02:14:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Chris the speller</username>
        <id>525927</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Cohen Committee Court of Inquiry */replaced: high altitude → high-altitude using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="101834">{{About|the jet airliner|the 1930s racing aircraft|de Havilland DH.88}}
{{DISPLAYTITLE:de Havilland Comet}}
{{Use British English|date=January 2013}}
&lt;!-- This article is a part of [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft]]. Please see [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft/page content]] for recommended layout, guidelines. --&gt;
{|{{Infobox aircraft begin
  |name= DH 106 Comet
  |image= File:BEA de Havilland DH-106 Comet 4B Berlin.jpg
  |caption= [[British European Airways]] (BEA) Comet 4B arriving at [[Berlin Tempelhof Airport]] in 1969
}}{{Infobox aircraft type
  |type= [[Narrow-body aircraft|Narrow-body]] [[jet airliner|jet]] [[airliner]]
  |manufacturer= [[de Havilland]]
  |first flight= 27 July 1949
  |introduced= 2 May 1952 with [[British Overseas Airways Corporation|BOAC]]
  |retired=14 March 1997 (Comet 4C XS235)&lt;ref name=&quot;walker 169&quot;/&gt;
  |status=Retired
  |primary user= [[BOAC]]
  |more users=[[British European Airways]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Dan-Air]] &lt;br/&gt;[[Royal Air Force]]
  |produced=
  |number built= 114 (including prototypes)&lt;ref name=bao&gt;Lo Bao 1996, pp. 36–47.&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|Total of Comets in production: 114,&lt;ref name =bao/&gt; or 136 (when including refitting of original airframes and conversions).&lt;ref&gt;Walker 2000, pp. 185–190.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=N}}
  |unit cost= Comet 1: [[Pound sign|£]]275,000 (1952)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1974/1974%20-%200411.html &quot;Great Airliners 11: de Havilland Comet&quot;.] ''Flight'', 14 March 1974. Retrieved 26 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
  |variants with their own articles=
  |developed into= [[Hawker Siddeley Nimrod]]
}}
|}

The '''de Havilland DH 106 Comet''' was the world's first commercial [[jet airliner|jetliner]]. Developed and manufactured by [[de Havilland]] at its [[Hatfield Aerodrome]], [[Hertfordshire]], United Kingdom headquarters, the Comet&amp;nbsp;1 prototype first flew on 27 July 1949. It featured an aerodynamically clean design with four [[de Havilland Ghost]] [[turbojet]] engines buried in the wings, a pressurised [[fuselage]], and large square windows. For the era, it offered a relatively quiet, comfortable passenger cabin and showed signs of being a commercial success at its 1952 debut.

A year after entering commercial service, the Comets began suffering problems, with three of them breaking up during mid-flight in well-publicised accidents. These were later found to be due to catastrophic [[fatigue (material)|metal fatigue]] in the [[airframe]]s, not well understood at the time. The Comet was withdrawn from service and extensively tested to discover the cause; the first incident had been incorrectly blamed on adverse weather. Design flaws, including dangerous stresses at the corners of the square windows and installation methods, were ultimately identified. As a result, the Comet was extensively redesigned with oval windows, structural reinforcement, and other changes. Rival manufacturers meanwhile heeded the lessons learned from the Comet while developing their own aircraft.

Although sales never fully recovered, the improved Comet&amp;nbsp;2 and the prototype Comet&amp;nbsp;3 culminated in the redesigned Comet&amp;nbsp;4 series which debuted in 1958 and had a productive career of over 30&amp;nbsp;years. The Comet was adapted for a variety of military roles such as VIP, medical and passenger transport, as well as surveillance. The most extensive modification resulted in a specialised [[maritime patrol aircraft]] variant, the [[Hawker Siddeley Nimrod]]. Nimrod remained in service with the [[Royal Air Force]] (RAF) until June 2011, over 60 years after the Comet's first flight.
{{TOC limit|2}}

==Development==

===Origins===
[[File:Design Studies for the DH 106 Comet.jpg|thumb|right|upright=1.7|Design studies for the DH 106 Comet 1944–1947 (artist's impression)]]

On 11 March 1943, the [[Cabinet of the United Kingdom]] formed the [[Brabazon Committee]] to determine the UK's airliner needs after the conclusion of the [[World War II|Second World War]].&lt;ref name = 'T H 88'&gt;Trischler and Helmuth 2003, p. 88.&lt;/ref&gt; One of its recommendations was for a pressurised, transatlantic mailplane that could carry non-stop, one [[long ton]] (1.0 t) of payload at a cruising speed of 400&amp;nbsp;mph (640&amp;nbsp;km/h).&lt;ref name=&quot;Birtles p. 124&quot;&gt;Birtles 1970, p. 124.&lt;/ref&gt; De Havilland chose to challenge the widely held scepticism of jet engines as too fuel-hungry and unreliable,{{refn| During the same era, both Lockheed with their [[Lockheed L-188 Electra]] and Vickers with the ground-breaking [[Vickers Viscount]] discounted the advantages of &quot;pure&quot; jet power to develop [[turboprop]]-powered airliners.&lt;ref&gt;Kodera et al. 2010, p. 16.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=N}} So committee member Sir [[Geoffrey de Havilland]], head of the de Havilland company, used his personal influence and his company's expertise to champion the development of a jet propelled aircraft; and proposed a specification for a pure [[turbojet]]-powered design.&lt;ref name = 'T H 88'/&gt; The committee accepted the proposal, calling it the &quot;Type IV&quot; (of five designs),{{refn|The &quot;Type IV&quot; Specifications issued on 3 February 1943 provided for a &quot;high-speed mail-carrying airliner, gas-turbine powered.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones p. 60&quot;&gt;Jones 2010, p. 60.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=N}} and awarded a development and production contract to de Havilland under the designation ''Type 106'' in February 1945.  The type and design were to be so advanced that De Havilland had to undertake the design and development of ''both'', the airframe, and the engines.  This was because in 1945 no turbojet engine manufacturer in the world was drawing up a design specification for an engine with the thrust and [[Thrust specific fuel consumption|specific fuel consumption]], that could power an aircraft at the proposed cruising altitude (40 thousand feet), speed, and transatlantic range as was called for by the Type 106.&lt;ref&gt;Jackson 1988, p. 453.&lt;/ref&gt; First-phase development of the DH 106 focused on short and intermediate range mailplanes with a small passenger compartment and as few as six seats, before being redefined as a long-range airliner with a capacity of 24 seats.&lt;ref name=&quot;Birtles p. 124&quot;/&gt; Out of all the Brabazon designs, the DH 106 was seen as the riskiest both in terms of introducing untried design elements and for the financial commitment involved.&lt;ref name = 'T H 88'/&gt; Nevertheless, the [[British Overseas Airways Corporation]] (BOAC) found the Type IV's specifications attractive, and initially proposed a purchase of 25 aircraft; in December 1945, when a firm contract was laid out, the order total was revised to 10.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones p. 62&quot;&gt;Jones 2010, p. 62.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote box|align=left|width=21%|quote=&quot;During the next few years, the UK has an opportunity, which may not recur, of developing aircraft manufacture as one of our main export industries. On whether we grasp this opportunity and so establish firmly an industry of the utmost strategic and economic importance, our future as a great nation may depend.&quot;|source=&lt;small&gt;[[Duncan Sandys]], Minister of Supply, 1952.&lt;ref name = 'T H 90'/&gt;&lt;/small&gt;}}
A design team was formed in 1946 under the leadership of chief designer [[Ronald Eric Bishop|Ronald Bishop]], who had been responsible for the [[de Havilland Mosquito|Mosquito]] fighter-bomber.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones p. 62&quot;/&gt; A number of unorthodox configurations were considered, ranging from [[Canard (aeronautics)|canard]] to [[Tailless aircraft|tailless]] designs;{{refn|From 1944 to 1946, the design group prepared submissions on a three-engined twin-boom design, a three-engined canard design with engines mounted in the rear, and a tailless design that featured a [[swept wing]] and four &quot;[[podded engine|podded]]&quot; engines.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones p. 62&quot;/&gt;|group=N}} all were subsequently rejected. The [[Ministry of Supply]] was, however, interested in the most radical of the proposed designs and ordered two experimental tailless [[de Havilland DH 108|DH 108]]s{{refn|The Ministry of Supply's order for DH 108s was listed as Operational Requirement OR207 to Specification E.18/45.&lt;ref name = 'watkins 39'/&gt;|group=N}} to serve as [[proof of concept]] aircraft for testing swept-wing configurations in both low-speed and high-speed flight.&lt;ref name=&quot;Birtles p. 124&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = 'watkins 39'&gt;Watkins 1996, p. 39.&lt;/ref&gt; During flight tests, the DH 108 gained a reputation for being accident-prone and unstable, leading de Havilland and BOAC to gravitate to conventional configurations and, necessarily, designs with less technical risk.&lt;ref&gt;Darling 2001, p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt; The DH 108s were later modified to test the DH 106's power controls.&lt;ref name=&quot;Birtles p. 125&quot;/&gt;

In September 1946, prior to the completion of the DH 108s, BOAC requests necessitated a redesign of the DH 106 from its previous 24-seat configuration to a larger 36-seat version.&lt;ref name=&quot;Birtles p. 124&quot;/&gt;{{refn|BOAC's requested capacity increase was known as Specification 22/46.&lt;ref name=&quot;Birtles p. 124&quot;/&gt;|group=N}} With no time to develop the technology necessary for a proposed tailless configuration, Bishop opted for a more conventional 20-degree swept-wing design{{refn|The wing was drastically redesigned from a 40˚ sweep.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones pp. 62–63&quot;/&gt;|group=N}} with unswept tail surfaces, married to an enlarged fuselage accommodating 36 passengers in a four-abreast arrangement with a central aisle.&lt;ref name=&quot;Winchester p. 109&quot;/&gt; Replacing previously specified [[de Havilland Goblin|Halford H.1 Goblin]] engines, four new, more powerful [[Rolls-Royce Avon]]s were to be incorporated in pairs buried in the wing roots; [[de Havilland Ghost|Halford H.2 Ghost]] engines were eventually applied as an interim solution while the Avons cleared certification. The redesigned aircraft was named the DH 106 ''Comet'' in December 1947.{{refn|The name &quot;Comet&quot;, previously used by the [[de Havilland DH.88]] racing aircraft, was revived.&lt;ref&gt;Jackson 1988, p. 356.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=N}} Revised first orders from BOAC and [[British South American Airways]]{{refn|British South American Airways merged with BOAC in 1949.&lt;ref name=&quot;Birtles p. 124&quot;/&gt;|group=N}} totalled 14 aircraft with delivery projected for 1952.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones pp. 62–63&quot;&gt;Jones 2010, pp. 62–63.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Testing and prototypes===

As the Comet represented a new category of passenger aircraft, more rigorous testing was a development priority.&lt;ref name=d17/&gt; From 1947 to 1948, de Havilland conducted an extensive research and development phase, including the use of several stress test rigs at Hatfield for small components and large assemblies alike. Sections of pressurised fuselage were subjected to high-altitude flight conditions via a large [[Pressure vessel|decompression chamber]] on-site,{{refn|The fuselage sections and nose simulated a flight up to 70,000 ft at a temperature of −70˚C, with 2,000 lb pressure applications at 9 lb pressure/square in.&lt;ref name=&quot;Birtles p. 125&quot;&gt;Birtles 1970, p. 125.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=N}} and tested to failure.&lt;ref name=d18/&gt; However, tracing fuselage failure points proved difficult with this method,&lt;ref name=d18/&gt; and de Havilland ultimately switched to conducting structural tests with a water tank that could be safely configured to increase pressures gradually.&lt;ref name=&quot;Birtles p. 125&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=d18/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1955/1955%20-%201835.html &quot;Tank Test Mk 2.&quot;] ''Flight,'' 1955, pp. 958–959. Retrieved 26 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; The entire forward fuselage section was tested for metal fatigue by repeatedly pressurising to {{convert|2.75|psi|kPa}} overpressure and depressurising through more than 16,000 cycles, equivalent to about 40,000&amp;nbsp;hours of airline service.&lt;ref name=&quot;Davies and Birtles&quot;&gt;Davies and Birtles 1999, p. 30.&lt;/ref&gt;  The windows were also tested under a pressure of {{convert|12|psi|kPa|abbr=on}}, {{convert|4.75|psi|kPa|abbr=on}} above expected pressures at the normal service ceiling of {{convert|36000|ft|m|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Davies and Birtles&quot;/&gt; One window frame survived {{convert|100|psi|kPa|abbr=on}}, about 1,250 percent over the maximum pressure it was expected to encounter in service.&lt;ref name=&quot;Davies and Birtles&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Comet Prototype at Hatfield.jpg|thumb|left|Comet 1 prototype (with square windows) at Hatfield, Hertfordshire in October 1949. It features square-shaped windows, which caused two hull-loss accidents in 1954.]]

The first prototype DH 106 Comet (carrying [[United Kingdom aircraft test serials|Class B markings]] G-5-1) was completed in 1949, and was initially used to conduct ground tests and brief early flights.&lt;ref name=d18&gt;Darling 2001, p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt; The prototype's maiden flight took place on 27 July 1949 out of [[Hatfield Aerodrome]] and lasted 31&amp;nbsp;minutes.&lt;ref&gt;Dick and Patterson 2010, pp. 134–137.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;greenp174&quot;&gt;Green and Swanborough April 1977, p. 174.&lt;/ref&gt;  At the controls was de Havilland chief test pilot [[John Cunningham (RAF officer)|John Cunningham]], a famous night-fighter pilot of the Second World War, along with co-pilot Harold &quot;Tubby&quot; Waters, engineers John Wilson (electrics) and Frank Reynolds (hydraulics), and flight test observer [[Tony Fairbrother]].&lt;ref&gt;Prins 1998, p. 43.&lt;/ref&gt;

The prototype was [[United Kingdom aircraft registration|registered]] G-ALVG just before it was publicly displayed at the 1949 [[Farnborough Airshow]] prior to the start of flight trials. A year later, the second prototype G-5-2 made its maiden flight. The second prototype was [[United Kingdom aircraft registration|registered]] G-ALZK in July 1950 and it was used by the BOAC Comet Unit at [[Bournemouth Airport|Hurn]] from April 1951 to carry out 500 flying hours of crew training and route proving.&lt;ref&gt;Swanborough 1962, p. 45.&lt;/ref&gt; Australian airline [[Qantas]] also sent its own technical experts to observe the performance of the prototypes, seeking to quell internal uncertainty about its prospective Comet purchase.&lt;ref&gt;Gunn 1987, p. 268.&lt;/ref&gt; Both prototypes could be externally distinguished from later Comets by the large single-wheeled main [[landing gear]], which was replaced on production models starting with G-ALYP by four-wheeled [[bogie]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Walker p. 25&quot;/&gt;
{{clear}}

==Design==

===Overview===
[[File:Museum of Flight DH Comet interior.jpg|thumb|upright|[[Dan-Air]] Comet 4C cabin at the [[National Museum of Flight]], East Fortune, Scotland]]

The Comet was an all-metal [[Cantilever wing|low-wing cantilever]] monoplane powered by four jet engines; it had a four-place [[Cockpit (aviation)|cockpit]] occupied by two pilots, a flight engineer, and a navigator.&lt;ref name = 'francis 99'/&gt; The clean, low-drag design of the aircraft featured many design elements that were fairly uncommon at the time, including a swept-wing leading edge, integral wing fuel tanks, and four-wheel [[bogie]] main undercarriage units designed by de Havilland.&lt;ref name = 'francis 99'&gt;Francis 1950, p. 99.&lt;/ref&gt; Two pairs of turbojet engines (on the Comet 1s, Halford H.2 Ghosts, subsequently known as [[de Havilland Ghost]] 50 Mk1s) were buried into the wings.&lt;ref name = 'francis 100-101'&gt;Francis 1950, pp. 100–101.&lt;/ref&gt;

The original Comet was approximately the length of the later [[Boeing 737|Boeing 737-100]], but carried fewer people in a significantly more spacious environment. BOAC installed 36 reclining &quot;slumberseats&quot; with {{convert|45|in|mm|adj=on}} centres on its first Comets, allowing for greater leg room in front and behind;&lt;ref&gt;Hill 2002, p. 27.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Air France]] had 11 rows of seats with four seats to a row installed on its Comets.&lt;ref name = 'popmech 149'&gt;Cookman, Aubery O. Jr. [https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=6NkDAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA149&amp;dq=de+havilland+comet&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=Y03HTNKBFciVOrn2qbEB&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=10&amp;ved=0CFUQ6AEwCTgK#v=onepage&amp;q=de%20havilland%20comet&amp;f=false &quot;Commute by Jet.&quot;] ''Popular Mechanics'', 93(4), April 1950, pp. 149–152.&lt;/ref&gt; Large [[picture window]] views and table seating accommodations for a row of passengers afforded a &quot;feel of comfort and luxury&quot; atypical of transportation of the period.&lt;ref&gt;Smith 2010. 30(4), pp. 489, 506.&lt;/ref&gt; Amenities included a [[Galley (kitchen)|galley]] that could serve hot and cold food and drinks, a [[Bar (counter)|bar]], and separate men's and women's toilets.&lt;ref name = 'francis 98'&gt;Francis 1950, p. 98.&lt;/ref&gt; Provisions for emergency situations included several [[Lifeboat (shipboard)|life raft]]s stored in the wings near the engines, and individual [[Personal flotation device|life vest]]s were stowed under each seat.&lt;ref name = 'francis 99'/&gt;

One of the most striking aspects of Comet travel was the quiet, &quot;vibration-free flying&quot; as touted by BOAC.&lt;ref name ='walker 69'&gt;Walker 2000, p. 69.&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|BOAC flight crew revelled in standing a pen on end and pointing that out to passengers; invariably, the pen remained upright throughout the entire flight.&lt;ref&gt;Windsor-Liscombe, Rhodri. [http://pi.library.yorku.ca/ojs/index.php/topia/article/view/2680/1885 &quot;Usual Culture: The Jet.&quot;] ''Topia: Canadian Journal of Cultural Studies (Toronto: York University),''  Number 11, Spring 2004. Retrieved 26 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; |group=N}} For passengers used to propeller-driven airliners, smooth and quiet jet flight was a novel experience.&lt;ref name = 'francis 100'&gt;Francis 1950, p. 100.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Avionics and systems===
For ease of training and fleet conversion, de Havilland designed the Comet's flight deck layout with a degree of similarity to the [[Lockheed Constellation]], an aircraft that was popular at the time with key customers such as BOAC.&lt;ref name=&quot;d18&quot;/&gt; The cockpit included full dual-controls for the captain and first officer, while a flight engineer controlled various key systems, including fuel, air conditioning, and electrical systems.&lt;ref&gt;Darling 2001, pp. 35–36.&lt;/ref&gt; The navigator occupied a dedicated station with a table across from the flight engineer.&lt;ref name=d36&gt;Darling 2001, p. 36.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:De Havilland DH106 Comet 4 G-APDB Cockpit.JPG|left|thumb|The flight deck of a Comet 4]]
Several of the Comet's avionics systems were new to civil aviation. One such feature was irreversible powered [[Aircraft flight control system|flight controls]], which increased the pilot's ease of control and the safety of the aircraft by preventing aerodynamic forces from changing the directed positions and placement of the aircraft's [[flight control surfaces|control surfaces]].&lt;ref&gt;Abzug and Larrabee 2002, pp. 80–81.&lt;/ref&gt; Additionally, a large number of the control surfaces, such as the elevators, were equipped with a complex gearing system as a safeguard against accidentally over-stressing the surfaces or airframe at higher speed ranges.&lt;ref&gt;Darling 2001, p. 2.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Comet had a total of four [[hydraulic system]]s, two primaries, one secondary, and a final emergency system for basic functions such as lowering the undercarriage.&lt;ref&gt;Darling 2001, pp. 16–17.&lt;/ref&gt; The undercarriage could also be lowered by a combination of gravity and a hand-pump.&lt;ref&gt;Darling 2001, p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt; Power was syphoned from all four engines for the hydraulics, cabin [[air conditioning]], and the [[de-icing system]]; these systems had operational [[Redundancy (engineering)|redundancy]] in that they could keep working even if only a single engine was active.&lt;ref name=d17&gt;Darling 2001, p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt; The majority of hydraulic components were centred in a single avionics bay.&lt;ref&gt;Darling 2001, p. 45.&lt;/ref&gt; A pressurised refuelling system, developed by [[Cobham plc|Flight Refuelling Ltd]], allowed the Comet's fuel tanks to be refuelled at a far greater rate than other methods.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1951/1951%20-%200887.html &quot;F.R. equipment speeds refuelling.&quot;] ''Flight,'' 11 May 1951. Retrieved 26 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:DeHavillandCometCockpit.jpg|thumb|The Comet 4 navigator's station]]
The cockpit was significantly altered for the Comet 4's introduction, on which an improved layout focusing on the onboard navigational suite was introduced.&lt;ref name=d40&gt;Darling 2001, pp. 40–41.&lt;/ref&gt; An [[EKCO]] E160 [[radar]] unit was installed in the Comet 4's [[nose cone]], providing search functions as well as ground and cloud mapping capabilities,&lt;ref name=d36/&gt; and a radar interface was built into the Comet 4 cockpit along with redesigned instruments.&lt;ref name=d40/&gt;

[[Sud Aviation|Sud-Est]]'s design bureau, while working on the [[Sud Aviation Caravelle]] in 1953, licensed several design features from de Havilland, building on previous collaborations on earlier licensed designs, including the [[De Havilland Vampire|DH 100 Vampire]];{{refn|The Sud-Est SE 530/532/535 Mistral (FB 53) was a single-seat fighter-bomber version of the de Havilland Vampire jet fighter, used by ''[[French Air Force|L'Armée de l'Air]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Watkins 1996, pp. 181–182.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=N}} the nose and cockpit layout of the Comet 1 was grafted onto the Caravelle.&lt;ref&gt;Motem 1990, p. 143.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1969, when the Comet 4's design was modified by [[Hawker Siddeley]] to become the basis for the Nimrod, the cockpit layout was completely redesigned and bore little resemblance to its predecessors except for the control yoke.&lt;ref&gt;Darling 2001, p. 96.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fuselage===
Diverse geographic destinations and cabin pressurisation alike on the Comet demanded the use of a high proportion of alloys, plastics, and other materials new to civil aviation across the aircraft in order to meet certification requirements.&lt;ref name=engineering&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1953/1953%20-%200555.html &quot;Comet Engineering: The Performance of Airframe, Engines, and Equipment in Operational Service.&quot;] ''Flight International,'' 1 May 1953, p. 551. Retrieved 26 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; The Comet's high cabin pressure and fast operating speeds were unprecedented in commercial aviation, making its fuselage design an experimental process.&lt;ref name=engineering/&gt; At its introduction, Comet airframes would be subjected to an intense, high-speed operating schedule which included simultaneous extreme heat from desert airfields and frosty cold from the kerosene-filled fuel tanks.&lt;ref name=engineering/&gt;

[[File:De Havilland Comet RAF Museum Cosford (1).jpg|thumb|left|A Comet 1's fuselage and [[de Havilland Ghost]] engine intakes]]
The Comet's thin metal skin was composed of advanced new alloys{{refn|Fuselage alloys detailed in Directorate of Technical Development 564/L.73 and DTD 746C/L90.|group=N}} and was both riveted and chemically bonded, which saved weight and reduced the risk of fatigue cracks spreading from the rivets.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rafmuseum.org.uk/online-exhibitions/comet/comet2.cfm &quot;Comet Enters Service.&quot;] ''Royal Air Force Museum Cosford''. Retrieved 1 November 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; The chemical bonding process was accomplished using a new [[adhesive]], [[Redux (adhesive)|Redux]], which was liberally used in the construction of the wings and the fuselage of the Comet; it also had the advantage of simplifying the manufacturing process.&lt;ref&gt;Moss, C. J. [http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1951/1951%20-%200269.html &quot;Metal to Metal Bonding – For Aircraft Structures: Claims of the Redux Process.&quot;] ''Flight International,'' 8 February 1951, p. 169. Retrieved 26 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

When several of the fuselage alloys were discovered to be vulnerable to weakening via [[metal fatigue]], a detailed routine inspection process was introduced. As well as thorough visual inspections of the outer skin, mandatory structural sampling was routinely conducted by both civil and military Comet operators. The need to inspect areas not easily viewable by the naked eye led to the introduction of widespread [[radiography]] examination in aviation; this also had the advantage of detecting cracks and flaws too small to be seen otherwise.&lt;ref&gt;Jefford 2001, pp. 123–125.&lt;/ref&gt;

Operationally, the design of the cargo holds led to considerable difficulty for the ground crew, especially [[baggage handler]]s at the airports. The cargo hold had its doors located directly underneath the aircraft, so each item of baggage or cargo had to be loaded vertically upwards from the top of the baggage truck, then slid along the hold floor to be stacked inside. The individual pieces of luggage and cargo also had to be retrieved in a similarly slow manner at the arriving airport.&lt;ref&gt;Birtles 1970, p. 132.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jones 2010, p. 67.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{anchor|Engines}}

===Propulsion===

The Comet was powered by two pairs of turbojet engines buried in the wings close to the fuselage. Chief designer Bishop chose the Comet's embedded-engine configuration because it avoided the drag of [[podded engine]]s and allowed for a smaller [[Vertical stabilizer|fin and rudder]], since the hazards of asymmetric thrust were reduced.&lt;ref name = 'francis 101-102'&gt;Francis 1950, pp. 101–102.&lt;/ref&gt; The engines were outfitted with [[Sound baffle|baffle]]s to reduce noise emissions, and extensive [[soundproofing]] was also implemented to improve passenger conditions.&lt;ref&gt;Darling 2001, pp. 35, 46.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:De Havilland Comet pic 1 REJS.jpg|thumb||The Comet 4's enlarged [[Rolls-Royce Avon]] engine intakes]]
Placing the engines within the wings had the advantage of a reduction in the risk of [[foreign object damage]], which could seriously damage jet engines. The low-mounted engines and good placement of service panels also made aircraft maintenance easier to perform.&lt;ref name=&quot;Withuhn p. 88&quot;/&gt; However, the Comet's buried engine configuration increased its structural weight and complexity. Armour had to be placed around the engine cells to contain debris from any serious engine failures; also, placing the engines inside the wing required a more complicated wing structure.&lt;ref name = 'francis 103'&gt;Francis 1950, p. 103.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Comet 1 featured {{convert|5050|lbf|kN|abbr=on}} de Havilland Ghost 50 Mk1 turbojet engines.&lt;ref name=&quot;francis 100-101&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rafmuseum.org.uk/online-exhibitions/comet/comet3.cfm &quot;Ghost engine.&quot;] ''Royal Air Force Museum Cosford''. Retrieved 1 November 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Two [[hydrogen peroxide]]-powered [[de Havilland Sprite]] booster rockets were originally intended to be installed to [[RATO|boost]] [[takeoff]] under [[hot and high]] altitude conditions from airports such as Khartoum and Nairobi.&lt;ref name = 'popmech 149'/&gt;&lt;ref name = 'francis 98-102'&gt;Francis 1950, pp. 98–102.&lt;/ref&gt; These were tested on 30 flights, but the Ghosts alone were considered powerful enough and some airlines concluded that rocket motors were impractical.&lt;ref name=&quot;Birtles p. 125&quot;/&gt; Sprite fittings were retained on production aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;Gunn 1987, p. 269.&lt;/ref&gt; Comet 1s subsequently received more powerful {{convert|5700|lbf|kN|abbr=on}} Ghost DGT3 series engines.&lt;ref name=walker190/&gt;

From the Comet 2 onwards, the Ghost engines were replaced by the newer and more powerful  {{convert|7000|lbf|kN|abbr=on}} [[Rolls-Royce Avon|Rolls-Royce Avon AJ.65]] engines. To achieve optimum efficiency with the new powerplants, the air intakes were enlarged to increase mass air flow.&lt;ref name=d33/&gt; Upgraded Avon engines were introduced on the Comet 3,&lt;ref name=d33/&gt; and the Avon-powered Comet 4 was highly praised for its takeoff performance from high altitude locations such as Mexico City.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=qiEDAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=RA1-PA52&amp;dq=comet+jet&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=aF7HTK2JMMyVOsrF3LYB&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=5&amp;ved=0CD4Q6AEwBDgK# &quot;Comet Gets Stronger Engines.&quot;] ''Popular Science'', 160(6), June 1952, p. 142.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Operational history==

===Introduction===
The earliest production aircraft, registered G-ALYP (&quot;Yoke Peter&quot;), first flew on 9 January 1951 and was subsequently lent to BOAC for development flying by its Comet Unit.&lt;ref name=&quot;Davies and Birtles p. 31&quot;&gt;Davies and Birtles 1999, p. 31.&lt;/ref&gt;  On 22 January 1952, the fifth production aircraft, registered G-ALYS, received the first Certificate of Airworthiness awarded to a Comet, six months ahead of schedule.&lt;ref name=&quot;Davies and Birtles p. 34&quot;&gt;Davies and Birtles 1999, p. 34.&lt;/ref&gt; On 2 May 1952, as part of BOAC's route-proving trials, G-ALYP took off on the world's first jetliner{{refn|The [[Avro Canada C102 Jetliner]], for which it was [[neologism|coined]], first used the term; &quot;jetliner&quot; later became a generic term for all jet airliners.&lt;ref&gt;Floyd 1986, p. 88.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=N}} flight with fare-paying passengers and inaugurated scheduled service from London to Johannesburg.&lt;ref name=&quot;McNeil 2002, p. 39&quot;&gt;McNeil 2002, p. 39.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=bbc&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/may/2/newsid_2480000/2480339.stm &quot;On This Day: Comet inaugurates the jet age.&quot;] ''BBC News,'' 2 May 1952. Retrieved 26 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=WNwDAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA90&amp;dq=true#v=onepage&amp;q=true&amp;f=true &quot;I Rode The First Jet Airliner.&quot;] ''Popular Mechanics'', July 1952, pp. 90–94. Retrieved 26 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; The final Comet from BOAC's initial order, registered G-ALYZ, began flying in September 1952 and carried cargo along South American routes while simulating passenger schedules.&lt;ref&gt;Jackson 1988, pp. 173–174.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:BOAC Comet 1952 Entebbe.jpg|thumb|left|[[British Overseas Airways Corporation|BOAC]] Comet 1 at [[Entebbe International Airport|Entebbe Airport]], Uganda in 1952]]

The Comet was a hit with passengers including [[Elizabeth Bowes-Lyon|Queen Elizabeth, the Queen Mother]] and [[Princess Margaret, Countess of Snowdon|Princess Margaret]], who were guests on a special flight on 30 June 1953 hosted by Sir Geoffrey and Lady de Havilland, and thus became the first members of the British Royal Family to fly by jet.&lt;ref&gt;Lane 1979, p. 205.&lt;/ref&gt; Flights on the Comet were about 50 percent faster than on advanced piston-engined aircraft such as the [[Douglas DC-6]] (490&amp;nbsp;mph for the Comet compared to the DC-6's 315&amp;nbsp;mph), and a faster rate of climb further cut flight times. In August 1953 BOAC scheduled nine-stop London to Tokyo flights by Comet for 36 hours, compared to 86 hours and 35 minutes on their [[Canadair North Star|Argonaut]] piston airliner. ([[Pan American World Airways|Pan Am]]'s DC-6B was scheduled for 46 hours 45 minutes.) The five-stop flight from London to Johannesburg  was scheduled for 21 hr 20 min.&lt;ref&gt;BOAC Comet [http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1953/1953%20-%200551.html schedules] for May 1953&lt;/ref&gt;

In their first year Comets carried 30,000 passengers. As the aircraft could be profitable with a load factor as low as 43 percent, commercial success was expected.&lt;ref name=&quot;Walker p. 25&quot;&gt;Walker 2000, p. 25.&lt;/ref&gt; The Ghost engines allowed the Comet to fly above weather which competitors had to fly through. They ran smoothly and were less noisy than piston engines, had low maintenance costs,&lt;!--lower for parts, lower for labour, &amp; also faster turnaround times--&gt; and were fuel-efficient above {{convert|30000|ft|m|abbr=on}}.{{refn|Depending on weight and temperature, cruise fuel consumption was 6 to 10 kg per nautical mile, the higher figure being at the lower altitude needed at high weight.|group=N}} In summer 1953 eight BOAC Comets left London each week: three to Johannesburg, two to Tokyo, two to Singapore and one to Colombo.&lt;ref&gt;Davies and Birtles 1999, p. 22 (Route map illustration).&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1953 the Comet appeared to have achieved success for de Havilland.&lt;ref&gt;Schnaars 2002, p. 71.&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to the sales to BOAC, two French airlines, [[Union Aéromaritime de Transport]] and Air France, each acquired three Comet 1As, an upgraded variant with greater fuel capacity, for flights to West Africa and the Middle East.&lt;ref name=1A&gt;Schnaars 2002, p. 70.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1953/1953%20-%201135.html &quot;Preludes and Overtures: de Havilland Comet 1&quot;.] ''Flight'', 4 September 1953. Retrieved 30 May 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; A slightly longer version of the Comet 1 with more powerful engines, the Comet 2, was being developed,&lt;ref&gt;Darling 2001, p. 20.&lt;/ref&gt; and orders were placed by [[Air India]],&lt;ref&gt;Cacutt 1989, p. 146.&lt;/ref&gt; [[British Commonwealth Pacific Airlines]],&lt;ref name=&quot;darling119&quot; /&gt; [[Japan Air Lines]],&lt;ref name=&quot;JAPL&quot;/&gt; [[Linea Aeropostal Venezolana]],&lt;ref name=&quot;JAPL&quot;/&gt; and [[Panair do Brasil]].&lt;ref name=&quot;JAPL&quot;/&gt; American carriers [[Capital Airlines]], [[National Airlines (NA)|National Airlines]], and [[Pan American World Airways|Pan Am]] placed orders for the planned Comet 3, an even larger, longer-range version for transatlantic operations.&lt;ref name=&quot;darling128&quot;&gt;Darling 2005, p. 128.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Proctor et al. 2010, p. 23.&lt;/ref&gt; Qantas was interested in the Comet 1 but concluded that a version with more range and better takeoff performance was needed for the London to Canberra route.&lt;ref&gt;Gunn 1987, pp. 268–270.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Early hull losses===

On 26 October 1952, the Comet suffered its first hull loss when a BOAC flight departing Rome's [[Ciampino]] airport failed to become airborne and ran into rough ground at the end of the runway. Two passengers sustained minor injuries, and the aircraft, G-ALYZ, was a total loss. On 3 March 1953, a new [[Canadian Pacific Airlines]] Comet 1A, registered CF-CUN and named ''Empress of Hawaii,'' failed to become airborne while attempting a night takeoff from Karachi, Pakistan, on a delivery flight to Australia. The aircraft plunged into a dry drainage canal and collided with an embankment, killing all five crew and six passengers on board.&lt;ref&gt;[http://aviation-safety.net/database/record.php?id=19530303-1 &quot;Comet Accident Record.&quot;] ''Aviation Safety Network.'' Retrieved: 22 September 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.edcoatescollection.com/ac4/CF-CUN.html &quot;CF-CUN&quot;] ''Ed Coates' Civil Aircraft Photograph Collection.'' Retrieved: 18 February 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The accident was the first fatal jetliner crash, as well as the Comet's first accident to result in fatalities.&lt;ref name=&quot;JAPL&quot;/&gt; In response, Canadian Pacific cancelled its remaining order for a second Comet 1A and never operated the type in commercial service.&lt;ref name=&quot;JAPL&quot;/&gt;

[[File:De Havilland Comet 1 BOAC Heathrow G-ALYX 1953.jpg|thumb|right|BOAC Comet 1 ''G-ALYX'' (Yoke X-Ray) at [[London Heathrow Airport]] in 1953 prior to a scheduled flight]]

Both early accidents were originally attributed to pilot error, as [[Rotation (aviation)|over-rotation]] had led to a loss of lift from the [[leading edge]] of the aircraft's wings. It was later determined that the Comet's wing profile experienced a loss of lift at a high [[angle of attack]], and its engine inlets also suffered a lack of pressure recovery in the same conditions. As a result, de Havilland re-profiled the wings' leading edge with a pronounced &quot;droop&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Withuhn p. 85&quot;&gt;Withuhn 1976, p. 85.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[wing fence]]s were added to control spanwise flow.&lt;ref name=&quot;Birtles p. 127&quot;&gt;Birtles 1970, p. 127.&lt;/ref&gt; A fictionalised investigation into the Comet's takeoff accidents was the subject of the 1959 novel ''Cone of Silence'' by Arthur David Beaty, a former BOAC captain. ''Cone of Silence'' was made into a [[Cone of Silence (1960 film)|film]] in 1960, and Beaty also recounted the story of the Comet's takeoff accidents in a chapter of his 1984 non-fiction work, ''Strange Encounters: Mysteries of the Air''.&lt;ref&gt;Beaty 1984, pp. 113–114.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Comet's second fatal accident occurred on 2 May 1953, when BOAC Flight 783, a Comet 1, registered G-ALYV, crashed in a severe [[Squall|thundersquall]] six minutes after taking off from Calcutta-Dum Dum (now [[Netaji Subhash Chandra Bose International Airport]]), India,&lt;ref&gt;Darling 2005, p. 36.&lt;/ref&gt; killing all 43 on board. Witnesses observed the wingless Comet on fire plunging into the village of Jagalgori,&lt;ref name=&quot;lokurNS&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last1=Lokur|first1=N. S.|title=Report of the court investigation on the accident to COMET G-ALYV|url=http://lessonslearned.faa.gov/Comet1/G-ALYV_Report.pdf|website=Lessons Learned|publisher=Federal Aviation Administration|accessdate=23 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; leading investigators to suspect structural failure.&lt;ref name=&quot;Walker P. 37&quot;/&gt;

====India Court of Inquiry====
After the loss of G-ALYV, the [[Government of India|Central Government of India]] convened a court of inquiry&lt;ref name=&quot;lokurNS&quot;/&gt; to examine the cause of the accident.{{refn|The court acted under the provisions of Rule 75 of the Indian Aircraft Rules 1937.&lt;ref name=&quot;Walker P. 37&quot;&gt;Walker 2000, p. 37.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=N}} Professor [[Natesan Srinivasan]] joined the inquiry as the main technical expert. A large portion of the aircraft was recovered and reassembled at Farnborough,&lt;ref name=&quot;Walker P. 37&quot;/&gt; during which the break-up was found to have begun with a left elevator spar failure in the [[Tailplane|stabilizer]]. The inquiry concluded that the aircraft had encountered extreme negative [[g-force|G force]]s during takeoff; severe turbulence generated by adverse weather was determined to have induced down-loading, leading to the loss of the wings. Examination of the cockpit controls suggested that the pilot may have inadvertently over-stressed the aircraft when pulling out of a steep dive by over-manipulation of the fully powered [[Aircraft flight control system|flight controls]]. Investigators did not consider metal fatigue as a contributory cause.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lo Bao p. 7&quot;&gt;Lo Bao 1996, p. 7.&lt;/ref&gt;

The inquiry's recommendations revolved around the enforcement of stricter speed limits during turbulence, and two significant design changes also resulted: all Comets were equipped with [[weather radar]] and the &quot;Q feel&quot; system was introduced, which ensured that control column forces (invariably called stick forces) would be proportional to control loads. This [[Aircraft flight control system#Artificial feel devices|artificial feel]] was the first of its kind to be introduced in any aircraft.&lt;ref name=&quot;Walker P. 37&quot;/&gt;  The Comet 1 and 1A had been criticised for a lack of &quot;[[Feedback|feel]]&quot; in their controls,&lt;ref&gt;Job 1996, p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt;  and investigators suggested that this might have contributed to the pilot's alleged over-stressing of the aircraft;&lt;ref&gt;Darling 2001, p. 26.&lt;/ref&gt; Comet chief test pilot John Cunningham contended, however, that the jetliner flew smoothly and was highly responsive in a manner consistent with other de Havilland aircraft.&lt;ref name=&quot;Faith&quot;&gt;Faith 1996, pp. 63–64.&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|Cunningham: &quot;[the Comet] flew extremely smoothly and responded to the controls in the best way de Havilland aircraft usually did.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Faith&quot;/&gt;|group=N}}

===Comet disasters of 1954===
{{Main article|BOAC Flight 781|South African Airways Flight 201}}
[[File:Fuselage of de Havilland Comet Airliner G-ALYP.JPG|thumb|right|Fuselage fragment of G-ALYP at the [[Science Museum (London)|Science Museum]] in London]]

Rome's Ciampino airport, the site of the first Comet hull loss, was the origin of more disastrous Comet flights just over a year later. On 10 January 1954, 20&amp;nbsp;minutes after taking off from Ciampino, the first production Comet, G-ALYP, broke up in mid-air while operating [[BOAC Flight 781]] and crashed into the Mediterranean off the Italian island of [[Elba]] with the loss of all 35 on board.&lt;ref name = 'withey fatigue'&gt;Withey, P. A. [http://www.sciencedirect.com/science?_ob=ArticleURL&amp;_udi=B6V2X-3SP79HW-6&amp;_user=10&amp;_coverDate=06%2F30%2F1997&amp;_rdoc=1&amp;_fmt=high&amp;_orig=search&amp;_origin=search&amp;_sort=d&amp;_docanchor=&amp;view=c&amp;_searchStrId=1514800499&amp;_rerunOrigin=scholar.google&amp;_acct=C000050221&amp;_version=1&amp;_urlVersion=0&amp;_userid=10&amp;md5=0678fbac546ca7fe4fbd9bb50950bf92&amp;searchtype=a &quot;Fatigue Failure of the de Havilland Comet I.&quot;] ''Engineering Failure Analysis'', 4(2), June 1997, pp. 147–154. Retrieved 26 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1954/1954%20-%200130.html &quot;B.O.A.C. Comet Lost: Services Suspended.&quot;] ''Flight,'' January 1954, p. 58. Retrieved 26 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; With no witnesses to the disaster and only partial radio transmissions as incomplete evidence, no obvious reason for the crash could be deduced. Engineers at de Havilland immediately recommended 60 modifications aimed at any possible design flaw while the Abell Committee met to determine potential causes of the crash.&lt;ref&gt;Faith 1996, p. 66.&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|The Abell Committee, named after chairman C. Abell, Deputy Operations Director (Engineering) of BOAC, consisted of representatives of the Allegation Review Board (A.R.B.), BOAC, and de Havilland.&lt;ref&gt;Keith 1997, p. 288.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=N}} BOAC also voluntarily grounded its Comet fleet pending investigation into the causes of the accident.&lt;ref name=d29&gt;Darling 2001, pp. 28–30.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Abell Committee Court of Inquiry====
Media attention centred on [[sabotage]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Withuhn p. 85&quot;/&gt; while other speculation ranged from [[clear-air turbulence]] to an explosion of vapour in an empty fuel tank. The Abell Committee focused on six potential aerodynamic and mechanical causes: control [[Wing flutter|flutter]] (which had led to the loss of DH 108 prototypes), structural failure due to high loads or [[Fatigue (material)|metal fatigue]] of the wing structure, failure of the powered flight controls, failure of the window panels leading to explosive decompression, or fire and other engine problems. The committee concluded that fire was the most likely cause of the problem, and a number of changes were made to the aircraft to protect the engines and wings from damage that might lead to another fire.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20080703165044/http://www.geocities.com/CapeCanaveral/Lab/8803/comgalyp.htm &quot;Report of the Public Inquiry into the causes and circumstances of the accident which occurred on the 10 January 1954, to the Comet aircraft G-ALYP, Part IX (d).&quot;] ''geocities.com.'' Retrieved: 3 September 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote box|align=left|width=20%|quote=&quot;The cost of solving the Comet mystery must be reckoned neither in money nor in manpower.&quot;|source=&lt;small&gt;[[Prime Minister]] [[Winston Churchill]], 1954.&lt;ref&gt;Job 1996, p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/small&gt;}}
During the investigation, the [[Royal Navy]] conducted recovery operations.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1954/1954%20-%200224.html &quot;Elba Accident Developments.&quot;] ''Flight,'' January 1954, p. 108. Retrieved 26 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; The first pieces of wreckage were discovered on 12 February 1954&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20080703165044/http://www.geocities.com/CapeCanaveral/Lab/8803/comgalyp.htm &quot;Report of the Public Inquiry into the causes and circumstances of the accident which occurred on the 10 January 1954, to the Comet aircraft G-ALYP, Part IX (c): Action taken after the accident and prior to the accident to Comet G-ALYY: Naval search for wreckage.&quot;] ''geocities.com.'' Retrieved: 3 September 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; and the search continued until September 1954, by which time 70 percent by weight of the main structure, 80 percent of the power section, and 50 percent of the aircraft's systems and equipment had been recovered.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rafmuseum.org.uk/online-exhibitions/comet/comet5.cfm &quot;Comet Failure.&quot;] ''Royal Air Force Museum Cosford''. Retrieved 1 November 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;flight54 p652&quot;&gt;''Flight'' 29 October 1954, p. 652.&lt;/ref&gt; The forensic reconstruction effort had just begun when the Abell Committee reported its findings. No apparent fault in the aircraft was found,{{refn|On 4 April, [[John Moore-Brabazon, 1st Baron Brabazon of Tara|Lord Brabazon]] wrote to the Minister of Transport, &quot;Although no definite reason for the accident has been established, modifications are being embodied to cover every possibility that imagination has suggested as a likely cause of the disaster. When these modifications are completed and have been satisfactorily flight tested, the Board sees no reason why passenger services should not be resumed.&quot;&lt;ref name=d29/&gt;|group=N}} and the British government decided against opening a further public inquiry into the accident.&lt;ref name=d29/&gt; The prestigious nature of the Comet project, particularly for the British aerospace industry, and the financial impact of the aircraft's grounding on BOAC's operations, both served to pressure the inquiry to end without further investigation.&lt;ref name=d29/&gt; Comet flights resumed on 23 March 1954.&lt;ref name=&quot;Birtles pp. 128–129&quot;&gt;Birtles 1970, pp. 128–129.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 8 April 1954, Comet G-ALYY (&quot;Yoke Yoke&quot;), on charter to [[South African Airways]], was on a leg from Rome to Cairo (of a longer route, [[South African Airways Flight 201|SA Flight 201]] from London to Johannesburg), when it crashed in the Mediterranean near Naples with the loss of all 21 passengers and crew on board.&lt;ref name = 'withey fatigue'/&gt; The Comet fleet was immediately grounded once again and a large investigation board was formed under the direction of the [[Royal Aircraft Establishment]] (RAE).&lt;ref name = 'withey fatigue'/&gt; Prime Minister [[Winston Churchill]] tasked the Royal Navy with helping to locate and retrieve the wreckage so that the cause of the accident could be determined.&lt;ref name=&quot;Davies and Birtles pp. 30–31&quot;/&gt; The Comet's Certificate of Airworthiness was revoked and Comet 1 line production was suspended at the Hatfield factory while the BOAC fleet was permanently grounded, [[cocooning (aircraft)|cocooned]] and stored.&lt;ref name=&quot;Withuhn p. 85&quot;/&gt;

====Cohen Committee Court of Inquiry====
[[File:DH.106 Comet 1 G-ALYW BOAC LAP (2) 12.09.54 edited-3.jpg|thumb|right|BOAC Comet 1 cocooned and stored in the maintenance area at London Heathrow Airport in September 1954]]

On 19 October 1954, the Cohen Committee was established to examine the causes of the Comet crashes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones p. 68&quot;/&gt;  Chaired by [[Lionel Cohen, Baron Cohen|Lord Cohen]], the committee tasked an investigation team led by [[Arnold Alexander Hall|Sir Arnold Hall]], Director of the RAE at Farnborough, to perform a more detailed investigation.  Hall's team began considering fatigue as the most likely cause of both accidents, and initiated further research into measurable strain on the aircraft's skin.&lt;ref name = 'withey fatigue'/&gt; With the recovery of large sections of G-ALYP from the Elba crash and BOAC's donation of an identical airframe, G-ALYU, for further examination, an extensive &quot;water torture&quot; test eventually provided conclusive results. This time, the entire fuselage was tested in a dedicated water tank that was built specifically at Farnborough to accommodate its full length.&lt;ref name=d29/&gt; Stress around the window corners was found to be much higher than expected and stresses on the skin were generally more than previously expected or tested.&lt;ref&gt;Atkinson et al. 1962, p. 9.&lt;/ref&gt; This was due to [[stress concentration]], a consequence of the windows' square shape, which generated levels of stress two or three times greater than across the rest of the fuselage.&lt;ref&gt;Atkinson et al. 1962, pp. 4, 6, 27.&lt;/ref&gt;

In water tank testing, engineers subjected G-ALYU to repeated re-pressurisation and over-pressurisation, and on 24 June 1954, after 3,057 flight cycles (1,221 actual and 1,836 simulated),&lt;ref name ='raf webarchive'&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20061002072008/http://www.rafmuseum.org.uk/london/exhibitions/comet/comet5.cfm &quot;Comet.&quot;] ''RAF Museum''. Retrieved 3 September 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; G-ALYU burst open. Hall, Geoffrey de Havilland and Bishop were immediately called to the scene, where the water tank was drained to reveal that the fuselage had ripped open at a corner of the forward left escape hatch cutout. A further test reproduced the same results.&lt;ref name=&quot;Withuhn p. 87&quot;&gt;Withuhn 1976, p. 87.&lt;/ref&gt;  Based on these findings, Comet 1 structural failures could be expected at anywhere from 1,000 to 9,000 cycles. Before the Elba accident, G-ALYP had made 1,290 pressurised flights, while G-ALYY had made 900 pressurised flights before crashing. Dr P.B. Walker, Head of the Structures Department at the RAE, said he was not surprised by this, noting that the difference was about three to one, and previous experience with metal fatigue suggested a total range of nine to one between experiment and outcome in the field could result in failure.&lt;ref name ='raf webarchive'/&gt;

The RAE also reconstructed about two-thirds of G-ALYP at Farnborough and found fatigue crack growth from a rivet hole at the low-drag [[fibreglass]] forward [[aperture]] around the [[Automatic Direction Finder]], which had caused a catastrophic break-up of the aircraft in high-altitude flight.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Summary: Aircraft Investigation.&quot; ''Aircraft Engineering'', 37, 1965, p. 38.&lt;/ref&gt;  The punch rivet construction technique employed in the Comet's design had exacerbated its structural fatigue problems;&lt;ref name = 'withey fatigue'/&gt; the aircraft's windows had been engineered to be glued and riveted, but had been punch riveted only. Unlike drill riveting, the imperfect nature of the hole created by punch riveting could cause fatigue cracks to start developing around the rivet. Principal investigator Hall accepted the RAE's conclusion of design and construction flaws as the likely explanation for G-ALYU's structural failure after 3,060 pressurisation cycles.{{refn|Hall: &quot;In the light of known properties of the aluminium alloy D.T.D. 546 or 746 of which the skin was made and in accordance with the advice I received from my Assessors, I accept the conclusion of RAE that this is a sufficient explanation of the failure of the cabin skin of Yoke Uncle by fatigue after a small number, namely, 3,060 cycles of pressurisation.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Report of the Public Inquiry into the causes and circumstances of the accident which occurred on 10 January 1954, to the Comet aircraft G-ALYP, Part XI (a. 69).&lt;/ref&gt;|group=N}} The Cohen inquiry closed on 24 November 1954, and although the inquiry had &quot;found that the basic design of the Comet was sound&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones p. 68&quot;/&gt; de Havilland nonetheless began a refit programme to strengthen the fuselage and wing structure, employing thicker gauge skin and replacing all square windows and panels with rounded versions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Davies and Birtles pp. 30–31&quot;&gt;Davies and Birtles 1999, pp. 30–31.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Resumption of service===
[[File:MSA Comet Groves.jpg|thumb|[[Malaysia-Singapore Airlines]] Comet 4 at [[Kai Tak Airport]] in 1966]]

With the discovery of the structural problems of the early series, all remaining Comets were withdrawn from service, while de Havilland launched a major effort to build a new version that would be both larger and stronger. All outstanding orders for the Comet 2 were cancelled by airline customers.&lt;ref name=d33&gt;Darling 2001, p. 33.&lt;/ref&gt; The square windows of the Comet 1 were replaced by the oval versions used on the Comet 2, which first flew in 1953, and the skin sheeting was thickened slightly.&lt;ref name='bao 11'/&gt; Remaining Comet 1s and 1As were either scrapped or modified with oval windows and [[Crack arrestor|rip-stop doublers]].

All production Comet 2s were also modified to alleviate the fatigue problems (most of these served with the [[Royal Air Force|RAF]] as the Comet C2), while a programme to produce a Comet 2 with more powerful Avons was delayed. The prototype Comet 3 first flew in July 1954, and was tested in a non-pressurised state pending completion of the Cohen inquiry.&lt;ref name=d33/&gt; Comet commercial flights would not resume until 1958.&lt;ref&gt;Swanborough 1962, pp. 47–48.&lt;/ref&gt;

Development flying and route proving with the Comet 3 allowed accelerated certification of what was destined to be the most successful variant of the type, the Comet 4. All airline customers for the Comet 3 subsequently cancelled their orders and switched to the Comet 4,&lt;ref name=d33/&gt; which was based on the Comet 3 but with improved fuel capacity. BOAC ordered 19 Comet 4s in March 1955, while American operator [[Capital Airlines]] ordered 14 Comets in July 1956.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Capital Comet.&quot; ''Canadian Aviation'', 29(9–12), 1956, p. 51.&lt;/ref&gt; Capital's order included 10 Comet 4As, a variant modified for short-range operations with a stretched fuselage and short wings, lacking the pinion (outboard wing) fuel tanks of the Comet 4.&lt;ref name=&quot;darling128&quot; /&gt; However, because of financial problems and a subsequent takeover by [[United Airlines]], Capital would never operate the Comet.

[[File:United Arab Airlines Comet Soderstrom.jpg|thumb|left|[[EgyptAir|United Arab Airlines]] Comet 4C at [[Geneva International Airport|Geneva Airport]] in 1968]]
The Comet 4 first flew on 27 April 1958 and received its Certificate of Airworthiness on 24 September 1958; the first was delivered to BOAC the next day.&lt;ref name='bao 11'&gt;Lo Bao 1996, p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Walker 2000, pp. 187–188.&lt;/ref&gt; The base price of a new Comet 4 was around £1,140,000, equivalent to £{{formatnum:{{Inflation|UK|1140000|1958|r=-4}}}} in today's pounds.{{Inflation-fn|UK}}&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1960/1960%20-%202684.html &quot;De Hhavilland.&quot;] ''Flightglobal.com,'' 18 November 1960. Retrieved 13 August 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; The Comet 4 enabled BOAC to inaugurate the first regular jet-powered transatlantic services on 4 October 1958 between London and New York (albeit still requiring a fuel stop at [[Gander International Airport]], Newfoundland, on westward North Atlantic crossings).&lt;ref name=&quot;McNeil 2002, p. 39&quot;/&gt; While BOAC gained publicity as the first to provide transatlantic jet service, by the end of the month rival Pan American World Airways was flying the [[Boeing 707]] on the same route,&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=BZdQhOW-ys0C&amp;pg=PA940&amp;dq=London+New+York+Comet+707&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=fC3RTOzxN87z4gbbyeCIDA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CDoQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=London%20New%20York%20Comet%20707&amp;f=false &quot;The Comet's chance to shine.&quot;] ''The New Scientist'', 4(98), 2 October 1958, p. 940. Retrieved 26 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; and in 1960 the [[Douglas DC-8]] as well. The American jets were larger, faster, longer-ranged, and more cost-effective than the Comet.&lt;ref&gt;Haddon-Cave 2009, p. 16.&lt;/ref&gt; After analysing route structures for the Comet, BOAC reluctantly cast about for a successor, and in 1956 entered into an agreement with Boeing to purchase the 707.&lt;ref&gt;Lo Bao 1996, p. 12.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:DH.106 Comet 5H-AAF EAA LHR 10.05.64 edited-3.jpg|thumb|right|Comet 4 of East African Airways at London Heathrow in 1964]]
The Comet 4 was ordered by two other airlines: [[Aerolíneas Argentinas]] took delivery of six Comet 4s from 1959 to 1960, using them between Buenos Aires and Santiago, New York and Europe, while [[East African Airways]] received three new Comet 4s from 1960 to 1962 and operated them to the United Kingdom and to Kenya, Tanzania, and Uganda.&lt;ref name=&quot;darling114&quot;&gt;Darling 2005, p. 114.&lt;/ref&gt; The Comet 4A ordered by Capital Airlines was instead built for BEA as the Comet 4B with a further fuselage stretch of 38&amp;nbsp;in (97&amp;nbsp;cm) and seating for 99 passengers. The first Comet 4B flew on 27 June 1959 and BEA began Tel Aviv to London-Heathrow services on 1 April 1960.&lt;ref name=&quot;Davies and Birtles p. 62&quot;/&gt; [[Olympic Airways]] was the only other customer to order the type.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jackson dh p459&quot;&gt;Jackson 1987, p. 459.&lt;/ref&gt; The last Comet 4 variant, the Comet 4C, first flew on 31 October 1959 and entered service with [[Mexicana de Aviacion|Mexicana]] in 1960.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1962/1962%20-%200749.html &quot;Comet 4Cs for Mexicana.&quot;] ''Flight International'', 76, 6 November 1959, p. 491. Retrieved 26 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; The Comet 4C had the Comet 4B's longer fuselage and the longer wings and extra fuel tanks of the original Comet 4, which gave it a longer range than the 4B. Ordered by [[Kuwait Airways]], [[Middle East Airlines]], [[EgyptAir|Misrair]] (later United Arab Airlines), and [[Sudan Airways]], it was the most popular Comet variant.&lt;ref name=&quot;JAPL&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Howard, Paul. [http://www.abpic.co.uk/photo/1101609/ &quot;De Havilland DH.106 Comet 4C, OD-ADT, MEA – Middle East Airlines.&quot;] ''Air-Britain Photographic Images Collection''. Retrieved 19 November 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Later service===
[[File:Comet Canopus.jpg|thumb|Comet 4C ''Canopus'' on display at the [[Bruntingthorpe Aerodrome]]]]

In 1959 BOAC began shifting its Comets from transatlantic routes&lt;ref&gt;The Feb 1959 OAG shows eight transatlantic Comets a week out of London with 10 BOAC Britannias and 11 DC-7Cs. In April 1960, 13 Comets, 19 Britannias and 6 DC-7Cs. Comets quit flying the North Atlantic in October 1960 (but reportedly made a few flights in summer 1964).&lt;/ref&gt; and released the Comet to associate companies, making the Comet 4's ascendancy as a premier airliner brief. Besides the 707 and DC-8, the introduction of the [[Vickers VC10]] allowed competing aircraft to assume the high-speed, long-range passenger service role pioneered by the Comet.&lt;ref&gt;Lo Bao 1996, p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1960, as part of a government-backed consolidation of the British aerospace industry, de Havilland itself was acquired by Hawker Siddeley, within which it became a wholly owned division.&lt;ref name=post&gt;[http://www.rafmuseum.org.uk/online-exhibitions/dehavilland/post_war.cfm &quot;De Havilland – Post War&quot;], ''rafmuseum.org.uk''. Retrieved 30 May 2012&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1960s orders declined, with a total of 76 Comet 4s being delivered from 1958 to 1964. In November 1965 BOAC retired its Comet 4s from revenue service, while other operators continued commercial passenger flights with the Comet until 1981. [[Dan-Air]] played a significant role in the fleet's later history and, at one time, owned all 49 remaining airworthy civil Comets.&lt;ref&gt;Swanborough 1980, p. 35.&lt;/ref&gt; On 14 March 1997 a Comet 4C [[United Kingdom military aircraft serials|serial]] ''XS235'' and named ''Canopus'',&lt;ref name=d5/&gt; which had been acquired by the British [[Minister of Technology|Ministry of Technology]] and used for radio, radar and avionics trials, made the last documented production Comet flight.&lt;ref name = 'walker 169'&gt;Walker 2000, p. 169.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
[[File:Dan-Air Comet.jpg|thumb|Dan-Air Comet 4C, G-BDIW exhibited at the ''Flugausstellung Hermeskeil'' in Germany]]

The Comet is widely regarded jointly as an adventurous step forward and a supreme tragedy; nevertheless, the aircraft's legacy does include numerous advances in aircraft design and in accident investigations. The inquiries into the accidents that plagued the Comet 1 were perhaps some of the most extensive and revolutionary that have ever taken place, establishing precedents in accident investigation; many of the deep-sea salvage and aircraft reconstruction techniques employed have remained in use within the aviation industry.&lt;ref&gt;Bibel 2008, p. 68.&lt;/ref&gt; In spite of the Comet being subjected to what was then the most rigorous testing of any contemporary airliner, pressurisation and the dynamic stresses involved were not thoroughly understood at the time of the aircraft's development, nor was the concept of metal fatigue. While these lessons could be implemented on the drawing board for future aircraft, corrections could only be retroactively applied to the Comet.&lt;ref&gt;Bibel 2008, pp. 115–116.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to de Havilland's chief test pilot [[John Cunningham (RAF officer)|John Cunningham]], who had flown the prototype's first flight, representatives from American manufacturers such as [[Boeing]] and [[Douglas Aircraft Company|Douglas]] privately disclosed that if de Havilland had not experienced the Comet's pressurisation problems first, it would have happened to them.&lt;ref&gt;Faith 1996, p. 72.&lt;/ref&gt; Cunningham likened the Comet to the later [[Concorde]], and added that he had assumed that the aircraft would change aviation, which it subsequently did.&lt;ref name=&quot;Faith&quot;/&gt; Aviation author Bill Withuhn concluded that the Comet had pushed &quot;'the state-of-the-art' beyond its limits.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Withuhn p. 88&quot;&gt;Withuhn 1976, p. 88.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote box|align=left|width=19%|quote=&quot;I don't think it is too much to say that the world changed from the moment the Comet's wheels left the ground.&quot;|source=&lt;small&gt;[[Tony Fairbrother]], manager, upgraded Comet development.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fairbrother&quot;&gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/comment/obituaries/article506335.ece &quot;Obituary: Tony Fairbrother.&quot;] ''[[The Times]]'', 26 January 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ramsden, J.M.[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1989/1989%20-%202331.html &quot;Jet Transport's Next 40 Years.&quot;] ''Flight International,'' 29 July 1989. Retrieved: 2 May 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/small&gt;}}

Aeronautical engineering firms were quick to respond to the Comet's commercial advantages and technical flaws alike; other aircraft manufacturers learned from, and profited by, the hard-earned lessons embodied by de Havilland's Comet.&lt;ref name = 'T H 90'&gt;Trischler and Helmuth 2003, p. 90.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Job 1996, p. 21.&lt;/ref&gt; While the Comet's buried engines were used on some other early jet airliners, such as the [[Tupolev Tu-104]],&lt;ref&gt;Stroud 1968, p. 201.&lt;/ref&gt; later aircraft, such as the Boeing 707 and Douglas DC-8, would differ by employing podded engines held on pylons beneath the wings.&lt;ref&gt;Taylor 1996, p. 151.&lt;/ref&gt; Boeing stated that podded engines were selected for their passenger airliners because buried engines carried a higher risk of catastrophic wing failure in the event of engine fire.&lt;ref&gt;Tegler 2000, p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt; In response to the Comet tragedies, manufacturers also developed various means of pressurisation testing, often going so far as to explore rapid depressurisation; subsequent fuselage skins were of a greater thickness than the skin of the Comet.&lt;ref&gt;Dennies 2005, p. 27.&lt;/ref&gt;
{{clear}}

==Variants==

===Comet 1===
[[File:Aeromaritime de Havilland Comet 1 Groves.jpg|thumb|right|[[Union Aéromaritime de Transport]] Comet 1A at [[Le Bourget Airport]] in 1952]]

The square-windowed '''Comet 1''' was the first model produced, a total of 12 aircraft in service and test. Following closely the design features of the two prototypes, the only noticeable change was the adoption of four-wheel bogie main undercarriage units, replacing the single main wheels. Four Ghost 50 Mk 1 engines were fitted (later replaced by more powerful Ghost DGT3 series engines). The span was 115&amp;nbsp;ft (35.05&amp;nbsp;m), and overall length 93&amp;nbsp;ft (28.35&amp;nbsp;m); the [[maximum takeoff weight]] was over 105,000&amp;nbsp;lb (47.628&amp;nbsp;kg) and over 40 passengers could be carried.&lt;ref name=walker190&gt;Walker 2000, p. 190.&lt;/ref&gt;

* An updated '''Comet 1A''' was offered with higher-allowed weight, greater fuel capacity,&lt;ref name=1A/&gt; and water-methanol injection; 10 were produced. In the wake of the 1954 disasters, all Comet 1s and 1As were brought back to Hatfield, first placed in a protective cocoon and retained for testing.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rafmuseum.org.uk/online-exhibitions/comet/comet6.cfm &quot;Last Comet 1.&quot;] ''Royal Air Force Museum Cosford''. Retrieved 1 November 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;  All were substantially damaged in stress testing or were scrapped entirely.&lt;ref name=&quot;Walker p. 40&quot;/&gt;
* '''Comet 1X''': Two RCAF Comet 1As were rebuilt with heavier-gauge skins to a Comet 2 standard for the fuselage, and renamed Comet 1X.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones p. 68&quot;&gt;Jones 2010, p. 68.&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Comet 1XB''': Four Comet 1As were upgraded to a 1XB standard with a reinforced fuselage structure and oval windows. Both 1X series were limited in number of pressurisation cycles.&lt;ref name=&quot;Walker p. 40&quot;&gt;Walker 2000, p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt;
* The '''DH 111 Comet Bomber''', a nuclear bomb carrying variant developed to [[Air Ministry specification]] B35/46, was submitted to the Air Ministry on 27 May 1948. It had been originally proposed in 1948 as the &quot;PR Comet&quot;, a high-altitude photo reconnaissance adaptation of the Comet 1. The Ghost DGT3-powered airframe featured a narrowed fuselage, a bulbous nose with [[H2S radar|H2S Mk IX]] radar, and a four-crewmember pressurised cockpit under a large bubble canopy. Fuel tanks carrying {{convert|2400|impgal|L }} were added to attain a range of {{convert|3350|miles|km}}. The proposed DH 111 received a negative evaluation from the [[Royal Aircraft Establishment]] over serious concerns regarding weapons storage; this along with the redundant capability offered by the RAF's proposed [[V bomber]] trio led de Havilland to abandon the project on 22 October 1948.&lt;ref&gt;Walker 2000, pp. 171–172.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Comet 2===
[[File:De Havilland Comet CMk.2.jpg|thumb|right|Comet C2, XK671 ''Aquila'' at [[RAF Waterbeach]], fitted with revised round windows]]

The '''Comet 2''' had a slightly larger wing, higher fuel capacity and more powerful [[Rolls-Royce Avon]] engines, which all improved the aircraft's range and performance;&lt;ref name = 'Jackson 175'/&gt; its fuselage was {{convert|3|ft|1|in|abbr=on}} longer than the Comet 1's.&lt;ref name=ca1953/&gt; Design changes had been made to make the aircraft more suitable for transatlantic operations.&lt;ref name = 'Jackson 175'&gt;Jackson 1980, p. 175.&lt;/ref&gt; Following the Comet 1 disasters, these models were rebuilt with heavier gauge skin and rounded windows, and the Avon engines featuring larger air intakes and outward-curving jet tailpipes.{{refn|Avon-powered Comets were distinguished by larger air intakes and curved tailpipes that reduced the thermal effect on the rear fuselage.&lt;ref name=&quot;Munson p. 155&quot;/&gt;|group=N}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Munson p. 155&quot;&gt;Munson 1967, p. 155.&lt;/ref&gt; A total of 12 of the 44-seat Comet 2s were ordered by BOAC for the South Atlantic route.&lt;ref name=&quot;Times52516&quot;&gt;&quot;Comet Service To South America Planned&quot; (News). ''The Times'', Saturday, Issue 52516, 10 January 1953, col G, p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt; The first production aircraft (G-AMXA) flew on 27 August 1953.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jackson dh p456&quot;&gt;Jackson 1987, p. 456.&lt;/ref&gt; Although these aircraft performed well on test flights on the South Atlantic, their range was still not suitable for the North Atlantic. All but four Comet 2s were allocated to the RAF with deliveries beginning in 1955.  Modifications to the interiors allowed the Comet 2s to be used in a number of different roles. For VIP transport, the seating and accommodations were altered while provisions for carrying medical equipment including iron lungs were incorporated. Specialised [[Signals intelligence|ELINT]] and electronic surveillance capability was later added to some airframes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Swanborough p. 48&quot;/&gt;
* '''Comet 2X''': Limited to a single Comet Mk 1 powered by four Rolls-Royce Avon 502 turbojet engines and used as a development aircraft for the Comet 2.&lt;ref name = 'Jackson 175'/&gt;
* '''Comet 2E''': Two Comet 2 airliners were fitted with Avon 504s in the inner nacelles and Avon 524s in the outer ones. These aircraft were used by BOAC for proving flights during 1957–1958.&lt;ref name = 'Jackson 175'/&gt;
* '''Comet T2''': The first two of 10 Comet 2s for the RAF were fitted out as crew trainers, with the first aircraft (XK669) flying for the first time on 9 December 1955.&lt;ref name=&quot;Swanborough p. 48&quot;&gt;Swanborough 1962, p. 48.&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Comet C2''': Eight Comet 2s originally destined for the civil market were completed for the RAF and assigned to [[No. 216 Squadron RAF|No. 216 Squadron]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Swanborough p. 48&quot;/&gt;
* '''Comet 2R''': Three Comet 2s were modified for use in radar and electronic systems development, initially assigned to No. 90 Group (later [[RAF Signals Command|Signals Command]]) for the RAF.&lt;ref name=&quot;Swanborough p. 48&quot;/&gt; In service with [[No. 192 Squadron RAF|No. 192]] and [[No. 51 Squadron RAF|No. 51 Squadron]]s, the 2R series was equipped to monitor [[Warsaw Pact]] signal traffic and operated in this role from 1958.&lt;ref name=&quot;Walker p. 159&quot;/&gt;{{refn|The 2R ELINT series was operational until 1974, when replaced by the Nimrod R1, the last Comet derivative in RAF service.&lt;ref name=&quot;Walker p. 159&quot;&gt;Walker 2000, p. 159.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=N}}

===Comet 3===
[[File:DH106 Comet 3 G-ANLO FAR 1954.jpg|thumb|left|Comet 3 G-ANLO in BOAC markings at [[Farnborough Airshow]] in September 1954]]

The '''Comet 3''', which flew for the first time on 19 July 1954, was a Comet 2 lengthened by {{convert|15|ft|5|in|abbr=on}} and powered by Avon M502 engines developing {{convert|10000|lbf|kN|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=thenew/&gt; The variant added wing pinion tanks, and offered greater capacity and range.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jackson dh p457&quot;&gt;Jackson 1987, p. 457.&lt;/ref&gt; The Comet 3 was destined to remain a development series since it did not incorporate the fuselage-strengthening modifications of the later series aircraft, and was not able to be fully pressurised.&lt;ref name=&quot;Birtles p. 129&quot;&gt;Birtles 1970, p. 129.&lt;/ref&gt; Only two Comet 3s began construction with G-ANLO, the only airworthy Comet 3, demonstrated at the [[Farnborough Airshow|Farnborough SBAC Show]] in September 1954. The other Comet 3 airframe was not completed to production standard and was used primarily for ground-based structural and technology testing during development of the similarly sized Comet 4. Nine additional Comet 3 airframes were not completed and their construction was abandoned at Hatfield.&lt;ref&gt;Walker 2000, pp. 51–52.&lt;/ref&gt; In BOAC colours, G-ANLO was flown by John Cunningham in a marathon round-the-world promotional tour in December 1955.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jackson dh p457&quot;/&gt; As a flying testbed, it was later modified with Avon RA29 engines fitted, as well as replacing the original long-span wings with reduced span wings as the '''Comet 3B''' and demonstrated in [[British European Airways]] (BEA) livery at the Farnborough Airshow in September 1958.&lt;ref name=&quot;Birtles p. 129&quot;/&gt; Assigned in 1961 to the Blind Landing Experimental Unit (BLEU) at RAE Bedford, the final testbed role played by G–ANLO was in [[autoland|automatic landing system]] experiments. When retired in 1973, the airframe was used for foam arrester trials before the fuselage was salvaged at [[Woodford, Greater Manchester|BAE Woodford]], to serve as the mock-up for the [[Hawker Siddeley Nimrod|Nimrod]].&lt;ref&gt;Davies and Birtles 1999, p. 36.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Comet 4===
[[File:BEA De Havilland DH-106 Comet 4B Tempelhof Manteufel.jpg|thumb|[[British European Airways]] Comet 4B at [[Berlin Tempelhof Airport]] in October 1968]]

The '''Comet 4''' was a further improvement on the stretched Comet 3 with even greater fuel capacity. The design had progressed significantly from the original Comet 1, growing by 18&amp;nbsp;ft 6&amp;nbsp;in (5.64&amp;nbsp;m) and typically seating 74 to 81 passengers compared to the Comet 1's 36 to 44 (119 passengers could be accommodated in a special charter seating package in the later 4C series).&lt;ref name=&quot;Winchester p. 109&quot;&gt;Winchester 2004, p. 109.&lt;/ref&gt; The Comet 4 was considered the definitive series, having a longer range, higher cruising speed and higher maximum takeoff weight. These improvements were possible largely because of Avon engines with twice the thrust of the Comet 1's Ghosts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Davies and Birtles p. 62&quot;&gt;Davies and Birtles 1999, p. 62.&lt;/ref&gt; Deliveries to BOAC began on 30 September 1958 with two 48-seat aircraft, which were used to initiate the first scheduled transatlantic services.

* '''Comet 4B''': Originally developed for Capital Airlines as the 4A, the 4B featured greater capacity through a 2m longer fuselage, and a shorter wingspan; 18 were produced.
* '''Comet 4C''': This variant featured the Comet 4's wings and the 4B's longer fuselage; 23 were produced.

The last two Comet 4C fuselages were used to build prototypes of the Hawker Siddeley Nimrod maritime patrol aircraft.&lt;ref name=haddon/&gt; A Comet 4C (SA-R-7) was ordered by Saudi Arabian Airlines with eventual disposition to the [[Royal Saudi Air Force|Saudi Royal Flight]] for the exclusive use of [[Saud of Saudi Arabia|King Saud bin Abdul Aziz]]. Extensively modified at the factory, the aircraft included a VIP front cabin, a bed, special toilets with gold fittings and was distinguished by a green, gold and white colour scheme with polished wings and lower fuselage that was commissioned from aviation artist John Stroud. Following its first flight, the special order Comet 4C was described as &quot;the world's first executive jet.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Davies and Birtles 1999, p. 50.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Comet 5 proposal===
The '''Comet 5''' was proposed as an improvement over previous models, including a wider fuselage with five-abreast seating, a wing with greater sweep and podded [[Rolls-Royce Conway]] engines. Without support from the [[Department for Transport|Ministry of Transport]], the proposal languished as a hypothetical aircraft and was never realised.&lt;ref name=&quot;Walker p. 62&quot;/&gt;{{refn|The MoT subsequently backed BOAC's order of Conway-powered Boeing 707s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Walker p. 62&quot;&gt;Walker 2000, p. 62.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=N}}

===Hawker Siddeley Nimrod===
{{Main article|Hawker Siddeley Nimrod}}

The last two Comet 4C aircraft produced were modified as prototypes (XV148 &amp; XV147) to meet a British requirement for a [[maritime patrol aircraft]] for the [[Royal Air Force]]; initially named &quot;Maritime Comet&quot;, the design was designated '''Type HS 801'''.&lt;ref name=haddon&gt;Haddon-Cave 2009, p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt; This variant became the Hawker Siddeley Nimrod and production aircraft were built at the [[Hawker Siddeley]] factory at [[Woodford Aerodrome]]. Entering service in 1969, five Nimrod variants were produced.&lt;ref&gt;Haddon-Cave 2009, p. 19.&lt;/ref&gt;  The final Nimrod aircraft were retired in June 2011.&lt;ref name=dmj-r1&gt;[http://www.defencemanagement.com/news_story.asp?id=16738 &quot;Nimrod R1 makes final flight&quot;] ''Defence Management Journal,'' 28 June 2011. Retrieved 28 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Operators==
{{Main article|List of de Havilland Comet operators}}

[[File:Gatwick1976-mrh.jpg|thumb|Dan-Air Comet 4s at [[Gatwick Airport|London Gatwick Airport]] in 1976]]

The original operators of the early Comet 1 and the Comet 1A were BOAC, Union Aéromaritime de Transport, and Air France. All early Comets were withdrawn from service for accident inquiries, during which orders from British Commonwealth Pacific Airlines, Japan Air Lines, Linea Aeropostal Venezolana, National Airlines, Pan American World Airways, and Panair do Brasil were cancelled.&lt;ref name=&quot;darling119&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;JAPL&quot;/&gt; When the redesigned Comet 4 entered service, it was flown by customers BOAC, Aerolíneas Argentinas, and East African Airways,&lt;ref name=d47-61&gt;Darling 2001, pp. 47–61.&lt;/ref&gt; while the Comet 4B variant was operated by customers BEA and Olympic Airways,&lt;ref name=d47-61/&gt; and the Comet 4C model was flown by customers Kuwait Airways, Mexicana, Middle East Airlines, Misrair Airlines, and Sudan Airways.&lt;ref name=&quot;JAPL&quot;/&gt;

Other operators used the Comet either through leasing arrangements or through second-hand acquisitions. BOAC's Comet 4s were leased out to [[Air Ceylon]], [[Air India]], AREA Ecuador, [[Central African Airways]],{{dubious|date=January 2012}} and [[Qantas|Qantas Empire Airways]];&lt;ref name=&quot;darling119&quot;&gt;Darling 2005, p. 119.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Macfarlane, Ian. [http://www.abpic.co.uk/photo/1003492/ &quot;De Havilland DH.106 Comet 4, G-APDJ, Air Ceylon.&quot;] ''Air-Britain Photographic Images Collection''. Retrieved 19 November 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; after 1965 they were sold to AREA Ecuador, [[Dan-Air]], [[Mexicana de Aviación|Mexicana]], [[Malaysian Airways]], and the Ministry of Defence.&lt;ref name=&quot;JAPL&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=d47-61/&gt;&lt;ref name = 'MoF'/&gt; BEA's Comet 4Bs were chartered by [[Cyprus Airways]], Malta Airways, and [[Transportes Aéreos Portugueses]].&lt;ref name=&quot;darling117&quot;&gt;Darling 2005, p. 117.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Channel Airways]] obtained five Comet 4Bs from BEA in 1970 for inclusive tour charters.&lt;ref name=&quot;darling138&quot;&gt;Darling 2005, p. 138.&lt;/ref&gt; Dan-Air bought all of the surviving flyable Comet 4s from the late 1960s into the 1970s; some were for spares reclamation but most were operated on the carrier's inclusive tour charters; a total of 48 Comets of all marks were acquired by the airline.&lt;ref&gt;Davies and Birtles 1999, p. 54.&lt;/ref&gt;

In military service, the United Kingdom's [[Royal Air Force]] was the largest operator, with the [[No. 51 Squadron RAF|51 Squadron]] (1958–1975; Comet C2, 2R), [[No. 192 Squadron RAF|192 Squadron]] (1957–1958; Comet C2, 2R), [[No. 216 Squadron RAF|216 Squadron]] (1956–1975; Comet C2 and C4), and the [[Royal Aircraft Establishment]] using the aircraft.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jones p. 68&quot;/&gt;
&lt;ref&gt;Institution of Electrical Engineers 1978, p. 89.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Royal Canadian Air Force]] also operated Comet 1As (later retrofitted to 1XB) through its [[No. 412 Squadron RCAF|412 Squadron]] from 1953 to 1963.&lt;ref name=&quot;Walker p. 40&quot;/&gt;

==Accidents and incidents==

The Comet was involved in &lt;!--28 [[Aviation accidents and incidents|aviation occurrences]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://aviation-safety.net/database/dblist.php?Type=190|title &quot;de Havilland Comet incidents.&quot;] ''Aviation Safety Network.'' Retrieved: 28 May 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; of which --&gt; 26 [[hull loss|hull-loss accidents]], including 13 fatal crashes which resulted in 426 fatalities.&lt;ref name=asn&gt;[http://aviation-safety.net/database/dblist.php?field=typecode&amp;var=190%&amp;cat=%1&amp;sorteer=datekey&amp;page=1 &quot;de Havilland Comet hull-losses.&quot;] ''Aviation Safety Network.'' Retrieved: 28 May 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; Pilot error was blamed for the type's first fatal accident, which occurred during takeoff at [[Jinnah International Airport|Karachi, Pakistan]] on 3 March 1953 and involved a Canadian Pacific Airlines Comet 1A.&lt;ref name=&quot;JAPL&quot;&gt;Roach and Eastwood 1992, pp. 331–335.&lt;/ref&gt; Three fatal Comet 1 crashes due to structural problems, specifically BOAC Flight 783/057 on 2 May 1953, [[BOAC Flight 781]] on 10 January 1954, and [[South African Airways Flight 201]] on 8 April 1954, led to the grounding of the entire Comet fleet. After design modifications were implemented, Comet services resumed in 1958.&lt;ref name=&quot;JAPL&quot;/&gt;

[[File:BOAC Comet Manteufel.jpg|thumb|left|Comet 4 G-APDN [[1970 Dan-Air de Havilland Comet crash|crashed]] in the Spanish Montseny range in July 1970 during a Dan-Air flight.&lt;ref name=asn/&gt;]]

Pilot error resulting in [[controlled flight into terrain]] was blamed for five fatal Comet 4 accidents: an Aerolíneas Argentinas crash near Asunción, Paraguay on 27 August 1959, [[Aerolíneas Argentinas Flight 322]] at [[Campinas]] near São Paulo, Brazil on 23 November 1961, [[United Arab Airlines Flight 869 (1962)|United Arab Airlines Flight 869]] in Thailand's Khao Yai mountains on 19 July 1962, a Saudi Arabian Government crash in the Italian Alps on 20 March 1963, and United Arab Airlines Flight 844 in Tripoli, Libya on 2 January 1971.&lt;ref name=&quot;JAPL&quot;/&gt; The [[Dan-Air Flight 1903|Dan-Air de Havilland Comet crash]] in Spain's Montseny range on 3 July 1970 was attributed to navigational errors by [[air traffic control]] and pilots.&lt;ref&gt;[http://aviation-safety.net/database/record.php?id=19700703-0 &quot;ASN Aircraft accident de Havilland DH-106 Comet 4 G-APDN Sierra del Montseny&quot;]. Aviation Safety Network, 28 May 2012. Retrieved 28 May 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; Other fatal Comet 4 accidents include a British European Airways crash in Ankara, Turkey following instrument failure on 21 December 1961, [[United Arab Airlines Flight 869 (1963)|United Arab Airlines Flight 869]] during inclement weather near Bombay, India on 28 July 1963, and the terrorist bombing of [[Cyprus Airways Flight 284]] off the Turkish coast on 12 October 1967.&lt;ref name=&quot;JAPL&quot;/&gt;

Nine Comets, including Comet 1s operated by BOAC and Union Aeromaritime de Transport and Comet 4s flown by Aerolíneas Argentinas, Dan-Air, Malaysian Airlines, and United Arab Airlines, were irreparably damaged during takeoff or landing accidents that were survived by all on board.&lt;ref name=&quot;JAPL&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=asn/&gt; A hangar fire damaged a [[No. 192 Squadron RAF]] Comet 2R beyond repair on 13 September 1957, and three Middle East Airlines Comet 4Cs were destroyed by Israeli troops at Beirut, Lebanon on 28 December 1968.&lt;ref name=&quot;JAPL&quot;/&gt;

==Aircraft on display==
[[File:De Havilland Comet RAF Museum Cosford.jpg|thumb|right|Comet 1 G-APAS at the [[RAF Museum Cosford]]]]

Since retirement, three early-generation Comet airframes have survived in museum collections. The only complete remaining Comet 1, a Comet 1XB with the registration G-APAS, is displayed at the [[RAF Museum Cosford]].&lt;ref name=cosford/&gt; While painted in BOAC colours, it never flew for the airline, having been first delivered to [[Air France]] and then to the [[Ministry of Supply]] after conversion to 1XB standard;&lt;ref name=cosford&gt;[http://www.rafmuseum.org.uk/cosford/collections/aircraft/de-havilland-comet-1a.cfm &quot;de Havilland Comet 1A.&quot;] ''Royal Air Force Museum Cosford''. Retrieved 1 November 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; this aircraft also served with the RAF as XM823. The sole surviving Comet fuselage with the original square-shaped windows, part of a Comet 1A registered F-BGNX, has undergone restoration and is on display at the [[de Havilland Aircraft Museum]] in Hertfordshire, England.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.dehavillandmuseum.co.uk/aircraft/de-havilland-dh106-comet-1a/|title=de Havilland DH106 Comet 1A – de Havilland Aircraft Museum|website=www.dehavillandmuseum.co.uk|access-date=2016-04-25}}&lt;/ref&gt; A Comet C2 ''Sagittarius'' with [[United Kingdom military aircraft serials|serial]] ''XK699'', later maintenance serial 7971M, has been on display at the gate of [[RAF Lyneham]] in Wiltshire, England since 1987.&lt;ref&gt;Barratt, Tristan p. [http://www.flickr.com/photos/tristanbarratt/2044161326/ &quot;Gate Guardian Comet C2 Sagittarius – XK699 – RAF Lyneham.&quot;] ''Flickr''. Retrieved 2 November 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=XK699&gt;Araujo, Ignacio. [http://www.publictenders.net/node/1664492 GB-High Wycombe: &quot;Dismantlement and relocation of Gate Guardian Comet C2 XK699.&quot;] ''Defence Equipment &amp; Support''. Retrieved 31 May 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2012, with the planned closure of RAF Lyneham, the aircraft was slated to be dismantled and shipped to the RAF Museum Cosford where it will be re-assembled for display.&lt;ref name=XK699/&gt;

[[File:De Havilland Comet - Imperial War Museum Duxford.jpg|thumb|left|Comet 4 G-APDB outdoors at the [[Imperial War Museum Duxford]]]]
Seven complete Comet 4s are housed in museum collections. The [[Imperial War Museum Duxford]] has a Comet 4 (G-APDB), originally in
Dan-Air colours as part of its Flight Line Display, and later in BOAC livery at its AirSpace building.&lt;ref&gt;Oakey, Michael, ed. &quot;Duxford's AirSpace opens&quot;. ''Aeroplane'', Vol. 35, No. 9, September 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; A Comet 4B (G-APYD) is stored in a facility at the [[Science Museum at Wroughton]] in Wiltshire, England.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ssplprints.com/image.php?id=82768 &quot;De Havilland Comet 4B airliner, serial no 6438, 1960.&quot;] ''Science &amp; Society Picture Library''. Retrieved 2 November 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Comet 4Cs are exhibited at the ''[[:de:Flugausstellung Hermeskeil|Flugausstellung Leo Junior]]'' at Hermeskeil, Germany (G-BDIW),&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.luftfahrtmuseum.com/htmi/imr/dhj.htm &quot;DeHavilland DH 106 Comet 4 C.&quot;] ''luftfahrtmuseum.com''. Retrieved 2 November 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Museum of Flight]] near Seattle, Washington (N888WA),&lt;ref name = 'MoF'&gt;[http://www.museumofflight.org/aircraft/de-havilland-dh-106-comet-mk-4c &quot;de Havilland D.H. 106 Comet Mk. 4C.&quot;] ''Museum of Flight''. Retrieved 2 November 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; the [[National Museum of Flight]] near Edinburgh, Scotland (G-BDIX),&lt;ref&gt;&quot;emdjt42.&quot; [http://www.flickr.com/photos/emdjt42/4063299981/ &quot;De Havilland Comet 4C G-BDIX Interior View Scottish Museum of Flight.&quot;] ''Flickr''. Retrieved 2 November 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; and the ''Parque Zoológico Irapuato'' in Guanajuato, Mexico (N777WA).&lt;ref&gt;Soto, Ernesto Perales. [http://www.flickr.com/photos/eperales/36341723/in/photostream/ &quot;A treasure found!&quot;] ''Flickr''. Retrieved 2 November 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

The last Comet to fly, Comet 4C ''Canopus'' (XS235),&lt;ref name = 'walker 169'/&gt; is kept in running condition at [[Bruntingthorpe Aerodrome]], where fast taxi runs are regularly conducted.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_9onvxO2DxE &quot;De Havilland Comet XS235 G-CPDA Fast Taxi Run.&quot;] ''youtube.com''. Retrieved 2 November 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; Since the 2000s, various parties have proposed restoring ''Canopus'', which is maintained by a staff of volunteers,&lt;ref name=bruntingthorpe&gt;[http://www.bruntingthorpeaviation.com/the-aircraft/ &quot;Bruntingthorpe Aircraft Museum&quot;]. Bruntingthorpe Aviation. Retrieved 2 June 2012.]&lt;/ref&gt; to airworthy, fully flight-capable condition.&lt;ref name=d5&gt;Darling 2001, p. 5.&lt;/ref&gt; The Bruntingthorpe Aerodrome also displays a related Hawker Siddeley Nimrod MR2 aircraft.&lt;ref name=bruntingthorpe/&gt;

==Specifications==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;
!
! Comet 1 !! Comet 2 !! Comet 3 !! Comet 4
|-
!Cockpit crew
| colspan=4 | 4 (2 pilots, flight engineer and radio operator/navigator)&lt;ref name=&quot;JAWA65 p153-4&quot;/&gt;
|-
! Passengers
| colspan=2 | 36–44&lt;ref name=&quot;Winchester p. 109&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Times52516&quot;/&gt; || 58–76&lt;ref name=thenew/&gt; || 56–81&lt;ref name=pax/&gt;
|-
! Length
| {{convert|93|ft|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name=ca1953/&gt; || {{convert|96|ft|1|in|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name=ca1953/&gt; || colspan=2 | {{convert|111|ft|6|in|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name=thenew/&gt;&lt;ref name=more/&gt;
|-
! Wingspan
|colspan=&quot;4&quot;| {{convert|115|ft|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name=more/&gt;&lt;ref name=trans1955/&gt;
|-
! Tail height
|colspan=&quot;4&quot;| {{convert|29|ft|6|in|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name=more/&gt;
|-
! Wing area
| colspan=3 | {{convert|2015|sqft|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name=ca1953/&gt; || {{convert|2121|sqft|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name=more/&gt;
|-
!Airfoil
|colspan=&quot;4&quot;| [[NACA airfoil|NACA 63A116 mod]] root, NACA 63A112 mod tip&lt;ref&gt;Lednicer, David. [http://www.ae.illinois.edu/m-selig/ads/aircraft.html &quot;The Incomplete Guide to Airfoil Usage.&quot;] ''UIUC Applied Aerodynamics Group'', 15 September 2010. Retrieved 26 April 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- |-
! Empty weight
| {{convert|75400|lb|abbr=on}} --&gt;
|-
! [[Maximum takeoff weight]] (MTOW)
|{{convert|110000|lb|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name=ca1953/&gt;||{{convert|120000|lb|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name=ca1953/&gt;||{{convert|150000|lb|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name=ca1953/&gt;||{{convert|156000|lb|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name=more/&gt;
|-
! Operating range (typical performance)
|{{convert|1500|mi|nmi km|abbr=on|lk=on}}&lt;ref name=bbc/&gt; ||{{convert|2600|mi|nmi km|abbr=on|lk=on}}&lt;ref name=trans1955/&gt;||{{convert|2700|mi|nmi km|abbr=on|lk=on}}&lt;ref&gt;Darling 2001, p. 35.&lt;/ref&gt;||{{convert|3225|mi|nmi km|abbr=on|lk=on}}&lt;ref name=&quot;JAWA65 p153-4&quot;/&gt;
&lt;!-- |-
!Max speed
|{{convert|846|kph|kn mph|abbr=on}} --&gt;
|-
!Cruising speed
|{{convert|740|kph|kn mph|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name=ca1953/&gt;||{{convert|790|kph|kn mph|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name=trans1955/&gt;|| colspan=2 | {{convert|840|kph|kn mph|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name=trans1955/&gt;&lt;ref name=ltd/&gt;
|-
!Cruise altitude
| colspan=2 | {{convert|42000|ft|abbr=on}}}&lt;ref name=ca1953/&gt;&lt;ref name=trans1955/&gt; || {{convert|45000|ft|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name=trans1955/&gt; || {{convert|42000|ft|abbr=on}}&lt;ref name=&quot;JAWA65 p153-4&quot;/&gt;
|-
!Powerplants (x 4)
|[[de Havilland Ghost|Halford H.2 Ghost]] 50 turbojets: {{convert|5000|lbf|abbr=on|lk=on}}&lt;ref name=ca1953/&gt;||[[Rolls-Royce Avon]] Mk 503/504 turbojets: {{convert|7000|lbf|abbr=on|lk=on}}&lt;ref name=ca1953/&gt;||[[Rolls-Royce Avon]] Mk 502/521 turbojets: {{convert|10000|lbf|abbr=on|lk=on}}&lt;ref name=thenew/&gt;||[[Rolls-Royce Avon]] Mk 524 turbojets: {{convert|10500|lbf|abbr=on|lk=on}}&lt;ref name=ltd/&gt;
|}

Sources: ''Jane's All The World's Aircraft 1965–66'',&lt;ref name=&quot;JAWA65 p153-4&quot;&gt;Taylor 1965, pp. 153–154.&lt;/ref&gt; ''De Havilland Aircraft since 1909'',&lt;ref name=&quot;Jackson dh p464&quot;&gt;Jackson 1987, p. 464.&lt;/ref&gt; and ''Flight International''.&lt;ref name=ca1953&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1953/1953%20-%200296.html &quot;Commercial Aircraft 1953: De Havilland Comet.&quot;] ''Flight International,'' 6 March 1953. Retrieved 1 May 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=thenew&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1954/1954%20-%202137.html &quot;The New Comet.&quot;] ''Flight International,'' 30 July 1954, p. 132. Retrieved 1 May 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=pax&gt;''Flight'', 28 March 1958, pp. 422–423.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=more&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1957/1957%20-%201676.html &quot;Comet 4C: More Payload on Medium Stages.&quot;] ''Flight International,'' 15 November 1957, p. 764. Retrieved 1 May 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=trans1955&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1955/1955%20-%200337.html &quot;Transport Aircraft – 1955.&quot;] ''Flight International,'' 11 March 1955, p. 337. Retrieved 1 May 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=ltd&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1957/1957%20-%201214.html? &quot;The De Havilland Aircraft Co., Ltd.&quot;] ''Flight International,'' 30 August 1957, p. 302. Retrieved 1 May 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Popular culture==
{{Main article|Aircraft in fiction#de Havilland Comet|l1=De Havilland Comet in fiction}}
&lt;!-- ===============({{NoMoreCruft}})===============--&gt;
&lt;!-- Please READ [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft/page content#Popular_culture]] and [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Military history/Style guide#Popular_culture]] before adding any &quot;Popular culture&quot; items.

Please do not add the many minor appearances of the aircraft. This section is only for major cultural appearances where the aircraft plays a MAJOR part in the story line, or has an &quot;especially notable&quot; role in what is listed. A verifiable source proving the appearance's notability may be required. Random cruft, including ALL Ace Combat, Battlefield, and Metal Gear Solid appearances, and ALL anime/fiction lookalike speculation, WILL BE removed.

If your item has been removed, please discuss it on the talk page FIRST. A verifiable source proving the appearance's notability may be required. If a consensus is reached to include your item, a regular editor of this page will add it back. Thank you for your cooperation.--&gt;

==See also==
{{multiple image
|align=right
|width1=175
|image1=De Havilland Comet.svg
|alt1=
|width2=250
|caption1=Comet 4B 3-view schematic (front, side, and dorsal views)
|image2=Comet 1 3-view.jpg
|alt2=
|caption2= Comet 1 3-view in silhouette (note differences in Comet 4 insert, reproduced in same scale)
}}
*[[Arnold Alexander Hall]]
*[[Royal Aircraft Establishment]]
* {{Portal-inline|Aviation}}
* {{Portal-inline|United Kingdom}}
*[[Seymour Collection]], an [[aerophilately]] collection relating to the Comet in the British Library.

'''Other early jet-powered commercial aircraft (excluding pure prototypes):'''
* [[Avro Canada C102 Jetliner]] ''(first flight August 1949, never entered service)''
* [[Sud Aviation Caravelle]] ''(first flight May 1955, entered service 1959)''
* [[Tupolev Tu-104]] ''(first flight June 1955, entered service 1956)''
* [[Tupolev Tu-110]] ''(first flight March 1957, never entered service)''
* [[Boeing 707]] ''(first flight December 1957, entered service 1958)''
* [[Douglas DC-8]] ''(first flight May 1958, entered service 1959)''
* [[Baade 152]] ''(first flight December 1958, never entered service)''
* [[Convair 880]] ''(first flight 1959, entered service 1960)''

{{Aircontent
|lists=
* [[List of civil aircraft]]
* [[List of jet airliners]]
}}
{{clear}}

==References==
;Notes
{{reflist|45em|group=N}}

;Citations
{{Reflist|30em}}

;Bibliography
{{refbegin}}
* Abzug, Malcolm J. and Eugene Larrabee. ''Airplane Stability and Control: A History of the Technologies That Made Aviation Possible''. Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press, 2002. ISBN 0-521-80992-4.
* ''Antennas and Propagation, Part 1.'' London: Institution of Electrical Engineers, 1978. ISBN 0-85296-196-0.
* Atkinson, R. J., W. J. Winkworth and G. M. Norris. [http://naca.central.cranfield.ac.uk/reports/arc/rm/3248.pdf &quot;Behaviour of Skin Fatigue Cracks at the Corners of Windows in a ''Comet'' I Fuselage.&quot;] ''Ministry of Aviation'' via ''[[Her Majesty's Stationery Office]]'', 1962.
* Avrane, A. ''Sud Est Caravelle''. London: Jane's Publishing, 1981. ISBN 0-7106-0044-5.
* Beaty, David. ''Strange Encounters: Mysteries of the Air.'' London: Atheneum, 1984. ISBN 978-0-689-11447-2.
* Bibel, George D. ''Beyond the Black Box: The Forensics of Airplane Crashes.'' Baltimore, Maryland: JHU Press, 2008. ISBN 0-8018-8631-7.
* Birtles, P.J. ''Classic Civil Aircraft 3: De Havilland Comet.'' Shepperton, UK: Ian Allen, 1990. ISBN 0-7110-1947-9.
* Birtles, P.J. &quot;The de Havilland Comet Srs. 1–4.&quot; ''Aircraft in Profile, Volume 5.'' New York: Doubleday, 1970, First edition 1967.
* Cacutt, Len. ''The World's Greatest Aircraft''. Devon, UK: Exeter Books, 1989. ISBN 0-7917-0011-9.
* [http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1954/1954%20-%202971.html &quot;The Comet Accidents: History of Events: Sir Lionel Heald's Introductory Summary at the Enquiry&quot;]. ''[[Flight International|Flight]]'', 29 October 1954, pp.&amp;nbsp;652–654.
* [http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1958/1958%20-%200404.html &quot;Comet Resurgent: A decade of D.H. Jet Transport Design&quot;]. ''[[Flight International|Flight]]'', 28 March 1958, pp.&amp;nbsp;420–425.
* Darling, Kev. ''De Havilland Comet''. North Branch, Minnesota: Specialty Press, 2001. ISBN 1-58007-036-1.
* Darling, Kev. ''De Havilland Comet''. Ramsbury, Marlborough, Wiltshire, UK: Crowood Press, 2005. ISBN 1-86126-733-9.
* Davies, R.E.G. and Philip J. Birtles. ''Comet: The World's First Jet Airliner''. McLean, Virginia: Paladwr Press, 1999. ISBN 1-888962-14-3.
* Dennies, Daniel P. ''How to Organize And Run a Failure Investigation.'' Materials Park, Ohio: ASM International, 2005. ISBN 0-87170-811-6.
* Dick, Ron and Dan Patterson. ''50 Aircraft That Changed the World.'' Erin, Ontario, Canada: Boston Mills Press, 2010. ISBN 978-1-55407-658-1.
* Faith, Nicholas. ''Black Box: Why Air Safety is no Accident, The Book Every Air Traveller Should Read''. London: Boxtree, 1996. ISBN 0-7522-2118-3.
* Floyd, Jim. ''The Avro Canada C102 Jetliner.'' Erin, Ontario: Boston Mills Press, 1986. ISBN 0-919783-66-X.
* Francis, Decon. [https://books.google.com/books?id=MC0DAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA98&amp;dq=popular+science+1950+I+saw+this+jet&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=FE65TMfpGaWxnAefke3XDQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CDMQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=popular%20science%201950%20I%20saw%20this%20jet&amp;f=true &quot;I Saw This Jet Liner Fly 500 m.p.h.&quot;] ''Popular Science'', 156(5), May 1950, pp.&amp;nbsp;98–104.
* Green, William and Gordon Swanborough, eds. &quot;Jet Jubilee (Part 1)&quot;. ''[[Air International]]'', Vol. 12, No. 3, March 1977, pp.&amp;nbsp;124–131 (Part 2); ''[[Air International]]'', Vol. 12, No. 4, April 1977, pp.&amp;nbsp;171–180.
* Gunn, John. ''Challenging Horizons: Qantas 1939–1954.'' St Lucia, Queensland: University of Queensland Press, 1987. ISBN 0-7022-2017-5.
* Haddon-Cave, Charles. [https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=3ddbUjc_RvgC&amp;pg=PA16&amp;dq=de+havilland+comet&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=JlHHTLPhDMuWOovKqdgB&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCwQ6AEwADge#v=onepage&amp;q=de%20havilland%20comet&amp;f=false ''The Nimrod Review: an Independent Review into the Broader Issues Surrounding the Loss of the RAF Nimrod MR2 Aircraft XV230 in Afghanistan in 2006.''] London: The Stationery Office, 2009.
* Hill, Malcolm L. &quot;de Havilland's Comet: Pushing the Boundaries.&quot; ''Airliners,'' Volume 15, No. 4, July/August 2002.
* Jackson, A.J. ''British Civil Aircraft 1919–1972: Volume II''. London: Putnam (Conway Maritime Press), 1988. ISBN 0-85177-813-5.
* Jackson, A.J. ''De Havilland Aircraft since 1909''. London: Putnam, Third edition, 1987. ISBN 0-85177-802-X.
* Jefford, C.G., ed. [http://www.rafmuseum.org.uk/research/documents/Journal%2026%20-%20Seminar%20the%20RAF%20and%20Nuclear%20Weapons%201960-98.pdf ''The RAF and Nuclear Weapons, 1960–1998.''] London: Royal Air Force Historical Society, 2001.
* [[Macarthur Job|Job, Macarthur]]. ''Air Disaster: Volume 1''. Fyshwick, Australian Capital Territory: Aerospace Publications, 1996. ISBN 1-875671-11-0.
* Jones, Barry. &quot;Database: D.H. 016 Comet.&quot; ''Aeroplane,'' Volume 38, No. 4, Issue no. 444, April 2010.
* Keith, Ronald A. ''Bush Pilot with a Briefcase: The Incredible Story of Aviation Pioneer Grant McConachie.'' Vancouver: Douglas &amp; McIntyre Ltd., 1997, First edition 1992. ISBN 978-1-55054-586-9.
* Kodera, Craig, Mike Machat and Jon Proctor. ''From Props to Jets: Commercial Aviation's Transition to the Jet Age 1952–1962.'' North Branch, Minnesota: Specialty Press, 2010. ISBN 978-1-58007-146-8.
* Lane, Peter. [https://books.google.co.uk/books?ei=oC7RTOfTBI2d4QbGotnkDA&amp;ct=result&amp;id=iwt8AAAAIAAJ&amp;dq=Queen+Mother+Comet&amp;q=Comet ''The Queen Mother.''] London: Hale, 1979. ISBN 0-7091-7648-1.
* Lo Bao, Phil, ed. ''The de Havilland Comet (Airlines &amp; Airliners)''. Middlesex, UK: The Aviation Data Centre Ltd., 1996.
* McNeil, Ian, ed. ''An Encyclopedia of the History of Technology''. London: Routledge, 2002 (E-edition), First edition 1990. ISBN 0-203-19211-7.
* Motem, John, ed. [https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=IOGCd7QreKgC&amp;pg=PA143&amp;dq=Sud+Aviation+Caravelle+de+havilland+Comet&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=10rRTJ3WDNy4jAef7OWMDA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CDAQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=Sud%20Aviation%20Caravelle%20de%20havilland%20Comet&amp;f=false &quot;European Civil Background.&quot;] ''The Putnam Aeronautical Review, Volume Three''. London: Conway Maritime Press, 1990. ISBN 1-55750-676-0.
* Munson, Kenneth. ''Civil Airliners since 1946.'' London: Blandford Press, 1967.
* Painter, Martin. ''The DH. 106 Comet: An Illustrated History''. Tonbridge, Kent, UK: Air Britain (Historians) Ltd., 2002. ISBN 0-85130-330-7.
* Proctor, Jon, Mike Machat and Craig Kodera. ''From Props to Jets: Commercial Aviation's Transition to the Jet Age 1952–1962.'' North Branch, Minnesota: Specialty Press, 2010. ISBN 1-58007-146-5.
* Prins, François. &quot;World Beater: Homage to the DH. 106 Comet.&quot; ''Air Enthusiast,'' Issue 78, November/December 1998.
* Roach, J. R. and A. B. Eastwood. ''Jet Airliner Production List.'' West Drayton, UK: The Aviation Hobby Shop, 1992, ISBN 0-907178-43-X.
* Schnaars, Stephen P. ''Managing Imitation Strategies.'' New York: Simon &amp; Schuster, 2002. ISBN 0-7432-4265-3.
* Smith, Adrian. &quot;The Dawn of the Jet Age in Austerity Britain: David Lean's The Sound Barrier&quot;. ''Historical Journal of Film, Radio and Television'', 2010. 30(4), pp.&amp;nbsp;487–514.
* Stewart, Stanley. ''Air Disasters.'' London: Arrow Books, 1989, First edition 1986. ISBN 0-09-956200-6.
* Stroud, John. ''Soviet Transport Aircraft since 1945.'' London: Putnam, 1968. ISBN ISBN 0-370-00126-5.
* Swanborough, F. G. ''Civil Aircraft of the World.'' London: C. Scribner's Sons, 1980. ISBN 0-684-12895-0.
* Swanborough, F. G. ''Turbine-engined Airliners of the World.'' London: Temple Press Books, 1962.
* [[John W. R. Taylor|Taylor, John W. R.]] ''Jane's All The World's Aircraft 1965–66''. London: Sampson Low, Marston &amp; Company, 1965.
* Taylor, John William Ransom. ''The Lore of Flight.'' New York: Barnes &amp; Noble, 1996, First edition 1988. ISBN 0-7607-0364-7.
* Tegler, Jan. [https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=1QOkMX3Xc4cC&amp;pg=PA6&amp;dq=Boeing+podded+catastrophic+engine&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=OSvRTOSmIqOU4gb20PC7DA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CDUQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Boeing%20podded%20catastrophic%20engine&amp;f=false ''B-47 Stratojet: Boeing's Brilliant Bomber'' (Walter J. Boyne Military Aircraft Series).] New York: McGraw-Hill Professional, 2000. ISBN 0-07-135567-7.
* Trischler, Helmuth and Stefan Zeilinger, eds. [https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=jGUBczN_Ap4C&amp;pg=PA88&amp;dq=The+First+Jet+Airliner:+The+Story+of+the+de+Havilland+Comet&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=jWrNTObZFsjKjAfqgunWBw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=5&amp;ved=0CEAQ6AEwBDgo#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false ''Tackling Transport, Volume 3'' (Artefacts Series: Studies in the History of Science and Technology).] London: NMSI Trading Ltd, 2003. ISBN 1-900747-53-7.
* Walker, Timothy. ''The First  Jet Airliner: The Story of the de Havilland Comet''. Newcastle upon Tyne, UK: Scoval Publishing Ltd., 2000. ISBN 1-902236-05-X.
* Watkins, David. ''de Havilland Vampire: The Complete History.'' Thrupp, Stroud, UK: Budding Books, 1996. ISBN 1-84015-023-8.
* Winchester, Jim, ed. &quot;De Havilland DH.106 Comet.&quot; ''Civil Aircraft (The Aviation Factfile)''. London: Grange Books plc, 2004. ISBN 1-84013-642-1.
* Withuhn, Bill. &quot;Triumph, Tragedy and Triumph Again... The Comet Story.&quot; ''Air Classics Airliner Special No. 2'', Summer 1976.
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|De Havilland DH 106 Comet}}
* [http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1949/1949%20-%201324.html &quot;The Comet Emerges&quot; a 1949 ''Flight'' article on the unveiling of the Comet prototype]
* [http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1949/1949%20-%201356.html &quot;Comet in the Sky&quot; a 1949 ''Flight'' article on the Comet's maiden flight]
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=242TXAq79I8 Film of BOAC De Havilland Comet 3 G-ANLO at Vancouver International Airport in December 1955 ]
* [http://www.airforce.forces.gc.ca/v2/hst/page-eng.asp?id=621 The de Havilland Comet in RCAF Service]
* [http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1951/1951%20-%200803.html &quot;Comet Construction Methods&quot;] a 1951 ''Flight'' article
* [http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1952/1952%20-%201127.html &quot;The Tale of the Comet&quot; a 1952 ''Flight'' article on the design and development of the Comet]
*[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1953/1953%20-%200539.html &quot;Conversion to Comets&quot; a 1953 ''Flight'' article on the Comet's handling]
*[http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1953/1953%20-%200555.html &quot;Comet Engineering&quot; a 1953 ''Flight'' article] by [[Bill Gunston]]
* [http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1954/1954%20-%202971.html &quot;The Comet Accidents: History of Events,&quot; a 1954 ''Flight'' article of Sir Lionel Heald's summary of the enquiry]
* [http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1955/1955%20-%200193.html &quot;Report of the Comet Inquiry&quot;, a 1955 ''Flight'' article on the publishing of the enquiry into the Comet design]
* [http://www.kbtc.org/page.php?id=795 Project Comet]  Documentary produced by [[Full Focus]]
* [http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1969/1969%20-%202527.html &quot;The Comet is Twenty&quot;] a 1969 ''Flight'' article
* [http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1989/1989%20-%202330.html &quot;Jet Transport's Next 40 Years&quot;] a 1989 ''Flight'' article on the Comet's influence

{{de Havilland Comet related}}
{{de Havilland aircraft}}
{{good article}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2013}}

[[Category:British airliners 1940–1949]]
[[Category:De Havilland aircraft|Comet]]
[[Category:Quadjets]]</text>
      <sha1>rpfb2buv90om97v94npun8pmdfcpkmw</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
