<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Devon County War Memorial</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>49132691</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750425426</id>
      <parentid>745459829</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-19T17:44:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>HJ Mitchell</username>
        <id>9336033</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* History and design */ ce</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14288">{{about|the memorial outside the cathedral|the memorial in Northernhay Gardens|Exeter War Memorial}}
{{Infobox Military Memorial
|name           = Devon County War Memorial
|image          = File:Devon County War Memorial.jpg
|country        = United Kingdom
|commemorates   = approximately 11,600 men and women from Devon killed in the First World War  
|unveiled       = 1921
|coordinates    = {{coord|50.7227094|-3.5315417|type:landmark_region:GB|display=inline, title}}
|location       = Cathedral Green, [[Exeter]], [[Devon]]
|nearest_town   = 
|designer =    [[Edwin Lutyens|Sir Edwin Lutyens]]
|inscription = THE COUNTY OF DEVON TO HER GLORIOUS DEAD / 1914–1919 / TE DEUM LAUDAMUS / 1939–1945 
| embedded={{infobox designation list
| embed=yes
| designation1 = Grade II*
| designation1_offname = Devon County War Memorial and Processional Way
| designation1_date = 16 April 2009
| designation1_number = 1393228
}}  
}}
The '''Devon County War Memorial''' is a [[World War I memorials|First World War memorial]], designed by [[Edwin Lutyens|Sir Edwin Lutyens]] and situated on the cathedral green in [[Exeter]], the [[county town]] of [[Devon]], in the south west of England. It is one of fifteen War Crosses designed by Lutyens to a similar specification, and one of two to serve as a civic memorial in a city. The authorities in Devon originally planned to complete the construction of a [[cloister]] at [[Exeter Cathedral]] to be dedicated to the county's war dead, but this scheme was abandoned due to lack of funds. The Devon County War Memorial Committee commissioned Lutyens to design a War Cross instead, deciding on the green of Exeter Cathedral after scouting for several locations. A war memorial for Exeter itself was being considered concurrently, but the two committees failed to work together, resulting in two separate memorials—the county memorial by the cathedral and [[Exeter City War Memorial]] in Northernhay Gardens.

The memorial, a simple granite cross hewn from a single stone quarried from [[Haytor]] on [[Dartmoor]], stands just to the west of the cathedral, in alignment with the altar. The cross sits on a granite plinth, which itself sits on three steps. It was unveiled by [[Edward_VIII#Prince of Wales|Edward, Prince of Wales]] on 16 May 1921. The area around the memorial was remodelled after archaeological excavations in the 1970s. A processional way was added, leading to the [[cathedral close]] from the cathedral itself, along with a set of steps to a platform in front of the memorial, which emphasises its connection to the cathedral. The memorial is a grade II* [[listed building]]; since 2015, all of Lutyens' war memorials in England have been protected by listed building status.

==Background==
In the aftermath of the [[First World War]], thousands of war memorials were built across Britain. Amongst the most prominent designers of memorials was architect [[Edwin Lutyens|Sir Edwin Lutyens]], described by [[Historic England]] as &quot;the leading English architect of his generation&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;NHLE&quot; /&gt; Prior to the First World War, Lutyens established his reputation designing country houses for wealthy patrons, including [[Castle Drogo]] to the north of Exeter. Following the war he devoted much of his time to memorialising the casualties; he served as one of the three principal architects to the [[Imperial War Graves Commission]] (IWGC; later the Commonwealth War Graves Commission, CWCG) and designed numerous war memorials for towns and villages across Britain, as well as several elsewhere in the Commonwealth. Lutyens designed [[The Cenotaph, Whitehall|the Cenotaph]] on [[Whitehall]] in London, which became the focus for the national [[Remembrance Sunday]] commemorations, as well as the [[Thiepval Memorial to the Missing]]—the largest British war memorial anywhere in the world—and the [[Stone of Remembrance]] which appears in all large [[Commonwealth War Graves Commission]] cemeteries.&lt;ref name=&quot;NHLE&quot;&gt;{{National Heritage List for England |num=1393228 |desc=Devon County War Memorial and Processional Way}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Harvey 171&quot;/&gt;

The Devon County memorial is one of fifteen War Crosses designed by Lutyens to a similar specification between 1920 and 1925. Most of Lutyens' War Crosses were commissioned for small villages, but the Devon County memorial is one of two commissioned as a civic memorial in a city—the other being the [[York City War Memorial]].&lt;ref name=&quot;NHLE&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Harvey 171&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Skelton, p. 112.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Commissioning==
The first plan was for the completion of the [[cloister]] of [[Exeter Cathedral]] to serve as a war memorial, but the idea was abandoned due to a lack of funds. The idea of building a war memorial at all proved controversial; the chairman of the local branch of the [[National Federation of Discharged and Demobilized Sailors and Soldiers]] was of the opinion that the funds would be better spent caring for surviving veterans and condemned the idea of a memorial as a &quot;useless waste of money&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Parker 125&quot;/&gt; The County War Memorial Committee, chaired by [[Hugh Fortescue, 4th Earl Fortescue]], realised that it was unlikely to raise a large sum of money as communities across Devon would be focusing on their own commemorations and commissioning individual war memorials. Despite this, the committee was determined to erect some sort of memorial to the county's war dead, but as a compromise sought a simple but elegant monument.&lt;ref name=&quot;Parker 125&quot;&gt;Parker, p. 125.&lt;/ref&gt; They commissioned Lutyens in 1920 and opted for his War Cross design. The committee considered several potential sites, including Cawsand Beacon on [[Dartmoor]] and the [[Haldon Hills]] in south Devon, but the committee's preferred location was the [[cathedral close]] of Exeter, Devon's [[county town]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Parker 127&quot;&gt;Parker, p. 127.&lt;/ref&gt; The specific site was chosen so that the memorial would be visible from the High Street and Broadgate.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harvey 171&quot;&gt;Harvey, p. 171.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Monument 2 Devonshire 08284.JPG|thumb|left|The 2nd Devonshires' memorial at [[La Ville-aux-Bois-lès-Pontavert]], whose construction was supported by the Devon County War Memorial Committee]]
The memorial is one of two civic war memorials in Exeter, the other being the [[Exeter City War Memorial]] in Northernhay Gardens (the former grounds of [[Rougemont Castle]]), while Exeter Cathedral also contains memorials to the [[Devonshire Regiment]] and the Wessex Field Ambulance. The city war memorial was the responsibility of a separate committee; the city and county memorial committees conspicuously failed to cooperate. According to Sir James Owen, chairman of the city committee, the city offered a joint committee but the county &quot;slammed the door in our face&quot;, while Lord Fortescue accused the city of proceeding with its own project without any discussion with the county. The result was that two very different memorials were constructed in Exeter—the city's memorial takes the form a figure of Victory on a large pedestal surrounded by further sculptures to form a cross. With its remaining funds, the Devon County War Memorial Committee supported the construction of a battlefield memorial at [[La Ville-aux-Bois-lès-Pontavert]] in France to honour the 2nd Battalion of the Devonshire Regiment, who endured particularly heavy fighting at [[Bois des Buttes (Battle honour)|Bois des Buttes]] during the [[Third Battle of the Aisne]].&lt;ref&gt;Parker, pp. 128–129.&lt;/ref&gt;

==History and design==
[[File:Devon County War Memorial and Exeter Cathedral (cropped).jpg |thumb|A view of the memorial and Exeter Cathedral]]
[[File:Devon County War Memorial (detail).jpg|thumb|Detail of the inscription on the base]]
The project proceeded simply once the original idea of completing the cloisters was abandoned. The memorial stands on the Cathedral Green, just to the west of the cathedral itself, in alignment with the [[altar]]. It takes the form of a {{convert|30|ft|m|adj=on|abbr=off}} granite cross, quarried from [[Haytor]] on Dartmoor to the north of Exeter, and hewn from a single stone—the largest Lutyens was able to acquire.&lt;ref name=&quot;NHLE&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Harvey 171&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Meller&quot;&gt;Meller, pp. 22–23.&lt;/ref&gt; The cross has a diamond-shaped tapered shaft with [[chamfer]]ed arms, no wider than the base, close to the top to form a cross. The cross sits on a three-tiered base and a rectangular plinth, which itself sits on three stone steps as is customary for Lutyens' war memorials. The central tier of the base bears the inscription &quot;THE COUNTY OF DEVON TO HER GLORIOUS DEAD / 1914–1919 / TE DEUM LAUDAMUS / 1939–1945&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;NHLE&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;IWM&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.iwm.org.uk/memorials/item/memorial/46017|title=War Memorial: County of Devon|work=War Memorials Inventory|publisher=[[Imperial War Museum]]|accessdate=11 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lutyens wrote of his design: &quot;it is very simple and a monolith and its subtlety in line means labour, care and thought [...] it should endure forever&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;NHLE&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Meller&quot;/&gt;

The memorial was unveiled on [[Whit Monday]], 16 May 1921, by Edward, Prince of Wales (later King [[Edward VIII]]), the heir to the throne, with Lutyens in attendance.&lt;ref name=&quot;NHLE&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Harvey 171&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Skelton, p. 75.&lt;/ref&gt; Upon its completion, Lutyens said of the monument, &quot;it is very simple and a monolith and its subtlety in line means labour, care and thought. [...] It should endure forever&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;NHLE&quot; /&gt; At the unveiling ceremony, Lord Fortescue estimated that 11,600 men and women from Devon had been killed while serving in the war; he later estimated that a total of 63,700 (8,000 regulars, 36,700 volunteers, and 19,000 conscripts) had served.&lt;ref name=&quot;Parker 127&quot; /&gt; The names of the fallen were recorded on a roll of honour, of which three copies were made: one for Exeter Cathedral, one to be held by the county, and one which the Prince of Wales placed in a hollow in the base of the war memorial. The prince's visit generated considerable excitement in the area; local people lined the street to welcome his motorcade and banners were flown from businesses on the High Street. After the unveiling, he spent ten days touring the local area.&lt;ref&gt;Harvey, pp. 171–172.&lt;/ref&gt;   

In 1971, archaeological excavations were undertaken around the western fringe of the cathedral and the remains of several Roman buildings, including a baths, were discovered and re-buried due to lack of funds;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-devon-30081921|title=Excavation plans for Exeter's Roman Baths|last=Jones|first=Claire|date=16 January 2015|publisher=[[BBC News]]|accessdate=15 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; the ruins were [[Scheduled monument|scheduled]] as an ancient monument.&lt;ref&gt;{{National Heritage List for England |num=1002632 |desc=Part of the Roman town of Exeter, beneath Cathedral Green}}&lt;/ref&gt; The cathedral green, including the area around the war memorial, was remodelled by [[Geoffrey Jellicoe|Sir Geoffrey Jellicoe]] in 1974. Jellicoe created a processional way leading to the cathedral from the cathedral close, past the war memorial. At the same time, Jellicoe introduced a set of steps and a platform leading to the memorial which emphasises the memorial's alignment with the altar and strengthens the visual connection between the memorial and the cathedral.&lt;ref name=&quot;NHLE&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Pevsner, p. 410.&lt;/ref&gt; A set of metal railings was erected around the foot of the memorial in June 2001—described by Lutyens researcher Tim Skelton as &quot;an unfortunate addition&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Skelton, p. 168.&lt;/ref&gt; The railings were partly funded by a grant from the [[War Memorials Trust]]; they were intended to combat problems with vandalism and anti-social behaviour.&lt;ref name=&quot;WMT&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.warmemorials.org/search-grants/?gID=295|title=Showcase result: Devon County|publisher=[[War Memorials Trust]]|accessdate=11 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

On 16 April 2009, the memorial—including the processional way—was designated by English Heritage (now Historic England) a grade II* [[listed building]] for its special architectural or historic interest, a status which offers legal protection from unauthorised demolition or modification.&lt;ref name=&quot;NHLE&quot; /&gt;

In November 2015, as part of commemorations for the centenary of the First World War, Lutyens' war memorials were recognised as a &quot;national collection&quot;; all 44 of his free-standing memorials in England were listed or had their listing status reviewed and their [[National Heritage List for England]] list entries updated and expanded.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://historicengland.org.uk/whats-new/news/lutyens-war-memorials|title=National Collection of Lutyens’ War Memorials Listed|date=7 November 2015|publisher=[[Historic England]]|accessdate=15 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Clear}}

==See also==
{{commonscat|Devon County War Memorial}}
*[[Grade II* listed buildings in Exeter]]
*[[Grade II* listed war memorials in England]]

==References==
'''Bibliography'''
*{{cite book|last1=Cherry|first1=Bridget|authorlink1=Bridget Cherry|last2=Pevsner|first2=Nikolaus|authorlink2=Nikolaus Pevsner|title=Devon: The Buildings of England|year=1991|publisher=[[Yale University Press]]|location=New Haven, Connecticut|isbn=9780300095968|page=410}}
*{{cite book|last=Harvey|first=Hazel|title=The Story of Exeter|year=2011|publisher=Phillimore|location=[[Bognor Regis]]|isbn=9781860776786}}
*{{cite book|last=Meller|first=Hugh|title=Exeter Architecture|year=1989|publisher=Phillimore|location=Chichester|isbn=9780850336931}}
*{{cite book|last=Parker|first=David|title=Exeter: Remembering 194–18|year=2014|publisher=[[The History Press]]|location=Stroud, Gloucestershire|isbn=9780750960267}}
*{{cite book|last1=Skelton|first1=Tim|last2=Gliddon|first2=Gerald|title=Lutyens and the Great War|year=2008|publisher=[[Frances Lincoln Publishers]]|location=London|isbn=9780711228788}}

'''Citations'''
{{reflist|30em}}

{{Good article}}
[[Category:Exeter]]
[[Category:Exeter Cathedral]]
[[Category:Monuments and memorials in Devon]]
[[Category:Grade II* listed buildings in Devon]]
[[Category:Works of Edwin Lutyens]]
[[Category:World War I memorials in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Military history of Devon]]</text>
      <sha1>o9abc5vo4in44nzl5txkra8g7ws41vt</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
