<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>España-class battleship</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>16938194</id>
    <revision>
      <id>698170719</id>
      <parentid>698168257</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-01-04T12:20:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marcus Cyron</username>
        <id>299667</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>([[c:GR|GR]]) [[c:COM:FR|File renamed]]: [[File:Acorazado Jaime I, 1937, no text.svg]] → [[File:Acorazado Jaime I (en 1937).svg]] [[c:COM:FR#reasons|File renaming criterion #1]]: Wunsch oder Zustimmung des HochladendenMore details.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24971">{{good article}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2013}}
{|{{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
|Ship image=[[File:Acorazado España (en 1913).svg|300px]]
|Ship caption=''España'' as she appeared in 1913
}}
{{Infobox ship class overview
|Name=''España''
|Builders=[[Sociedad Española de Construcción Naval]], El [[Ferrol, Spain]]
|Operators=
|Class before=
|Class after=
|Subclasses=
|Cost=
|Built range=1909–1921
|In service range=
|In commission range=1913 to 1937
|Total ships completed=3
|Total ships lost=3
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
|Hide header=
|Header caption
|Ship displacement=*Normal: {{convert|15700|t|LT|abbr=on}}
*Full Load: {{convert|16450|t|LT|abbr=on}}
|Ship length={{convert|140|m|abbr=on}} [[o/a]]
|Ship beam={{convert|24|m|abbr=on}}
|Ship draft={{convert|7.8|m|abbr=on}}
|Ship propulsion=*12 × Yarrow coal-fired boilers
*4 × turbines
*4 × shafts
|Ship speed={{convert|19.5|kn|km/h}}
|Ship range={{convert|5000|nmi|km|abbr=on}} at {{convert|10|kn|km/h}}
|Ship complement=854
|Ship armament=*8 × {{convert|305|mm|in|0|abbr=on}}/50 cal guns
*20 × {{convert|102|mm|in|0|abbr=on}} guns
*4 × 3-pounder guns
*2 × machine guns
|Ship armor=*[[Belt armor]]: {{convert|203|mm|in|0|abbr=on}}
*Deck: {{convert|38|mm|in|abbr=on}}
*[[Gun turret|Turrets]]: 203&amp;nbsp;mm
*[[Conning tower]]: {{convert|254|mm|in|0|abbr=on}}
}}
|}

The '''''España'' class''' was a series of three [[dreadnought]] [[battleships]] built for the [[Spanish Navy]] between 1909 and 1921. The construction of the ships, particularly the third vessel, were significantly delayed due to shortages of materiel supplied by Great Britain during [[World War I]], particularly armament. The class comprised [[Spanish battleship España|''España'']] (Spain), [[Spanish battleship Alfonso XIII|''Alfonso XIII'']], and [[Spanish battleship Jaime I|''Jaime I'']]. The three ships were the only Spanish dreadnoughts ever built. They were also the smallest battleships of the type constructed, owing to the weak Spanish economy. The ships were armed with eight {{convert|12|in|adj=on|0}} guns, but their small displacement—only {{convert|15700|MT|sp=us}}—forced the designers to compromise on armor protection and speed.

''España'', ''Alfonso XIII'', and ''Jaime I'' served in the 1st Squadron of the Spanish Fleet, which became the Training Squadron in the 1920s. They all saw action during the [[Rif War (1920)|Rif War]] in the early 1920s supporting Spanish ground forces in North Africa. ''España'' ran aground in August 1923 and the Navy could not salvage her; she instead broke up under tidal forces. ''Alfonso XIII'' was renamed ''España'' in 1931 after her namesake, King [[Alfonso XIII of Spain|Alfonso XIII]] was forced into exile. The two surviving ships served on opposite sides of the [[Spanish Civil War]], and both were destroyed during the conflict. ''España'' struck a [[naval mine]] laid by her own side in on 30 April 1937 and sank, and ''Jaime I'' was destroyed by an internal explosion in June 1937.

==Development==
The Spanish public blamed the disastrous losses in the [[Spanish–American War]] of 1898 on the Navy, but recognized the need to modernize and rebuild it. The first attempt to rebuild the Navy came in the Fleet Plan of 1903, which called for a fleet centered on seven {{convert|15000|t|LT|sp=us|adj=on}} battleships and three {{convert|10000|t|LT|sp=us|adj=on}} cruisers. This plan proved to be far too ambitious for the weak [[Economy of Spain|Spanish economy]], and an unstable Spanish parliament proved unable to provide funding. It was followed by the Fleet Plan of 1905, which proposed a fleet of eight {{convert|14000|t|LT|sp=us|abbr=on}} battleships along with a number of [[torpedo boat]]s and [[submarine]]s. It too fell victim to the weaknesses of the Spanish government. It was not until early 1907 that a strong [[Cabinet (government)|cabinet]] led by [[Antonio Maura]] came to power that the question of naval construction was settled.&lt;ref&gt;Fernandez, Mituckov &amp; Crawford, p. 63&lt;/ref&gt; The Fleet Plan of 1907 proposed three 15,000&amp;nbsp;MT battleships along with several [[destroyer]]s, torpedo boats, and other craft. The construction plan was to last for eight years. Debates over the plan took place in the ''[[Cortes Generales]]'' (General Courts—the Spanish legislature) through November, with a final approval vote on 2 December. The Fleet Plan was formally signed into law on 7 January 1908.&lt;ref&gt;Fernandez, Mituckov &amp; Crawford, pp. 63, 65&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=F856&gt;Fitzsimons, p. 856&lt;/ref&gt;

The delay enabled Spain to take advantage of experience gained by Britain with the world's first commissioned [[dreadnought|all-big-gun battleship]], {{HMS|Dreadnought|1906|6}}, and by the United States with its own new battleship, {{USS|South Carolina|BB-26|6}}.&lt;ref name=F856/&gt; The Spanish Navy was principally concerned with defending its three main naval bases: [[Ferrol, Galicia|Ferrol]], [[Cádiz]], and [[Cartagena, Spain|Cartagena]]. Of secondary importance was the need to keep the new battleship design tightly constrained due to the frail Spanish economy and industrial sector.&lt;ref name=FMC667&gt;Fernandez, Mituckov &amp; Crawford, pp. 66–67&lt;/ref&gt; A third constraint was the need to build ships small enough to fit in existing dockyard facilities, since there were insufficient funds to both build larger battleships and to enlarge the navy's dockyards.&lt;ref name=GG378/&gt; As a result, the design requirements called for relatively heavy offensive power with minimal range and armor protection. The Navy began discussing the design requirements with [[Armstrong Whitworth]] and [[Vickers]] in 1907 well before the law was actually passed. On 5 September 1907, Vickers provided a proposed design for a 15,000-ton battleship armed with eight 12-inch guns. This design was the basis for the requirements for the design competition, which was issued on 21 April 1908.&lt;ref name=FMC667/&gt;

[[File:Espana class line-drawing, Brassey 1911.png|left|thumb|Line-drawing of the final SECN design]]
Four shipbuilders submitted bids: the Italian [[Gio. Ansaldo &amp; C.]] led a group that also included the Austro-Hungarian [[Škoda Works]] and the French ''[[Marrel Freres Forges de La Loire et du Midi]]''; the French [[Schneider-Creusot]] firm partnered with ''[[Société Nouvelle des Forges et Chantiers de la Méditerranée]]'' and ''[[Forges et Chantiers de la Gironde]]''; the Spanish ''[[Sociedad Española de Construcción Naval]]'' (SECN), which was formed by Vickers, Armstrong Whitworth, and [[John Brown &amp; Company]]; and a group of Spanish industrialists backed by [[Palmers Shipbuilding and Iron Company]] and [[William Beardmore and Company]]. Only the first three proposals were seriously considered, as the fourth was considered to be too vague. The ''Junta Superior de la Armada'' (the Navy Staff) and the Navy Minister were responsible for reviewing the three proposals. Ansaldo prepared two design variants; the first called for four twin [[gun turret]]s for the main battery, with one forward, one aft, and two offset [[amidships]]. The second proposal had two triple turrets, fore and aft, with a twin turret on the centerline amidships. Artillery experts in the Navy rejected the second variant. The SECN and Schneider designs also featured the same arrangement as the first Ansaldo proposal.&lt;ref&gt;Fernandez, Mituckov &amp; Crawford, pp. 67&amp;ndash;68&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 1908, the Artillery Committee met to make its recommendations to the ''Junta Superior''. The Committee concluded the SECN and Schneider proposals were superior to the Ansaldo version, but neither had a marked advantage over the other. The following month, the Naval Construction Committee met to evaluate the proposals. It recommended the SECN design first, followed by Schneider, with Ansaldo last. The Office of the Navy Controller also evaluated the proposals in November, and advised the ''Junta Superior'' that only the SECN bid met the design requirements without any legal, administrative, or cost problems.&lt;ref&gt;Fernandez, Mituckov &amp; Crawford, pp. 68&amp;ndash;70&lt;/ref&gt; In February 1909, the Navy requested a revised design from SECN to incorporate several alterations, including an increased [[Freeboard (nautical)|freeboard]] to improve seakeeping, an increased height and length of the main [[belt armor]], and the addition of individual [[rangefinder]]s for each gun turret. SECN agreed to make the changes on 20 March, and the company received the contract on 14 April.&lt;ref&gt;Fernandez, Mituckov &amp; Crawford, p. 72&lt;/ref&gt; Due to the constraints imposed by the Spanish economy, the resulting design produced the smallest dreadnought-type battleships ever built.&lt;ref name=GG378/&gt; They were also obsolescent before completion due to rapid technological change&amp;mdash;most significantly the rise of the [[superdreadnought]] battleships&amp;mdash;and lengthy delays in completion of the later units of the class.&lt;ref&gt;Fitzsimons, p. 857&lt;/ref&gt;

===General characteristics===
The ships of the class were {{convert|132.6|m|abbr=on}} [[length at the waterline|long at the waterline]] and {{convert|140|m|abbr=on}} [[length overall|long overall]]. They had a [[beam (nautical)|beam]] of {{convert|24|m|abbr=on}} and a [[draft (hull)|draft]] of {{convert|7.8|m|abbr=on}}; their freeboard was {{convert|4.6|m|abbr=on}} amidships, much lower than was normal for battleships of the period. They [[Displacement (ship)|displaced]] {{convert|15700|t|LT|sp=us}} as designed and up to {{convert|16450|t|LT|abbr=on|sp=us}} at combat load. The vessels had two tripod [[Mast (sailing)|mast]]s and a small [[superstructure]].&lt;ref name=GG378&gt;Gardiner &amp; Gray, p. 378&lt;/ref&gt; They were equipped with six {{convert|75|cm|abbr=on}} searchlights.&lt;ref&gt;Fernandez, Mituckov &amp; Crawford, p. 95&lt;/ref&gt; The ships were reasonably stable compared to foreign designs, but they had a low [[metacentric height]] of {{convert|1.56|m|abbr=on}} at full loading. This caused them to have very low stability when damaged.&lt;ref&gt;Fernandez, Mituckov &amp; Crawford, p. 77&lt;/ref&gt;

Each ship had a crew of 854&amp;nbsp;officers and enlisted men.&lt;ref name=GG378/&gt; The enlisted crew spaces were located forward in the upper deck, and were cramped and unhygienic. The cabins for non-commissioned officers were also located here. The superstructure included several cabins for senior officers.&lt;ref&gt;Fernandez, Mituckov &amp; Crawford, p. 102&lt;/ref&gt; The ships were initially painted black but in the 1920s they were repainted gray. ''Alfonso XIII'' wore a white identification band on her funnel and ''Jaime I'' wore two, though both ships had them removed after the start of the Civil War. ''Jaime I'' was also repainted dark gray at this time.&lt;ref name=FMC104&gt;Fernandez, Mituckov &amp; Crawford, p. 104&lt;/ref&gt;

===Machinery===
Their propulsion system consisted of four-shaft [[Parsons Marine Steam Turbine Company|Parsons]] [[steam turbine]]s and twelve coal-fired [[water-tube boiler|water-tube]] [[Yarrow boiler]]s.&lt;ref name=GG378/&gt; The turbines drove three-bladed screw propellers that were {{convert|2.4|m|abbr=on}} wide in diameter. Two spare screws were kept aboard each ship.&lt;ref name=FMC101&gt;Fernandez, Mituckov &amp; Crawford, p. 101&lt;/ref&gt; The boilers were trunked into a single funnel that was placed amidships; the location of the funnel, far from the [[foremast]], kept the latter's [[spotting top]] free from smoke interference, but still rendered the spotting top on the mainmast essentially useless.&lt;ref name=FMC84/&gt;

The engines were rated at {{convert|15500|shp|lk=in}} and produced a top speed of {{convert|19.5|kn|lk=in}}.&lt;ref name=GG378/&gt; According to the design contract, the engines were to be capable of a normal maximum of {{convert|22000|shp|abbr=on}} with a top speed of {{convert|19.9|kn}} and up to {{convert|26000|shp|abbr=on}} and {{convert|20.2|kn}} at forced draft. All three ships exceeded {{convert|20|kn}} on speed trials.&lt;ref name=FMC101/&gt; Each ship could store up to {{convert|1900|t|LT|abbr=on}} of coal, which permitted a cruising radius of {{convert|5000|nmi|lk=in}} at a speed of {{convert|10|kn}}.&lt;ref name=GG378/&gt;

===Armament===
[[File:Espana class main weapon.svg|thumb|left|Arrangement of the main armament, bow pointing right]]

Their main armament consisted of eight 12-inch (305&amp;nbsp;mm) 50-[[Caliber (artillery)|caliber]] guns manufactured by Vickers. Each weighed {{convert|65.646|t|LT|sp=us}} and fired an 850-pound (385&amp;nbsp;kg) shell at a [[muzzle velocity]] of 3,000&amp;nbsp;ft/s (914&amp;nbsp;m/s). The guns had a maximum range of 23,500 yards (21,500 m) and a [[rate of fire]] of one round per minute.&lt;ref&gt;Friedman, p. 65&lt;/ref&gt; These guns were housed in four twin [[turret]]s, arranged with two on the centerline fore and aft, the others ''en echelon'' on the wings. The turrets were hydraulically operated, and could be loaded at any angle of elevation. The ''en echelon'' arrangement was chosen over [[superfire|superfiring]] turrets—such as those used in the American dreadnoughts—to save weight and cost. All four turrets could in theory fire on the broadside, and three could fire ahead or astern.&lt;ref name=F856/&gt;&lt;ref name=GG378/&gt; However, blast effects from the wing turrets generally prohibited firing them across the deck or directly ahead and astern.&lt;ref name=FMC84&gt;Fernandez, Mituckov &amp; Crawford, pp. 84&lt;/ref&gt;

The secondary battery comprised twenty {{convert|4|in|abbr=on|0}} 50-caliber guns mounted individually in [[casemate]]s along the length of the hull. They fired a {{convert|31|lb|adj=on}} shell.&lt;ref&gt;Friedman, p. 107&lt;/ref&gt; The guns were too close to the waterline, however, and were unusable in heavy seas; they also suffered from insufficient elevation, which limited their range. The guns were also too weak to be effective against contemporary destroyers, which were becoming increasingly powerful.&lt;ref name=FMC84/&gt; The ships also carried four 3-pounder guns, two machine guns, and two landing guns that could be taken ashore.&lt;ref name=F856/&gt;&lt;ref name=GG378/&gt;

===Armor===
The armor layout for the ''España'' class was essentially a scaled down version of that used in the British {{sclass-|Bellerophon|battleship|4}}.&lt;ref&gt;Fernandez, Mituckov &amp; Crawford, pp. 95&lt;/ref&gt; The reductions were due primarily to the heavy armament in a vessel of such limited displacement.&lt;ref name=GD437&gt;Garzke &amp; Dulin, p. 437&lt;/ref&gt; The main [[belt armor]] was only {{convert|8|in|abbr=on|0}} thick, and tapered to {{convert|4|in|abbr=on|0}} on either end of the central citadel. The upper belt that protected the casemate guns was {{Convert|6|in|abbr=on|0}} thick. Each turret, which had 8&amp;nbsp;in sides, sat on a [[barbette]] that was protected with {{convert|10|in|abbr=on|0}} thick plating. The [[conning tower]] also had 10-inch thick sides. Both the armored deck and the [[torpedo bulkhead]] were {{convert|1.5|in|abbr=on}} thick.&lt;ref name=GG378/&gt; The ships' heavy armor plating consisted of [[Krupp cemented steel]], with [[Krupp homogeneous steel]] used for armor thinner than {{convert|4|in|abbr=on}}; both types were manufactured in Britain.&lt;ref name=FMC96&gt;Fernandez, Mituckov &amp; Crawford, pp. 96&lt;/ref&gt;

Though the ships were poorly armored compared to foreign designs in general, the ships' underwater protection was the greatest weakness in the armor scheme. The torpedo bulkhead was placed too close to the outer hull, which reduced its ability to absorb damage. This weakness played a central role in the loss of both ''España'' to grounding in 1923 and the sinking of ''Alfonso XIII'' by a single [[naval mine|mine]] in 1937.&lt;ref name=FMC96/&gt;

===Modifications===
Only limited modifications were possible due to technical constraints imposed by the need to keep displacement low and insufficient funds to effect a major reconstruction to free up tonnage for other uses.&lt;ref&gt;Fernandez, Mituckov &amp; Crawford, p. 76&lt;/ref&gt; The Navy considered proposals to modernize the three battleships in the early 1920s, but the Spanish military budget was being consumed by the costs of the [[Rif War]] in North Africa and so nothing came of the proposed modernization. These plans called for installing  new fire control equipment with more effective rangefinders, along with additional, newer anti-aircraft guns, and building [[anti-torpedo bulge]]s into the hull to improve underwater protection for a loss of one knot of speed. Deck armor was also to be strengthened.&lt;ref&gt;Fernandez, Mituckov &amp; Crawford, pp. 104–105&lt;/ref&gt;

Ultimately, only minor modifications were possible. In 1926, both ''Jaime I'' and ''Alfonso XII'' had a pair of [[QF 3-inch 20 cwt|Vickers {{convert|76.2|mm|sp=us|adj=on}} anti-aircraft guns]] installed, one each on top of turret numbers 1 and 2. And in the 1930s, the foremast was reduced slightly on the two surviving ships.&lt;ref name=FMC104/&gt; After she was seized by the Nationalists in 1936, ''España'' (ex-''Alfonso XIII'') had these two guns removed for use ashore. They were replaced with four German [[8.8 cm Flak 18/36/37/41|{{convert|8.8|cm|abbr=on}} SK C/30 flak guns]] and two [[2 cm Flak 30/38/Flakvierling|{{convert|2|cm|abbr=on}} C/30 anti-aircraft guns]]. ''Jaime I'', which remained with the Republicans, was reequipped with two Vickers {{convert|47|mm|abbr=on}} 50-caliber anti-aircraft guns and a twin {{convert|25|mm|abbr=on}} Hotchkiss mounting.&lt;ref&gt;Fernandez, Mituckov &amp; Crawford, pp. 91–93&lt;/ref&gt;

==Construction==
A new {{convert|184|by|35|m|abbr=on}} drydock and two {{convert|180|by|35|m|abbr=on}} slipways were built at Ferrol to accommodate the construction of the three battleships. All material, save the armor plate, heavy guns, and fire control equipment, was manufactured in Spain. The contract specified a build time of four years for the first ship, five years for the second, and seven years for the third.&lt;ref name=FMC73&gt;Fernandez, Mituckov &amp; Crawford, p. 73&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the allowance for longer construction times for the later units, their completion, and particularly the third unit, ''Jaime I'', was held up by a lack of materials from Britain as a result of the outbreak of [[World War I]].&lt;ref name=F856/&gt; Most importantly, the main guns for ''Jaime I'' were not delivered until 1919.&lt;ref name=FMC73/&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable plainrowheaders unsortable&quot;
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Name
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Builder&lt;ref name=GG378/&gt;
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Laid down&lt;ref name=GG378/&gt;
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Launched&lt;ref name=GG378/&gt;
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Completed&lt;ref name=GG378/&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | [[Spanish battleship España|''España'']]
|[[Sociedad Española de Construcción Naval|SECN]], [[Ferrol, Galicia|Ferrol]]
|6 December 1909
|5 February 1912
|23 October 1913
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | [[Spanish battleship Alfonso XIII|''Alfonso XIII'']]
| SECN, Ferrol
|23 February 1910
|7 May 1913
|16 August 1915
|-
! scope=&quot;row&quot; | [[Spanish battleship Jaime I|''Jaime I'']]
| SECN, Ferrol
|5 February 1912
|21 September 1914
|20 December 1921
|-
|}

== History ==
[[File:Acorazado Jaime I (en 1937).svg|thumb|''Jaime I'' as she appeared in 1937]]

''España'' was the only member of the class completed by the outbreak of World War I in August 1914, though she did not see action, as Spain remained neutral for the duration of the war.&lt;ref name=GG376&gt;Gardiner &amp; Gray, p. 376&lt;/ref&gt; In August 1914, she participated in the opening ceremonies for the [[Panama Canal]].&lt;ref&gt;''Our Navy'', p. 28&lt;/ref&gt; ''Alfonso XIII'' joined her in August 1915 in the 1st Squadron of the Spanish fleet. In late 1921, ''Jaime I'' was finally completed. Throughout the early 1920s, the three ships served in the Training Squadron.&lt;ref name=GG376/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Garzke &amp; Dulin, p. 438&lt;/ref&gt; During this period, Spain became involved in the [[Rif War (1920)|Rif War]] in Morocco; all three ships saw action during the conflict, primarily by providing artillery support to Spanish ground forces engaging the Rif rebels.&lt;ref&gt;Miller, p. 131&lt;/ref&gt; In August 1923, while bombarding Rif positions, ''España'' ran aground off [[Cape Tres Forcas]]. A lengthy salvage operation failed to free the ship, and in November 1924, the stress of repeated tidal battering broke the wreck in half.&lt;ref name=FMC106&gt;Fernandez, Mituckov &amp; Crawford, p. 106&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1931, after the overthrow of King [[Alfonso XIII of Spain|Alfonso XIII]], his namesake battleship was renamed ''España''.&lt;ref name=GG378/&gt; In the mid-1930s, the Spanish Navy considered modernization programs for the two surviving battleships, but none came to fruition, primarily as a result of the outbreak of the [[Spanish Civil War]] in 1936.&lt;ref&gt;Garzke &amp; Dulin, pp. 438–439&lt;/ref&gt; The two ships found themselves on opposite sides during the conflict; ''España'' served on the side of [[Francisco Franco]]'s [[Nationalist faction (Spanish Civil War)|Nationalists]], and ''Jaime I'' fought for the Republicans.&lt;ref&gt;Gardiner &amp; Chesneau, p. 398&lt;/ref&gt; ''España'' was used for coastal bombardment and to enforce the blockade of Republican ports, while ''Jaime I'' unsuccessfully attempted to disrupt the blockade, though neither ship engaged the other.&lt;ref&gt;Fernandez, Mituckov &amp; Crawford, pp. 107&amp;ndash;108&lt;/ref&gt; In August 1936, ''Jaime I'' was attacked and moderately damaged by Nationalist bombers;&lt;ref&gt;Nofi, p. 32&lt;/ref&gt; while undergoing repairs in Cartagena, she was destroyed by an internal explosion in June 1937.&lt;ref&gt;Gibbons, p. 195&lt;/ref&gt; ''España'' was sunk on 30 April 1937 after striking a mine laid by her own side off the coast of [[Santander, Spain|Santander]] in northern Spain.&lt;ref&gt;Roskill, p. 381&lt;/ref&gt;

Many of the guns from the first ''España'' were recovered and employed in coastal fortifications, some of which remained in service until 1999.&lt;ref name=FMC106/&gt; Six of ''Jaime I''{{'}}s 12-inch guns were also salvaged and similarly employed after she was broken up in the 1940s&amp;mdash;they too remained in service until they were decommissioned in the mid-1990s. The second ''España'' was never raised, and her wreck was discovered in the early 1980s. Several expeditions to survey the wreck took place between February and May 1984.&lt;ref&gt;Fernandez, Mituckov &amp; Crawford, pp. 108&amp;ndash;109&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{Commons category|España class Battleships}}
{{Portal|Battleships}}
{{reflist|20em}}

==References==
* {{cite journal | last1 = Fernandez | first1 = Rafael | first2= Nicholas|last2=Mitiukov|first3=Kent|last3=Crawford |date=March 2007 | title = The Spanish Dreadnoughts of the ''España'' class | journal = Warship International | volume = 44 | issue = 1 | pages = 63–117 | location = Toledo, Ohio | publisher = International Naval Research Organization | issn = 0043-0374 | oclc = 1647131 |lastauthoramp=y}}
* {{cite encyclopedia|editor-last=Fitzsimons| editor-first = Bernard | encyclopedia = The Illustrated Encyclopedia of 20th Century Weapons and Warfare| year = 1979  | publisher = London, UK | volume = 8  | location = Phoebus Publishing  | oclc = | pages = 856–57|isbn=0-8393-6175-0}}
*{{cite book|last=Friedman|first=Norman|title=Naval Weapons of World War I|year=2011|location=Annapolis, Maryland|publisher=Naval Institute Press|isbn= 978-1-84832-100-7}}
*{{cite book |editor1-last=Gardiner|editor1-first=Robert|editor2-last=Gray|editor2-first=Randal|title=Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships: 1906–1922|year=1984|location=Annapolis, Maryland|publisher=Naval Institute Press|isbn=0-87021-907-3}}
* {{cite book |last1=Garzke|first1=William H.|last2=Dulin|first2=Robert O.|title=Battleships: Axis and Neutral Battleships in World War II|year=1985|location=Annapolis, Maryland|publisher=Naval Institute Press|isbn=978-0-87021-101-0}}
*{{cite book|last=Gibbons|first=Tony|title=The Complete Encyclopedia of Battleships and Battlecruisers: A Technical Directory of the World's Capital Ships From 1860 to the Present Day|location=London, UK|publisher=Salamander Books, Ltd.|year=1983|isbn=0-86101-142-2}}
*{{cite book|last=Miller|first=David|title=Illustrated Directory of Warships of the World|year=2001|publisher=MBI Pub. Co.|location=Osceola, Wisconsin|isbn=0-7603-1127-7}}
* {{cite book| last = Nofi| first = Albert A.| authorlink = Albert Nofi| year = 2010| title = To Train The Fleet For War: The U.S. Navy Fleet Problems, 1923–1940| publisher = Naval War College Press| location = Washington, DC| isbn = 978-1-884733-87-1}}
* {{cite journal | year = February 1915| journal = Our Navy | volume = VIII | publisher = Our Navy Publishing Co. | location = New York, New York| issue = 10|oclc=41114005}}
*{{cite book|last=Roskill|first=Stephen|year=1976|title=Naval Policy Between the Wars, Volume 1|publisher=Collins|location=London, UK|isbn=0-00-211561-1}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite book|last=Lyon|first=Hugh|year=1978|title=Encyclopedia of the World's Warships: A Technical Directory of Major Fighting Ships from 1900 to the Present Day|publisher=Salamander Books|isbn=0-86101-007-8|location=London, UK}}

{{España class battleship}}
{{SpanishCivilWarShips}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Espana Class Battleship}}
[[Category:Battleship classes]]
[[Category:España-class battleships|Espana-class battleships]]</text>
      <sha1>2rgy690tx4kb3zlbqwn3bt7hj2rgf0n</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
