<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>George Ingram</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1218177</id>
    <revision>
      <id>741542614</id>
      <parentid>719703008</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-28T04:28:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Abraham, B.S.</username>
        <id>4540583</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>year format in infobox</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18552">{{Use Australian English|date=August 2013}}
{{Infobox military person
|name= George Ingram
|image= George Ingram.JPG
|alt= A head and shoulders portrait of a man in military uniform wearing medals.
|image_size= 220
|caption= George Ingram c.1919
|nickname= 
|birth_date= {{birth date|1889|03|18|df=yes}}
|death_date= {{death date and age|1961|6|30|1889|3|18|df=yes}}
|birth_place= [[Bendigo, Victoria]]
|death_place= [[Hastings, Victoria]]
|placeofburial= Frankston Cemetery
|allegiance= Australia
|branch= [[Australian Army Reserve|Citizens Military Force]]&lt;br/&gt;[[First Australian Imperial Force|Australian Imperial Force]]
|serviceyears= 1905–19&lt;br/&gt;1939–44
|rank= [[Captain (British Army and Royal Marines)|Captain]]
|unit= 
|commands= 
|battles= First World War
* [[Asian and Pacific theatre of World War I|Asian and Pacific Theatre]]
* [[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]]
* [[Battle of Passchendaele]]
* [[Battle of St. Quentin Canal]]
[[Second World War]]
|awards= [[Victoria Cross]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Military Medal]]
|relations= 
|laterwork= 
}}
'''George Morby Ingram''', [[Victoria Cross|VC]], [[Military Medal|MM]] (18 March 1889 – 30 June 1961) was an [[List of Australian Victoria Cross recipients|Australian recipient]] of the [[Victoria Cross]], the highest decoration for gallantry &quot;in the face of the enemy&quot; that can be awarded to members of the British and [[Commonwealth of Nations|Commonwealth]] armed forces. Ingram became Australia's final recipient of the Victoria Cross during the [[First World War]] following his actions during an attack on the village of [[Montbrehain]] in France. Leading a platoon during the engagement, he instigated several charges against a number of German strong points that eventuated in the seizure of ten machine guns and sixty-two prisoners, as well as inflicting high casualties.

Born in the [[Victoria (Australia)|Victorian]] town of [[Bendigo, Victoria|Bendigo]], Ingram was apprenticed as a carpenter and joiner upon leaving school. Joining the militia at the age of fourteen, he later settled in [[Melbourne]] where he worked as a building contractor. Following the outbreak of the First World War, Ingram enlisted in the [[Australian Naval and Military Expeditionary Force]] and served on New Guinea before receiving his discharge in early 1916. Enlisting in the Australian Imperial Force on the same day, he embarked for the Western Front. He was decorated with the [[Military Medal]] following his actions as a member of a bombing section during an attack on [[Bapaume]]. Commissioned as a second lieutenant in June 1918, Ingram returned to Australia in 1919 where he was discharged soon after. Re-settling in Melbourne, he was employed as a foreman for a building contractor company. Enlisting for service in the [[Second World War]], he was allotted to the [[Royal Australian Engineers]] and achieved the rank of captain before being placed on the Retired List in 1944. Ingram died in 1961 at the age of 72.

==Early life==
Ingram was born in Bendigo, Victoria,&lt;ref name=&quot;AF&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Staunton|2005|p=195}}&lt;/ref&gt; on 18 March 1889 to George Ronald Ingram, a farmer, and his wife Charlotte (née Hubbard).&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB&quot;&gt;{{Australian Dictionary of Biography|last=McIntyre|first=Darryl|year=1983|id=A090426b|title=Ingram, George Mawby (1889–1961)|accessdate=3 November 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; Initially educated at the Lilydale State School, he left school at age fourteen and was apprenticed as a carpenter and joiner. Joining the [[Citizens Military Force|militia]] at this time, he was attached to No.&amp;nbsp;7 Company of the Australian Garrison Artillery and in 1906 attended a military exhibition in New Zealand as a member of the Australian contingent.&lt;ref name=&quot;AF&quot;/&gt; Completing his apprenticeship, Ingram moved to [[Caulfield, Victoria|Caulfield]], Melbourne, where he entered into business as a [[building contractor]].&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs98&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Gliddon|2000|p=98}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 19 January 1910, Ingram married Jane Francis Nichols in a Congregational ceremony at [[Prahran, Victoria|East Prahran]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB&quot;/&gt;

==First World War==
On 10 December 1914, Ingram enlisted as a [[Private (rank)|private]] in the 3rd Battalion, [[Australian Naval and Military Expeditionary Force]] at South Yarra. Initially posted for service on the newly captured German territory of [[New Guinea]],&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs98&quot;/&gt; he returned to Australia 6 December 1915,&lt;ref name=&quot;AIF&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aif.adfa.edu.au:8080/showPerson?pid=149421|title=George Morby INGRAM |accessdate=6 November 2008|work=The AIF Project|publisher=Australian Defence Force Academy}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was discharged on 19 January with the rank of [[corporal]]. That same day, he enlisted in the [[First Australian Imperial Force|Australian Imperial Force]] and was allotted to the 16th Reinforcements of the [[24th Battalion (Australia)|24th Battalion]] as a private.&lt;ref name=&quot;AF&quot;/&gt; In October, Ingram embarked with the unit from Melbourne aboard HMAT ''Nestor''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/cms_images/awm8/23_41_4/pdf/0402.pdf|title=George Morby Ingram|accessdate=6 November 2008|format=PDF|work=First World War Embarkation Roll|publisher=Australian War Memorial}}&lt;/ref&gt; Arriving in France, he was appointed acting corporal and joined the 24th Battalion in January 1917.&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs98&quot;/&gt;

On the night of 15/16 March 1917,&lt;ref name=&quot;MMrec&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/cms_images/awm28/1/84/0048.pdf|title=Recommendation for George Morby Ingram to be awarded a Military Medal|accessdate=6 November 2008|format=PDF|work=Recommendations: First World War|publisher=Australian War Memorial}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ingram took part in the battalion's attack on the village of [[Bapaume]] during the German withdrawal to the [[Hindenburg Line]].&lt;ref name=&quot;AF&quot;/&gt; Posted to a bombing section during the engagement, he became involved in a fight with German troops who outnumbered his unit. Making effective use of their grenades, the unit was able to hold off the German attack. Later during the assault, the German forces returned in large numbers, forcing the bombing section to retreat. Ingram, in conjunction with two others, covered the party's withdrawal which thus minimised casualties.&lt;ref name=&quot;MMrec&quot;/&gt; For his actions during the battle, Ingram was awarded the [[Military Medal]], the citation noting his &quot;...&amp;nbsp;great courage and initiative&amp;nbsp;...&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;AIF&quot;/&gt; The announcement of the award was published in a supplement to the ''[[London Gazette]]'' on 11 May 1917.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=30064|date=11 May 1917|startpage=4601|supp=yes|accessdate=6 November 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Promoted to temporary [[sergeant]] on 18 March,&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs98&quot;/&gt; Ingram fell ill in April and was hospitalised in Britain until June when he was deemed fit to return to his battalion. He was hospitalised once again in September after dislocating his knee, and upon returning to his unit on 10 October he was made [[company sergeant major]].&lt;ref name=&quot;AF&quot;/&gt; It was at this time that the Australian focus for the remainder of the year was to be the [[Ypres]] sector in Belgium, and as such the 24th Battalion participated in the [[Battle of Passchendaele]].&lt;ref name=&quot;24th&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/units/unit_11211.asp|title=24th Battalion|accessdate=6 November 2008|publisher=Australian War Memorial}}&lt;/ref&gt; During this time, Ingram was recommended for a [[Officer's commission|commission]] in the 24th Battalion as a [[second lieutenant]], which was confirmed on 20 June 1918. Three days later, however, he was once again admitted to hospital suffering from an illness, and as such was unable to assume his duties as an officer until 12 July when he returned to the battalion.&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs99&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Gliddon|2000|p=99}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Victoria Cross===
On 4 October 1918, the 24th Battalion took part in the attack that captured the [[Beaurevoir]] sector in France, and was, therefore, expecting to have a rest the following day when the unit was unexpectedly ordered to take part in another attack. The assault was to commence at 06:05 from the village of [[Remicourt, Marne|Remicourt]], and lead to the capture of [[Montbrehain]] by the 21st and 24th Battalions with tanks to provide support.&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs97&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Gliddon|2000|p=97}}&lt;/ref&gt; The action was to prove the final engagement for the Australian infantry during the war, and it was during this attack that Ingram was to earn the Victoria Cross; the sixty-fourth, and final, Australian to do so during the First World War.&lt;ref name=&quot;AF&quot;/&gt;

At the designated time, the two infantry battalions commenced the attack under the cover of an artillery barrage. The advance was heavily counter-attacked by German machine gun and artillery fire, but the Australians managed to continue despite the late arrival of the tanks.&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs97&quot;/&gt; Approximately {{convert|100|yd|m}} from the German trenches, the 24th Battalion's B Company—in which Ingram was commanding a platoon—became the object of severe sniper and machine gun fire, halting the unit's advance.&lt;ref name=&quot;AF&quot;/&gt; Under the cover of a [[Lewis Gun]], Ingram dashed ahead of his men and led them against the German strong point. After a fierce fight, the platoon succeeded in capturing nine machine guns and killing all forty-two Germans who had occupied the line; Ingram accounting for at least eighteen of them himself.&lt;ref name=&quot;VCrec1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/cms_images/awm28/1/122P2/0015.pdf|title=Recommendation for George Morby Ingram to be awarded a Victoria Cross|accessdate=9 November 2008|format=PDF|work=Recommendations: First World War|publisher=Australian War Memorial}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:G M Ingram J03067.JPG|thumb|alt=A full length portrait of a man in military uniform wearing medals. His hand is resting atop a small table.|upright|left|175px|Lt. G.M. Ingram]]

Soon after, the company came under heavy fire from an old quarry occupied by over one hundred German soldiers who possessed as many as forty machine guns. Severe casualties were sustained as they began to advance for attack, including the company commander who fell seriously wounded. Taking command of the attack, Ingram rallied the men and rushed forward. Jumping into the quarry, he charged the first post himself, shooting six German soldiers and capturing a machine gun.&lt;ref name=&quot;AF&quot;/&gt; The German forces were soon overcome, and thirty troops subsequently surrendered.&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs97&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;VCrec1&quot;/&gt;

While his men were clearing up the remaining German positions, Ingram scouted ahead in search of machine gun nests in the village. He soon located one positioned in a house, which had been firing through the cellar ventilator.&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs97&quot;/&gt; Managing to enter the house, he shot the gunner through the ventilator. He fired several more shots into the cellar before rushing to the head of the cellar stairs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/cms_images/awm28/1/122P2/0016.pdf|title=Recommendation for George Morby Ingram to be awarded a Victoria Cross (cont)|accessdate=9 November 2008|format=PDF|work=Recommendations: First World War|publisher=Australian War Memorial}}&lt;/ref&gt; By thus cutting off any means of escape, a further thirty Germans were taken [[Prisoner of war|prisoner]].&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs97&quot;/&gt;

The battle for Montbrehain raged until 20:00 that night, during which time the line had been linked up and consolidated. The casualties of the 24th Battalion had been so high that two companies of the 27th Battalion had to be attached for support;&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs98&quot;/&gt; the 24th Battalion left the frontline for the last time on 6 October.&lt;ref name=&quot;24th&quot;/&gt;

The full citation for Ingram's Victoria Cross appeared in a supplement to the ''London Gazette'' on 6 January 1919, it read:&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=31108|date=6 January 1919|startpage=306|endpage=307|supp=yes|accessdate=9 November 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|''War Office, 6th January, 1919.''

His Majesty the KING has been graciously pleased to approve of the award of the Victoria Cross to the undermentioned Officers, Non-commissioned Officers and Men: —

Lt. George Morby Ingram, M.M., 24th Bn., A.I.F.

For most conspicuous bravery and initiative during the attack on Montbrehain, East of Peronne, on 5th&amp;nbsp;October, 1918. When early in the advance his platoon was held up by a strong point, Lt. Ingram, without hesitation, dashed out and rushed the post at the head of his men, capturing nine machine guns and killing 42 enemy after stubborn resistance.

Later, when the company had suffered severe casualties from enemy posts, and many leaders had fallen, he at once took control of the situation, rallied his men under intense fire, and led them forward. He himself rushed the first post, shot six of the enemy, and captured a machine gun, thus overcoming serious resistance.

On two subsequent occasions he again displayed great dash and resource in the capture of enemy posts, inflicting many casualties and taking 62 prisoners.

Throughout the whole day he showed the most inspiring example of courage and leadership, and freely exposed himself regardless of danger.}}

Ingram was promoted to [[lieutenant]] on 24 October,&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB&quot;/&gt; and was training away from the frontline with his battalion when the [[Armistice]] was signed on 11 November 1918; thus ending the war. On 25 February 1919, Ingram was decorated with his Victoria Cross by [[George V of the United Kingdom|King George V]] in the ballroom of [[Buckingham Palace]].&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs98&quot;/&gt; Boarding a troopship bound for Australia soon after, he arrived in Melbourne on 5 March and was discharged from the Australian Imperial Force on 2 June.&lt;ref name=&quot;AF&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AIF&quot;/&gt;

==Later life==
[[File:VC Anzac Day 1927 P02349.005.JPG|thumb|alt=Lines of men in rows of four wearing military uniforms or suits and military medals.|right|250px|A group of Victoria Cross recipients lined up to march in the 1927 Melbourne [[Anzac Day]] march. Ingram is front row, second from left.]]
Following his discharge, Ingram re-settled in Melbourne and gained employment as a general foreman with ''E. A. &amp; Frank Watts Pty Ltd'', building contractors. In 1926, Ingram's marriage with his wife Jane was dissolved upon his instigation on the grounds of desertion on her behalf. On 10 February the following year, he married Lillian Wakeling (née Hart), a widow, at the Methodist parsonage, [[Malvern, Victoria|Malvern]];&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB&quot;/&gt; the pair were later to have one son.&lt;ref name=&quot;AF&quot;/&gt;

On 11 November 1929, Ingram attended the Victoria Dinner for recipients of the Victoria Cross in Melbourne. Following the completion of Melbourne's [[Shrine of Remembrance]] in 1935, Ingram was chosen as a member of its permanent guard. There had been two hundred and fifty applications for the position, of which only fourteen were appointed; Ingram being one of the earliest.&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs99&quot;/&gt; Following the outbreak of the [[Second World War]], Ingram once again volunteered his services and enlisted in the militia on 17 November 1939.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ww2roll.gov.au/Veteran.aspx?serviceId=A&amp;veteranId=578474|title=Ingram, George Mawby|accessdate=11 November 2008|work=World War II Nominal Roll|publisher=Commonwealth of Australia}}&lt;/ref&gt; Posted to a unit in the [[Royal Australian Engineers]], he achieved the rank of [[Captain (British Army and Royal Marines)|captain]] before being placed on the Retired List on 6 May 1944.&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs99&quot;/&gt;

[[File:George ingram VC medals.jpg|thumb|left|225px|George Ingram's medals at the Australian War Memorial, Canberra.]]

Ingram's wife Lillian died in May 1951, and on 24 December of the same year he married another widow, Myrtle Lydia Thomas (née Cornell), in a ceremony at Brunswick Methodist Church;&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB&quot;/&gt; the couple later had a son, Alex.&lt;ref name=&quot;AF&quot;/&gt; In 1954, Ingram attended the dedication of the Shrine of Remembrance by [[Elizabeth II of the United Kingdom|Queen Elizabeth II]] and the [[Prince Philip, Duke of Edinburgh|Duke of Edinburgh]] on 28 February following an expansion on the monument to encompass Australia's contributions to the Second World War. Two years later, he joined the Australian contingent of Victoria Cross recipients who attended the parade in London's [[Hyde Park, London|Hyde Park]] to commemorate the centenary of the institution of the Victoria Cross. On 30 June 1961, Ingram died of [[Coronary disease|coronary vascular disease]] at his home in [[Hastings, Victoria]], and was buried at Frankston Cemetery. He is commemorated by a street name in [[Canberra]].&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs99&quot;/&gt;

On 27 May 2008, the Victoria Cross, Military Medal and campaign medals awarded to Ingram were sold at auction by [[Sotheby's]] of Melbourne for an approximate hammer price of [[Australian dollar|A$]]383,760. The purchaser of the medals is unknown, but indicated that the Victoria Cross would be donated to the [[Australian War Memorial]] in Canberra.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.victoriacross.org.uk/bbingram.htm|title=Medals awarded to Captain George Ingram sold at auction|publisher=victoriacross.org.uk|accessdate=10 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; This subsequently took place, and Ingram's Victoria Cross is currently on display along with his other medals in the Memorial's Hall of Valour.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/virtualtour/valour.asp|title=Hall of Valour: Victoria Crosses at the Memorial|accessdate=11 November 2008|publisher=Australian War Memorial}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
* {{Cite book|last=Gliddon|first=Gerald|year=2000|title=The Final Days 1918|series=[[VCs of the First World War]]|publication-place=Sparkford, England|publisher=Sutton Publishing|isbn=0-7509-2485-3|ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book|last=Staunton|first=Anthony|year=2005|title=Victoria Cross: Australia's Finest and the Battles they Fought|publication-place=Prahran, Victoria, Australia|publisher=Hardie Grant Books|isbn=1-74066-288-1|ref=harv}}

==External links==
* {{cite web|url=http://www.diggerhistory.info/pages-vc/ingram-vc.htm|title=Ingram VC|accessdate=2 November 2008|work=VC Recipients|publisher=Diggerhistory.info}}

{{Good article}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2011}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Ingram, George Morby}}
[[Category:1889 births]]
[[Category:1961 deaths]]
[[Category:Australian Army officers]]
[[Category:Australian carpenters]]
[[Category:Australian military personnel of World War II]]
[[Category:Australian World War I recipients of the Victoria Cross]]
[[Category:Military personnel from Melbourne]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Military Medal]]</text>
      <sha1>i07ujstvubcctvpnyie8qu67kaj590u</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
