<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>George Kistiakowsky</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1074761</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750189642</id>
      <parentid>750189403</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-18T06:48:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>DadaNeem</username>
        <id>2715142</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* External links */ imdb</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="33316">{{Infobox scientist
|name              = George Kistiakowsky
|image             = Kistiakowsky.jpg
|image_size        =
|alt               = Head and shoulders of middle-aged man in suit and tie
|caption           = George Kistiakowsky
|birth_date        = {{Birth date|1900|11|18}}
|birth_place       = [[Kiev]], [[Russian Empire]]
|death_date        = {{death date and age|1982|12|7|1900|11|18}}
|death_place       = [[Cambridge]], [[Massachusetts]], United States
|residence         =
|citizenship       = [[United States|American]]
|nationality       = [[Ukrainian-American]]
|ethnicity         =
|field             = [[Physical Chemistry]]
|work_institutions = {{Plainlist|
* [[Harvard University]]
* [[Los Alamos Laboratory]]
}}
|alma_mater        = [[University of Berlin]]
|doctoral_advisor  = [[Max Bodenstein]]
|doctoral_students = {{Plainlist|
* [[Herbert S. Gutowsky]]
* [[Bruce H. Mahan]]
}}
|known_for         = {{Plainlist|
* [[Explosive forming]]
* [[Manhattan Project]]
}}
|author_abbrev_bot =
|author_abbrev_zoo =
|influences        =
|influenced        =
|prizes            = {{Plainlist|
* [[Department of the Air Force Decoration for Exceptional Civilian Service]]
* [[Medal for Merit]]
* [[Medal of Freedom]]
* [[National Medal of Science]]
* [[Priestley Medal]] (1972)
* [[Franklin Medal]]
* [[Willard Gibbs Award]] (1960)
}}
|signature         = Kistiakowsky signature.png
}}

'''George Bogdanovich Kistiakowsky''' (November 18, 1900&amp;nbsp;– December 7, 1982) ({{lang-uk|Георгій Богданович Кістяківський}}, {{lang-ru|Георгий Богданович Кистяковский}}) was a [[Ukrainian-American]] [[physical chemistry]] professor at [[Harvard]] who participated in the [[Manhattan Project]] and later served as President [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]]'s [[President's Science Advisory Committee|Science Advisor]].

Born in [[Kiev]] in the old [[Russian Empire]], Kistiakowsky fled his homeland during the [[Russian Civil War]]. He made his way to Germany, where he earned his [[PhD]] in physical chemistry under the supervision of [[Max Bodenstein]] at the [[University of Berlin]]. He emigrated to the United States in 1926, where he joined the faculty of [[Harvard University]] in 1930, and became a citizen in 1933.

During World War II, Kistiakowsky was the head of the [[National Defense Research Committee]] (NDRC) section responsible for the development of explosives, and the technical director of the Explosives Research Laboratory (ERL), where he oversaw the development of new explosives, including [[RDX]] and [[HMX]]. He was involved in research into the [[hydrodynamic]] theory of explosions, and the development of [[shaped charge]]s. In October 1943, he was brought into the Manhattan Project as a consultant. He was soon placed in charge of X Division, which was responsible for the development of the [[explosive lens]]es necessary for an [[implosion-type nuclear weapon]]. In July 1945, he watched as the first one was detonated in the [[Trinity test]]. A few weeks later another [[Fat Man]] implosion-type weapon was dropped on [[Nagasaki]].

From 1962 to 1965, Kistiakowsky chaired the [[National Academy of Sciences]]'s [[Committee on Science, Engineering, and Public Policy]] (COSEPUP), and was its vice president from 1965 to 1973. He severed his connections with the government in protest against the [[Vietnam War|war in Vietnam]], and became active in an antiwar organization, the [[Council for a Livable World]], becoming its chairman in 1977.

== Early life ==
George Bogdanovich Kistiakowsky was born in [[Kiev]], in the [[Kiev Governorate]] of the [[Russian Empire]] (now part of [[Ukraine]]), on November 18, 1900.{{sfn|Dainton|1985|pp=379–380}}  George's grandfather Oleksandr Fedorovych Kistiakovsky was a professor of law and an attorney of the Russian Empire who specialized in [[criminal law]].{{sfn|Heuman|1998|pp=7–8, 213}} His father Bogdan Kistiakovsky was Professor of Legal Philosophy at the University of Kiev,{{sfn|Dainton|1985|pp=379–380}} and was  elected a member of the [[National Academy of Sciences of Ukraine]] in 1919.{{sfn|Heuman|1998|pp=37–38}} Kistiakowsky's mother was Maria Berendshtam, and he had a brother, Alexander.{{sfn|Dainton|1985|pp=379–380}} George's uncle Ihor Kistiakovsky was the Minister of Internal Affairs of the [[Ukrainian State]].{{sfn|Heuman|1998|pp=37–38}}

Kistiakowsky attended private schools in Kiev and [[Moscow]] until the [[Russian Revolution of 1917|Russian Revolution]] broke out in 1917. He then joined the anti-Communist [[White Army]]. In 1920 he escaped from Russia in a commandeered French ship. After spending time in Turkey and [[Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes|Yugoslavia]], he made his way to [[Weimar Republic|Germany]], where he enrolled at the [[University of Berlin]] later that year.{{sfn|Dainton|1985|pp=379–380}} In 1925, he earned his [[PhD]] in [[physical chemistry]] under the supervision of [[Max Bodenstein]], writing his thesis on the [[photochemical]] decomposition of [[chlorine monoxide]] and [[ozone]]. He then became Bodenstein's graduate assistant.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harvard&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://oasis.lib.harvard.edu/oasis/deliver/~hua08001 |title=Kistiakowsky, George B. (George Bogdan), 1900– Papers of George B. Kistiakowsky : an inventory |publisher=[[Harvard University]] |accessdate=7 May 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Dainton|1985|pp=379–380}} His first two published papers were elaborations of his thesis, co-written with Bodenstein.{{sfn|Dainton|1985|p=401}}

In 1926, Kistiakowsky traveled to the United States as an [[International Education Board]] fellow. [[Hugh Stott Taylor]], another student of Bodenstein,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://academictree.org/chemistry/tree.php?pid=52121&amp;pnodecount=4&amp;cnodecount=2&amp;fontsize=3 |title=Chemistry Tree&amp;nbsp;— Max Ernst August Bodenstein Family Tree |publisher=Chemistry Tree |accessdate=7 May 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; accepted  Bodenstein's assessment of Kistiakowsky, and gave him a place at [[Princeton University]]. That year, Kistiakowsky married a Swedish woman, Hildegard Moebius.{{sfn|Dainton|1985|pp=379–380}} In 1928, they had a daughter, [[Vera Kistiakowsky|Vera]], who later became a [[Professor Emerita]] of Physics at [[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Vera&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www2.cambridgema.gov/historic/cwhp/bios_k.html |title=Vera   Kistiakowsky |publisher=Cambridge Women's Heritage Project |accessdate=7 May 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; When Kistiakowsky's two-year fellowship ran out in 1927, he received a Research Associate and DuPont Fellowship. On October 25, 1928, he became an associate professor at Princeton.&lt;ref name=&quot;Harvard&quot; /&gt;{{sfn|Dainton|1985|pp=379–380}} Taylor and Kistiakowsky  published a series of papers together.{{sfn|Dainton|1985|p=401}} Encouraged by Taylor, Kistiakowsky also published an [[American Chemical Society]] [[monograph]] on photochemical processes.{{sfn|Dainton|1985|p=401}}{{sfn|Dainton|1985|pp=379–380}}

In 1930, Kistiakowsky joined the faculty of [[Harvard University]], an affiliation that continued throughout his career. At Harvard, his research interests were in [[thermodynamics]], [[spectroscopy]], and [[chemical kinetics]]. He became increasingly involved in consulting for the government and industry. He became an associate professor again, this time at Harvard in 1933. That year he also became an American citizen. In 1938, he became the Abbott and James Lawrence Professor of Chemistry.{{sfn|Dainton|1985|p=382}}

== World War II ==

=== National Defense Research Committee ===
[[File:George Kistiakowsky ID badge.png|thumb|right|Kistiakowsky's Los Alamos wartime security badge|alt=Head and shoulders mug shot of middle-aged man in suit and tie. Lettering reads &quot;C 16&quot;]]
Foreseeing an expanded role for science in [[World War II]], which the United States had not yet joined, [[President of the United States|President]] [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]] created the [[National Defense Research Committee]] (NDRC) on June 27, 1940, with [[Vannevar Bush]] as its chairman. [[James B. Conant]], the President  of Harvard,{{sfn|Stewart|1948|p=7}} was appointed head of Division B, which was responsible for bombs, fuels, gases and chemicals. He appointed Kistiakowsky to head its Section A-1, which was concerned with explosives.{{sfn|Stewart|1948|p=10}} In June 1941, the NDRC was absorbed into the [[Office of Scientific Research and Development]] (OSRD). Bush became Chairman of the OSRD, Conant succeeded him as Chairman of the NDRC, and Kistiakowsky became head of Section B.{{sfn|Stewart|1948|pp=52–54}} In a reorganization in December 1942, Division B was broken up, and he became head of Division 8, which was responsible for explosives and propellants, remaining in this position until February 1944.{{sfn|Stewart|1948|p=88}}

Kistiakowsky was unhappy with the state of American knowledge of explosives and propellants.{{sfn|Dainton|1985|p=383}} Conant established the Explosives Research Laboratory (ERL) near the [[Experimental Mine, U.S. Bureau of Mines|laboratories]] of the [[United States Bureau of Mines|Bureau of Mines]] in [[Bruceton, Pennsylvania]] in October 1940,{{sfn|Noyes|1948|p=25}} and Kistiakowsky initially supervised its activities, making occasional visits; but Conant did not formally appoint him as its Technical Director until the spring of 1941.{{sfn|Noyes|1948|p=27}} Although initially hampered by a shortage of facilities, the ERL grew from five staff in 1941 to a wartime peak of 162 full-time laboratory staff in 1945.{{sfn|Noyes|1948|p=28}} An important field of research was [[RDX]]. This powerful explosive had been developed by the British before the war. The challenge was to develop an industrial process that could produce it on a large scale. RDX was also mixed with TNT to produce Composition B, which was widely used in various munitions, and [[torpex]], which was used in torpedoes and depth charges. Pilot plants were in operation by May 1942, and large-scale production followed in 1943.{{sfn|Noyes|1948|pp=36–42}}

In response to a special request for an explosive that could be smuggled through Japanese checkpoints by Chinese guerrillas, Kistakowsky mixed [[HMX]], a non-toxic explosive produced as a by-product of the RDX process, with flour to create &quot;[[Aunt Jemima]]&quot;, after a brand of pancake flour. This was an edible explosive, which could pass for regular flour, and even be used in cooking.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://www.military-history.org/articles/back-to-the-drawing-board-aunt-jemima.htm |journal=Military History Monthly |title=Back to the Drawing Board&amp;nbsp;– Aunt Jemima |date=June 12, 2012  |first=George |last=Clode |accessdate=May 4, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Noyes|1948|p=51}}

In addition to research into synthetic explosives like RDX and HMX, the ERL investigated the properties of [[detonation]]s and [[shock wave]]s. This was initiated as a pure research project, without obvious or immediate applications. Kistiakowsky visited England in 1941 and again in 1942, where he met with British experts, including [[William Penney]] and [[G. I. Taylor|Geoffrey Taylor]]. When Kistiakowsky and [[Edgar Bright Wilson, Jr.]], surveyed the existing state of knowledge, they found several areas that warranted further investigation. Kistiakowsky began to look into the [[Chapman–Jouguet condition|Chapman–Jouguet model]],{{sfn|Noyes|1948|pp=58–64}} which describes the way the [[shock wave]] created by a detonation propagates.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Chapman |first=David Leonard |authorlink=David Chapman (scientist)|title=On the Rate of Explosion in Gases |journal=Philosophical Magazine |location=London |series=Series 5 |volume=47 |issue=284 |pages=90–104 |date=January 1899 |issn=1941-5982 |lccn=sn86025845 |doi=10.1080/14786449908621243 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

At this time, the efficacy of the Chapman–Jouguet model was still in doubt, and it was the subject of studies by [[John von Neumann]] at the [[Princeton Institute for Advanced Study]]. Kistiakowsky realized that the deviations from [[hydrodynamic]] theory were the result of the speed of the chemical reactions themselves. To control the reaction, calculations down to the microsecond level were needed.{{sfn|Noyes|1948|pp=58–64}} Section 8 was drawn into the investigation of [[shaped charge]]s, whose mechanism was explained by Taylor and [[James L. Tuck|James Tuck]] in 1943.{{sfn|Noyes|1948|p=73}}

=== Manhattan Project ===
At the [[Manhattan Project]]'s [[Los Alamos Laboratory]], research into [[Implosion (mechanical process)|implosion]] had been proceeding under [[Seth Neddermeyer]], but his division had worked with cylinders and small charges, and had only produced objects that looked like rocks. Their research was accorded a low priority, owing to expectations that a [[gun-type nuclear weapon]] design would work for both [[uranium-235]] and [[plutonium]], and implosion technology would not be required.{{sfn|Hoddeson|Henriksen|Meade|Westfall|1993|pp=130–133}}

In September 1943, the Los Alamos Laboratory's director, [[Robert Oppenheimer]], arranged for von Neumann to visit Los Alamos and investigate implosion with a fresh set of eyes. After reviewing Neddermeyer's studies, and discussing the matter with [[Edward Teller]], von Neumann suggested the use of high explosive in [[shaped charge]]s to implode a sphere, which he showed could not only result in a faster assembly of [[fissile]] material than was possible with the gun method, but which could greatly reduce the amount of material required. The prospect of more efficient nuclear weapons impressed Oppenheimer, Teller and [[Hans Bethe]], but they decided that an expert on explosives was required. Kistiakowsky's name was immediately suggested, and he was brought into the project as a consultant in October 1943.{{sfn|Hoddeson|Henriksen|Meade|Westfall|1993|pp=130–133}}

[[File:Implosion nuclear weapon design - explosive lenses.svg|left|thumb|250px|In an implosion-type nuclear weapon, polygonal [[explosive lens]]es are arranged around the spherical [[Pit (nuclear weapon)|pit]].|alt=Cut away diagram of soccer ball like arrangement, with an inner and an outer ball.]]
Kistiakowsky was initially reluctant to come, &quot;partly because&quot;, he later explained, &quot;I didn't think the bomb would be ready in time and I was interested in helping to win the war&quot;.{{sfn|Hoddeson|Henriksen|Meade|Westfall|1993|p=137}} At Los Alamos, he began reorganizing the implosion effort. He introduced techniques such as photography and X-Rays to study the behavior of shaped charges. The former had been extensively employed by the ERL, while the latter had been described in papers by Tuck, who also suggested using three-dimensional [[explosive lens]]es. As with other aspects of the Manhattan Project, research into explosive lenses followed multiple lines of inquiry simultaneously because, as Kistiakowsky noted, it was &quot;impossible to predict which of these basic techniques will be the more successful.&quot;{{sfn|Hoddeson|Henriksen|Meade|Westfall|1993|p=137}}

Kistiakowsky brought with him to Los Alamos a detailed knowledge of all the studies into shaped charges, of explosives like Composition B, and of the procedures used at the ERL in 1942 and 1943. Increasingly, the ERL itself would be drawn into the implosion effort; its deputy director Duncan MacDougall also took charge of the Manhattan Project's Project Q.{{sfn|Hoddeson|Henriksen|Meade|Westfall|1993|p=166}} Kistiakowsky replaced Neddermeyer as head of E (for explosives) Division in February 1944.{{sfn|Hoddeson|Henriksen|Meade|Westfall|1993|pp=130–133}}

The implosion program acquired a new urgency after [[Emilio Segrè]]'s group at Los Alamos verified that plutonium produced in the [[nuclear reactor]]s contained [[plutonium-240]], which made it unsuitable for use in a gun-type weapon.{{sfn|Hoddeson|Henriksen|Meade|Westfall|1993|pp=236–240}}  A series of crisis meetings in July 1944 concluded that the only prospect for a working plutonium weapon was implosion. In August, Oppenheimer reorganized the entire laboratory to concentrate on it. A new explosives group, X Division, was created under Kistiakowsky to develop the lenses.{{sfn|Hoddeson|Henriksen|Meade|Westfall|1993|pp=241–247}}

Under Kistiakowsky's leadership, X-Division designed the complex explosive lenses needed to compress the fissile plutonium [[Pit (nuclear weapon)|pit]]. These employed two explosives with significantly different [[explosive velocity|velocities of detonation]] in order to produce the required wave form. Kistiakowsky chose [[Baratol]] for the slow explosive. After experimenting with various fast explosives, X-Division settled on Composition B. Work on molding the explosives into the right shape continued into 1945. The lenses needed to be flawless, and techniques for casting Composition B and Baratol had to be developed. The ERL managed to accomplish this by devising a procedure for preparing Baratol in a form that was easy to cast.{{sfn|Hoddeson|Henriksen|Meade|Westfall|1993|pp=294–299}} In March 1945, Kistiakowsky became part of the Cowpuncher Committee, so-called because it rode herd on the implosion effort.{{sfn|Hoddeson|Henriksen|Meade|Westfall|1993|p=316}} On July 16, 1945, Kistiakowsky watched as the first device was detonated in the [[Trinity test]].{{sfn|Dainton|1985|p=384}} A few weeks later a [[Fat Man]] implosion-type nuclear weapon was dropped on [[Nagasaki]].{{sfn|Hoddeson|Henriksen|Meade|Westfall|1993|pp=394–396}}

Along with his work on implosion, Kistiakowsky contributed to skiing in Los Alamos by using rings of explosives to fell trees for a ski slope&amp;nbsp;— leading to the establishment of Sawyer's Hill Ski Tow Association.{{sfn|Gibson|Michnovicz|Michnovicz|2005|p=78}} He divorced Hildegard in 1942 and married Irma E. Shuler in 1945. They were divorced in 1962, and he married Elaine Mahoney.&lt;ref name=&quot;imdb&quot;&gt;{{IMDb name|1687977|George Kistiakowsky|section=bio}}. Accessed May 10, 2013&lt;/ref&gt;

== White House service ==
In 1957, during the Eisenhower Administration, Kistiakowsky was appointed to the [[President's Science Advisory Committee]], and succeeded [[James R. Killian]] as chairman in 1959. He directed the [[Office of Science and Technology Policy]] from 1959 to 1961, when he was succeeded by [[Jerome B. Wiesner]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.whitehouse.gov/administration/eop/ostp/about/leadershipstaff/previous |accessdate=May 10, 2013 |title=Previous Science Advisors |publisher=[[Office of Science and Technology Policy]]}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Atlas missile launch.jpg|right|thumb|upright| [[Atlas (rocket family)|Atlas]], a first-generation [[intercontinental ballistic missile]]|alt=A rocket takes off from the launch pad. ]]
In 1958, Kistiakowsky suggested to President Eisenhower that inspection of foreign military facilities was not sufficient to control their nuclear weapons. He cited the difficulty in monitoring missile submarines, and proposed that the arms control strategy focus on disarmament rather than inspections.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
  | title = Space Policy Project (summary of Foreign Relations of the US, text not online)
  | year = 1961
  | journal = Foreign Relations of the United States 1958–1960
  | volume = National Security Policy; Arms Control and Disarmament, Volume III
  | place = Washington, DC
  | publisher = US Department of State (summary by Federation of American Scientists)
  | url = https://fas.org/spp/starwars/offdocs/ike/index.html
  | id = FRUS58
  | ref = harv
  | postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt; }}&lt;/ref&gt; In January 1960, as part of arms control planning and negotiation, he suggested the &quot;threshold concept&quot;. Under this proposal, all nuclear tests above the level of seismic detection technology would be forbidden. After such an agreement, the US and USSR would work jointly to improve detection technology, revising the permissible test yield downward as techniques improved. This example of the &quot;national means of technical verification&quot;, a euphemism for sensitive intelligence collection used in arms control, would provide safeguards, without raising the on-site inspection requirement to a level unacceptable to the Soviets. The US introduced the threshold concept to the Soviets at the Geneva arms control conference in January 1960 and the Soviets, in March, responded favorably, suggesting a threshold of a given seismic magnitude. Talks broke down as a result of the [[U-2 Crisis of 1960]] in May.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gwu.edu/~nsarchiv/NSAEBB/NSAEBB94/ |title=The Making of the Limited Test Ban Treaty, 1958–1963 |publisher=[[George Washington University]] |editor-first=William     |editor-last=Burr  |editor2-first=Hector L. |editor2-last=Montford |accessdate=May 10, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At the same time as the early nuclear arms control work, the [[Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff]], General [[Nathan F. Twining]], sent a memorandum,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last = Twining  | first = Nathan F.  | authorlink = Nathan F. Twining
  | title = Document 2: J.C.S. 2056/131, Notes by the Secretaries to the Joint Chiefs of Staff, enclosing memorandum from JCS Chairman Nathan Twining to Secretary of Defense, &quot;Target Coordination and Associated Problems,&quot;
  | work = The Creation of SIOP-62: More Evidence on the Origins of Overkill National Security Archive Electronic Briefing Book No. 130
  | publisher = George Washington University National Security Archive
  | date = 20 August 1959
  | url = http://www.gwu.edu/~nsarchiv/NSAEBB/NSAEBB130/SIOP-2.pdf
  |format=PDF| accessdate = September 22, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; in August 1959, to the [[Secretary of Defense]], [[Neil McElroy]], which suggested that the [[Strategic Air Command]] (SAC) formally be assigned responsibility to prepare the national nuclear target list, and a single plan for nuclear operations. Up to that point, the Army, Navy, and Air Force had done their own target planning. This had led to the same objectives being targeted multiple times by the different services. The separate service plans were not mutually supporting as in, for example, the Navy destroying an air defense facility on the route of an Air Force bomber going to a deeper target. While Twining had sent the memo to McElroy, the members of the [[Joint Chiefs of Staff]] disagreed on the policy during early 1960.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last = Twining  | first = Nathan F. |authorlink= Nathan F. Twining
  | title = Document 3A: JCS 2056/143, Note by the Secretaries to the Joint Chiefs of Staff, 5 October 1959, enclosing Memorandum for the Joint Chiefs of Staff, &quot;Target Coordination and Associated Problems,&quot;
  | work = The Creation of SIOP-62: More Evidence on the Origins of Overkill National Security Archive Electronic Briefing Book No. 130
  | publisher = George Washington University National Security Archive
  | date = 5 October 1959
  | url = http://www.gwu.edu/~nsarchiv/NSAEBB/NSAEBB130/SIOP-3A.pdf
  |format=PDF| accessdate = September 22, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
  | last = Burke  | first = Arleigh |authorlink=Arleigh Burke
  | title = Document 3B: attached memorandum from Chief of Naval Operations
  | work = The Creation of SIOP-62: More Evidence on the Origins of Overkill National Security Archive Electronic Briefing Book No. 130
  | publisher = George Washington University National Security Archive
  | date = 30 September 1959
  | url = http://www.gwu.edu/~nsarchiv/NSAEBB/NSAEBB130/SIOP-3A.pdf
  |format=PDF| accessdate = September 22, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Thomas Sovereign Gates, Jr.|Thomas Gates]], who succeeded McElroy, asked [[President]] [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]] to decide the policy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal
  | last = McKinzie  | first = Matthew G.
  | last2 = Cochran  | first2 = Thomas B.
  | first3= Robert S. |last3 = Norris
  | first4 = William M. |last4 = Arkin
  | title = The U.S. Nuclear War Plan: A Time for Change
  | place=
  | publisher = National Resources Defense Council
  | year = 2001
  | location =
  | volume = Chapter Two: The Single Integrated Operational Plan and U.S. Nuclear Forces
  | url = http://holtz.org/Library/Social%20Science/Political%20Science/US%20Nuclear%20War%20Plan%20-%20NRDC%202001.pdf
  | format=PDF
  | ref = harv
  | postscript = &lt;!--None--&gt;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Eisenhower said he would not &quot;leave his successor with the monstrosity&quot; of the uncoordinated and un-integrated forces that then existed. In early November 1960, he sent Kistiakowsky to SAC Headquarters in Omaha to evaluate its war plans. Initially, Kistiakowsky was not given access, and Eisenhower sent him back, with a much stronger set of orders for SAC officers to cooperate. Kistiaknowsky's report, presented on November 29, described uncoordinated plans with huge numbers of targets, many of which would be attacked by multiple forces, resulting in overkill. Eisenhower was shocked by the plans, and focused not just on the creation of the [[Single Integrated Operational Plan]] (SIOP), but on the entire process of picking targets, generating requirements, and planning for nuclear war operations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.gwu.edu/~nsarchiv/NSAEBB/NSAEBB130/ |title=The Creation of SIOP-62 More Evidence on the Origins of Overkill |publisher=[[George Washington University]] |editor-first=William |editor-last=Burr  |accessdate=May 10, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Later life ==
Between his work for the Manhattan Project and his White House service, and again after he left the White House, Kistiakowsky was a professor of physical chemistry at Harvard. When asked to teach a freshmen class in 1957, he turned to [[Hubert Alyea]], whose lecture style had impressed him. Alyea sent him some 700 {{convert|4|by|6|in|cm|1|adj=on}} [[index card]]s containing details of lecture demonstrations. Aside from the cards, Kistiakowsky  never prepared the demonstrations. He later recalled:{{quote|I didn't think that was giving mother Nature a sporting chance. I would come into the lecture hall, glance at the chemicals and pile of cards and announce to the students &quot;let's see what Alyea has for us today&quot;. I never used a text book, only your cards. I would glance at the instructions and carry out the experiment. If it worked we would bless you and pass on to the next demonstration. If it didn't work we would curse you, and spend the rest of the lecture trying to make it work.{{sfn|Dainton|1985|p=382}} }} He retired from Harvard as professor emeritus in 1972.&lt;ref name=&quot;LANL&quot; /&gt;

From 1962 to 1965, Kistiakowsky chaired the National Academy of Science's [[Committee on Science, Engineering, and Public Policy]] (COSEPUP),&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web  | title = Origins of COSEPUP  | publisher = National Academy of Sciences |url = http://www7.nationalacademies.org/cosepup/About%20COSEPUP.html  | accessdate = September 22, 2007 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20070423030409/http://www7.nationalacademies.org/cosepup/About+COSEPUP.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = April 23, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; and was its vice president from 1965 to 1973.{{sfn|Dainton|1985|p=386}} He received several awards over the years, including the [[Department of the Air Force Decoration for Exceptional Civilian Service]] in 1957. He was awarded the [[Medal for Merit]] by President Truman, the [[Medal of Freedom]] by President Eisenhower in 1961, and the [[National Medal of Science]] by President [[Lyndon Johnson]] in 1967. He was also a recipient of the [[Priestley Medal]] from the American Chemical Society in 1972 and the [[Franklin Medal]] from Harvard.{{sfn|Dainton|1985|p=400}}&lt;ref name=&quot;BAS&quot; /&gt;

In later years, Kistiakowsky was active in an antiwar organization, the [[Council for a Livable World]]. He severed his connections with the government in protest against the US involvement in the [[Vietnam War]]. In 1977, he assumed the chairmanship of the Council, campaigning against nuclear proliferation.&lt;ref name=&quot;LANL&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.lanl.gov/history/people/G_Kistiakowsky.shtml |title=George B. Kistiakowsky |publisher=[[Los Alamos National Laboratory]] |accessdate=May 9, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; He died of cancer in [[Cambridge, Massachusetts]], on December 17, 1982.&lt;ref name=&quot;BAS&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |journal=[[Bulletin of Atomic Scientists]] |title=George B. Kistiakowsky (1900–1982) |date=April 1983 |volume=39 |issue=4 |last=Rathjens |first=George |pages=2–3 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=3QUAAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA2&amp;lpg=PA2&amp;dq=official+site+of+the+medal+of+freedom+-+kistiakowsky#v=onepage&amp;q=official%20site%20of%20the%20medal%20of%20freedom%20-%20kistiakowsky&amp;f=false |accessdate=May 10, 2013 }}&lt;/ref&gt; His body was cremated, and his ashes scattered near his summer home on [[Cape Cod, Massachusetts]].&lt;ref name=&quot;imdb&quot; /&gt; His papers are in the Harvard University archives.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://oasis.lib.harvard.edu/oasis/deliver/~hua08001 |title=Kistiakowsky, George B. (George Bogdan), 1900– Papers of George B. Kistiakowsky: an inventory. Harvard University Archives |publisher=Harvard University  |accessdate=May 9, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Notes ==
{{reflist |30em}}

== References ==
* {{Cite journal | last1 = Dainton | first1 = F. | authorlink = Frederick Dainton, Baron Dainton| doi = 10.1098/rsbm.1985.0013 | title = George Bogdan Kistiakowsky. 18 November 1900-7 December 1982 | journal = [[Biographical Memoirs of Fellows of the Royal Society]] | volume = 31 | pages = 376–326 | year = 1985| jstor = 769930 | pmid =  | pmc =| ref = harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Gibson |first=Toni Michnovicz |first2=Jon |last2=Michnovicz |first3=John |last3=Michnovicz |last-author-amp=yes|year=2005 |title=Los Alamos: 1944–1947 |location=Charleston, South Carolina |publisher=Arcadia |isbn=978-0-7385-2973-8 |oclc=59715051 |ref=harv }}
* {{cite book |last=Heuman |first=Susan Eva |year=1998 |title=Kistiakovsky: The Struggle for National and Constitutional Rights in the Last Years of Tsarism |location=Cambridge, Massachusetts |publisher=Distributed by Harvard University Press for the Harvard Ukrainian Research Institute |isbn=978-0-916458-61-4  |oclc=38853810 |ref=harv }}
* {{cite book |last=Hoddeson |first=Lillian |first2=Paul W. |last2=Henriksen |first3=Roger A. |last3=Meade |first4=Catherine L. |last4=Westfall |last-author-amp=yes|title=Critical Assembly: A Technical History of Los Alamos During the Oppenheimer Years, 1943–1945 |location=New York|publisher=Cambridge University Press |year=1993 |isbn=0-521-44132-3|oclc=26764320|ref=harv }}
*{{cite book |editor-last=Noyes |editor-first=W. Albert |year=1948 |title=Chemistry, a History of the Chemistry Components of the National Defense Research Committee, 1940–1946 |location=Boston |publisher=Little, Brown |url=http://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015014208352?urlappend=%3Bseq=53 |accessdate=May 9, 2013 |oclc=14669626 |ref=harv }}
* {{cite book |last=Stewart |first=Irvin |url=https://archive.org/details/organizingscient00stew |accessdate= April 1, 2012 |title=Organizing Scientific Research for War: The Administrative History of the Office of Scientific Research and Development |location=Boston |publisher=Little, Brown and Company |year=1948 |oclc=500138898 |ref=harv }}

== Further reading ==
* Lawrence Badash, J.O. Hirschfelder &amp; H.P. Broida, eds., Reminiscences of Los Alamos 1943–1945 (Studies in the History of Modern Science), Springer, 1980, ISBN 90-277-1098-8.
* Confessions of a Weaponeer, ''[[PBS Nova]]'', with [[Carl Sagan]] [http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/nova/listseason/14.html pbs.org]

== External links ==
*[http://manhattanprojectvoices.org/oral-histories/george-kistiakowskys-interview 1982 Audio Interview with George Kistiakowsky] by [[Richard Rhodes]] at [[Voices of the Manhattan Project]]
*[http://manhattanprojectvoices.org/oral-histories/vera-kistiakowskys-interview 2014 Video Interview with Vera Kistiakowsky, daughter of George Kistiakowsky], by Cynthia C. Kelly at Voices of the Manhattan Project 
*[http://eisenhower.archives.gov/Research/Finding_Aids/K.html Diary of George B. Kistiakowsky], [[Dwight D. Eisenhower Presidential Library]]
*[http://eisenhower.archives.gov/Research/Finding_Aids/W.html Records of the White House Office of the Special Assistant for Science and Technology, Dwight D. Eisenhower Presidential Library]
* [http://alsos.wlu.edu/qsearch.aspx?browse=people/Kistiakowsky,+George Annotated bibliography for George Kistiakowsky] from the [[Alsos Digital Library for Nuclear Issues]]
* {{imdb character|143708|George Kistiakowski (Character)}}

{{Winners of the National Medal of Science}}
{{Manhattan Project}}
{{Portal bar|Biography|Chemistry|History of science|Nuclear technology|World War II}}
{{Authority control}}

{{good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Kistiakowsky, George}}
[[Category:1900 births]]
[[Category:1982 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Kiev]]
[[Category:People from Kiev Governorate]]
[[Category:American physical chemists]]
[[Category:Manhattan Project people]]
[[Category:National Medal of Science laureates]]
[[Category:Medal for Merit recipients]]
[[Category:Members of the United States National Academy of Sciences]]
[[Category:Office of Science and Technology Policy officials]]
[[Category:Princeton University faculty]]
[[Category:Harvard University faculty]]
[[Category:Foreign Members of the Royal Society]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Medal of Freedom]]
[[Category:American people of Ukrainian descent]]</text>
      <sha1>idoevlcq71nv6hukh1qcrexvhyqyy3s</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
