<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Gia Long</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1101834</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750517910</id>
      <parentid>747808609</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-20T06:45:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Duyet-pho</username>
        <id>4663536</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>remove inaccuracy. photography was still in its infacny in the 1820s. Such a photo in Siam in 1780s would be impossible, and clearly not of Prince Nguyen-Anh</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="60611">{{Infobox royalty
| name            =Gia Long
| title           =[[List of Vietnamese monarchs|Emperor of Vietnam]]
| image           =Emperor Gia Long.jpg
| caption         =
| succession      =Emperor of [[Nguyễn Dynasty]]
| reign           =1802&amp;ndash;1820
| full name       =Nguyễn Phúc Chủng&lt;br&gt;Nguyễn Phúc Noãn&lt;br&gt;Nguyễn Phúc Ánh
| predecessor     =[[Tây Sơn Dynasty]]
| successor       =[[Minh Mạng]]
| succession1      =[[Nguyễn lords|Lord of Nguyễn Clan]]
| reign1           =1777&amp;ndash;1802
| predecessor1     =[[Nguyễn Phúc Dương]]
| successor1       =End of Military Commander
| spouse          =Empress [[Thừa Thiên (empress)|Thừa Thiên]]&lt;br&gt;Empress [[Thuận Thiên (Nguyễn dynasty empress)|Thuận Thiên]]&lt;br&gt;Noble Consort [[Lê Ngọc Bình]]
| issue           =[[Nguyễn Phúc Cảnh|Nguyễn Phúc Cảnh, Crown Prince Anh Duệ]]&lt;br&gt;[[Minh Mạng|Nguyễn Phúc Đảm, Emperor Minh Mạng]]&lt;br&gt;13 other sons and 18 daughters
| house           =[[Nguyễn Dynasty]]
| anthem          =[[Đăng đàn cung]]
| birth_date   =8 February 1762
| death_date   = {{Death date and age|1820|2|3|1762|2|8|df=y}}
| place of burial = [[Thien Tho Tomb]]
| father = [[Nguyễn Phúc Luân]]
| mother = Nguyễn Thị Hoàn
| posthumous name = Khai thiên Hoằng đạo Lập kỷ Thùy thống Thần văn Thánh võ Tuấn đức Long công Chí nhân Đại hiếu '''Cao Hoàng đế'''&lt;br&gt;開天弘道立紀垂統神文聖武俊德隆功至仁大孝'''高皇帝'''
| temple name = Thế Tổ
| era name = Gia Long
| era dates = 1801&amp;ndash;1820
| signature = }}
Emperor '''Gia Long''' (8 February 1762 &amp;ndash; 3 February 1820), born '''Nguyễn Phúc Ánh of Nguyễn clan''', often referred to simply as '''Nguyễn Ánh'''&lt;ref&gt;In this Vietnamese name, the family name is ''Nguyễn'', but is often simplified to ''Nguyen'' in English-language text. According to Vietnamese custom, this person should properly be referred to by the given name ''Ánh'' or ''Anh'' (in English-language text).&lt;/ref&gt;), was the first Emperor of the [[Nguyễn Dynasty]] of [[Vietnam]]. Unifying what is now modern [[Vietnam]] in 1802, he founded the [[Nguyễn Dynasty]], the last of the [[List of Vietnamese dynasties|Vietnamese dynasties]].

A nephew of the last [[Nguyễn lords|Nguyễn lord]] who ruled over southern Vietnam, Nguyễn Ánh was forced into hiding in 1777 as a fifteen-year-old when his family was slain in the [[Tây Sơn]] revolt.  After several changes of fortune in which his loyalists regained and again lost Saigon, he befriended the French [[Catholic Church|Catholic]] priest [[Pigneau de Behaine]]. Pigneau championed his cause to the French government&amp;mdash;and managed to recruit volunteers when this fell through&amp;mdash;to help Nguyễn Ánh regain the throne. From 1789, Nguyễn Ánh was once again in the ascendancy and began his northward march to defeat the Tây Sơn, eventually moving by 1802 to the border with China, which had previously been under the control of the [[Trịnh lords]]. When this was over, he had reunited Vietnam after centuries of internecine feudal warfare with a greater land mass than ever before, stretching from China down to the [[Gulf of Siam]].

Gia Long's rule was noted for its [[Confucianism|Confucian orthodoxy]]. He repealed [[Tây Sơn Dynasty|Tây Sơn rebellion]] and reinstated the classical Confucian education and civil service system. He moved the capital from [[Hanoi]] south to [[Huế]] as the country's populace had also shifted south over the preceding centuries, and built up fortresses and a [[Imperial City, Huế|palace]] in his new capital. Using French expertise, he modernized Vietnam's defensive capabilities. In deference to the assistance of his French friends, he tolerated the activities of Roman Catholic missionaries, something that became increasingly restricted under his successors. Under his rule, Vietnam strengthened its military dominance in Indochina, expelling [[Siam]]ese forces from [[Cambodia]] and turning it into a vassal state.

==Early years==
{{Infobox Chinese
|vie=Gia Long
|hn={{linktext|嘉|隆}}
}}
{{infobox Vietnamese
|title=Birth name
|qn=Nguyễn Phúc Ánh
|hn={{linktext|阮|福|暎}}
}}
Born on 8 February 1762,&lt;ref name=&quot;tdas&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Trần Đức Anh Sơn|year=2004|title=Huế Triều Nguyễn một cái nhìn|publisher=Thuận Hóa Publishing House|page=75}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nguyễn Ánh was the son of [[Nguyễn Phúc Luân]] and [[Nguyen Thi Hoan]]. Luan was the designated heir of [[Nguyễn lords|Lord]] [[Nguyễn Phúc Khoát]] of southern Vietnam. However, a high-ranking [[mandarin (bureaucrat)|mandarin]] named [[Trương Phúc Loan]] changed Khoat's will of succession on his deathbed, and installed Luan's younger brother [[Nguyễn Phúc Thuần]] on the throne in 1765. Luan was jailed and died in the same year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Phan Khoang|year=2001|title=Việt sử xứ Đàng Trong|publisher=Văn Học Publishing House|place=Hanoi|language=Vietnamese| pages=187&amp;ndash;188}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kim, p. 335.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Phan Thuận An|year=2005|title=Quần thể di tích Huế|language=Vietnamese|publisher=Tre Publishing House|page=112}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, Thuan lost his position as lord of southern Vietnam and was killed during the [[Tây Sơn Dynasty|Tây Sơn rebellion]]  led by the brothers [[Nguyễn Nhạc]], [[Nguyễn Huệ]] and Nguyễn Lữ in 1777.&lt;ref&gt;Hall, p. 426.&lt;/ref&gt; Nguyễn Ánh was the most senior member of the ruling family to have survived the Tây Sơn victory, which pushed the Nguyễn from their heartland in central Vietnam, southwards towards [[Saigon]] and into the [[Mekong Delta]] region in the far south.&lt;ref name=&quot;h423&quot;&gt;Hall, p. 423.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;c282&quot;&gt;Cady, p. 282.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;b266&quot;/&gt; Nguyễn Ánh fled to [[Hà Tiên]] on the southern coastal tip of Vietnam, where he met [[Pigneau de Behaine]],&lt;ref name=&quot;m520&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;m7&quot;&gt;McLeod, p. 7.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;k75&quot;&gt;Karnow, p. 75.&lt;/ref&gt; a French priest who became his adviser and played a major part in his rise to power.&lt;ref name=&quot;k75&quot;/&gt; Together, they escaped to the island of Pulo Panjang in the [[Gulf of Siam]].&lt;ref name=&quot;h423&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Buttinger, p. 234.&lt;/ref&gt; Pigneau hoped that by playing a substantial role in a Nguyễn Ánh victory, he would be in position to lever important concessions for the Catholic Church in Vietnam, helping its expansion in South East Asia.&lt;ref name=&quot;m9&quot;&gt;McLeod, p. 9.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Pigneau de Behaine portrait.jpg|thumb|[[Pigneau de Behaine]], the French priest who recruited armies for Nguyễn Ánh during the war against the Tây Sơn.]]
In late 1777, the main part of the Tây Sơn army left Saigon to go north and attack the [[Trịnh lords]], who ruled the other half of Vietnam. Nguyễn Ánh stealthily returned to the mainland, rejoining his supporters and reclaimed the city.&lt;ref&gt;Buttinger, p. 233.&lt;/ref&gt; He was crucially aided by the efforts of [[Đỗ Thanh Nhơn]], who had organized an army for him,&lt;ref name=&quot;h427&quot;&gt;Hall, p. 427.&lt;/ref&gt; which was supplemented by Cambodian mercenaries and Chinese pirates.&lt;ref name=&quot;b235&quot;&gt;Buttinger, p. 235.&lt;/ref&gt; The following year, Nhon expelled further Tây Sơn troops from the surrounding province of [[Gia Định Province|Gia Định]], and inflicted heavy losses on the Tây Sơn naval fleet. Taking advantage of the more favorable situation, Nguyễn Ánh sent a diplomatic mission to [[Siam]] to propose a treaty of friendship. However, this pact was derailed in 1779 when the Cambodians held an uprising against their pro-Siamese leader [[Ang Non]]. Nguyễn Ánh sent Nhon to help the uprising, which saw Ang Non defeated decisively and executed.&lt;ref name=&quot;h427&quot;/&gt;

Nhon returned to Saigon with high honor and concentrated his efforts on improving the Nguyễn navy. In 1780, in an attempt to strengthen his political status, Nguyễn Ánh proclaimed himself Nguyễn vương (''Nguyễn king'' or ''Nguyễn ruler'' in Vietnamese).&lt;ref&gt;Dutton, p. 45.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kim, p. 342.&lt;/ref&gt; Then, in 1781, Nguyễn Ánh sent further forces to prop up the Cambodian regime against Siamese armies who wanted to reassert their control.&lt;ref name=&quot;c282&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;h427&quot;/&gt;  Shortly thereafter, Nguyễn Ánh had Nhon brutally murdered. The reason remains unclear, but it was postulated that he did so because Nhon's fame and military success was overshadowing him. The Tây Sơn brothers reportedly broke out in celebration upon hearing of Nhon's execution, as Nhon was the Nguyễn officer that they feared the most. Nhon's supporters rebelled, weakening the Nguyễn army, and within a few months, the Tây Sơn had recaptured Saigon mainly on the back of naval barrages.&lt;ref name=&quot;h427&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;b235&quot;/&gt; Nguyễn Ánh was forced to flee to Ha Tien, and then onto the island of [[Phú Quốc]]. Meanwhile, some of his forces continued to resist in his absence.&lt;ref name=&quot;h428&quot;&gt;Hall, p. 428.&lt;/ref&gt;

In October 1782, the tide shifted again, when forces led by [[Nguyễn Phúc Mân]], Nguyễn Ánh's younger brother, and [[Châu Văn Tiếp]] drove the Tây Sơn out of Saigon.&lt;ref name=&quot;h428&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kim, p. 323.&lt;/ref&gt; Nguyễn Ánh returned to Saigon, as did Pigneau&lt;ref name=&quot;h428&quot;/&gt; The hold was tenuous, and a counterattack by the Tây Sơn in early 1783 saw a heavy defeat for the Nguyễn, with Nguyen Man killed in battle.&lt;ref name=&quot;c282&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;h428&quot;/&gt; Nguyễn Ánh again fled to Phú Quốc, but this time his hiding place was discovered.&lt;ref name=&quot;h428&quot;/&gt; He managed to escape the pursuing Tây Sơn fleet to [[Koh Rong]] island in the [[Bay of Kompong Som]]. Again, his hideout was discovered and encircled by the rebel fleet. However, a typhoon hit the area, and he managed to break the naval siege and escape to another island amid the confusion.&lt;ref name=&quot;b235&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;h428&quot;/&gt; In early-1784, Nguyễn Ánh went to seek Siamese aid, which was forthcoming, but the extra 20,000 men failed to weaken the Tây Sơn's hold on power.&lt;ref name=&quot;b235&quot;/&gt; This forced Nguyễn Ánh to become a refugee in Siam in 1785.&lt;ref name=&quot;h428&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;c283&quot;&gt;Cady, p. 283.&lt;/ref&gt; To make matters worse, the Tây Sơn regularly raided the rice growing areas of the south during the harvesting season, depriving the Nguyễn of their food supply.&lt;ref name=&quot;m520&quot;&gt;Mantienne, p. 520.&lt;/ref&gt; Nguyễn Ánh eventually came to the conclusion that using Siamese military aid would generate a backlash amongst the populace, due to prevailing Vietnamese hostility towards Siam.&lt;ref name=&quot;m7&quot;/&gt;

==Pigneau and French assistance==
{{main article|French assistance to Nguyễn Ánh}}
[[Image:Prince Canh MEP.jpg|thumb|left|Portrait of [[Prince Cảnh]], the eldest son of Gia Long in France when he was 6 year old, 1787 .]]
Deflated by his situation, Nguyễn Ánh asked Pigneau to appeal for French aid, and allowed Pigneau to take his son [[Nguyễn Phúc Cảnh]] with him as a sign of good faith.&lt;ref name=&quot;m9&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;h428&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;k76&quot;&gt;Karnow, p. 76.&lt;/ref&gt; This came about after Nguyễn Ánh had considered enlisting English, Dutch, Portuguese and Spanish assistance.&lt;ref&gt;Buttinger, pp. 236, 266.&lt;/ref&gt; Pigneau advised against Nguyễn Ánh's original plan to seek Dutch aid from [[Batavia, Dutch East Indies|Batavia]], fearing that the support of the Protestant Dutch would hinder the advancement of Catholicism.&lt;ref name=&quot;m9&quot;/&gt; Pigneau left Vietnam in December,&lt;ref name=&quot;h428&quot;/&gt; arriving in [[Puducherry|Pondicherry]], India in February 1785 with Nguyễn Ánh's royal seal. Nguyễn Ánh had authorized him to make concessions to France in return for military assistance.&lt;ref name=&quot;b236&quot;&gt;Buttinger, p. 236.&lt;/ref&gt; The French administration in Pondicherry, led by acting governor [[Coutenceau des Algrains]], was conservative in outlook and resolutely opposed intervention in southern Vietnam.&lt;ref name=&quot;b236&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;h429&quot;&gt;Hall, p. 429.&lt;/ref&gt; To compound the already complex situation, Pigneau was denounced by Spanish Franciscans in the [[Roman Curia|Vatican]], and he sought to transfer his political mandate to Portuguese forces. The Portuguese had earlier offered Nguyễn Ánh 56 ships to use against the Tây Sơn.&lt;ref name=&quot;b237&quot;&gt;Buttinger, p. 237.&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 1786, after more than 12 months of fruitless lobbying in Pondicherry, [[Governor de Cossigny]] allowed Pigneau to travel back to France to directly ask the royal court for assistance.&lt;ref name=&quot;k76&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;h429&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;m10&quot;&gt;McLeod, p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt; Arriving at the court of [[Louis XVI]] in [[Palace of Versailles|Versailles]] in February 1787, Pigneau had difficulty in gathering support for a French expedition in support of Nguyễn Ánh.&lt;ref name=&quot;h429&quot;/&gt; This was due to the parlous financial state of the country prior to the [[French Revolution]]. Pigneau was helped by [[Pierre Poivre]], who had previously been involved in seeking French commercial interests in Vietnam.&lt;ref name=&quot;h429&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;b238&quot;&gt;Buttinger, p. 238.&lt;/ref&gt; Pigneau told the court that if France invested in Nguyễn Ánh and acquired a few fortified positions on the Vietnamese coast in return, then they would have the capability to &quot;dominate the seas of China and of the archipelago&quot;, and with it, control of Asian commerce.&lt;ref name=&quot;b238&quot;/&gt; In November 1787, a treaty of alliance was concluded between France and Cochinchina&amp;mdash;the European term for southern Vietnam&amp;mdash;in Nguyễn Ánh's name. Pigneau signed the treaty as the &quot;Royal Commissioner of France for Cochinchina&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;k76&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;b238&quot;/&gt; France promised four frigates, 1,650 fully equipped French soldiers and 250 Indian [[sepoy]]s in return for the cession of [[Côn Sơn Island|Pulo Condore]] and Tourane ([[Da Nang]]),&lt;ref name=&quot;k76&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;h429&quot;/&gt; as well as tree trade to the exclusion of all other countries.&lt;ref name=&quot;c282&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;k76&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;m10&quot;/&gt; However, the freedom to spread Christianity was not included.&lt;ref name=&quot;k76&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;b238&quot; /&gt; However, Pigneau found that Governor [[Thomas Conway]] of Pondicherry was unwilling to fulfill the agreement;&lt;ref name=&quot;m10&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;b239&quot;&gt;Buttinger, p. 239.&lt;/ref&gt; Conway had been instructed by Paris to determine when to organize the aid, if at all.&lt;ref name=&quot;k76&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;b239&quot;/&gt; Pigneau was thus forced to use funds raised in France to enlist French volunteers and mercenaries.&lt;ref name=&quot;c283&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;h429&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;b239&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;k77&quot;&gt;Karnow, p. 77.&lt;/ref&gt; He also managed to procure several shipments of arms and munitions from [[Mauritius]] and Pondicherry.&lt;ref name=&quot;m520&quot;/&gt;

Meanwhile, Nguyễn Ánh had stayed in Siam with a contingent of troops until August 1787. His soldiers served in [[Burmese–Siamese War (1785–86)|Siam's war against Bodawpaya of Burma (1785–86)]].&lt;ref name=&quot;c282&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;h430&quot;/&gt; Having consolidated their hold on southern Vietnam, the Tây Sơn decided to move north to unify the country. However, the withdrawal of troops from the [[Gia Định]] garrison weakened them their hold on the south.&lt;ref name=&quot;b237&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;h430&quot;/&gt; This was compounded by reports that Nguyễn Nhạc was being attacked near [[Qui Nhơn]] by his own brother [[Nguyễn Huệ]],&lt;ref&gt;Dutton, p. 47.&lt;/ref&gt; and that more Tây Sơn troops were being evacuated from Gia Dinh by their commander [[Dang Van Tran]] in order to aid Nguyễn Nhạc. Sensing Tây Sơn vulnerability in the south, Nguyễn Ánh assembled his forces at home and abroad in preparation for an immediate offensive.&lt;ref name=&quot;m7&quot;/&gt;
Nguyễn Ánh secretly left Siam and headed for southern Vietnam, but he failed in his first attempt to recapture Gia Dinh. He eventually succeeded in taking [[Mỹ Tho]], made it the main staging point for his operations, and rebuilt his army. After a hard-fought battle, his soldiers captured Saigon on  7 September 1788.&lt;ref name=&quot;h430&quot;/&gt; Eventually, Pigneau assembled four vessels to sail to Vietnam from Pondicherry, arriving in Saigon on  24 July 1789.&lt;ref&gt;Hall, p. 429&amp;ndash;430.&lt;/ref&gt; The combined forces helped to consolidate Nguyễn Ánh's hold on southern Vietnam.&lt;ref name=&quot;c282&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;h430&quot;&gt;Hall, p. 430.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Buttinger, pp. 239&amp;ndash;240.&lt;/ref&gt; The exact magnitude of foreign aid and the importance of their contribution to Gia Long's success is a point of dispute. Earlier scholars asserted that up to 400 Frenchmen enlisted,&lt;ref name=&quot;b266&quot;&gt;Buttinger, p. 266.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;c283&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;h429&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;k77&quot;/&gt; but more recent work has claimed that less than 100 soldiers were present, along with approximately a dozen officers.&lt;ref name=&quot;m11&quot;&gt;McLeod, p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;m521&quot;&gt;Mantienne, p. 521.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Consolidation of southern Vietnam==
The French officers enlisted by Pigneau helped to train Nguyễn Ánh's armed forces and introduced Western technological expertise to the war effort. The navy was trained by [[Jean-Marie Dayot]],&lt;ref name=&quot;h430&quot;/&gt; who supervised the construction of bronze-plated naval vessels.&lt;ref name=&quot;m11&quot;/&gt; [[Olivier de Puymanel]] was responsible for training the army and the construction of fortifications.&lt;ref name=&quot;k77&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;h430&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;c284&quot;&gt;Cady, p. 284.&lt;/ref&gt; He taught the troops various methods of manufacturing and using European-style artillery and introduced European infantry formations and tactics.&lt;ref name=&quot;m11&quot; /&gt; Pigneau and other missionaries acted as business agents for Nguyễn Ánh, purchasing munitions and other military supplies.&lt;ref name=&quot;m10&quot;/&gt; Pigneau also served as an advisor and de facto foreign minister until his death in 1799.&lt;ref name=&quot;c284&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;h431&quot;&gt;Hall, p. 431.&lt;/ref&gt; Upon Pigneau's death,&lt;ref name=&quot;k77&quot;/&gt; Gia Long's funeral oration described the Frenchman as &quot;the most illustrious foreigner ever to appear at the court of Cochinchina&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;b267&quot;&gt;Buttinger, p. 267.&lt;/ref&gt; Pigneau was buried in the presence of the crown prince, all mandarins of the court, the royal bodyguard of 12,000 men and 40,000 mourners.&lt;ref name=&quot;b267&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;k78&quot;&gt;Karnow, p. 78.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fortifications===
[[Image:Citadel of Saigon before 1835.png|thumb|300px|Layout of the original citadel.]]
{{main article|Citadel of Saigon}}
Following the recapture of Saigon, Nguyễn Ánh consolidated his power base and prepared the destruction of the Tây Sơn. His enemies had regularly raided the south and confiscated the annual rice harvests, so Nguyễn Ánh was keen to strengthen his defense. One of Nguyễn Ánh's first actions was to ask the French officers to design and supervise the construction of a modern European-style citadel in Saigon. The citadel was designed by [[Theodore Lebrun]] and de Puymanel, with 30,000 people mobilized for its construction in 1790.&lt;ref name=&quot;m522&quot;/&gt; The townfolk and their mandarins were punitively taxed for the work; the laborers were worked so hard that they revolted. When finished, the stone citadel had a perimeter measuring 4,176 meters in a [[Sébastien Le Prestre de Vauban|Vauban]] model.&lt;ref name=&quot;m522&quot;&gt;Mantienne, p. 522.&lt;/ref&gt; The fortress was bordered on three sides by pre-existing waterways, bolstering its natural defensive capability.&lt;ref name=&quot;m524&quot;&gt;Mantienne, p. 524.&lt;/ref&gt; Following the construction of the citadel, the Tây Sơn never again attempted to sail down the [[Saigon River]] and try to recapture the city&amp;mdash;its presence having endowed Nguyễn Ánh with a substantial psychological advantage over his opponents.&lt;ref name=&quot;m525&quot;&gt;Mantienne, p. 525.&lt;/ref&gt; Nguyễn Ánh took a keen personal interest in fortifications, ordering his French advisors to travel home and bring back books with the latest scientific and technical studies on the subject.&lt;ref name=&quot;m527&quot;&gt;Mantienne, p. 527.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Agrarian reform and economic growth===
With the southern region secured, Nguyễn Ánh turned his attention to agrarian reforms.&lt;ref name=&quot;m8&quot;&gt;McLeod, p. 8.&lt;/ref&gt; Due to Tây Sơn naval raids on the rice crop via inland waterways, the area suffered chronic rice shortages.&lt;ref name=&quot;m530&quot;&gt;Mantienne, p. 530.&lt;/ref&gt; Although the land was extremely fertile, the region was agriculturally underexploited, having been occupied by Vietnamese settlers only relatively recently. Furthermore, agricultural activities had also been significantly curtailed during the extended warfare with the Tây Sơn. Nguyễn Ánh's agricultural reforms were based around extending to the south a traditional form of agrarian expansion, the ''đồn điền'', which roughly translates as &quot;military settlement&quot; or &quot;military holding&quot;, the emphasis being on the military origin of this form of colonization. These were first used during the 15th century reign of [[Lê Thánh Tông]] in the southward expansion of Vietnam. The central government supplied military units with agricultural tools and grain for nourishment and planting. The soldiers were then assigned land to defend, clear and cultivate, and had to pay some of their harvest as tax. In the past, a military presence was required because the land was being seized from the conquered indigenous population. Under Nguyễn Ánh's rule, pacification was not usually needed but the basic model remained intact. Settlers were granted fallow land, given agricultural equipment, work animals and grain. After several years, they were required to pay grain tax. The program greatly reduced the amount of idle, uncultivated land. Large surpluses of grain, taxable by the state, resulted.&lt;ref name=&quot;m8&quot;/&gt;

By 1800, the increased agricultural productivity had allowed Nguyễn Ánh to support a sizeable army of more than 30,000 soldiers and a navy of more than 1,200 vessels. The surplus from the state granary was sold to European and Asian traders to facilitate the importation of raw materials for military purposes, in particular iron, bronze, and sulfur. The government also purchased castor sugar from local farmers and traded it for weapons from European manufacturers.&lt;ref name=&quot;m9&quot; /&gt; The food surplus allowed Nguyễn Ánh to engage in welfare initiatives that improved morale and loyalty among his subjects, thereby increasing his support base. The surplus grain was deposited in granaries built along the northward route out of Saigon, following the advance of the Nguyễn army into Tây Sơn territory. This allowed his troops to be fed from southern supplies, rather than eating from the areas that he was attempting to conquer or win over. Newly acquired regions were given tax exemptions, and surrendered Tây Sơn mandarins were appointed to equivalent positions with the same salaries in the Nguyễn administration.&lt;ref name=&quot;m9&quot;/&gt;

===Naval buildup===
[[Image:Jean-Baptiste Chaigneau 1805.jpg|thumb|The French Navy officer [[Jean-Baptiste Chaigneau]] served Emperor Gia Long.]]
Nguyễn Ánh used his new base to improve his inferior navy, which was much smaller than the Tây Sơn fleet and hitherto unable to prevent their rice raids.&lt;ref name=&quot;m530&quot;/&gt; Nguyễn Ánh had first attempted to acquire modern naval vessels in 1781, when on the advice of Pigneau, he had chartered Portuguese vessels of European design, complete with crew and artillery. This initial experience proved to be disastrous. For reasons that remain unclear, two of the vessels fled in the midst of battle against the Tây Sơn, while angry Vietnamese soldiers killed the third crew.&lt;ref name=&quot;m530&quot;/&gt; In 1789, Pigneau returned to Vietnam from [[Puducherry|Pondicherry]] with two vessels, which stayed in the Nguyễn service long-term. Over time, Vietnamese sailors replaced the original French and Indian crew under the command of French officers. These vessels became the foundation for an expanded military and merchant Nguyen naval force, with Nguyễn Ánh chartering and purchasing more European vessels to reinforce Vietnamese-built ships. However, traditional Vietnamese-style galleys and small sailing ships remained the majority of the fleet. By 1794, two European vessels were operating together with 200 Vietnamese boats against the Tây Sơn near [[Qui Nhơn]]. In 1799, a British trader by the name of Berry reported that the Nguyễn fleet had departed Saigon along the [[Saigon River]] with 100 galleys, 40 junks, 200 smaller boats and 800 carriers, accompanied by three European sloops.&lt;ref name=&quot;m530&quot;/&gt; In 1801, one naval division was reported to have included nine European vessels armed with 60 guns, five vessels with 50 guns, 40 with 16 guns, 100 junks, 119 galleys and 365 smaller boats.&lt;ref name=&quot;m530&quot;/&gt;

Most of the European-style vessels were built in the shipyard that Nguyễn Ánh had commissioned in Saigon. He took a deep personal interest in the naval program, directly supervising the work and spending several hours a day dockside. One witness noted &quot;One principal tendency of his ambition is to naval science, as a proof of this he has been heard to say he would build ships of the line on the European plan.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;m531&quot;&gt;Mantienne, p. 531.&lt;/ref&gt; By 1792, fifteen frigates were under construction, with a design that mixed Chinese and European specifications, equipped with 14 guns. The Vietnamese learned European naval architecture by dismantling an old European vessel into its components, so that Vietnamese shipbuilders could understand the separate facets of European shipbuilding, before reassembling it. They then applied their newfound knowledge to create replicas of the boats. Nguyễn Ánh studied naval carpentry techniques and was said to be adept at it, and learned navigational theory from the French books that Pigneau translated, particularly [[Denis Diderot]] and [[Jean le Rond d'Alembert]]'s ''[[Encyclopédie]]''. The Saigon shipyard was widely praised by European travelers.&lt;ref name=&quot;m531&quot;/&gt;

Despite his extensive reliance on French officers on matters of military technology, Nguyễn Ánh limited his inner military circle to Vietnamese. The Frenchmen decried his refusal to take their tactical advice. Chaigneau reported that the Europeans continually urged Nguyễn Ánh to take the initiative and launch bold attacks against Tây Sơn installations. Nguyễn Ánh refused, preferring to proceed slowly, consolidating his gains in one area and strengthening his economic and military base, before attacking another. Over time, Nguyễn Ánh gradually reduced the military role of his French allies on the battlefield.&lt;ref name=&quot;m11&quot;/&gt; In the naval battle at [[Thị Nại]] in 1792, Dayot led the Nguyễn naval attack, but by 1801, a seaborne offensive in the same area was led by the [[Nguyen Van Truong]], [[Võ Di Nguy]] and [[Lê Văn Duyệt]], with Chaigneau, Vannier, and de Forsans in supporting positions. The infantry attack on Qui Nhơn in 1793 was conducted, according to Nguyen historiography, in cooperation with &quot;Western soldiers&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;m11&quot;/&gt; The same source recorded that by 1801, Nguyen operations in the same area were directed by Vietnamese generals, whereas Chaigneau and Vannier were responsible for organizing supply lines.&lt;ref name=&quot;m11&quot;/&gt;

==Unification of Vietnam==
[[Image:Vietnamese Tirrailleurs of Nguyen.jpg|left|thumb|Vietnamese &quot;Tirailleur&quot; soldiers of the Nguyễn Dynasty.]]
In 1792, the middle and the most notable of the three [[Tây Sơn]] brothers, Nguyễn Huệ [[Quang Trung]], who had gained recognition as Emperor of Vietnam by driving the [[Lê Dynasty]] and China out of northern Vietnam, died suddenly. Nguyễn Ánh took advantage of the situation and attacked northwards.&lt;ref name=&quot;h431&quot;/&gt; By now, the majority of the original French soldiers, whose number peaked at less than 80 by some estimates, had departed.&lt;ref name=&quot;m11&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;m521&quot;/&gt; The majority of the fighting occurred in and around the coastal towns of [[Nha Trang]] in central Vietnam and [[Qui Nhơn]] further to the south in [[Bình Định Province]], the birthplace and stronghold of the Tây Sơn.&lt;ref name=&quot;m520&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;m7&quot;/&gt;
Nguyễn Ánh began by deploying his expanded and modernised naval fleet in raids against coastal Tây Sơn territory. His fleet left Saigon and sailed northward on an annual basis during June and July, carried by southwesterly winds. The naval offensives were reinforced by infantry campaigns. His fleet would then return south when the monsoon ended, on the back of northeasterly winds.&lt;ref name=&quot;m525&quot;/&gt; The large European wind-powered vessels gave the Nguyễn navy a commanding artillery advantage, as they had a superior range to the Tây Sơn cannons on the coast. Combined with traditional galleys and a crew that was highly regarded for its discipline, skill and bravery,&lt;ref name=&quot;m532&quot;&gt;Mantienne, p. 532.&lt;/ref&gt; the European-style vessels in the Nguyễn fleet inflicted hundreds of losses against the Tây Sơn in 1792 and 1793.&lt;ref name=&quot;m532&quot;/&gt;

In 1794, after a successful campaign in the Nha Trang region, Nguyễn Ánh ordered de Puymanel to build a citadel at [[Duyen Khanh]], near the city, instead of retreating south with the seasonal northeasterly breeze. A Nguyen garrison was established there under the command of Nguyễn Ánh's eldest son and heir, [[Nguyễn Phúc Cảnh]], assisted by Pigneau and de Puymanel. The Tây Sơn laid siege to Duyen Khanh in May 1794, but Nguyen forces were able to keep them out. Shortly after the siege ended, reinforcements arrived from Saigon and offensive operations against the Tây Sơn duly resumed. The campaign was the first time that the Nguyễn were able to operate in Tây Sơn heartland during an unfavorable season. The defensive success of the citadel was a powerful psychological victory for the Nguyễn, demonstrating their ability to penetrate Tây Sơn territory at all times of year. The Nguyễn then proceeded to slowly erode the Tây Sơn heartland.&lt;ref name=&quot;m525&quot;/&gt;

Heavy fighting occurred at the fortress of [[Qui Nhơn]], until it was captured in 1799 by Nguyen Canh's forces.&lt;ref name=&quot;k77&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;h430&quot;/&gt; However, the city was quickly lost and was not regained until 1801.&lt;ref name=&quot;c284&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;h431&quot;/&gt; The superior firepower of the improved navy played the decisive role in the ultimate recapture of the city, supporting a large overland attack.&lt;ref name=&quot;m532&quot;/&gt; After the capture of their stronghold at Qui Nhơn, the Tây Sơn, led by Quang Trung's son Quang Toan, came quickly. In June, the central city of [[Huế]]&amp;mdash;the former capital of the Nguyễn&amp;mdash;fell and Nguyễn Ánh crowned himself emperor, under the reign name Gia Long, which was derived from ''Gia Định'' (Saigon) and
''Thăng Long'' (Hanoi) to symbolize the unification of north and south Vietnam.&lt;ref name=&quot;k77&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;h431&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Tarling, p. 245.&lt;/ref&gt; He then quickly overran the north, with [[Hanoi]] captured on  22 July 1802.&lt;ref name=&quot;b241&quot;&gt;Buttinger, p. 241.&lt;/ref&gt; After a quarter-century of continuous fighting, Gia Long had unified what is now modern Vietnam,&lt;ref name=&quot;h431&quot;/&gt; and elevated his family to a position never previously occupied by Vietnamese royalty.&lt;ref name=&quot;h431&quot;/&gt; Vietnam had never before occupied a larger landmass. Gia Long became the first Vietnamese ruler to reign over territory stretching from China in the north, all the way to the Gulf of Siam and the [[Cà Mau]] peninsula in the south.&lt;ref name=&quot;m9&quot;/&gt; Gia Long's then petitioned the [[Qing Dynasty]] of China for official recognition, which was promptly granted.&lt;ref name=&quot;h431&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;b270&quot;&gt;Buttinger, p. 270.&lt;/ref&gt; The French failure to honour the treaty signed by Pigneau meant Vietnam was not bound to cede the territory and trading rights that they had promised.&lt;ref&gt;McLeod, pp. 11&amp;ndash;12.&lt;/ref&gt;

Due to a Tay Son massacre against ethnic Chinese, the Nguyen were supported by ethnic Chinese against the Tay Son.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wook2004&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Choi Byung Wook|title=Southern Vietnam Under the Reign of Minh Mạng (1820-1841): Central Policies and Local Response|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=foZAdRgB-nwC&amp;pg=PA35#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|year=2004|publisher=SEAP Publications|isbn=978-0-87727-138-3|pages=35–37}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Tay Son's downfall and defeat at the hands of Nguyễn Phúc Ánh was due to ethnic Chinese support to the Nguyen.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wook2004 2&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Choi Byung Wook|title=Southern Vietnam Under the Reign of Minh Mạng (1820-1841): Central Policies and Local Response|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=foZAdRgB-nwC&amp;pg=PA74#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|year=2004|publisher=SEAP Publications|isbn=978-0-87727-138-3|pages=74–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Rule==
Gia Long's rule was noted for its strict Confucian orthodoxy.&lt;ref name=&quot;b240&quot;&gt;Buttinger, p. 240.&lt;/ref&gt; Upon toppling the Tây Sơn, he repealed their reforms and reimposed a classical Confucian education and civil service system. He moved the capital from Hanoi in the north to Huế in central Vietnam to reflect the southward migration of the population over the preceding centuries. The emperor built new fortresses and a palace in his new capital. Using French expertise, Gia Long modernised Vietnam's defensive capabilities. In deference to the assistance of his French friends, he tolerated the activities of Catholic missionaries, something that was increasingly restricted by his successors. Under Gia Long's rule, Vietnam strengthened its military dominance in Indochina, expelling Siam from Cambodia and turning it into a vassal. Despite this, he was relatively isolationist in outlook towards European powers.

===Renaming Vietnam===
The Qing [[Jiaqing Emperor]] of China refused the Vietnamese ruler Gia Long's request to change his country's name to Nam Việt, instead the Jiaqing Emperor changed the name instead to [[Names of Vietnam#Origin of the name .22Vietnam.22|Việt Nam]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Woodside1971&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Alexander Woodside|title=Vietnam and the Chinese Model: A Comparative Study of Vietnamese and Chinese Government in the First Half of the Nineteenth Century|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=0LgSI9UQNpwC&amp;pg=PA120#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|year=1971|publisher=Harvard Univ Asia Center|isbn=978-0-674-93721-5|pages=120–}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gia Long's [[Đại Nam thực lục]] contains the diplomatic correspondence over the naming.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kyong-McClainDu2013&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=Jeff Kyong-McClain|author2=Yongtao Du|title=Chinese History in Geographical Perspective|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=j9OSLSLWzJUC&amp;pg=PA67&amp;lpg=PA67&amp;dq=confucianism+in+vietnam+kelley&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=M9QqApXWtx&amp;sig=yNWQEJOJHf1tFr1acEhmNjQaD34&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjj5cm7qrXOAhXICsAKHRcZDKIQ6AEISjAI#v=onepage&amp;q=confucianism%20in%20vietnam%20kelley&amp;f=false|year=2013|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield|isbn=978-0-7391-7230-8|pages=67–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&quot;Trung Quốc&quot; 中國 was used as a name for Vietnam by Gia Long in 1805.&lt;ref name=&quot;Woodside1971&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Alexander Woodside|title=Vietnam and the Chinese Model: A Comparative Study of Vietnamese and Chinese Government in the First Half of the Nineteenth Century|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=0LgSI9UQNpwC&amp;pg=PA18#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|year=1971|publisher=Harvard Univ Asia Center|isbn=978-0-674-93721-5|pages=18–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It was said &quot;Hán di hữu hạn&quot; 漢夷有限 (&quot;''the Vietnamese and the barbarians must have clear borders''&quot; by the Gia Long Emperor (Nguyễn Phúc Ánh) when differentiating between Khmer and Vietnamese.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wook2004&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Choi Byung Wook|title=Southern Vietnam Under the Reign of Minh Mạng (1820-1841): Central Policies and Local Response|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=foZAdRgB-nwC&amp;pg=PA34#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|year=2004|publisher=SEAP Publications|isbn=978-0-87727-138-3|pages=34–}}&lt;/ref&gt; Minh Mang implemented an acculturation integration policy directed at minority non-Vietnamese peoples.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wook2004 2&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Choi Byung Wook|title=Southern Vietnam Under the Reign of Minh Mạng (1820-1841): Central Policies and Local Response|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=foZAdRgB-nwC&amp;pg=PA136#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|year=2004|publisher=SEAP Publications|isbn=978-0-87727-138-3|pages=136–}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thanh nhân 清人 was used to refer to ethnic Chinese by the Vietnamese while Vietnamese called themselves as Hán nhân 漢人 in Vietnam during the 1800s under Nguyễn rule.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wook2004 3&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Choi Byung Wook|title=Southern Vietnam Under the Reign of Minh Mạng (1820-1841): Central Policies and Local Response|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=foZAdRgB-nwC&amp;pg=PA137#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|year=2004|publisher=SEAP Publications|isbn=978-0-87727-138-3|pages=137–}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Administrative structure===
During the war era, Nguyễn Ánh had maintained an embryonic bureaucracy in an attempt to prove his leadership ability to the people. Due to the incessant warfare, military officers were generally the most prominent members of his inner circle.&lt;ref name=&quot;m15&quot;&gt;McLeod, p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt; This dependency on military backing continued to manifest itself throughout his reign.&lt;ref name=&quot;m15&quot;/&gt; Vietnam was divided into three administrative regions. The old patrimony of the Nguyễn formed the central part of the empire (''vùng Kinh Kỳ''), with nine provinces, five of which were directly ruled by Gia Long and his mandarins from Huế.&lt;ref name=&quot;h431&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;m15&quot;/&gt;
The central administration at Huế was divided into six ministries: Public affairs, finance, rites, war, justice and public works. Each was under a minister, assisted by two deputies and two or three councillors.&lt;ref name=&quot;h431&quot; /&gt; Each of these ministries had around 70 employees assigned to various units.&lt;ref name=&quot;m15&quot;/&gt; The heads of these ministries formed the Supreme Council. A treasurer general and a Chief of the Judicial Service assisted a governor general, who was in charge of a number of provinces.&lt;ref name=&quot;h432&quot;&gt;Hall, p. 432.&lt;/ref&gt; The provinces were classified into ''trấn'' and ''dinh''. These were in turn divided into [[Districts of Vietnam|''phủ'', ''huyện'' and ''châu'']].&lt;ref name=&quot;h432&quot;/&gt; All important matters were examined by the Supreme Council in the presence of Gia Long. The officials tabled their reports for discussion and decision-making. The bureaucrats involved in the Supreme Council were selected from the high-ranking mandarins of the six ministries and the academies.&lt;ref name=&quot;m15&quot;/&gt;

Gia Long handled the northern and southern regions of Vietnam cautiously, not wanting them to be jarred by rapid centralization after centuries of national division.&lt;ref name=&quot;m15&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McLeod, p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt;[[Tonkin]], with the administrative seat of its imperial military protector (''quan tổng trấn'') at [[Hanoi]] had thirteen provinces (''tổng trấn Bắc Thành''), and in the Red River Delta, the old officials of the Le administration continued in office. In the south, Saigon was the capital of the four provinces of [[Cochinchina]] (''tổng trấn Nam Hà''), as well as the seat of the military protector.&lt;ref name=&quot;h431&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;m16&quot;&gt;McLeod, p. 16.&lt;/ref&gt; The citadels in the respective cities directly administered their military defense zones. This system allowed Gia Long to reward his leading supporters with highly powerful positions, giving them almost total autonomy in ordinary administrative and legal matters. This system persisted until 1831&amp;ndash;32, when his son [[Minh Mạng]] centralized the national government.&lt;ref name=&quot;m16&quot;/&gt;

In his attempts to re-establish a stable administration after centuries of civil war, Gia Long was not regarded as being innovative, preferring the traditional administration framework.&lt;ref name=&quot;h432&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Buttinger, p. 278.&lt;/ref&gt; When Gia Long unified the country, it was described as Charles Maybon as being chaotic: &quot;The wheels of administration were warped or no longer existed; the cadres of officials were empty, the hierarchy destroyed; taxes were not being collected, lists of communal property had disappeared, proprietary titles were lost, fields abandoned; roads bridges and public granaries had not been maintained; work in the mines had ceased. The administration of justice had been interrupted, every province was a prey to pirates, and violation of law went unpunished, while even the law itself had become uncertain.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;h432&quot;/&gt;

===Foreign military relations===
During the 17th and 18th centuries, the Cambodian empire had been in decline as Vietnamese people migrated south into the [[Mekong Delta]], which was hitherto Khmer territory.&lt;ref name=&quot;c266&quot;&gt;Cady, p. 266.&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, Cambodia had been periodically invaded by both Vietnam and Siam. Cambodia lurched uneasily between both poles of domination as dictated by the internal strife of her two larger neighbors.&lt;ref&gt;Hall, pp. 432&amp;ndash;433.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1796, [[Ang Eng]], a pro-Siamese king had died, leaving [[Ang Chan]], who was born in 1791.&lt;ref name=&quot;h433&quot;&gt;Hall, p. 433.&lt;/ref&gt; When Gia Long unified Vietnam, Eng was given investiture by Siam in order to hold out Vietnamese influence,&lt;ref name=&quot;h433&quot;/&gt; but in 1803, a Cambodian mission paid tribute to Vietnam in attempt to placate Gia Long, something that became an annual routine.&lt;ref name=&quot;h433&quot;/&gt; In 1807, Ang Chan requested formal investiture as a vassal of Gia Long.&lt;ref name=&quot;h434&quot;&gt;Hall, p. 434.&lt;/ref&gt; Gia Long responded by sending an ambassador bearing the book of investiture, together with a seal of gilded silver. In 1812, Ang Chan refused a request from his brother [[Ang Snguon]] to share power, leading to a rebellion. Siam sent troops to support the rebel prince, hoping to enthrone him and wrest influence from Gia Long over Cambodia.&lt;ref name=&quot;h434&quot;/&gt; In 1813, Gia Long responded by sending a large military contingent that forced the Siamese and Ang Snguon out of Cambodia. As a result, a Vietnamese garrison was permanently installed in the citadel at [[Phnom Penh]], the Cambodian capital. Thereafter, Siam made no attempts to regain control of Cambodia during Gia Long's rule.&lt;ref name=&quot;h434&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Buttinger, p. 305.&lt;/ref&gt;

Napoleon's aims to conquer Vietnam as a base to challenge British supremacy in India never materialized,&lt;ref name=&quot;b272&quot;&gt;Buttinger, p. 272.&lt;/ref&gt; having been preoccupied by vast military ambitions on mainland Europe.&lt;ref name=&quot;h434&quot;/&gt; However, France remained the only European power with permanent spokesmen in Vietnam during his reign.&lt;ref name=&quot;b272&quot;/&gt;

===Trade relations===
Pigneau's aborted deal with France allowed Gia Long to keep his country closed to western trade.&lt;ref name=&quot;b240&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Buttinger, pp. 270&amp;ndash;271.&lt;/ref&gt; Gia Long was generally dismissive of European commercial overtures.&lt;ref name=&quot;b271&quot;&gt;Buttinger, p. 271.&lt;/ref&gt; This was part of a policy of trying to maintain friendly relations with every European power by granting favors to none.&lt;ref name=&quot;k78&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Buttinger, pp. 271&amp;ndash;273.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1804, a British delegation attempted to negotiate trading privileges with Vietnam. It was the only offer of its kind until 1822, such was the extent of European disinterest in Asia during the Napoleonic Wars. Gia Long had purchased arms from British firms in [[Chennai|Madras]] and [[Calcutta]] on credit,&lt;ref name=&quot;b307&quot;&gt;Buttinger, p. 307.&lt;/ref&gt; prompting the [[British East India Company]] to send [[John Roberts (diplomat)|John Roberts]] to Huế. However, Roberts's gifts were turned away and the negotiations for a commercial deal never started. The United Kingdom then made a request for the exclusive right to trade with Vietnam and the cession of the island of [[Cham (island)|Cham]] near [[Hội An|Faifo]],&lt;ref name=&quot;b307&quot;/&gt; which was rejected, as were further approaches from the Netherlands. Both of these failed attempts were attributed to the influence of the French mandarins.&lt;ref name=&quot;b308&quot;&gt;Buttinger, p. 308.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1817, the French Prime Minister [[Armand-Emmanuel du Plessis, Duc de Richelieu|Armand-Emmanuel du Plessis]] dispatched the ''Cybele'', a frigate with 52 guns to Tourane (now [[Da Nang]]) to &quot;show French sympathy and to assure Gia Long of the benevolence of the King of France&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;b272&quot; /&gt; The captain of the vessel was turned away, ostensibly on grounds of protocol for not carrying a royal letter from the French king.&lt;ref name=&quot;b272&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;b309&quot;&gt;Buttinger, p. 309.&lt;/ref&gt;

Gia Long kept four French officers in his service after his coronation: [[Philippe Vannier]], [[Jean-Baptiste Chaigneau]], de Forsans and the doctor Despiau. All became high ranking mandarins and were treated well.&lt;ref name=&quot;h434&quot; /&gt; They were given 50 bodyguards each, ornate residences and were exempt for having to prostrate before the emperor.&lt;ref name=&quot;k78&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;c408&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;buttinger, p. 268.&lt;/ref&gt;  Recommendations from French officials in [[Puducherry|Pondicherry]] to [[Napoleon Bonaparte]] suggesting the re-establishment of diplomatic relations with Vietnam were fruitless due to the preoccupation with war in Europe.&lt;ref name=&quot;k78&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;h434&quot;/&gt; However, French merchants from [[Bordeaux]] were later able to begin trading with Vietnam after the further efforts of the Duc de Richelieu.&lt;ref name=&quot;h435&quot;&gt;Hall, p. 435.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Domestic policies and capital works===
[[File:Jean-Marie Dayot.jpg|Jean-Marie Dayot (left) took a leading role in the training of Gia Long's navy.|thumb]]
Gia Long abolished all large landholding by princes, nobles and high officials. He dismantled the 800-year-old practice of paying officials and rewarding or endowing nobles with a portion of the taxes from a village or a group thereof.&lt;ref&gt;Buttinger, p. 279.&lt;/ref&gt; Existing highways were repaired and new ones constructed, with the north-south road from Saigon to [[Lạng Sơn]] put under restoration.&lt;ref name=&quot;b312&quot;&gt;Buttinger, p. 312.&lt;/ref&gt; He organised a postal service to operate along the highways and public storehouses were built to alleviate starvation in drought-affected years. Gia Long enacted monetary reform and implemented a more socialized agrarian policy.&lt;ref name=&quot;b312&quot;/&gt; However, the population growth far outstripped that of land clearing and cultivation.&lt;ref&gt;Buttinger, p. 280.&lt;/ref&gt; There was little emphasis on innovation in agricultural technology, so the improvements in productivity were mainly derived from increasing the amount of cultivated farmland.&lt;ref&gt;Buttinger, pp. 281&amp;ndash;282.&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the civil war was over, Gia Long decided to add to the two citadels that had been built under the supervision of French officers. Gia Long was convinced of their effectiveness and during his 18-year reign, a further 11 citadels were built throughout the country.&lt;ref name=&quot;m525&quot;/&gt; The majority were built in the [[Sébastien Le Prestre de Vauban|Vauban]] style, with pentagonal or hexagonal geometry, while a minority, including the one in Huế, were built in a four-sided traditional Chinese design. The fortresses were built at [[Vinh]], [[Thanh Hóa]], [[Bắc Ninh]], [[Hà Tĩnh]], [[Thái Nguyên]] and [[Hải Dương]] in the north, Huế, [[Quảng Ngãi]], [[Khánh Hòa Province|Khánh Hòa]] and [[Bình Định]] in the centre, and [[Vĩnh Long]] in the Mekong Delta. Construction was at its most intense in the early phase of Gia Long's reign&amp;mdash;only one of the 11 were built in the last six years of his rule.&lt;ref name=&quot;m526&quot;&gt;Mantienne, p. 526.&lt;/ref&gt; De Puymanel and Lebrun left Vietnam before the end of the war, so the forts were designed by Vietnamese engineers who oversaw the construction. The position of Citadel Supervision Officer was created under the Ministry of War and made responsible for the work, underlining the importance that Gia Long placed on fortifications.&lt;ref name=&quot;m528&quot;&gt;Mantienne, p. 528.&lt;/ref&gt; Gia Long's fortifications program was marred by accusations that the people labored all day and part of the night in all weather conditions,&lt;ref&gt;Buttinger, pp. 281, 316.&lt;/ref&gt; and that as a direct consequence, land went fallow. Complaints of mandarin corruption and oppressive taxation were often levelled at his government.&lt;ref name=&quot;b309&quot;/&gt; Following his coronation, Gia Long drastically reduced his naval fleet and by the 1810s, only two of the European-style vessels were still in service. The downsizing of the navy was mainly attributed to budgetary constraints caused by heavy spending on fortifications and transport infrastructure such as roads, dykes and canals. However, in 1819, a new phase of shipbuilding was launched, with Gia Long personally supervising the dockyards.&lt;ref name=&quot;m532&quot;/&gt;

===Social policy===
In order to train and recruit government officials, Gia Long revived the Confucian court examinations that had been abolished by the Tây Sơn. In 1803, he founded the [[Imperial Academy, Huế|National Academy]] (''Quốc Tử Giám'') at Huế. Its objective was to educate the sons of mandarins and meritorious students in the Confucian classical literature.&lt;ref name=&quot;m16&quot; /&gt; In 1804, Gia Long promulgated edicts establishing similar schools in the provinces, and guidelines to regulate their staff and curriculum. He appointed Directors of Education (''quan đốc học'') to oversee the provincial education system and the selection process for the entrance examinations into the National Academy, beginning in 1802. The directors were assisted by Subordinate and Assistant Directors (phó đốc học ''or'' trợ-giáo). Gia Long explained to his court in 1814 that the goal was to create a cadre of classically educated, politically loyal administrators:&lt;ref name=&quot;m16&quot;/&gt;

{{quote|The schools are where men of talent can be found. Wanting to follow the example of the former kings, I have established schools in order that learned and talented men will arise and the state may thus employ them.&lt;ref name=&quot;m16&quot;/&gt;}}

In 1807, Gia Long opened the first civil service examinations held under the Nguyễn Dynasty, staged at regional level.&lt;ref name=&quot;m16&quot;/&gt; From then on, the training and selection process for the imperial bureaucracy was largely centered on examinations.&lt;ref name=&quot;m16&quot;/&gt; The curriculum for the examinations consisted of the &quot;five classics and the four books&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;m16&quot;/&gt; which focused on Chinese history leading up to the [[Song Dynasty]], while regarding other knowledge as irrelevant.&lt;ref name=&quot;m17&quot;&gt;McLeod, p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt;

Gia Long promulgated a new legal code to replace the system that had existed since the [[Hong Duc]] era of [[Lê Thánh Tông]] in the 15th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;m17&quot;/&gt; Work started in 1811 under a group of scholars led by [[Nguyễn Văn Thành]], and in 1815, the ''Bộ luật Gia Long'' (''[[Gia Long Code]]'') was issued.&lt;ref name=&quot;m17&quot;/&gt; Although Gia Long claimed that his new system was a mixture of the Le code and [[Qing Dynasty]] system of China, most scholars regard it as being a near complete copy of the Qing code.&lt;ref name=&quot;m17&quot;/&gt; The code was later translated into French by [[Paul-Louis-Félix Philastre]].&lt;ref name=&quot;c408&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Buttinger, p. 314.&lt;/ref&gt; It focused on strengthening the power and authority of the emperor, his mandarins, and the traditional family unit. In cases of serious crimes, particularly those against the state, collective punishment was meted out to the family of the convict, including the death penalty.&lt;ref name=&quot;m18&quot;&gt;McLeod, p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Ngomon2.jpg|The entrance to Gia Long's palace and citadel complex in Huế.|thumb]]
Now that Vietnam was unified, the center of gravity of the country was further to the south following centuries of southerly migration and conquest,&lt;ref name=&quot;c266&quot;/&gt;  so Gia Long moved the seat of government from Hanoi to Huế.&lt;ref name=&quot;h432&quot;/&gt; Gia Long rebuilt the old [[Phú Xuân|citadel of Phú Xuân]] into a [[Imperial City, Huế|fortress stronghold]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Ring&quot;&gt;Ring, Salkin and La Boda, p. 364.&lt;/ref&gt; The structure was a square shape of 2.5&amp;nbsp;km per side.&lt;ref name=&quot;c408&quot;&gt;Cady, p. 408.&lt;/ref&gt; A 9&amp;nbsp;m rampart was cased with masonry and protected by protruding bastions, each defended by 36 guns.&lt;ref name=&quot;c408&quot;/&gt; The exterior and interior were flanked and reinforced by a series of moats. The citadel's defenders included an 800-strong elephant troop.&lt;ref name=&quot;c408&quot;/&gt; The new palace structure, protocol and court dress were all taken directly from Qing Dynasty styles, and his palace and fortress was intended to be a smaller copy of the [[China|Chinese]] [[Forbidden City]] in the 1800s.&lt;ref name=&quot;k78&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Woodside, pp. 126&amp;ndash;130.&lt;/ref&gt;

Gia Long tolerated the Catholic faith of his French allies and permitted unimpeded missionary activities out of respect to his benefactors.&lt;ref&gt;Buttinger, pp. 241, 311.&lt;/ref&gt; The missionary activity was dominated by the Spanish in Tonkin and French in the central and southern regions.&lt;ref name=&quot;c408&quot;/&gt; At the time of his death, there were six European bishops in Vietnam.&lt;ref name=&quot;c408&quot;/&gt; The population of Christians was estimated at 300,000 in Tonkin and 60,000 in Cochinchina.&lt;ref name=&quot;c409&quot;&gt;Cady, p. 409.&lt;/ref&gt; However, he expressed dismay at the Catholic condemnation of the traditional [[ancestor worship]], a basic tenet of Vietnamese culture.&lt;ref&gt;Buttinger, pp. 310, 262.&lt;/ref&gt; Gia Long was also known for his disdain for [[Buddhism]], the religion practiced by the majority of the population. Despite its popularity among ladies of the court, Gia Long often restricted the activities of Buddhists.&lt;ref&gt;Buttinger, p. 310.&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 1802, Gia Long retaliated against the captured Tây Sơn leadership who had executed his family in the 1770s. The surviving members of the family and its leading generals and their families were executed.&lt;ref&gt;Buttinger, pp. 235, 266.&lt;/ref&gt; The remains of Quang Trung and his queen were exhumed and desecrated, and his son, the last Tây Sơn monarch [[Quang Toản]] was bound to four elephants and torn apart.&lt;ref name=&quot;k77&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;b267&quot;/&gt; Gia Long repealed the changes enacted by Quang Trung and reverted to the prior Confucian orthodoxy. This included restoring the civil service to the forefront of decision making, ahead of the army, and reversed Quang Trung's education reforms, which put science before the study of Confucian literature.&lt;ref name=&quot;b265&quot;&gt;Buttinger, p. 265.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Family and succession==
[[Image:MinhMang.jpg|thumb|Minh Mạng, Gia Long's fourth son and successor.]]
Gia Long had three wives. In 1780, during the war against the Tây Sơn, he married [[Tống Thị Lan]], the daughter of a Nguyen general. She bore him two sons, the first being Nguyễn Phúc Chiêu, who died shortly after birth in [[Phú Quốc]] island, and later Crown Prince [[Nguyễn Phúc Cảnh]]. Following Gia Long's ascension to the throne, she became Empress consort and was given the title of Empress Thừa Thiên posthumously.&lt;ref name=&quot;Binh&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Tôn Thất Bình|year=1997|title= Kể chuyện chín Chúa mười ba Vua triều Nguyễn|place=Da Nang|publisher=Đà Nẵng Publishing House|language=Vietnamese| pages=45&amp;ndash;47}}&lt;/ref&gt; Around 1781, during the war with the Tây Sơn, he married his second wife [[Thuận Thiên (Nguyễn dynasty empress)|Trần Thị Đang]], a daughter of one of his ministers. She bore him three sons, Nguyễn Phúc Đảm, Nguyen Phuc Dai and Nguyen Phuc Chan, and was posthumously given the title of Empress Thuận Thiên.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Thi Long|year=1998|title= Nhà Nguyễn chín Chúa mười ba Vua|place=Da Nang|publisher=Đà Nẵng Publishing House|page=85 |language=Vietnamese}}&lt;/ref&gt; After his conquest of Vietnam, Gia Long, took his third wife, [[Lê Ngọc Bình]]. A daughter of [[Lê Hiển Tông]], the second-last emperor of the [[Lê Dynasty]], she was betrothed by Emperor Quang Trung to his son Quang Toản. After Gia Long defeated the Tây Sơn and executed Quang Toan, he took her as his wife. Binh bore him two princes, Nguyen Phuc Quan and Nguyen Phuc Cu, and princesses An Nghia Ngoc Ngon and My Khue Ngoc Khue.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Đặng Việt Thủy|author2=Đặng Thành Trung|year=2008|title=18 vị Công chúa Việt Nam|place=Hanoi|publisher=Quan Doi Nhan Dan Publishing House|pages=102&amp;ndash;105 |language=Vietnamese}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gia Long had almost 100 concubines who were daughters of his mandarins; Gia Long did not favour [[polygamy]] but he did so to secure the loyalty of his inner circle.&lt;ref name=&quot;Binh&quot;/&gt;

As Crown Prince Nguyen Canh had died of [[smallpox]] during the war against the Tây Sơn, it was assumed that Canh's son would succeed Gia Long as emperor, but in 1816 [[Minh Mạng|Nguyễn Phúc Đảm]], the son of his second wife, was appointed instead, and ruled as Minh Mạng.&lt;ref name=&quot;b268&quot;&gt;Buttinger, p. 268.&lt;/ref&gt; Gia Long chose him for his strong character and his deep aversion to westerners, whereas Canh's lineage had converted to Catholicism and were reluctant to maintain their Confucian traditions such as ancestor worship. Before his ascension, Nguyễn Phúc Đảm was reported to have praised the Japanese for having expelled and eradicated Christianity from their country.&lt;ref name=&quot;b269&quot;&gt;Buttinger, p. 269.&lt;/ref&gt; Gia Long told his son to treat the Europeans respectfully, especially the French, but not to grant them any position of preponderance.&lt;ref name=&quot;b268&quot;/&gt; Gia Long died on 3 February 1820 and was buried at the [[Thien Tho Tomb]] and posthumously named Thế Tổ Cao Hoàng đế.&lt;ref name=&quot;tdas&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Duiker, p. 60&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kim, p. 416.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist|3}}

==References==
{{commons category|Gia Long}}
{{Portal|Vietnam|History|Biography}}
*{{cite book|title= The Smaller Dragon: A Political History of Vietnam | authorlink=Joseph Buttinger| first= Joseph|last=Buttinger | publisher=Praeger |year=1958|location=New York}}
*{{cite book|title= Southeast Asia: Its Historical Development| first= John F.|last=Cady | publisher=McGraw Hill |year=1964|location=New York}}
*{{cite book |first=William J. |last=Duiker |authorlink=William J. Duiker|title=Historical dictionary of Vietnam|publisher=Scarecrow Press |isbn=0-8108-2164-8| year=1989 |location=Metuchen, New Jersey}}
*{{cite book |first=George Edson |last=Dutton |title=The Tây Sơn uprising: society and rebellion in eighteenth-century Vietnam|publisher=University of Hawaii Press |isbn=0-8248-2984-0| year=2006}}
*{{cite book|title= A History of South-east Asia| first= D. G. E.|last=Hall | publisher=Macmillan |year=1981 |isbn=0-333-24163-0 |location=Basingstoke, Hampshire}}
*{{cite book| title=Vietnam: A history| first=Stanley |last=Karnow |authorlink=Stanley Karnow| year=1997 |publisher=Penguin Books | isbn=0-670-84218-4|location=New York}}
*{{cite journal |last= Mantienne |first=Frédéric
 |journal=[[Journal of Southeast Asian Studies]] |date=October 2003 |title=The Transfer of Western Military Technology to Vietnam in the Late Eighteenth and Early Nineteenth Centuries: The Case of the Nguyen |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=Singapore |volume=34 |issue=3 |pages=519&amp;ndash;534 |doi=10.1017/S0022463403000468}}
*{{cite book |first=Mark W. |last=McLeod | title=The Vietnamese response to French intervention, 1862&amp;ndash;1874 |publisher=Praeger | year=1991 |isbn=0-275-93562-0|location=New York}}
*{{cite book|last1=Ring|first1=Trudy|last2=Salkin|first2=Robert M.|last3=La Boda|first3=Sharon|title=International Dictionary of Historic Places: Asia and Oceania|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|year=1994|isbn=1-884964-04-4}}
*{{cite book |title=The Cambridge History of Southeast Asia |last=Tarling |first=Nicholas |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=1999 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location= |isbn=0-521-66370-9 |page= |pages= |url= |accessdate= |volume=1 (part 2)}}
*{{cite book|author=Tran Trong Kim|authorlink=Tran Trong Kim|year=2005|title=[[Việt Nam sử lược]]|publisher=Ho Chi Minh City General Publishing House|location=Ho Chi Minh City|language=Vietnamese}}
*{{cite book |first=Alexander |last=Woodside |title=Vietnam and the Chinese model: a comparative study of Vietnamese and Chinese government in the first half of the nineteenth century |location=Cambridge, Massachusetts |publisher=Harvard University Press |isbn=0-674-93721-X |year=1988}}

{{S-start}}
{{S-hou|[[Nguyễn Dynasty]]|1762|||1820}}
{{S-bef|before=[[Nguyễn Phúc Thuần]]&lt;br&gt;[[Nguyen Phuc Duong]]}}
{{S-ttl|title=[[Nguyễn Lord]]|years=1780&amp;ndash;1802}}
{{S-non|reason=''New title''&lt;br/&gt;Foundation of [[Nguyễn Dynasty]]}}
{{S-bef|before=[[Quang Toan]] of [[Tây Sơn Dynasty]]}}
{{S-ttl|title=Emperor of Vietnam|years=1802&amp;ndash;1822}}
{{S-aft|after=[[Minh Mạng|Emperor Minh Mạng]]}}
{{S-end}}

{{Gia Long}}
{{NguyenLord}}
{{Emperors of Nguyen Dynasty}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Gia Long}}
[[Category:1762 births]]
[[Category:1820 deaths]]
[[Category:Gia Long| ]]
[[Category:Nguyen dynasty emperors]]
[[Category:19th-century Vietnamese monarchs]]</text>
      <sha1>b4zrdzaxr3ajazn2rxsn8hgtd0gizbx</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
