<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Heinz-Wolfgang Schnaufer</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3173887</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748491934</id>
      <parentid>748380025</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-08T13:11:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Later life and death */clean up; http&amp;rarr;https for [[Google Books]] and other Google services using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="84384">{{good article}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2014}}
{{EngvarB|date=October 2014}}
{{Infobox military person
|name=Heinz-Wolfgang Schnaufer
|birth_date={{birth date|1922|2|16|df=y}}
|death_date={{death date and age|1950|7|15|1922|2|16|df=y}}
|birth_place=[[Calw]], [[Free People's State of Württemberg|Württemberg]], [[Weimar Republic|Weimar Germany]]
|death_place=[[Bordeaux]], [[French Fourth Republic|France]]
|placeofburial=Calw, Village Cemetery
|image=File:Heinz-Wolfgang Schnaufer.jpg
|image_size=150px
|caption=Heinz Schnaufer wearing the Diamonds to his Knight's Cross
|alt=Black-and-white photograph showing an uniformed man wearing a pilot's leather jacket with fur collar, with an Iron Cross displayed at the front of his shirt collar.
|nickname=''Spook of [[Sint-Truiden]]''
|allegiance={{flag|Nazi Germany}}
|branch={{Luftwaffe}}
|serviceyears=1939–45
|rank=[[Major (Germany)|Major]]
|commands=12./[[NJG 1]], IV./[[NJG 1]], [[NJG 4]]
|unit=[[NJG 1]], [[NJG 4]]
|battles=[[World War II]]
*[[Operation Cerberus]]
*[[Defence of the Reich]]
:*[[Battle of the Ruhr]]
:*[[Battle of Berlin (RAF campaign)|Battle of Berlin]]
|awards=[[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves, Swords and Diamonds]]
|laterwork=Wine business
}}

'''Heinz-Wolfgang Schnaufer''' (16 February 1922&amp;nbsp;– 15 July 1950) was a German [[Luftwaffe]] [[night fighter]] pilot and is the highest scoring [[flying ace|night fighter ace]] in the history of [[aerial warfare]]. A flying ace or fighter ace is a [[military aviation|military aviator]] credited with shooting down five or more enemy [[aircraft]] during combat.&lt;ref&gt;Spick 1996, pp. 3–4.&lt;/ref&gt; All of his 121 victories were claimed during [[World War II]] at night, mostly against British four-engine bombers,&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;For a list of Luftwaffe night fighter aces see ''[[List of German World War II night fighter aces]]''&lt;/ref&gt; for which he was awarded the coveted [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves, Swords and Diamonds]] on 16 October 1944, Germany's highest military decoration at the time.{{refn|In 1944, the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves, Swords and Diamonds was second only to the [[Grand Cross of the Iron Cross]], which was awarded only to senior commanders for winning a major battle or campaign, in the military order of the Third Reich. The Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves, Swords and Diamonds as the highest military order was surpassed on 29 December 1944 by the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Golden Oak Leaves, Swords and Diamonds.&lt;ref&gt;Williamson and Bujeiro 2004, pp. 3, 7.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=&quot;Note&quot;}} He was nicknamed &quot;The Spook of [[Sint-Truiden|St. Trond]]&quot;, from the location of his unit's base in occupied Belgium.

Born in [[Calw]], Schnaufer grew up in the [[Weimar Republic]] and [[Third Reich]] as the first of four children of Alfred Schnaufer and his wife Martha. The family owned and operated a [[winery]] business. Schnaufer, a good student and already a [[Gliding|glider pilot]] at school, began military service in the [[Wehrmacht]] by joining the Luftwaffe in 1939. After training at various pilot and fighter-pilot schools, he was posted to [[Nachtjagdgeschwader 1|''Nachtjagdgeschwader'' 1]] (NJG 1—1st Night Fighter Wing), operating on the [[Western Front (World War II)|Western Front]], in November 1941. He flew [[Operation Donnerkeil|his first combat sorties]] in support of [[Operation Cerberus]], the breakout of the German ships {{ship|German battleship|Scharnhorst||2}}, {{ship|German battleship|Gneisenau||2}}, and {{ship|German cruiser|Prinz Eugen||2}} from [[Brest, France|Brest]]. Schnaufer participated in the [[Defence of the Reich]] campaign from 1942 onwards, in which he would achieve most of his success. He claimed his first aerial victory on the night of 1/2 June 1942. As the war progressed, he accumulated further victories and he later became a squadron leader and group commander. He was awarded the [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross]] on 31 December 1943 for reaching 42 aerial victories.

Schnaufer achieved his 100th aerial victory on 9 October 1944 and was awarded the Diamonds to his Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves and Swords on 16 October. He was appointed ''[[Geschwaderkommodore]]'' (wing commander) of [[Nachtjagdgeschwader 4|''Nachtjagdgeschwader'' 4]] (NJG 4) on 4 November 1944. By the end of hostilities, Schnaufer's night fighter crew held the unique distinction that every member—radio operator and [[air gunner]]—was decorated with the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross. Schnaufer was taken prisoner of war by British forces in May 1945. After his release a year later, he returned to his home town and took over the family wine business. He sustained injuries in a road accident on 13 July 1950 during a wine-purchasing visit to France, and died in a [[Bordeaux]] hospital two days later.

==Early life==
Heinz-Wolfgang Schnaufer was born on 16 February 1922 in [[Calw]], located in the [[Free People's State of Württemberg]] of the [[German Reich]], during the [[Weimar Republic]] era.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann p4&quot;&gt;Schumann 2000, p. 4.&lt;/ref&gt; He was the first of four children of mechanical engineer and merchant Alfred Schnaufer and his wife Martha, née Frey. The other three children were his brother Manfred, his sister Waltraut and his brother Eckart.{{refn|Waltraut married Schanufer's adjutant, ''[[Oberleutnant]]'' Georg Fengler, on 15 April 1950.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hinchliffe p268&quot;/&gt;|group=&quot;Note&quot;}} His father owned and operated the family business, the winery ''Schnaufer-Schlossbergkellerei'' ([[literal translation|lit.]] &quot;Schnaufer's Castle Mountain Winery&quot;), in the Lederstraße, Calw.&lt;ref name=&quot;Entwicklung&quot;&gt;{{cite web |work=Schnaufer—Schlossbergkellerei GmbH |title=Die Entwicklung bis 1945 |trans_title=The Development up to 1945 |url=http://www.schlossbergkellerei.de/kellerei/ein-historischer-r%C3%BCckblick/die-aufbaujahre/ |language=German |accessdate=25 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Calw schnaufer1.jpg|thumb|left|upright|House Schnaufer&lt;br /&gt;Home of the ''Schlossbergkellerei''|alt=A colour photograph of a timber framed house with a red truck standing in front.]]
The winery had been founded by both his father and his grandfather, Hermann Schnaufer, in 1919, shortly after [[World War I]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |work=Schnaufer—Schlossbergkellerei GmbH |title=Die Firmengründung im Jahr 1919 |trans_title=The Company Formation in 1919 |url=http://www.schlossbergkellerei.de/kellerei/ein-historischer-r%C3%BCckblick/die-firmengr%C3%BCndung/ |language=German |accessdate=19 August 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following the death of his grandfather in 1928 the winery was run by his father alone. When his father unexpectedly died in 1940, his mother ran the business until the children took over the winery after World War II. The company then expanded the business and in addition to the winery offered wine imports, [[sparkling wine]]s, and a [[distillery]] for wine and [[liqueur]]. The distribution channel worked with agents and sales offices throughout Germany.&lt;ref name=&quot;Entwicklung&quot;/&gt;

Schnaufer, at the age of six, went to the local ''[[Volksschule]]'' (primary school) at Calw. After completing his fourth grade, he received two years of schooling at the ''[[Oberschule]]'', also in Calw. At an early age he expressed his wish to join an organisation of military character and joined the ''[[Deutsches Jungvolk]]'' (German Youth) in 1933.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt; After completing his sixth grade at school he took and passed the entry examination at the [[Backnang]] [[National Political Institutes of Education]] (''Nationalpolitische Erziehungsanstalt''—Napola), a [[Secondary school|secondary]] [[boarding school]] founded under the recently established [[Nazi Germany|Nazi state]]. The goal of the Napola schools was to raise a new generation for the political, military and administrative leadership of the [[Third Reich]]. Schnaufer was considered a very good student, finishing top of his class every year. Aged seventeen he graduated with his ''[[Abitur]]'' (diploma) in November 1939 with distinction. At the Napola school he also received the [[German Sports Badge|Reich Youth Sports Badge]] (''Reichsjugendsportabzeichen''), the base-certificate of the German Life Saving Association (''[[DLRG|Deutsche Lebens-Rettungs-Gesellschaft]]''), the bronze [[Hitler Youth]]-Performance Badge (''HJ-Leistungsabzeichen''), and completed his B-license to fly [[Glider (aircraft)|glider aircraft]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann p4&quot;/&gt; In 1939 Schnaufer was one of two students posted to the Napola in [[Potsdam]]. The Flying Platoon (''Fliegerzug'') stationed in Potsdam centralised all the destined flyers from all the Napolas. Here he learned to fly glider aircraft, at first short hops on the [[DFS SG 38 Schulgleiter]], and later on the two-seater [[Göppingen Gö 4]] which was towed by a [[Klemm Kl 25]].&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, pp. 20–21.&lt;/ref&gt; During his stay at Potsdam, the film producer [[Karl Ritter (director)|Karl Ritter]] was making the [[Universum Film AG|Ufa]] film ''[[Cadets (film)|Cadets]]'' in Potsdam. The Napola had detached two companies to work on the film, among them Schnaufer. It remains unclear exactly what role he played in this film.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 21.&lt;/ref&gt;

Following his graduation from school, Schnaufer passed his entry exams for officer cadets of the Luftwaffe. He joined the Luftwaffe on 15 November 1939 and underwent his [[Recruit training|basic military training]] at the ''Fliegerausbildungsregiment'' 42 (42nd Flight Training Regiment) at [[Salzwedel]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann p4&quot;/&gt; Schnaufer was appointed as ''[[Fahnenjunker]]'' (cadet) on 1 April 1940.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann p2&quot;&gt;Schumann 2000, p. 2.&lt;/ref&gt; He then received his flight training at the ''Flugzeugführerschule'' A/B 3 (FFS A/B 3—flight school for the [[pilot license]]) at [[Guben]], now the [[Cottbus-Drewitz Airport]].&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;Flight training in the Luftwaffe progressed through the levels A1, A2 and B1, B2, referred to as A/B flight training. A training included theoretical and practical training in aerobatics, navigation, long-distance flights and dead-stick landings. The B courses included high-altitude flights, instrument flights, night landings and training to handle the aircraft in difficult situations. For pilots destined to fly multi-engine aircraft, the training was completed with the Luftwaffe Advanced Pilot's Certificate (''Erweiterter Luftwaffen-Flugzeugführerschein''), also known as the C-Certificate.&lt;/ref&gt; He completed his A/B flight training on 20 August 1940. He was trained to fly the [[Focke-Wulf Fw 44]], [[Focke-Wulf Fw 56|Fw 56]] and [[Focke-Wulf Fw 58|Fw 58]], and the [[Heinkel He 72]], [[Heinkel HD 41|HD 41]] and [[Heinkel He 51|He 51]], the [[Bücker Bü 131]], the [[Klemm Kl 35]], the [[Arado Ar 66]] and [[Arado Ar 96|Ar 96]], the [[Gotha Go 145]] and the [[Junkers W 34]] and [[Junkers A 35|A 35]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann p4&quot;/&gt;

Schnaufer then attended the advanced ''Flugzeugführerschule'' C 3 (FFS C 3—advanced flight school) at [[Falkenberg/Elster|Alt Lönnewitz]] near [[Torgau]] and the [[blind flying]] school ''Blindflugschule'' 2 (BFS 2—2nd blind flying school) at [[Neuburg an der Donau]] from August 1940 to May 1941. This qualified him to fly multi-engine aircraft. During this assignment he was promoted to ''[[Fähnrich]]'' (cadet sergeant) on 1 September 1940, to ''Oberfähnrich'' (rank equivalent to [[Company Sergeant Major]]) on 1 February 1941 and to the officer rank of ''[[Leutnant]]'' (second lieutenant) on 1 April 1941.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann p4&quot;/&gt; He was then posted for ten weeks to the ''Zerstörerschule'' (destroyer school) at [[Wunstorf]] near [[Hanover]]. At Wunstorf, Schnaufer and the radio operator (''Bordfunker'') [[Friedrich Rumpelhardt]] were assigned as an aircrew team on 3 July 1941. Schnaufer's previous radio operator had proved unable to cope with aerobatics, and Schnaufer thoroughly tested Rumpelhardt's ability to cope with aerobatics before they teamed up. Here the two decided to volunteer to fly night fighters to defend against the increasing [[Royal Air Force]] (RAF) [[RAF Bomber Command|Bomber Command]] offensive against Germany.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, pp. 28–30.&lt;/ref&gt; Following their training at Wunstorf, the two were sent to the ''Nachtjagdschule'' 1 (1st night fighter school) at [[Schleißheim]] near [[Munich]], formerly the ''Zerstörerschule'' 1 (ZS 1—1st destroyer school), to learn the rudiments of night-fighting.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann p4&quot;/&gt; The night fighter training was carried out on the Ar 96, the Fw 58 and the [[Messerschmitt Bf 110]]. Training at night focused on night [[takeoff]]s and [[landing]]s, cooperation with [[searchlight]]s, [[Electric beacon|radio-beacon]] [[direction finding]] and cross country flights.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hinchliffe p38&quot;&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 38.&lt;/ref&gt;

==World War II==
&lt;!-- [[Image:Kammhuber Line Map - Agent Tegal.png|thumb|right|A map of part of the ''Kammhuber Line'' stolen by a [[Belgian]] agent and passed-on to the British in 1942. The 'belt' and night fighter 'boxes' are shown.|alt=Black-and-white photograph of a gritted map indicating the position of radar stations.]] --&gt;
In November 1941, Schnaufer was posted to the II. ''[[Organization of the Luftwaffe (1933–45)#Gruppe|Gruppe]]'' of [[Nachtjagdgeschwader 1|''Nachtjagdgeschwader'' 1]] (II./NJG 1—2nd group of the 1st Night Fighter Wing) at the time based at [[Stade]] near [[Hamburg]].&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;For an explanation of the meaning of ''Luftwaffe'' unit designation see [[Organization of the Luftwaffe (1933–45)|Organisation of the Luftwaffe during World War II]].&lt;/ref&gt; Here, Schnaufer was assigned to the 5. ''[[Organization of the Luftwaffe (1933–45)#Staffel|Staffel]]'' (5./NJG 1—5th squadron of 1st Night Fighter Wing).&lt;ref name=&quot;Hinchliffe p38&quot;/&gt; The Bf 110's of II./NJG 1 at the time were not equipped with airborne radar such as the [[Lichtenstein radar|''Lichtenstein'' radar]]. Night fighter intercept tactics had matured since their early beginnings in July 1940, and II. ''Gruppe'' had already been credited with 397 victories. Missions against enemy bombers at the time were usually flown by means of [[ground-controlled interception]], although the Luftwaffe was already experimenting with airborne radar. This air defence system, consisting of a series of radar stations with overlapping coverage, layered three deep, was conceived by ''[[Generalleutnant]]'' (lit. Lieutenant General; [[Comparative officer ranks of World War II|equivalent to Major General]]) [[Josef Kammhuber]] and was organised in the so-called [[Kammhuber Line]]. Conceptually, the system was based on a combination of ground-based radar stations, search lights and a ''Jägerleitoffizier'' (fighter pilot control officer). The ''Jägerleitoffizier'' had to vector the airborne night fighter by means of radio communication to a point of visual interception of the illuminated bomber. These interception tactics were referred to as the ''Himmelbett'' (canopy bed) procedure.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, pp. 32–37, 39.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 15 January 1942, II./NJG 1 transferred to [[Sint-Truiden]]—Saint-Trond in the French pronunciation—in Belgium. Schnaufer entered front-line service at a time when the RAF was reassessing the [[air offensive]] against Germany. The effectiveness of British Bomber Command to accurately hit German targets had been questioned by the War Cabinet Secretary [[David Bensusan-Butt]] who published the [[Butt Report]] in August 1941. The report in parts concluded that the British crews failed to navigate to, identify, and bomb their targets. Although the report was not widely accepted by senior RAF commanders, Prime Minister [[Winston Churchill]], instructed Commander-in-Chief [[Richard Peirse]] that during the winter months only limited operations were to be conducted. Flight operations were also hindered by bad weather in the first months of 1942, so II./NJG 1 only saw very limited action during that period.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, pp. 40–41.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Channel Dash and night fighter pilot===
On 8 February 1942, II. ''Gruppe'' was transferred to [[Koksijde Air Base]] without having scored any victories while stationed at Sint-Truiden. The objective of this assignment was to give the German [[battleship]]s {{ship|German battleship|Scharnhorst||2}} and {{ship|German battleship|Gneisenau||2}} and the [[heavy cruiser]] {{ship|German cruiser|Prinz Eugen||2}} fighter protection in the breakout from [[Brest, France|Brest]] to Germany. The [[Channel Dash]] operation (11–13 February 1942) by the ''[[Kriegsmarine]]'' (Navy) was codenamed Operation Cerberus by the Germans. In support of this, the Luftwaffe under the leadership of ''[[General der Jagdflieger]]'' (General of the Fighter Force) [[Adolf Galland]], formulated an [[air superiority]] plan dubbed [[Operation Donnerkeil]] for the protection of the three German capital ships. II./NJG 1 was briefed of these plans on the early morning on 12 February. The plan called for protection of the German ships at all costs. The crews were told that if they ran out of ammunition they must ram the enemy aircraft. To the relief of the night fighters they were assigned to the first-line reserves.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, pp. 41–42.&lt;/ref&gt; The operation, which took the British by surprise, was successful and the night fighters were kept in their reserve role. On the evening of 12 February, II./NJG 1 was relocated to [[Amsterdam Airport Schiphol]]. On the afternoon of 13 February, Schnaufer flew a reconnaissance mission over the [[Zuiderzee]] and the [[North Sea]] and then relocated to [[Westerland, Germany|Westerland]] on the island of [[Sylt]]. They then relocated again to [[Aalborg]]-West in Denmark from where they made a low-level flight in close formation over the [[Skaggerak]], landing at [[Stavanger Airport, Sola|Stavanger-Sola]]. Over the following days they operated from the airfield at [[Forus]], making a short term landing at [[Bergen Airport, Flesland|Bergen-Herdla]]. In total, Schnaufer made two operational flights without contact with the enemy. Following this assignment they relocated to 5. ''Staffel''{{'}}s new base in Germany at [[Sankt Augustin|Bonn-Hangelar]] via [[Oslo Airport, Gardermoen|Oslo-Gardermoen]], Aalborg, and [[Lüneburg]].&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, pp. 43–45.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-680-8274A-15A, Funkleitstelle für Nachtjäger.jpg|thumb|left|Radio control center for night fighters, ''Jägerleitoffiziere'' and assistants plotting courses and directing the airborne fighters.|alt=Black-and-white photograph of men and women wearing headsets standing around a table and making notes on a large map.]]
Following the analysis of the Butt Report, the British High Command made a number of decisions in February 1942 that changed the nature of the bomber war against Germany. On 14 February, [[Air Chief Marshal]] [[Norman Bottomley]] issued the &quot;[[Area bombing directive|Area Bombing Directive]]&quot;, which lifted the restrictions placed on the bombers in 1941. Air Chief Marshal [[Sir Arthur Harris, 1st Baronet|Arthur Harris]], commonly known as &quot;Bomber&quot; Harris, was appointed Commander-in-Chief of Bomber Command. These decisions, coupled with the introduction of [[Gee (navigation)|Gee]], a [[radio navigation]] system which enabled better target-finding and bombing accuracy, led to the first Allied 1,000 bomber raid. In [[Bombing of Cologne in World War II|Operation Millennium]], the RAF targeted and bombed [[Cologne]] on the night of 30/31 May 1942.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, pp. 44–46.&lt;/ref&gt; Schnaufer did not participate in the missions in defence of Cologne. The ''Himmelbett'' procedure had limitations in the number of aircraft which can be controlled. Therefore, only the most experienced crews were deployed, and Rumpelhardt and Schnaufer, who had yet to achieve their first aerial victory, were left out.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 47.&lt;/ref&gt; Prior to Operation Millennium, Schnaufer had been appointed ''Technischer Offizier'' (TO—Technical Officer) on 10 April 1942 and was located at Sint-Truiden again. As a Technical Officer, Schnaufer was responsible for the supervision of all technical aspects such as routine maintenance, servicing and modifications of the ''Gruppe''. In this role he was no longer a member of the 5. ''Staffel'' but was then a member of the ''[[Stab (Luftwaffe designation)|Stab]]'' (staff) of II./NJG 1.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, pp. 45–46.&lt;/ref&gt;

Schnaufer claimed his first aerial victory on their thirteenth combat mission flown one day after the attack on Cologne on the night 1/2 June 1942. Nominally this was the RAF's second 1,000 bomber raid against Germany, although the attacking force actually numbered 956 aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, pp. 47–48.&lt;/ref&gt; Schnaufer shot down a [[Handley Page Halifax]] south of [[Leuven|Louvain]] in [[Belgium]].&lt;ref&gt;Foreman, Matthews and Parry 2004, p. 43.&lt;/ref&gt; The aircraft probably was a Halifax from [[No. 76 Squadron RAF|No. 76 Squadron]] piloted by [[Sergeant]] Thomas Robert Augustus West, which was shot down at 01:55 on 2 June 1942 and crashed at [[Grez-Doiceau]], {{convert|15|km|mi}} south of Louvain. West and another member of the crew were killed. This victory was achieved by ground-controlled interception through the Kammhuber Line. Once near to the target, Rumpelhardt had visually found the bomber and directed Schnaufer into attack position from below and astern. The Halifax caught on fire after two firing passes. During this mission the ''Himmelbett'' flight officer vectored them to a second bomber, a [[Bristol Blenheim]]. The attack had to be aborted after ''[[Hauptmann]]'' (Captain) [[Walter Ehle]] shot down the bomber from a more favourable attack position. Shortly before 03:00, they were then flying in the vicinity of [[Ghent]], they spotted another target. Schnaufer made two unsuccessful attacks.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 49.&lt;/ref&gt; During their third attack, which closed the distance to {{Convert|20|m|ft}}, they were hit by the defensive gunfire. Schnaufer was hit in his left calf, the port engine was burning, the rudder control cables were severed, and an electrical short circuit caused the [[Aircraft landing lights|landing lights]] to be permanently on. Rumpelhardt and Schnaufer considered [[Parachute|bailing out]] but decided to make an attempt for their home airfield after they managed to put out the flames and restart the engine. While Rumpelhardt made radio contact with the Sint-Truiden airbase, Schnaufer landed the aircraft without rudder control and on [[aileron]]s and engine-power alone.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 50.&lt;/ref&gt; This was the only time that their aircraft sustained damage in combat or any member of the crew was wounded. Both Rumpelhardt and Schnaufer were awarded the [[Iron Cross]] 2nd Class for their first aerial victory. Schnaufer had hoped that he could stay on active duty and that the bullet lodged in his calf would isolate itself. However, he had to be admitted to a hospital in Brussels from 8–25 June for surgery. Rumpelhardt was given home leave until 26 June while Schnaufer was in the hospital.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, pp. 51, 298.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Lichtenstein FuG 202 Viestimuseo 2.JPG|thumb|right|''Lichtenstein'' [[cathode-ray]] tubes:&lt;br /&gt;{{*}}The left tube indicated other aircraft ahead as bumps.&lt;br /&gt;{{*}}The centre tube indicated range to a specific target and whether they were higher or lower.&lt;br /&gt;{{*}}The right tube indicated whether the target was to left or right.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hinchliffe p56&quot;&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 56.&lt;/ref&gt;|alt=An electrical device with three round displays, cables and control knobs.]]
Schnaufer had to wait two months to achieve another victory, claiming the destruction of two [[Vickers Wellington]]s and one [[Armstrong Whitworth Whitley]] within the space of 62 minutes in the early hours of 1 August.&lt;ref&gt;Foreman, Matthews and Parry 2004, p. 53.&lt;/ref&gt; Rumpelhardt and Schnaufer flew their first combat mission with the ''Lichtenstein'' radar on the night 5/6 August 1942. Though they managed to make contact with an enemy aircraft they failed to shoot it down.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, pp. 55–56.&lt;/ref&gt; On the night of the 24/25 August 1942, Schnaufer became an ace (his fifth aerial victory), when he filed a claim for another Wellington. This was the first time Rumpelhardt had guided him into contact using the FuG 202 ''Lichtenstein B/C'' UHF-band airborne radar.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hinchliffe p56&quot;/&gt; His next claim was made on the night of 28/29 August.&lt;ref&gt;Foreman, Matthews and Parry 2004, p. 56.&lt;/ref&gt; This was probably a [[No. 78 Squadron RAF|No. 78 Squadron]] Halifax II ''W7809'', piloted by Sergeant John A. B. Marshall of the [[Royal Australian Air Force]], on a secondary attack against [[Saarbrücken]]. The primary attack force was targeting [[Nuremberg]] that night.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, pp. 60–61.&lt;/ref&gt; On the night of the 21/22 December 1942, Schnaufer shot down an [[Avro Lancaster]]; his first victory against this type. It was Schnaufer's seventh victory.&lt;ref&gt;Foreman, Matthews and Parry 2004, p. 63.&lt;/ref&gt; Schnaufer may also have been responsible for the destruction of another Lancaster that night. Rumpelhardt and Schnaufer had attacked a Lancaster and observed it catching fire followed by the aircraft plunging earthwards. ''Hauptmann'' [[Wilhelm Herget]] from I./[[Nachtjagdgeschwader 4|''Nachtjagdgeschwader'' 4]] (I./NJG 4—1st group of the 4th Night Fighter Wing) had also attacked a four-engined bomber in the same vicinity. The [[Tie (draw)|draw]] decided in favour of Herget who was given credit for the destruction of the Lancaster.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, pp. 64–65.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Rumpelhardt is absent===
By the end of 1942, Schnaufer's total stood at seven, with three victories recorded on the night of 1 August, which had earned him the Iron Cross 1st Class in early September 1942. From 29 November to 16 December 1942, Rumpelhardt was confined to the hospital bed with high fever.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 61.&lt;/ref&gt; Rumpelhardt then attended various officer training courses from February to October 1943. Between 14 May to 3 October 1943, Schnaufer claimed 21 further aerial victories in Rumpelhardt's absence; 12 with ''Leutnant'' Dr. Leo Baro, five with ''Oberfeldwebel'' [[Erich Handke]], two with ''Oberleutnant'' Freymann and two with ''Unteroffizier'' Heinz Bärwolf as his radio operators.&lt;ref&gt;Schumann 2000, p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Unteroffizier'' Heinz Wenning had also flown with Schnaufer on three flights while Rumpelhardt was out ill.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 72.&lt;/ref&gt;

II./NJG 1 saw little action in the first few months of 1943, and Schnaufer did not claim his next aerial victory until 14 May 1943. II./NJG 1 ''Himmelbett'' control areas were located to catch the bombers heading for the [[Ruhr Area]]. Bomber Command had only made ten major attacks in that region from January to April 1943. Consequently, II./NJG 1 claimed no victories in January, two in February, one in March and three in April.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, pp. 68, 70.&lt;/ref&gt; Schnaufer's number of aerial victories increased again during the [[Battle of the Ruhr]]. Schnaufer, with Baro as his radio operator, shot down a [[No. 214 Squadron RAF|No. 214 Squadron]] [[Short Stirling]] ''R9242'' at 02:14 on 14 May 1943 on an attack mission against Bochum. Four members of the crew, including pilot Sergeant R. M. Gibney, lost their lives. His next victory on the same mission at 03:07, his 9th overall, was a No. 98 Squadron Halifax ''JB873'' returning from Bochum. The captain, Sergeant G. Dane and 2nd pilot Sergeant J. H. Body were killed in the crash.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 74&quot;&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 74.&lt;/ref&gt; On the night of 29/30 May, Bomber Command attacked [[Wuppertal]]. Schnaufer and Baro took off on the first wave at 23:51 on 29 May and returned at 02:31 on the 30 May. They shot down two Stirlings, one at 00:48 and the other at 02:22, and one Halifax at 01:43.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 75.&lt;/ref&gt;

In June 1943, Schnaufer filed claims for a further five aerial victories. Schnaufer and Baro were scrambled on 11/12 June in Bomber Command's attack on [[Düsseldorf]], and on 16/17 June in defence of Cologne. However, in both missions they failed to make contact with the enemy. Their next success came when they shot down a Stirling from No. 218 Squadron on 22 June 1943 at 01:33.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, pp. 77–78.&lt;/ref&gt; With Baro on the radio and radar, they managed another victory over a Wellington on 25 June 1943 at 02:58. On 29 June 1943, the two shot down three bombers in another attack on Cologne, a Lancaster and two Halifax bombers at 01:25, 01:45 and 01:55 respectively.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 74&quot;/&gt; This brought the number of aerial victories he was credited with up to seventeen. Schnaufer was promoted to ''[[Oberleutnant]]'' (first lieutenant) on 1 July 1943.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 87.&lt;/ref&gt; He had been eligible for this promotion since April 1943, why he was overlooked at the time remains unknown.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, pp. 72–73.&lt;/ref&gt;

Schnaufer claimed his last two aerial victories with Baro operating the radio on the night of 3/4 July, Bomber Command had again targeted Cologne. Their victims were a [[No. 196 Squadron RAF|No. 196 Squadron]] Wellington shot down at 00:48 and a [[No. 149 Squadron RAF|No. 149 Squadron]] Stirling at 02:33, bringing his total to 19 victories.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 81.&lt;/ref&gt; His next radio operator was ''Oberleutnant'' Freymann, the signals operator of II. ''Gruppe''. Under ''Himmelbett'' control they shot down a [[No. 49 Squadron RAF|No. 49 Squadron]] Lancaster, on another Cologne bombing mission, on 9 July 1943 at 02:33.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 85.&lt;/ref&gt; He was awarded the [[Honour Goblet of the Luftwaffe]] ({{Lang|de|''Ehrenpokal der Luftwaffe''}}) on 26 July 1943.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann p5&quot;&gt;Schumann 2000, p. 5.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Window - Lancaster Dropping Window.jpg|thumb|left|A Lancaster dropping Window]]
In mid-July, the Battle of the Ruhr was coming to an end and Bomber Command refocused its efforts on the port city of Hamburg in northern Germany. The codename for the attack was [[Operation Gomorrah]]; the objective was the destruction of Hamburg. The operations began on 24 July 1943 and during four major night-attacks by the RAF and two minor day-attacks by [[United States Army Air Forces]] (USAAF) between 40,000 and 50,000 civilians were killed. To counter the mounting success of the German night fighter force, which was directly attributed to the introduction of the ''Lichtenstein'' radar, the RAF introduced [[Chaff (countermeasure)|Window]] (Chaff or ''Düppel'' to the Germans). Window was a radar [[countermeasure]] in which aircraft spread a cloud of small, thin pieces of [[aluminium]] which effectively made it impossible for the German radar operator to identify the genuine target.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, pp. 85–86.&lt;/ref&gt; Saturation of the ''Himmelbett'' control areas by a [[bomber stream]] and the introduction of Window practically made the previous ''Himmelbett'' procedure obsolete. This was also evident to the German high command. To counter these British measures two new strategies were pursued, ''[[Wilde Sau]]'' (Wild Boar) and ''[[Zahme Sau]]'' (Tame Boar). ''Wilde Sau'', conceived by [[Hajo Herrmann|Hans-Joachim Herrmann]], was a technique by which the RAF bombers were mainly engaged by single-seat fighter planes, illuminated by searchlights, over the target area. The ''Zahme Sau'' procedure, proposed by [[Viktor von Loßberg]], called for a night fighter to infiltrate the bomber stream. The position, altitude, and general direction was then broadcast. The information was received by other night fighters, who navigated to the bomber stream by themselves.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 88.&lt;/ref&gt; In ''Zahme Sau'', the German night fighters were tracked and radio-controlled by means of [[Luftwaffe radio equipment (Funkgerät) of World War II|Y-''Verfahren'']] (Y-Control).&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 89.&lt;/ref&gt; Schnaufer did not make any claims during Operation Gomorrah. Their next success came when he and Freymann shot down a Lancaster on 10/11 August 1943 at 00:32. The target that night was Nuremberg and it was the first aerial victory of the entire German night fighter force achieved by Y-Control. This was also the last victory with Freymann and his last as a member of II. ''Gruppe''.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 90.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Squadron leader of 12.''Staffel''/NJG 1===
Schnaufer was transferred to IV ''Gruppe'' of NJG 1 (IV./NJG 1—4th group of the 1st Night Fighter Wing), based in the Netherlands at [[Leeuwarden Air Base]], where he was appointed ''[[Staffelkapitän]]'' (squadron leader) of the 12. ''Staffel'' (12./NJG 1—12th squadron of 1st Night Fighter Wing) on 13 August 1943. He took over command from ''Oberleutnant'' Eberhard Gardiewski, who had been taken [[prisoner of war]].{{refn|Gardiewski was shot down in combat with a USAAF [[Boeing B-17 Flying Fortress|B-17 Flying Fortress]] over the North Sea on a daylight mission and was rescued by an RAF [[air-sea rescue]] vessel.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hinchliffe p91&quot;&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 91.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=&quot;Note&quot;}} At the time, IV./NJG 1 was under the leadership of ''[[Gruppenkommandeur]]'' (Group Commander) ''Hauptmann'' [[Hans-Joachim Jabs]]. Jabs' first impression of Schnaufer was not entirely favourable. Shortly after Schnaufer's arrival, on one of his first missions in Leeuwarden, Schnaufer had taken right of way during [[taxiing]]. This forced Jabs into second place in order of takeoff, an act of [[insubordination]] and perceived as arrogant by Jabs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hinchliffe p91&quot;/&gt;

Schnaufer, who had received the [[German Cross]] in Gold on 16 August 1943, flew his first operational mission with 12./NJG 1 on the night of 17/18 August 1943.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann p5&quot;/&gt; Although uncertain, it is assumed that Handke was Schnaufer's radio and radar operator on this mission. Bomber Command had targeted [[Peenemünde]] and the [[Peenemünde Army Research Center|V-weapons test centre]] that night. Schnaufer, who had been tasked with leading one of the first ''Zahme Sau'' missions under Y-Control, had to abort the mission early due to engine trouble.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 93.&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|Five [[Bristol Beaufighter]] [[night fighter]]s of [[No. 141 Squadron RAF|No. 141 Squadron]], under the command of [[Wing Commander (rank)|Wing Commander]] [[Bob Braham]], intercepted the German flight, and ''Feldwebel'' Georg Kraft and ''Feldwebel'' [[Heinz Vinke]] were both shot down by Braham. Kraft's radio operator ''Unteroffizier'' Rudi Dunger and Vinke were the only ones to survive.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, pp. 93–94.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=&quot;Note&quot;}}

[[File:Me 110 SM.jpg|thumb|right|Rear view of a Bf 110G's rear cockpit glazing with [[MG FF cannon|MG FF/M]] ''Schräge Musik''.]]
Around mid-September 1943, the two-man Bf 110 crew was augmented by a third member, sometimes referred to as ''Bordmechaniker'' ([[Flight engineer|air mechanic]]) or ''Bordschütze'' ([[air gunner]]). The reason for this was that the decline of the ''Himmelbett'' procedure, the introduction of the broadcast procedure ''Zahme Sau'', and the growing threat of RAF [[Intruder (air combat)|intruder]] night fighter operations, had necessitated the need for another pair of watchful eyes to the rear. ''Unteroffizier'' [[Wilhelm Gänsler]], who had already contributed to 17 claims made by ''Hauptmann'' [[Ludwig Becker (pilot)|Ludwig Becker]], was Schnaufer's new [[lookout]].&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, pp. 98–100.&lt;/ref&gt; With Handtke and Gänsler as his crew, Schnaufer claimed his 26th aerial victory on 23 September 1943 over a [[No. 218 Squadron RAF|No. 218 Squadron]] Stirling during a ''Wilde Sau'' intercept mission.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, pp. 102, 299.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the second half of 1943, Schnaufer and his crew began experimenting with upward-firing [[autocannon]]s, dubbed ''[[Schräge Musik]]''. This allowed the night fighter to approach and attack the bombers from below—outside the enemy crew's usual field of view. An attack by a ''Schräge Musik''-equipped night fighter typically came as a complete surprise to the bomber crew, who only realised a night fighter was close by when they came under fire. It is not exactly known when Schnaufer's Bf 110 was equipped with ''Schräge Musik''. Rumpelhardt stated that the weapons system was installed prior to his return from officer training.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, pp. 105–110.&lt;/ref&gt; It is also not exactly known how many of his victories had been claimed using the upwards firing cannons. According to Fritz Engau, who had known Schnaufer since ''Flugzeugführerschule'' C 3, 20 to 30 of Schnaufer's aerial victories had been claimed using upwards firing guns.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, pp. 62, 112.&lt;/ref&gt;

Rumpelhardt had returned from his officer training courses in early October 1943 and rejoined Schnaufer's crew. Gänsler, Rumpelhardt and Schnaufer claimed aerial victories 29 and 30 on 9 October.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 121.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Oberleutnant'' Schnaufer was awarded the [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross]] for 42 victories on 31 December 1943. The presentation was made by ''[[Generalmajor]]'' (lit. Major General; equivalent to [[Brigadier]]) [[Joseph Schmid]], commanding general of the [[1st Fighter Corps (Germany)|I. ''Jagdkorps'']] (1st Fighter Corps), on 3 January 1944.&lt;ref&gt;Schumann 2000, pp. 7, 16.&lt;/ref&gt;

On the night before his 22nd birthday, on 15 February 1944, Schnaufer and his crew claimed aerial victories 45 to 47. Bomber Command had sent 561 Lancasters and 314 Halifax four-engined bombers, supported by [[de Havilland Mosquito]] night-fighters and bombers, destined for Berlin.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 144.&lt;/ref&gt; Schnaufer, who had been suffering from stomach pains all day, and his crew returned to Leeuwarden at 00:14. Rumpelhardt had been the first to congratulate him on his birthday over the intercom. Their fellow airmen had prepared a birthday celebration.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 145.&lt;/ref&gt; The stomach pains had become unbearable and Schnaufer was taken to a hospital with [[appendicitis]]. He stayed in the hospital for about two weeks before, together with Rumpelhardt, he went on vacation back home. Carelessly lifting his suitcase, the stitches burst, mandating further hospitalisation. He flew his first mission after these events on 19 March 1944.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 146.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Group commander of the IV./NJG 1===
[[File:Lang Hartmann Schnaufer Kaubisch Skrizpek Glunz.jpg|thumb|right|[[Friedrich Lang]], [[Erich Hartmann]] and Heinz-Wolfgang Schnaufer receive the Oak Leaves with Swords, [[Horst Kaubisch]], [[Eduard Skrzipek]] and [[Adolf Glunz]] the Oak Leaves to the Knight's Cross from [[Adolf Hitler]]|alt=Six men all wearing military uniforms and decorations standing in row. The third man from the far right is shaking hands with another man.]]
Schnaufer was appointed ''Gruppenkommandeur'' IV./NJG 1 on 1 March 1944, taking over command of the ''Gruppe'' from Jabs who was given command of NJG 1.&lt;ref&gt;Schumann 2000, p. 7.&lt;/ref&gt; He was promoted to ''Hauptmann'' on 1 May 1944.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 174.&lt;/ref&gt; Schnaufer became an [[Aviators who became ace in a day|ace-in-a-day]] for the first time on 25 May 1944 when he claimed five RAF bombers shot down between 01:15 and 01:29 for victories 70 to 74. The bombers had targeted the railway [[marshalling yard]] at [[Aachen]].&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, pp. 176, 300–301.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 6 June 1944, the [[Western Allies|Western Allied]] forces landed in [[Normandy]], during [[Operation Overlord]]. In support of the [[invasion of Normandy]] General [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]], the [[Supreme Allied Commander]], assigned Bomber Command to support the ground forces. On the night of 12/13 June, Schnaufer claimed his first victory following the invasion when 671 bombers attacked various railway targets in France. Schnaufer claimed three bombers shot down that night, the first as a Lancaster and the second and third as a Lancaster or Halifax, between 00:27 and 00:34.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 179.&lt;/ref&gt;

''Hauptmann'' Schnaufer was awarded the [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves]] on 24 June following four aerial victories claimed on 22 June, which took his total to 84 victories.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, pp. 185–186.&lt;/ref&gt; For Schnaufer, July 1944 was less successful than the previous three months. He claimed two bombers on the night of 20/21 July and three on 28/29 July, taking his total to 89 aerial victories.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, pp. 189–192.&lt;/ref&gt; One day later, on 30 July, he received a letter from Göring telling him that he had been awarded the [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves and Swords]].&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 196.&lt;/ref&gt; Hitler himself made the presentation. It is said that when he came to the presentation his first words were, &quot;Where is the night fighter?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 201.&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly following the presentation of the ''Schwerter'' both Rumpelhardt and Gänsler received the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross on 8 August. His crew was the only night fighter crew in the entire Luftwaffe of which all crew members wore this decoration.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 204&quot;&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 204.&lt;/ref&gt;

In early September 1944, NJG 1 was forced to abandon its airfields in the Netherlands and Belgium. Continuous heavy attacks by RAF and USAAF bombers and strafing by Allied [[fighter-bomber]]s rendered the airfields unsuitable for operations. On 2 September, VI./NJG 1 relocated from Sint-Truiden to Dortmund-Brackel.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 204&quot;/&gt; Schnaufer achieved his 100th victory on 9 October 1944, when he claimed two bombers shot down from an attack force of 415 bombers targeting [[Bochum]]. In recognition of this achievement, he was mentioned in the  ''[[Wehrmachtbericht]]'' on 10 October 1944 and awarded the [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves, Swords and Diamonds]] on 16 October 1944.&lt;ref name=&quot;Kurowski p380&quot;&gt;Kurowski 1996, p. 380.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 216.&lt;/ref&gt; He was the 94th ''Luftwaffe'' pilot to achieve the century mark.&lt;ref&gt;Obermaier 1989, p. 243.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Wing commander of ''Nachtjagdgeschwader'' 4===
Schnaufer was then appointed ''[[Geschwaderkommodore]]'' (wing commander) of ''Nachtjagdgeschwader'' 4 (NJG 4—4th Night Fighter Wing) on 20 November 1944; the youngest ''Geschwaderkommodore'' in the Luftwaffe at the age of 22. The ''Geschwaderstab'' and the II. ''Gruppe'' were stationed at [[Gütersloh]]. He flew his first combat mission as ''Geschwaderkommodore'' on the 22 November 1944 from Gütersloh and claimed two victories in the area of [[Dortmund]]. Schnaufer and his crew flew from Gütersloh to [[Berlin-Staaken]] on 27 November 1944 for the official presentation of the Diamonds to the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves and Swords by Hitler.&lt;ref&gt;Schumann 2000, p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt; Following the official photo session by Hitler's photographer [[Heinrich Hoffmann (photographer)|Heinrich Hoffmann]], Schnaufer met with ''[[Oberst]]'' (Colonel) [[Nicolaus von Below]], Hitler's Luftwaffe adjutant, at the ''[[Ministry of Aviation (Nazi Germany)|Reichsluftfahrtministerium]]'' (Ministry of Aviation). Here Schnaufer and his crew were filmed for the German [[newsreels]] ''[[Die Deutsche Wochenschau]]''. Three days later they returned to Gütersloh.&lt;ref&gt;Schumann 2000, pp. 18–21.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:RAAF 462 Sqn crew with Me 110 of W Schnaufer 1945.jpg|thumb|left|Members of the [[Royal Australian Air Force]] pose with Schnaufer's [[Bf 110|Bf 110G]]-4 (G9+BA, ''Stab''/NJG 1) at Schleswig, Germany, shortly after the end of the war (19 June 1945)]]
Schnaufer became the leading night fighter pilot on 9 November 1944. Schnaufer surpassed ''Oberst'' [[Helmut Lent]]'s record of 102 night-time victories, after he claimed three Lancasters shot down from a force of 235 Lancasters from [[No. 5 Group RAF|No 5. Group]] which attacked the [[Dortmund-Ems Canal]].&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 218.&lt;/ref&gt; Schnaufer, whose victory total stood at 106 at the end of 1944, failed to shoot down a single bomber in January 1945. It was his first month without filing a claim since April 1943.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 230.&lt;/ref&gt;

Schnaufer was ordered to [[Carinhall]], the residence of the ''[[Reichsmarschall]]'' [[Hermann Göring]], on 8 February 1945. Göring informed him about the intent to appoint him as ''Inspekteur der Nachtjäger'' (Inspector of the night fighter force), a role held by ''Oberst'' [[Werner Streib]] at the time. Schnaufer pushed back, not wanting to push out his friend and mentor from this position. He argued that he would better serve the German cause fighting the enemy. Göring was convinced and Schnaufer remained in his position as ''Geschwaderkommodore''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann p23&quot;&gt;Schumann 2000, p. 23.&lt;/ref&gt;

The British propaganda radio station ''[[Soldatensender Calais]]'' (Soldiers' Radio Calais) congratulated Schnaufer on account of his 23rd birthday on 16 February 1945. The radio station explicitly addressed the soldiers of NJG 4 stationed in Gütersloh followed by the song &quot;''Das Nachtgespenst''&quot; [The Bogeyman] praising him for the honorary title given to him by the British bomber crews &quot;The spook of St. Trond&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann p23&quot;/&gt;

Schnaufer's greatest one-night success and the second time he became an ace-in-a-day was on 21 February 1945, when he claimed nine Lancaster heavy bombers in the course of one day. Two were claimed in the early hours of the morning and a further seven, in just 19 minutes, in the evening between 20:44 and 21:03.&lt;ref&gt;Foreman, Matthews and Parry 2004, p. 236.&lt;/ref&gt; On 7/8 March, he claimed three RAF four-engine bombers for victories 119 to 121. These were his last victories of the war. He was then banned from further combat flying and was given the task of evaluating the then new [[Dornier Do 335]], a twin-engine [[heavy fighter]] with a unique &quot;[[push-pull configuration|push-pull]]&quot; layout, for its suitability as night fighter. Disobeying his ban from combat flying, he flew his last mission of the war on 9 April 1945. Attempting to chase a Lancaster, he took off from [[Faßberg Air Base]] at 22:00 and landed after 79 minutes at 23:19 without success.&lt;ref&gt;Schumann 2000, p. 24.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Prisoner of war==
Schnaufer was taken prisoner of war by the British Army in [[Schleswig-Holstein]] in May 1945. According to Schumann, he was taken to England for [[interrogation]]. In this account British authorities were especially interested in knowing whether his achievements had been made under the influence of [[methamphetamine]] or other [[Stimulant|stimulating]] [[psychoactive drug]]s which induce temporary improvements in either mental or physical functions or both. He was released later that year in November following a bout of [[diphtheria]].&lt;ref&gt;Schumann 2000, p. 32.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Hinchliffe, this is an incorrect statement. Hinchliffe based his account on Rumpelhardt's testimony who claims that Schnaufer was never taken to England. Rumpelhardt was released on 4 August 1945 and soon after Schnaufer was admitted to a hospital in Flensburg, ill with a combination of diphtheria and [[scarlet fever]].&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 257.&lt;/ref&gt; Interrogation had begun in late May 1945 by a team of twelve officers from the [[Technical intelligence|Department of Air Technical Intelligence]] (DAT), led by [[Air Commodore]] [[Roderick Aeneas Chisholm]].&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 248.&lt;/ref&gt; The German prisoners were brought to [[Eggebek]]. Here they conducted a number of interviews with various members of the night fighter force.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 251.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Later life and death==
Following his release from the hospital and as a prisoner of war—the exact date is unknown—Schnaufer took over the family wine business. He had never planned to run the family winery as his ambition had always been to pursue an officer's career in the Luftwaffe. However, in the immediate aftermath of World War II the business had virtually ceased to exist and Schnaufer was given the task of rebuilding it from scratch. He had to re-establish business links to suppliers and customers and to consolidate them. Then he had to make new contacts in order to facilitate expansion and growth of the business. Lastly, he had to create an infrastructure which supported the growth of the business.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 260.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote_box
|quote=&quot;Quality before Quantity.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hinchliffe p261&quot;&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 261.&lt;/ref&gt;
|source=Heinz Schnaufer's business motto
|width=20%
|align=left
}}
As the wine business began to prosper, Schnaufer also gave thought to alternative employment possibilities in peacetime aviation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hinchliffe p261&quot;&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 261.&lt;/ref&gt; With his wartime friend [[Hermann Greiner]], he traveled from [[Weil am Rhein]] to Bern in Switzerland to meet South American diplomats; the two hoped to find employment as pilots in South America. To get to Bern, they crossed the Swiss-German border illegally.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 262.&lt;/ref&gt; The meeting was a failure. As they returned to Germany, they were caught by Swiss border guards attempting to make a second illegal border crossing. The Swiss handed them over to the French occupation authorities and they were imprisoned in [[Lörrach]], where they remained until Schnaufer managed to make contact with a French general, who was a customer of the Schnaufer winery and had them released. This misadventure kept him away from his business for about half a year.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 263.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Heinz-Wolfgang Schnaufer tail fin.JPG|thumb|right|One of the tail fins of Heinz-Wolfgang Schnaufer's Bf 110. It displays all of his 121 victories,Imperial War Museum (2010)]]
In July 1950, Schnaufer was on a wine buying visit to France. On the afternoon of the 13 July, he was heading south on the [[Route nationale 10|''Route Nationale No.'' 10]] in his [[Mercedes-Benz 170S|Mercedes-Benz 170]] [[convertible]] with a registration number &quot;AWW 44-3425&quot;. Just south of [[Bordeaux]], at about 18:30, he was involved in a collision with a Renault 22 truck. The accident occurred at the intersection of road D1, present-day D211, and the N10, present-day D1010, in [[Cestas]] ({{coord|44|42|04|N|0|42|20|W|name=Heinz-Wolfgang Schnaufer road accident}}). The truck, driven by Jean Antoine Gasc, was carrying a {{Convert|6|MT|STabbr=off}} load of empty gas cylinders. The collision ruptured the fuel tank of the Mercedes and ignited the petrol. Witnesses to the accident quickly put out the flames. Alice Ducourneau gave first aid to Schnaufer, who was bleeding from a wound from the back of his head. The police appeared at the scene of the accident at about 19:30, followed by an ambulance shortly thereafter. Schnaufer had suffered a [[fractured skull]], and was immediately taken to the Saint-André Hôpital in Bordeaux.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hinchliffe p268&quot;&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 268.&lt;/ref&gt;

Schnaufer never regained consciousness and succumbed to his injuries at the hospital two days later on 15 July 1950. The investigation into the accident concluded that though the impact of the two vehicles was severe, it seemed unlikely that the collision itself was the cause of his injuries. It was speculated that at least one of the truck's cargo of 30 empty gas cylinders, which were thrown off by the collision, had struck Schnaufer on the head.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hinchliffe p268&quot;/&gt; Subsequently, the truck driver was charged with [[manslaughter]] and breach of traffic regulations before a court at Jauge, Cestas. The hearing began on 29 July 1950 and concluded with his conviction on 16 November 1950. Gasc was found guilty of not yielding the right of way, and his speed was considered too high. It was ruled that as a consequence of not observing the law, he involuntarily caused the death of Schnaufer.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 270.&lt;/ref&gt;

Schnaufer's Messerschmitt Bf 110 G-4/U 8 was brought to England after the war. The aircraft was displayed in London's [[Hyde Park, London|Hyde Park]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann p29&quot;/&gt; The port-side [[vertical stabiliser]] of this [[twin tail]]ed aircraft, tallying all his victories, is preserved at the [[Imperial War Museum]] in London.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |year=2011 |url=http://www.iwm.org.uk/collections/item/object/30084143 |accessdate=1 July 2012 |title=EPH 2961 - fin fragment from a German Messerschmitt Me 110 aircraft (flown by Major Heinz Wolfgang Schnaufer) |work=Imperial War Museum Collection Search |author=[[Imperial War Museum]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; A fin from another Bf 110 flown by Schnaufer is at the [[Australian War Memorial]] in Canberra. The street &quot;Heinz-Schnaufer-Straße&quot; in Calw was named after him.&lt;ref&gt;{{Google maps|url=https://maps.google.com/maps?hl=en&amp;q=from:+%20Waldenserstraße%20@+48.71760,%20+8.7607+to:+B-295%20@+48.7115,%20+8.7685|accessdate=24 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aerial victory credits==
Heinz-Wolfgang Schnaufer was the top-scoring night fighter pilot of World War II. He was credited with 121 aerial victories claimed in just 164 combat missions. His victory total includes 114 RAF four-engine bombers; arguably accounting for more RAF casualties than any other Luftwaffe fighter pilot and becoming the third highest Luftwaffe claimant against the Western Allied Air Forces. His flight book indicated 2,300 takeoffs and 1,133 flying hours.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann p29&quot;&gt;Schumann 2000, p. 29.&lt;/ref&gt;

Until late 1944, Schnaufer documented his aerial victories with detailed geographical locations. After this date, he claimed his victories over territory occupied by the Allies, and his victories were logged in a ''Planquadrat'' (grid reference), for example &quot;KP-IP&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 207.&lt;/ref&gt; The grid map was composed of rectangles measuring 15 [[Minute of arc|minutes]] of [[latitude]] by 30 minutes of [[longitude]], an area of about {{Convert|360|sqmi|sqkm}}.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 208.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{legend2|#e3d9ff|This and the ♠ ([[Ace of spades]]) indicates those aerial victories which made Schnaufer an ace-in-a-day, a term which designates a fighter pilot who has shot down five or more airplanes in a single day. |border=1px solid #AAAAAA}}&lt;br /&gt;
{{legend2|#C0EFBA|This along with the + (plus) indicates almost certain identification.|border=1px solid #AAAAAA}}&lt;br /&gt;
{{legend2|#fbec5d;|This along with the * (asterisk) indicates probable identification.|border=1px solid #AAAAAA}}&lt;br /&gt;
{{legend2|#ffdead|This along with the ? (question mark) indicates possible identification.|border=1px solid #AAAAAA}}
&lt;center&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable plainrowheaders&quot; style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;
|-
! colspan=&quot;7&quot; | Chronicle of aerial victories&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, pp. 298–302.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
!scope=&quot;col&quot;| Victory
!scope=&quot;col&quot; style=&quot;width:115px&quot;| Date
!scope=&quot;col&quot;| Time
!scope=&quot;col&quot;| Type
!scope=&quot;col&quot;| Location
!scope=&quot;col&quot;| Unit
!scope=&quot;col&quot;| Serial No./Squadron No.
|-
! colspan=&quot;7&quot; | – II. ''Gruppe''/''Nachtjagdgeschwader'' 1 –
|-
| 1
| 2 June 1942
| 01:55
| [[Handley Page Halifax|Halifax II]]
| [[Grez-Doiceau]], {{Convert|15|km|mi|abbr=on}} S of [[Leuven|Louvain]], Belgium
| [[No. 76 Squadron RAF|No. 76 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#fbec5d;&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''W1064''/MP-J*
|-
| 2
| 1 August 1942
| 02:47
| [[Vickers Wellington|Wellington IC]]
| {{Convert|1|km|mi|abbr=on}} SW [[Loon op Zand]], Netherlands
| [[No. 25 Operational Training Unit RAF|25 Operational Training Unit]]
| style=&quot;background:#fbec5d;&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''DV439''/-H*
|-
| 3
| 1 August 1942
| 03:17
| Wellington IC
| [[Huldenberg]], Belgium
| [[No. 27 Operational Training Unit RAF|27 Operational Training Unit]]
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''DV552''/UJ-N+
|-
| 4
| 1 August 1942
| 03:45
| [[Armstrong Whitworth Whitley|Whitley V]]
| [[Gilly, Belgium|Gilly]], [[Charleroi]], Belgium
| [[No. 24 Operational Training Unit RAF|24 Operational Training Unit]]
| style=&quot;background:#fbec5d;&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''BD347''*
|-
| 5
| 25 August 1942
| 02:54
| Wellington III
| Near [[Loonbeek]], Belgium
| [[No. 150 Squadron RAF|No. 150 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#fbec5d;&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''BJ651''/JN-M*
|-
| 6
| 29 August 1942
| 01:16
| Halifax II
| [[Overijse|Tombeek]], {{Convert|16|km|mi|abbr=on}} SE of [[Brussels]], Belgium
| [[No. 78 Squadron RAF|No. 78 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#fbec5d;&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''W7809''/EJ*
|-
| 7
| 21 December 1942
| 23:53
| [[Avro Lancaster|Lancaster I]]
| [[Poelkapelle]], Belgium
| [[No. 106 Squadron RAF|No. 106 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''R5914''/ZN-+
|-
| 8
| 14 May 1943
| 02:14
| [[Short Stirling|Stirling I]]
| [[Heerlen]], Netherlands
| [[No. 214 Squadron RAF|No. 214 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#fbec5d;&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''R9242''/BU-O*
|-
| 9
| 14 May 1943
| 03:07
| Halifax II
| Near [[Blanden]], Belgium
| [[No. 78 Squadron RAF|No. 78 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''JB873''/EY-J+
|-
| 10
| 30 May 1943
| 00:48
| Stirling III
| S of [[Baelen]], Belgium
| [[No. 218 Squadron RAF|No. 218 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''BF565''/HA-H+
|-
| 11
| 30 May 1943
| 01:43
| Halifax II
| [[Budingen]], {{Convert|7|km|mi|abbr=on}} NW of [[Sint-Truiden]], Belgium
| [[No. 35 Squadron RAF|No. 35 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''DT804''/TL-C+
|-
| 12
| 30 May 1943
| 02:22
| Stirling III
| [[Schaffen Air Base]], {{Convert|22|km|mi|abbr=on}} N of Sint-Truiden, Belgium
| No. 218 Squadron
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''BK688''/HA-A+
|-
| 13
| 22 June 1943
| 01:33
| Stirling III
| [[Langdorp]], Belgium
| No. 218 Squadron
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''BK712''/HA-D+
|-
| 14
| 25 June 1943
| 02:58
| Wellington
| Hamme-Mille, S of Louvain, Belgium
|
| 
|-
| 15
| 29 June 1943
| 01:25
| Lancaster III
| Solwaster, SE of [[Verviers]], Belgium
| [[No. 97 Squadron RAF|No. 97 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''LM323''/OF-U+
|-
| 16
| 29 June 1943
| 01:45
| Halifax V
| Wandre, NE of [[Liège]], Belgium
| No. 76 Squadron
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''DK137''/NP-R+
|-
| 17
| 29 June 1943
| 01:55
| Halifax II
| Near [[Vottem]], N of Liège, Belgium
| No. 35 Squadron
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''HR812''/TL-F+
|-
| 18
| 4 July 1943
| 00:48
| Wellington X
| Averbode, {{Convert|7|km|mi|abbr=on}} NW of [[Diest]], Belgium
| [[No. 196 Squadron RAF|No. 196 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''HE980''ZO-+
|-
| 19
| 4 July 1943
| 01:01
| Stirling III
| Near [[Geetbets]], {{Convert|9|km|mi|abbr=on}} NW of Sint-Truiden, Belgium
| [[No. 149 Squadron RAF|No. 149 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''BF530''/OJ-B+
|-
| 20
| 9 July 1943
| 02:33
| Lancaster III
| Near [[Grobbendonk]], {{Convert|23|km|mi|abbr=on}} ESE of [[Antwerp]], Belgium
| [[No. 49 Squadron RAF|No. 49 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''ED663''/EA-+
|-
| 21
| 11 August 1943
| 00:32
| Lancaster
| [[Alsbach-Hähnlein|Hähnlein]], {{Convert|25|km|mi|abbr=on}} SSW of [[Darmstadt]], Germany
|
| 
|-
! colspan=&quot;10&quot; | – 12. ''Staffel''/''Nachtjagdgeschwader'' 1 –
|-
| 22
| 28 August 1943
| 03:59
| Halifax II
| [[Jemeppe-sur-Sambre]], {{Convert|15|km|mi|abbr=on}} W of [[Namur (city)|Namur]], Belgium
| [[No. 102 Squadron RAF|No. 102 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''JB835''/DY-X+
|-
| 23
| 31 August 1943
| 22:41
| Halifax II
| {{Convert|2|km|mi|abbr=on}} SE [[Kuinre]], [[Zuider Zee]]
| [[No. 35 Squadron RAF|No. 35 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''HR878''/TL-J+
|-
| 24
| 31 August 1943
| 03:53
| Wellington X
| Near Lozen, N of [[Bree, Belgium|Bree]], Belgium
| [[No. 166 Squadron RAF|No. 166 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#fbec5d;&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''HE988''/AS-U*
|-
| 25
| 24 August 1943
| 00:09
| Halifax II
| Near [[Eschede]], {{Convert|20|km|mi|abbr=on}} NNE of [[Celle]], Germany
| [[No. 77 Squadron RAF|No. 77 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#fbec5d;&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''JD379''/KN-M*
|-
| 26
| 23 September 1943
| 23:00
| Stirling III
| {{Convert|5|km|mi|abbr=on}} S [[Kirchheimbolanden]], Germany
| [[No. 218 Squadron RAF|No. 218 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''EJ104''/HA-G+
|-
| 27
| 27 September 1943
| 23:31
| Halifax
| Near [[Stemmen]], W of [[Stadthagen]], Germany
|
|
|-
| 28
| 3 October 1943
| 21:50
| Halifax II
| Near Lande, {{Convert|8|km|mi|abbr=on}} N of [[Minden]], Germany
| [[No. 51 Squadron RAF|No. 51 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#ffdead&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''HR728''/LK-D?
|-
| 29
| 9 October 1943
| 01:13
| Halifax II
| Near [[Schwaförden]], {{Convert|9|km|mi|abbr=on}} N of [[Sulingen]], Germany
| [[No. 158 Squadron RAF|No. 158 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#fbec5d;&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''HR945''/NP-Y*
|-
| 30
| 9 October 1943
| 01:42
| Four-engined bomber
| Near [[Barsinghausen|Holtensen]], SW of [[Hanover]], Germany
|
|
|-
| 31
| 18 October 1943
| 20:25
| Lancaster III
| Near [[Negenborn]], NNW of Hanover, Germany
| [[No. 101 Squadron RAF|No. 101 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#fbec5d;&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''DV230''/SR-T*
|-
| 32
| 20 October 1943
| 19:13
| Lancaster III
| Near [[Gieten]], E of [[Assen]], Netherlands
| [[No. 7 Squadron RAF|No. 7 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''JB175''/MG-A+
|-
| 33
| 20 October 1943
| 19:25
| Lancaster III
| Near [[Hümmling|Harrenstätte]], NW of [[Werlte]], Germany
| [[405 Maritime Patrol Squadron|No. 405 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''JB348''/LQ-R+
|-
| 34
| 22 October 1943
| 21:40
| Lancaster III
| Near [[Dransfeld]], Hanover, Germany
| [[No. 57 Squadron RAF|No. 57 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#fbec5d;&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''JB320''/DX-X*
|-
| 35
| 23 November 1943
| 18:50
| Lancaster III
| {{Convert|2|km|mi|abbr=on}} NW [[Ter Apel]], near [[Emmen, Netherlands|Emmen]], Netherlands
| No. 405 Squadron
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''JA939''/LQ-C+
|-
| 36
| 23 November 1943
| 19:00
| Lancaster III
| [[Lorup]], NNW [[Cloppenburg]], Germany
| [[No. 12 Squadron RAF|No. 12 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#ffdead&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''JB537''/PH-N?
|-
| 37
| 16 December 1943
| 18:01
| Lancaster III
| Near [[Follega]], Netherlands
| No. 7 Squadron
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''JA853''/MG-L+
|-
| 38
| 16 December 1943
| 18:12
| Lancaster I
| Near  [[Lemmer]], Netherlands
| [[No. 101 Squadron RAF|No. 101 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''DV300''/SR-W+
|-
| 39
| 16 December 1943
| 18:23
| Lancaster III
| SW [[Wolvega]], Netherlands
| [[No. 49 Squadron RAF|No. 49 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''JB545''/EA-O+
|-
| 40
| 16 December 1943
| 18:41
| Lancaster II
| {{Convert|2|km|mi|abbr=on}} SW [[Wirdum, Friesland|Wirdum]], Netherlands
| [[No. 432 Squadron RAF|No. 432 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''DS831''/QO-N+
|-
| 41
| 29 December 1943
| 18:50
| Halifax II
| {{Convert|5|km|mi|abbr=on}} NE [[Meppel]], Netherlands
| [[No. 10 Squadron RAF|No. 10 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''JD314''/ZA-X+
|-
| 42
| 29 December 1943
| 19:45
| Lancaster II
| Near [[Wietmarschen]], W of [[Lingen]], Germany
| [[No. 408 Squadron RAF|No. 408 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''DS718''/EQ-R+
|-
| 43
| 27 January 1944
| 19:45
| Lancaster III
| Near [[Essen]], {{Convert|4|km|mi|abbr=on}} NW of [[Quakenbrück]], Germany
| No. 12 Squadron
| style=&quot;background:#ffdead&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''JB283''/PH-W?
|-
| 44
| 30 January 1944
| 22:15
| Lancaster
| In GK5, W of [[Amsterdam]], Houtrakpolder, Netherlands
| No. 97 Squadron
| style=&quot;background:#ffdead&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''JB659''/OF-J?&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |work=Battle of Berlin — November 1943–March 1944 |title=Crew Alan Hart |url=http://www.firebynight.co.uk/Crew%20Hart.html |accessdate=26 December 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 45
| 15 February 1944
| 22:58
| Lancaster III
| In the sea, DJ93
| [[No. 103 Squadron RAF|No. 103 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''ND363''/PM-A+
|-
| 46
| 15 February 1944
| 23:19
| Lancaster II
| Near [[Hoorn]], Netherlands
| [[No. 115 Squadron RAF|No. 115 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''LL689''/KO-P+&lt;ref&gt;Chorley 1992, p. 78.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 47
| 15 February 1944
| 23:33
| Lancaster I
| EL78 in the [[Wattenmeer]], Netherlands
| [[No. 622 Squadron RAF|No. 622 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''W4272''/GJ-C+
|-
| 48
| 22 March 1944
| 23:10
| Lancaster III
| Halle, near [[Lembeck]], {{Convert|18|km|mi|abbr=on}} S of [[Brussels]], Belgium
| [[No. 9 Squadron RAF|No. 9 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''LM430''/WS-B+
|-
| 49
| 25 March 1944
| 00:12
| Four-engined bomber
| E of [[Dortmund]], Germany
| 
|
|-
| 50
| 25 March 1944
| 00:21
| Lancaster I
| [[Warendorf|Neuwarendorf]], E of [[Münster]], Germany
| [[No. 626 Squadron RAF|No. 626 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#fbec5d;&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''HK539''/UM-A2*
|-
| 51
| 25 March 1944
| 00:41
| Four-engined bomber
| Near [[Varsseveld]], Netherlands, NE [[Emmerich am Rhein|Emmerich]], Germany
| 
|
|-
! colspan=&quot;7&quot; | – IV. ''Gruppe''/''Nachtjagdgeschwader'' 1 –
|-
| 52
| 11 April 1944
| 23:15
| Lancaster III
| Near [[Beerse]], {{Convert|6|km|mi|abbr=on}} W of [[Turnhout]], Belgium
| [[No. 83 Squadron RAF|No. 83 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''ND389''/OL-A+
|-
| 53
| 11 April 1944
| 23:25
| Lancaster I
| {{Convert|2|km|mi|abbr=on}} N [[Brecht, Belgium|Sint-Lenaarts]], Belgium
| No. 49 Squadron
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''LL899''/EA-P+
|-
| 54
| 25 April 1944
| 02:03
| Lancaster I
| Near [[Alken, Belgium|Alken]], Belgium
| No. 115 Squadron
| style=&quot;background:#fbec5d;&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''HK542''/KO-J*
|-
| 55
| 25 April 1944
| 02:28
| Lancaster II
| {{Convert|3|km|mi|abbr=on}} N [[Mechelen]], Belgium
| No. 115 Squadron
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''DS734''/KO-Y+
|-
| 56
| 25 April 1944
| 02:30
| Halifax III
| {{Convert|1|km|mi|abbr=on}} W of [[Haasdonk]], Belgium
| [[No. 192 Squadron RAF|No. 192 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#fbec5d;&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''LW622''/DT-R*
|-
| 57
| 25 April 1944
| 02:40
| Halifax
| In the sea at LG 35
| 
|
|-
| 58
| 27 April 1944
| 02:05
| Lancaster III
| {{Convert|1|km|mi|abbr=on}} S [[Achtmaal]], Netherlands
| [[No. 156 Squadron RAF|No. 156 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''JB307''/GT-H+
|-
| 59
| 27 April 1944
| 02:18
| Lancaster II
| Over the sea, LG 38
| No. 408 Squadron
| style=&quot;background:#fbec5d;&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''DS719''/LQ-U*
|-
| 60
| 28 April 1944
| 01:30
| Halifax V
| {{Convert|8|km|mi|abbr=on}} N [[Aubel]], Belgium, {{Convert|15|km|mi|abbr=on}} SW of [[Aachen]], Germany
| [[No. 434 Squadron RAF|No. 434 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''LL258''/WL-W+
|-
| 61
| 28 April 1944
| 01:40
| Halifax III
| Verviers, Belgium
| No. 432 Squadron
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''MZ588''/QO-W+
|-
| 62
| 9 May 1944
| 03:34
| Halifax III
| Near [[Grand-Reng]], {{Convert|30|km|mi|abbr=on}} SW of Charleroi, Belgium
| No. 432 Squadron
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''LW594''/QO-G+
|-
| 63
| 13 May 1944
| 00:44
| Halifax III
| [[Londerzeel]], {{Convert|8|km|mi|abbr=on}} W of [[Mechelen]], Belgium
| No. 426 Squadron
| style=&quot;background:#fbec5d;&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''LK883''/OW-E*
|-
| 64
| 13 May 1944
| 00:46
| Halifax III
| {{Convert|5|km|mi|abbr=on}} ENE [[Hasselt]], Belgium
| No. 158 Squadron
| style=&quot;background:#ffdead&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''HX334''/NP-C?
|-
| 65
| 13 May 1944
| 00:48
| Halifax III
| [[Hoogstraten]], {{Convert|16|km|mi|abbr=on}} NW of Turnhout, Belgium
| [[No. 466 Squadron RAF|No. 466 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''LV919''/HD-O+
|-
| 66
| 22 May 1944
| 01:34
| Lancaster
| {{Convert|3|km|mi|abbr=on}} S of [[Mol, Belgium|Mol]], Belgium
| 
|
|-
| 67
| 22 May 1944
| 01:51
| Lancaster
| {{Convert|10|km|mi|abbr=on}} S of [[Herentals]], Belgium
| [[No. 550 Squadron RAF|No. 550 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''DV309''/BQ-S+&lt;ref&gt;Chorley 1992, p. 231.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 68
| 23 May 1944
| 01:23
| Lancaster I
| Near [[Neerpelt]], Belgium
| [[No. 75 Squadron RAF|No. 75 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''ME690''/AA-Z+
|-
| 69
| 23 May 1944
| 01:36
| Lancaster I
| Near [[Brecht]], {{Convert|22|km|mi|abbr=on}} NE of Antwerp, Belgium
| [[No. 100 Squadron RAF|No. 100 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#fbec5d;&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''ME670''/HW-Q*
|-
| style=&quot;background:#e3d9ff&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; | 70♠
| 25 May 1944
| 01:15
| Halifax III
| {{Convert|3|km|mi|abbr=on}} NW of [[Eindhoven]], Netherlands
| [[No. 51 Squadron RAF|No. 51 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''LK885''/MH-Z+
|-
| style=&quot;background:#e3d9ff&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; | 71♠
| 25 May 1944
| 01:18
| Halifax III
| {{Convert|2|km|mi|abbr=on}} NNW of [[Tilburg]], Netherlands
| No. 158 Squadron
| style=&quot;background:#ffdead&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''LW653''/NP-T?
|-
| style=&quot;background:#e3d9ff&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; | 72♠
| 25 May 1944
| 01:22
| Halifax III
| {{Convert|1.5|km|mi|abbr=on}} W Goirle, SSW of Tilburg, Netherlands
| No. 76 Squadron
| style=&quot;background:#fbec5d;&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''MZ622''/MP-L*
|-
| style=&quot;background:#e3d9ff&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; | 73♠
| 25 May 1944
| 01:25
| Halifax III
| Between [[Dongen]] and Tilburg, Netherlands
| [[No. 429 Squadron RAF|No. 429 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#ffdead&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''LW124''/AL-N?
|-
| style=&quot;background:#e3d9ff&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; | 74♠
| 25 May 1944
| 01:29
| Lancaster
| {{Convert|7|km|mi|abbr=on}} SW of Tilburg, Netherlands
| 
|
|-
| 75
| 13 June 1944
| 00:27
| Lancaster II
| Avesnes-les-Auvert, E of [[Cambrai]], France
| No. 408 Squadron
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''DS772''/EQ-T+
|-
| 76
| 13 June 1944
| 00:31
| Lancaster II
| [[Cambrai-Niergnies Airport|Cambrai airfield]]
| No. 408 Squadron
| style=&quot;background:#fbec5d;&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''DS726''/EQ-Y*
|-
| 77
| 13 June 1944
| 00:34
| Lancaster II
| [[Tilloy-lez-Cambrai|Tilloy]], N of Cambrai, France
| No. 408 Squadron
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''DS688''/EQ-R+
|-
| 78
| 16 June 1944
| 01:00
| Lancaster
| N of [[Arras]], France
| 
|
|-
| 79
| 17 June 1944
| 01:54
| Four-engined bomber
| [[Dreumel]], N of s'Hertogenbosch, Netherlands
| 
|
|-
| 80
| 17 June 1944
| 02:04
| Halifax III
| [[Berkel]], Netherlands
| [[No. 77 Squadron RAF|No. 77 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#C0EFBA&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''NA524''/KN-F+
|-
| 81
| 22 June 1944
| 01:25
| Lancaster III
| [[Valkenswaard]], Netherlands
| [[No. 44 Squadron RAF|No. 44 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#fbec5d;&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''LM582''/KM-Q*
|-
| 82
| 22 June 1944
| 01:30
| Lancaster I
| {{Convert|2|km|mi|abbr=on}} S of [[Meeuwen-Gruitrode|Meeuwen]], Belgium
| [[No. 207 Squadron RAF|No. 207 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#fbec5d;&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''ME683''/EM-W*
|-
| 83
| 22 June 1944
| 01:36
| Lancaster III
| {{Convert|5|km|mi|abbr=on}} S of [[Opoeteren]], Belgium
| [[No. 44 Squadron RAF|No. 44 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#ffdead&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''LM434''/KM-F?
|-
| 84
| 22 June 1944
| 02:05
| Lancaster I
| {{Convert|6|km|mi|abbr=on}} S of [[Hamont]], Belgium
| [[No. 630 Squadron RAF|No. 630 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#fbec5d;&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''ME843''/LE-U*
|-
| 85
| 21 July 1944
| 01:40
| Lancaster I
| {{Convert|1.5|km|mi|abbr=on}} N of [[Boxtel]], Netherlands
| [[No. 90 Squadron RAF|No. 90 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#ffdead&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''LM183''/WP-L?
|-
| 86
| 21 July 1944
| 01:51
| Four-engined bomber
| {{Convert|8|km|mi|abbr=on}} N of [[Breda]], Netherlands
| 
|
|-
| 87
| 29 July 1944
| 01:38
| Lancaster I
| [[Pforzheim]], Germany
| [[No. 467 Squadron RAF|No. 467 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#ffdead&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''ME856''/PO-T?
|-
| 88
| 29 July 1944
| 01:50
| Four-engined bomber
| [[Eutingen]], near Pforzheim, Germany
| 
|
|-
| 89
| 29 July 1944
| 01:57
| Lancaster I
| [[Renningen|Malmsheim]], {{Convert|20|km|mi|abbr=on}} W of [[Stuttgart]], Germany
| [[No. 106 Squadron RAF|No. 106 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#ffdead&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''ME778''/ZN-O?
|-
| 90
| 13 August 1944
| 00:48
| Four-engined bomber
| [[Wasserliesch]], Germany
| 
|
|-
| 91
| 13 August 1944
| 01:09
| Lancaster III
| [[Ferrières, Belgium|Werbomont]], SSE of Liège, Belgium
| [[No. 635 Squadron RAF|No. 635 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#fbec5d;&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''ND694''/F2-R*
|-
| 92
| 13 August 1944
| 01:15
| Four-engined bomber
| [[Gouvy]], {{Convert|28|km|mi|abbr=on}} SSW of [[Malmédy]], Belgium
|
| 
|-
| 93
| 13 August 1944
| 01:19
| Four-engined bomber
| {{Convert|3|km|mi|abbr=on}} W of [[Mons]], near Liège, Belgium
|
| 
|-
| 94
| 12 September 1944
| 23:07
| Four-engined bomber
| RQ-RP
|
| 
|-
| 95
| 23 September 1944
| 22:56
| Four-engined bomber
| JP-HP
|
| 
|-
| 96
| 23 September 1944
| 23:10
| Four-engined bomber
| JO
|
| 
|-
| 97
| 23 September 1944
| 23:15
| Four-engined bomber
| HO-JO
|
| 
|-
| 98
| 23 September 1944
| 23:25
| Four-engined bomber
| JN-HN
|
| 
|-
| 99
| 9 October 1944
| 20:32
| Four-engined bomber
| S of [[Bochum]], Germany
|
| 
|-
| 100
| 9 October 1944
| 20:55
| Four-engined bomber
| JO
|
| 
|-
| 101
| 6 November 1944
| 20:55
| Four-engined bomber
| KP-IP
|
| 
|-
| 102
| 6 November 1944
| 19:34
| Four-engined bomber
| KP-IP
|
| 
|-
| 103
| 6 November 1944
| 19:41
| Four-engined bomber
| KP-IP
| 
|
|-
! colspan=&quot;7&quot; | – ''Stab''/''Nachtjagdgeschwader'' 4 –
|-
| 104
| 21 November 1944
| 19:05
| Four-engined bomber
| KP
|
| 
|-
| 105
| 21 November 1944
| 19:11
| Four-engined bomber
| KP
|
| 
|-
| 106
| 12 December 1944
| 20:00
| Four-engined bomber
| MO-LO
|
| 
|-
| 107
| 3 February 1945
| 21:09
| Four-engined bomber
| LO
|
| 
|-
| style=&quot;background:#e3d9ff&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; | 108♠
| 21 February 1945
| 01:53
| Lancaster
| MM-MN
|
| 
|-
| style=&quot;background:#e3d9ff&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; | 109♠
| 21 February 1945
| 01:58
| Lancaster
| MM
|
| 
|-
| style=&quot;background:#e3d9ff&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; | 110♠
| 21 February 1945
| 20:44
| Lancaster
| HQ-HP
|
| 
|-
| style=&quot;background:#e3d9ff&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; | 111♠
| 21 February 1945
| 20:48
| Lancaster
| HP-HO
|
| 
|-
| style=&quot;background:#e3d9ff&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; | 112♠
| 21 February 1945
| 20:51
| Lancaster
| HP-HO
|
| 
|-
| style=&quot;background:#e3d9ff&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; | 113♠
| 21 February 1945
| 20:55
| Lancaster
| HP-HO
|
| 
|-
| style=&quot;background:#e3d9ff&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; | 114♠
| 21 February 1945
| 20:58
| Lancaster
| IO-JN
|
| 
|-
| style=&quot;background:#e3d9ff&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; | 115♠
| 21 February 1945
| 21:00
| Lancaster
| JN-KM
|
| 
|-
| style=&quot;background:#e3d9ff&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; | 116♠
| 21 February 1945
| 21:03
| Lancaster
| KM-KL
|
| 
|-
| {{center|—}}{{refn|Schnaufer did not claim this aerial victory. His cannon had malfunctioned during the attack and the crew did not observe the result of the attack.&lt;ref&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 302.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=&quot;Note&quot;}}
| 21 February 1945
| 21:10
| Lancaster I
| KM-KL
| [[No. 463 Squadron RAF|No. 463 Squadron]]
| style=&quot;background:#fbec5d;&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; | ''NG329''/JO-Z*
|-
| 117
| 3 March 1945
| 21:55
| Lancaster
| HQ
|
| 
|-
| 118
| 3 March 1945
| 22:04
| Lancaster
| HQ
|
| 
|-
| 119
| 7 March 1945
| 20:41
| Lancaster
| LR-MR
|
| 
|-
| 120
| 7 March 1945
| 20:47
| Lancaster
| LS-MS
|
| 
|-
| 121
| 7 March 1945
| 21:56
| Lancaster
| GC-HC
|
|
|}
&lt;/center&gt;

==Awards==
* [[Front Flying Clasp of the Luftwaffe]] for Night Fighters in Gold&lt;ref name=&quot;Berger p314&quot;&gt;Berger 1999, p. 314.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Combined Pilots-Observation Badge]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Berger p314&quot;/&gt;
* [[Wound Badge]] in Black&lt;ref name=&quot;Berger p314&quot;/&gt;
* [[Iron Cross]] (1939)
** 2nd Class (2 June 1942)&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomas p273&quot;&gt;Thomas 1998, p. 273.&lt;/ref&gt;
** 1st Class (19 October 1942)&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomas p273&quot;/&gt;
* [[Honour Goblet of the Luftwaffe]] (''Ehrenpokal der Luftwaffe'') on 26 July 1943 as ''[[Leutnant]]'' and pilot&lt;ref&gt;Patzwall 2008, p. 184.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[German Cross]] in Gold on 16 August 1943 as ''[[Oberleutnant]]'' in the II./NJG 1&lt;ref&gt;Patzwall &amp; Scherzer 2001, p. 417.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves, Swords and Diamonds]]
** Knight's Cross on 31 December 1943 as ''Oberleutnant'' and ''[[Staffelkapitän|Staffelführer]]'' of 12./NJG 1&lt;ref name=&quot;Scherzer p675&quot;&gt;Scherzer 2007, p. 675.&lt;/ref&gt;
** 507th Oak Leaves on 24 June 1944 as ''[[Hauptmann]]'' and ''[[Gruppenkommandeur]]'' of IV./NJG 1&lt;ref name=&quot;Scherzer p675&quot;/&gt;
** 84th Swords on 3 August 1944 as ''Hauptmann'' and ''Gruppenkommandeur'' of IV./NJG 1&lt;ref name=&quot;Scherzer p675&quot;/&gt;
** 21st Diamonds on 16 October 1944 as ''Hauptmann'' and ''Gruppenkommandeur'' of IV./NJG 1&lt;ref name=&quot;Scherzer p675&quot;/&gt;
* Mentioned in the ''[[Wehrmachtbericht]]'' on 10 October 1944

==Dates of rank==
{| style=&quot;background:none;&quot;
|-
| 1 April 1940: || ''[[Fahnenjunker]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann p2&quot;/&gt;
|-
| 1 April 1941: || ''Fahnenjunker''-''[[Gefreiter]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann p2&quot;/&gt;
|-
| 1 July 1941: || ''Fahnenjunker''-''[[Unteroffizier]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann p2&quot;/&gt;
|-
| 1 September 1941: || ''[[Fähnrich]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann p2&quot;/&gt;
|-
| 1 February 1941: || ''Oberfähnrich''&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann p2&quot;/&gt;
|-
| 1 April 1941: || ''[[Leutnant]]'' (Second Lieutenant)&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann p2&quot;/&gt;
|-
| 1 July 1943: || ''[[Oberleutnant]]'' (First Lieutenant)&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann p2&quot;/&gt;
|-
| 1 May 1944: || ''[[Hauptmann]]'' (Captain)&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann p2&quot;/&gt;
|-
| 1 December 1944: || ''[[Major (Germany)|Major]]'' (Major)&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann p2&quot;/&gt;
|}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|group=&quot;Note&quot;}}

==References==

===Citations===
{{Reflist|20em}}

===Bibliography===
{{Refbegin}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Berger
  |first=Florian
  |year=1999
  |title=Mit Eichenlaub und Schwertern. Die höchstdekorierten Soldaten des Zweiten Weltkrieges
  |trans_title=With Oak Leaves and Swords. The Highest Decorated Soldiers of the Second World War
  |language=German
  |location=Vienna, Austria
  |publisher=Selbstverlag Florian Berger
  |isbn=978-3-9501307-0-6
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Bowman
  |first=Martin
  |year=2011
  |title=100 Group (Bomber Support): RAF Bomber Command in World War II
  |location=Barnsley, South Yorkshire
  |publisher=Pen and Sword
  |isbn=1-84415-418-1
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Chorley
  |first=W. R.
  |year=1992
  |title=Royal Air Force Bomber Command Losses of the Second World War: Aircraft and Crew Losses, 1944
  |location=London
  |publisher=Midland Counties Publications
  |isbn=978-0-904597-91-2
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last1=Foreman
  |first1=John
  |last2=Matthews
  |first2=Johannes
  |last3=Parry
  |first3=Simon
  |year=2004
  |title=Luftwaffe Night Fighter Claims 1939–1945
  |location=Walton on Thames, UK
  |publisher=Red Kite
  |isbn=978-0-9538061-4-0
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Hagen
  |first=Hans-Peter
  |year=1998
  |title=Husaren des Himmels—Berühmte deutsche Jagdflieger und die Geschichte ihrer Waffe
  |trans_title=Hussars of the Sky—Famous German Fighter Pilots and the History of their Force
  |language=German
  |location=Rastatt, Germany
  |publisher=Moewig
  |isbn=978-3-8118-1456-1
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Hinchliffe
  |first=Peter
  |year=1999
  |title=Schnaufer: Ace of Diamonds
  |location=Brimscombe Port, UK
  |publisher=Tempus
  |isbn=978-0-7524-1690-8
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Kurowski
  |first=Franz
  |year=1996
  |title=Luftwaffe Aces
  |location=Winnipeg, Canada
  |publisher=J.J. Fedorowicz Publishing Inc
  |isbn=978-0-921991-31-1
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Obermaier
  |first=Ernst
  |year=1989
  |title=Die Ritterkreuzträger der Luftwaffe Jagdflieger 1939–1945
  |trans_title=The Knight's Cross Bearers of the Luftwaffe Fighter Force 1939–1945
  |language=German
  |location=Mainz, Germany
  |publisher=Verlag Dieter Hoffmann
  |isbn=978-3-87341-065-7
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last1=Patzwall
  |first1=Klaus D.
  |last2=Scherzer
  |first2=Veit
  |year=2001
  |title=Das Deutsche Kreuz 1941–1945 Geschichte und Inhaber Band II
  |trans_title=The German Cross 1941–1945 History and Recipients Volume 2
  |language=German
  |location=Norderstedt, Germany
  |publisher=Verlag Klaus D. Patzwall
  |isbn=978-3-931533-45-8
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last1=Patzwall
  |first1=Klaus D.
  |year=2008
  |title=Der Ehrenpokal für besondere Leistung im Luftkrieg
  |trans_title=The Honor Goblet for Outstanding Achievement in the Air War
  |language=German
  |location=Norderstedt, Germany
  |publisher=Verlag Klaus D. Patzwall
  |isbn=978-3-931533-08-3
}}
* Price, Alfred (1967). &quot;One of our planes is missing...&quot; (a.k.a. &quot;Schnaufer's 13th Kill&quot;), ''History of the Second World War'' (Magazine series), Vol. 4, No. 15. London: Purnell and Sons. {{oclc|
2146764}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Scherzer
  |first=Veit
  |year=2007
  |title=Die Ritterkreuzträger 1939–1945 Die Inhaber des Ritterkreuzes des Eisernen Kreuzes 1939 von Heer, Luftwaffe, Kriegsmarine, Waffen-SS, Volkssturm sowie mit Deutschland verbündeter Streitkräfte nach den Unterlagen des Bundesarchives
  |trans_title=The Knight's Cross Bearers 1939–1945: The Holders of the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross 1939 by Army, Air Force, Navy, Waffen-SS, Volkssturm and Allied Forces with Germany According to the Documents of the Federal Archives
  |language=German
  |location=Jena, Germany
  |publisher=Scherzers Militaer-Verlag
  |isbn=978-3-938845-17-2
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Schumann
  |first=Ralf
  |year=2000
  |title=Ritterkreuzträger Profile Nr. 1 Heinz-Wolfgang Schnaufer — der erfolgreichste Nachtjäger des zweiten Weltkrieges
  |trans_title=Knight's Cross Profiles Nr. 1 Heinz-Wolfgang Schnaufer — The Most Successful Night Fighter of World War II
  |language=German
  |publisher=UNITEC-Medienvertrieb
  |id={{ASIN| B0072RS3Q2 | country=de| date=23 July 2013}}
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Scutts
  |first=Jerry
  |year=1998
  |title=German Night Fighter Aces of World War 2
  |location=Oxford, UK
  |publisher=Osprey Publishing
  |isbn=978-1-85532-696-5
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Spick
  |first=Mike
  |year=1996
  |title=Luftwaffe Fighter Aces
  |location=New York
  |publisher=Ivy Books
  |isbn=978-0-8041-1696-1
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Thomas
  |first=Franz
  |year=1998
  |title=Die Eichenlaubträger 1939–1945 Band 2: L–Z
  |trans_title=The Oak Leaves Bearers 1939–1945 Volume 2: L–Z
  |language=German
  |location=Osnabrück, Germany
  |publisher=Biblio-Verlag
  |isbn=978-3-7648-2300-9
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last1=Williamson
  |first1=Gordon
|authorlink1=Gordon Williamson (writer)
  |last2=Bujeiro
  |first2=Ramiro
  |year=2004
  |title=Knight's Cross and Oak Leaves Recipients 1939–40
  |location=Oxford, UK
  |publisher=[[Osprey Publishing]]
  |isbn=978-1-84176-641-6
  |ref=harv
}}
* {{Cite book
  |year=1985
  |title=Die Wehrmachtberichte 1939–1945 Band 3, 1. Januar 1944 bis 9. Mai 1945
  |trans_title=The Wehrmacht Reports 1939–1945: Volume 3, 1 January 1944 to 9 May 1945
  |language=German
  |location=München, Germany
  |publisher=Deutscher Taschenbuch Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KG
  |isbn=978-3-423-05944-2
}}
{{Refend}}

==External links==
* {{DNB portal|119199866|TYP=}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-mil}}
{{succession box
| before = Oberleutnant [[Wolfgang Thimmig]]
| after  = none
| title  = Commander of [[Nachtjagdgeschwader 4|''Nachtjagdgeschwader'' 4]]
| years  = 20 November 1944 – 8 May 1945
}}
{{s-end}}

{{RKDiamonds}}
{{KCwithOLandSW}}
{{KCwithOL}}
{{Knight's Cross recipients of NJG 1}}
{{Top German World War II Aces}}
{{Top German World War II night fighter aces}}
{{Authority control}}
{{Subject bar
| portal1=Aviation
| portal2=Biography
| portal3=Military of Germany
| portal4=World War II
| commons=y
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Schnaufer, Heinz-Wolfgang}}
[[Category:1922 births]]
[[Category:1950 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Calw]]
[[Category:Luftwaffe pilots]]
[[Category:German World War II flying aces]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Gold German Cross]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves, Swords and Diamonds]]
[[Category:Military personnel referenced in the Wehrmachtbericht]]
[[Category:German prisoners of war in World War II held by the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Road incident deaths in France]]
[[Category:People from the Free People's State of Württemberg]]</text>
      <sha1>i7t8m16kyr1kdaysvdcqrbq13d7zorn</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
