<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Helmut Wick</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6627272</id>
    <revision>
      <id>746658194</id>
      <parentid>744723041</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-28T18:59:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>K.e.coffman</username>
        <id>22615369</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* External links */ in foreign lagng</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="26594">{{good article}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2014}}
{{EngvarB|date=October 2014}}
{{Infobox military person
|name=Helmut Wick
|birth_date={{birth date|1915|8|5|df=y}}
|death_date={{death date and age|1940|11|28|1915|8|5|df=y}}
|image=Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1986-013-04, Helmut Wick (cropped).jpg|250px
|caption=Helmut Wick, October 1940
|birth_place=[[Mannheim]]
|death_place= [[Missing in action]] – [[English Channel]]
|nickname=
|allegiance={{flag|Nazi Germany}}
|branch={{Luftwaffe}}
|serviceyears=1936–40
|rank=''[[Major (Germany)|Major]]''
|commands=[[JG 2]]
|unit=[[JG 133]], [[JG 53]]
|battles=World War II
*[[Battle of France]]
*[[Battle of Britain]]
|awards=[[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves]]
|laterwork=}}

''[[Major (Germany)|Major]]'' '''Helmut Paul Emil Wick''' (5 August 1915 – 28 November 1940) was a [[Germany|German]] ''[[Luftwaffe]]'' [[Flying ace|ace]] and the fourth recipient of the [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves]]. The Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross and its higher grade, the Oak Leaves, was awarded by the [[Third Reich]] to recognise extreme bravery in battle or successful military leadership. It was Germany's highest military decoration at the time of its presentation to Helmut Wick.{{refn|In 1940, the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves was second only to the [[Grand Cross of the Iron Cross]] ({{Lang|de|''Großkreuz des Eisernen Kreuzes''}}), which was awarded only to senior commanders for winning a major battle or campaign, in the military order of the Third Reich. The Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves as highest military order was surpassed on 28 September 1941 by the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves and Swords.&lt;ref&gt;Williamson and Bujeiro 2004, pp. 3, 7.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=&quot;Note&quot;}}

Born in [[Mannheim]], Wick joined the ''Luftwaffe'' in 1936 and was trained as a [[fighter pilot]]. He was assigned to [[Jagdgeschwader 2|''Jagdgeschwader'' 2]] &quot;Richthofen&quot; (JG 2—2nd Fighter Wing), and saw combat in the [[Battle of France|Battles of France]] and [[Battle of Britain|Britain]].&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;See [[Organization of the Luftwaffe during World War&amp;nbsp;II]] for an explanation of the ''Luftwaffe'' structure.&lt;/ref&gt; Promoted to ''Major'' in October 1940, he was given the position of ''[[Geschwaderkommodore]]'' (wing commander) of JG 2—the youngest in the ''Luftwaffe'' to hold this rank and position. He was shot down in the vicinity of the [[Isle of Wight]] on 28 November 1940, very likely by the British ace [[John Dundas (RAF officer)|John Dundas]], who was subsequently shot down by Wick's wingman. Helmut Wick was posted as [[missing in action]], presumed dead. By then he had been credited with destroying 56 enemy aircraft in aerial combat, making him the leading German fighter pilot at the time. Flying the [[Messerschmitt Bf 109]], he claimed all of his victories against the [[Western Allies]].

==Early life and pre-war service==
Helmut Paul Emil Wick was born on 5 August 1915 in [[Mannheim]], Germany, the youngest of three children of a civil engineer, Karl Wick and Berta Wick, née Schenck.{{refn|According to Ringlstetter, Helmut's fathers name is spelled Karl Wick.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ringlstetter p10&quot;&gt;Ringlstetter 2005, p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=&quot;Note&quot;}} Helmut's eldest brother Walter was born in [[Swakopmund]], at the time in the German protectorate in [[German South-West Africa|South-West Africa]]. The outbreak of World War I forced the family to return to Germany and Helmut's sister, Doris, was born in Rohrbach, near [[Heidelberg]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Ringlstetter p10&quot;/&gt; Owing to the demand for his father's skills and expertise building roads and bridges, Helmut spent most of his childhood traveling throughout the German Reich. The Wick family moved to [[Hanover]] in 1919; Helmut's mother died there in February 1922. His father then took the family to Oliva, near [[Gdańsk|Danzig]] and [[Königsberg]] in East Prussia, finally settling in [[Berlin]] in 1935.&lt;ref&gt;Ringlstetter 2005, p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt;

Upon graduating from ''[[Gymnasium (school)|Gymnasium]]'' (high school) in 1935, Wick, who initially considered a career as a forester, applied to the officer candidate course of the new German Air Force. Scoring well on the suitability tests, he was accepted into the German military on 6 April 1936 at the ''[[Luftwaffe]]'' officer candidate school in [[Dresden]], after completing compulsory ''[[Reichsarbeitsdienst]]'' (Reich Labour Service). He swore the [[Hitler oath|oath of allegiance to Adolf Hitler]] on 16 April. After passing officer training courses, Wick was assessed as &quot;well suited to become an officer&quot; on 13 July.&lt;ref&gt;Ringlstetter 2005, p. 12.&lt;/ref&gt; He then started flight training and shortly later soloed in a [[Focke-Wulf Fw 44]] &quot;Stieglitz&quot;. Wick was considered an average pilot and had difficulties with his theoretical training, especially those topics that were of little or no interest to him. In early May 1937, he was briefly transferred to the 6. ''[[Luftwaffe Organization#Staffel|Staffel]]'' (6th squadron) of [[Kampfgeschwader 254|''Kampfgeschwader'' 254]] (254th Bomber Wing). A month later he returned to Dresden to complete his officer training.&lt;ref&gt;Ringlstetter 2005, p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt;

Wick failed to pass the third course of his training but was given a second chance and on 1 April 1938 reported to the officer candidate school at the ''Luftkriegsschule III'' (3rd air war school), Wildpark-West near [[Werder (Havel)|Werder]]. He successfully completed the course and in mid-1938 started special pilot training at the Fighter Training facility at [[Werneuchen]]. Upon graduation, he was assigned to II.[[Group (military aviation unit)|Gruppe]] [[Jagdgeschwader 135|''Jagdgeschwader'' 135]] (135th Fighter Wing) which on 1 November 1938 became [[Jagdgeschwader 333|''Jagdgeschwader'' 333]] (333rd Fighter Wing) under ''[[Oberstleutnant]]'' (Lieutenant Colonel) [[Max Ibel]] at [[Herzogenaurach]], flying obsolete [[Arado Ar 68]] biplane fighters. On 8 November 1938, ''Oberfähnrich'' (senior ensign) Wick was promoted to [[Leutnant]] (second lieutenant) and on 1 January 1939 was transferred to 1. ''Staffel'' of [[Jagdgeschwader 133|''Jagdgeschwader'' 133]] (133rd Fighter Wing), which was later renamed [[Jagdgeschwader 53|''Jagdgeschwader'' 53]] (JG 53—53rd Fighter Wing).&lt;ref&gt;Ringlstetter 2005, p. 16.&lt;/ref&gt; It was there that Wick began flying the [[Messerschmitt Bf 109]] monoplane fighter under the tutelage of [[Werner Mölders]], a [[Spanish Civil War]] [[flying ace]] credited with 14 aerial victories. Under Mölders' guidance, Wick became a ''Schwarmführer'' (flight leader).&lt;ref name=&quot;Ringlstetter 2005, p. 17&quot;&gt;Ringlstetter 2005, p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt;

==World War II==

===Phoney War and Battle of France===
On 31 August 1939 Wick was given orders to transfer to &quot;Jagdgeschwader Richthofen Nr. I&quot;. At the time there was no such unit; the intention was to send him to [[Jagdgeschwader 1 (World War II)|Jagdgeschwader 1]] (JG 1−1st Fighter Wing), based in [[Döberitz]], near Berlin. During [[World War I]] the &quot;Richthofen Geschwader&quot; name had been attached to the World War I era [[Jagdgeschwader 1 (World War I)|Jagdgeschwader 1]]. The &quot;Richthofen&quot; name had been incorrectly put on Wick's order. Only Wick noticed the mistake, realizing that he could now choose between JG 1 or the famous [[Jagdgeschwader 2]] (JG 2—2nd Fighter Wing) which currently bore the &quot;Richthofen&quot; name.&lt;ref&gt;Neher 1943, p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt;  He chose the Richthofen Geschwader, commanded by ''[[Oberst]]'' (Colonel) [[Gerd von Massow]], the unit was equipped with the [[Messerschmitt Bf 109 variants#Bf 109E &quot;Emil&quot;|Bf 109 E-3]] and used the tactical code ''Yellow 3''. On 1 September, Wick joined its ''3. Staffel'', serving in the air defence of Berlin during the [[Polish September Campaign|Polish Campaign]]. Following the German victory in Poland, JG 2 was transferred to [[Frankfurt]]-Rebstock and tasked with protection of Germany's Western border during the [[Phoney War]]—the phase between Britain and France's declaration of war on Germany in September 1939, and the [[Battle of France]] in May 1940.&lt;ref&gt;Ringlstetter 2005, p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt; Flying his sixth combat mission, Leutnant Wick claimed his first, and the ''Geschwader's'' second victory on 22 November 1939.{{refn|According to Ringlstetter the ''Geschwader's'' first victory was credited to ''Oberfeldwebel'' Erwin Kley, who received a gold watch and for this achievement.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ringlstetter p20&quot;&gt;Ringlstetter 2005, p. 20.&lt;/ref&gt; Weal states that the first victory went to Wick.&lt;ref&gt;Weal 2000, p. 26.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=&quot;Note&quot;}} Near [[Nancy, France|Nancy]], he shot down a French [[Curtiss P-36 Hawk|Curtiss Hawk 75]] fighter piloted by Sergent Saillard of the Groupe de Chasse II/4 [[French Air Force|Armée de l’Air]], who was killed. For this feat, Wick received the [[Iron Cross]] 2nd Class ({{Lang|de|''Eisernes Kreuz 2. Klasse''}}).&lt;ref name=&quot;Ringlstetter p20&quot;/&gt; Wick was allowed to take home leave from his Geschwader and spent Christmas with his wife Ursel, his baby son Walter, and his parents, before returning to his Gruppe at Frankfurt-Rebstock. From 10 to 17 February 1940, Wick and six other members from JG 2 spent a week in the [[Black Forest]] on the [[Feldberg (Black Forest)|Feldberg]], skiing and relaxing.&lt;ref&gt;Ringlstetter 2005, p. 21.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 10 May 1940, German forces launched an [[Battle of France|offensive in Western Europe]], but Wick remained on the ground while his aircraft, Bf 109 ''Yellow 2'', underwent an engine change. Seven days later, he was back in the air, recording three victories over French [[Lioré-et-Olivier|LeO 45]] bombers in one mission. By 6 June, Wick had 10 confirmed and two unconfirmed victories, including four French [[Bloch MB.150|Bloch 151/152]] fighters that he shot down on 5 June to record his fifth through eighth victories. The two unconfirmed victories were [[Royal Navy]] [[Fairey Swordfish]] biplane torpedo bombers claimed on 19 May and for which he had no witnesses. On 6 June, Wick became the first pilot of the I. ''Gruppe'' to complete 100 combat missions, claiming his ninth and tenth victory the same day. For this achievement he was awarded the Iron Cross 1st Class ({{Lang|de|''Eisernes Kreuz 1. Klasse''}}) by ''Oberstleutnant'' [[Harry von Bülow-Bothkamp]]. By the end of the [[Battle of France|French Campaign]], Wick's total stood at 14 confirmed victories, trailing only ''[[Hauptmann]]'' (Captain) Mölders of [[Jagdgeschwader 53|JG 53]] with 25 victories and ''Hauptmann'' [[Wilhelm Balthasar]] of [[Jagdgeschwader 27|JG 27]] with 23 victories as the ''Luftwaffe''{{'}}s top scorer. At the end of the French campaign, 3. ''Staffel'' headquarters moved into the house of [[Louis Aston Knight]], an artist who had fled a few days before the Germans arrived.&lt;ref&gt;Ringlstetter 2005, p. 31.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Battle of Britain===
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1968-015-19, Helmut Wick.jpg|thumb|right|Joachim Seegert (left), Helmut Wick (center), [[Erich Leie]] (right) on 6 October 1940&lt;ref&gt;Ringlstetter 2005, p. 83.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
During the [[Battle of Britain]] against the [[Royal Air Force]] (RAF) in mid-1940, Wick rose quickly in rank and in profile, both in the battle zone and as a public figure back in Germany. On 21 July 1940, the just promoted ''[[Oberleutnant]]'' (first lieutenant) also became leader of ''3. Staffel'', succeeding ''Major'' [[Henning Stümpell]].&lt;ref&gt;Ringlstetter 2005, p. 47.&lt;/ref&gt; Although the fighting in the air grew increasingly difficult, Wick kept adding victories to his tally. He recorded his 20th victory on 24 August and added two more fighters a day later. This achievement earned Wick a reference in the ''[[Wehrmachtbericht]]'' (his first of five in total), an information bulletin issued by the headquarters of the Wehrmacht. To be singled out individually in the ''Wehrmachtbericht'' was an honour and was entered in the Orders and Decorations' section of a soldier's Service Record Book. Twenty aerial victories also made Wick eligible for the [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross]] ({{Lang|de|''Ritterkreuz des Eisernen Kreuzes''}}), a higher grade of the Iron Cross. Wick was awarded the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross on 27 August 1940 at [[Karinhall]] by ''[[Reichsmarschall]]'' (Empire's Marshal) [[Hermann Göring]].&lt;ref&gt;Ringlstetter 2005, p. 64.&lt;/ref&gt; He was also interviewed by an ''Adler'' (Eagle—the ''Luftwaffe'' weekly magazine) journalist prior to the presentation. Several articles about Wick appeared at the time.&lt;ref name=&quot;Michulec 2002, p. 36&quot;&gt;Michulec 2002, p. 36.&lt;/ref&gt; Wick was granted four days of leave, which he spent with his family in Berlin.&lt;ref&gt;Ringlstetter 2005, p. 66.&lt;/ref&gt;

Upon his return to France Wick was promoted to ''Hauptmann'' and on 9 September was named ''[[Gruppenkommandeur]]'' (group commander) of ''I. Gruppe'' [[Jagdgeschwader 2|JG 2]].&lt;ref&gt;Ringlstetter 2005, p. 68.&lt;/ref&gt; During September he continued adding to his score, and on 5 October gained his 41st combat victory on his way to overtake his two closest rivals, ''Major ''[[Adolf Galland]] and ''Oberstleutnant'' Mölders. The 41st victory earned him his second reference in the ''Wehrmachtbericht'' on 6 October 1940. He also became the fourth member of the armed forces to receive the [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves]] ({{Lang|de|''Ritterkreuz des Eisernen Kreuzes mit Eichenlaub''}}) directly from Hitler at [[Berghof (Hitler)|Berghof]] in [[Bavaria]] on 8 September 1940.&lt;ref&gt;Ringlstetter 2005, p. 87.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote_box
|width=32%
|align=left
|quote={{Lang|de|''Ich glaube, wir siegen uns über England zu Tode, mein Lieber.''}}&lt;br /&gt;{{Centre|—}}I think, we are winning ourselves to death over England, my dear.
|source=Helmut Wick during the Battle of Britain&lt;ref&gt;Hagen 1998, p. 255.&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
Wick received orders in the late afternoon of 6 October to report to ''Reichsmarschall'' Göring in Berlin by 3&amp;nbsp;p.m. the following day. Due to bad weather, he chose to drive from Normandy to Berlin by car. Together with his [[wingman]] and friend, [[Rudolf Pflanz]], Wick travelled all night and arrived at the [[Reich Air Ministry]] right on time to meet with Göring, ''[[Generalfeldmarschall]]'' (Field Marshal) [[Erhard Milch]], ''[[Generaloberst]]'' (Colonel General) [[Ernst Udet]], ''[[General der Flieger]]'' (General of the Flyers) [[Kurt Student]] and ''General der Flieger'' [[Karl Bodenschatz]]. After the meeting in Berlin, Wick and Göring drove to [[Berchtesgaden]] in the ''Reichsmarschall'''s personal train, where they arrived at 5&amp;nbsp;p.m. on 8 October for the official Oak Leaves presentation.&lt;ref&gt;Ringlstetter 2005, pp. 85–87.&lt;/ref&gt; Wick was then exposed by [[Otto Dietrich]], the Third Reich's Press Chief, to the international public at a press conference and presented as a &quot;hero&quot;. His performance left a predominantly negative impression, since Wick presented himself as a &quot;[[busybody]]&quot; ([[Life (magazine)|Life Magazine]]), and made fun of his victims.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|work=''[[The New York Times]]'' of 13 October 1940|title=Nazi Flier Laughs at British Airmen|url=http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F50C12FE3955177A93C1A8178BD95F448485F9&amp;scp=1&amp;sq=Nazi+Flier+Laughs+at+British+Airmen&amp;st=p|accessdate=22 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Fliegerpokal Wick.jpg|thumb|upright=0.8|right|Wick's received this ''Fliegerpokal'' on account of his 50th victory. On display at the [[Aviation Museum Hannover-Laatzen]].]]
On 19 October 1940, Wick was promoted to [[Major (Germany)|Major]] and appointed ''[[Geschwaderkommodore]]'' (wing commander) of [[Jagdgeschwader 27|''Jagdgeschwader'' 27]] (JG 27—27th Fighter Wing). He had no ambition to leave his ''Gruppe'' in JG 2 &quot;Richthofen&quot; and, after giving the matter some thought, asked Göring to let him remain with his ''Gruppe'' instead. The next day Göring revoked his decision and gave Wick command of JG 2 &quot;Richthofen&quot;. At 25 years of age, he thus became the youngest ''Major'' and ''Geschwaderkommodore'' in the ''Luftwaffe''. ''Major'' [[Wolfgang Schellmann]], who had commanded JG 2 since the beginning of September 1940, was placed in command of JG 27 instead of Wick.&lt;ref&gt;Ringlstetter 2005, p. 97.&lt;/ref&gt;

JG 2 &quot;Richthofen&quot; claimed its 500th aerial victory on 16 November 1940, earning Wick another reference in the ''Wehrmachtbericht''. To celebrate the 500th victory, Wick, the ''Gruppenkommandeure'', all of the headquarters personnel, and the ''Staffelkapitäne'' went to Paris on 22 November—exactly one year after JG 2's first aerial victory. They visited the show at &quot;''[[Casino de Paris]]''&quot; and dined at the &quot;''[[Hôtel Salomon de Rothschild]]''&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Ringlstetter 2005, p. 111.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Death===
[[File:Bf109E4 Wick Gr.Ko.gelb kl.96.jpg|thumb|left|upright=1.5|Bf 109 E-4 &quot;Schwarzer Doppelwinkel&quot;, ''Werknummer'' 5344, flown by ''Major'' Wick, October 1940]]
Helmut Wick, accompanied by his ''Stabsschwarm''—including ''Oberleutnant'' Rudolf Pflanz, ''Leutnant'' [[Franz Fiby]] and ''Oberleutnant'' Erich Leie — claimed his 55th aerial victory when he shot down a Spitfire on the afternoon of 28 November 1940.{{refn|The book ''Helmut Wick—Das Leben eines Fliegerhelden (Helmut Wick—Life of a Flying Hero)'', published in 1943, was based in large part on Franz Fiby's diary.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ringlstetter p142&quot;&gt;Ringlstetter 2005, p. 142.&lt;/ref&gt; The prime author was ''Kriegsberichter'' ([[war correspondent]]) Josef Grabler. Grabler was [[killed in action]] on 21 May 1941 during the [[Invasion of Crete]].&lt;ref&gt;Grabler 1943, p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=&quot;Note&quot;}} His opponent could have been [[No. 602 Squadron RAF|No. 602 Squadron]]'s [[Pilot Officer]] Archibald Lyall, who was reported killed in the engagement. This made Wick the highest-scoring fighter pilot in the ''Luftwaffe'', surpassing Mölders, whose score at the time stood at 54 victories. Returning from this mission to [[Cherbourg]]- [[Querqueville]], Wick ordered the aircraft refueled and re-armed. Together with [[Erich Leie]] as his wingman, Wick took off at 4:10&amp;nbsp;p.m. and returned to the vicinity of the [[Isle of Wight]]. Spotting a flight of Spitfires he climbed to intercept from a more favourable attack position. In a diving attack Wick shot down and killed Pilot Officer Paul A. Baillon, of [[No. 609 Squadron RAF|No. 609 Squadron]], flying Spitfire ''R6631''.&lt;ref&gt;Weal 2000, p. 69.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote_box
|width=32%
|align=right
|quote=Wick was a real daredevil, He had excellent eyesight and therefore was usually the first to see enemy aircraft. Then he opened the throttle and simply went after them. I didn't do that, but that's probably why I'm still alive and he isn't.
|source=Franz Fiby—Wick's wingman in the Stabsschwarm&lt;ref name=&quot;Ringlstetter p142&quot;/&gt;
}}
Shortly afterwards, around 5 p.m., Wick's Bf 109 E-4 (''Werknummer'' 5344 — factory number) was shot down, probably by twelve–victory ace [[Flight Lieutenant]] [[John Dundas (RAF officer)|John Dundas]] of No. 609 Squadron, though it is also possible that Wick fell victim to Pilot Officer Eric Marrs;&lt;ref name=&quot;Michulec 2002, p. 36&quot;/&gt; Polish pilot Zygmunt Klein of [[No. 234 Squadron RAF|234 Squadron]] may have also scored hits on Wick's aircraft; he was also shot down and killed during the battle.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bbm.org.uk/Klein.htm |title=The Airmen's Stories - Sgt. Z Klein |author= |date= |work= |publisher=The Battle of Britain London Monument|accessdate=29 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Rudolf Pflanz saw a Spitfire shoot down a Bf 109, whose pilot bailed out. Pflanz then shot down the Spitfire, which he observed to crash in the sea with its pilot still inside.

Only later did Pflanz find out that it was Wick he saw bailing out. Göring had ordered ''[[Kriegsmarine]]'' [[torpedo boat]]s on a night-long search-and-rescue mission for Wick. The next day, other naval vessels and the ''[[Seenotdienst]]'' ([[air-sea rescue]]) service, escorted by fighters of JG 2, continued in vain to search for him.&lt;ref&gt;Ringlstetter 2005, p. 9.&lt;/ref&gt; He was never found, however, and the ''Luftwaffe'' declared him [[missing in action]], presumed dead, on 4 December 1940, earning him his last reference in the daily ''Wehrmachtbericht''.&lt;ref&gt;Ringlstetter 2005, pp. 124–127.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wehrmachtbericht p375&quot;&gt;''Die Wehrmachtberichte 1939–1945 Band 1'', p. 375.&lt;/ref&gt; Wick, on his 168th combat mission, was the first Oak Leaves recipient to lose his life in combat.&lt;ref&gt;''Helden der Wehrmacht'' 2004, p. 210.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Obermaier 1989, p. 45.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Family==
On 5 August 1939, Wick married Ursel Rolfs (1916–1968) in Berlin. The marriage produced two children, Walter (born in October 1939) and a girl, Sabine, born after Wick's death, in February 1941.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ringlstetter 2005, p. 17&quot;/&gt; On 23 January 1941, Wick's father received a telephone call from [[Karl Bodenschatz]] at the [[Führer Headquarters]] that Helmut Wick had been rescued and taken [[prisoner of war]]. Apparently an official [[Reuters]] report had indicated that a 25-year-old ''Luftwaffe'' ''Major'', credited with 56 aerial victories, had been interned in a prisoner-of-war camp in Canada. Both Hitler and Göring initiated steps to get confirmation of the report.&lt;ref&gt;Ringlstetter 2005, p. 140.&lt;/ref&gt; On 5 February 1941, a telegram from [[Ottawa]] informed Ursel that Wick was not interned in Canada. Ursel married the military doctor, ''Stabsarzt'' (equivalent to captain) Dr. Gerhard Tausch, later in the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ringlstetter p142&quot;/&gt;

==Awards==
[[File:Helmut Wick EK I und Eichenlaub Stecknadel.JPG|thumb|right|upright=0.8|Wick's Iron Cross and Oak Leaves pin (family possession)]]
* [[Iron Cross]] (1939) 2nd Class (21 December 1939) &amp; 1st Class (6 June 1940)&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomas p441&quot;&gt;Thomas 1998, p. 441.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Pilot/Observer Badge]] in Gold with Diamonds&lt;ref&gt;F.L.Neher: ''WICK''. Hanns Arens Verlag / Berlin - Herrlingen, 1943 S. 1 (in German)&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves]]
** Knight's Cross on 27 August 1940 as ''[[Oberleutnant]]'' and ''[[Staffelkapitän]]'' of the 3./''Jagdgeschwader'' 2 &quot;Richthofen&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Scherzer p783&quot;&gt;Scherzer 2007, p. 783.&lt;/ref&gt;
** 4th Oak Leaves on 25 October 1940 as ''[[Major (Germany)|Major]]'' and ''[[Gruppenkommandeur]]'' of the I./''Jagdgeschwader'' 2 &quot;Richthofen&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Scherzer p783&quot;/&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist|group=&quot;Note&quot;}}

==References==

===Citations===
{{Reflist|25em}}

===Bibliography===
{{Refbegin}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Grabler
  |first=Josef
  |year=1943
  |title=Helmut Wick — Das Leben eines Fliegerhelden
  |language=German
  |location=Berlin, Germany
  |asin=B0025WIWAQ |asin-tld=de
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Hagen
  |first=Hans-Peter
  |year=1998
  |title=Husaren des Himmels Berühmte deutsche Jagdflieger und die Geschichte ihrer Waffe
  |trans_title=
  |language=German
  |location=Rastatt, Germany
  |publisher=Moewig
  |isbn=978-3-8118-1456-1
}}
* Michulec, Robert (2002). ''Luftwaffe at War/Luftwaffe Aces of the Western Front''. London: Greenhill Books. ISBN 1-85367-486-9.
* Neher, F. L. (1943). ''WICK'' (in German). Berlin - Herrlingen: Hanns Arens Verlag.
* {{Cite book
  |last=Obermaier
  |first=Ernst
  |year=1989
  |title=Die Ritterkreuzträger der Luftwaffe Jagdflieger 1939 – 1945
  |trans_title=The Knight's Cross Bearers of the Luftwaffe Fighter Force 1939 – 1945
  |language=German
  |location=Mainz, Germany
  |publisher=Verlag Dieter Hoffmann
  |isbn=978-3-87341-065-7
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Ringlstetter
  |first=Herbert
  |year=2005
  |title=Helmut Wick, An Illustrated Biography of the Luftwaffe Ace and Commander of Jagdgeschwader 2 During the Battle of Britain
  |location=Atglen, PA
  |publisher=[[Schiffer Publishing]]
  |isbn=978-0-7643-2217-4
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Scherzer
  |first=Veit
  |year=2007
  |title=Die Ritterkreuzträger 1939–1945 Die Inhaber des Ritterkreuzes des Eisernen Kreuzes 1939 von Heer, Luftwaffe, Kriegsmarine, Waffen-SS, Volkssturm sowie mit Deutschland verbündeter Streitkräfte nach den Unterlagen des Bundesarchives
  |trans_title=The Knight's Cross Bearers 1939–1945 The Holders of the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross 1939 by Army, Air Force, Navy, Waffen-SS, Volkssturm and Allied Forces with Germany According to the Documents of the Federal Archives
  |language=German
  |location=Jena, Germany
  |publisher=Scherzers Militaer-Verlag
  |isbn=978-3-938845-17-2
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Thomas
  |first=Franz
  |year=1998
  |title=Die Eichenlaubträger 1939–1945 Band 2: L–Z
  |trans_title=The Oak Leaves Bearers 1939–1945 Volume 2: L–Z
  |language=German
  |location=Osnabrück, Germany
  |publisher=Biblio-Verlag
  |isbn=978-3-7648-2300-9
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Weal
  |first=John
  |year=2000
  |title=Jagdgeschwader 2 'Richthofen'
  |location=Oxford, UK
  |publisher=[[Osprey Publishing]]
  |isbn=978-1-84176-046-9
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last1=Williamson
  |first1=Gordon
|authorlink1=Gordon Williamson (writer)
  |last2=Bujeiro
  |first2=Ramiro
  |year=2004
  |title=Knight's Cross and Oak Leaves Recipients 1939–40
  |location=Oxford, UK
  |publisher=[[Osprey Publishing]]
  |isbn=978-1-84176-641-6
}}
* {{Cite book
  |year=1985
  |title=Die Wehrmachtberichte 1939–1945 Band 1, 1. September 1939 bis 31. Dezember 1941
  |trans_title=The Wehrmacht Reports 1939–1945 Volume 1, 1 September 1939 to 31 December 1941
  |language=German
  |location=München, Germany
  |publisher=Deutscher Taschenbuch Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KG
  |isbn=978-3-423-05944-2
}}
{{Refend}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-mil}}
{{succession box
| before = Major [[Wolfgang Schellmann]]
| after  = Hauptmann [[Karl-Heinz Greisert]]
| title  = Commander of [[Jagdgeschwader 2]] ''Richthofen''
| years  = 20 September 1940 – 28 November 1940
}}
{{s-end}}

{{KCwithOL}}
{{Knight's Cross recipients of JG 2}}

{{Authority control}}
{{Subject bar
| portal1=Aviation
| portal2=Biography
| portal3=Military of Germany
| portal4=World War II
| commons=y
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Wick, Helmut}}
[[Category:1915 births]]
[[Category:1940 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Mannheim]]
[[Category:Luftwaffe pilots]]
[[Category:German World War II flying aces]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves]]
[[Category:Military personnel referenced in the Wehrmachtbericht]]
[[Category:German military personnel killed in World War II]]
[[Category:Missing in action of World War II]]
[[Category:People from the Grand Duchy of Baden]]
[[Category:Aviators killed by being shot down]]
[[Category:Aerial disappearances of military personnel in action]]</text>
      <sha1>bi62vxhzc327uu5aym2k2qqyjfjvhr0</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
