<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Hermann Fegelein</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1801372</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750763840</id>
      <parentid>750761647</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-21T18:12:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Favonian</username>
        <id>7007500</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contribs/2607:FB90:6114:5949:0:39:3DA9:4F01|2607:FB90:6114:5949:0:39:3DA9:4F01]] ([[User talk:2607:FB90:6114:5949:0:39:3DA9:4F01|talk]]) to last version by Hmains</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="51304">{{redirect|Fegelein|his brother|Waldemar Fegelein}}
{{Use British English|date=June 2013}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2013}}
{{Infobox military person
| name = Hermann Fegelein
| birth_date = {{birth date|1906|10|30|df=y}}
| death_date = {{death date and age|1945|4|28|1906|10|30|df=y}}
| image = Hermann Fegelein.jpg
| alt = A black-and-white photograph of a smiling man in semi profile wearing a military uniform and a neck order in shape of an Iron Cross.
| caption = Hermann Fegelein as ''SS-Standartenführer''
| birth_place = [[Ansbach]], [[Kingdom of Bavaria]], [[German Empire]]
| death_place = [[Berlin]], [[Free State of Prussia]], [[Nazi Germany]]
| nickname = &quot;Flegelein&quot;{{efn|name=nickname}}
| allegiance =
 {{plainlist |
* {{flag|Weimar Republic}} (until 1933)
* {{flag|Nazi Germany}} (from 1933 to 1945)
 }}
| serviceyears = 1925–45
| branch = {{flagdeco|Weimar Republic|naval}} [[Reichswehr]]&lt;br/&gt;[[File:Flag Schutzstaffel.svg|23px|link=|alt=]] ''[[Waffen-SS]]''
| rank = ''[[SS]]-[[Gruppenführer]] und [[Generalleutnant]] der Waffen-SS''
| servicenumber = [[NSDAP]] #1,200,158&lt;br/&gt;[[SS]] #66,680
| commands =
 {{plainlist |
* [[SS Cavalry Brigade]]
* [[8th SS Cavalry Division Florian Geyer|8th SS Cavalry Division ''Florian Geyer'']]
 }}
| unit = 
| battles = [[World War II]]
| relations = {{plainlist |
* [[Waldemar Fegelein]] (brother)
* [[Eva Braun]] (sister-in-law)
* [[Gretl Braun]] (wife)
}}
| awards = [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves and Swords]]
| laterwork = 
}}

'''Hans Georg Otto Hermann Fegelein''' (30 October 1906&amp;nbsp;– 28 April 1945) was an ''SS-[[Gruppenführer]]'' ([[general]]) of the ''[[Waffen-SS]]'' in [[Nazi Germany]]. He was a member of [[Adolf Hitler]]'s entourage and brother-in-law to [[Eva Braun]] through his marriage to her sister, [[Gretl Braun|Gretl]].

Fegelein joined the ''Reiter-Regiment'' 17 (Cavalry Regiment 17) in 1925 and transferred to the [[SS]] on 10 April 1933. He became a leader of an SS equestrian group, and was in charge of preparation of the courses and facilities for the equestrian events of the [[Berlin Olympic Games]] in 1936. He tried out for the Olympic equestrian team himself, but was eliminated in the qualifying rounds.

In September 1939, after the successful [[Invasion of Poland]], Fegelein commanded the SS ''[[Totenkopf]] Reiterstandarte'' (Death's-Head Horse Regiment). They were garrisoned in [[Warsaw]] until December. In May and June 1940, he participated in the [[Battle of Belgium]] and [[Battle of France|France]] as a member of the ''SS-[[Verfügungstruppe]]'' (later renamed the ''Waffen-SS''). For his service in these campaigns he was awarded the [[Iron Cross]] 2nd Class on 15 December 1940. Units under his command on the Eastern Front in 1941 were responsible for the deaths of over 17,000 civilians during the [[Pripyat swamps (punitive operation)|Pripyat swamps punitive operation]] in the [[Byelorussian Soviet Socialist Republic|Byelorussian SSR]]. As commander of the [[SS Division Florian Geyer|8th SS Cavalry Division ''Florian Geyer'']] in 1943, he was involved in operations against partisans as well as defensive operations against the [[Red Army]], for which he was awarded the [[Close Combat Clasp]] in bronze.

Fegelein was seriously wounded in September 1943, and was reassigned by [[Heinrich Himmler]] to Hitler's headquarters staff as his liaison officer and representative of the SS. Fegelein was present at the [[20 July plot|failed attempt]] on Hitler's life on 20 July 1944. He was on duty at Hitler's ''[[Führerbunker]]'' in Berlin in the closing months of the war, and was shot for desertion on 28 April 1945, two days before Hitler's suicide. Historians [[William L. Shirer]] and [[Ian Kershaw]] characterise him as cynical and disreputable. [[Albert Speer]] called him &quot;one of the most disgusting people in Hitler's circle&quot;.{{sfn|Fest|2006|p=143}} Fegelein was an opportunist who ingratiated himself with Himmler, who granted him the best assignments and rapid promotions.

== Career ==

Fegelein was born in [[Ansbach]], [[Bavaria]], to the retired ''[[Oberleutnant]]'' Hans Fegelein. As a boy working at his father's equestrian school in [[Munich]], he became proficient in riding skills and participated in jumping events. During this period he met [[Christian Weber (SS general)|Christian Weber]], an original member of the [[Nazi Party]]. Weber later sponsored Fegelein's entry into the ''[[Schutzstaffel]]'' (SS).{{sfn|Miller|2006|p=306}}

In 1925, after studying for two terms at [[Ludwig Maximilian University of Munich|Munich University]], Fegelein joined the ''Reiter-Regiment'' 17 (Cavalry Regiment 17). On 20 April 1927, he joined the [[Bavarian State Police]] in Munich as an officer cadet.{{sfn|Joachimsthaler|1999|p=285}} In 1929 he left the police service when he was caught stealing examination solutions from a teaching superior's office. The official communication at the time was that he resigned for &quot;family reasons&quot;. Fegelein later stated that he had left the police on &quot;his own account&quot; to better serve the Nazi Party and SS. His father had started the ''Reitinstitut Fegelein'' (Riding Institute Fegelein) in 1926. In Munich Fegelein came into contact with [[Nazism|National Socialism]] and the SS. His father had made the institute available to the SS as a meeting place, and the training facilities and horses were used by equestrian units of the ''[[Sturmabteilung]]'' (SA) and SS.{{sfn|Krüger|Scharenberg|2014|p=80}}{{sfn|Pieper|2015|p=14}}

Fegelein joined the Nazi Party (membership number 1,200,158) and the SA in 1930. He transferred to the SS on 10 April 1933, with membership number 66,680.{{sfn|Miller|2006|p=305}} He worked as an instructor at the ''Reitinstitut Fegelein'' and became the leader of the ''SS-Reitersturm'', the SS equestrian group based at the facility. By the mid-1930s he took over administration of the school from his father.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|p=14}} He was promoted to the ''[[Allgemeine-SS]]'' rank of ''SS-[[Untersturmführer]]'' that year and to ''SS-[[Obersturmführer]]'' on 20 April 1934 and to ''SS-[[Hauptsturmführer]]'' on 9 November 1934.{{sfn|Stockert|2012|p=227}} Beginning in November 1935, Fegelein oversaw the preparation of the courses and facilities for the equestrian events of the [[Berlin Olympic Games]].{{sfn|Miller|2006|pp=306, 307}} He was promoted to the rank of ''SS-[[Sturmbannführer]]'' on 30 January 1936.{{sfn|Stockert|2012|p=227}} He participated in the selection process for the German equestrian team, but was unable to prevail against the strong competition from the [[:de:Kavallerieschule der Reichswehr|''Kavallerieschule Hannover'']] (cavalry school [[Hanover]]), who went on to win all the [[Equestrian at the 1936 Summer Olympics|equestrian gold medals]].{{sfn|Krüger|Scharenberg|2014|p=81}}

Fegelein won the ''[[:de:Deutsches Spring- und Dressurderby|Deutsches Spring- und Dressurderby]]'' international tournament in 1937, as did his brother, [[Waldemar Fegelein|Waldemar]], in 1939.{{sfn|Jaeger|2004}} He was promoted to the rank of ''SS-[[Obersturmbannführer]]'' on 30 January.{{sfn|Stockert|2012|p=227}} On 25 July 1937 ''[[Reichsführer-SS]]'' [[Himmler]], by special order of the ''[[SS-Oberabschnitt Süd]]'', created the ''Haupt-Reitschule München'' (SS Main Riding School) in Munich. The school was started from his father's [[stud farm]].{{sfn|Krüger|Scharenberg|2014|p=81}} Fegelein was named its commander and promoted to ''SS-[[Standartenführer]]'' the same day.{{sfn|Stockert|2012|p=227}} Funding for the very expensive horses came in part from then ''SS-[[Brigadeführer]]'' Weber, who supported the school with more than 100,000 [[Reichsmark]]s annually.{{sfn|Krüger|Scharenberg|2014|p=82}} Fegelein won the &quot;''[[:de:Braunes Band von Deutschland|Braunes Band von Deutschland]]''&quot; (Brown Ribbon of Germany), an annual horse race which in 1938 was held on the premises of the riding school in Munich.{{sfn|Krüger|Scharenberg|2014|p=83}} Fegelein at the time had strong ambitions to participate in the [[1940 Summer Olympics]]. With the help of his friend {{Lang|de|[[SS and Police Leader|''Höherer SS- und Polizeiführer'']]}} (HSSPF; Higher SS and Police Leader) [[Karl von Eberstein]], he arranged the transfer of all the Bavarian State Police horses to the SS riding school in case of [[mobilization]]. His fear was that the horses would be handed to the [[Wehrmacht]].{{sfn|Krüger|Scharenberg|2014|p=83}}

=== World War II ===
In September 1939, Fegelein commanded the SS ''[[Totenkopf]] Reiterstandarte'' (Death's-Head Horse Regiment), which arrived in Poland shortly after the end of the [[Polish Campaign]].{{sfn|Pieper|2015|p=29}} The unit was placed under the command of the ''[[Ordnungspolizei]]'' (Orpo; order police) and was split into small groups assigned to support police activities at posts throughout the [[Poznan]] district.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|p=29}} On 15 November, Himmler ordered the expansion of the regiment from four to thirteen squadrons and renamed it as ''1. SS-Totenkopf-Reiterstandarte'' (1st Death's Head Cavalry Regiment). Additional men were recruited from ethnic Germans living in the [[General Government]] and further afield. Many of the officers, including Fegelein, had never attended officer training school, so much of the training provided to new recruits was rudimentary. However, it was rigorous, and the men developed a strong camaraderie.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|pp=29–31}} Fegelein's unit was involved alongside the Orpo in the extermination, ordered by Hitler, of members of the Polish elite such as intellectuals, aristocrats, and clergy, in an action called ''[[Intelligenzaktion]]''.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|p=38}} On 7 December 1939 Fegelein's unit was involved in the mass shooting of 1,700 such people in the [[Kampinos Forest]].{{sfn|Miller|2006|p=308}}

On 15 December, the unit was split into two ''Standarten'' (regiments), with Fegelein commanding the ''1. Standarte'' under the overall command of ''[[Höherer SS- und Polizeiführer]]-Ost'' [[Friedrich-Wilhelm Krüger]].{{sfn|Miller|2006|p=308}} The unit was short of basic supplies such as weapons, food, and uniforms, which led to deteriorating morale and ill health. Incidents of corruption and theft took place, particularly among members of the regimental staff in Warsaw.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|p=33}} On 23 April 1941, Fegelein faced court-martial charges for an incident in 1940 where he and his unit had been caught stealing money and luxury goods for transportation back to Germany. Fegelein's court-martial was quashed by direct order of Himmler.{{sfn|Miller|2006|p=309}}{{sfn|Krüger|Scharenberg|2014|p=84}} The allegations brought forward against Fegelein had included &quot;murder motivated by greed&quot;. Apparently he had ordered arrests and executions in the [[Gestapo]] prison in Warsaw. In addition to this, Fegelein was charged with having had an unlawful sexual relationship with a Polish woman. The woman had become pregnant and Fegelein forced her to have an abortion. [[Reinhard Heydrich]] attempted multiple times to investigate the accusations against Fegelein, but each time the attempt was put down by Himmler.{{sfn|Krüger|Scharenberg|2014|p=85}}

Fegelein's unit took part in anti-partisan fighting against a group of about 100 former Polish soldiers in the area of [[Kamienna, Świętokrzyskie Voivodeship|Kammienna]]–[[Końskie|Konsky]]–[[Kielce]] in March and April 1940. They killed about half the partisans, and the remainder escaped. On 8 April, Fegelien's unit killed 250 Polish men in villages in the area. While in his report he described the behaviour of his troops as &quot;clean and decent&quot;, there were many incidents in this period where his men behaved in an undisciplined way, killing and robbing civilians without any orders.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|pp=39–40}}

In May and June 1940, Fegelein, who had been promoted to ''SS-Obersturmbannführer'' of the [[Military reserve force|Reserves]] in the ''[[Waffen-SS]]'' on 1 March 1940, participated in the [[Battle of Belgium]] and [[Battle of France|France]] as a member of the ''SS-[[Verfügungstruppe]]''. For his service in these campaigns he was awarded the [[Iron Cross]] 2nd Class on 15 December 1940. In March 1941 the SS ''Totenkopf Reiterstandarte'' 1 was renamed to 1st SS Cavalry Regiment.{{sfn|Stockert|2012|p=228}}

=== War against the Soviet Union ===
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101III-Bueschel-056-21A, Russland, Hermann Fegelein mit Sturmbannführer Karl Gesele.jpg|right|thumb|Fegelein (right) with [[Karl Gesele]] (1942)|alt=A black-and-white photograph of two men wearing military uniforms with various military decorations attached to their uniforms. The man on the left is wearing glasses and is smoking a cigarette, the man on the right is smoking a cigar.]]

With the start of the [[Operation Barbarossa|German invasion of the Soviet Union]], which began on 22 June 1941, Fegelein saw active service on the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]]. His unit was assigned on the [[87th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|87th Infantry Division]] on 23 June to cover a gap in the lines of the [[9th Army (Wehrmacht)|9th Army]] near [[Białystok]]. The motorized elements of the 1st SS Cavalry reached the right flank of the operational area on 24 June, but the mounted elements were unable to maintain the pace. The exhausted horses had to be left behind and the men transported to the combat zone in lorries, while the horse-drawn artillery pieces were towed using any available vehicles. The first units to arrive crossed the [[Narew]] near [[Wizna]] and engaged the Soviets but were unable to break through. They were ordered to retreat and move further north. Infantry elements of the 87th Division captured [[Osowiec Fortress]] on 26 June, and Fegelein's cavalry was sent on a reconnaissance mission to the south-east. Himmler, not keen to have his SS units under Wehrmacht control or used in combat other than as reserves, withdrew the SS cavalry from control of the 87th Division on 27 June. The ambitious Fegelein stressed in his reports that he believed his unit was combat ready and had played a bigger role in the operation than they actually had. Ten of his men received the Iron Cross, Second Class for their efforts, and Fegelein was awarded the Iron Cross, First Class.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|pp=53–56}}

The engagement had demonstrated the shortcomings of the cavalry units in modern mobile warfare, which requires quick redeployments in ever-changing conditions. Fegelein sought to improve this by asking Himmler to combine the 1st and 2nd SS cavalry regiments into a brigade, with additional support units. As a temporary measure, Himmler assigned Fegelein to be in charge of both regiments.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|pp=52–53}} Fegelein's unit was one of several that undertook field training and political indoctrination in the coming weeks.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|p=60}} Himmler himself addressed the 1st Cavalry on 5 July, offering the opportunity for any men unwilling to participate in the upcoming &quot;special tasks&quot; to transfer to another unit. Nobody took advantage of this offer, at least partly because it was not made clear that the upcoming work would include the mass shooting of unarmed civilians.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|p=62}}

On 19 July 1941 Himmler assigned Fegelein's regiments to the general command of HSSPF [[Erich von dem Bach-Zelewski]] for the &quot;systematic combing&quot; of the [[Pripyat swamps (punitive operation)|Pripyat swamps]], an operation designed to round up and exterminate [[Jews]], partisans and civilians in that area of [[Byelorussian Soviet Socialist Republic|Byelorussian SSR]].{{sfn|Pieper|2015|pp=62, 80}} Himmler's orders for the operation were passed to Fegelein via ''[[SS-Brigadefuhrer]]'' {{illm|Kurt Knoblauch|de}}, who met with him and Bach-Zelewski on 28 July in their new quarters at [[Lyakhavichy|Liakhovichi]] in Byelorussia. General instructions were given to &quot;cleanse&quot; the area of partisans and Jewish collaborators. Jewish women and children were to be driven away. Fegelein interpreted these orders as follows: Enemy soldiers in uniform were to be taken prisoner, and those found out of uniform were to be shot. Jewish males, with the exception of a few skilled workers such as doctors and leather workers, would be shot.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|pp=80–81}}{{efn|name=orders}} Fegelein split the territory to be covered into two sections divided by the [[Pripyat River]], with the 1st Regiment taking the northern half and the 2nd Regiment the south.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|p=81}} The regiments worked their way from east to west through their assigned territory, and filed daily reports on the number of people killed and taken prisoner. In a meeting with Bach-Zelewski on 31 July, Himmler announced the amalgamation of the two regiments into the [[SS Cavalry Brigade]]. Additional units such as a bicycle reconnaissance detachment were formed and added to the brigade's complement.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|pp=81–82}} On 5 August Himmler assigned leadership of the brigade to Fegelein.{{sfn|Stockert|2012|p=228}}

Himmler notified Fegelein by telegram on 1 August that the numbers killed were far too low. A few days later, Himmler issued regimental order no. 42, which called for all male Jews over the age of 14 to be killed. The women and children were to be driven into the swamps and drowned. Thus Fegelein's units were among the first in [[the Holocaust]] to wipe out entire Jewish communities.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|pp=86, 88–89}} As the water in the swamps was too shallow and some areas had no swamps, it proved impractical to drown the women and children, so they were shot.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|pp=89–90}} Fegelein's final report on the operation, dated 18 September 1941, states that they killed 14,178 Jews, 1,001 partisans, 699 Red Army soldiers, with 830 prisoners taken and losses of 17 dead, 36 wounded, and 3 missing.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|pp=119–120}}{{sfn|Miller|2006|p=310}} The historian Henning Pieper estimates the actual number of Jews killed was closer to 23,700.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|p=120}}

Fegelein received the [[Infantry Assault Badge]] on 2 October. Four days later, he was again brought before a court for [[Wiktionary:peculation#Etymology|peculation]] of captured goods. Again the prosecution was halted by Himmler.{{sfn|Stockert|2012|p=228}} In mid-October 1941 the brigade left Byelorussia and moved first to [[Toropets]] and then on to [[Rogachev]] by train, where they were subordinated to [[Army Group Centre]]. The new operational area had more partisan activity than the Pripyat swamps, with guerrillas who were well organised and difficult to find.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|pp=133–134}} Fegelein's report for the period between 18 October and 18 November 1941 shows 3,018 partisans and Red Army soldiers killed and 122 taken prisoner. However, as fewer than 200 weapons were captured, historians Martin Cüppers and Henning Pieper conclude that the majority of those killed must have been unarmed civilians. Brigade losses were seven dead and nine wounded.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|p=133}}

Army Group Centre renewed their offensive on Moscow in mid-November.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|p=144}} Fegelein and the SS Cavalry Brigade were held back as an operational reserve in the rearward area of the 9th Army.{{sfn|Stockert|2012|p=228}} Massive counter-attacks by the Red Army led to a weakening of the entire German line, and the brigade was called in to fight at the front on 28 December. While Fegelein reported that his forces were the equivalent to one or two [[Division (military)|divisions]], in reality he had only 4,428 men in total at this point, of which 1,800 were ready for action.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|pp=144–146}} The brigade was deployed at the south-eastern sector of the [[XXIII Army Corps (Wehrmacht)|XXIII Army Corps]], where it defended against attacks in the rearward area of the [[206th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|206th Infantry Division]] in the [[Battles of Rzhev]].{{sfn|Stockert|2012|p=228}} The SS Cavalry Brigade took serious losses, with casualties of up to 60 per cent in some squadrons.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|pp=146–147}}

On 1 February 1942 Fegelein was promoted to ''SS-Standartenführer'' in the ''Waffen-SS'' and transferred from the reserve force to active service. Four days later, on 5 February, Fegelein on his own initiative led an attack on a strong enemy group northwest of Chertolino. The attack, carried out in difficult weather conditions, secured an important road junction and the railway station at Chertolino. In a nocturnal attack on 9 February, the brigade encircled and destroyed enemy forces at Chertolino, killing 1,800 Red Army soldiers. Yershovo was captured on 14 February, leading to the annihilation of the enemy units in the [[Rzhevsky District|Rzhev area]]. For his leadership in these battles, Fegelein was awarded the [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross]] on 2 March 1942. Fegelein was then granted home leave and was appointed Inspector of Cavalry and Transportation ({{Lang|de|''Inspekteur des Reit- und Fahrwesens''}}) in the ''[[SS-Führungshauptamt]]'' on 1 May 1942. In this position he was awarded the [[Eastern Front Medal]] and the [[War Merit Cross]] 2nd Class with Swords, both on 1 September 1942.{{sfn|Stockert|2012|p=228}} The SS Cavalry Brigade was disbanded in March 1942 and the remaining men and equipment were formed into a [[battalion]]-strength unit called ''Kampfgruppe Zehender'', commanded by ''[[SS-Sturmbannführer]]'' [[August Zehender]].{{sfn|Pieper|2015|p=156}}

Fegelein was sent back to the front line on 1 December 1942 and on the same day promoted to ''SS-[[Oberführer]]''. He was given command of ''[[Kampfgruppe]]'' &quot;Fegelein&quot;, based in the great bend of the [[Don River (Russia)|Don]].{{sfn|Stockert|2012|p=228}} He was wounded in action by Soviet [[sniper]]s on 21 December and 22 December 1942.{{sfn|Miller|2006|p=309}}

On 20 April 1943 he was appointed commander of the [[8th SS Cavalry Division Florian Geyer|SS Cavalry Division]].{{sfn|Miller|2006|pp=312, 313}} Fegelein and his division were involved in operations against partisans in May to July 1943, which included Operation ''Weichsel'', Operation ''Zeithen'' and [[Operation Seydlitz|Operation ''Seydlitz'']]. On 17 May they annihilated a partisan group south west of Novoselki. He personally blew up a bunker in the attack. A week later, on 24 May, the division attacked another partisan strongpoint, and no prisoners were taken. During ''Weichsel'' (27 May – 10 June 1943) he reported the unit had killed 4,018 persons and deported 18,860, confiscated 21,000 cattle and destroyed 61 villages southwest of [[Gomel]]. During ''Zeithen'' (13–16 June 1943) they destroyed a further 63 villages and (under direct orders from Hitler) killed all suspected partisans. During ''Seydlitz'' (26 June – 27 July 1943) he reported the destruction of 96 additional villages, with 5,016 killed and 9,166 deported and 19,941 cattle confiscated.{{sfn|Stockert|2012|p=229}}

The division was then deployed in defensive operations against massed Soviet attacks. From 26 August to 15 September the division repulsed five attacks of divisional strength and a further 85 attacks of battalion strength. The heaviest combat occurred on 26 August near Bespalovka and on 28 August, when the division halted a Soviet breakthrough at Bol'shaya Gomol'sha. Fegelein led a counterattack on 8 September, recapturing the height 199,0 at Verkhniy Bishkin. On 11 September 1943, during these defensive battles, he was awarded the [[Close Combat Clasp]] in bronze. Fegelein was severely wounded on 30 September 1943 and was hospitalised for a few weeks. He received the [[German Cross]] in gold on 1 November 1943. Following his convalescence he was appointed chief of ''Amt'' VI—Office for Rider and Driver Training—in the ''SS-Führungshauptamt'' on 1 January 1944.{{sfn|Stockert|2012|p=229}}

At the same time, Himmler assigned him to Hitler's headquarters staff as his liaison officer and representative of the SS.{{sfn|Miller|2006|p=313}} He was promoted to the rank of ''SS-[[Gruppenführer]] und [[Generalleutnant]] der Waffen-SS'' on 10 June 1944.{{sfn|Miller|2006|p=306}} On 20 July 1944 Fegelein was present at the [[20 July plot|failed attempt]] on Hitler's life at the [[Wolf's Lair]] headquarters in [[Rastenburg]], [[East Prussia]] and received a minor wound to his left thigh from the bomb blast.{{sfn|Miller|2006|p=314}} Fegelein often showed around the photographs of the hanged men who had been executed as a result of this failed assassination attempt.{{sfn|Görtemaker|2011|p=216}}

=== Marriage ===

Fegelein's politically motivated marriage to [[Gretl Braun]], [[Eva Braun]]'s sister, took place on 3 June 1944 in [[Salzburg]]. Historians Kershaw and Shirer believe he courted Braun as a way to advance his career.{{sfn|Shirer|1960|p=1121}}{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=942}} Hitler, Himmler and [[Martin Bormann]] acted as witnesses at the ceremony.{{sfn|Miller|2006|p=316}} A two-day celebration was then held at Hitler's and Bormann's [[Obersalzberg]] mountain homes and the [[Kehlsteinhaus|Eagle's Nest]].{{sfn|Eberle|Uhl|2005|p=144}} Fegelein was a known playboy and had many extramarital affairs.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=942}} Hitler's secretaries, [[Christa Schroeder]] and [[Traudl Junge]], state Fegelein was popular socially, particularly with women. He could be funny, amusing and charming. After his marriage to Gretl, Eva was glad to have someone in the entourage with whom she could dance and flirt, as Hitler was distant in social situations and refrained from publicly showing affection.{{sfn|Joachimsthaler|1999|pp=264, 270–273}} Thereafter, Fegelein worked hard to develop a friendship with Hitler's powerful private secretary, Martin Bormann. Fegelein &quot;never missed&quot; Bormann's drinking parties and told Junge that the only things that mattered were &quot;his career and a life full of fun.&quot;{{sfn|Joachimsthaler|1999|pp=270–271}}

== Death ==

By early 1945, Germany's military situation was on the verge of total collapse. Hitler, presiding over a rapidly disintegrating [[Third Reich]], retreated to his ''[[Führerbunker]]'' in Berlin on 16 January 1945. To the Nazi leadership, it was clear that the [[Battle of Berlin|battle for Berlin]] would be the final battle of the war.{{sfn|Beevor|2002|p=139}} Berlin was bombarded by Soviet artillery for the first time on 20 April 1945 (Hitler's birthday). By the evening of 21 April, [[Red Army]] tanks reached the outskirts of the city.{{sfn|Beevor|2002|pp=255–256, 262}} By 27 April, Berlin was cut off from the rest of Germany.{{sfn|Beevor|2002|p=323}}

On 27 April 1945, ''[[Reichssicherheitsdienst]]'' (RSD) deputy commander ''SS-Obersturmbannführer'' [[Peter Högl]] was sent out from the [[Reich Chancellery]] to find Fegelein who had abandoned his post at the ''Führerbunker'' after deciding he did not want to &quot;join a suicide pact&quot;.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=942}} Fegelein was caught by the RSD squad in his Berlin apartment, wearing civilian clothes and preparing to flee to [[Sweden]] or [[Switzerland]]. He was carrying cash—German and foreign—and jewellery, some of which belonged to Braun. Högl also uncovered a briefcase containing documents with evidence of Himmler's attempted peace negotiations with the [[Western Allies]].{{sfn|Joachimsthaler|1999|pp=277, 278}} According to most accounts, he was intoxicated when arrested and brought back to the ''Führerbunker''.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=942}} He was kept in a makeshift cell until the evening of 28 April. That night, Hitler was informed of the [[BBC]] broadcast of a [[Reuters]] news report about Himmler's attempted negotiations with the western Allies via [[Count Folke Bernadotte of Wisborg|Count Bernadotte]].{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|pp=942, 943, 945, 946}} Hitler flew into a rage about this apparent betrayal and ordered Himmler's arrest.{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|pp=945, 946}} Sensing a connection between Fegelein's disappearance and Himmler's betrayal, Hitler ordered ''SS-Gruppenführer'' [[Heinrich Müller (Gestapo)|Heinrich Müller]] to interrogate Fegelein as to what he knew of Himmler's plans.{{sfn|Beevor|2002|pp=341, 342}} Thereafter, according to [[Otto Günsche]] (Hitler's personal adjutant), Hitler ordered that Fegelein be stripped of all rank and to be transferred to ''Kampfgruppe'' &quot;Mohnke&quot; to prove his loyalty in combat. However, Günsche and Bormann expressed their concern to Hitler that Fegelein would only desert again. Hitler then ordered Fegelein court-martialed.{{sfn|Joachimsthaler|1999|pp=277, 278}}

Journalist [[James P. O'Donnell]], who conducted extensive interviews in the 1970s, provides one account of what happened next. ''SS-Brigadeführer'' [[Wilhelm Mohnke]], who presided over the court martial for desertion, told O'Donnell that Hitler ordered him to set up a tribunal. Mohnke arranged for a court martial panel, which consisted of generals [[Wilhelm Burgdorf]], [[Hans Krebs (general)|Hans Krebs]], ''SS-Gruppenführer'' [[Johann Rattenhuber]], and himself. Fegelein, still drunk, refused to accept that he had to answer to Hitler, and stated that he was responsible only to Himmler. Fegelein was so drunk that he was crying and vomiting; he was unable to stand up, and even urinated on the floor. Mohnke was in a quandary, as German military and civilian law both require a defendant to be of sound mind and to understand the charges against them. Although Mohnke was certain Fegelein was &quot;guilty of flagrant desertion&quot;, it was the opinion of the judges that he was in no condition to stand trial, so Mohnke closed the proceedings and turned the defendant over to General Rattenhuber's security squad. Mohnke never saw Fegelein again.{{sfn|O'Donnell|1978|pp=182, 183}}

An alternative scenario of Fegelein's death is based on the 1948/49 Soviet [[NKVD]] [[The Hitler Book|dossier of Hitler]] written for [[Joseph Stalin]]. The dossier is based on the interrogation reports of Günsche and [[Heinz Linge]] (Hitler's valet). This dossier differs in part from the accounts given by Mohnke and Rattenhuber.{{sfn|O'Donnell|1978|pp=182, 183}}{{sfn|Vinogradov|2005|pp=191, 192}} After the intoxicated Fegelein was arrested and brought back to the ''Führerbunker'', Hitler at first ordered Fegelein to be transferred to ''Kampfgruppe'' &quot;Mohnke&quot; to prove his loyalty in combat. Günsche and Bormann expressed their concern to Hitler that Fegelein would desert again. Hitler then ordered Fegelein to be demoted and court-martialed by a court led by Mohnke.{{sfn|Eberle|Uhl|2011|pp=430–431}} At this point the accounts differ, as the NKVD dossier states that Fegelein was court-martialed on the evening of 28 April, by a court headed by Mohnke, ''SS-Obersturmbannführer'' Alfred Krause, and ''SS-Sturmbannführer'' Herbert Kaschula. Mohnke and his fellow officers sentenced Fegelein to death. That same evening, Fegelein was shot from behind by a member of the ''[[Sicherheitsdienst]]''.{{sfn|Eberle|Uhl|2011|p=436}} Based on this stated chain of events, author Veit Scherzer concluded that Fegelein, according to German law, was deprived of all honours and honorary signs and must therefore be considered a ''[[de facto]]'' but not ''[[de jure]]'' recipient of the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross.{{sfn|Scherzer|2007|pp=115–116, 128}}

Fegelein's wife was then in the late stages of pregnancy (the baby was born in early May). Hitler considered releasing him without punishment or assigning him to Mohnke's troops.{{sfn|Fest|2002|p=99}}{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=946}} Junge—an eye-witness to bunker events—stated that Braun pleaded with Hitler to spare her brother-in-law and tried to justify Fegelein's actions. However, he was taken to the garden of the Reich Chancellery on 28 April, and was &quot;shot like a dog&quot;.{{sfn|Junge|2004|p=180}}{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=945}} [[Rochus Misch]], who was the last survivor from the ''Führerbunker'', disputed aspects of this account in a 2007 interview with ''[[Der Spiegel]]''. According to Misch, Hitler did not order Fegelein's execution, only his demotion. Misch claimed to know the identity of Fegelein's killer, but refused to reveal his name.{{sfn|Simon|2007}}

== Assessment ==
Historians [[William L. Shirer]] and [[Ian Kershaw]] characterise Fegelein as cynical and disreputable;{{sfn|Shirer|1960|p=1121}}{{sfn|Kershaw|2008|p=942}} [[Albert Speer]] called him &quot;one of the most disgusting people in Hitler's circle&quot;.{{sfn|Fest|2006|p=143}} Fegelein was an opportunist who ingratiated himself with Himmler, who in return granted him the best assignments—mostly related to cavalry—and rapid promotion through the ranks.{{sfn|Miller|2006|p=306}}{{sfn|Joachimsthaler|1999|pp=267–269, 285}} The historian Henning Pieper, who studied the period up until March 1942, notes Fegelein's lack of formal training as an officer led to deficiencies in the way the SS Cavalry Brigade was prepared for active service.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|p=30}} Fegelein repeatedly over-stated the combat readiness of his troops and exaggerated their accomplishments, in Pieper's opinion in order to be seen as a leader worthy of promotion and honours.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|p=167–168}} Fegelein's faulty analysis of his brigade's readiness led to their use in December 1941 through March 1942 in combat situations for which they were unsuitable and untrained.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|p=146}} (However, as the military situation was deteriorating, they would eventually have been thrown into this role regardless.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|p=170}}) By the end of March 1942, the brigade had suffered casualties of 50 per cent, much higher than army units deployed in the same area.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|p=171}}

Fegelein's parents and his brother Waldemar survived the war.{{sfn|Miller|2006|p=315}} Gretl, who inherited some of Eva's valuable jewellery, also survived the war. She gave birth to a daughter (named Eva Barbara Fegelein, after her late aunt) on 5 May 1945.{{sfn|Miller|2006|p=316}} Eva Fegelein committed suicide on 25 April 1971 after her boyfriend was killed in a car accident.{{sfn|Miller|2006|p=316}} Gretl Braun-Fegelein moved to Munich and remarried in 1954. She died in 1987, aged 72.{{sfn|Miller|2006|p=316}}

== Awards and decorations ==
* [[Olympic Games Decoration]] (1st Class){{sfn|Miller|2006|p=315}}
* [[German Equestrian Badge]] (gold){{sfn|Miller|2006|p=315}}
* [[German Sports Badge]] (bronze){{sfn|Miller|2006|p=315}}
* [[SA Sports Badge]] (bronze){{sfn|Miller|2006|p=315}}
* [[Nazi Party Long Service Award]] (bronze){{sfn|Miller|2006|p=315}}
* [[General Assault Badge]] (silver){{sfn|Berger|1999|p=70}}
* [[Infantry Assault Badge]] (silver){{sfn|Berger|1999|p=70}}
* [[Close Combat Clasp]] (silver){{sfn|Berger|1999|p=70}}
* [[Wound Badge]] (silver){{sfn|Berger|1999|p=70}}
* [[Wound Badge#Wound Badge of 20 July 1944|Wound Badge of 20 July 1944]] (silver){{sfn|Miller|2006|p=315}}
* [[Iron Cross]] (1939)
** 2nd Class (15 December 1940){{sfn|Thomas|1997|p=161}}
** 1st Class (28 June 1941){{sfn|Thomas|1997|p=161}}
* [[German Cross]] in Gold on 1 November 1943 as ''SS-[[Brigadeführer]]'' and ''[[Generalmajor]]'' of the ''Waffen-SS'' in the ''SS-Kavallerie-Division''{{sfn|Patzwall|Scherzer|2001|p=110}}
* [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves and Swords]]
** Knight's Cross on 2 March 1942 as ''SS-[[Standartenführer]]'' and commander of the ''SS-Kavallerie-Brigade''{{sfn|Fellgiebel|2000|p=178}}{{sfn|Von Seemen|1976|p=124}}
** 157th Oak Leaves on 22 December 1942 as ''SS-[[Oberführer]]'' and commander of a ''[[Kampfgruppe]]'' {{sfn|Fellgiebel|2000|pp= 63, 477}}{{sfn|Von Seemen|1976|p=31}}{{efn|name=Krätschmer}}
** 83rd Swords on 30 July 1944 as ''SS-[[Gruppenführer]]'' and ''[[Generalleutnant]]'' of the ''Waffen-SS'' and commander of the ''8. SS-Freiwilligen-Kavallerie-Division Florian Geyer''{{sfn|Fellgiebel|2000|p=44}}{{sfn|Von Seemen|1976|p=17}}

The death sentence on 28 April resulted in the loss of all orders, awards, and honorary signs.{{sfn|Scherzer|2007|p=128}}{{sfn|O'Donnell|1978|pp=182, 183, 215}}

== Dates of rank ==
Fegelein held various ranks in both the ''Allgemeine-SS'' and ''Waffen-SS''. The following table shows that progression was not synchronous.{{sfn|Stockert|2012|pp=227–230}}

{| style=&quot;background:none;&quot;
! Date
! ''Allgemeine-SS''
! ''Waffen-SS''
|-
| 12 June 1933: || ''SS-[[Untersturmführer]]''{{sfn|Stockert|2012|p=227}} || {{center|—}}
|-
| 20 April 1934: || ''SS-[[Obersturmführer]]''{{sfn|Stockert|2012|p=227}} || {{center|—}}
|-
| 9 November 1934: || ''SS-[[Hauptsturmführer]]''{{sfn|Stockert|2012|p=227}} || {{center|—}}
|-
| 30 January 1936: || ''SS-[[Sturmbannführer]]''{{sfn|Stockert|2012|p=227}} || {{center|—}}
|-
| 30 January 1937: || ''SS-[[Obersturmbannführer]]''{{sfn|Stockert|2012|p=227}} || {{center|—}}
|-
| 25 July 1937: || ''SS-[[Standartenführer]]''{{sfn|Stockert|2012|p=227}} || {{center|—}}
|-
| 1 March 1940: || {{center|—}} || ''SS-[[Obersturmbannführer]]'' of the [[Military reserve force|Reserves]] {{sfn|Stockert|2012|p=228}}
|-
| 1 February 1942: || {{center|—}} || ''SS-Standartenführer''{{sfn|Stockert|2012|p=228}}
|-
| 1 May 1943: || {{center|—}} || ''SS-[[Brigadeführer]]'' and ''[[Generalmajor]]'' of the ''Waffen-SS''{{sfn|Stockert|2012|p=228}}
|-
| 21 June 1944: || {{center|—}} || ''SS-[[Gruppenführer]]'' and ''[[Generalleutnant]]'' of the ''Waffen-SS''{{sfn|Stockert|2012|p=230}}
|}

== References ==

=== Explanatory notes ===
{{notes
| refs =
{{efn
| name = nickname
| Those close to Fegelein had nicknamed him &quot;''F'''l'''egelein''&quot; ({{harvnb|O'Donnell|1978|p=186}}). In German, one refers to someone as a ''Flegel'' (lout or brat) for lack of manners and appropriate behaviour. ''Flegelein'' is the [[hypocoristic]] form of a ''Flegel''.
}}
{{efn
| name = orders
| The historian [[Peter Longerich]] notes that most orders to carry out criminal activities such as the killing of civilians were vague, and couched in terminology that had a specific meaning for members of the regime. Leaders were given briefings about the need to be &quot;severe&quot; and &quot;firm&quot;; all Jews were to be viewed as potential enemies that had to be dealt with ruthlessly. {{harvnb|Longerich|2010|pp=189–190}}.
}}
{{efn
| name = Krätschmer
| According to Krätschmer, 157th Oak Leaves as commander of Kampfgruppe &quot;Fegelein&quot; ({{harvnb|Krätschmer|1999|p=265}}).
}}
}}

=== Citations ===
{{reflist|30em}}

=== Bibliography ===
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book
  | last = Beevor
  | first = Antony
  | authorlink = Antony Beevor
  | year = 2002
  | title = [[Berlin: The Downfall 1945|Berlin&amp;nbsp;– The Downfall 1945]]
  | publisher = Viking-Penguin
  | location = New York
  | isbn = 978-0-670-03041-5
  | ref = harv
}}
* {{cite book
  | last = Berger
  | first = Florian
  | year = 1999
  | language = German
  | title = Mit Eichenlaub und Schwertern. Die höchstdekorierten Soldaten des Zweiten Weltkrieges
  | trans_title = With Oak Leaves and Swords. The Highest Decorated Soldiers of the Second World War
  | publisher = Berger
  | location = Wien, Austria
  | isbn = 3-9501307-0-5
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
 | editor1-last = Eberle
 | editor1-first = Henrik
 | editor2-last = Uhl
 | editor2-first = Matthias
 | title = The Hitler Book: The Secret Dossier Prepared for Stalin
 | year = 2005
 | publisher = Public Affairs
 | location = New York
 | ref = harv
}}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Eberle
  | first1 = Henrik
  | last2 = Uhl
  | first2 = Matthias
  | year = 2011
  | language = German
  | title = [[The Hitler Book|Das Buch Hitler]]: Geheimdossier des NKWD für Josef W. Stalin, zusammengestellt aufgrund der Verhörprotokolle des Persönlichen Adjutanten Hitlers, Otto Günsche und des Kammerdieners Heinz Linge, Moskau 1948/49
  | trans_title = The Hitler Book: The Secret NKWD Dossier Prepared for Josef W. Stalin, Compiled on the Basis of Interrogation Records of Hitler's Personal Adjutant, Otto Günsche and the Valet Heinz Linge, Moscow 1948/49
  | location = Bergisch Gladbach, Germany
  | publisher = Bastei Lübbe
  | isbn = 978-3-404-64219-9
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Fellgiebel
  | first = Walther-Peer
  | authorlink = Walther-Peer Fellgiebel
  | year = 2000
  | origyear = 1986
  | language = German
  | title = Die Träger des Ritterkreuzes des Eisernen Kreuzes, 1939–1945: Die Inhaber der höchsten Auszeichnung des Zweiten Weltkrieges aller Wehrmachtteile
  | trans_title = The Bearers of the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross 1939–1945 — The Owners of the Highest Award of the Second World War of all Wehrmacht Branches
  | publisher = Podzun-Pallas
  | location = Friedberg, Germany
  | isbn = 978-3-7909-0284-6
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Fest
  | first = Joachim C
  | authorlink = Joachim Fest
  | year = 2002
  | title = [[Inside Hitler's Bunker|Inside Hitler's Bunker: The Last Days of the Third Reich]]
  | publisher = Picador
  | location = New York
  | isbn = 978-0-312-42392-6
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Fest
  | first = Joachim C
  | authorlink = Joachim Fest
  | year = 2006
  | language = German
  | title = Die unbeantwortbaren Fragen: Notizen über Gespräche mit Albert Speer zwischen Ende 1966 und 1981
  | trans_title = The unanswered Questions: Conversation Notes with Albert Speer between late 1966 and 1981
  | publisher = Rowohlt
  | location = Hamburg
  | isbn = 978-3-499-62159-8
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Görtemaker
  | first = Heike B.
  | year = 2011
  | title = Eva Braun: Life with Hitler
  | publisher = [[Alfred A. Knopf]]
  | location = New York
  | isbn = 978-0-307-59582-9
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite web
  | last = Jaeger
  | first = Hans-Eckart
  | date = 18 May 2004
  | title = Als Hitlers Schwager das Spring-Derby gewann
  | publisher = ''[[Hamburger Abendblatt]]'' online
  | language = German
  | url = http://www.abendblatt.de/sport/article682017/Als-Hitlers-Schwager-das-Spring-Derby-gewannnbsp-nbsp-nbsp.html
  | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20100818072044/http://www.abendblatt.de/sport/article682017/Als-Hitlers-Schwager-das-Spring-Derby-gewannnbsp-nbsp-nbsp.html
  | archivedate = 18 August 2010
  | accessdate = 8 July 2015
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Joachimsthaler
  | first = Anton
  | others = Trans. Helmut Bögler
  | year = 1999
  | origyear = 1995
  | title = The Last Days of Hitler: The Legends, the Evidence, the Truth
  | publisher = Brockhampton Press
  | location = London
  | isbn = 978-1-86019-902-8
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Junge
  | first = Traudl
  | authorlink = Traudl Junge
  | year = 2004
  | title = [[Until the Final Hour|Until the Final Hour: Hitler's Last Secretary]]
  | publisher = Arcade
  | location = New York
  | isbn = 978-1-55970-728-2
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Kershaw
  | first = Ian
  | authorlink = Ian Kershaw
  | year = 2008
  | title = Hitler: A Biography
  | publisher = W. W. Norton &amp; Company
  | location = New York
  | isbn = 978-0-393-06757-6
  | ref = harv
  }}
*  {{cite book
  | last = Krätschmer
  | first = Ernst-Günther
  | year = 1999
  | title = Die Ritterkreuzträger der Waffen-SS
  | trans_title = The Knight's Cross Bearers of the Waffen-SS
  | language = German
  | location = Coburg, Germany
  | publisher = [[Nation und Europa|Nation Europa Verlag GmbH]]
  | isbn = 3-920677-43-9
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Krüger
  | first1 = Arnd
  | last2 = Scharenberg
  | first2 = Swantje
  | year = 2014
  | title = Zeiten für Helden – Zeiten für Berühmtheiten im Sport
  | trans_title = Times for Heroes – Times for Celebrities in Sports
  | language = German
  | location = Münster, Germany
  | publisher = LIT Verlag
  | isbn = 978-3-643-12498-2
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Longerich
  | first = Peter
  | authorlink = Peter Longerich
  | title = Holocaust: The Nazi Persecution and Murder of the Jews
  | year = 2010
  | publisher = Oxford University Press
  | location = Oxford; New York
  | isbn = 978-0-19-280436-5
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Miller
  | first = Michael
  | year = 2006
  | title = Leaders of the SS and German Police, Vol. 1
  | publisher = R. James Bender
  | location = San Jose, CA
  | isbn = 978-93-297-0037-2
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = O'Donnell
  | first = James P.
  | authorlink = James P. O'Donnell
  | year = 1978
  | title = [[The Bunker (book)|The Bunker: The History of the Reich Chancellery Group]]
  | publisher = Houghton Mifflin
  | location = Boston
  | isbn = 978-0-395-25719-7
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Patzwall
  | first1 = Klaus D.
  | last2 = Scherzer
  | first2 = Veit
  | year = 2001
  | language = German
  | title = Das Deutsche Kreuz 1941–1945 Geschichte und Inhaber Band II
  | trans_title = The German Cross 1941 – 1945 History and Recipients Volume 2
  | publisher = Patzwall
  | location = Norderstedt, Germany
  | isbn = 3-931533-45-X
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Pieper
  | first = Henning
  | year = 2015
  | title = Fegelein's Horsemen and Genocidal Warfare: The SS Cavalry Brigade in the Soviet Union
  | publisher = Palgrave Macmillan
  | location = Houndmills, Basingstoke, Hampshire
  | isbn = 978-1-137-45631-1
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Scherzer
  | first = Veit
  | year = 2007
  | language = German
  | title = Ritterkreuzträger 1939–1945 Die Inhaber des Ritterkreuzes des Eisernen Kreuzes 1939 von Heer, Luftwaffe, Kriegsmarine, Waffen-SS, Volkssturm sowie mit Deutschland verbündeter Streitkräfte nach den Unterlagen des Bundesarchives
  | trans_title = The Knight's Cross Bearers 1939–1945 The Holders of the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross 1939 by Army, Air Force, Navy, Waffen-SS, Volkssturm and Allied Forces with Germany According to the Documents of the Federal Archives
  | location = Jena, Germany
  | publisher = Scherzers Miltaer-Verlag
  | isbn = 978-3-938845-17-2
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Shirer
  | first = William L.
  | authorlink = William L. Shirer
  | title = [[The Rise and Fall of the Third Reich]]
  | publisher = Simon &amp; Schuster
  | location = New York
  | year = 1960
  | isbn = 978-0-671-62420-0
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite journal
  | last = Simon
  | first = Ralf
  | title = Interview With Hitler's Bodyguard: The Secrets of Hitler's Last Living Aide
  | journal = [[Der Spiegel]]
  | publisher = SPIEGEL-Verlag
  | date = 30 July 2007
  | url = http://www.spiegel.de/international/germany/interview-with-hitler-s-bodyguard-the-secrets-of-hitler-s-last-living-aide-a-497306.html
  | accessdate = 10 September 2012
  | location = Hamburg, Germany
  | issn = 0038-7452
  | ref = harv
}}
* {{Cite book
  | last = Stockert
  | first = Peter
  | year = 2012
  | origyear = 1997
  | title = Die Eichenlaubträger 1939–1945 Band 2
  | trans_title = The Oak Leaves Bearers 1939–1945 Volume 2
  | edition = 4th
  | language = German
  | location = Bad Friedrichshall, Germany
  | publisher = Friedrichshaller Rundblick
  | isbn = 978-3-9802222-9-7
  | ref = harv
}}
* {{cite book
  | last = Thomas
  | first = Franz
  | year = 1997
  | language = German
  | title = Die Eichenlaubträger 1939–1945 Band 1: A–K
  | trans_title = The Oak Leaves Bearers 1939–1945 Volume 1: A–K
  | location = Osnabrück, Germany
  | publisher = Biblio-Verlag
  | isbn = 978-3-7648-2299-6
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Vinogradov
  | first = V. K.
  | title = Hitler's Death: Russia's Last Great Secret from the Files of the KGB
  | location = London, UK
  | publisher = Chaucer Press
  | year = 2005
  | isbn = 978-1-904449-13-3
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{Cite book
  | last = Von Seemen
  | first = Gerhard
  | year = 1976
  | title = Die Ritterkreuzträger 1939–1945 : die Ritterkreuzträger sämtlicher Wehrmachtteile, Brillanten-, Schwerter- und Eichenlaubträger in der Reihenfolge der Verleihung : Anhang mit Verleihungsbestimmungen und weiteren Angaben
  | trans_title = The Knight's Cross Bearers 1939–1945 : The Knight's Cross Bearers of All the Armed Services, Diamonds, Swords and Oak Leaves Bearers in the Order of Presentation: Appendix with Further Information and Presentation Requirements
  | language = German
  | location = Friedberg, Germany
  | publisher = Podzun-Verlag
  | isbn = 978-3-7909-0051-4
  | ref = harv
}}
{{refend}}

== Further reading ==
{{Refbegin}}
* {{cite book
  | last = Jahns
  | first = Joachim
  | year = 2009
  | language = German
  | title = Der Warschauer Ghettokönig
  | trans_title = The Warsaw Ghetto King
  | publisher = Dingsda-Verlag
  | location = Leipzig
  | isbn = 978-3-928498-99-9
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Schaulen
  | first = Fritjof
  | year = 2003
  | language = German
  | title = Eichenlaubträger 1940–1945 Zeitgeschichte in Farbe I Abraham&amp;nbsp;– Huppertz
  | trans_title = Oak Leaves Bearers 1940–1945 Contemporary History in Color I Abraham – Huppertz
  | publisher = Pour le Mérite
  | location = Selent
  | isbn = 978-3-932381-20-1
  }}
{{Refend}}

== External links ==
* {{DNB portal|122319524|TYP=}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-mil}}
{{succession box
| before = none
| after  = SS-Brigadeführer [[Wilhelm Bittrich]]&lt;!-- Bittrich was Brigadeführer on 2 March 1942 --&gt;
| title  = Commander of [[SS Cavalry Brigade|SS-Kavallerie-Brigade]]
| years  = 5 August 1941&amp;nbsp;– 2 March 1942
}}
{{succession box
| before = SS-Standartenführer der Reserve [[Gustav Lombard]] &lt;!-- Lombard was Standartenführer der Reserve on 20 April 1943 --&gt;
| after  = SS-Standartenführer [[Bruno Streckenbach]] &lt;!-- Streckenbach was Standartenführer on 30 September 1943 --&gt;
| title  = Commander of [[8th SS Cavalry Division Florian Geyer|8. SS-Kavallerie-Division ''Florian Geyer'']]
| years  = 20 April 1943&amp;nbsp;– 30 September 1943
}}
{{succession box
| before = SS-Standartenführer [[Bruno Streckenbach]]
| after  = SS-Standartenführer [[Bruno Streckenbach]]
| title  = Commander of [[8th SS Cavalry Division Florian Geyer|8. SS-Kavallerie-Division ''Florian Geyer'']]
| years  = 22 October 1943&amp;nbsp;– 1 January 1944
}}
{{s-end}}

{{Final occupants of the Führerbunker}}
{{KCwithOLandSW}}
{{KCwithOL}}
{{Knight's Cross recipients of the 8th SS CD}}

{{People killed or wounded in the 20 July plot}}
{{Authority control}}
{{Subject bar
| portal1=Biography
| portal2=Fascism
| portal3=Military of Germany
| portal4=World War II
| commons=y
}}
{{Good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Fegelein, Hermann}}
[[Category:1906 births]]
[[Category:1945 deaths]]
[[Category:Hitler family]]
[[Category:Nazi war crimes]]
[[Category:People from Ansbach]]
[[Category:SS-Gruppenführer]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Close Combat Clasp]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Gold German Cross]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves and Swords]]
[[Category:People condemned by Nazi courts]]
[[Category:People from Bavaria executed by Nazi Germany]]
[[Category:People executed by Germany by firearm]]
[[Category:People from the Kingdom of Bavaria]]
[[Category:Heinrich Himmler]]
[[Category:Executed German people]]
[[Category:Nazis executed by Nazi Germany]]
[[Category:Waffen-SS personnel]]
[[Category:20th-century Freikorps personnel]]</text>
      <sha1>barnb2pajwqg4vb8eayxg4ljrz5nnas</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
