<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Hyacinth Graf Strachwitz</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1973617</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749248047</id>
      <parentid>747925243</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-13T08:12:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[User:AnomieBOT/docs/TemplateSubster|Substing templates]]: {{ill}}. See [[User:AnomieBOT/docs/TemplateSubster]] for info.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="90281">{{good article}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2016}}
{{Use British English|date=November 2014}}

{{Infobox military person
|name          = Hyacinth Graf Strachwitz von Groß-Zauche und Camminetz
|birth_date    = {{birth date|1893|7|30|df=y}}
|death_date    = {{death date and age|1968|4|25|1893|7|30|df=y}}
|image         = Hyazinth Graf Strachwitz.jpg
|alt           = A smiling man in a black uniform holding a sheaf of documents
|caption       = Strachwitz as ''Oberst'' and commander of ''Panzer-Regiment'' &quot;Großdeutschland&quot;, June 1943
|birth_place   = [[Kamień Śląski|Groß Stein]], [[Province of Silesia]], [[Kingdom of Prussia]], [[German Empire]] &lt;small&gt;(now [[Kamień Śląski]], [[Opole Voivodeship]], [[Poland]])&lt;/small&gt;
|death_place   = [[Trostberg]], [[Bavaria]], [[West Germany]]&lt;ref&gt;Von Ehrenkrook 2000, p. 497.&lt;/ref&gt;
|placeofburial = Cemetery in [[Grabenstätt]]
|nickname      = ''Conté'', ''Der Panzergraf''
|allegiance    = {{flag|German Empire}} (to 1918)&lt;br /&gt;{{flag|Weimar Republic}} (to 1933)&lt;br /&gt;{{flag|Nazi Germany}}
|branch        = [[German Army (German Empire)|Deutsches Heer]]&lt;br /&gt;[[German Army (Wehrmacht)|Wehrmacht Heer]]
|serviceyears  = 1912{{ndash}}45
|rank          = ''[[Generalleutnant]]'' of the [[Military reserve force|Reserves]]
|servicenumber = {{ubl|[[NSDAP]] 1,405,562|[[SS]] 82,857}}
|commands      = [[Grossdeutschland Division|''Panzer-Regiment'' &quot;Großdeutschland&quot;]]
|unit          = {{ubl|[[Guards Cavalry Division (German Empire)|Guards Cavalry Division]]|''[[Freikorps]]'' &quot;[[Bernhard von Hülsen|von Hülsen]]&quot;|[[1st Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|1. Panzer Division]]}}
|battles       = {{hidden
|''See battles''
|[[World War I]]
{{hr}}
[[Silesian Uprisings]]
* [[Battle of Annaberg]]
{{hr}}
[[World War II]]
* [[Invasion of Poland]]
* [[Battle of France]]
:*[[Battle of Sedan (1940)|Battle of Sedan]]
:*[[Battle of Dunkirk]]
* [[Invasion of Yugoslavia]]
* [[Operation Barbarossa]]
:*[[Battle of Kiev (1941)|Battle of Kiev]]
* [[Battle of Stalingrad]]
* [[Third Battle of Kharkov]]
* [[Battle of Kursk]]
* [[Battle of Narva (1944)|Battle of Narva]]
:*[[Narva Offensive (18–24 March 1944)]]
:*[[Battle for Narva Bridgehead]]
* [[Soviet re-occupation of Latvia in 1944]]
:*[[Šiauliai Offensive]]
:*[[Operation Doppelkopf]]
|-
|headerstyle=background:#dbdbdb
|style=text-align:center;
}}
|awards        = ''[[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross|Ritterkreuz des Eisernen Kreuzes mit Eichenlaub, Schwertern und Brillanten]]''
|laterwork     = Land owner and farmer, and [[military advisor]]}}

'''Hyacinth Graf Strachwitz von Groß-Zauche und Camminetz'''{{refn|According to Röll his first name is spelled &quot;Hya&lt;u&gt;c&lt;/u&gt;inth&quot;. Groß-Zauche, in German, is spelled with a &quot;sharp S&quot;; see [[ß]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p13&quot;&gt;Röll 2011, p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt; Later, the spelling of his first name was changed to &quot;Hya&lt;u&gt;z&lt;/u&gt;inth&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Bagdonas 2013, p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt; {{German title|Graf}}|group=&quot;Note&quot;}} (30 July 1893 – 25 April 1968) was a German [[German Army (Wehrmacht)|Army]] officer of aristocratic descent. Strachwitz saw action in [[World War I]], but rose to fame for his command of armoured forces in [[World War II]]. For these services he was awarded the [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves, Swords and Diamonds]] ({{Lang-de|Ritterkreuz des Eisernen Kreuzes mit Eichenlaub, Schwertern und Brillanten|link=no}}), an award created to recognise extreme battlefield bravery or outstanding military leadership. At the time of its presentation to Strachwitz it was Germany's highest military decoration.{{refn|In 1944, the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves, Swords and Diamonds was second only to the [[Grand Cross of the Iron Cross]] ({{lang|de|''Großkreuz des Eisernen Kreuzes''}}), which was awarded only to senior commanders for winning a major battle or campaign, in the military order of the Third Reich. The Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves, Swords and Diamonds as the highest military order was surpassed on 29 December 1944 by the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Golden Oak Leaves, Swords and Diamonds ({{lang|de|''Ritterkreuz des Eisernen Kreuzes mit Goldenem Eichenlaub, Schwertern und Brillanten''}}).&lt;ref&gt;Williamson and Bujeiro 2004, pp. 3, 7.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=&quot;Note&quot;}}

Strachwitz was born in 1893 on his family estate in [[Silesia]]. He was educated at various [[Prussia]]n military academies and served with distinction as a [[cavalry]] officer in the opening weeks of World War I. He was captured by the French in October 1914. He was nearly shot as a spy after he was caught wearing civilian clothes, but was later sentenced to [[forced labor|forced labour]]. He attempted to escape several times, but was unsuccessful, and returned to Germany after the war ended in late 1918. In the aftermath of World War I, Strachwitz fought with the [[Freikorps]] in the [[Spartacist uprising]] of the [[German Revolution of 1918–1919|German Revolution]] in Berlin, and in the [[Silesian Uprisings]] against the [[Poles]] and Polish [[Silesians]] of [[Upper Silesia]]. In the mid-1920s he took over the family estate, Groß Stein, from his father and became a member of the [[Nazi Party]]  and the ''[[Allgemeine SS]]''. He remained an officer in the [[military reserve force|reserves]], and participated in various military exercises during the 1930s.

At the outbreak of World War II, Strachwitz was appointed as an [[Military logistics|ordnance]] officer. He participated in the [[Invasion of Poland]] and later in the [[Battle of France]]. Transferred to the [[16th Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|16th Panzer Division]] he fought in the [[Invasion of Yugoslavia]] and [[Operation Barbarossa]], the German invasion of the Soviet Union. He fought with distinction on the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]] and received awards such as the [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves]], for his actions during the tank battle of [[Battle of Kalach|Kalach]]. He was given command of [[Panzer-Grenadier-Division Großdeutschland|''Panzer-Regiment'' &quot;Großdeutschland&quot;]] and received the Swords to his Knight's Cross, for his contribution to the counterattack at [[Third Battle of Kharkov|Kharkov]]. He then fought in the [[Battle of Kursk]] and the German retreat to the [[Battle of the Dnieper|Dnieper]]. While commanding a battle group on the [[Battle of Narva (1944)|Narva front]] in early 1944 he was awarded the Diamonds to his Knight's Cross on 15 April. He was wounded 12 times during the war, and was also injured in an automobile accident.

In 1945, he surrendered to US forces and was taken into custody. By the time of his release in June 1947, his youngest son had been killed in action, his wife had been killed in a road accident, and his Silesian estate had been confiscated by Poland. He remained in West Germany, married again and briefly worked for the [[Syrian Armed Forces]] as a military consultant. He lived on an estate in Bavaria from 1951 until his death from [[lung cancer]] on 25 April 1968. He was buried with [[Military funeral|military honours]] in Grabenstätt, Bavaria.

== Childhood, education and early career ==
Strachwitz was born on 30 July 1893 in Groß Stein, in the district of [[Groß Strehlitz]] in [[Province of Silesia|Silesia]], a [[Provinces of Prussia|province]] in the [[Kingdom of Prussia]]. Today it is [[Kamień Śląski]], in [[Gmina Gogolin|Gogolin]], [[Opole Voivodeship]], Poland. Strachwitz was the second child of Hyacinth Graf Strachwitz (1864–1942) and his wife Aloysia (1872–1940),{{refn|Her full name was Maria Aloysia Hedwig Friederike Therese Oktavie, Gräfin von Matuschka, Freiin von Toppolczan und Spaetgen.&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, p. 16.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=&quot;Note&quot;}} née Gräfin von Matuschka Freiin von Toppolczan und Spaetgen.&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, pp. 13, 16.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;{{German title |Freiin}}&lt;/ref&gt; He had an older sister, Aloysia (1892–1972), followed by his younger brother Johannes (1896–1917) nicknamed &quot;Ceslaus&quot;, his sister Elisabeth (1897–1992), his brother Manfred (1899–1972), his brother Mariano (1902–1922), and his youngest sister Margarethe (1905–1989).&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p13&quot; /&gt; His family were members of the old Silesian nobility (''[[Uradel]]''), and held large estates in [[Upper Silesia]], including the family ''[[Palace|Schloss]]'' (Palace) at Groß Stein. As the first-born son he was the heir to the title Graf (Count) Strachwitz, and following family tradition he was christened Hyacinth, after the 12th century [[Hyacinth of Poland|saint]]. Some clothing belonging to the saint were in the family's possession until 1945.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p13&quot; /&gt;

[[File:Strachwitz-Wappen2.png|thumb|left|alt=Two knight's helmets over of an escutcheon in the shape of a heart with boar head in the upper left and lower right corner, and shells in the upper right and lower left.|Graf Strachwitz [[Coat of Arms]]]]

Strachwitz attended the ''[[Volksschule]]'' (primary school) and the ''[[Gymnasium (school)|Gymnasium]]'' (advanced secondary school) in [[Opole|Oppeln]]—present-day Opole. He received further schooling and paramilitary training at the ''Königlich Preußischen Kadettenkorps'' (Royal Prussian cadet corps) in [[Legnickie Pole|Wahlstatt]]—present-day Legnickie Pole—before he transferred to the ''Hauptkadettenanstalt'' (Main [[Military Academy]]) in [[Berlin-Lichterfelde]]. Among his closest friends at the cadet academy were [[Manfred von Richthofen]], the World War I [[flying ace]] and a fellow Silesian, and Hans von Aulock, brother of the World War II colonel [[Andreas von Aulock]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p13&quot; /&gt; In August 1912, Cadet Strachwitz was admitted to the élite ''[[Gardes du Corps (Prussia)|Gardes du Corps]]'' (Life Guards) cavalry regiment in Potsdam as a ''[[Fähnrich]]'' (Ensign). The Life Guards had been established by Prussian King [[Frederick the Great]] in 1740, and were considered the most prestigious posting in the [[German Army (German Empire)|Imperial German Army]]. Their patron was Emperor [[Wilhelm II]], who nominally commanded them. Strachwitz was sent to an officer training course at the ''[[Kriegsschule (Wehrmacht)|Kriegsschule]]'' (War School) in [[Hanover]] in late 1912, where he excelled at various sports.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p13&quot; /&gt; Strachwitz was commissioned as ''[[Leutnant]]'' (Second Lieutenant) on 17 February 1914.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p188&quot;&gt;Röll 2011, p. 188.&lt;/ref&gt; At this early stage of his career in Potsdam, Strachwitz began insisting on being addressed as &quot;''Herr Graf''&quot; rather than &quot;''Herr Leutnant''&quot;, even from higher-ranking officers, which he maintained throughout his career. According to Roll, he always felt prouder of his aristocratic descent than of his military rank.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p19&quot;&gt;Röll 2011, p. 19.&lt;/ref&gt; His close friends called him ''Conté'' (Count).&lt;ref&gt;Berger 1999, p. 348.&lt;/ref&gt;

Upon his return to the Prussian Main Military Academy from Hanover, Strachwitz was appointed as the sports officer for the Life Guards. He introduced daily [[gymnastics]] and weekly [[endurance running]]. The Life Guards sports team was selected to participate in the planned [[1916 Summer Olympics|1916 Olympic Games]], and this further encouraged his ambition. He participated [[Equestrianism|equestrian]], [[fencing]] and [[track and field]] athletics, which became his prime focus. Strachwitz continued to excel as a sportsman, and with his friend [[Prince Friedrich Karl of Prussia (1893–1917)|Prince Friedrich Karl of Prussia]], according to Roll Strachwitz was among the best athletes to train for the Olympic Games.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p13&quot; /&gt;

== World War I ==
The outbreak of [[World War I]], which was triggered by the [[Assassination of Archduke Franz Ferdinand of Austria|assassination]] of [[Archduke Franz Ferdinand of Austria]] and his wife [[Sophie, Duchess of Hohenberg]] on 28 June 1914 in [[Sarajevo]], ended Strachwitz's Olympic ambitions. The [[Russian Empire]] ordered a partial [[mobilization]] one day later and the [[German Empire]] mobilized on 30 July 1914. Strachwitz received his mobilization order while on vacation in Silesia, and returned to his unit in Berlin immediately. His regiment was subordinated to the [[Guards Cavalry Division (German Empire)|Guards Cavalry Division]] and scheduled for deployment in the west.&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt;

Shortly after the mobilization, the Life Guards arrived at their assigned position near the Belgian border. Strachwitz and his platoon volunteered for a mounted, long-distance [[reconnaissance]] patrol, which would penetrate far behind Belgian lines. His orders were to gather intelligence on rail and communications connections and potentially disturb them, as well as report on the war preparations being made by their opponents. If the situation allowed, he was to destroy railway and telephone connections and to [[Derailment|derail trains]], causing as much havoc as possible.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p19&quot; /&gt; His patrol ran into many obstacles and they were constantly on the verge of being detected by either British or French forces. Their objective was the Paris–[[Limoges]]–[[Bordeaux]] train track. Strachwitz dispatched a messenger, who broke through to the German lines and delivered the intelligence they had gathered. The patrol blew up the [[Signalling control|signal box]] at the [[Fontainebleau]] railway station,&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, pp. 20–22.&lt;/ref&gt; and tried to force their way through to presumed German troops at the [[Marne (river)|Marne]] near [[Châlons-en-Champagne|Châlons]]. However, the French forces were too strong and they were unable to get through. After six weeks behind the lines their rations were depleted and they had to resort to stealing or begging. Strachwitz then decided to head for Switzerland, hoping that the French–Swiss border was not as heavily protected.&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, pp. 23–24.&lt;/ref&gt; After a brief skirmish with French forces, one of Strachwitz's men was seriously wounded, which forced them to seek medical attention. During many weeks of outdoor living their uniforms had deteriorated, so Strachwitz took that opportunity to buy new clothes for his men. Their progress was slowed by the wounded man, and the group was caught in civilian clothes by French forces.&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, pp. 24–25.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Fort Barraux L1040224.jpg|thumb|right|Fort Barraux, 2011]]

Strachwitz and his men were questioned by a French captain and accused of being [[espionage|spies]] and [[saboteur]]s. They were taken to the prison at Châlons the next day where they were separated. Strachwitz, as an officer, was placed in [[solitary confinement]]. Early in the morning they were all lined up for the [[firing squad]], but a French captain arrived just in time to stop the execution. Strachwitz and his men were then tried before a French [[military court]] on 14 October 1914. The court sentenced them all to five years of [[forced labor|forced labour]] on the [[Devil's Island|prison island of Cayenne]]. At the same time they were deprived of rank, thus losing the status of prisoners of war. Strachwitz was then taken to the prisons at [[Lyon]] and [[Montpellier]], and then to the [[Île de Ré]], from where the prison ship would depart for Cayenne. It is unclear what circumstances prevented his departure, but he was imprisoned at [[Riom]] and [[Avignon]] instead. At Avignon prison he was physically and mentally tortured by both the guards and the other prisoners. This included being chained naked to a wall, deprivation of food and severe beatings. After one year at Avignon he was given a German uniform and taken to the prisoner of war camp at [[Barraux|Fort Barraux]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll pp26–27&quot;&gt;Röll 2011, pp. 26–27.&lt;/ref&gt;

At Barraux he learned that the fighting in the west had turned into a [[Attrition warfare|war of attrition]] and that only on the [[Eastern Front (World War I)|Eastern Front]] were German troops still reporting successes. His health improved rapidly and Strachwitz started making escape plans. With other German soldiers he started digging an escape tunnel, which was detected. Strachwitz was again put in solitary confinement. As a deterrence against German [[U-boat]] attacks, German prisoners of war were sometimes carried in the cargo holds of French merchant ships. Now classified as &quot;determined to escape&quot;, Strachwitz was put in the cargo hold of a ship which commuted between [[Marseilles]] or [[Toulon]] and [[Thessaloniki]], Greece. Malnourished after four trips without food, he was returned to Barraux. During further solitary confinement he recovered again, and made further escape plans. With a fellow soldier, he climbed over the prison walls, planning to head for neutral Switzerland. However, Strachwitz injured his foot when he fell into [[barbed wire]], and the injury caused [[blood poisoning]]. While searching for help, they were picked up by the French police and turned over to a military court. He was then sent to a war prison for officers at [[Carcassonne]] where his request for medical attention was ignored. The injury was severe and he became delirious. An inspection by the Swiss medical commission from the [[International Red Cross]] resulted in him being transferred to a hospital in [[Geneva]], Switzerland, where he awoke after days of unconsciousness.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll pp26–27&quot; /&gt;

Strachwitz recovered quickly in Geneva. During his convalescence he was visited by members of various European royal houses and clergymen who stopped by to pay their respects. The doctors told Strachwitz that the French government had requested his [[extradition]] back to France once he had fully recovered, to serve his full term of five years of forced labour. Strachwitz then moved into a villa in [[Luzern]] where he was visited by his mother and sister. He had a great fear of being returned to France, and together they came up with a plan to avoid his extradition. He would &quot;sit out the war&quot; in a [[mental asylum]] in Switzerland. The plan worked, although Strachwitz's mental health genuinely deteriorated in the process. The war ended and Strachwitz was released to return to Germany.&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, p. 30.&lt;/ref&gt; For his service during the war while imprisoned by the French he was awarded the [[Iron Cross]] ({{lang|de|''Eisernes Kreuz''}}) Second and First Class.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p31&quot;&gt;Röll 2011, p. 31.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Interwar period ==

=== In the Weimar Republic ===

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 119-1577, Revolution in Berlin.jpg|thumb|right|Troops loyal to the government at the [[Berlin Ostbahnhof|Silesian Station]], 1919]]

After the [[Armistice with Germany|Armistice]] in November 1918, Strachwitz was repatriated and returned to a Germany in civil turmoil. He travelled to Berlin via [[Konstanz]], at the Swiss–German border, and [[Munich]]. On his journey he saw many former German soldiers whose military discipline had broken down. Unable to tolerate this situation and fearing a [[Communist]] revolution, he travelled on to Berlin, arriving at the [[Berlin Anhalter Bahnhof]] where he was met by a friend. Strachwitz had called ahead asking his friend to bring him his Gardes du Corps uniform, which he put on immediately. Berlin was in a state of revolution. The newly established provisional government under the leadership of [[Chancellor of Germany|Chancellor]] [[Friedrich Ebert]] was threatened by the [[Spartacist uprising]] of the [[German Revolution of 1918–1919|German Revolution]], whose ambition was a Soviet-style [[proletarian]] dictatorship. Ebert ordered the former soldiers, organized in ''[[Freikorps]]'' ([[paramilitary]] organizations) among them Strachwitz, to attack the workers and put down the uprising.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p31&quot; /&gt;

In early 1919, following the events in Berlin, Strachwitz returned to his home estate, where he found his family palace had been taken over by French officers. Upper Silesia was occupied by British, French and Italian forces, and being governed by an [[Military Inter-Allied Commission of Control|Inter-Allied Committee]] headed by a French general, Henri Le Rond. The [[Versailles Treaty]] at the end of World War I had shifted formerly German territory into neighbouring countries, some of which had not existed at the beginning of the war. In the case of the new [[Second Polish Republic]], the Treaty detached some {{Convert|54,000|km2|sqmi}} of territory, which had formerly been part of the German Empire, to recreate the country of Poland, which had disappeared as a result of the [[Third Partition of Poland]] in 1795.&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, pp. 31–32.&lt;/ref&gt; His father urged him to prepare and educate himself in order to take over the family estate and business. He was put under the guidance of his father's ''Oberinspektor'' (Chief Inspector). At the same time, Strachwitz, fearing that Silesia was being &quot;handed over to the Poles&quot;, as he viewed the actions of the Inter-Allied Committee, joined the ''Oberschlesischer [[Selbstschutz]]'' (Upper Silesian Self Defence). Strachwitz collected weapons and recruited volunteers, which was prohibited. He was caught four times and put in prison in Oppeln by the French. His father was also imprisoned for his opposition to the Inter-Allied Committee. Roll states that Strachwitz's distrust for the French, rooted in his experiences as a prisoner of war during World War I, was immense. He believed that only the Italians had played an honest and neutral role in the occupation of Upper Silesia. On 25 July 1919, he married Alexandrine Freiin Saurma-Jeltsch, nicknamed &quot;Alda&quot;, and their first child, a son, was born on 4 May 1920.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p32&quot;&gt;Röll 2011, p. 32.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Kamień Śląski pałac.jpg|thumb|left|The ancestral home of the Strachwitz family, the palace in Kamień Śląski in 2006&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, p. 48.&lt;/ref&gt;]]

In 1921, during the [[Silesian Uprisings]], when Poland tried to separate Upper Silesia from the [[Weimar Republic]], Strachwitz served under the Generals [[Bernhard von Hülsen]] and [[Karl Höfer]]. At the peak of the conflict when the Poles dug in on the Annaberg, a hill near the village of [[Góra Świętej Anny|Annaberg]]—present-day Góra Świętej Anny. The German ''Freikorps'' launched the assault in what would become the [[Battle of Annaberg]], which was fought between 21 May and 26 May 1921. Strachwitz and his two battalions outflanked the Polish positions and overran part of them in [[hand-to-hand combat]] around midnight on 21 May. Strachwitz was the first German to reach the summit. They captured six field guns, numerous machine guns, rifles and ammunition.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p43&quot;&gt;Röll 2011, p. 43.&lt;/ref&gt; On 4 June, the ''Freikorps'' attacked Polish positions at Kandrzin—present-day [[Kędzierzyn-Koźle|Kędzierzyn]]—and Slawentzitz—present-day [[Sławięcice]]. In this battle Strachwitz and his men captured a Polish artillery battery which they turned against the Poles.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p43&quot; /&gt; For these services he received the ''Schlesischer Adler'' ([[Silesian Eagle]]) medal, Second and First Class with Oak Leaves and Swords. His younger brother Manfred also fought for Silesia, and was severely wounded leading his men at [[Krizova]]. Two months later his wife gave birth to their second child, a daughter named Alexandrine Aloysia Maria Elisabeth Therese born on 30 July 1921, nicknamed &quot;Lisalex&quot;. The [[Ministry of the Reichswehr]] informed him in 1921 that he had been promoted to ''[[Oberleutnant]]'' (First Lieutenant), the promotion backdated to 1916. The Strachwitz family grew further when on 22 March 1925 a third child, a son named Hubertus Arthur, nicknamed &quot;Harti&quot;, was born on their manor at Schedlitz, later renamed Alt Siedel—present-day [[Siedlec, Strzelce County|Siedlec]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p44&quot;&gt;Röll 2011, p. 44.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1925, Strachwitz and his family moved from their palace in Groß Stein to their manor in Alt Siedel, because of personal differences with his father, who remained in Groß Stein. Between 1924 and 1933 Strachwitz founded two [[dairy]] [[cooperative]]s which many local farmers joined. In parallel he studied a few semesters of forestry. He used his knowledge to influence the Silesian forest owners to sell their wood to the [[paper mill]]s. He continued to use his influence in Upper Silesia to modernize forestry and farming. His ambitions were aided by his presidency of the ''Forstausschuss'' (Forestry Committee) of Upper Silesia and his membership in the ''Landwirtschaftskammer'' (Chamber of Agriculture).&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p44&quot; /&gt; Strachwitz completely took over his father's estate in 1929, first as the General Manager and then as owner, with full responsibility. This made Strachwitz one of the most wealthy land and forest owners in Silesia. Along with the palace in Groß Stein he owned a [[lime kiln]] and [[quarry]] in Klein Stein—present-day [[Kamionek, Opole Voivodeship|Kamionek]]—and Groß Stein, a [[distillery]] in Groß Stein and Alt Siedel.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p49&quot;&gt;Röll 2011, p. 49.&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|Annual production at Groß Stein was {{Convert|92894|l|USgal}} and {{Convert|116386|l|USgal}} at Alt Siedel. Of his {{Convert|4109|ha|acre|adj=on}} property, {{Convert|1182.6|ha|acre}} were farmland, {{Convert|69.9|ha|acre}} meadows, {{Convert|26.3|ha|acre}} pastures, {{Convert|6.1|ha|acre}} water, {{Convert|2737.3|ha|acre}} forest, {{Convert|10|ha|acre}} parks, and {{Convert|6.6|ha|acre}} gardens, {{Convert|35|ha|acre}} wasteland and {{Convert|19.4|ha|acre}} buildings and farms, as well as 16 roads. His agricultural production included forest seeds, [[rye]], [[barley]], [[corn]], [[potato]]es, [[lupins]] and [[malt]]. In [[animal husbandry]] he had [[feral]], [[cattle]], [[horse breeding]], ''Deutsches Edelschwein'' (German pig), [[merino]]s and fish.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p49&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Strachwitz also owned the manor in Alt Siedel with a property size of {{Convert|583|ha|acre}}. {{Convert|278|ha|acre}} were farmland, {{Convert|13.5|ha|acre}} pastures, {{Convert|3.5|ha|acre}} gardens, {{Convert|279|ha|acre}} forest, {{Convert|1.5|ha|acre}} water, and {{Convert|5|ha|acre}} were buildings. The manor in Einsiedel, in [[Bruntál|Freudenthal]]—present-day Bruntál in the Czech Republic—Upper Silesia, with its [[oak]] forests and farmland, belonged to him as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p49&quot; /&gt;|group=&quot;Note&quot;}}

=== National Socialism ===

Strachwitz applied for membership in the Nazi Party (NSDAP—National Socialist German Workers' Party) with the ''Reichsleitung'' (Reich Leadership) of the NSDAP in Munich in 1931.{{refn|Röll states that Strachwitz believed that he could better politically represent his Upper Silesian agricultural and forestry interests by joining the NSDAP.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p49&quot; /&gt;|group=&quot;Note&quot;}} He was accepted and in 1932 joined the ''Ortsgruppe'' (Local Group) of the NSDAP in [[Breslau]] with a membership number 1,405,562. On 17 April 1933 he became a member of the [[Allgemeine SS]] with the SS membership number 82,857. A series of quick promotions within the SS followed. He progressed to SS-''[[Obersturmführer]]'' by the end of 1934 and SS-''[[Sturmbannführer]]'' in 1936. In parallel to his SS-career, his military rank in the [[military reserve force]] also advanced. He attained the rank of ''[[Hauptmann]]'' (Captain) of the Reserves in 1934 and a year later became a ''[[Rittmeister]]'' (Cavalry Captain) of the Reserves.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p49&quot; /&gt;

On 30 January 1933, the Nazi Party, under the leadership of [[Adolf Hitler]], came to power and began to rearm Germany. The ''[[German Army (Wehrmacht)|Heer]]'' (Germany Army) was increased and modernized with a strong focus on the [[Panzer]] (tank) force. Personnel were recruited from the cavalry. In October 1935 ''Panzer-Regiment'' 2 was created and was subordinated to the [[1st Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|1st Panzer Division]], at the time under command of General [[Maximilian von Weichs]]. The soldiers of the I. ''Abteilung'' (1st Battalion) came from Saxony and Thuringia, the II. ''Abteilung'' (2nd Battalion) was made up from soldiers from Silesia. Strachwitz, who had served as an officer of the reserves in ''Reiter-Regiment'' 7 (7th Cavalry Regiment) in Breslau, had asked to be transferred to the Panzer force and, in May 1936, participated in his first [[Maneuver warfare|manoeuvre]] on the training ground at [[Ohrdruf]], followed by an exercise of live firing on the gunnery training ground at [[Putlos]]—today in the administrative district of [[Oldenburg-Land]]—near the [[Baltic Sea]]. A year later, from July to August 1937, he participated in a second reserve training exercise on the Silesian training grounds at [[Świętoszów|Neuhammer]]—present-day Świętoszów.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p49&quot; /&gt;

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 136-B3542, Wehrmachtsmanöver, Hitler, Mussolini, Hossbach.jpg|thumb|right|Mussolini, Hitler and [[Friedrich Hoßbach]] at the Wehrmacht manoeuvre, September 1937]]

Following a brief vacation in Silesia, Strachwitz returned to the 1st Panzer Division at the training grounds at [[Königsbrück]], near [[Dresden]]. During the preparations for the fall manoeuvres the ''[[General of the Cavalry (Germany)|General der Kavallerie]]'' (General of the Cavalry) von Weichs was dismissed. On 18 September ''Panzer-Regiment'' 2 was relocated from Königsbrück to [[Fürstenberg/Havel|Fürstenberg]] and then to [[Neustrelitz]]. Here, under the watchful eyes of Hitler and [[Benito Mussolini]] from the [[Schmooksberg]] near [[Laage]], the [[German 1st Panzer Brigade (1st Panzer Division)|1st]] and 3rd Panzer-Brigade, supported by ''[[Kampfgeschwader]]'' (Bomber Wings), practiced a large scale tank attack. The regiment returned to [[Eisenach]] on 30 September. Strachwitz returned to his estate but was called back shortly before the ''[[Anschluss|Anschluß]]'', the [[annexation]] of Austria by Germany, in March 1938.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p49&quot; /&gt;

Strachwitz and ''Panzer-Regiment'' 2 were placed on standby from 21 September to 2 October 1938 at the training grounds in [[Grafenwöhr]] during the [[Munich Agreement|Sudeten Crisis]], the German annexation of Czechoslovakia's northern and western border regions, known collectively as the [[Sudetenland]]. On 3 October, the regiment headed for [[Karlovy Vary|Karlsbad]], via [[Krajková|Gossengrün]] and [[Chodov (Sokolov District)|Chodau]], where they arrived on 5 October. The regiment was stationed at [[Žatec|Saatz]] and [[Kadaň|Kaaden]] in the Sudetenland until 15 October before it returned to Eisenach on 16 October 1938. He was again put on standby in March 1939, when the remaining Czech territories became the [[Protectorate of Bohemia and Moravia]], a German [[Satellite state|satellite]]. Following this, ''Panzer-Regiment'' 2 was sent to Berlin to participate in the [[Wehrmacht]] [[parade]] held to celebrate Hitler's 50th birthday on 20 April 1939. In July and August 1939, ''Panzer-Regiment'' 2 participated in the summer manoeuvres in [[Jüterbog]] and Putlos, followed by exercises at [[Dörnitz|Altengrabow]]. In preparation for the opening stages of World War II, the 1st Panzer Division left their training grounds in Thuringia and Hesse on 21 August 1939 and were transported by train to Silesia between [[Olesno|Rosenberg]]—present day Olesno—and Oppeln, where they arrived on the night of 24/25 August 1939. Strachwitz arrived at his regiment on 26 August where he, as the oldest Reserve officer, was assigned the task of organizing the regiment's [[military logistics|battlefield resupply]].&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, pp. 50, 187.&lt;/ref&gt;

== World War II ==
''Panzer-Regiment'' 2, under the command of ''[[Oberst]]'' (Colonel) Karl Keltsch, as part of the 1st Panzer Division, consisted of four light companies and two medium companies totalling 54 [[Panzer I]]s, 62 [[Panzer II]]s, 6 [[Panzer III]]s, 28 [[Panzer IV]]s and 6 command Panzers. The regiment located further east in a forest near [[Lasowice Małe, Opole Voivodeship|Klein-Lassowitz]] on the eve of 28 August 1939. ''Fall Weiß'' (Case White), [[Adolf Hitler's directives|Hitler's directive]] for the [[invasion of Poland]], became effective and forces of the ''Wehrmacht'' invaded Poland without a formal [[declaration of war]] on 1 September 1939 which marked the beginning of World War II in Europe. His regiment also crossed the border that day at [[Bodzanowice|Grunsruh]] and reached the river [[Liswarta|Lisswarthe]] at noon. They took [[Kłobuck|Klobutzko]] that evening without much resistance. On 2 September they proceeded on towards [[Biała Górna]], where they suffered their first casualties of the war. They then crossed the [[Warthe]] at [[Gidle]] and [[Pławno, Łódź Voivodeship|Plauno]] heading for [[Radomsko]]. Suffering further losses, they captured [[Piotrków Trybunalski|Petrikau]] on 5 September. The regiment reached [[Góra Kalwaria]] at the [[Vistula]] via [[Wolbórz]] and [[Zawada, Tomaszów Mazowiecki County|Zawada]] on 8 September. Here the regiment was allowed to rest until 10 September. On this day, Keltsch informed him that Strachwitz had been nominated for the [[Clasp to the Iron Cross]] ({{lang|de|''Spange zum Eisernen Kreuz''}}) 2nd Class for his organizational achievements, which he received on 5 October 1939.&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, pp. 51, 189.&lt;/ref&gt; Keltsch also announced that the ''Panzer-Brigade'' 1 (1st Panzer Brigade) had requested his transfer. ''[[Generalmajor]]'' (Major General) [[Ferdinand Schaal]], commander of ''Panzer-Brigade'' 1 at the time, welcomed him and made him responsible for organizing the replenishment of the entire brigade. On 3 October 1939, three days before the victory over Poland the 1st Panzer Division was ordered back to their home bases in Germany. They arrived on 12 October 1939. The equipment underwent intensive maintenance and Strachwitz went home to the manor at Alt Siedel for a lengthy vacation. The palace in Groß Stein had been made available to the Wehrmacht and was being used as a field hospital. When Strachwitz returned to his division in late 1939, the 1st Panzer Division had been relocated to the greater [[Dortmund]] area with the ''Stab'' (staff) located in [[Düsseldorf]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p51&quot;&gt;Röll 2011, p. 51.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Battle of France ===
At the end of February 1940 the commanding general of the 1st Panzer Division, ''[[Generalleutnant]]'' (Lieutenant General) [[Rudolf Schmidt]], was replaced by ''Generalmajor'' [[Friedrich Kirchner]]. At the time, Strachwitz was sick with [[meningitis]] and was hospitalised in early March. While he was on sick leave, the division was relocated to the [[South Eifel]] on 3 March. The ''Stab'' established the headquarters in the hotel &quot;Union&quot; in [[Cochem]]. The division, along with [[2nd Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|2nd]] and [[10th Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|10th Panzer Divisions]], were subordinated to XIX ''Armeekorps'' under the command of ''[[General der Panzertruppe]]'' (General of the Armoured Corps) [[Heinz Guderian]]. The soldiers were awaiting the order for ''Fall Gelb'' (Case Yellow), Hitler's directive for the [[Battle of France]]. The 1st Panzer Division had orders to cross the border at [[Wallendorf (Eifel)|Wallendorf]] heading towards Luxemburg, taking the Belgian first line of defence at [[Martelange]] and then [[Neufchâteau, Luxembourg Province|Neufchâteau]]. The first main objective was the [[Meuse (river)|Meuse River]] (Maas River) northwest of [[Sedan, Ardennes|Sedan]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p51&quot; /&gt; Strachwitz was hospitalised again from 28 April to 9 May 1940, receiving treatment for an injured foot.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p52&quot;&gt;Röll 2011, p. 52.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1978-062-24, Floing, Pontonbrücke über die Maas.jpg|thumb|right|1st Panzer Division crossing the Meuse on 14 May 1940]]

Kirchner received the order for ''Fall Gelb'' at 13:15, during lunch, on 9 May 1940. The German attack began at 5:35 on the morning of 10 May 1940. The XIX ''Armeekorps'' advanced without resistance through Luxemburg and reached the Belgian border at 10:00. The 1st and 2nd Panzer Division reached the line Menufontaine (south of [[Bastogne]]) – [[Fauvillers]], the 10th Panzer Division the line [[Rulles]] (west of [[Habay]]) – St. Marie (west of [[Étalle, Belgium|Étalle]]), that evening. The advance breached the second Belgian line of defence at [[Bouillon]] and Neufchâteau on 11 May. The German forces, consisting of the 1st and 10th Panzer Division reached the area north of Sedan on the night of 12/13 May. The following day at 8:00 German [[Junkers Ju 87|Ju 87 Stuka]]s and bombers from [[Luftflotte 3]] (3rd Air Fleet) targeted the French and Belgian forces in what would become the [[Battle of Sedan (1940)|Battle of Sedan]]. At 15:30 the German artillery began a 30-minute bombardment followed by an aerial attack. German troops began crossing the Meuse at 16:00 in rubber assault boats. The assault company of ''Kradschützen-Bataillon I'' (1st Motorcycle Infantry Battalion) under the command of [[Wend von Wietersheim]] established the first [[bridgehead]] north of Igles and west of [[Saint-Menges]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p52&quot; /&gt;

By 01:00 on 14 May, a [[pontoon bridge]] had been erected over which elements of the 1st Panzer Division began crossing the Meuse into the bridgeheads. General [[Marcel Têtu]], commander of the [[Allied Tactical Air Forces]] ordered an air strike against the pontoon bridge. Between 15:00 and 16:00 Allied bombers and fighters attacked the bridge. During this attack, Strachwitz organized the traffic across the bridge and ensured delivery of the anti-aircraft ammunition to help fend off the aerial attack, which inflicted only minor damage and did not stop the German advance. ''Panzer-Pionierbataillon'' 37 and ''Sturm-Pionierbataillon'' 43 ran into enemy tanks at [[Chéhéry]] and ''Panzer-Brigade'' I into French tanks at [[Battle of Bulson (1940)|Bulson]]. More than 70 French tanks were left destroyed on the battlefield. While Kirchner ordered the bulk of 1st Panzer Division to keep heading west, French General [[Charles Huntziger]] ordered elements of his ''[[Second Army (France)|IIe Armée]]'' to protect the heights of [[Stonne]], south of Sedan. This dissipated his forces and the French resistance was broken near [[Vendresse]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p53&quot;&gt;Röll 2011, p. 53.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Roll, during the advance in France Strachwitz adopted the thinking that &quot;Tanks must be led from the front!&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p53&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fraschka 1994, p. 139.&lt;/ref&gt; Even in his role as supply officer he led &quot;from the front&quot;, often carrying out &quot;solo runs&quot;. During one of these, Strachwitz and his driver stumbled into a French-occupied barracks. Unable to withdraw, he requested to speak to the French commanding officer and convinced him to surrender his unit. Leading the way, Strachwitz drove 600 French soldiers and their vehicles into captivity. The element of surprise was enough to overcome a numerically superior enemy force.&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, pp. 53–54.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Quote box
|quote=&quot;One can achieve enormous success with only a few, but good people.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Fraschka 1994, p. 141.&lt;/ref&gt;
|source=Hyacinth Graf Strachwitz von Gross-Zauche und Camminetz
|width=30%
|align=left
}}
Following these events the 1st Panzer Division continued to push forward, reaching the [[English Channel|Channel]] coast near [[Calais]] on 23 May 1940, where they encountered heavy British resistance. The 10th Panzer Division was tasked with taking Calais, while Guderian ordered the 1st Panzer Division to head for [[Gravelines]].&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, p. 54.&lt;/ref&gt; Elements of the ''Panzer-Brigade'' I, the subordinated [[Grossdeutschland Division|''Infanterie-Regiment'' (motorized) &quot;Großdeutschland&quot;]] and the ''Panzeraufklärungsabteilung'' 4 (Tank Reconnaissance Detachment 4) reached the [[Aa River (France)|Aa river]] south of Gravelines that night, {{Convert|16|km|mi}} southwest of [[Dunkirk]]. Strachwitz again went on one of his solo runs, penetrated the French and British lines and almost reached Dunkirk, where he observed the [[Battle of Dunkirk|evacuation of British and allied forces by sea]]. He quickly reported his observations to his divisional command. The Ia (operations officer) ''Major im Generalstab'' (in the [[General Staff]]) [[Walther Wenck]] informed him that aerial reconnaissance had made the same observations but the ''[[Führerhauptquartier]]'' had ordered the Panzers to halt. Three days later Hitler ordered the attack to continue but the opportunity to capture the majority of the Allied forces had been lost. The remaining defenders of Dunkirk continued to hold out until 4 June.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p69&quot;&gt;Röll 2011, p. 69.&lt;/ref&gt;

Parts of the 1st Panzer Division were relocated via [[Arras]], [[Cambrai]] and [[Hirson]] to [[Rethel]] on 2 June. The second phase of the Battle of France, ''[[Fall Rot]]'' (Case Red), was about to begin and Strachwitz returned to his ''Panzer-Regiment'' 2 where he again organized the replenishment of the troops. The 1st Panzer Division flanked on the right by the 2nd Panzer Division and the [[XXXXI Panzer Corps (Germany)|XXXXI. Armeekorps (motorized)]] on the left, was ordered to cross the [[Aisne River]] breaching the French defences and head south. The first main objective was the [[Canal du Rhine au Marne]] which was roughly {{Convert|100|km|mi}} away. The French defenders of the Weygand Line, named after [[Maxime Weygand]], had built strong defences, running parallel to the Aisne and [[Canal de l'Oise à l'Aisne|Aisne Canal]]. The German attack began on 5 June with ''[[Heeresgruppe B]]'' (Army Group B), under the command of ''[[Generaloberst]]'' (Colonel General) [[Fedor von Bock]], attacking between the Channel coast and the Aisne. ''[[Heeresgruppe A]]'' (Army Group A), under ''Generaloberst'' [[Gerd von Rundstedt]], to which the 1st Panzer Division was subordinated, was held back until 9 June. Strachwitz in the meantime had been awarded the Clasp to the Iron Cross 1st Class on 6 June for his daring &quot;solo runs&quot;. The two regiments of the 1st Panzer Division cross the Aisne on the night of 9/10 June 1940. The two regiments advanced quickly to [[Neuflize]] and [[Juniville]], where they were engaged in combat with French tanks. The advance proceeded along La Neuveville to [[Bétheniville]] and [[Saint-Hilaire-le-Petit]]. The military training grounds at [[Mourmelon-le-Grand]] was captured on 12 June. The fortress [[Langres]] surrendered to ''Panzer-Regiment'' 2 on 15 June and [[Besançon]] the following day. The final objective was [[Belfort]], which capitulated after a short resistance. This ended the Battle of France for Strachwitz's regiment. ''Panzer-Regiment'' 2 was then stationed at [[Doubs]] until 3 July 1940, it was then relocated to [[Saint-Denis, Seine-Saint-Denis|Saint Denis]], north of Paris, from 3–8 July.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p69&quot; /&gt;

On 21 July the regiment was relocated again, this time in the vicinity of [[Orléans]] where it was based for four weeks. The regiment was ordered to detach two Panzer companies and the headquarters unit of the I. ''Abteilung'' (1st Department). These units, augmented by other Panzer companies, formed four ''Schwimm-Panzerabteilungen'' ([[amphibious tank]] departments) for [[Operation Sea Lion]], the planned and aborted invasion of the [[United Kingdom]]. The remnants of ''Panzer-Regiment'' 2 were then transferred to East Prussia, where they were based at [[Mamonovo|Heiligenbeil]], present-day Mamonovo.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p70&quot;&gt;Röll 2011, p. 70.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Balkans campaign ===

On 2 October 1940, following the Battle of France, ''Panzer-Regiment'' 2 was subordinated to the [[16th Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|16th Panzer Division]]. Strachwitz asked the divisional commander ''Generalmajor'' [[Hans Hube]] for the command of a Panzer company, and Hube gave Strachwitz the I. Bataillon, a position he held until October 1942.&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, pp. 70, 188.&lt;/ref&gt; Strachwitz and his men trained on the new Panzer III with [[5 cm KwK 38]] cannon. He paid special attention to the training and integration of the replacements crews which joined his unit. In December 1940, 16th Panzer Division was declared a ''Lehrtruppe'' (demonstration troop), a unit to be involved in experimentation with new weapons and tactics. Via Bavaria, Austria and Hungary they were transferred to Romania, with Strachwitz's I. Battalion stationed at [[Mediaș]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p70&quot; /&gt;

The division was tasked with the protection of the oil fields at [[Ploiești]], which were vital to the German war effort. They trained some Romanian officers in German Panzer tactics. Apart from training and maintaining their equipment, the soldiers had nothing to do and became bored. In March 1941 Strachwitz was sent back to Cosel in Germany where a new replacement unit was to be founded. He returned via his home town and 24 hours later a telegram from Hube called him back. This was preceded by a series of events in [[Belgrade]]. On 25 March 1941, the government of [[Prince Paul of Yugoslavia]] had signed the [[Tripartite Pact]], joining the [[Axis powers of World War II|Axis powers]] in an effort to stay out of the war. This was immediately followed by mass protests in Belgrade and a [[Yugoslav coup d'état|military coup d'état]] led by Air Force commander General [[Dušan Simović]]. As a result, Hitler chose not only to support Mussolini's ambitions in [[Albanian Kingdom (1939–1943)|Albania]] and in the [[Greco-Italian War]] but also to attack Yugoslavia. For this purpose the mobilized forces of [[1st Panzer Army|''Panzergruppe'' I]] (1st Panzer Group) under the command of ''Generaloberst'' [[Paul Ludwig Ewald von Kleist]] were ordered to attack Belgrade in what would become the [[Invasion of Yugoslavia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p70&quot; /&gt;

[[File:Serbia, Belgrade, Pancevo bridge, 07.08.2011, 2.jpg|thumb|upright=1.5|right|alt=A large bridge spanning a body of water.|Pančevo Bridge in 2011]]
Strachwitz's I. Battalion received the order to prepare for the attack on 6 April 1941 at 09:00. His orders were to break through with the ''Infanterie-Regiment'' (motorized) &quot;Großdeutschland&quot; to Belgrade via [[Werschetz]]—present-day Vršac. His right flank was protected by the [[2nd SS Panzer Division Das Reich|SS-Division &quot;Das Reich&quot;]] and his left flank by the [[11th Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|11th Panzer Division]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p70&quot; /&gt; The attack was preceded by a heavy artillery barrage and the Germans crossed the border at 10:30. The defences were quickly taken and the German troops reached the Werschetz where they were greeted by cheering inhabitants and a band. Their next objective was the [[River Danube]]. They reached the Danube at [[Pančevo]] only to find the [[Pančevo Bridge|bridge]] there destroyed. At Pančevo Strachwitz's unit linked up with the 11th Panzer Division, and he encountered his oldest son, Hyacinth, who was serving with that formation. Strachwitz started confiscating boats and barges in an attempt to cross the Danube. This work had begun when Strachwitz received the order to halt all activities. His unit was ordered to retreat to [[Timișoara]]. On 16 April, Hube announced that the 16th Panzer Division would no longer be needed in the campaign and were ordered to regroup at [[Plovdiv]]. In early May 1941 ''Oberstleutnant'' [[Rudolf Sieckenius]] was given command of ''Panzer-Regiment'' 2, succeeding ''Oberst'' Hero Breusing. The entire 16th Panzer Division was ordered back to their home bases in Germany, with ''Panzer-Regiment'' 2 ordered to [[Racibórz|Ratibor]]—present-day Racibórz—where their equipment was overhauled. Strachwitz was awarded the [[Coroana României]] on 9 June 1941.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p71&quot;&gt;Röll 2011, p. 71.&lt;/ref&gt;

In mid-June 1941, the division received new orders to relocate. The 16th Panzer Division crossed the German–Polish border at [[Syców|Groß Wartenberg]] heading for [[Ożarów]] at the Vistula, which was reached on 19 June 1941. The German soldiers initially believed that they were just going to transit through Russia, on their way to the [[Middle East]] where they would link up with [[Erwin Rommel]]'s [[Afrika Corps]]. But ''[[Generalfeldmarschall]]'' (Field Marshal) [[Walther von Reichenau]], who visited his son, a ''Leutnant'' in the 4th company of ''Panzer-Regiment'' 2, revealed to them the true objective of the next campaign. It would be [[Operation Barbarossa]], the invasion of the Soviet Union.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p71&quot; /&gt;

=== War against the Soviet Union ===

[[File:Operation Barbarossa corrected border.png|thumb|left|alt=A map of Eastern Europe depicting the movement of military units and formations.|Arrow PG1 illustrates the main thrust of the 16th Panzer Division]]

The German offensive against the Soviet Union began early on 22 June 1941 with an artillery barrage. The 16th Panzer Division was subordinated to ''[[Army Group South|Heeresgruppe Süd]]'' (Army Group South) under the command of ''Generalfeldmarschall'' Von Rundstedt. The goal, together with the [[6th Army (Wehrmacht)|6. Armee]] and [[17th Army (Wehrmacht)|17. Armee]] as well as ''Panzergruppe'' I, was to follow the pincers of both armies, heading for [[Kiev]] and rolling up the Soviet flanks in the process, and finally encircling them at the [[Dnieper River]]. The main objective was to conquer the economically important [[Donets Basin]] as well as the oil field in the [[Caucasus]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p72&quot;&gt;Röll 2011, p. 72.&lt;/ref&gt;

German army reconnaissance aircraft spotted the first Soviet formations in the vicinity of the 16th Panzer Division on the morning of 26 June. By this date the division had already progressed {{Convert|125|km|mi}} beyond the German-Soviet [[demarcation line]] and had suffered numerous losses due to mechanical failures caused by the dusty roads. ''Panzer-Regiment'' 2 was ordered to engage the Soviet [[T-26]] tanks which were supported by strong infantry units. In the resulting battle Strachwitz was wounded in his left arm, but he remained with his unit. The heavy counter-attack was repulsed and the bridgehead over the [[Bug River]], held by the division's motorcycle battalion (''Kradschützen-Bataillon'' 16), was secured.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p72&quot; /&gt; The logistics system could not keep up and his regiment was not resupplied until 28 June. His unit first encountered the [[T-34]] and a few [[Kliment Voroshilov tank|KV-1]] and KV-2 tanks the following day. These tanks had stronger armour and outgunned his Panzer III tanks. Only with the support of the [[8.8 cm Flak 18/36/37/41|8.8 cm Flak artillery]], deployed in an anti tank role, were they able to repulse the Soviet forces.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p73&quot;&gt;Röll 2011, p. 73.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[Battle of Uman]] (15 July – 8 August 1941) Strachwitz received a head injury on 29 July and was hit again by shrapnel in the arm the next day. He received first aid in the field and stayed with his men.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p74&quot;&gt;Röll 2011, p. 74.&lt;/ref&gt; The injured arm became infected and he had to receive medical attention in a field hospital on 10 August. He released himself again on 12 August returning to the regiment which had been led by ''Oberleutnant'' von Kleist during his absence.&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, p. 87.&lt;/ref&gt;
Strachwitz, advancing his Panzer III ahead of his troops, engaged a Soviet supply convoy, destroying a large number of soft-skinned vehicles and several artillery batteries. Strachwitz was awarded the [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross]] for his part in this action on 25 August 1941. The presentation was made by Hube in the field on 5 September.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p81&quot;&gt;Röll 2011, p. 81.&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the Battle of Uman ''Panzer-Regiment'' 2 was given a rest. On 8 September the attack resumed and the regiment crossed the Dnjepr on the night of 11/12 September. Together with the I. battalion of ''Schützen-Regiment'' 79 they started their attacked on [[Lubny]] and ambushed and destroyed a Soviet supply convoy. The attack on Lubny ended on 14 September. The [[Battle of Kiev (1941)|Kiev pocket]] was sealed when panzers of the [[3rd Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|3. ''Panzer-Division'']] linked up with ''Panzer-Regiment'' 2 on 15 September 1941. The spearhead of [[2nd Panzer Group|''Panzergruppe'' 2]], under Guderian and [[1st Panzer Group|''Panzergruppe'' 1]], under Von Kleist had captured 50 Soviet Divisions. ''Panzer-Regiment'' 2 was then dispatched to prevent Soviet troops from escaping the pocket. For ''Panzer-Regiment'' 2 the battle of Kiev continued until 4 October 1941.&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, pp. 88–89.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Towards Stalingrad ===

Strachwitz was promoted to ''[[Oberstleutnant]]'' (lieutenant colonel) of the Reserves on 1 January 1942. He had left the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]] at the end of November 1941, returning home to receive treatment for the numerous injuries he had sustained over the year. From 1 December 1941 – 9 January 1942 he stayed at hospitals in Opplen and Breslau. He then went on an extended leave, staying in Groß Stein and Alt Siedel, before returning to the Eastern Front in mid-March 1942. He received the 1939 version of the [[Wound Badge]] in Silver on 17 March 1942.&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, p. 93.&lt;/ref&gt;

Throughout the summer of 1942 Strachwitz led his tanks in the advance to the [[Don River (Russia)|Don River]] and across it to [[Stalingrad]]. At [[Kalach-na-Donu|Kalach on the Don]] his regiment claimed the destruction of more than 270 Soviet tanks within 48 hours. His unit was the first to reach the [[Volga River]] north of Stalingrad on 23 August 1942. According to Williamson, it was during this campaign that Strachwitz gained the nickname ''der Panzergraf'' (the Armoured Count). By late August, the 16th Panzer Division was assigned to ''General der Panzertruppe'' [[Friedrich Paulus]]' 6. Armee, and Strachwitz had been promoted to command the entire ''Panzer-Regiment'' 2. During one engagement on the northern flank of the ''[[Kessel (cauldron)|Kessel]]'', his unit claimed to have destroyed 105 [[T-34]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Williamson 2006, p. 26.&lt;/ref&gt;

Strachwitz and his driver, ''[[Feldwebel]]'' Haase, were severely wounded on 13 October 1942, requiring immediate treatment in a [[field hospital]]. A direct hit on their command Panzer caused severe burns. Strachwitz had to hand over command of his I./''Panzer-Regiment'' 2 to ''Hauptmann'' [[Bernd Freytag von Loringhoven]].&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, p. 109.&lt;/ref&gt; He then had to be flown out and was treated at a hospital at Breslau until 10 November 1942. He received further treatment at the [[Charité]] in Berlin from 11–18 November 1942. During this stay he received news that he had been awarded the 144th [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves|Oak Leaves]] to his Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross. He was ordered to the ''Führerhauptquartier'' in December 1942 for the presentation of the Oak Leaves by Hitler himself. He then went to Bad Gastein for a period of convalescence before spending his vacation at home in Alt Siedel. Strachwitz was promoted to ''Oberst'' (colonel) of the Reserves on 1 January 1943. He then learned that Hube had been ordered to the ''Führerhauptquartier'' for the presentation of the Oak Leaves to the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross. Strachwitz took the opportunity and reported to Hube, volunteering for service in the [[Battle of Stalingrad|Stalingrad pocket]]. Hube rejected this request, stating that Strachwitz would be better deployed somewhere else.&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, p. 110.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Großdeutschland Panzer-Regiment ===

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-J22216, Russland, Hyazinth Graf von Strachwitz.jpg|thumb|right|Strachwitz near Kharkov, May 1943]]

At the end of January 1943 Strachwitz was ordered to the ''Führerhauptquartier''. Talking to General [[Rudolf Schmundt]] and [[Kurt Zeitzler]], the Chief of Staff of the ''[[Oberkommando des Heeres]]'', he was tasked with the creation of the Panzerregiment &quot;Großdeutschland&quot;. The regiment was subordinated to the [[Panzer-Grenadier-Division Großdeutschland|Infantrie-Division (motorized) &quot;Großdeutschland&quot;]] then under the command of ''Generalmajor'' [[Walter Hörnlein]].&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, p. 111.&lt;/ref&gt; He led the regiment when it took part in the [[Third Battle of Kharkov]], fighting alongside SS-''[[Gruppenführer]]'' [[Paul Hausser]]'s [[II SS Panzer Corps]].&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, pp. 112–113.&lt;/ref&gt; Strachwitz was awarded the Wound Badge in Gold on 16 February 1943 and on 28 March 1943 the Swords to his Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves. He received the latter for his leadership at Kharkov and [[Belgorod]].&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, p. 114.&lt;/ref&gt; He received the award together with [[Georg-Wilhelm Postel]] who had been awarded the Oak Leaves to his Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross.&lt;ref&gt;Berger 1999, p. 349.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 5 July 1943, the first day of [[Operation Citadel]] (5–16 July 1943), the German code name for the Battle of Kursk, in the ''Großdeutschland'' area of operations, the Panther battalion got bogged down in the mud near Beresowyj and failed to support the ''Füsilier''{{'}}s attack. Nipe indicates that often ''Oberst'' [[Karl Decker]] and ''Oberstleutnant'' [[Meinrad von Lauchert]] have been made responsible for this failure. However, Nipe argues &quot;that it can safely be assumed that Strachwitz was present; thus, any responsibility regarding actions of ''Großdeutschland''{{'}}s Panzers belongs to the Panzer Count.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Nipe 2011, pp. 92–93.&lt;/ref&gt; Following the battle, Decker wrote a letter to Guderian complaining about the unnecessary losses incurred by the ''Großdeutschland'' division. In this letter Decker stated that how Strachwitz led his tanks on the first day of Kursk was &quot;idiotic&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Nipe 2011, p. 447.&lt;/ref&gt; Strachwitz was wounded again on 10 July. His battle group had been ordered into combat by Hörnlein. The objective was to capture Hill 258.4, about {{convert|4|km|mi}} west of Werchopenje. The battle group encountered roughly 30 Soviet tanks on evening of 9 July. An attack proved unfeasible due to the settling darkness. During these events he received news that his son, Hyacinth, had been severely wounded. At dusk on 10 July he ordered the attack on the Soviet tanks. The first T-34s had been destroyed and Strachwitz was directing the attack from his command Panzer and had ordered his gunner to hold fire. Strachwitz was carelessly resting his left arm on the [[Breech-loading weapon|gun-breech]]. The gunner, without orders, fired the gun, causing the [[recoil]]ing gun to smash his left arm. Strachwitz was immediately evacuated to a field hospital.&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, p. 135.&lt;/ref&gt; Strachwitz's arm was put in a cast and against medical advice he returned to his regiment. When Hörnlein learned of this he gave Strachwitz a direct order to return to the field hospital.&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, p. 136.&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 1943, Strachwitz left the &quot;Großdeutschland&quot; on grounds of ill-health, ostensibly due to his injuries.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p138&quot;&gt;Röll 2011, p. 138.&lt;/ref&gt; Röll speculates, however, that tension between him and the division's commander, Hörnlein, may have been the true reason for Strachwitz's departure.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p139&quot;&gt;Röll 2011, p. 139.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Otto Carius]] stated that:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;Gossip mongers maintained that the Großdeutschland Panzer-Regiment was taken away from Strachwitz because he had too many losses. I had justifiable doubts concerning this claim. Graf Strachwitz and his staff were always employed at hot spots on the front, where they had to carry out extremely pressing operations, for which every form of support was provided to them. Painful losses couldn't always be avoided during those types of operations. But it was through these losses that the lives of many soldiers from other units were saved.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Carius 2003, p. 100.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

=== Battle for the Narva Bridgehead ===

The severe injury to Strachwitz's left arm forced him to retire from the front line.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p138&quot; /&gt; After a stay in the hospital at Breslau and a period of convalescence at home he received a [[teleprinter]] message commanding him as &quot;''Höheren Panzerführer''&quot; (higher tank commander) to the [[Army Group North]]. Strachwitz reported to the commander-in-chief of the [[18th Army (Wehrmacht)|18th Army]], ''Generaloberst'' [[Georg Lindemann]], who was tasked with the leadership of Army Group North.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p139&quot; /&gt;

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-701-0357-17, Russland, Hyazinth Graf von Strachwitz.jpg|thumb|left|Strachwitz with fellow soldiers prior to the offensive, 21 March 1944]]

On 26 March 1944, the Strachwitz Battle Group consisting of the German [[170th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|170th]], [[11th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|11th]], and [[227th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|227th Infantry Divisions]] and tanks, attacked the flanks of the Soviet 109th Rifle Corps south of the [[Tallinn]] railway, supported by an air strike. The tanks led the attack and the East Prussian grenadiers followed, penetrating the fortified positions of the Soviet [[Rifle corps (Soviet)|rifle corps]]. By the end of the day, the Soviet 72nd and parts of the 109th Rifle Corps in the ''Westsack'' (west sack) of the bridgehead were encircled. The rest of the Soviet rifle corps retreated, shooting the local civilians who had been used for carrying ammunition and supplies from the rear.&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, p. 140.&lt;/ref&gt;

As Strachwitz had predicted, the rifle corps counterattacked on the following day. It was repelled by the 23rd East Prussian Grenadier Regiment which inflicted heavy casualties on the Soviets. Two small groups of tanks broke through the lines of the rifle corps on 28 March in several places, splitting the bridgehead in two. Fierce air combat followed, with 41 German [[dive bomber]]s shot down. The west half of the bridgehead was destroyed by 31 March, with an estimated 6,000 Soviet casualties.&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, pp. 140–142.&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''Ostsack'' (east sack) of the Krivasoo bridgehead, defended by the Soviet 6th and the 117th Rifle Corps, were confused by the Strachwitz Battle Group's diversionary attack on 6 April. The attack deceived the Soviet forces into thinking that the German attack intended to cut them out from the west flank. The actual assault came directly at the [[59th Army (Soviet Union)|59th Army]] and started with a heavy bombardment. The positions of the 59th Army were attacked by dive bombers and the forest there was set afire. At the same time, the [[61st Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|61st Infantry Division]] and the Strachwitz tank squadron pierced deep into the 59th Army's defences, splitting the two rifle corps apart and forcing them to retreat to their fortifications. [[Marshal of the Soviet Union]] [[Leonid Govorov]] was outraged by the news, sending in the freshly re-deployed [[8th Army (Soviet Union)|8th Army]]. Their attempt to cut off the Tiger I tanks was repelled by Lieutenant [[Günther Famula]], who received a posthumous Knight's Cross for these actions, keeping their supply lines open. On 7 April, Govorov ordered his troops to switch on to the defensive. The 59th Army, having lost another 5,700 troops from all causes, was withdrawn from the bridgehead. For these successes Strachwitz received the [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross#Knight's Cross with Oak Leaves, Swords, and Diamonds (mit Eichenlaub, Schwertern und Brillianten)|Knight's Cross with Oak Leaves, Swords, and Diamonds]] on 15 April 1944. News of the award had reached his headquarters on the early morning of 15 April via teleprinter message.&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, p. 148.&lt;/ref&gt; The official presentation was made a few weeks later by Hitler.&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, p. 152.&lt;/ref&gt;

The advance brought the Strachwitz Battle Group hope of destroying the entire bridgehead. However, the spring thaw meant that the tanks were impossible to use. The 8th Army repelled the German attack, which lasted from 19–24 April 1944. The Germans lost 2,235 troops, dead and captured, in the offensive, while the total of German casualties in April, from all causes, was 13,274. Soviet casualties in April are unknown, but are estimated by [[Mart Laar]] to be at least 30,000 men from all causes. The losses exhausted the strengths of both sides. The front subsequently stagnated with the exception of artillery, air, and sniper activity and clashes between reconnaissance platoons for the next several months.&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, pp. 149–151.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Final battles ===

Strachwitz led an ad-hoc formation in [[Operation Doppelkopf|Operation ''Doppelkopf'']] (double-head) as part of [[Dietrich von Saucken]]'s [[XXXIX Panzer Corps (Germany)|XXXIX Panzer Corps]] counter-offensive following the major Soviet advance in [[Operation Bagration]]. Von Saucken's goal was to relieve the encircled forces in the [[Courland Pocket]]. Strachwitz's attack on 18 August 1944 was preceded by a heavy artillery bombardment from the [[heavy cruiser]] ''[[German cruiser Prinz Eugen|Prinz Eugen]]''; forces inside the pocket attacked to link up with Strachwitz's force. His troops reached the [[16th Army (Wehrmacht)|16. Armee]] at [[Tukums]] by midday.&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, pp. 167–170.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:BagrationMap2.jpg|thumb|upright=1.5|right|alt=A map of Eastern Europe depicting the movement of military units and formations.|Eastern Front, June–August 1944. The attack at the connection between Army Groups Centre (3rd Panzer Army) and North (16th Army) west of Riga is marked.]]

During a visit to a division command post on 24 August 1944 Strachwitz was badly injured in an automobile accident. The vehicle rolled over and the other occupants were killed. He sustained a fractured skull, and broken ribs, legs, arms and hands, and he was in critical condition. He was immediately taken to a field hospital, before being transferred to a hospital at [[Riga]]. He was then flown to Breslau in a [[Junkers Ju 52]] for further treatment, where he was visited by his son, Harti. The doctors informed him that it would take him eight months to recover fully. Refusing to accept this, he worked out his own rehabilitation plan, and after seven days, Strachwitz signed himself out of the hospital, officially having himself transferred to the hospital at Oppeln. On the drive back he lost consciousness at almost every turn, arriving at his manor in Alt Siedel on 28 November 1944. Here he convalesced until 23 December 1944.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p171&quot;&gt;Röll 2011, p. 171.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Red Army]] started the [[Vistula–Oder Offensive]] on 12 January 1945. The attack began with an intense bombardment by the guns of the [[1st Ukrainian Front]] against elements of [[Army Group A]], initially under the command of ''Generaloberst'' [[Josef Harpe]]. Within a matter of days the Soviet forces involved had advanced hundreds of kilometres, taking much of Poland and striking deep within the borders of the Reich. The offensive broke Army Group A, and much of Germany's remaining capacity for military resistance. The Soviet forces crossed the Silesian border on 19 January and Harpe was relieved of his command and replaced by ''Generaloberst'' [[Ferdinand Schörner]] on 20 January.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p172&quot;&gt;Röll 2011, p. 172.&lt;/ref&gt; Schörner established his headquarters at Oppeln. Here Strachwitz, on crutches, went to see Schörner, requesting a front command to defend his homeland. Schörner declined the offer and Strachwitz insisted on another assignment. Bending to the request, Schörner initially kept him in his staff where Strachwitz conceived the plan of creating a specialized ''Panzerjagdbrigade'' (tank-hunting brigade).&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, pp. 172–173.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[3rd Guards Tank Army (Soviet Union)|3rd Guards Tank Army]] conquered Oppeln and Groß Strehlitz on 23 January 1945. The following day Groß Stein fell into the hands of the advancing Red Army and Strachwitz's palace and entire estate were confiscated.&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, pp. 173–174.&lt;/ref&gt; Schörner yielded to the demands of Strachwitz, and authorized the creation of the ''Panzerjägerbrigade''. These brigades were not mechanized units but rather infantry soldiers deploying hand-held weapons such as the [[Panzerfaust]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p174&quot; /&gt; On 30 January 1945, he was promoted to ''Generalleutnant'' of the Reserves and organized his staff of the [[Panzerjäger Brigade Upper Silesia|Panzerjäger-Brigade ''Oberschlesien'']] at [[Kudowa-Zdrój|Bad Kudova]]—present-day Kudowa-Zdrój in [[Kłodzko Land]].&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, pp. 174, 189.&lt;/ref&gt;

His staff searched for volunteers in the ''Unteroffiziersschulen'' ([[non-commissioned officer]]s schools) and supplementary units. They were able to bring together roughly 8,000 volunteers, mostly from the threatened territories of [[Pomerania]], [[East Prussia]] and Silesia. Strachwitz's tactics quickly made news within the Wehrmacht, and even ''Generalfeldmarschall'' [[Albert Kesselring]], [[OB West|Commander-in-Chief, West]] as of 11 March 1945, expressed an interest. Strachwitz subsequently had one of his officers transferred to Kesselring's staff.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p174&quot;&gt;Röll 2011, p. 174.&lt;/ref&gt;

Following a visit of the commander of the ''Panzerjagdverbände'' (tank-hunting detachment) of [[Army Group Vistula]], ''Oberst'' [[Ernst-Wilhelm Freiherr Gedult von Jungenfeld]], all of the ''Panzerjagdverbände'' were to be centralized under Strachwitz' command. In April the ''Panzerjagdeinheiten'' (tank-hunting units) of [[Army Group Center|Army Group Centre]] were all put under his command, this included ''Panzerjagdverbände'' A, B and C ([[Wehrkreis]] VIII), the ''Heeres-Panzerjagdbrigaden'' 1 and 3, two ''[[Volkssturm]]-Panzerjagdbrigaden'' and the [[Panzerjäger Brigade Lower Silesia|Panzerjäger-Brigade ''Niederschlesien'']] (Lower Silesia) and Free Ukrainians. Strachwitz deployed his men in small combat groups, sometimes operating behind Allied lines, which lured Soviet tanks into traps and attacked them with Panzerfausts. Combat reached its peak in April 1945, and some of his men were credited with more than ten enemy tanks destroyed each. The German front line of Army Group Centre at the time was in mid-Silesia along the [[Mount Ślęża|Zobten]], and via [[Schweidnitz]] and [[Jawor|Jauer]] to [[Lauban]]. The main Soviet thrust was towards Berlin and Dresden, threatening the German troops in Silesia with encirclement. Strachwitz and his men fought under the command of Schörner until the [[German Instrument of Surrender|German capitulation]] on 8 May 1945.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p174&quot; /&gt;

In the aftermath, Strachwitz led his men in a successful breakout from their encirclement in [[Czechoslovakia]] to the U.S.-held region of [[Bavaria]], where they surrendered to U.S. Army forces near Felgen.{{refn|Röll explicitly mentions the location &quot;Felgen&quot;. It is unclear what place is meant by &quot;Felgen&quot;. It could be ''Auf den Folgen'' near Všemily, [[Jetřichovice]] or [[Velden (Pegnitz)|Velden]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p175&quot;&gt;Röll 2011, p. 175.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=&quot;Note&quot;}} Strachwitz was taken to the prisoner of war camp at [[Allendorf, Giessen|Allendorf]] near [[Marburg]], where he was interned together with [[Franz Halder]], Guderian and [[Adolf Galland]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p175&quot; /&gt;

== Involvement with the German resistance ==

In 1969, Peter Hoffmann, a Canadian historian of German descent, published a book with the title &quot;Widerstand, Staatsstreich, Attentat — Der Kampf der Opposition gegen Hitler&quot; ''[Resistance, Coup d'etat, Assassination — The Battle of the Opposition against Hitler]''. This work lists Strachwitz as being part of the [[German Resistance to Nazism|German military resistance to Nazism]]. With Generals [[Hubert Lanz]], [[Hans Speidel]] and {{Interlanguage link multi|Paul Loehning|de|3=Paul Wilhelm Loehning}} he is shown as being associated with &quot;Plan Lanz&quot;, as testified by ''[[General der Gebirgstruppe]]'' Hubert Lanz. According to Lanz, the plan was to arrest or kill Hitler in early February 1943 during Hitler's scheduled  visit to ''[[Army Detachment Lanz|Armeeabteilung Lanz]]''. In his account, Strachwitz's role was to surround Hitler and his escorts shortly after Hitler's arrival with his tanks. Lanz stated that he would have then arrested Hitler, and in the event of resistance, Strachwitz's tanks would have shot and killed the entire delegation. Hitler cancelled the visit and the plan was dropped.&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, pp. 182–183.&lt;/ref&gt; Author Röll casts doubt on this account citing that Strachwitz's cousin, [[Rudolf Christoph Freiherr von Gersdorff]], who attempted to assassinate Hitler in 1943, had recounted that Strachwitz had expressed the belief to him several times that killing Hitler would have constituted murder. Röll concludes that Strachwitz was too much a Prussian officer to consider assassinating Hitler.&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, pp. 184–186.&lt;/ref&gt;

== After World War II and final years ==
Strachwitz was released by the Allies in June 1947. He had lost his wife, his youngest son and his estate during the war. Alda had been killed on 6 January 1946 in a traffic accident with US military truck in [[Velden (Vils)|Velden an der Vils]]. Strachwitz, still a US prisoner of war in camp Allendorf near Marburg, was denied permission to attend the funeral.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p175&quot; /&gt; Harti, who had lost a leg, was killed in action shortly before the end of the war on 25 March 1945 near [[Holstein]]. Strachwitz married again on 30 July 1947 in Holzhausen. With his new wife Nora, née von Stumm (1916–2000), he had four children, two daughters and two sons, born between 1951 and 1960.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p176&quot; /&gt;

He and his wife accepted the invitation of [[Husni al-Za'im]] to move to Syria to work as an [[Agricultural extension|agricultural]] and [[military advisor]] to the [[Military of Syria|Syrian Armed Forces]]. This he did from January to June 1949, a period during the [[1948 Arab–Israeli War]] (15 May 1948 – 10 March 1949), in which Syria fought.&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, pp. 176, 188.&lt;/ref&gt; Strachwitz, bragging about his military successes in the Soviet Union, had a very difficult time with the Syrian officers, and his agricultural suggestions were ignored as well. When [[Adib Shishakli]] seized power, Strachwitz and his wife left Syria. In the meantime, they had received a visa for Argentina, where they hoped to find another advisory position. Via Lebanon, they arrived in [[Livorno]], Italy, where they changed their plans and ran a [[winery]]. They returned to Germany in 1951 with a Red Cross passport. Strachwitz settled on an estate in Winkl near [[Grabenstätt]] in Bavaria and founded the &quot;''Oberschlesisches Hilfswerk''&quot; (Upper Silesian Fund) supporting fellow Silesians in need.&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p176&quot;&gt;Röll 2011, p. 176.&lt;/ref&gt;

Strachwitz lived out his final years quietly and died on 25 April 1968 of [[lung cancer]] in hospital in [[Trostberg]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p176&quot; /&gt; ''Der Panzergraf'' was laid to rest in the village cemetery of Grabenstätt, beside his first wife.&lt;ref name=&quot;BP&quot;&gt;Hartmann 2000, p. 160.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Bundeswehr]] provided an honour guard as a mark of respect. [[Heinz-Georg Lemm]] delivered the [[eulogy]].&lt;ref&gt;Röll 2011, p. 181.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Career summary ==

=== Awards ===

* [[Iron Cross]] (1914)
** 2nd Class (1914)&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p189&quot;&gt;Röll 2011, p. 189.&lt;/ref&gt;
** 1st Class (1914)&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p189&quot; /&gt;
* [[Silesian Eagle]] 2nd and 1st Class with Oak Leaves and Swords (1921)&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p189&quot; /&gt;
* [[Clasp to the Iron Cross]] (1939)
** 2nd Class (5 October 1939)&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomas p356&quot;&gt;Thomas 1998, p. 356.&lt;/ref&gt;
** 1st Class (7 June 1940)&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomas p356&quot; /&gt;
* ''Deutsches Reichssportabzeichen'' (1941)&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p189&quot; /&gt;
* [[Order of the Crown (Romania)]] (9 June 1941)&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p71&quot; /&gt;
* [[Panzer Badge]]
** in Silver (1941)&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p189&quot; /&gt;
** in Gold with engagement numeral &quot;100&quot; (1943/1944)&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p189&quot; /&gt;
* [[Eastern Front Medal]] (August 1942)&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p189&quot; /&gt;
* [[Wound Badge]] (1939)
** in Black (1941)&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p189&quot; /&gt;
** in Silver (17 March 1942)&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p189&quot; /&gt;
** in Gold (16 February 1943)&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p189&quot; /&gt;
* [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves, Swords and Diamonds]]
** Knight's Cross on 25 August 1941 as ''[[Major (Germany)|Major]]'' of the [[Military reserve force|Reserves]] and commander of the I./''Panzer-Regiment'' 2&lt;ref name=&quot;Scherzer p728&quot;&gt;Scherzer 2007, p. 728.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fellgiebel 2000, p. 413.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Von Seemen 1976, p. 331.&lt;/ref&gt;
** 144th Oak Leaves on 13 November 1942 as ''[[Oberstleutnant]]'' of the Reserves and commander of the I./''Panzer-Regiment'' 2&lt;ref name=&quot;Scherzer p728&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fellgiebel 2000, p. 63.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Von Seemen 1976, p. 31.&lt;/ref&gt;
** 27th Swords on 28 March 1943 as ''[[Oberst]]'' of the Reserves and commander of the ''Panzer-Regiment'' &quot;Großdeutschland&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Scherzer p728&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fellgiebel 2000, p. 41.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Von Seemen 1976, p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt;
** 11th Diamonds on 15 April 1944 as ''Oberst'' of the Reserves and commander of a Panzer-Gruppe with the Heeresgruppe Nord&lt;ref name=&quot;Scherzer p728&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fellgiebel 2000, p. 37.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Von Seemen 1976, p. 12.&lt;/ref&gt;
* Units under his command were mentioned numerous times in the [[Wehrmachtbericht]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p189&quot; /&gt;

Strachwitz is often credited with the [[German Cross]] in Gold awarded on 29 May 1943, this however was awarded to his son, also named Hyacinth, who received this award as ''Oberleutnant'' in the 4./Panzer-Regiment 15.&lt;ref&gt;Patzwall &amp; Scherzer 2001, p. 463.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Promotions ===

{| style=&quot;background:none;&quot;
|-
| 17 February 1914: || ''[[Leutnant]]'' (Second Lieutenant)&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p188&quot; /&gt;
|-
| 1921: || ''[[Oberleutnant]]'' (First Lieutenant), effective as 1916&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p188&quot; /&gt;
|-
| 9 August 1933: || SS-''[[Mann (military rank)|Mann]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p188&quot; /&gt;
|-
| 15 September 1933: || SS-''[[Scharführer]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p188&quot; /&gt;
|-
| 19 December 1933: || SS-''[[Truppführer]]'' (Troop Leader)&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p188&quot; /&gt;
|-
| 10 March 1934: || SS-''[[Obertruppführer]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p188&quot; /&gt;
|-
| 28 April 1934: || SS-''[[Untersturmführer]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p188&quot; /&gt;
|-
| 9 November 1934: || SS-''[[Obersturmführer]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p188&quot; /&gt;
|-
| 1934: || ''[[Hauptmann]]'' (Captain) of the [[Military reserve force|Reserves]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p188&quot; /&gt;
|-
| 15 September 1935: || SS-''[[Hauptsturmführer]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p188&quot; /&gt;
|-
| 1935: || ''[[Rittmeister]]'' (Cavalry Master) of the Reserves&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p189&quot; /&gt;
|-
| 13 September 1936: || SS-''[[Sturmbannführer]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p189&quot; /&gt;
|-
| 30 January 1939: || SS-''[[Obersturmbannführer]]''&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p189&quot; /&gt;
|-
| 1940: || ''[[Major (Germany)|Major]]'' (Major) of the Reserves&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p189&quot; /&gt;
|-
| 1 January 1942: || ''[[Oberstleutnant]]'' (Lieutenant Colonel) of the Reserves&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p189&quot; /&gt;
|-
| 1 January 1943: || ''[[Oberst]]'' (Colonel) of the Reserves&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p189&quot; /&gt;
|-
| 3 November 1943: || SS-''[[Standartenführer]]'', effective as 1 September 1943&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p189&quot; /&gt;
|-
| 1 April 1944: || ''[[Generalmajor]]'' (Brigadier General) of the Reserves&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p189&quot; /&gt;
|-
| 30 January 1945: || ''[[Generalleutnant]]'' (Major General) of the Reserves&lt;ref name=&quot;Röll p189&quot; /&gt;
|}

== Notes ==

{{reflist|group=&quot;Note&quot;}}

== References ==

{{Research help|Mil}}

=== Citations ===

{{Reflist|20em}}

=== Bibliography ===

{{Refbegin}}
* {{Cite book
  | last       = Bagdonas
  | first      = Raymond
  | year       = 2013
  | title      = The Devil's General: The Life of Hyazinth Graf Strachwitz – the &quot;Panzer Graf&quot;
  | url        = https://books.google.com/books?id=_ZPUAgAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false
  | location   = Philadelphia; Oxford
  | publisher  = Casemate
  | isbn       = 978-1-61200-222-4
  | accessdate = 6 July 2016
  }}
* {{Cite book
  | last        = Berger
  | first       = Florian
  | year        = 1999
  | title       = Mit Eichenlaub und Schwertern. Die höchstdekorierten Soldaten des Zweiten Weltkrieges
  | trans_title = With Oak Leaves and Swords. The Highest Decorated Soldiers of the Second World War
  | language    = German
  | location    = Vienna, Austria
  | publisher   = Selbstverlag Florian Berger
  | isbn        = 978-3-9501307-0-6
  }}
* {{Cite book
  | last       = Carius
  | first      = Otto
  | authorlink = Otto Carius
  | year       = 2003
  | title      = Tigers in the Mud – The Combat Career of German Panzer Commander Otto Carius
  | location   = Mechanicsburg, PA
  | publisher  = Stackpole Books
  | isbn       = 978-0-8117-2911-6
  }}
* {{Cite book
  | last        = Von Ehrenkrook
  | first       = Hans Friedrich
  | year        = 2000
  | title       = Genealogisches Handbuch des Adels, Gräfliche Häuser Band XVI. Band 123 der Gesamtreihe
  | trans_title = 
  | language    = German
  | location    = Limburg (Lahn), Germany
  | publisher   = C. A. Starke Verlag
  | isbn        = 978-3-7980-0823-6
  }}
* {{Cite book
  | last      = Federl
  | first     = Christian
  | year      = 2000
  | title     = Die Ritterkreuzträger der Deutschen Panzerdivisionen 1939–1945 Die Panzertruppe
  | language  = German
  | location  = Zweibrücken, Germany
  | publisher = VDM Heinz Nickel
  | isbn      = 978-3-925480-43-0
  }}
* {{Cite book
  | last        = Fellgiebel
  | first       = Walther-Peer
  | authorlink  = Walther-Peer Fellgiebel
  | year        = 2000
  | origyear    = 1986
  | title       = Die Träger des Ritterkreuzes des Eisernen Kreuzes 1939–1945 — Die Inhaber der höchsten Auszeichnung des Zweiten Weltkrieges aller Wehrmachtteile
  | trans_title = The Bearers of the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross 1939–1945 — The Owners of the Highest Award of the Second World War of all Wehrmacht Branches
  | language    = German
  | location    = Friedberg, Germany
  | publisher   = Podzun-Pallas
  | isbn        = 978-3-7909-0284-6
  }}
* {{Cite book
  | last      = Fraschka
  | first     = Günther
  | year      = 1994
  | title     = Knights of the Reich
  | location  = Atglen, Pennsylvania
  | publisher = Schiffer Military/Aviation History
  | isbn      = 978-0-88740-580-8
  }}
* {{Cite book
  | last       = Hartmann
  | first      = Wolfgang
  | title      = Breslauer Passion 1945–1947: Festschrift zum 70. Geburtstag des schlesischen Heimatforschers Horst G.W. Gleiss am 26. August 2000
  | language   = German
  | url        = https://books.google.com/books?id=mfJoAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=Strachwitz+Breslauer+Passion+1945%E2%80%931947&amp;dq=Strachwitz+Breslauer+Passion+1945%E2%80%931947
  | accessdate = 24 December 2012
  | year       = 2000
  | publisher  = Natura et Patria Verlag
  | isbn       = 978-3-921060-06-3
  }}
* {{Cite book
  | last        = Hoffmann
  | first       = Peter
  | year        = 1985
  | title       = Widerstand&amp;nbsp;– Staatsstreich – Attentat. Der Kampf der Opposition gegen Hitler
  | trans_title = Resistance, Coup d'etat, Assassination — The Battle of the Opposition against Hitler
  | language    = German
  | location    = München, Germany
  | publisher   = Piper
  | isbn        = 978-3-492-00718-4
  }}
* {{Cite book
  | last        = Meyer
  | first       = Hermann Frank
  | year        = 2008
  | title       = Blutiges Edelweiß: Die 1. Gebirgs-Division im Zweiten Weltkrieg
  | trans_title = Bloody Edelweiss: The 1st Mountain Division in World War II
  | language    = German
  | publisher   = Ch. Links Verlag
  | location    = Berlin, Germany
  | isbn        = 978-3-86153-447-1
  | url         = https://books.google.com/books?id=_Hpr-PK39UkC&amp;pg=PA260&amp;lpg=PA260&amp;dq=blutiges+edelwei%C3%9F+strachwitz#v=onepage&amp;q=blutiges%20edelwei%C3%9F%20strachwitz&amp;f=false
  | accessdate  = 6 July 2016
  }}
* {{Cite book
  | last      = Nipe
  | first     = George M.
  | year      = 2011
  | title     = Blood, Steel and Myth—The II. SS-Panzer-Korps and the road to Prochorowka, July 1943
  | location  = Stamford, CT
  | publisher = RZM Publishing
  | isbn      = 978-0-9748389-4-6
  }}
* {{Cite book
  | last1       = Patzwall
  | first1      = Klaus D.
  | last2       = Scherzer
  | first2      = Veit
  | year        = 2001
  | title       = Das Deutsche Kreuz 1941–1945 Geschichte und Inhaber Band II
  | trans_title = The German Cross 1941–1945 History and Recipients Volume 2
  | language    = German
  | location    = Norderstedt, Germany
  | publisher   = Verlag Klaus D. Patzwall
  | isbn        = 978-3-931533-45-8
  }}
* {{Cite book
  | last        = Röll
  | first       = Hans-Joachim
  | year        = 2011
  | title       = Generalleutnant der Reserve Hyacinth Graf Strachwitz von Groß-Zauche und Camminetz: Vom Kavallerieoffizier zum Führer gepanzerter Verbände
  | trans_title = Lieutenant General of the Reserve Hyacinth Graf Strachwitz von Groß-Zauche und Camminetz: From a Cavalry Officer to a Leader of Armoured Units
  | language    = German
  | location    = Würzburg, Germany
  | publisher   = Flechsig
  | isbn        = 978-3-8035-0015-1
  }}
* {{Cite book
  | last        = Schaulen
  | first       = Fritjof
  | year        = 2005
  | title       = Eichenlaubträger 1940–1945 Zeitgeschichte in Farbe III Radusch – Zwernemann
  | trans_title = Oak Leaves Bearers 1940–1945 Contemporary History in Color III Radusch – Zwernemann
  | language    = German
  | location    = Selent, Germany
  | publisher   = Pour le Mérite
  | isbn        = 978-3-932381-22-5
  }}
* {{Cite book
  | last        = Scherzer
  | first       = Veit
  | year        = 2007
  | title       = Die Ritterkreuzträger 1939–1945 Die Inhaber des Ritterkreuzes des Eisernen Kreuzes 1939 von Heer, Luftwaffe, Kriegsmarine, Waffen-SS, Volkssturm sowie mit Deutschland verbündeter Streitkräfte nach den Unterlagen des Bundesarchives
  | trans_title = The Knight's Cross Bearers 1939–1945 The Holders of the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross 1939 by Army, Air Force, Navy, Waffen-SS, Volkssturm and Allied Forces with Germany According to the Documents of the Federal Archives
  | language    = German
  | location    = Jena, Germany
  | publisher   = Scherzers Militaer-Verlag
  | isbn        = 978-3-938845-17-2
  }}
* {{Cite book
  | last        = Von Seemen
  | first       = Gerhard
  | year        = 1976
  | title       = Die Ritterkreuzträger 1939–1945 : die Ritterkreuzträger sämtlicher Wehrmachtteile, Brillanten-, Schwerter- und Eichenlaubträger in der Reihenfolge der Verleihung : Anhang mit Verleihungsbestimmungen und weiteren Angaben
  | trans_title = The Knight's Cross Bearers 1939–1945 : The Knight's Cross Bearers of All the Armed Services, Diamonds, Swords and Oak Leaves Bearers in the Order of Presentation: Appendix with Further Information and Presentation Requirements
  | language    = German
  | location    = Friedberg, Germany
  | publisher   = Podzun-Verlag
  | isbn        = 978-3-7909-0051-4
  }}
* {{Cite book
  | last        = Thomas
  | first       = Franz
  | year        = 1998
  | title       = Die Eichenlaubträger 1939–1945 Band 2: L–Z
  | trans_title = The Oak Leaves Bearers 1939–1945 Volume 2: L–Z
  | language    = German
  | location    = Osnabrück, Germany
  | publisher   = Biblio-Verlag
  | isbn        = 978-3-7648-2300-9
  }}
* {{Cite book
  |last1=Williamson
  |first1=Gordon
|authorlink1=Gordon Williamson (writer)
  |last2=Bujeiro
  |first2=Ramiro
  |year=2004
  |title=Knight's Cross and Oak Leaves Recipients 1939–40
  |location=Oxford, UK
  |publisher=[[Osprey Publishing]]
  |isbn=978-1-84176-641-6
  |ref=harv
}}
* {{Cite book
  | last      = Williamson
  | first     = Gordon
  | year      = 2006
  | title     = Knight's Cross with Diamonds Recipients 1941–45
  | location  = Oxford, UK
  | publisher = Osprey Publishing
  | isbn      = 978-1-84176-644-7
  }}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Zuber
  |first=Terence
  |year=2002
  |title=Inventing the Schlieffen Plan: German War Planning 1871–1914
  |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=yuDVsT6JvtsC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=schlieffen+plan#v=onepage&amp;q=schlieffen%20plan&amp;f=false
  |location=Oxford, UK
  |publisher=Oxford University Press
  |id={{ASIN| B008B3963U | date=12 February 2014}}
|isbn=9780191647710
  }}
{{Refend}}

== External links ==

* {{DNB portal|129959596|TYP=}}
* {{cite web
  | title      = Strachwitz, Hyazinth Graf von Groß-Zauche und Camminetz
  | work       = Lexikon der Wehrmacht
  | url        = http://www.lexikon-der-wehrmacht.de/Personenregister/Strachwitz.htm
  | language   = German
  | accessdate = 30 January 2013
  }}
* {{cite web
  | title      = Count Hyazinth Strachwitz von Gross-Zauche und Camminetz
  | work       = Achtung Panzer.com
  | url        = http://www.achtungpanzer.com/gen11.htm
  | accessdate = 30 January 2013
  }}
* {{cite web
  | work       = Der Spiegel
  | volume     = 8
  | year       = 1949
  | title      = Hyazinth Graf Strachwitz
  | url        = http://www.spiegel.de/spiegel/print/d-44435520.html
  | language   = German
  | accessdate = 10 February 2013
  }}

{{RKDiamonds}}
{{KCwithOLandSW}}
{{KCwithOL}}
{{Knight's Cross recipients of the 16th PD}}
{{Knight's Cross recipients of the GD Division}}
{{Authority control}}
{{Subject bar
| portal1=Biography
| portal2=Military of Germany
| portal3=Silesia
| portal4=Tank
| portal5=World War I
| portal6=World War II
| commons=y
| commons-search=Hyazinth Graf Strachwitz
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Strachwitz Von Gross-Zauche Und Camminetz, Hyazinth Graf}}
[[Category:20th-century Freikorps personnel]]
[[Category:1893 births]]
[[Category:1968 deaths]]
[[Category:Deaths from lung cancer]]
[[Category:German prisoners of war in World War I]]
[[Category:German prisoners of war in World War II held by the United States]]
[[Category:Lieutenant generals of the German Army (Wehrmacht)]]
[[Category:Panzer commanders]]
[[Category:People from the Province of Silesia]]
[[Category:Prussian Army personnel]]
[[Category:Recipients of the clasp to the Iron Cross, 1st class]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves, Swords and Diamonds]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of the Crown (Romania)]]
[[Category:Reichswehr personnel]]
[[Category:World War I prisoners of war held by France]]</text>
      <sha1>8zodhwrjjgae4x35gnme94i9rohkypm</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
