<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Ikarus IK-2</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2267354</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748154481</id>
      <parentid>747928085</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-06T17:26:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>23 editor</username>
        <id>16532586</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Specifications (Ikarus IK-2) */ c.e.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20159">{{good article}}
{|{{Infobox Aircraft Begin
  |name = Ikarus IK 2
  |image = 
  |caption = 
}}
{{Infobox Aircraft Type
  |type = [[Fighter aircraft|Fighter]]
  |manufacturer = [[Ikarbus|Ikarus A.D.]]
  |designer = Ljubomir Ilić and Kosta Sivčev
  |first flight = 22 April 1935
  |introduced = 1935
  |retired = 1945
  |status = 
  |primary user = [[Royal Yugoslav Air Force]]
  |more users = [[Air Force of the Independent State of Croatia]]
  |produced = &lt;!--years in production, e.g. 1970-1999, if still in active use but no longer built--&gt;
  |number built = 12
  |unit cost = 
  |variants with their own articles = 
}}
|}
The '''Ikarus IK-2''' was a 1930s high-wing, single-seat, [[monoplane]] [[fighter aircraft]] of Yugoslav design built for the [[Royal Yugoslav Air Force]]. The IK-2 was designed by French-trained engineers Kosta Sivčev and Ljubomir Ilić, who saw the desirability of a developing a home-grown aircraft industry. A [[gull-wing]] design, it was armed with a [[propeller hub|hub]]-firing [[autocannon]] and [[fuselage]]-mounted [[Synchronization gear|synchronised]] [[machine gun]]s. Just 12 production models were built, as the aircraft was obsolescent at the time it was brought into service in 1935, and only eight were serviceable at the time of the [[Nazi Germany|German]]-led [[Axis powers|Axis]] [[invasion of Yugoslavia]] in April 1941. After the defeat of Yugoslavia, the remaining four aircraft were taken onto the strength of the [[Air Force of the Independent State of Croatia|air force]] of the Axis [[puppet state]], the [[Independent State of Croatia]], but none survived the war.

==Background==
In the late 1920s, a scheme promoted by the [[Royal Yugoslav Air Force]] ({{lang-sh|Vazduhoplovstvo vojske Kraljevine Jugoslavije}}, VVKJ) and the Royal Aero Club of Yugoslavia sent aspiring aeronautical engineers to France to develop their knowledge. It was intended that after this advanced training, they would return to Yugoslavia and be offered specialist roles in the VVKJ or in the aeronautical industry. Ljubomir Ilić and Kosta Sivčev went through this program, but when they returned to Yugoslavia, both were employed in administrative work. Frustrated by this, in 1931 they decided to design a replacement for the [[Czechoslovakia]]n-built [[Avia BH-33]]E biplane [[Fighter aircraft|fighter]] then in service with the VVKJ. Working in a basement in [[Belgrade]], then in Ilić's apartment in [[Novi Sad]], they devoted their spare time to secretly working on their design. Their original concept was for a low-wing monoplane with a retractable undercarriage, but contemporary thinking led them to modify their initial design into a strut-braced high-wing monoplane armed with a [[propeller hub|hub]]-firing [[autocannon]] and [[fuselage]]-mounted [[Synchronization gear|synchronised]] [[machine gun]]s. The [[gull-wing]] design emphasised power and manoeuvrability over other characteristics.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|pp=170 &amp; 176}}

==Design and development==
===IK-1===
The aircraft was designed around a French-made [[V12 engine|12-cylinder]] [[Hispano-Suiza 12Y]]crs engine with a [[Hispano-Suiza HS.404]] {{convert|20|mm|adj=on|abbr=on}} autocannon mounted between the cylinder banks of the engine and firing through the propeller hub. This powerful {{convert|860|shp|link=on}} engine combined with the hub-firing cannon mandated the use of a metal fuselage.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|pp=170–171}} Other armament consisted of two synchronised French-made {{convert|7.9|mm|abbr=on}} [[Darne machine gun]]s, mounted under and to each side of the engine. The wing was braced with two [[strut]]s on each side of the fuselage; the [[Landing gear|fixed conventional landing gear]] was [[Aircraft fairing|spatted]] and mounted off the wing struts.  The fixed tailwheel was also spatted.  The enclosed [[cockpit]] was located behind the wing. The [[horizontal stabilizer]] on each side was braced from below with two rigid braces from the lower tailcone, and tied from above with two [[flying wires]] from the [[vertical stabilizer]]. The three-bladed propeller was manually adjustable in pitch.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|p=171}}

Considerable work was needed to fully develop the design but, by early 1933, the two men had moved the project through the pre-project, basic aerodynamic and evaluation stages, including the building of a wooden scale model that Ilić took to [[Paris]] to test in the Eiffel-built wind tunnel. Up to this point, the two men had received no outside help, and had been forced to borrow from family to keep the project going. They then decided to approach the head of the technical department of the VVKJ, ''Potpukovnik'' (Lieutenant Colonel) Srbobran Stanojević with their design. Stanojević was surprised but impressed with their work and an official report proposing to build the design was presented on 22 September 1933. Some senior VVKJ officers opposed the concept, as did ''Kapetan'' (Captain) Leonid Bajdak, an &quot;acknowledged outstanding exponent of fighter tactics&quot;, who considered that a biplane with a {{convert|600|shp|abbr=on}} engine was the ultimate in fighter design.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|p=171}}

Despite this opposition, support from Stanojević and some younger pilots meant that the concept was approved, and in 1934 a prototype was ordered from the [[Ikarbus|Ikarus A.D.]] factory in [[Zemun]] near Belgrade, for delivery by the end of that year. The prototype was designated IK-1, with the &quot;IK&quot; standing for (Ljubomir) Ilić and Kosta (Sivčev). It is believed that the prototype was complete by September 1934, but the first flight was delayed due to concerns about the wing structure.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|pp=171–172}} The following month, Bajdak was appointed as test pilot for the prototype, but he did not co-operate in the preparations for the maiden flight, and decided to develop his own test program.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|p=173}}

Permission was granted for flight testing to begin in April 1935, and Bajdak conducted his first flight in the prototype on 22 April 1935. For this initial uneventful flight, no weapons were installed and a light fuel load was used. The following day, Bajdak put the IK-1 into unplanned aerobatic manoeuvres, after which the wing fabric was observed as being slack. An official from Ikarus checked it and stated that this would resolve once the fabric varnish had completely dried. Bajdak took the aircraft for a third test flight the next day, which involved more unplanned aerobatics. When the aircraft was at {{convert|1000|m|abbr=on}}, Bajdak put it into a shallow dive and pulled up abruptly at high speed, at which point the wing fabric began to tear rapidly, to the extent that it could be seen from the ground.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|p=173}} The aircraft dropped into a spin to [[starboard]], and Bajdak baled out safely while the IK-1 crashed into the ground.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|p=174}}

===IK-2===
Critics exploited the accident to undermine the IK-1 concept, with Bajdak joining those criticising the aircraft. The three flights were not considered sufficient to give a verdict on the design, and the debate over its future was fierce. This placed significant pressure on the designers, as every element of the aircraft design was subsequently attacked. Eventually, it was generally agreed that the aircraft was well-designed, but it needed more testing. At this point, Ikarus decided to build a second prototype, as it was evident that the hand-sewn fabric seam on the wing had not stood up to the strain of aerobatics, and their workmanship was in question. The second prototype took 10 months to build, with the two designers closely involved.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|p=175}}

The main difference from the IK-1 was that the IK-2 had wings covered with metal sheeting, leaving only the rear fuselage and tailplane fabric covered. The new wing was tested with both fabric and metal covering at the request of the VVKJ. Other changes were a radiator of reduced size and improved shape, and modified air intakes, making for a more streamlined fuselage.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|p=175}} The two Darne machine guns were replaced with two {{convert|7.92|mm|abbr=on|sigfig=2}} [[M1919 Browning machine gun#Other calibers|Browning/FN]] machine guns.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|p=191}}

After the second prototype was delivered, the aircraft was placed in the hands of a different test pilot, ''Poručnik'' (1st Lieutenant) Janko Dobnikar, who conducted its first flight on 24 August 1934. Dobnikar had worked closely with the designers and Ikarus during its construction and static testing, and his suggestions had resulted in an improved cockpit layout. He strictly followed a completely new test program, while installed testing equipment recorded the various characteristics of the aircraft. After gaining complete mastery of the aircraft, he conducted some aerobatic manoeuvres during a visit by the future Turkish president [[İsmet İnönü]], which included a complete inverted loop.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|p=175}} In mid-October 1935, Dobnikar broke the unofficial European air speed record for an aircraft with a fixed undercarriage, attaining a speed of {{convert|435|km/h|abbr=on}}, which was also a Yugoslav air speed record. The aircraft was able to achieve greater than expected power at altitudes of {{convert|4000|–|5000|m|abbr=on}}. Dobnikar completed the testing program and submitted his report to the VVKJ on 23 May 1937.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|p=176}}

After VVKJ acceptance, a group of pilots conducted 16 mock dogfights between the IK-2 and the [[Hawker Fury]] I biplane already in service with the VVKJ, during which the IK-2 displayed overall superiority over the British-built aircraft. At one point, Bajdak declared his continuing doubts about the aircraft, and Dobnikar challenged him to a duel, with Bajdak flying his preferred aircraft, the Fury I. After Dobnikar won the climbing competition and a race to Zemun and back from Belgrade, the final dogfight forced Bajdak to concede that the IK-2 was the better aircraft. On 20 November 1937, the VVKJ submitted a proposal to order a batch of 12 IK-2s, which was approved the following month. The production version included some additional improvements, but continued testing resulted in further delays, with the aircraft not entering service for another year. By this time, international consensus had coalesced around the superiority of the low-wing monoplane, and the IK-2 was already obsolescent by the time it was delivered to VVKJ fighter units.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|p=176}}

==Operational history==
The first six production aircraft were delivered to the 6th Fighter Regiment of the VVKJ, based at Zemun, in early 1939. The pilots subjected them to considerable additional testing, before they entered normal service around mid-year. The remaining six entered service during the remainder of 1939. The aircraft were delivered without radios or armament, which were fitted in VVKJ workshops. In October 1939, the IK-2s were transferred to the 4th Fighter Regiment in [[Zagreb]] until licence-built [[Hawker Hurricane]]s were delivered from Zemun, after which the IK-2s were to be transferred to the 5th Fighter Regiment in [[Niš]]. By the end of 1940, all the production IK-2s were concentrated in the 107th Fighter Squadron of the 34th Fighter Group, which consisted solely of IK-2s. This was only an interim allocation, as the other squadron of the group was equipped with Hurricanes, and as soon as the 107th Fighter Squadron could be equipped with Hurricanes, the IK-2s were to move to the 5th Fighter Regiment. The threat of war overtook this planned deployment, and on 13 March 1941, the IK-2s of the 107th Fighter Squadron were moved to [[Laktaši|Bosanski Aleksandrovac]] near [[Banja Luka]],{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|pp=176–177}} under the command of ''Kapetan'' Zarko Vukajlović.{{sfn|Shores|Cull|Malizia|1987|p=188}}

When the [[Nazi Germany|German]]-led [[Axis powers|Axis]] [[invasion of Yugoslavia]] commenced on 6 April 1941, only eight IK-2s were serviceable. One had been damaged in a landing accident, two were at the workshops in Zagreb being repaired, and the fourth unserviceable machine was in a badly damaged condition at Bosanski Aleksandrovac. That day and the next, the 107th Fighter Squadron patrolled over [[Bosnia (region)|Bosnia]] but did not make any contact with the enemy. Two machines conducted a [[combat air patrol]] over the airfield of the 8th Bomber Regiment at [[Nova Topola, Gradiška|Nova Topola]]. This pattern continued the following day without incident, but patrol duration and coverage was limited by the short range of the aircraft. On 8 April, a patrol unsuccessfully gave chase to a lone German reconnaissance aircraft, and later in the day, one of the IK-2s force landed, leaving seven operational aircraft.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|pp=178–179}}

About 14:00 on 9 April, two ''[[Organization of the Luftwaffe (1933–45)#Staffel|Staffeln]]'' of German [[Messerschmitt Bf 109]] fighters from II. Gruppe of ''[[Jagdgeschwader 54]]'' were observed heading towards Nova Topola just as two IK-2s were landing after a patrol in poor flying weather.{{sfn|Shores|Cull|Malizia|1987|pp=216–217}} One of the IK-2s managed to overshoot and climbed to meet them, but the other was unable to, and had to complete its landing. ''Podnarednik'' (Junior Sergeant) Branko Jovanović used the extreme manoeuvrability of his IK-2 to avoid the nine Bf 109s that swooped in to attack, while a total of eight Hurricanes and five more IK-2s from the 4th Fighter Regiment scrambled to meet the Germans. For the following seven or eight minutes, a furious dogfight ensued over Novo Topola, during which two German aircraft were claimed and two Hurricanes and one IK-2 were lost.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|p=179}} German records indicate that only one of their aircraft was lost, and that the pilot survived. ''Podnarednik'' Stikić survived the loss of his IK-2, but was badly wounded. The Germans, low on fuel, broke off and headed north.{{sfn|Shores|Cull|Malizia|1987|pp=216–217}}

The following day, one IK-2 force landed due to engine failure, reducing the number of serviceable IK-2s to five. Despite deteriorating weather conditions and revolts within the Yugoslav forces, combat patrols continued. At 12:00 on 11 April, all aircraft were grounded by the weather.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|p=179}} On 12 April, aircraft of the 4th Fighter Regiment took to the air again, chasing German reconnaissance aircraft, but the IK-2s did not record any victories. The following day, the 4th Fighter Regiment continued carrying out sorties, but around 12:00 the commander of the 2nd Mixed Air Brigade ordered the remaining aircraft of the 4th Fighter Regiment to be destroyed, and all personnel to withdraw via road to [[Sarajevo]].{{sfn|Shores|Cull|Malizia|1987|p=223}}

At the end of the brief campaign, the [[Air Force of the Independent State of Croatia]] ({{lang-hr|Zrakoplovstvo Nezavisne Države Hrvatske}}, ZNDH) made the three or four surviving IK-2s serviceable using other captured aircraft for spares.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|p=179}} At the beginning of 1942, there were four IK-2s in service with the ZNDH, but they lacked spare parts.{{sfn|Savić|Ciglić|2002|p=60}} Later that year, an operational IK-2 was observed at Rajlovac airfield near Sarajevo,{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|p=179}} and in October 1943, two of the IK-2s were operating from [[Banja Luka Zalužani Airport|Zalužani airfield]] north of Banja Luka, and remained there for nearly a year conducting strafing missions. At the end of 1943, all four IK-2s were still in service, but at the end of the following year, just two IK-2s remained.{{sfn|Savić|Ciglić|2002|p=61}} No IK-2s survived the war.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|p=179}}

==Further development==
A proposed development of the IK-2 was the IK-4, a dual control two-seater fast reconnaissance monoplane, but it was never ordered.{{sfn|Oštrić|Janić|1973|p=179}}

==Operators==
;{{flag|Kingdom of Yugoslavia}}
*[[Royal Yugoslav Air Force]]
;{{flag|Independent State of Croatia}}
*[[Air Force of the Independent State of Croatia]]

==Specifications (Ikarus IK-2)==
'''Source''': {{harvtxt|Oštrić|Janić|1973|pp=191–192}}

{{Aircraft specs
|ref=
|prime units?=met
&lt;!--
        General characteristics
--&gt;
|crew=1
|length m=7.88
|span m=11.4
|height m=3.84
|wing area sqm=18
|empty weight kg=1,502
|gross weight kg=1,857
|fuel capacity={{convert|250|kg|abbr=on}}

&lt;!--
        Powerplant
--&gt;
|eng1 number=1
|eng1 name=[[Hispano-Suiza 12Y]]crs
|eng1 type=liquid-cooled V-12 piston engine
|eng1 shp=860

|prop blade number=3
|prop name=adjustable pitch
&lt;!--
        Performance
--&gt;
|max speed kmh=435
|max speed note=at {{convert|5,000|m|ft|abbr=on|0}}
|cruise speed kmh=250
|range km=700
|ceiling m=12,000
|time to altitude=5 minutes 25 seconds to {{convert|5000|m|abbr=on}}
|wing loading kg/m2=103
&lt;!--
        Armament
--&gt;
|armament=
* 1 × [[20 mm caliber|20 mm]] [[Hispano-Suiza HS.404]] cannon with 60 rounds in a spiral drum
* 2 × [[7.92 mm caliber|7.92 mm]] [[M1919 Browning machine gun|Browning/FN]] machine guns with 250 rounds per gun
}}

==See also==
* [[Rogožarski IK-3]], a Yugoslav single engine low-wing monoplane single-seat interceptor fighter designed by the same men

{{Aircontent|
|related=
* Ikarus IK-4
|similar aircraft=
* [[Avia B-534]]
* [[Hawker Fury]]
* [[PZL P.8]]
* [[PZL P.11]]
* [[PZL P.24]]
|sequence=
|lists=
* [[List of aircraft of World War II]]
* [[List of fighter aircraft]]
|see also=
}}

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Oštrić
  | first1 = Šime I.
  | last2 = Janić
  | first2 = Čedomir J.
  | year = 1973
  | chapter = IK Fighters (Yugoslavia: 1930–40s)
  | editor1-last = Cain
  | editor1-first = Charles W.
  | editor2-last = Windrow
  | editor2-first = Martin
  | pages = 169–193
  | title = Aircraft in Profile
  | volume = 13
  | series = 241–246
  | publisher = Profile Publications
  | location = Windsor, Berkshire
  | isbn = 0-85383-022-3
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Savić
  | first1 = Dragan
  | last2 = Ciglić
  | first2 = Boris
  | title = Croatian Aces of World War 2
  | year = 2002
  | publisher = Osprey Publishing
  | location = London, England
  | isbn = 978-1-84176-435-1
  | url = http://books.google.ca/books?id=RaBh3kd2HoMC
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Shores
  | first1 = Christopher F.
  | last2 = Cull
  | first2 = Brian
  | last3 = Malizia
  | first3 = Nicola
  | title = Air War for Yugoslavia, Greece, and Crete, 1940–41
  | year = 1987
  | publisher = Grub Street
  | location = London, England
  | isbn = 978-0-948817-07-6
  | ref = harv
  }}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
{{commons category|Ikarus aircraft}}
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book
  | last = Green
  | first = William
  | title = War Planes of the Second World War, Volume Four: Fighters
  | year = 1969
  | publisher = MacDonald &amp; Co.
  | location = London, England
  | isbn = 0-356-01448-7
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Grujic
  | first = Zlatomir
  | title = Avijacija Srbije i Jugoslavije, 1901–1994
  | trans-title = Aviation of Serbia and Yugoslavia, 1901–1994
  | language = Serbo-Croatian| year = 1997
  | publisher = Vojna knjiga
  | location = Belgrade, Yugoslavia
  | isbn = 86-335-0019-1
  }}
*{{cite book
  | last1 = Janić
  | first1 = Čedomir
  | last2 = Petrović
  | first2 = O.
  | title = Short History of Aviation in Serbia
  | year = 2011
  | publisher = Aerokomunikacije
  | location = Belgrade, Serbia
  | isbn = 978-86-913973-2-6
  }}
{{refend}}
==External links==
* [http://www.ipmssrbija.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/04/maketar-plus-03-1-2.pdf ''„Ikarus IK-2 – Royal Story“''], by Nenad M. Miklusev (p 14 In English)
{{Ikarus aircraft}}

[[Category:Gull-wing aircraft]]
[[Category:Yugoslav fighter aircraft 1930–1939]]
[[Category:Ikarus aircraft]]
[[Category:Monoplanes]]
[[Category:Propeller aircraft]]
[[Category:Single-engine aircraft]]</text>
      <sha1>4jiy0yow5695ue41kjnx8tdnx3vzryt</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
