<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Japanese aircraft carrier Jun'yō</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1269814</id>
    <revision>
      <id>744812561</id>
      <parentid>744687630</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-17T16:11:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Llammakey</username>
        <id>21878292</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Footnotes */ fixed columns</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="28320">{|{{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
|Ship image=[[Image:Image-Japanese aircraft carrier Junyo 2 cropped.jpg|300px]]
|Ship caption=''Jun'yō'' moored at [[Sasebo, Nagasaki|Sasebo]], [[Japan]] on 26 September 1945
}}
{{Infobox ship career
| Hide header =
| Ship name =SS ''Kashiwara Maru''
| Ship owner = ''[[Nippon Yusen Kaisha]]'' (Japan Mail Steamship Company)
| Ship country =[[Empire of Japan]]
| Ship flag = {{shipboxflag|Japan|civil}}
|Ship ordered=Late 1938
|Ship builder=[[Mitsubishi Heavy Industries]], [[Nagasaki]]
|Ship laid down=20 March 1939
|Ship launched=26 June 1941
|Ship yard number=900
|Ship way number=3
| Ship fate =Sold to the Imperial Japanese Navy, 10 February 1941
| Ship notes =
}}
{{Infobox ship career
|Hide header=title
|Ship country=
|Ship flag={{shipboxflag|Empire of Japan|naval}}
|Ship renamed=''Jun'yō''
|Ship launched=26 June 1941
|Ship acquired=10 February 1941
|Ship commissioned=3 May 1942
|Ship stricken=30 November 1945
|Ship namesake=[[Peregrine falcon]]
|Ship struck=30 November 1945
|Ship fate=[[ship breaking|Scrapped]], 1946–47
|Ship notes=
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
|Hide header=
|Header caption=(as built)
|Ship class={{sclass-|Hiyō|aircraft carrier}}
|Ship displacement= {{convert|24150|t|LT|abbr=on|lk=in}} ([[Standard displacement#Standard displacement|standard]])
|Ship length= {{convert|219.32|m|ftin|abbr=on}} ([[Length overall|o/a]])
|Ship beam={{convert|26.7|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
|Ship draft={{convert|8.15|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
|Ship power=*{{convert|56250|shp|kW|abbr=on|lk=in}}
* 6 [[Kampon]] [[water-tube boiler]]s
|Ship propulsion=*2 shafts
* 2 geared [[steam turbine]] sets
|Ship speed={{convert|25.5|kn|lk=in}}
|Ship range={{convert|12251|nmi|lk=in|abbr=on}} at {{convert|18|kn}}
|Ship complement=1,187–1,224
|Ship sensors=1 × [[List of Japanese World War II radar#Shipborne Radar|Type 2, Mark 2, Model 1]] air search [[radar]]
|Ship armament=*6 × twin [[12.7 cm/40 Type 89 naval gun|{{convert|12.7|cm|abbr=on|1}} Type 89]] [[dual-purpose gun]]s
* 8 × triple [[Type 96 25 mm AT/AA Gun|{{convert|25|mm|abbr=on|1}} Type 96]] [[AA gun]]s
|Ship armor=*[[Belt armor|Belt]]: {{convert|25|-|50|mm|abbr=on}}
* [[Deck (ship)|Deck]]: {{convert|25|mm|in|abbr=on}}
|Ship aircraft=48–53
|Ship aircraft facilities=
|Ship notes=
}}
|}

{{Nihongo|'''''Jun'yō'''''|隼鷹|&quot;Peregrine Falcon&quot;}}&lt;ref&gt;Silverstone, p. 332&lt;/ref&gt; was a {{sclass-|Hiyō|aircraft carrier}} of the [[Imperial Japanese Navy]] (IJN). She was [[laid down]] as the [[passenger liner]] {{Nihongo|'''''Kashiwara Maru'''''|橿原丸}}, but was purchased by the IJN in 1941 while under construction and converted into an aircraft carrier. Completed in May 1942, the ship participated in the [[Aleutian Islands Campaign]] the following month and in several battles during the [[Guadalcanal Campaign]] later in the year. Her aircraft were used from land bases during several battles in the [[New Guinea campaign|New Guinea]] and [[Solomon Islands campaign|Solomon Islands Campaigns]].

''Jun'yō'' was torpedoed in November 1943 and spent three months under repair. She was damaged by several bombs during the [[Battle of the Philippine Sea]] in mid-1944, but quickly returned to service. Lacking aircraft, she was used as a transport in late 1944 and was torpedoed in December. ''Jun'yō'' was under repair until March 1945 when the repairs were cancelled as uneconomical. She was then effectively [[hulk (ship)|hulked]] for the rest of the war. After the [[surrender of Japan]] in September, the Americans also deemed her not worth the cost to make her serviceable for use as a repatriation ship and she was [[ship breaking|broken]] up in 1946–47.

==Design and description==
The ship was ordered in late 1938 as the fast luxury passenger liner ''Kashiwara Maru'' by ''[[Nippon Yusen Kaisha]]'' (the Japan Mail Steamship Company) in late 1938. In exchange for a 60% subsidy of her building costs by the Navy Ministry, she was designed to be converted to an auxiliary aircraft carrier, one of 10 such ships subsidized by the IJN.&lt;ref&gt;Lengerer &amp; Rehm-Takahara, pp. 17, 106&lt;/ref&gt;

''Jun'yō'' had a length of {{convert|219.32|m|ftin|sp=us}} [[length overall|overall]]. She had a [[beam (nautical)|beam]] of {{convert|26.7|m|ftin|sp=us}} and a [[draft (ship)|draft]] of {{convert|8.15|m|ftin|sp=us}}. She [[displacement (ship)|displaced]] {{convert|24150|t|LT|sp=us}} at [[Standard displacement#Standard displacement|standard load]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Lengerer &amp; Rehm-Takahara, p. 107&quot;&gt;Lengerer &amp; Rehm-Takahara, p. 107&lt;/ref&gt; Her crew ranged from 1,187 to 1,224 officers and men.&lt;ref&gt;Jentschura, Jung &amp; Mickel, p. 52&lt;/ref&gt; The ship was fitted with two [[Mitsubishi Heavy Industries|Mitsubishi-Curtis]] geared [[steam turbine]] sets with a total of {{convert|56250|shp|kW|lk=in}}, each driving one [[propeller shaft]], using steam provided by six Mitsubishi three-drum [[water-tube boiler]]s. ''Jun'yō'' had a designed speed of {{convert|25.5|kn|lk=in}}, but reached {{convert|26|kn}} during her [[sea trial]]s. The ship carried {{convert|4100|t|LT|sp=us}} of [[fuel oil]] which gave her a range of {{convert|12251|nmi|lk=in}} at {{convert|18|kn}}.&lt;ref&gt;Lengerer &amp; Rehm-Takahara, pp. 189–90&lt;/ref&gt;

===Flight deck arrangements===
[[File:SC 218543.jpeg|thumb|upright|left|Aft view of ''Jun'yō''{{'}}s island, 19 October 1945]]
''Jun'yō''{{'}}s [[flight deck]] was {{convert|210.3|m|ftin|sp=us}} long and had a maximum width of {{convert|27.3|m|ftin|sp=us}}. A large [[Glossary of nautical terms#I|island]] was fitted on the starboard side that was integrated with, for the first time in a Japanese carrier, the ship's [[funnel (ship)|funnel]]. The ship was designed with two superimposed [[hangar]]s, each approximately {{convert|153|m|ftin|sp=us}} long, {{convert|15|m|ftin|sp=us}} wide and {{convert|5|m|ftin|sp=us}} high. Each hangar could be subdivided by four [[fire curtain]]s and they were fitted with [[fire fighting foam]] dispensers on each side. The hangars were served by two square [[Elevator#Aircraft elevators|aircraft elevators]] with rounded corners, {{convert|14.03|m|ftin|sp=us}} on each side.&lt;ref&gt;Lengerer &amp; Rehm-Takahara, pp. 108–14&lt;/ref&gt;

The ship's air group was originally intended to consist of 12 [[Mitsubishi A5M]] &quot;Claude&quot; fighters, plus 4 in storage, 18 [[Aichi D3A]] &quot;Val&quot; dive bombers, plus 2 in reserve, and 18 [[Nakajima B5N]] &quot;Kate&quot; [[torpedo bomber]]s. This was revised to substitute a dozen [[Mitsubishi A6M Zero]] fighters, together with 3 more in storage, for the A5Ms by the time the ship commissioned in 1942. As a result of the lessons learned from the [[Battle of Midway]] in June, the ship's fighter complement was strengthened to 21 Zeros, and the other aircraft reduced to 12 D3As and 9 B5Ns. By the end of the year, 6 more Zeros replaced an equal number of D3As. Although it was possible to fit all these aircraft into the hangars, 8 or 9 were usually stored on the flight deck to reduce cramping below decks.&lt;ref name=lr111&gt;Lengerer &amp; Rehm-Takahara, p. 111&lt;/ref&gt;

===Armor, armament and sensors===
As a conversion from an ocean liner, it was not possible to add much armor, although the ship had a [[double bottom]]. Two plates of Ducol steel, each {{convert|25|mm|abbr=on}} thick, protected the sides of the ship's machinery spaces. The ship's [[aviation gasoline]] tanks and [[magazine (artillery)|magazines]] were protected by one layer of Ducol steel. In addition, her machinery spaces were further subdivided by transverse and longitudinal [[bulkhead (partition)|bulkheads]] to limit any flooding.&lt;ref&gt;Lengerer &amp; Rehm-Takahara, p. 188&lt;/ref&gt;

The ship's primary armament consisted of a dozen 40-[[caliber (artillery)|caliber]] [[12.7 cm/40 Type 89 naval gun|{{convert|12.7|cm|abbr=on|1}} Type 89]] [[anti-aircraft gun|anti-aircraft (AA) guns]] in six twin-gun mounts on [[sponson]]s along the sides of the hull. ''Jun'yō'' was also initially equipped with eight triple mounts for [[Type 96 25 mm AT/AA Gun|25&amp;nbsp;mm Type 96]] light AA guns, also in sponsons along the sides of the hull. In mid-1943, four more triple mounts were added and another four triple mounts in late 1943–early 1944. Two of these last four mounts were mounted on the stern and the others were placed in front of and behind the island. A dozen single mounts were also added, some of which were portable and could be mounted on the flight deck. After the Battle of the Philippine Sea in June 1944, the ship's anti-aircraft armament was reinforced with three more triple mounts, two twin mounts and eighteen single mounts for the 25&amp;nbsp;mm Type 96 gun. These guns were supplemented by six 28-round AA rocket launchers. In October 1944, ''Jun'yō'' had a total of 91 Type 96 guns; 57 in nineteen triple mounts, 4 in two twin mounts, and 30 single mounts.&lt;ref&gt;Lengerer &amp; Rehm-Takahara, pp. 188, 193&lt;/ref&gt;

Two Type 94 high-angle [[Fire-control system#Naval fire control|fire-control directors]], one on each side of the ship, were fitted to control the Type 89 guns. Each director mounted a {{convert|4.5|m|ftin|adj=on|sp=us}} [[rangefinder]]. When ''Jun'yō'' was first commissioned only the rangefinders were fitted and the directors were added later. Four Type 95 directors controlled the 25&amp;nbsp;mm guns and another pair were added in early 1943. Early warning was provided by two [[List of Japanese World War II radar#Shipborne Radar|Type 2, Mark 2, Model 1]] [[early-warning radar]]s. The first of these was mounted on the top of the island in July 1942, shortly after she was completed, and the other was added later in the year on the port side of the hull, outboard of the rear elevator.&lt;ref&gt;Lengerer &amp; Rehm-Takahara, pp. 188–89, 193&lt;/ref&gt; A smaller [[List of Japanese World War II radar#Land-based Radar|Type 3, Mark 1, Model 3]] air search radar was added in 1944.&lt;ref&gt;Stille, p. 23&lt;/ref&gt;

==Career==
''Jun'yō''{{'}}s [[keel]] was laid down by Mitsubishi on [[Slipway]] No. 3 at their [[shipyard]] in [[Nagasaki]] on 20 March 1939. She was [[yard number]] 900 and had the name ''Kashiwara Maru'' at that time. The ship was purchased on 10 February 1941 by the Navy Ministry and she was temporarily referred to as No. 1001 Ship (''Dai 1001 bankan'') to keep her conversion secret. She was [[Ship naming and launching|launched]] on 26 June 1941 and [[Ship commissioning|commissioned]] on 3 May 1942 as ''Jun'yō''.&lt;ref&gt;Lengerer &amp; Rehm-Takahara, pp. 17, 106–07&lt;/ref&gt;

Upon commissioning, the ship was assigned to the [[Fourth Carrier Division]] of the [[1st Air Fleet (Imperial Japanese Navy)|1st Air Fleet]], together with {{ship|Japanese aircraft carrier|Ryūjō||2}}, under the command of [[Rear Admiral]] [[Kakuji Kakuta]]. She was tasked to support [[Operation AL]], an attack planned to seize several [[Aleutian Islands]] to provide advance warning in case of an American attack from the Aleutians down the [[Kurile Islands]] while the main body of the American fleet was occupied defending Midway. ''Jun'yō'' carried 18 A6M2 Zeros and 18 D3As for this operation. At dawn on 3 June, she launched 9 Zeros and a dozen D3As to attack [[Battle of Dutch Harbor|Dutch Harbor]] on [[Unalaska Island]]. They had to turn back due to bad weather, although an American [[PBY Catalina]] [[reconnaissance aircraft]] was shot down by a Zero. A second airstrike was launched later in the day to attack a group of destroyers discovered by aircraft from the first attack, but they failed to find the targets. Another airstrike was launched on the following day by the two carriers that consisted of 15 Zeros, 11 D3As, and 6 B5Ns and successfully bombed Dutch Harbor. As the aircraft from ''Jun'yō'' were regrouping after the attack, they were attacked by 8 [[Curtiss P-40]] fighters that shot down 2 Zeros and a pair of D3As while losing 2 of their own. One more D3A got lost and failed to make it back to the carrier. Shortly after the aircraft were launched, the Americans attacked the carriers, but failed to inflict any damage. A [[Martin B-26 Marauder]] bomber and a PBY were shot down by Zeros, and a [[Boeing B-17 Flying Fortress]] bomber was shot down by [[flak]] during the attack.&lt;ref&gt;Brown, pp. 144–48&lt;/ref&gt;

''Jun'yō'' had initially been designated as an auxiliary aircraft carrier (''Tokusetsu kokubokan''), but following the loss of four Japanese fleet carriers in the Battle of Midway, she was redesignated as a regular carrier (''Kokubokan'') in July.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lengerer &amp; Rehm-Takahara, p. 107&quot;/&gt; Captain [[Okada Tametsugu]] assumed command on 20 July 1942. Upon arrival at [[Chuuk State|Truk]] on 9 October, together with her [[sister ship]] {{ship|Japanese aircraft carrier|Hiyō||2}}, the ship was assigned to the [[Second Carrier Division]] to begin operations against American forces in the Guadalcanal area as part of the [[3rd Fleet (Imperial Japanese Navy)|3rd Fleet]].&lt;ref name=t1&gt;Tully&lt;/ref&gt; On 15 October, the two carriers reached the vicinity of [[Malaita Island]] in the [[Solomon Islands]] and their aircraft discovered a resupply convoy for [[Guadalcanal]] that was escorted by the destroyer {{USS|Meredith|DD-434|2}}. The A6M Zeros and D3As from the sisters attacked and sank the destroyer. The next day, they found the small [[seaplane tender]], {{USS|McFarland|DD-237|2}}, in [[Lunga Roads]] offloading [[avgas]] into barges. Nine D3As attacked, blowing the ship's stern off and destroying the barge. ''McFarland'' was not sunk, but required months of repairs. The two carriers were intended to play a prominent role in the Japanese effort to retake Guadalcanal Island and were assigned to the Advance Force for this operation. Their aircraft were supposed to provide air cover for a planned Japanese night attack to retake [[Henderson Field (Guadalcanal)|Henderson Field]], and then be flown ashore.&lt;ref&gt;Brown, pp. 178–79&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:SantaCruzENearMiss.jpg|thumb|One of ''Jun'yō''{{'}}s aircraft near missing ''Enterprise'' during the Battle of the Santa Cruz Islands]]
In late October 1942, during the Guadalcanal Campaign, ''Jun'yō'' took part in the [[Battle of the Santa Cruz Islands]]. At this time, her air group consisted of eighteen Zeros, eighteen D3As and nine B5Ns. On 05:00 on 26 October 1942, she had launched fourteen Zeros and a few D3As to land at Henderson Field on Guadalcanal, which had been falsely reported by the [[Imperial Japanese Army]] as in their hands, but they were greeted by [[United States Marine Corps|Marine]] [[Grumman F4F Wildcat]]s and all were shot down. At 09:30, ''Jun'yō'' launched another air strike that attacked the carrier {{USS|Enterprise|CV-6|2}}, the [[battleship]] {{USS|South Dakota|BB-57|2}} and the [[light cruiser]] {{USS|San Juan|CL-54|2}}, scoring hits on the latter two, but inflicting little substantial damage. Three D3As and a B5N were shot down by returning [[Douglas SBD Dauntless]] dive bombers. Kakuta ordered another air strike to be launched at 14:15, using six B5Ns from the damaged {{ship|Japanese aircraft carrier|Shōkaku||2}} and nine D3As from both carriers. Shortly afterwards, more aircraft were launched to attack the American ships, including six B5Ns and six D3As which were escorted by half a dozen Zeros. All of these aircraft attacked the carrier {{USS|Hornet|CV-8|2}}, which had been badly damaged by the attacks earlier in the day. American damage control measures had been partially successful, but one torpedo hit by a B5N from ''Shōkaku'' increased her [[List (watercraft)|list]] from 7.5° to 14.5° and near-misses by the dive bombers started enough seams in her plating that her list increased to 18°. The Americans finally ordered the ship abandoned and the last wave of dive bombers hit ''Hornet'' twice more, but inflicted little further damage.&lt;ref&gt;Brown, pp. 181–86&lt;/ref&gt;

In mid-November 1942, ''Jun'yō'' was tasked to provide air cover for the convoy bringing reinforcements for the Japanese forces on Guadalcanal during the three-day-long [[Naval Battle of Guadalcanal]]. The ship had twenty-seven A6M3 Zeros, a dozen D3A2s and nine B5N2s for this task. Six of her Zeros were on [[Combat Air Patrol]] when the convoy was discovered by two SBDs from ''Enterprise'' and shot down one dive bomber after it had made its spot report. They were unable to protect the convoy against further attacks by aircraft based at Henderson Field; seven transports were sunk and the remaining four transports were damaged before the end of the day. That afternoon, ''Enterprise'' had been discovered by a searching B5N and ''Junyo'' launched an air strike with her remaining aircraft, but they failed to locate the American carrier.&lt;ref&gt;Brown, pp. 188–93&lt;/ref&gt; In December 1942 – January 1943, the carrier covered several convoys that brought reinforcements to [[Wewak]], [[New Guinea]] and her air group was based there for several days to protect the forces there before returning to Truk on 20 January. The ship then covered the evacuation of forces from Guadalcanal through early February.&lt;ref&gt;Hata, Izawa &amp; Shores, p. 141&lt;/ref&gt;

''Jun'yō'' briefly returned to Japan in February before she sailed for Truk on 22 March together with ''Hiyō''.&lt;ref name=t1/&gt; Her air group was detached to [[Rabaul]] on 2 April to participate in [[Operation I-Go]], a land-based aerial offensive against Allied bases in the Solomon Islands and New Guinea. Before returning to Truk in the middle of the month, ''Jun'yō''{{'}}s aircraft claimed to have shot down sixteen American aircraft for the loss of seven A6Ms and two D3As&lt;ref&gt;Hata, Izawa &amp; Shores, pp. 52–54&lt;/ref&gt; and they sank the destroyer {{USS|Aaron Ward|DD-483|6}}.&lt;ref name=t1/&gt; The ship's air group was deployed to [[Buin, Papua New Guinea]] on 2 July in response to the American attack on [[Rendova Island]] on 30 June. Her fighters claimed 37 victories for the loss of nine aircraft before disbanding on 1 September.&lt;ref&gt;Hata, Izawa &amp; Shores, p. 142&lt;/ref&gt; Leaving her aircraft behind, the carrier returned to Japan in late July.&lt;ref name=t1/&gt;

''Jun'yō'' ferried aircraft to [[Sumatra]] in mid-August and troops and equipment to the [[Caroline Islands]] in September and October. En route from Truk to Kure on 5 November 1943,  ''Jun'yō'' was hit off [[Bungo Suido]] by a torpedo from the submarine {{USS|Halibut|SS-232|2}}. Four men were killed, but the damage was light, other than the disabled rudder. The ship was under repair and refit until 29 February 1944 at [[Kure, Hiroshima|Kure]]. Meanwhile, her air group had been reconstituted at [[Singapore]] on 1 November with 24 Zeros, 18 D3As and 9 B5Ns.&lt;ref name=t1/&gt; The aircraft transferred to Truk on 1 December and then to [[Kavieng]] at the end of December before reaching Rabaul on 25 January 1944. Her fighters claimed 40 Allied aircraft shot down and an additional 30 probably destroyed, but the air group was virtually annihilated.&lt;ref&gt;Hata, Izawa &amp; Shores, pp. 142–43&lt;/ref&gt; The survivors were back at Truk on 20 February and the air group was disbanded.&lt;ref name=t1/&gt;

In the meantime, the Japanese Navy had restructured its carrier air groups so that one air group was assigned to one carrier division and [[Air Group 652]] was assigned to the [[2nd Carrier Division]] with ''Hiyō'', ''Jun'yō'' and ''Ryūhō'' on 1 March. The air group was last in priority to be rebuilt and only had 30 Model 21 Zeros, 13 Model 52 Zeros and four D3As on hand on 1 April of its authorized 81 fighters, 36 dive bombers and 27 torpedo bombers. The ship conducted training for her aircraft in the Inland Sea until 11 May when she sailed for [[Tawi-Tawi]] in the [[Philippines]].&lt;ref&gt;Hata, Izawa &amp; Shores, p. 235&lt;/ref&gt; The new base was closer to the oil wells in [[Borneo]] on which the Navy relied and also to the [[Palau]] and western Caroline Islands where the Japanese expected the next American attack. However, the location lacked an airfield on which to train the green pilots and American submarines were very active in the vicinity which restricted the ships to the anchorage.&lt;ref&gt;Palomar &amp; Genda, pp. 380–81&lt;/ref&gt;

===Battle of the Philippine Sea===
{{main|Battle of the Philippine Sea}}
The Japanese fleet was en route to Guimares Island in the central Philippines on 13 June, where they intended to practice carrier operations in an area better protected from submarines, when [[Vice Admiral]] [[Jisaburō Ozawa]] learned of the American attack on the [[Mariana Islands]] the previous day. Upon reaching Guimares, the fleet refuelled and sortied into the [[Philippine Sea]] where they spotted [[Task Force 58]] on 18 June. The Americans failed to locate Ozawa's ships that day and the Japanese turned south to maintain a constant distance between them and the American carriers as Ozawa had decided on launching his air strikes early the following morning. At this time, Air Group 652 consisted of 81 Zeros, 27 D3As, 9 [[Yokosuka D4Y]] &quot;Judy&quot; dive bombers and 18 [[Nakajima B6N]] &quot;Jill&quot; torpedo bombers, roughly evenly divided among the three ships. The three carriers began launching their first air strike of 26 bomb-carrying A6M2 Zeros, 16 A6M5 Zeros to escort the other aircraft and 7 B6Ns at about 09:30. Most of these aircraft were misdirected and failed to find any American ships, although a dozen persisted in their search and found one of the American task groups. A B6N, 5 bomb-carrying Zeros, and an escorting Zero were shot down by the defending fighters and no damage was inflicted on any American ships.&lt;ref&gt;Brown, pp. 252, 257–61&lt;/ref&gt;

A second air strike of 27 D3As, 9 D4Ys, 2 B6Ns and 26 escorting Zeros was launched around 11:00, accompanied by at least 18 A6Ms and B6Ns from ''Shōkaku'' and {{ship|Japanese aircraft carrier|Zuikaku||2}}. They had also been given an erroneous spot report and could not find any American ships. The 652nd aircraft headed for airfield at [[Rota (island)|Rota]] and [[Guam]] to refuel while those from the other two carriers headed back to them. A pair of Zeros and 6 D4Ys bound for Rota spotted the carriers {{USS|Wasp|CV-18|2}} and {{USS|Bunker Hill|CV-17|2}} en route and failed to inflict any damage on the American ships while losing 5 D4Ys to anti-aircraft fire. Radar had spotted those aircraft headed for Guam and they were intercepted by 41 [[Grumman F6F Hellcat]]s. Only a single A6M5, 1 D4Y and 7 D3As of the 49 Japanese aircraft survived the encounter and landed.&lt;ref&gt;Brown, pp. 261–62&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Japanese aircraft carrier Junyo.jpg|''Jun'yō'' at anchor at Sasebo, 1945|thumb|left]]
At dusk, the Japanese turned away to the northwest to regroup and to refuel and the Americans turned west to close the distance. They discovered the retiring Japanese fleet during the afternoon of the following day and Vice Admiral [[Marc Mitscher]] ordered an air strike launched.&lt;ref&gt;Brown, pp. 263–64&lt;/ref&gt; They discovered the ships of the Second Carrier Division and hit ''Jun'yō'' with two bombs near her island. The ship was not badly damaged, but the damage did stop flight operations.&lt;ref name=t1/&gt; Air Group 652 claimed seven American aircraft shot down and four more probably shot down, but lost eleven Zeros, plus another three that had to [[emergency landing|ditch]]. The air group was disbanded on 10 July with many of its remaining personnel being assigned to [[Air Group 653]].&lt;ref&gt;Hata, Izawa &amp; Shores, p. 236&lt;/ref&gt;

After repairs at Kure, ''Jun'yō'' remained in the Inland Sea without aircraft until 27 October when she was tasked to transport material to Borneo. On 3 November, she was attacked by the submarine {{USS|Pintado|SS-387|2}} near [[Makung]], but her escorting [[destroyer]], {{ship|Japanese destroyer|Akikaze||2}}, deliberately intercepted the torpedoes and sank with no survivors. On her return voyage, the ship was unsuccessfully attacked by the submarines {{USS|Barb|SS-220|2}} and {{USS|Jallao|SS-368|2}}. On 25 November, she sailed for [[Manila]] via Makung to rendezvous with the battleship {{ship|Japanese battleship|Haruna||2}} and the destroyers [[Japanese destroyer Suzutsuki|''Suzutsuki'']], [[Japanese destroyer Fuyutsuki|''Fuyutsuki'']], and [[Japanese destroyer Maki|''Maki'']]. Having loaded 200 survivors of the battleship {{ship|Japanese battleship|Musashi||2}}, ''Jun'yō'' was attacked by the submarines {{USS|Sea Devil|SS-400|2}}, {{USS|Plaice|SS-390|2}} and {{USS|Redfish|SS-395|2}} early in the morning of 9 December 1944. She was hit by three torpedoes that flooded several compartments and killed 19 men. These gave her a 10°–12° list to starboard, but she was able to proceed on one engine. She reached [[Sasebo, Nagasaki|Sasebo]] the following day and began repairs on 18 December.&lt;ref name=t1/&gt;

The repairs were abandoned in March 1945 for lack of materials and the ship was moved from the dock to Ebisu Bay, Sasebo on 1 April. Efforts to camouflage the ship began on 23 April and she was reclassified as a [[guard ship]] on 20 June. ''Jun'yō''{{'}}s armament was ordered removed on 5 August and the ship was surrendered to the Allies on 2 September. An American technical team evaluated the ship's condition on 8 October and deemed her a [[constructive total loss]]. ''Jun'yō'' was stricken from the [[Navy List]] on 30 November and scrapped between 1 June 1946 and 1 August 1947 by the Sasebo Ship Company.&lt;ref&gt;Lengerer &amp; Rehm-Takahara, p. 193&lt;/ref&gt;

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book|last=Brown|first=J. D.|title=Carrier Operations in World War II|year=2009|publisher=Naval Institute Press|location=Annapolis, Maryland|isbn=978-1-59114-108-2}}
* {{cite book|last1=Hata|first1=Ikuhiko|authorlink=Ikuhiko Hata|last2=Shores|first2=Christopher|last3=Izawa|first3=Yasuho|year=2011|title=Japanese Naval Air Force Fighter Units and Their Aces 1932–1945|publisher=Grub Street|location=London|isbn=978-1-906502-84-3|lastauthoramp=y}}
* {{cite book|last=Jentschura|first=Hansgeorg|first2=Dieter|last2=Jung|first3=Peter|last3=Mickel|year=1977|title=Warships of the Imperial Japanese Navy, 1869–1945| publisher=United States Naval Institute|location=Annapolis, Maryland|isbn=0-87021-893-X|lastauthoramp=y}}
* {{cite book|last=Lengerer|first=Hans| first2 = Tomoko|last2=Rehm-Takahara|editor=Lambert, Andrew|title=Warship IX|year=1985|publisher=Conway Maritime Press|location=London|isbn=0-85177-403-2|chapter=The Japanese Aircraft Carriers Junyo and Hiyo|pages=9–19, 105–114, 188–193|lastauthoramp=y}}
* {{cite book|last1=Polmar|first1=Norman|last2=Genda |first2=Minoru |authorlink2=Minoru Genda|title=Aircraft Carriers: A History of Carrier Aviation and Its Influence on World Events: 1909–1945|publisher=Potomac Books|location=Washington, D.C.|year=2006|volume=1|isbn=1-57488-663-0|lastauthoramp=y}}
* {{cite book|last=Silverstone|first=Paul H.|title=Directory of the World's Capital Ships|year=1984|publisher=Hippocrene Books|location=New York|isbn=0-88254-979-0}}
* {{cite book| last = Stille| first = Mark| series =New Vanguard|volume=109| year = 2005| title = Imperial Japanese Navy Aircraft Carriers 1921–1945| publisher = Osprey Publishing | location = Oxford, UK | isbn = 1-84176-853-7}}
* {{cite web|last=Tully|first=Anthony P.|year=2013|url=http://www.combinedfleet.com/junyo.htm|title=IJN Junyo: Tabular Record of Movement|work=Kido Butai|publisher=Combinedfleet.com|accessdate=23 November 2015}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book|title=Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships 1922–1946|editor1-last=Chesneau|editor1-first=Roger|publisher=Conway Maritime Press|location=Greenwich|year=1980|isbn=0-85177-146-7}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Junyō (ship, 1942)|''Jun’yō''}}
* [http://www.history.navy.mil/photos/sh-fornv/japan/japsh-j/junyo.htm US Navy photos of ''Junyo'']
* [http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/USN/rep/Midway/Midway-Interrogations.html Battle of Midway: Interrogation of Japanese Prisoners]

&lt;!-- non-breaking space to keep AWB drones from altering the space before the navbox--&gt;

{{Hiyō class aircraft carrier}}
{{December 1944 shipwrecks}}
{{Good Article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Junyo}}
[[Category:Hiyō-class aircraft carriers|Jun'yō]]
[[Category:Ships built by Mitsubishi Heavy Industries|Jun'yō]]
[[Category:1941 ships|Jun'yō]]
[[Category:World War II aircraft carriers of Japan|Jun'yō]]
[[Category:Ships of the Aleutian Islands Campaign|Jun'yō]]
[[Category:Maritime incidents in December 1944]]</text>
      <sha1>nlxizpw0dpclauu3bpvc15f3auv9lm3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
