<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Joseph Maxwell</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1220101</id>
    <revision>
      <id>712611344</id>
      <parentid>712039904</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-03-30T03:12:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cydebot</username>
        <id>1215485</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Robot - Moving category Recipients of the Military Cross and Bar to [[:Category:Recipients of the Military Cross]] per [[WP:CFD|CFD]] at [[Wikipedia:Categories for discussion/Log/2016 March 20]].</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="26268">{{for|the politician|Joseph Edward Maxwell}}
{{Use Australian English|date=September 2013}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2013}}
{{Infobox military person
|name         = Joseph Maxwell
|image        = Joseph Maxwell.jpg
|caption      = Joseph Maxwell c.1919
|birth_date   = 10 February 1896
|death_date   = {{Death date and age|1967|7|6|1896|2|10|df=yes}}
|birth_place  = [[Forest Lodge, New South Wales]]
|death_place  = [[Matraville, New South Wales]]
|nickname     =
|allegiance   = Australia
|branch       = [[Australian Army Reserve|Citizens Military Forces]] (1913–15)&lt;br/&gt;[[First Australian Imperial Force|Australian Imperial Force]] (1915–19)
|serviceyears = 1913–19&lt;br/&gt;1940
|rank         = [[Lieutenant]]
|unit         =
|commands     =
|battles      = First World War
* [[Gallipoli Campaign]]
* [[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]]
* [[Battle of the Somme]]
* [[Battle of Pozières]]
* [[Battle of Passchendaele]]
* [[Battle of Amiens (1918)|Battle of Amiens]]
* [[Battle of the Hindenburg Line]]
Second World War
|awards      = [[Victoria Cross]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Military Cross]] &amp; [[Medal bar|Bar]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Distinguished Conduct Medal]]
|relations   =
|laterwork   =
}}

'''Joseph &quot;Joe&quot; Maxwell''', [[Victoria Cross|VC]], [[Military Cross|MC]] &amp; [[Medal bar|Bar]], [[Distinguished Conduct Medal|DCM]] (10 February 1896 – 6 July 1967) was an [[List of Australian Victoria Cross recipients|Australian recipient]] of the [[Victoria Cross]], the highest decoration for gallantry &quot;in the face of the enemy&quot; that can be awarded to members of British and [[Commonwealth of Nations|Commonwealth]] armed forces. Often described as Australia's second most decorated soldier of the [[First World War]],&lt;ref name=&quot;F&amp;S&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Franki|Slatyer|2003|p=36}}&lt;/ref&gt; he enlisted in the [[First Australian Imperial Force|Australian Imperial Force]] on 8 February 1915, and served at [[Gallipoli Campaign|Gallipoli]] before being transferred to the [[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]]. In just over twelve months he was [[Officer (armed forces)|commissioned]] and decorated four times for his bravery.

An apprentice [[boilermaker]] before the war, Maxwell returned to Australia in 1919 and worked as a gardener. In 1932, he published ''Hell's Bells and Mademoiselles'', a book written in collaboration with [[Hugh Buggy]] about his war experiences. Attempting to enlist for service during the [[Second World War]], Maxwell was rejected on the grounds of his age before enlisting under an alias in [[Queensland]]; his identity was discovered, and after a short period in a training position, he sought discharge. In 1967, aged 71, he died of a heart attack.

==Early life==
Maxwell was born in the [[Sydney]] suburb of [[Forest Lodge, New South Wales]],&lt;ref name=&quot;AF&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs&quot;/&gt; on 10 February 1896 to John Maxwell, a labourer, and his wife Elizabeth, née Stokes.&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB&quot;&gt;{{Australian Dictionary of Biography|last=Howard|first=E. J. H.|year=1986|id=A100447b|title=Maxwell, Joseph (1896–1967)|accessdate=21 August 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; A member of the Senior [[Australian Army Cadets]] for three years,&lt;ref name=&quot;AIF&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aif.adfa.edu.au:8080/showPerson?key=MAXWELL/J/607|title=Joseph MAXWELL|accessdate=21 August 2008|work=The AIF Project|publisher=Australian Defence Force Academy}}&lt;/ref&gt; he worked as an apprentice boilermaker at an engineering works near [[Newcastle, New South Wales|Newcastle]] upon leaving school.&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB&quot;/&gt; For two years, he served as a member of the [[Australian Army Reserve|Citizens Military Forces]], and on 6 February 1915, he enlisted in the [[First Australian Imperial Force|Australian Imperial Force]] enticed by the prospects of better pay.&lt;ref name=&quot;F&amp;S&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AIF&quot;/&gt;

==First World War==

===Training, February 1915 to Western Front, May 1917===
Having received his initial training at Liverpool Camp,&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Gliddon|2000|p=89}}&lt;/ref&gt; Maxwell was allotted to &quot;B&quot; Company of the [[18th Battalion (Australia)|18th Battalion]] as a [[lance corporal]], and embarked for [[Egypt]] aboard HMAT ''Ceramic'' on 25 May 1915.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/cms_images/awm8/23_35_1/pdf/0336.pdf|title=18 Infantry Battalion|work=First World War Embarkation Roll|accessdate=21 August 2008|format=PDF|publisher=Australian War Memorial}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 18th Battalion trained in Egypt from mid-June until mid-August, before proceeding to [[Gallipoli]], where they landed at [[Anzac Cove]] on 22 August.&lt;ref name=&quot;18th&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.awm.gov.au/units/unit_11205.asp |title=18th Battalion|work=Australian military units |accessdate=21 August 2008|publisher=Australian War Memorial}}&lt;/ref&gt; The battalion fought its first battle on the same day, staging an attack on the Turkish-held [[Battle of Hill 60 (Gallipoli)|Hill 60]]. The engagement lasted until 29 August, with half of the battalion becoming casualties,&lt;ref name=&quot;18th&quot;/&gt; and Maxwell briefly assuming the duties of a stretcher bearer.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Macklin|2008|pp=103–104}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Maxwell served at Gallipoli with his unit until 2 December, when he was admitted to 5th Field Ambulance and evacuated from the peninsula suffering from [[jaundice]]. Admitted to 3rd Auxiliary Hospital, [[Heliopolis (Cairo suburb)|Heliopolis]], he remained there until 11 December, when he was posted to a convalescent camp at Ras el Tin. He rejoined the 18th Battalion on 5 January 1916,&lt;ref name=&quot;AIF&quot;/&gt; which had been evacuated from the Gallipoli Peninsula on 20 December the previous year and posted to Egypt.&lt;ref name=&quot;18th&quot;/&gt; On 4 February, Maxwell was admitted to the Australian Dermatological Hospital, Abbassia with [[venereal disease]]. He returned to his battalion four days before it embarked for France, and the [[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]] on 18 March.&lt;ref name=&quot;AIF&quot;/&gt;

Arriving in [[Marseilles]], France, Maxwell was admitted to 7th Australian Field Ambulance and then transferred to the 3rd Canadian General Hospital following wounds sustained during battle.&lt;ref name=&quot;AIF&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Macklin|2008|p=105}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was moved to the 1st Convalescent Depot on 2 May, and then discharged to Base Details eleven days later. He was later found guilty of breaking ranks at the 07:30 parade on the same day and being [[AWOL|absent without leave]] from 08:00 until 13:00 on 24 May; for this transgression, he was reduced to the ranks. Rejoining his battalion on 1 June,&lt;ref name=&quot;AIF&quot;/&gt; he took part in the [[Battle of Pozières]] and received a promotion to [[sergeant]] in October.&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;18th&quot;/&gt;

Suffering [[synovitis]] to his right knee, Maxwell was hospitalised for two days and posted to a training battalion in England on 28 November 1916. He stayed there for five months before embarking for France on 9 May 1917 and rejoining the 18th Battalion five days later.&lt;ref name=&quot;AIF&quot;/&gt; Maxwell was only briefly in France before being selected for officer training. Shortly after arriving in England, he attended a boisterous party with a group of soldiers. The military police raided the party and called the local police for assistance after confronting Maxwell's group. Maxwell was fined £20 and sent back to his unit for his actions.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Macklin|2008|pp=105–106}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Western Front: May 1917 to August 1918===
Maxwell was again selected for officer training, and on 5 July, he was posted to No. 6 Officers' Cadet Battalion. He was promoted to [[company sergeant major]] on 7 August, before rejoining the 18th Battalion on 11 September.&lt;ref name=&quot;AIF&quot;/&gt; Nine days later, he was engaged in action near [[Westhoek (region)|Westhoek]] during the [[Third Battle of Ypres]] when he performed the deeds that earned him the [[Distinguished Conduct Medal]].&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs&quot;/&gt; In the battle, the commander of a platoon was killed; Maxwell took command and led it into attack. Noticing that one of the newly captured positions was under heavy fire, Maxwell dashed to it and led the men to a safer and more tactically secure position, thus minimizing casualties.&lt;ref name=&quot;AF&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Staunton|2005|p=191}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/cms_images/awm28/1/102/0031.pdf|title=Recommendation for Joseph Maxwell to be awarded a Distinguished Conduct Medal|work=Recommendations: First World War|accessdate=22 August 2008|format=PDF|publisher=Australian War Memorial}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Commissioned in the field as a [[second lieutenant]] on 29 September 1917,&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs2&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Gliddon|2000|p=90}}&lt;/ref&gt; Maxwell took part in the engagements around [[Battle of Passchendaele#Battle of Poelcappelle: 9 October|Poelcappelle]], Belgium, the following month.&lt;ref name=&quot;18th&quot;/&gt; He earned promotion to [[lieutenant]] on 1 January 1918 and was admitted to the 7th Australian Field Ambulance on 10 January suffering [[scabies]]. Having been discharged from the hospital, he rejoined the 18th Battalion on 17 January.&lt;ref name=&quot;AIF&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Joseph Maxwell VC AWM P00171.001.jpg|thumb|upright|left|180px|Studio portrait of Lt. J. Maxwell]]

On 8 March 1918,&lt;ref name=&quot;MC&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/cms_images/awm28/1/103/0004.pdf|title=Recommendation for Joseph Maxwell to be awarded a Military Cross|work=Recommendations: First World War|accessdate=23 August 2008|format=PDF|publisher=Australian War Memorial}}&lt;/ref&gt; Maxwell commanded a scouting patrol that was operating to the east of [[Ploegsteert]]. Having obtained the required information, he ordered the patrol to withdraw.&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs2&quot;/&gt; He and three of his men were covering the withdrawal of the main body when he noticed about thirty Germans nearby.&lt;ref name=&quot;AF&quot;/&gt; Recalling the patrol, he led an attack against the party, which had sheltered in an old trench; the Germans quickly withdrew, leaving three dead and one wounded [[Prisoner of War|prisoner of war]].&lt;ref name=&quot;MC&quot;/&gt; Maxwell was awarded the [[Military Cross]] for his actions during this engagement, news of which was published in a supplement to the ''[[London Gazette]]'' on 13 May 1918.&lt;ref&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue=30681|date=13 May 1918|startpage=5707|supp=yes|accessdate=23 August 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Throughout the spring of 1918, the 18th Battalion was involved in operations to repel the German [[Spring Offensive|offensive]].&lt;ref name=&quot;18th&quot;/&gt; Maxwell took part in these actions until he was granted leave and went back to England on 17 July. He returned to France and rejoined the 18th Battalion on 1 August,&lt;ref name=&quot;AIF&quot;/&gt; before taking part in the [[Battle of Amiens (1918)|Battle of Amiens]] where he was to earn a [[Medal bar|Bar]] to his Military Cross. On 9 August, the battalion was preparing to attack near Rainecourt. Maxwell took command of the company after all of its other officers became casualties. Under his leadership, the company was able to attack on time, despite being subjected to heavy fire. A tank that preceded the advance immediately became the object of enemy fire and was knocked out by a 77&amp;nbsp;mm gun.&lt;ref name=&quot;AF&quot;/&gt; Maxwell, who was in close proximity, rushed over and opened the hatch, allowing the crew to escape. After escorting the tank commander to safety, Maxwell returned to lead the company in the attack, which succeeded in reaching and consolidating their objective.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.awm.gov.au/cms_images/awm28/1/115P1/0044.pdf |title=Recommendation for Joseph Maxwell to be awarded a Bar to Military Cross |work=Recommendations: First World War |accessdate=23 August 2008|format=PDF|publisher=Australian War Memorial}}&lt;/ref&gt; The award of the bar was published in a supplement to the ''London Gazette'' on 1 February 1919.&lt;ref&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue=31158|date=1 February 1919|startpage=1636|supp=yes|accessdate=23 August 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Victoria Cross, October 1918 to repatriation, August 1919===
On 3 October 1918, the [[5th Brigade (Australia)|5th Brigade]]—of which the 18th Battalion was part—became engaged in its last battle of the First World War when breaching the [[Hindenburg Line]] close to [[Beaurevoir]] and [[Montbrehain]]. While taking part in this battle, Maxwell was a member of the attacking party along the Beaurevoir-Fonsomme line when he performed the acts for which he was awarded the Victoria Cross.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Gliddon|2000|p=88}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Early in the advance, Maxwell's company commander was severely wounded, resulting in Maxwell assuming control. Reaching the German barbwire defences under intense machine-gun fire, the company suffered heavy casualties, including all of the officers except Maxwell. Pushing forward alone through a narrow passageway in the wire, Maxwell captured the most dangerous machine gun, killed three Germans and took another four as prisoners; thereby enabling the company to move through the wire and reach their objective.&lt;ref name=&quot;AF&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;VCrec&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/cms_images/awm28/2/313/0087.pdf|title=Recommendation for Joseph Maxwell to be awarded a Victoria Cross|accessdate=14 January 2009|format=PDF|work=Recommendations: First World War|publisher=Australian War Memorial}}&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly afterwards, it was noticed that the company on their left flank was held up and failing to advance. Gathering a party of men, Maxwell led the group in an attempt to attack the German force from the rear. They soon came under heavy machine gun fire, and, single-handedly, Maxwell dashed forward and attacked the foremost gun. Firing his revolver, he managed to shoot five of the crew and silence the gun.&lt;ref name=&quot;VCrec&quot;/&gt;

Later in the advance, Maxwell learnt from an English-speaking prisoner that a group of Germans in the adjacent post wished to surrender, but were afraid to give themselves up.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Gliddon|2000|pp=88–89}}&lt;/ref&gt; Accompanied by two privates and the prisoner—who was to act as an interpreter—Maxwell approached the post.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Carlyon|2006|p=721}}&lt;/ref&gt; The three Australians, however, were immediately surrounded by a group of twenty German soldiers and disarmed. They seemed set to become prisoners themselves, before an artillery barrage fell on the position. Taking advantage of the resulting confusion,&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Macklin|2008|p=109}}&lt;/ref&gt; Maxwell pulled out a concealed revolver and shot two of the Germans before escaping with his men under heavy rifle fire; one of the privates was subsequently wounded. Organising a party of men, he immediately attacked and captured the post.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/cms_images/awm28/2/313/0089.pdf|title=Recommendation for Joseph Maxwell to be awarded a Victoria Cross (cont)|accessdate=14 January 2009|format=PDF|work=Recommendations: First World War|publisher=Australian War Memorial}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The full citation for Maxwell's Victoria Cross appeared in a supplement to the ''London Gazette'' on 6 January 1919, it read:&lt;ref&gt;{{LondonGazette |issue=31108 |date=6 January 1919 |startpage=307 |supp=yes |accessdate=23 August 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|''War Office, 6th&amp;nbsp;January, 1919''

His Majesty the KING has been graciously pleased to approve of the award of the Victoria Cross to the undermentioned Officers, Non-commissioned Officers and Men: —

Lt. Joseph Maxwell, M.C., D.C.M., 18th Bn., A.I.F.

For most conspicuous bravery and leadership in attack on the Beaurevoir-Fonsomme line near Estates, North of St. Quentin, on the 3rd&amp;nbsp;October, 1918.

His company commander was severely wounded early in the advance, and Lt. Maxwell at once took charge. The enemy wire when reached under intense fire was found to be exceptionally strong and closely supported by machine guns, whereupon Lt. Maxwell pushed forward single-handed through the wire and captured the most dangerous gun, killing three and capturing four enemy. He thus enabled his company to penetrate the wire and reach the objective. Later, he again dashed forward and silenced, single-handed, a gun which was holding up a flank company. Subsequently, when with two men only he attempted to capture a strong party of the enemy, he handled a most involved situation very skilfully, and it was due to his resource that he and his comrades escaped.

Throughout the day Lt. Maxwell set a high example of personal bravery, coupled with excellent judgment and quick decision.}}

The 18th Battalion was training away from the frontline when the [[Armistice]] was declared on 11 November 1918.&lt;ref name=&quot;18th&quot;/&gt; On 8 March 1919, Maxwell was invested with his Victoria Cross by [[George V of the United Kingdom|King George V]] in the ballroom of [[Buckingham Palace]].&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs&quot;/&gt; He headed for Australia on 1 May aboard HT ''China'', disembarking at Melbourne on 8 June and proceeding to Sydney, where he was discharged from the Australian Imperial Force on 20 August.&lt;ref name=&quot;AIF&quot;/&gt;

==Later life==
Following demobilisation, Maxwell worked as a gardener in [[Canberra]], [[Moree, New South Wales|Moree]] and the [[Maitland, New South Wales|Maitland]] district.&lt;ref name=&quot;AF2&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Staunton|2005|p=193}}&lt;/ref&gt; Having described himself as a reporter, Maxwell married 19-year-old [[tailoress]] Mabel Maxwell (unrelated) in a Catholic ceremony at Bellevue Hill, Sydney on 14 February 1921. The marriage produced a daughter, Jean, before being dissolved in 1926 upon Mabel's instigation.&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Maxwell Hamilton grave P01312.003.JPG|thumb|upright|right|180px|Joseph Maxwell (left) and [[John Patrick Hamilton]] (right) visit the grave of fellow Australian VC recipient [[Lewis McGee]] in Passchendaele, Belgium.]]

On 11 November 1929, Maxwell attended the New South Wales Dinner for recipients of the Victoria Cross in Sydney, and 1932 saw the publication of ''Hell's Bells and Mademoiselles'', a book written in collaboration with [[Hugh Buggy]] about his experiences in the war. At the time, Maxwell was working as a gardener with the Department of the Interior in Canberra.&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs91&quot;/&gt; The book was a success, but Maxwell soon spent what money he made from it.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bravest&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Macklin|2008|p=110}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the late 1930s, he wrote the manuscript for a second book entitled ''From the Hindenburg Line to the Breadline''. The book was never published and the manuscript was lost when it was lent to someone to read.&lt;ref name=&quot;hindenburg&quot;&gt;{{cite news |date=1967-08-21 |title= A Maxwell Manuscript |url= https://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=1301&amp;dat=19670821&amp;id=6mopAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=EuUDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=1568,4528419&amp;hl=en |newspaper=[[The Sydney Morning Herald]] |location=Sydney, Australia |access-date=14 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1933, Maxwell acted as a defence witness in the trial of Alfred Jamieson, who was accused of housebreaking. Maxwell was Jamieson's former platoon commander and testified that Jamieson had been of good character but had been strongly affected by the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs91&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Gliddon|2000|pp=91–92}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After the outbreak of the [[Second World War]], Maxwell made several attempts to enlist, but was unsuccessful due to his age,&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB&quot;/&gt; and deteriorating health.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bravest&quot;/&gt; He eventually travelled to [[Queensland]],&lt;ref name=&quot;AF2&quot;/&gt; where he enlisted under the alias of Joseph Wells on 27 June 1940.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ww2roll.gov.au/Veteran.aspx?serviceId=A&amp;veteranId=10506 |title=Wells, Joseph (Maxwell, Joseph)|accessdate=23 August 2008|work=World War II Nominal Roll|publisher=Commonwealth of Australia}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, his identity was soon discovered and he was given a training position; dissatisfied, he took his discharge on 9 September 1940.&lt;ref name=&quot;VC92&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Gliddon|2000|pp=92}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1952, Maxwell joined the contingent of Victoria Cross recipients invited to the coronation of Queen [[Elizabeth II of the United Kingdom|Elizabeth II]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bravest&quot;/&gt; On 6 March 1956, describing himself as a journalist from [[Bondi, New South Wales|Bondi]], Maxwell married widow Anne Martin, née Burton, in Sydney.&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB&quot;/&gt; Three years later, he attended the Victoria Cross centenary celebrations in London, before later re-visiting the battlefields in France. In 1964, together with his wife, Maxwell attended the opening of the VC Corner in the [[Australian War Memorial]], Canberra. He was determined that his Victoria Cross would not wind up in the collection, believing that the award would be devalued by &quot;lumping&quot; them together.&lt;ref name=&quot;VC92&quot;/&gt;

On 6 July 1967, Maxwell collapsed and died of a heart attack in a street in his home town [[Matraville, New South Wales]]. He had been an invalid pensioner for some time. His funeral service took place with full military honours at St Mathias Anglican Church, Paddington.&lt;ref name=&quot;VC92&quot;/&gt; Having been cremated, his ashes were interred at the Eastern Suburbs Crematorium in Botany.&lt;ref name=&quot;AF2&quot;/&gt; Anne Maxwell presented her husband's medals to the Army Museum of New South Wales at [[Victoria Barracks, Sydney|Victoria Barracks]], Paddington, and subsequently the medals, together with a portrait and a brass copy of his VC citation, were unveiled by the Minister of Defence, Allan Fairhall.&lt;ref name=&quot;VC92&quot;/&gt; In 2003, Maxwell's medals were presented to the Australian War Memorial on a permanent loan basis.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.victoriacross.org.uk/bbmaxwel.htm |title=Joseph Maxwell's Victoria Cross on permanent loan to the Australian War Memorial |date=19 August 2003 |accessdate=23 August 2008 |publisher=The History of the Victoria Cross}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
* {{Cite book|last=Carlyon|first=Les|authorlink=Les Carlyon|year=2006|title=The Great War|publication-place=Sydney, New South Wales, Australia|publisher=Macmillan|isbn=978-1-4050-3761-7|ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book|last=Franki|first=George|last2=Slatyer|first2=Clyde|year=2003|title=Mad Harry: Australia's Most Decorated Soldier|publication-place=Sydney, New South Wales, Australia|publisher=Kangaroo Press|isbn=0-7318-1188-7|ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book|last=Gliddon|first=Gerald|year=2000|title=The Final Days 1918|series=[[VCs of the First World War]]|publication-place=Sparkford, England|publisher=Sutton Publishing|isbn=0-7509-2485-3|ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book|last=Macklin|first=Robert|authorlink=Robert Macklin|year=2008|title=Bravest: How Some of Australia's Greatest War Heroes Won Their Medals|publication-place=Crows Nest, New South Wales, Australia|publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin|isbn=978-1-74114-882-4|ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book|last=Staunton|first=Anthony|year=2005|title=Victoria Cross: Australia's Finest and the Battles they Fought|publication-place=Prahran, Victoria, Australia|publisher=Hardie Grant Books|isbn=1-74066-288-1|ref=harv}}

==Further reading==
* {{Cite book|last=Ramsland|first=John|year=2012|title=Venturing Into No Man's Land: The Charmed Life of Joseph Maxwell VC, World War I Hero|publication-place=Melbourne, Australia |publisher=Brolga Publishing Pty Ltd |isbn=9781-9220-36-636 |ref=rams}}

==External links==
*{{cite web|url=http://www.diggerhistory.info/pages-vc/maxwell-vc.htm|title=Maxwell VC|accessdate=11 November 2008|work=VC Recipients|publisher=Diggerhistory.info}}
*{{cite web|url=http://www.victoriacross.org.uk/ggausnsw.htm|title=New South Wales – Australia|accessdate=11 November 2008|work=VC Burials|publisher=Victoriacross.org}}
*{{cite web|url=http://users.bigpond.net.au/jbuckley/vc/#maxwell|title=MAXWELL, Lieutenant Joseph 18th Australian Infantry Battalion AIF|accessdate=21 December 2008|author=Brian Day|publisher=Blue Mountains Vietnam Veterans and Associated Forces Inc}}

&lt;div class=&quot;NavFrame collapsed&quot; style=&quot;border:none; &quot;&gt;
   &lt;div class=&quot;NavHead&quot; style=&quot;font-weight:bold; background:silver; text-align:center; &quot;&gt;
Honours and awards
   &lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;div class=&quot;NavContent&quot; style=&quot;font-weight:normal; background-color:transparent; text-align:left; &quot;&gt;
==Honours and awards==
&lt;!-- [[Joseph Maxwell#Honours and awards]] links here --&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
|bgcolor=&quot;silver&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;|Ribbon ||bgcolor=&quot;silver&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;|Description
|-
|[[File:Victoria Cross (UK) ribbon.png|80px|Ribbon for the VC]] || [[Victoria Cross]] (VC)&lt;ref group=&quot;a&quot;&gt;Victoria Cross, 'Commonwealth Gazette' No. 61, 23 May 1919. ''[London Gazette: (Supplement) no. 31108, p. 307, 6 January 1919.]'' [http://www.aif.adfa.edu.au:8080/showPerson?key=MAXWELL/J/607]. Retrieved 17 November 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|[[File:Military Cross ribbon.png|80px|Ribbon for the MC]] || [[Military Cross]] (MC)&lt;ref group=&quot;a&quot;&gt;Military Cross, 'Commonwealth Gazette' No. 165, 24 October 1918. ''[London Gazette: (Supplement) no. 30681, p. 5707, 13 May 1918].'' [http://www.aif.adfa.edu.au:8080/showPerson?key=MAXWELL/J/607]. Retrieved 17 November 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; &amp; Bar&lt;ref  group=&quot;a&quot;&gt;Bar to Military Cross, 'Commonwealth Gazette' No. 67, 3 June 1919. ''[London Gazette: (Supplement) no. 31158, p. 1636, 1 February 1919.]'' [http://www.aif.adfa.edu.au:8080/showPerson?key=MAXWELL/J/607]. Retrieved 17 November 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|[[File:DCM UK ribbon.png|80px|Ribbon for the DCM]] || [[Distinguished Conduct Medal]] (DCM)&lt;ref name=DCM group=&quot;a&quot;&gt;Distinguished Conduct Medal, 'Commonwealth Gazette' No. 95, 27 June 1918.  [http://www.aif.adfa.edu.au:8080/showPerson?key=MAXWELL/J/607]. Retrieved 17 November 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|[[File:1914-15 Star ribbon.jpg|80px|Ribbon for the 1914–15 Star]] || [[1914-15 Star]]&lt;ref name=&quot;AIF&quot; group=&quot;a&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aif.adfa.edu.au:8080/showPerson?key=MAXWELL/J/607|title=Joseph MAXWELL|accessdate=21 August 2008|author=|publisher=The AIF Project}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|[[File:BWM ribbon.jpg|80px|Ribbon for the BWM]] || [[British War Medal]]&lt;ref name=&quot;AIF&quot;  group=&quot;a&quot;/&gt;
|-
|[[File:Victory medal (UK) ribbon.png|80px|Ribbon for the Victory Medal]] || [[Victory Medal (UK)|Victory Medal]]&lt;ref name=&quot;AIF&quot;  group=&quot;a&quot;/&gt;
|}
&lt;/center&gt;
{{reflist|group=&quot;a&quot;}}

{{Good article}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Maxwell, Joseph}}
[[Category:1896 births]]
[[Category:1967 deaths]]
[[Category:Australian Army officers]]
[[Category:Australian boilermakers]]
[[Category:Australian military personnel of World War II]]
[[Category:Australian non-fiction writers]]
[[Category:Australian recipients of the Distinguished Conduct Medal]]
[[Category:Australian World War I recipients of the Victoria Cross]]
[[Category:People from New South Wales]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Military Cross]]</text>
      <sha1>nb26kptmb7s34h3ffhii5tlfxmsq4e8</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
