<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Lewis McGee</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1221771</id>
    <revision>
      <id>742065699</id>
      <parentid>718873516</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-01T13:51:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Abraham, B.S.</username>
        <id>4540583</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>year format in infobox</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16533">{{Use Australian English|date=September 2013}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2013}}
{{Infobox military person
|name= Lewis McGee
|image= Lewis McGee A02623A.JPG
|image_size= 
|alt= A slightly grainy head and shoulders portrait of a man in military uniform wearing a slouch hat. He is looking at the camera.
|caption= Lewis McGee
|nickname= 
|birth_date= {{Birth date|1888|05|13|df=yes}}
|birth_place= [[Campbell Town, Tasmania]], Australia
|death_date= {{Death date and age|1917|10|12|1888|05|13|df=yes}}
|death_place= [[Passendale|Passchendaele]], Belgium
|placeofburial= [[Tyne Cot Cemetery]]
|allegiance= Australia
|branch= [[First Australian Imperial Force|Australian Imperial Force]]
|serviceyears= 1916–17
|rank= [[Sergeant]]
|unit= [[40th Battalion (Australia)|40th Battalion]]
|commands=
|battles= First World War
* [[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]]
* [[Battle of Messines (1917)|Battle of Messines]]
* [[Battle of Passchendaele]]
* [[Battle of Broodseinde]]
|awards= [[Victoria Cross]]
|relations=
|laterwork=
}}
'''Lewis McGee''', [[Victoria Cross|VC]] (13 May 1888 – 12 October 1917) was an [[List of Australian Victoria Cross recipients|Australian recipient]] of the [[Victoria Cross]], the highest decoration for gallantry &quot;in the face of the enemy&quot; that can be awarded to members of the British and [[Commonwealth of Nations|Commonwealth]] armed forces. As a sergeant in the [[First Australian Imperial Force|Australian Imperial Force]], McGee was awarded the Victoria Cross for his actions in the [[Battle of Broodseinde]]—part of the [[Battle of Passchendaele|Passchendaele offensive]]—on 4 October 1917. As his platoon came under heavy machine gun fire from a German [[Pillbox (military)|pillbox]], McGee rushed alone across open ground towards the emplacement. Armed solely with a revolver, he shot the gunners and captured the garrison. He then organised a bombing party, and led the group in the seizure of a second machine gun post.

Born in [[Tasmania]], McGee gained employment as an [[engine driver]] with the Tasmanian Department of Railways. In March 1916, he enlisted in the Australian Imperial Force for service in the [[First World War]]. He was posted to the [[40th Battalion (Australia)|40th Battalion]], and completed training in Tasmania and the United Kingdom, where he was promoted to lance corporal. Transferring to the [[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]] in November 1916, McGee was rapidly promoted to corporal then sergeant, and took part in the [[Battle of Messines (1917)|Battle of Messines]]. He was killed in action on 12 October 1917, eight days after his Victoria Cross exploit.

==Early life==
McGee was born in [[Campbell Town, Tasmania]], on 13 May 1888, the youngest of eleven children to John McGee, a labourer and farmer, and his wife Mary (née Green).&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB&quot;&gt;{{Australian Dictionary of Biography|last=Beresford|first=Quentin|year=1986|id=A100262b|title=McGee, Lewis (1888–1917)|accessdate=12 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs171&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Snelling|2000|p=171}}&lt;/ref&gt; Three of McGee's sisters had died in infancy prior to his birth, and—when Lewis was aged only seven—his mother succumbed to [[pleurisy]]. Following his wife's death, John relocated his remaining family to a new farming property near [[Avoca, Tasmania|Avoca]].&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs171&quot;/&gt; Here, Lewis gained employment as an [[engine driver]] with the Tasmanian Department of Railways.&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AF&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Staunton|2005|p=109}}&lt;/ref&gt; He also achieved a reputation as a &quot;powerful athlete&quot;,&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs171&quot;/&gt; particularly as a cyclist with the Avoca Cycling Club. On 15 November 1914, McGee married Eileen Rose Bailey; the couple had daughter Nada the following year.&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs171&quot;/&gt;

==First World War==
On 1 March 1916, McGee enlisted in the Australian Imperial Force for service during the First World War.&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB&quot;/&gt; Allotted to the 40th Battalion as a [[Private (rank)|private]], he was initially posted for training at [[Claremont, Tasmania|Claremont]] military camp with his unit for a period of three months. He was advanced to [[lance corporal]] on 22 May. On finalising its primary training,&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs171&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AF&quot;/&gt; the 40th Battalion embarked for the United Kingdom on 1 July, with McGee aboard HMAT ''Berrima''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/cms_images/AWM8/23_57_1/PDF/0151.pdf|title=Lewis McGee|accessdate=7 August 2009|format=PDF|work=First World War Embarkation Roll|publisher=Australian War Memorial}}&lt;/ref&gt; Arriving seven weeks later,&lt;ref name=&quot;AIF&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.aif.adfa.edu.au:8080/showPerson?pid=197704|title=McGee, Lewis|accessdate=7 August 2009|work=AIF Project|publisher=Australian Defence Force Academy}}&lt;/ref&gt; the battalion was dispatched to [[Salisbury Plain]] to complete an additional period of training in preparation of its deployment to the [[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]].&lt;ref name=&quot;AF&quot;/&gt;

McGee proceeded to France, and the Western Front, with his battalion on 23 November 1916, arriving the next day.&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AIF&quot;/&gt; The unit was ultimately posted to [[Armentières]], where McGee was raised to [[corporal]] on 4 December.&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs171&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AF&quot;/&gt; Five days after his promotion, the 40th Battalion was moved into the frontline, occupying a set of trenches just south of [[Lys, Pyrénées-Atlantiques|Lys]]. Over subsequent engagements, McGee gained a reputation as a &quot;natural soldier&quot;, which consequently led to his promotion to [[sergeant]] on 12 January 1917.&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs171&quot;/&gt; The 40th Battalion undertook various small-scale operations and raids throughout this period until June, when it fought in the [[Battle of Messines (1917)|Battle of Messines]]. This was followed by a period in reserve behind the lines, before the battalion was shipped to Belgium in preparation for its service in the [[Battle of Passchendaele|Passchendaele offensive]].&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs172&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Snelling|2000|p=172}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;40th&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/units/unit_11227.asp|title=40th Battalion|accessdate=5 October 2009|work=Australian military units|publisher=Australian War Memorial}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Victoria Cross===
As part of the third phase of the Passchendaele offensive, the 10th Australian Brigade—of which McGee's 40th Battalion was part—was detailed to execute an attack on [[Battle of Broodseinde|Broodseinde Ridge]]. The brigade was allocated four primary objectives to seize during the assault, one for each battalion, with the 40th Battalion to take the final target located on the ridge itself. The advance commenced at the predetermined time of 06:00 on 4 October 1917, under the cover of an artillery barrage.&lt;ref name=&quot;AF&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Snelling|2000|p=167}}&lt;/ref&gt; The first three battalions were able to seize their objectives, though the fighting intensified with each stage. As the 40th Battalion set to advance towards the final objective, its progress became hampered by increasingly heavy machine-gun and rifle fire, as well as by barbed wire entanglements and sectors of impassable swamp.&lt;ref name=&quot;AF&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs169&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Snelling|2000|p=169}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Lewis McGee VC and family.JPG|thumb|alt=Black and white photograph of a seated man in military uniform holding a baby dressed in a white, flowing gown, with a woman sitting next to him. The woman has her arm around the man's back.|left|250px|Lewis McGee with his wife Eileen and baby daughter Nada in 1916.]]

With McGee's B Company heading the 40th Battalion's advance, the unit was able to progress to a point approximately {{convert|270|m|yd}} in front of the crest, where it was confronted by a thick line of barbed wire and another bog, while simultaneously subject to the fire of ten machine guns in trenches and heavily defended [[Bunker#Pillbox|pillbox]]es. The men of B Company struggled to within {{convert|90|m|yd}} of the battalion's objective, when the severe fire of the German machine guns pinned them down in shellholes.&lt;ref name=&quot;AF&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs169&quot;/&gt;

McGee's platoon was suffering heavy casualties from a particular machine gun {{convert|50|m|yd}} in front of his position, which was set in a recess atop a concrete pillbox and firing directly at his men.&lt;ref name=&quot;AF&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs169&quot;/&gt; Armed solely with a revolver, McGee dashed alone towards the post across the fire-swept ground. Shooting the gunners, he captured the remaining soldiers in the garrison as [[Prisoner of war|prisoners]] and seized control of the pillbox.&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/cms_images/AWM28/1/148P1/0094.pdf|title=Recommendation for Lewis McGee to be awarded a Victoria Cross|accessdate=6 October 2009|format=PDF|work=Recommendations: First World War|publisher=Australian War Memorial}}&lt;/ref&gt; On returning to his unit, he reorganised his men and led a bombing party in the capture of a second machine-gun post.&lt;ref name=&quot;OffHist&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Bean|1941|p=865}}&lt;/ref&gt; McGee's actions reignited the 40th Battalion's advance, with McGee himself &quot;foremost in the remainder&quot; of the action.&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;LGVC&quot;&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue=30400|date=26 November 1917|startpage=12328|supp=yes|accessdate=6 October 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; By 09:12 on 5 October,&lt;ref name=&quot;AF&quot;/&gt; the 40th Battalion had seized its objective and held complete control of the Broodseinde Ridge, having captured 300 Germans as prisoners in the process.&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs169&quot;/&gt;

As a result of his actions at Broodseinde, McGee was awarded the Victoria Cross, one of two Australians to be so decorated that day.&lt;ref name=&quot;LGVC&quot;/&gt; However, he never saw the announcement of the award. On 12 October 1917—eight days after McGee's Victoria Cross action—the 40th Battalion returned to the frontline, in an attempt to exploit the success of the previous week.&lt;ref name=&quot;AF&quot;/&gt; The battlefield was drenched in rain, turning the ground into a [[Bog|quagmire]] that was additionally dominated by several German pillboxes. McGee—who had been appointed acting [[company sergeant major]] of B Company that morning—led his unit into the attack. As the men of the company advanced forward, a machine gun began firing upon them from the front, before a second opened up on their flank. Men ran to take cover in shellholes as the German fire inflicted several casualties. McGee, however, made a rush towards the guns in an apparent effort to silence them. As he ran towards the pillbox, a bullet struck him in the head, killing him instantly.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Snelling|2000|pp=170–171}}&lt;/ref&gt; McGee was later buried in [[Tyne Cot Cemetery]];&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cwgc.org/search/casualty_details.aspx?casualty=463754|title=McGee, Lewis|accessdate=7 October 2009|work=Casualty Details|publisher=Commonwealth War Graves Commission}}&lt;/ref&gt; he was one of 248 members of the 40th Battalion killed or wounded during the Battle of Passchendaele.&lt;ref name=&quot;40th&quot;/&gt; McGee's fellow Australian Victoria Cross recipient from Broodseinde, Lance Corporal [[Walter Peeler]], was also severely wounded on this day, receiving a bullet wound to his arm.&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs171&quot;/&gt;

==Legacy==
[[File:Maxwell Hamilton grave P01312.003.JPG|thumb|alt=Photograph of two men in suits standing over to the left gazing at a grave marker. Several other graves and a structure are in the background.|upright|right|175px|[[Joseph Maxwell]] (left) and [[John Patrick Hamilton]] (right) visit the grave of fellow Australian Victoria Cross recipient Lewis McGee in Passchendaele, Belgium c. 1956.]]

The announcement and accompanying citation for McGee's Victoria Cross was promulgated in a supplement to the ''[[London Gazette]]'' on 26 November 1917, reading:&lt;ref name=&quot;LGVC&quot;/&gt;

{{quote|''War Office, 26th November, 1917.''

His Majesty the KING has been graciously pleased to approve of the award of the Victoria Cross to the undermentioned Officer, Non-commissioned Officers and Men: —

No. 456 Sjt. Lewis McGee, late Aus. Imp. Force.

For most conspicuous bravery when in the advance to the final objective, Sjt. McGee led his platoon with great dash and bravery, though strongly opposed, and under heavy shell fire.

His platoon was suffering severely and the advance of the Company was stopped by machine gun fire from a &quot;Pill-box&quot; post. Single-handed Sjt. McGee rushed the post armed only with a revolver. He shot some of the crew and captured the rest, and thus enabled the advance to proceed. He reorganised the remnants of his platoon and was foremost in the remainder of the advance, and during consolidation of the position he did splendid work.

This Non-commissioned Officer's coolness and bravery were conspicuous and contributed largely to the success of the Company's operations.

Sjt. McGee was subsequently killed in action.}}

[[File:VCLewisMcGeeGrave.jpg|thumb|alt=A military gravestone marker.|left|150px|Lewis McGee's grave in [[Tyne Cot Cemetery]], Belgium.]]

McGee's wife, Eileen, was presented with her late husband's Victoria Cross by the [[Governor-General of Australia]], [[Ronald Munro Ferguson, 1st Viscount Novar|Sir Ronald Munro Ferguson]], at an investiture ceremony in [[Launceston, Tasmania|Launceston's]] [[York Park]] during October 1918. Additionally, Eileen McGee was later gifted an [[Iron Cross]] that her husband had captured from a German officer at Broodseinde, which was enclosed in a letter of condolence written to her by an officer of the 40th Battalion.&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs172&quot;/&gt;

Prior to his Victoria Cross action, McGee had been noted in the 40th Battalion for his leadership qualities, and had attained a &quot;famous fighting record&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;OffHist&quot;/&gt; In addition to his decoration, McGee had been recommended for a [[Officer (armed forces)|commission]] as a result of his actions at Broodseinde, with an officer in his battalion declaring &quot;had he lived his commission would have been assured&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs172&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;OffHist&quot;/&gt; His original company commander, Major Leslie Payne, noted McGee's &quot;sterling qualities as a leader&quot; and stated: &quot;His ability in the carrying out of certain important tasks early in the year was most marked and&amp;nbsp;...&amp;nbsp;there is in my opinion, and the opinion of many others, no more gallant and capable non-commissioned officer in the battalion.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs172&quot;/&gt;

McGee is commemorated on a war [[cenotaph]] located in [[Ross, Tasmania]], and his name was given to the McGee Soldiers' Club at [[Anglesea Barracks|Anglesea Army Barracks]], Tasmania, which was opened in 1956. During the 150th anniversary celebrations of the town of Avoca in March 1984, the [[Governor of Tasmania]], [[James Plimsoll|Sir James Plimsoll]], unveiled a memorial plaque on the Returned Serviceman's League cenotaph honouring McGee; his widow and their daughter attended the ceremony. McGee's Victoria Cross and other medals are held in the collections of the [[Queen Victoria Museum and Art Gallery]], Tasmania.&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs172&quot;/&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
* {{cite book|last=Bean|first=Charles|authorlink=Charles Bean|year=1941|origyear=1933|title=The Australian Imperial Force in France, 1917|edition=11th|series=Official History of Australia in the War of 1914–1918|volume=Volume IV|publisher=Australian War Memorial|location=Canberra, Australian Capital Territory|url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1069753/|oclc=17648490|ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book|last=Snelling|first=Stephen|year=2000|title=Passchendaele 1917|series=[[VCs of the First World War]]|publication-place=Great Britain|publisher=Sutton Publishing|isbn=0-905778-60-X|ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book|last=Staunton|first=Anthony|year=2005|title=Victoria Cross: Australia's Finest and the Battles They Fought|publication-place=Prahan, Victoria, Australia|publisher=Hardie Grant Books|isbn=1-74066-288-1|ref=harv}}

==External links==
* {{cite web|url=http://recordsearch.naa.gov.au/scripts/imagine.asp?B=1943989&amp;I=1&amp;SE=1|title=Digitised copy of Lewis McGee's service record|publisher=[[National Archives of Australia]]|accessdate=20 October 2009}}
* {{cite web|url=http://www.diggerhistory.info/pages-vc/mcgee-vc.htm|title=McGee VC|accessdate=8 July 2009|work=VC Recipients|publisher=Diggerhistory.info}}

{{Good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:McGee, Lewis}}
[[Category:1888 births]]
[[Category:1917 deaths]]
[[Category:Australian Army soldiers]]
[[Category:Australian military personnel killed in World War I]]
[[Category:Australian World War I recipients of the Victoria Cross]]
[[Category:People from Tasmania]]</text>
      <sha1>2n6kgjor8ntz8jqoz5dymnb5qubin14</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
