<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Lexington-class battlecruiser</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>23977292</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748764182</id>
      <parentid>744781502</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-10T06:48:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AustralianRupert</username>
        <id>8731061</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>fix mark up...article doesn't seem to use sfn; if I got this wrong, please simply revert</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="58585">{{about|the original battlecruiser class|the two ships that were converted to aircraft carriers|Lexington-class aircraft carrier}}
{|{{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
|Ship image=[[File:H41961.jpg|300px|alt=Painting of a dark ship with two funnels and two cage masts steaming through heavy seas]]
|Ship caption=A 1922 painting by Louise Larned depicting the definitive design of the ''Lexington'' class, with eight 16-inch (406 mm)/50 cal guns and two [[Chimney|funnels]]
}}
{{Infobox ship class overview
|Builders=[[Fore River Shipbuilding]], [[New York Shipbuilding]] and [[Northrop Grumman Shipbuilding|Newport News Shipbuilding and Drydock Company]]
|Operators={{navy|USA}}
|Class before=None
|Class after={{sclass-|Alaska|cruiser|4}}
|Built range=
|Total ships planned=6
|Total ships completed=0, though 2 were converted to [[aircraft carrier]]s
|Total ships cancelled=6
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
|Hide header=
|Header caption=
|Ship type=[[Battlecruiser]]
|Ship displacement=*{{convert|43500|LT|t|lk=in}}
*{{convert|44638|LT|t}} [[deep load]]
|Ship length={{convert|874|ft|m|1|abbr=on}} overall
|Ship beam={{convert|105|ft|4|in|m|1|abbr=on}}
|Ship power=*{{convert|180000|shp|lk=in|abbr=on}}
*16 [[water-tube boiler]]s
|Ship draft={{convert|31|ft|m|1|abbr=on}}
|Ship propulsion=*four shafts
*[[Turbo-electric]] drive
|Ship speed={{convert|33|kn|lk=in}}
|Ship range={{convert|10000|nmi|lk=in|abbr=on}} at {{convert|10|kn}}
|Ship complement=1297 (1326 as flagship)
|Ship armament=*4 × 2 – {{convert|16|in|mm|0|adj=on}} guns
*14 × 1 – {{convert|6|in|mm|0|adj=on}} guns
*4 (later 8) × 1 – {{convert|3|in|mm|0|adj=on}} [[AA gun]]s
*8 × {{convert|21|in|mm|0|adj=on}} [[torpedo tube]]s

| Ship armor =*[[Belt armor|Belt]]: {{convert|5|-|7|in|abbr=on|0}}
*[[Barbette]]s: {{convert|5|-|9|in|abbr=on|0}}
*[[Gun turret#Warships|Turret]] face: {{convert|11|in|abbr=on|0}}
*Turret sides: {{convert|6|in|abbr=on|0}}
*[[Conning tower]]: {{convert|12|in|abbr=on|0}}
*[[Deck (ship)|Deck]]: {{convert|1.5|-|2.25|in|mm|0|abbr=on}}

|Ship notes=
}}
|}

The '''''Lexington''-class battlecruisers''' were officially the only [[ship class|class]] of [[battlecruiser]] to ever be ordered by the [[United States Navy]].{{refn|The ''Lexington'' class were the only [[ship class|class]] of U.S. Navy ships to be officially designated to as battlecruisers. The World War II-era {{sclass-|Alaska|cruiser|4}}, were officially classified as &quot;large cruisers&quot;, although some modern historians have classified them as battlecruisers. The design of the ''Alaska''s owed little to the ''Lexington'' class or other true battlecruisers, instead using a scaled-up {{sclass-|Baltimore|heavy cruiser}} with the machinery of an {{sclass-|Essex|aircraft carrier}}.&lt;ref&gt;Gardiner and Cheasneau (1980), p. 122; Scarpaci (2008), p. 17&lt;/ref&gt;|group=A}} While these six vessels were requested in 1911 as a reaction to the building by Japan of the {{sclass-|Kongō|battlecruiser|4}}, the potential use for them in the U.S. Navy came from a series of studies by the [[Naval War College]] which stretched over several years and predated the existence of the first battlecruiser, {{HMS|Invincible|1907|6}} (a series of proposed battlecruiser designs was in fact submitted to the [[General Board of the United States Navy|General Board]] in 1909 but was not approved for construction). The fact they were not approved by Congress at the time of their initial request was due to political, not military considerations.

The ''Lexington''s were included as part of the [[Naval Act of 1916]]. Like the {{sclass-|South Dakota|battleship (1920)|0}} [[battleship]]s also included in the 1916 Act, their construction was repeatedly postponed in favor of escort ships and anti-submarine vessels. During these delays, the class was redesigned several times; they were originally designed to mount ten [[14&quot;/50 caliber gun|14-inch guns]] and eighteen [[5&quot;/51 caliber gun|five-inch guns]] on a hull with a maximum speed of {{convert|35|kn|lk=in}}, but by the time of the definitive design, these specifications had been altered to eight [[16&quot;/50 caliber Mark 2 gun|16-inch guns]] and sixteen [[6&quot;/53 caliber gun|six-inch guns]], with a speed of {{convert|33.25|kn}} to improve hitting power and armor (the decrease in speed was mostly attributed to the additions of armor).

The design challenges the Navy's [[Bureau of Construction and Repair]] (C&amp;R) faced with this class were considerable, as the combined requirements of optimum hitting power, extreme speed and adequate protection taxed the knowledge of its naval architects and the technology of the time. The desired speed of 35&amp;nbsp;knots had been attained previously only in [[destroyer]]s and smaller craft. To do so with a capital ship required a hull and a power plant of unprecedented size for a U.S. naval vessel and careful planning on the part of its designers to ensure it would have enough longitudinal strength to withstand bending forces underway and the added stresses on its structure associated with combat. Even so, it took years between initial and final designs for engine and boiler technology to provide a plant of sufficient power that was also compact enough to allow a practical degree of protection, even in such large ships.

While four of the ships were eventually canceled and scrapped on their building ways in 1922 to comply with the [[Washington Naval Treaty]], two, ({{USS|Lexington|CV-2|2}} and {{USS|Saratoga|CV-3|2}}) were converted into the United States' first [[fleet carrier]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Friedman43&quot;/&gt;{{refn|The U.S. Navy's first aircraft carrier was {{USS|Langley|CV-1|2}}, but she was never more than an experimental ship because she was too slow—at a top speed of {{convert|15.5|kn}}, she was not able to keep pace with any escorts including the slow battleships.&lt;ref&gt;Friedman (1983), p. 37; Gardiner and Gray, pp. 120–121; and the DANFS entry on [http://hazegray.org/danfs/auxil/ac3.htm ''Langley'']&lt;/ref&gt;|group=A}} Both saw extensive action in World War II, with ''Lexington'' conducting a number of raids before being sunk during the [[Battle of Coral Sea]] and ''Saratoga'' serving in multiple campaigns in the Pacific and the Indian Ocean. Though she was hit by torpedoes on two different occasions, ''Saratoga'' survived the war only to be sunk as a [[target ship]] during [[Operation Crossroads]].{{refn|For more information, see the entries for ''Saratoga'' and ''Lexington'' in the ''[[Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships]]'': [http://hazegray.org/danfs/carriers/cv2.htm &quot;''Lexington''&quot;] and [http://hazegray.org/danfs/carriers/cv3.htm &quot;''Saratoga''&quot;]|group=A}}

==Background==

===Armor or speed===
As early as 1903, questions arose in the [[Naval War College]] (NWC)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usnwc.edu/About.aspx |title=U.S. Naval War College: About|publisher= U.S. Naval War College|accessdate=6 May 2012}} Located in [[Newport, Rhode Island]], the Naval War College (NWC) is the education and research institution of the [[United States Navy]] that specializes in developing ideas for [[naval warfare]] and passing them along to officers of the Navy&lt;/ref&gt; about the overall effectiveness of large [[armored cruiser]]s such as the {{sclass-|Pennsylvania|cruiser|5}}- and {{sclass-|Tennessee|cruiser|0}} vessels just then coming into service. The NWC's 1903 annual summer conference report, which included a staff memorandum on all-big-gun capital ships, also suggested a new type of cruiser that would be armed and armored much like a battleship. The following year, the summer conference considered tactics for a ship armed with four {{convert|12|in|mm|adj=on|0}}, twenty-two {{convert|3|in|mm|adj=on}} guns, four submerged torpedo tubes and battleship-type protection. Ships such as these were essentially ''Tennessee''-class ships in which the {{convert|6|in|mm|adj=on}} intermediate battery had been traded for heavier main guns and protection. These ships figured in the college's studies for several years, and its 1906 summer conference report on a US building program strongly advocated the ships' construction for use in scouting and as fast wings in a fleet action, and for their resistance to 12-inch gunfire (much greater than the ''Tennessee'' class). Although the [[General Board of the United States Navy|General Board]] and the [[United States Secretary of the Navy|Secretary of the Navy]] refused to adopt the proposed new armored cruiser, perhaps because the Navy already had 10 new armored cruisers on hand, the college continued to test the design against a variety of foreign vessels, including the British {{sclass-|Invincible|battlecruiser}}.&lt;ref&gt;Friedman (1984), p. 61&lt;/ref&gt;

By 1908, the summer conference had come to favor battlecruisers over armored cruisers. The increasing range of [[torpedo]]es and the distances at which future gun battles were expected to be fought seemed to favor speed over armor. Gunnery officers &quot;laid great stress upon the value of getting the range first and then smothering, or beating down, the enemy's fire before he gets the range.&quot; The conference concluded that battlecruisers would be worth building, with the caveat that they be considered in the same category as armored cruisers, in support of the battle fleet but not to fight in the line with fully armored battleships. A majority report recommended a top speed of at least 20 percent above that of battleships. As U.S. battleships then being built were expected to steam at {{convert|21|kn|lk=in}}, this meant a minimum speed for battlecruisers of {{convert|25.4|kn}}. The [[Bureau of Construction and Repair]] (C&amp;R) sketched out such ships the following year, at the request of the Secretary of the Navy, as fast equivalents of the {{sclass-|Wyoming|battleship|0}} ships being considered. By adopting a {{convert|670|ft|m|adj=on|0}} hull on a displacement of {{convert|26000|LT|t|0}}, it could produce a vessel that could travel at {{convert|25.5|kn}} and carry eight 50-[[caliber (artillery)|caliber]] 12-inch guns in four twin turrets and equivalent armor; the savings in weight from eliminating two of the ''Wyoming''s{{'}} six turrets more than balanced the added length and height of the armor belt. An enlarged belt was required by a deeper hull, as all American battlecruiser studies required deep hulls to retain their girder strength because those hulls had to be abnormally long to attain their speed. If the armor belt were reduced by an average of three inches, a fifth turret could be added. Four intermediate proposals included one with intermediate armor and eight 12-inch guns and one with ''Wyoming'' armor and six 12-inch guns. None of these designs included [[superfire|superfiring]] turrets. The General Board retained these sketches but did not recommend construction.&lt;ref&gt;Friedman (1984), pp. 61–2&lt;/ref&gt;

===Pacific developments===
As the NWC continued its studies, the [[Imperial Japanese Navy]] (IJN) annihilated the Russian Baltic Fleet at the [[Battle of Tsushima]] in 1905. Japan had already been a concern of the U.S. Navy. Strategist and Admiral [[Alfred Thayer Mahan]] had warned then-Assistant Secretary of the Navy [[Theodore Roosevelt]] in 1897 of a much greater likelihood of conflict in the Pacific than in the Atlantic. Roosevelt himself, as President of the United States, had written before Tsushima to British diplomat [[Cecil Spring Rice]], &quot;The Japs interest me and I like them. I am perfectly well aware that if they win out it may possibly mean a struggle between them and us in the future.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Cooper (2009), p. 208&lt;/ref&gt; Tsushima sealed the outcome of the [[Russo-Japanese War]] in Japan's favor, signaled its emergence as a world power and began a period of rivalry with the United States over intentions in the Pacific theater, as the two now became the dominant military powers there.&lt;ref&gt;O'Brien (2007) pp. 28–9&lt;/ref&gt; An immediate consequence was the four {{sclass-|Tsukuba|cruiser|0}} armored cruisers, laid down between 1905 and 1908. These ships were designed to carry four {{convert|12|in|mm|adj=on|0}} guns, a size generally allocated to capital ships and unprecedented for armored cruisers. They would be protected with {{convert|8|in|mm|adj=off|0}} of belt and turret armour and {{convert|3|in|mm|adj=off|0}} of deck armour and be capable of a speed of 20.5 knots. The ''Tsukuba''s were intended to take the place of aging battleships and thus showed Japan's intention of continuing to use armored cruisers in fleet engagements. They were also exactly the type of ships for which the college had argued unsuccessfully to add to the U.S. Navy before switching to battlecruisers.&lt;ref&gt;Burr (2008) pp. 22, 24&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Osborne (2004), p. 73&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Perras (2003), p. 8&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Japanese battleship Kongo.jpg|thumb|left|IJN battlecruiser {{ship|Japanese battleship|Kongō||2}}, for which the ''Lexington'' class was to be a response]]
Therefore, while the Navy did not react as Germany and Britain built increasing numbers of battlecruisers, it took a very different tack when Japan laid down its first ship of this class, {{ship|Japanese battleship|Kongō||2}}, in Britain on 17 January 1911. On 13 June, U.S. Naval Intelligence confirmed she was to be the first of four ships, the other three to be built in Japan, which would form a fast division for the IJN. The following day, the Secretary of the Navy asked the General Board to consider the construction of American battlecruisers for Pacific service, as the ''Pennsylvania''s and ''Tennessee''s would no longer be viable units in the face of such opposition. The General Board, not willing to forego battleship construction in favor of auxiliary types such as battlecruisers, balked. On 29 August, it suggested that C&amp;R research a ship under 30,000 tons that could steam at {{convert|29|kn|km/h}}, carry eight {{convert|14|in|mm|adj=on}} and twenty-four {{convert|5|in|mm|adj=on}} guns and have a protective system comparable to the {{sclass-|Nevada|battleship|1}}s. In other words, the board requested an American version of the ''Kongō''.&lt;ref&gt;Friedman (1984), p. 62&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Morison70&gt;Morison and [[Norman Polmar|Polmar]] (2003), p. 70&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=A&gt;The ''Kongō''s would be cited a second time, almost 30 years later and this time by the General Board, as reason to build the {{sclass-|Iowa|battleship|0}} fast battleships (Friedman (1985), p. 307).&lt;/ref&gt;

In view of the board's lack of urgency, C&amp;R took nearly a year to research this project. The proposed main battery of eight 14-inch guns was kept constant while other factors were calculated—speeds of 26, 29 and 32 knots; operating ranges of 5000, 7000 and 8000 miles; and belt armor of 8, 11 and 14 inches. On 12 July 1912, Naval Constructor R.H. Robinson presented these studies at a lecture he gave at the Naval War College with the General Board in attendance. There, he emphasized 8 inches as an absolute minimum for armor protection and recommended a radius of 8000 miles, the same as in U.S. battleships. The General Board's reaction was to request two battlecruisers for the 1914 Naval Building Program and ask C&amp;R for a slightly modified version of the proposed ship, but the Naval War College felt the design had serious problems and that a fast battleship would be a more practical option.&lt;ref&gt;Friedman (1984), pp. 62–4&lt;/ref&gt;

There was also the political climate to consider—and the weather was not good for battlecruisers. Just as it was thought that Congress would not approve any battlecruisers without reducing the number of [[battleship]]s, the Navy decided that battleships, such as the new &quot;[[super-dreadnought]]&quot; {{sclass-|Nevada|battleship|4}} whose construction had just begun, were more important since Congress—in the Navy's eyes—was not approving enough battleships.&lt;ref name=&quot;Conway's 119&quot;&gt;Gardiner and Gray (1984), p. 119&lt;/ref&gt; In 1903 the [[General Board]] assumed that the U.S. would build two battleships per year, but Congress &quot;balked&quot;, approving just one ship in 1904 ([[fiscal year]] 1905), two ships in 1905 (FY 1906), one ship in both 1906 and 1907 (FY 1907–1908), and one ship in both 1912 and 1913 (FY 1913–1914). The approval of two {{sclass-|New York|battleship|0}} ships in 1910 (FY 1911) instead of just one was apparently &quot;something of a personal triumph for Secretary of the Navy [[George von Lengerke Meyer|von Lengerke Meyer]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Friedman (1985), p. 101&lt;/ref&gt;

Five years later—with the [[First World War]] raging in Europe—the political climate had changed. A tentative five-year program put together in October and supported by President [[Woodrow Wilson]] called for ten battleships, six battlecruisers and ten destroyers to be completed by 1922. This was submitted to [[United States Congress|Congress]] in December 1915. On 2 June 1916, the [[United States House of Representatives|House of Representatives]] passed the bill in a modified form, replacing five of the battleships with battlecruisers. On 29 August 1916, the [[United States Senate|Senate]] also passed an altered bill, keeping the original number of ships but stipulating that the program be completed in three years (FY 1917–19). The first four ships were paid for in FY 1917, the fifth in FY 1918, and the last in FY 1919.&lt;ref&gt;Friedman, ''U.S. Cruisers'', pp. 71–72&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''Lexington''s, along with the {{sclass-|Omaha|cruiser|5}} and {{sclass-|Wickes|destroyer|4}}es, were intended to be part of a 35-knot (40&amp;nbsp;mph) scouting force that would support a large [[:wikt:battle fleet|battle fleet]], but the battlecruisers' [[keel laying]] was delayed; capital ship construction had been suspended in favor of needed merchant ships and [[anti-submarine warfare]] destroyers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Conway's 119&quot;/&gt;

The six ''Lexington''-class ships were named ''Lexington'', ''Constellation'', ''Saratoga'', ''Ranger'', ''Constitution'', and ''United States'' and were designated CC-1 through CC-6,&lt;ref group=A&gt;This would be similar to the U.S.'s use of &quot;BB&quot; for [[battleship]]s and &quot;CV&quot; for [[aircraft carrier]]s, among many other designations. See [[Hull classification symbol]].&lt;/ref&gt; with &quot;CC&quot; signifying their status as battlecruisers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Conway's 119&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref group=A&gt;The designation &quot;CC&quot; was later revived for the &quot;[[command ship]]&quot; {{USS|Northampton|CLC-1}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Although the class was planned to be the U.S.'s first battlecruisers, it was not of a new design; instead, it expanded upon already-existing 10,000–14,000&amp;nbsp;ton cruiser designs.&lt;ref name=Morison70/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Conway's 119&quot;/&gt;

==Design development==
In their original 1916 configuration, the battlecruisers were to carry ten [[14&quot;/50 caliber gun]]s in four turrets, with two triple [[Superfire|superfiring]] over two dual because there was not enough beam to accommodate the larger [[barbette]]s of the triple turrets slight further forward and aft.&lt;ref name=Friedman86&gt;Friedman (1984), p. 86&lt;/ref&gt; They would have a secondary armament of eighteen 5&quot;/51 caliber guns on a displacement of {{convert|34300|LT|t|lk=in}} and steam at 35 knots. All of these specifications were tempered by their sparse armor compared with contemporary battleships. C&amp;R estimated 180,000&amp;nbsp;[[shaft horsepower|shaft&amp;nbsp;horsepower]] would be needed to obtain this planned speed. This would require 24 boilers, which became problematic, as there was not enough room for the boilers under the armored deck in such a long, comparatively narrow hull. The solution decided upon was to place half of the boilers above the deck on the centerline with armored boxes fitted around each one. There was also the challenge of the many exhaust uptakes needed. The ''Lexington''s were given &quot;no less than&quot; seven funnels, four of them side-by-side.&lt;ref name=Morison70/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Conway's 119&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;USN Ship Types&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.history.navy.mil/photos/usnshtp/bb/cc1.htm |title=Lexington Class (CC-1 through CC-6) |accessdate=8 December 2008 |date=26 February 2004 |work= |publisher=[[United States Department of the Navy|Navy Department]], [[Naval Historical Center]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Lexington original configuration edited.jpg|thumb|left|A painting of the ''Lexington'' class' original planned configuration|alt=A long, dark ship seen from the side with five small, thin funnels visible]]
[[File:Lexington class battlecruiser2.jpg|thumb|left|A painting that depicts the ''Lexington'' class' definitive design, 1919|alt=A long, dark ship with two large funnels steaming at sea]]

Also, with such a long, narrow hull came a consequent penchant for bending, which led to the challenge of adequate hull strength, especially [[Strength of ships#Primary hull loads, strength, and bending|longitudinal strength]]. This challenge was complicated in a capital ship by the heavy weight of main turrets and guns. This was an area in which British battlecruisers were notably deficient. Structural members on HMS ''Invincible'' were so weak that her [[double bottom|double-bottom]] [[Frame (nautical)|frame]]s distorted. {{HMS|Renown|1916|6}} had to go into [[drydock]] immediately following her preliminary gunnery tests because the hull structure could not withstand the bending stresses from firing her forward main guns. When the &quot;large light cruiser&quot; {{HMS|Courageous|50|6}} weathered a heavy gale during her initial trial run, a number of her outer hull plates were so distorted that they had to be removed, sent back to the foundry and renewed.&lt;ref&gt;Breyer, pp. 116, 136, 162; Friedman (1984), pp. 62, 86&lt;/ref&gt;

In the ''Lexington''s longitudinal strength was challenged further by the large amount of [[freeboard (nautical)|freeboard]] required at the forward section of the hull to keep the ships dry and maintain a high speed in various types of weather. Also, while the {{convert|8|in|mm}} of belt armor being considered was not an impressive amount in itself, the belt's running potentially along 80 percent of the waterline and covering the entire side amidships made the amount of armor protection impressive by European standards. Because of the difference in [[ultimate tensile strength]] between armor steel and hull steel, severe stresses on the hull were expected. These factors plus the ships' unusual length prompted Naval Constructor R. H. Robinson, who led the design group for the ''Lexington''s, to make careful analyses of strength, buoyancy and stresses expected in service. For instance, designers assumed customarily that a ship needed to withstand stresses caused by a wave of the ship's length with a ratio of height to length of 1:20. Robinson found a more reasonable ratio at 1:26 for the ''Lexington''s, which also promised considerable savings in weight.&lt;ref name=&quot;Friedman 1984, pp. 63, 86&quot;&gt;Friedman (1984), pp. 63, 86&lt;/ref&gt;

One suggestion from C&amp;R was to make the [[belt armor]] a load-bearing member by connecting plates end to end. This was found inordinately difficult to be practical and, while it would have added girder strength where most badly needed, was considered too radical a proposition to be truly safe. Another idea, subsequently adopted, was to design the [[forecastle]] to break abaft the turrets. The challenge then became to continue the longitudinal strength contributed by the armored deck past this point to the end of the stern. This became a difficult design problem, especially with the need to save weight wherever possible and the fact that light structural members combined with heavy armament weight had become a source of grief for the British.&lt;ref&gt;Breyer, 162&lt;/ref&gt; One proposed solution was to use a combination of three decks—a strength deck at the top of the hull, a protective deck which would rest atop the belt armor, {{convert|10|ft|m}} above the waterline, and a splinter deck below that, just above the waterline.  A third idea, also adopted, was to continue the longitudinal bulkhead between the protective and splinter decks down to the bottom of the ship to add strength. The severity of the strength and weight challenges necessitated a larger displacement of 33,000 tons and a hull of {{convert|850|ft|m}} instead of {{convert|800|ft|m}} to give enough internal volume to accommodate all the needed machinery. Even so, the size of the power plant meant pushing the main turrets further toward the ends of the ships, which increased hull stress. This was why the idea was adopted to place half the boilers above the armored deck.&lt;ref name=&quot;Friedman 1984, pp. 63, 86&quot;/&gt;

==Construction hold and redesign==
Plans to begin construction were placed on hold in 1917. Large numbers of anti-submarine warfare vessels and merchant ships were needed to ensure the safe passage of men and materiel to Europe during Germany's [[U-boat Campaign (World War I)|U-boat campaign]] and were given top priority. This opened the opportunity for a massive redesign, the need for which had become apparent in light of experience gained in the [[Battle of Jutland]], fought shortly after the initial design for the ''Lexington''s had been approved and in which three British battlecruisers had been lost. The fact that the U.S. Navy misunderstood the essential points of the battle initially was shown by its ignoring the ''Lexington''s staying power while increasing their main armament to eight [[16&quot;/50 caliber Mark 2 gun|16&quot;/50 caliber gun]]s and their secondary armament to fourteen [[6&quot;/53 caliber gun]]s. Other factors for this decision were the discovery of plans by Britain and Japan for new battlecruisers armed with 15- and 16-inch guns (respectively) and the recommendation of the [[Bureau of Ordnance]] to give these ships the ability &quot;to inflict fatal damage on the enemy's most powerful vessels at a distance no less than that at which she can be reached by the heavy gunfire of these opponent battleships.&quot; Only 20 of a newer style of boiler were needed, few enough to fit below the armored deck, and the number of funnels was reduced to five. The armor scheme was not modified, as that would have compromised the longitudinal strength of the hull.&lt;ref&gt;Breyer (1974), p. 234&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Friedman (1984), pp. 88, 91, 94&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Morison71&gt;Morison and Polmar (2003), p. 71&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:HMS Hood h60404.jpg|thumb|left|{{HMS|Hood|51|6}}, which influenced the design of the ''Lexington''s]]
Around 1918, the U.S. naval staff in Great Britain became extremely impressed by the British's newest battlecruiser, {{HMS|Hood|51|6}} of the {{sclass2-|Admiral|battlecruiser|4}}. Her side armor was comparable to that of previous battleships and her deck armor was the most extensive of any British capital ship. Because this ship was described as a &quot;[[fast battleship]]&quot; and the British Admiralty considered her a replacement for both the battleship and the battlecruiser, the staff advocated that the United States should develop a similar vessel of its own. Chief Constructor David Taylor agreed. On 8 April 1918, he told the ''Lexington'' design staff to plan a vessel combining the principal features of battleship and battlecruiser so that it would have the maximum possible speed, main armament and protection. Specifically, this meant arming her with the 16&quot; 50 caliber guns planned for the {{sclass-|South Dakota|battleship (1920)|0}} battleships, reducing armor protection 10 percent, a freeboard of at least {{convert|28|ft|m}} (compared to {{convert|32|ft|m}} for the 1917 battlecruiser and {{convert|29|ft|m}} for the ''Hood'') and a speed of at least 30 knots. Moreover, designs were to be prepared and submitted quickly.&lt;ref name=&quot;Friedman 1984, p. 97&quot;&gt;Friedman (1984), p. 97&lt;/ref&gt;

The Royal Navy temporarily assigned a young constructor, Stanley Goodall, to C&amp;R to assist in this task. Goodall brought a copy of the plans of ''Hood'' and accurate accounts of shell damage at the [[Battle of Jutland]].&lt;ref group=Note&gt;Those plans were eventually filed in C&amp;R's &quot;Spring Styles&quot; book of experimental naval design and can still been seen [http://www.history.navy.mil/photos/images/s-file/s584145c.htm here].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=Note&gt;Goodall would eventually become [[Director of Naval Construction]] (DNC) for the Royal Navy. Among his other tasks in this post was giving expert testimony and analysis on the loss of the ''Hood''in 1941 (Friedman (1985), p.&amp;nbsp;163; [http://www.hmshood.org.uk/reference/official/adm116/adm116-4351_89to144.htm ADM 116/4351: Report on the Loss of H.M.S. Hood.] Retrieved 8 May 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, a senior U.S. constructor who served on Admiral Sims's staff in London, L.C. McBride, became privy to much British experience and was able to share it with C&amp;R.&lt;ref&gt;Friedman (1985), p. 163&lt;/ref&gt; While C&amp;R worked concurrently on the more conventional, more heavily armed and armored ''South Dakota'' class, it quickly adopted and incorporated ideas from ''Hood'' into the ''Lexington'' project which included a reduction of the main armor belt, the change to &quot;[[Sloped armour|sloped armor]]&quot; and the addition of four above-water torpedo tubes that were added to the four underwater tubes that had been included in the original design. Other changes included a widening of the ship to allow for an adequate torpedo protection system and an increase in vertical belt armor to {{convert|7|in|mm}}. Another improvement in boiler technology reduced the number of boilers to 16 and the number of funnels to just two, but increased the normal displacement of the ship to 43,500 tons, 300 tons more than the ''South Dakota'' class and 10,900 tons greater than the previous battleship class, the {{sclass-|Colorado|battleship|4}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Friedman 1984, p. 97&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Conway's 118-119&quot;&gt;Gardiner and Gray (1984), pp. 118–119&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Morison and Polmar (2003), pp. 71–72&lt;/ref&gt;

Four proposed redesigns were submitted to the General Board on 3 June 1918, along with a letter that requested a formal reconsideration by the Navy that the ''Lexington''s be armored to protect them only against fire of guns {{convert|6|in|mm}} and under. The Board, concerned about the delay incorporating any of the redesigns would have on not just the ''Lexington''s but the 1916 building program in general and the subsequent cost, declined all four designs. The Board also feared that producing heavily armored fast battleships such as ''Hood'' would make the U.S. Navy's Standard type battleships obsolete, just as HMS ''Dreadnought'' made the Royal Navy's pre-dreadnought battleships obsolescent and negated its advantage in numbers over other navies. This did not stop the U.S. Commander in Chief in European waters, Admiral [[William S. Sims]], to argue for the redesigned vessels by pointing out that ''Hood'' had already brought about the very revolution that the Board wished to suppress. &lt;ref group=Note&gt;Sims' argument was based in part on erroneous information, as the Admiralty assured him that they planned to complete ''Hood''{{'}}s three sister-ships when they had actually been cancelled (Friedman (1984), pp. 98–9).&lt;/ref&gt; Debate continued while the project remained suspended until May 1919, when the Board decided that the battlecruisers should be built as planned, except for a slightly slower version of Design B from C&amp;R with increased protection for turrets, conning towers, magazines and communications. This amended version, labeled B3, was the final version of the ''Lexington'' battlecruiser design.&lt;ref&gt;Friedman (1984), pp. 98–9&lt;/ref&gt;

==Design==
[[File:USS Constitution (CC-5) NHC75498.jpg|thumb|''Constitution'' under construction in Philadelphia in July 1921, seven months before work was suspended pending the outcome of the Washington Naval Conference]]

===General characteristics===
The ''Lexington''-class ships had an [[length overall|overall length]] of {{convert|874|ft|m|1}}, a [[beam (nautical)|beam]] of {{convert|105|ft|4|in|m|1}}, and a [[draft (hull)|draft]] of {{convert|31|ft|m|1}}. They displaced {{convert|43500|LT|t}} at normal load and {{convert|44638|LT|MT}} at [[deep load]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Conway's 119&quot;/&gt; Because the demand for extreme speed necessitated a long hull with maximum freeboard, the [[forecastle]] was extended down 75 percent of the total length of the hull. For this class, Rear Admiral [[David W. Taylor]], who served as Chief Constructor for the [[Bureau of Construction and Repair]], used a relatively new kind of bow called the [[bulbous bow]] or Taylor bow. The result of a series of towing tests begun in 1910, this bow reduced water resistance by an average of six percent, supported the forecastle and reduced bending stress on the hull. At speeds of more than 25 knots, test results were highly favorable. A disadvantage was the formation of a heavy layer of water which would creep up along the outer plating of the forecastle at higher speeds. However, this tendency could be reduced to some degree by careful design of the frames. Taylor first introduced this bow, also known as a bulbous forefoot, in his design of {{USS|Delaware|BB-28|6}}, which entered service in 1910.&lt;ref name=Breyer235&gt;Breyer (1974), p. 235&lt;/ref&gt;

===Propulsion===
[[Turbo-electric]] propulsion was selected for the battlecruisers despite the fact it needed more room than [[geared turbine]]s to allow for better underwater protection that wartime experience showed was essential.&lt;ref name=&quot;Friedman86&quot;/&gt; First used in the {{sclass-|New Mexico|battleship}}s, it also had several other advantages. The turbines could run at their optimum speed, without regard to propeller speed, which was economical on fuel and the machinery could be easily sub-divided which increased the ships' ability to withstand torpedo hits. The substitution of flexible electric cables for bulky steam-lines meant that the motors could be mounted further to the rear of the ship, which reduced both vibration and weight by shortening the propeller shafts. Also, the ship could go astern at full power simply by reversing the [[electrical polarity]] of the motors.&lt;ref&gt;Hone (2011), p. 21&lt;/ref&gt; Despite these factors and the fact that American companies would have struggled to produce the very large geared [[steam turbine]]s needed for such big ships, the Curtis Company tried unsuccessfully to convince the Navy to reverse this decision. The Navy countered that doing so would mean a complete rearrangement of machinery spaces and a reduction in underwater protection.&lt;ref&gt;Anderson and Baker (1977), p. 311; Friedman (1984), p. 86&lt;/ref&gt;

Each propeller was {{convert|14|ft|9|in|m}} in diameter and each of the four propeller shafts was powered by two {{convert|22500|shp|lk=in|adj=on}} [[electric motor]]s acting in tandem. These motors were about five times the size of any earlier electric motor.&lt;ref name=ab12/&gt; Four [[General Electric]] [[turbo generator]]s powered each propeller shaft and each was rated at {{convert|35200|kW}}, 5000 [[volt]]s and 4620 [[ampere|amp]]s of [[direct current]] (DC). Each of the four [[alternating current|AC]] [[alternator]]s produced 40,000 [[Volt-ampere|KVA]]. Sixteen [[water-tube boiler]]s, each in their own individual compartment, provided steam for the generators at a working pressure of {{convert|295|psi|kPa kg/cm2|0|abbr=on|lk=on}} and a temperature of {{convert|460|°F}}. The turbo-electric machinery of the ''Lexington''-class ships was designed to produce a total of {{convert|180000|shp}} and propel the ships at {{convert|33.25|kn|lk=in}}, but each ship reached over {{convert|202000|shp|abbr=on}} and {{convert|34.5|knots}} during [[sea trial]]s in 1928. Six {{convert|750|kW|adj=on}} DC turbo generators were installed in the upper levels of the two main turbine compartments.&lt;ref name=ab12&gt;Anderson and Baker (1977), p. 312&lt;/ref&gt;

The estimated range would have been {{convert|10000|nmi|lk=in}} at a speed of {{convert|10|kn}}.&lt;ref&gt;Hone (2011), p. 25&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Sixteen-inch, 50 Caliber, Mark 2, Mod. 1 Gun Barrel - NH 81481.jpg|thumb|left|16&quot;/50 Mark 2 gun on display in [[Washington Navy Yard]]]]
[[File:5inch 51cal US naval gun.jpg|thumb|left|5&quot;/51 cal, possibly on {{USS|Texas|BB-35|6}}]]

===Armament===

====Main guns====
The original design of the ''Lexington'' class called for ten [[14&quot;/50 caliber gun]]s of either the Mark 4, 5, or 6 variety to be mounted in four turrets (two triple [[superfire|superfiring]] over two double turrets) for the main armament.&lt;ref name=Morison70/&gt;&lt;ref group=A&gt;Though no source states what Mark was used, the only three versions of the 14&quot; U.S. gun that were 50 caliber were Marks 4, 5 and 6.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=A&gt;Breyer's sketch shows two twin turrets superfiring over two triple turrets as in the {{sclass-|Nevada|battleship|4}} (Breyer, p. 236).&lt;/ref&gt; Designed in 1916 and put into service by 1918, these guns were installed on the {{sclass-|Tennessee|battleship|5}}- and ''New Mexico''-class battleships.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell (1985), pp. 123–24&lt;/ref&gt; The guns were capable of firing a {{convert|1400|lb|kg}} armor-piercing (AP) projectile at a muzzle velocity of 2,800 fps (853 mps) to a range of {{convert|24000|yd|km}} at a maximum angle of 15 degrees.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.navweaps.com/Weapons/WNUS_14-50_mk4.htm|title=United States of America 14&quot;/50 (35.6&amp;nbsp;cm) Mark 4 and Mark 6|date=31 December 2009|publisher=NavWeaps.com|accessdate=2 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Later designs called for eight [[16&quot;/50 caliber Mark 2 gun]], also slated to be used on the {{sclass-|South Dakota|battleship (1920)|0}} battleship of 1920.&lt;ref name=Morison71/&gt; Like the 14&quot;/50 caliber gun, the 16&quot; gun was designed in 1916. Basically an extended version of the [[16&quot;/45 caliber Mark 1 gun]] used on the {{sclass-|Colorado|battleship|4}}, it fired the same {{convert|2100|lb|kg|adj=on}} shell as the Mark 1 at a muzzle velicity of 2,800 fps (853 mps) and rate of two rounds per minute to a range of {{convert|44500|yd|m}} at an elevation of 45 degrees.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.navweaps.com/Weapons/WNUS_16-50_mk2.htm|title=United States of America 16&quot;/50 (40.6&amp;nbsp;cm) Mark 2 and Mark 3|date=26 January 2009|publisher=NavWeaps.com|accessdate=2 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A prototype Mark 2 was tested and proven on 8 April 1918, and the gun was scheduled to go into naval service in 1923. However, with the cancellation of both the ''Lexington'' and the ''South Dakota'' classes, no guns were installed on any ships even though 71 had been built and 44 were under construction. In 1922–24, twenty of the guns were given to the Army for use as coastal defense guns along with the Army's [[16&quot;/50 caliber M1919 gun]]s. Later planning called for the use of these guns in the {{sclass-|Iowa|battleship|2}}s, but miscommunication between design bureaus led to the [[16&quot;/50 caliber Mark 7 gun]] being used instead. As a result, all but three of the Navy's remaining Mark 2 and 3 guns were sent to the Army to also be used as coastal defense guns.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell (1985), p. 116&lt;/ref&gt;

====Secondary guns====
The original design called for eighteen [[5&quot;/51 caliber gun]]s. These guns were originally mounted on the {{sclass-|Florida|battleship|5}}- and {{sclass-|Wyoming|battleship|2}}s, but they found their way into the secondary armament of every U.S. battleship that was built prior to the Washington Naval Treaty. Also, many of the destroyers, submarines, and auxiliaries that were built during this time mounted this gun as their main gun.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell (1985), p. 136&lt;/ref&gt; They fired a {{convert|50|lb|kg|adj=on}} shell at a muzzle velocity of 3,150 fps (960 mps) and a rate of eight or nine rounds per minute to a range of {{convert|18880|yd|m}} at an elevation of 25 degrees.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.navweaps.com/Weapons/WNUS_5-51_mk7.htm|title=United States of America 5&quot;/51 (12.7&amp;nbsp;cm) Marks 7, 8, 9, 14 and 15|date=12 February 2012|publisher=NavWeaps.com|accessdate=2 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The secondary armament was later upped to fourteen [[6&quot;/53 caliber gun]]s in Mark 13 [[casemate]] mountings during one of the redesigns. Designed in 1920 and in service by 1923, these guns became the main armament on the {{sclass-|Omaha|cruiser|0}} light cruisers, {{USS|Narwhal|SS-167|2}}, {{USS|Nautilus|SS-168|2}}, and {{USS|Argonaut|SM-1|2}} submarines, and they were intended as secondary armament on the ''South Dakota''-class battleships.&lt;ref&gt;Morison and Polmar (2003), p. 69–71&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Campbell (1985), pp. 132–33&lt;/ref&gt; They fired a {{convert|105|lb|kg|adj=on}} shell at a muzzle velocity of 3,000 fps (914 mps) and a rate of six or seven rounds per minute to a range of {{convert|25300|yd|m}} at an elevation of 30 degrees.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.navweaps.com/Weapons/WNUS_6-53_mk12.htm|title=United States of America 6&quot;/53 (15.2&amp;nbsp;cm) Marks 12, 14, 15 and 18|date=8 February 2008|publisher=NavWeaps.com|accessdate=2 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Anti-aircraft guns====
Four [[3&quot;/23 caliber gun|3&quot;/23 caliber Mark 11]] [[Anti-aircraft warfare|anti-aircraft gun]]s were planned for the original and first redesigned versions of the ''Lexington''s. This was increased to eight guns in the final version.&lt;ref name=Breyer235/&gt; These could depress to −10 degrees and elevate to 85 degrees. They fired a {{convert|13|lb|kg|adj=on}} shell at a muzzle velocity of 1,650 fps (503 mps) and rate of between eight and nine rounds per minute to a range of {{convert|8800|yd|m}} and a height of {{convert|18000|ft|m}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.navweaps.com/Weapons/WNUS_3-23_mk13.htm|title=United States of America 3&quot;/23.5 (7.62&amp;nbsp;cm) Marks 4 and 14, 3&quot;/23 (7.62&amp;nbsp;cm) Marks 7, 9, 11 and 13 |date=14 January 2011|publisher=NavWeaps.com|accessdate=2 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Torpedo tubes====
Eight {{convert|21|in|mm|0|adj=on}} [[torpedo tube]]s were to be carried. Four of these would be mounted inside the hull below the waterline, two at either side of the bow; the others would be above the waterline at the stern, two at either side.&lt;ref name=Breyer235-7&gt;Breyer (1974), pp. 235–7&lt;/ref&gt;

===Armor===
[[File:SaratogaBuildingn11981.jpg|thumb|right|upright|''Saratoga'' on 8 March 1922, after her construction had been suspended. The circular [[barbette]]s on blocks on her deck were intended for the battlecruiser's [[main battery]]]]

The waterline [[Belt armor|belt]] of the ''Lexington''-class ships tapered {{convert|7|-|5|in|0}} in thickness from top to bottom and was angled 11° outwards at the top to increase the armor's relative thickness to horizontal, close-range fire (a concept taken from HMS ''Hood''). The down side to this practice was a reduction of the relative height of the belt, which increased the chance of plunging shellfire going over or under it. The belt covered the middle {{convert|530|ft|1}} of the ships. Forward, the belt ended in a [[bulkhead (partition)|bulkhead]] also tapered from seven to five inches in thickness. Aft, it terminated at a seven-inch bulkhead. This belt had a height of {{convert|9|ft|4|in|m|1}}.&lt;ref name=ab8/&gt; The upper [[deck (ship)|deck]] was {{convert|2.25|in|mm|0}} thick in two layers.&lt;ref&gt;Hone (2011), p. 26&lt;/ref&gt; The third deck over the ships' machinery and [[magazine (artillery)|magazine]] was armored with two layers of [[Special treatment steel]] (STS) totaling {{convert|2|in}} in thickness. The steering gear, however, was protected by two layers of STS that totaled {{convert|3|in|0}} on the slope and {{convert|4.5|in|0}} on the slope.&lt;ref name=ab8&gt;Anderson and Baker (1977), p. 308&lt;/ref&gt;

The turret faces were {{convert|11|in|0}} thick while their sides were {{convert|6|in|0}} in thickness, and the roof was five inches thick. The [[barbette]]s had a maximum of {{convert|9|in|0}} of armor, but were reduced in thickness in stages below decks to a minimum thickness of five inches. The [[conning tower]] armor was {{convert|12|in|0}} thick, and it had a communications tube with {{convert|10|in|0}} sides ran from the conning tower down to the lower conning position on the 1st platform deck. The [[torpedo]] defense system of the ''Lexington''-class ships consisted of three to six medium steel [[Torpedo bulkhead|protective bulkheads]] that ranged from {{convert|.375|to|.75|in|0}} in thickness. The spaces between them could be left empty or used as fuel tanks to absorb the detonation of a torpedo's [[warhead]].&lt;ref name=ab8/&gt;

===Aircraft===
None of the designs made provision for aircraft. However, the Navy planned to adapt the [[poop deck]] of these vessels to accommodate aircraft at a later date.&lt;ref name=Breyer235-7/&gt;

==Conversion ==
Construction finally began upon the battlecruisers in 1920 and 1921, after a delay of almost five months.&lt;ref name=&quot;Conway's 119&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sinesi (1998), p. 26&lt;/ref&gt; However, that July, U.S. Secretary of State [[Charles Evans Hughes]] called for [[Washington Naval Conference|a conference in Washington D.C.]] to be held that November. The stated goal was to curb the rapidly growing and extremely expensive naval construction programs.&lt;ref name=AmerBB74&gt;Morison and Polmar (2003), p. 74&lt;/ref&gt; It was obvious to the [[General Board]] that the expensive new battlecruisers,&lt;ref name=&quot;Friedman 41/43&quot;&gt;Friedman (1983), pp.&amp;nbsp;41 and 43&lt;/ref&gt; which some thought were already obsolete,&lt;ref name=AmerBB72&gt;Morison and Polmar (2003), p. 72&lt;/ref&gt; would be very attractive targets for cancellation. Accordingly, studies were done exploring the possibilities of converting one or more of the battlecruisers to different uses: one looked at a conversion to an aircraft carrier, while another contemplated a conversion to an Atlantic [[ocean liner]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Friedman 41/43&quot;/&gt;

Conversion of a ''Lexington'' to an aircraft carrier had both positive and negative aspects when compared with a &quot;specifically designed carrier&quot;. While the conversion would have better anti-torpedo protection, larger magazines for aircraft bombs than a keel-up carrier and a more room for aircraft landings (the after [[Elevator#Aircraft elevators|elevator]] would be 28 feet farther up), it would also be a half-knot slower with less hangar space (about 16 percent less), less emergency fuel and &quot;narrower lines&quot; aft (pilots landing on the converted battlecruiser would not have as wide of a runway to aim for). Comparing costs, a brand-new aircraft carrier would cost $27.1 million, while a conversion of one of the ''Lexington'' class, not counting the $6.7 million already sunk into them, would cost $22.4 million.&lt;ref name=Friedman43&gt;Friedman (1983), p. 43&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=A&gt;Both of these figures (the $6.7 and $22.4) are estimates for one of the lesser-advanced ships like ''Ranger''. The former cost would be higher and the second lower for one of the more-advanced ships.&lt;/ref&gt;

Any debate over converting them was quelled by the signing of the [[Washington Naval Treaty]]. Under the terms of the treaty, any [[capital ships]] that were under construction by the five signatories (the United States, Great Britain, France, Italy and Japan) had to be canceled and scrapped. For battlecruisers, this encompassed the United States' ''Lexington'' class, Japan's {{sclass-|Amagi|battlecruiser|4}}, and Great Britain's [[G3 battlecruiser]]s.&lt;ref&gt;See: [[s:Washington Naval Treaty, 1922#SECTION II REPLACEMENT AND SCRAPPING OF CAPITAL SHIPS|Washington Naval Treaty, Chapter II, Part III, Section II]]&lt;/ref&gt; However, the treaty did allow the participating nations to take two of the capital ships they had under construction and convert them to aircraft carriers;&lt;ref name=Friedman43/&gt; the U.S. Navy decided to complete the two ''Lexingtons'' that were closest to completion, {{USS|Lexington|CV-2|2}} and {{USS|Saratoga|CV-3|2}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Doooomed&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Lexington battlecruiser conversion models.jpg|thumb|right|Rear Admiral David W. Taylor (left), Chief of the Bureau of Construction and Repair, and Rear Admiral John K. Robison (right), Chief of the Bureau of Engineering, hold a model of the battlecruiser above a model of the proposed conversion to an aircraft carrier at the Navy Department on 8 March 1922.|alt=Two men in naval officer uniforms hold the ends of a two-meter model of a battlecruiser above a similarly sized model of a conversion to an aircraft carrier. Four men, mostly in civilian clothes, stand behind the models. The battlecruiser model has two large funnels and eight guns, and the conversion has a huge funnel and a long flight deck.]]
The problem was that the tonnage cap for new carrier construction had been set at 27,000 tons, which was too low for any practical conversion of the battlecruisers. An exception, spearheaded by [[Assistant Secretary of the Navy]] [[Theodore Roosevelt Jr.]], was added to the treaty. This gave the five nations the option to convert no more than two capital ships that were under construction to 33,000 ton aircraft carriers.&lt;ref name=Friedman43/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;See: [[s:Washington Naval Treaty, 1922#Article IX|Washington Naval Treaty, Chapter I, Article IX]]&lt;/ref&gt; But even that increase of 6,000 tons (from 27,000 to 33,000) was almost not enough for a conversion—it took creative interpreting of a clause in the treaty to allow for the conversion without removing half of the power plant, which the General Board did not want to do.&lt;ref name=Friedman43/&gt; The clause (Chapter II, Part III, Section I, (d)):

{{quote|No retained capital ships or aircraft carriers shall be reconstructed except for the purpose of providing means of defense against air and submarine attack, and subject to the following rules: The Contracting Powers may, for that purpose, equip existing tonnage with bulge or blister or anti-air attack deck protection, providing the increase of displacement thus effected does not exceed 3,000 tons (3,048 metric tons) displacement for each ship.&lt;ref&gt;See: [[s:Washington Naval Treaty, 1922#SECTION I.-RULES FOR REPLACEMENT|Chapter II, Part III, Section I, (d)]]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Without this clause, the two carriers would have likely been in serious trouble—1928 estimates for the two ships put ''Lexington'' at an actual tonnage of 35,689 tons and ''Saratoga'' at 35,544, though on official lists the number given was 33,000 tons with a footnote that stated &quot;[this number] does not include weight allowance under Ch. 11, pt. 3, Sec. 1, art. (d) of Washington Treaty for providing means against air and submarine attack&quot;. This tonnage was used by these ships for their entire careers.&lt;ref name=Friedman43/&gt;

==Ships==
[[File:USS Lexington (CV-2) on building ways, 1925.jpg|thumb|right|''Lexington'' shortly before her [[ship launching|launch]], circa 1925|alt=Large ship with no superstructure with scaffold-like steel surrounding her.]]

Following adoption of the [[Washington Naval Treaty]], construction on all the ships was stopped in February 1922. Two of the battlecruiser hulls were reordered as the {{sclass-|Lexington|aircraft carrier}}s {{USS|Lexington|CV-2|3}} and {{USS|Saratoga|CV-3|3}} under the terms of the Treaty, while the other four ships were formally cancelled and scrapped in place.&lt;ref name=&quot;USN Ship Types&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Doooomed&quot;&gt;{{Cite news| date = 2 May 1922| title = Board for Selling Doomed Warships; Admirals Oppose Sinking at Sea Under Terms of the Five Power Naval Treaty | work= The New York Times| page = 20| url = http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=9B01EFD71739EF3ABC4B53DFB3668389639EDE|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
!Ship
!Hull number
!Builder&lt;ref name=&quot;Conway's 119&quot;/&gt;
!Laid down
!Launched
!Commissioned
!Fate
|-
|{{USS|Lexington|CV-2|2}}
|CC-1
|[[Fore River Shipyard]], [[Quincy, Massachusetts]]
| 8 January 1921
| 3 October 1925&lt;ref name=dl&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.history.navy.mil/danfs/l6/lexington-iv.htm|title=''Lexington''|work=Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships|publisher=[[Naval History &amp; Heritage Command]] (NH&amp;HC)|accessdate=14 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| 14 December 1927&lt;ref name=dl/&gt;
| Converted to [[aircraft carrier]] 1922–1927&lt;br&gt;Sunk in [[Battle of the Coral Sea|air attack]], 8 May 1942&lt;ref name=dl/&gt;
|-
|''Constellation'' 
|CC-2
|[[Northrop Grumman Shipbuilding|Newport News Shipbuilding]], [[Newport News, Virginia]]
| 18 August 1920
| colspan=2 {{n/a}}
| Cancelled, August 1923&lt;ref name=&quot;USN Ship Types&quot;/&gt;&lt;br&gt;Broken up in place&lt;ref name=&quot;USN Ship Types&quot;/&gt;
|-
|{{USS|Saratoga|CV-3|2}}{{refn|Because more progress had been made on the construction of ''Saratoga'' (35.4% versus 22.7%), she was converted instead of ''Constellation''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Doooomed&quot;/&gt;|group=A}}
|CC-3
|[[New York Shipbuilding]], [[Camden, New Jersey]]
| 25 September 1920
| 7 April 1925&lt;ref name=ds&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.history.navy.mil/danfs/s6/saratoga-v.htm|title=''Saratoga''|work=Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships|publisher=NH&amp;HC|accessdate=14 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| 16 November 1927&lt;ref name=ds/&gt;
| Converted to [[aircraft carrier]] 1922–1927&lt;br&gt;Sunk as a [[target ship]] during [[Operation Crossroads]], 25 July 1946&lt;ref name=ds/&gt;
|-
|''Ranger''&lt;br&gt;(ex-''Lexington'') {{refn|''Ranger'' was originally named ''Lexington'', but was renamed on 10 December 1917.&lt;ref name=dr&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.history.navy.mil/danfs/r2/ranger-vii.htm|title=''Ranger''|work=Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships|publisher=NH&amp;HC|accessdate=14 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;|group=A}}
|CC-4 
|Newport News Shipbuilding, Newport News, Virginia
| 23 June 1921
| colspan=2 {{n/a}}
|rowspan=2|Cancelled, August 1923&lt;ref name=&quot;USN Ship Types&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=dr/&gt;&lt;br&gt;Broken up in place&lt;ref name=dr/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.history.navy.mil/photos/sh-usn/usnsh-c/cc5.htm |title=USS Constitution (CC-5), 1918 Program – construction cancelled in 1923  |accessdate=15 April 2012  |date=20 February 2000 |work= |publisher=NH&amp;HC}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|''Constitution''&lt;br&gt;(ex-''Ranger'')
|CC-5
|rowspan=2|[[Philadelphia Naval Shipyard]], [[Philadelphia, Pennsylvania]]
| 25 September 1920
|colspan=2 {{n/a}}
|-
|''United States'' 
|CC-6
|25 September 1920
|colspan=2 {{n/a}}
| Cancelled 17 August 1923&lt;ref name=&quot;USN Ship Types&quot;/&gt;&lt;br&gt;Broken up in place&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.history.navy.mil/danfs/u1/united_states.htm |title=''United States'' |work=Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships |publisher=NH&amp;HC |accessdate=14 April 2012 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=http://webarchive.loc.gov/all/20120207135551/http%3A//www%2Ehistory%2Enavy%2Emil/danfs/u1/united_states%2Ehtm |archivedate= 7 February 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|group=A}}

==References==
===Notes===
{{reflist|group=Note}}

===Footnotes===
{{Reflist|30em}}

===Bibliography===
{{Refbegin}}
*{{cite journal|last=Anderson|first=Richard M.|author2=Baker, Arthur D. III |year=1977|title=CV-2 Lex and CV-3 Sara|journal=Warship International|publisher=International Naval Research Organization|location=Toledo, OH|volume=XIV|issue=4|pages=291–328|issn=0043-0374}}
* {{cite book |last=Burr|first=Lawrence|title=US Cruisers 1883–1904: The Birth of the Steel Navy|publisher=Osprey Publishing|year=2008|isbn= 1-84603-267-9 }}
*{{cite book|last=Campbell|first=John|title=Naval Weapons of World War II|year=1985|publisher=Naval Institute Press|location=Annapolis, Maryland|isbn=0-87021-459-4}}
* {{cite book |last=Cooper|first=Michael L.|title=Theodore Roosevelt: A Twentieth-century Life|place=New York|publisher=Viking|year=2009|isbn=978-0-67001134-6 | url=https://books.google.com/books/about/Theodore_Roosevelt.html?id=TNmrjwEACAAJ&amp;redir_esc=y  }}
* {{cite book|author=Friedman, Norman | title=U.S. Aircraft Carriers: An Illustrated Design History |location=Annapolis, Maryland |publisher=Naval Institute Press |year=1983 |isbn=0-87021-739-9 |oclc=8763586 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=-UT7MDTeKj8C}}
* {{cite book| last = Friedman| first = Norman|authormask=2| title = U.S. Battleships: An Illustrated Design History| location = Annapolis, Maryland| publisher = Naval Institute Press| year = 1985| isbn = 0-87021-715-1| oclc = 12214729 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=Y41Ha_3HsrYC}}
* {{cite book |last=Friedman|first=Norman|authormask=3|title=U.S. Cruisers: An Illustrated History|location=Annapolis, Maryland|publisher=Naval Institute Press|year=1984 |isbn=0-87021-715-1}}
* {{cite book|author1=Gardiner, Robert |author2=Chesneau, Roger | title=Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships, 1922–1946 |location=Annapolis, Maryland |publisher=Naval Institute Press |year=1980 |isbn=0-87021-913-8 |oclc=18121784 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=bJBMBvyQ83EC}}
* {{cite book |editor1-last=Gardiner |editor1-first=Robert |editor2-last=Gray |editor2-first=Randal |title=Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships: 1906–1921 |year=1984 |location=Annapolis, Maryland |publisher=Naval Institute Press |isbn=0-87021-907-3 |oclc=12119866 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=V2r_TBjR2TYC}}
*{{cite book|editor=Jordan, John|publisher=Conway|author=Hone, Trent|chapter=High-Speed Thoroughbreds: The US Navy's ''Lexington'' Class Battlecruiser Designs|pages=8–31|location=London|year=2011|title=Warship 2011|isbn=978-1-84486-133-0}}
*{{Cite book|last1=Morison |first1=Samuel Loring |authorlink2=Norman Polmar|last2=Polmar |first2=Norman | title=The American Battleship |location=St. Paul, Minnesota |publisher=MBI |year=2003 |isbn=0-7603-0989-2 |oclc=50478540 |url=https://books.google.com/?id=yfNkP1-uXLYC}}
* {{cite book |last=O'Brien|first=Philip|title=Technology and Naval Combat in the Twentieth Century and Beyond|publisher=Routelege|year=2007 |isbn=0-415-44936-7 }}
* {{cite book|author=Osborne, Eric W. | title=Cruisers and Battle Cruisers: An Illustrated History of Their Impact |publisher=ABC-CLIO |year=2004 |isbn=1-85109-369-9|url=https://books.google.com/?id=PryqSiAk9y4C|location=Santa Barbara, California}}
* {{cite book|author=Perras, Galen Roger | title=Stepping Stones to Nowhere: The Aleutian Islands, Alaska, and American Military Strategy 1867–1945 |publisher=Military Institute Press |year=2003 |isbn=1-59114-836-7|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=HByyEWPFvSoC&amp;pg=PA200&amp;dq=theodore+roosevelt+japan+navy#v=onepage&amp;q=theodore%20roosevelt%20japan%20navy&amp;f=false|location=Annapolis, Maryland}}
* {{cite book |last1=Scarpaci |first1=Wayne |title=Iowa Class Battleships and Alaska Class Large Cruisers Conversion Projects 1942–1964: An Illustrated Technical Reference |date= April 2008 |publisher=Nimble Books|location= |isbn=1-934840-38-6 |oclc= |url=https://books.google.com/?id=L4z8UIRymR4C}}
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Battleships}}
* [http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/systems/ship/cc-1.htm Class description at Global Security]

{{Lexington class aircraft carrier}}
{{WWI US ships}}

{{good article}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2013}}

[[Category:Battlecruiser classes]]
[[Category:Lexington-class battlecruisers| ]]
[[Category:Abandoned military projects of the United States]]
[[Category:World War I battlecruisers of the United States| ]]</text>
      <sha1>mrybz76ajuaj804f2jh130lr9a6x15u</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
