<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Lockheed D-21</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>776844</id>
    <revision>
      <id>742535913</id>
      <parentid>732259901</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-04T08:12:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>3dSurveyor</username>
        <id>28781504</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Operational history */ Added the word &quot;the&quot; for correctness.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22200">&lt;!-- This article is a part of [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft]]. Please see [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft/page content]] for recommended layout, and guidelines. --&gt;
{|{{Infobox aircraft begin
  |name= D-21
  |image= File:M21Ship2-cropped.jpg
  |caption= The D-21 mounted on the back of the [[Lockheed A-12#M-21|M-21]]. Note the intake cover on the drone, which was used on early flights. 
  |alt=
}}{{Infobox aircraft type
  |type= High-altitude and high speed [[reconnaissance aircraft|reconnaissance]]  [[Unmanned aerial vehicle|drone]]
  |national origin= United States
  |manufacturer= [[Lockheed Corporation|Lockheed]]
  |designer=
  |first flight= 22 December 1964
  |introduced= 1969
  |retired= 1971
  |status=
  |primary user= [[Central Intelligence Agency]] 
  |more users= [[United States Air Force]]
  |produced=&lt;!-- 1964-? --&gt;
  |number built= 38
  |program cost=
  |unit cost=
  |developed from=
  |variants with their own articles=
}}
|}

The '''Lockheed D-21''' was an American [[reconnaissance aircraft|reconnaissance]] [[Unmanned aerial vehicle|drone]] with maximum speed in excess of {{convert|3.3|Mach|90000|0|lk=on}}. The D-21 was initially designed to be launched from the back of a [[Lockheed A-12#M-21|M-21]] carrier aircraft, a variant of the [[Lockheed A-12]] aircraft. Development began in October 1962. Originally known by the Lockheed designation Q-12, the drone was intended for reconnaissance deep in enemy airspace.

The D-21 was designed to carry a single high-resolution photographic camera over a preprogrammed path, then release the camera module into the air for retrieval, after which the drone would self-destruct.&lt;ref name=Donald_p154-6&gt;Donald 2003, pp. 154–56.&lt;/ref&gt; Following a fatal accident when launched from an M-21, the D-21 was modified to be launched from a [[Boeing B-52 Stratofortress]]. Several test flights were made, followed by four unsuccessful operational D-21 flights over the People's Republic of China, and the program was canceled in 1971.

==Design and development==
In the 1960s Lockheed's secret [[Skunk Works]] developed the Mach 3 [[Lockheed A-12|A-12]] reconnaissance aircraft for the [[Central Intelligence Agency]] (CIA). After the [[U-2 Crisis of 1960|shooting down]] of the [[Lockheed U-2|U-2]] piloted by  [[Gary Powers]] in 1960, a number of different concepts were proposed as alternatives. [[Kelly Johnson (engineer)|Kelly Johnson]], the leader of Skunk Works, developed the concept of a long-range drone that used much of the A-12's technology. In October 1962 the CIA and the [[United States Air Force|US Air Force]] instructed Lockheed to study a high-speed, high-altitude drone concept. Johnson specified speeds of Mach 3.3–3.5, an operational altitude of {{convert|87000|-|95000|ft|m}}, and a range of {{convert|3000|nmi|mi km}}. It was intended to make a one-way trip, eject its camera payload at the end of the mission for recovery, then self-destruct.&lt;ref name=gg_p106&gt;Goodall and Goodall 2002, p. 106.&lt;/ref&gt;  It had a double-[[delta wing]] similar to the A-12's wing design. The Q-12 was to be air-launched from the back of an A-12, and used key technology from the A-12 project, including [[titanium]] construction and [[radar cross-section]] reduction design features.&lt;ref name=Pace_p55/&gt;

[[File:M-21 Rear.jpg|thumb|left|Rear view of the D-21/M-21 combination on the ground, showing the exhaust shroud used on early flights |alt=]]
Johnson wanted to power the Q-12 with a [[ramjet]] engine built by [[Marquardt Corporation|Marquardt]] for the [[Boeing]] [[CIM-10 Bomarc]] long-range [[surface-to-air missile]]. Marquardt and Lockheed had already collaborated on several programs and had a close working relationship. The engine, the RJ43-MA-11, required modification, since it was only designed to burn as long as the missile needed to hit a target, while the Q-12's engine needed to operate at high temperatures for at least an hour and a half at high altitudes. The modified engine was designated as the RJ43-MA20S-4.&lt;ref name=gg_p106/&gt;

A full-scale [[mockup]] of the Q-12 was ready by 7 December 1962, and had already undergone preliminary tests to measure its radar cross-section. Marquardt had also successfully tested the modified RJ-43 in its [[wind tunnel]] in the meantime.&lt;ref&gt;Goodall and Goodall 2002, pp. 106–107.&lt;/ref&gt; However, the CIA was not enthusiastic about the Q-12, mostly because the agency was overextended at the time with U-2 missions, getting the A-12 up to speed, and covert operations in Southeast Asia. The Air Force, however, was interested in the Q-12 as both a reconnaissance platform and a [[cruise missile]], and the CIA finally decided to work with the USAF to develop the new drone. Lockheed was awarded a contract in March 1963 for full-scale development of the Q-12.&lt;ref name=Pace_p55&gt;Pace 2004, p. 55.&lt;/ref&gt;

The camera and its [[Camera magazine|film magazines]] with an [[inertial navigation system]] were carried in a cramped &quot;Q-bay&quot; below the drone's air [[intake]]. These components were built into a module that fit into the bay and was known as a &quot;hatch&quot;. The hatch would be ejected at the end of the mission and then snagged out of the air by a [[Lockheed C-130 Hercules|JC-130 Hercules]], a technique that had been developed by the Air Force to recover film canisters from satellites. If the C-130 missed, the hatch was equipped with flotation devices so it could be recovered by ship if released over water. [[Honeywell]] built the [[avionics]] systems; new construction techniques and materials had to be developed for the systems to withstand the high temperatures, extreme vibrations, and lack of space in the D-21.&lt;ref&gt;Goodall and Goodall 2002, pp. 112–114.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:LockheedM21-D21.jpg|thumb|M-21 carrying D-21 in flight|alt=]]
In late 1963 the project was named ''Tagboard''; the Q-12 was re-designated D-21 while the A-12 version launcher became [[Lockheed A-12#M-21|M-21]] (D- for &quot;daughter&quot; and M- for &quot;mother&quot;). Two of the original 18 A-12 aircraft were designated as M-21s with serial numbers 60-6940 and 60-6941. The M-21 was a two-seat version of the A-12, with a pylon on the fuselage centerline between the [[vertical stabilizer]]s to carry the drone in a nose-up attitude.&lt;ref&gt;Goodall and Goodall 2002, p. 107.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Testing and carrier change===
A D-21 mounted on an M-21 began captive flight-testing on 22 December 1964. [[Aerodynamic]] covers were initially placed over the D-21's intake and exhaust to reduce [[drag (physics)|drag]], but had to be removed after the first few tests, as no way of discarding them at Mach 3 without damaging the drone or carrier plane could be devised.&lt;ref&gt;Goodall and Goodall 2002, p. 109.&lt;/ref&gt;

The D-21 was first launched from an M-21 on 5 March 1966.&lt;ref name=Donald_p155&gt;Donald 2003, p. 155.&lt;/ref&gt; The drone was released but stayed close to the M-21's back for a few seconds, which seemed like &quot;two hours&quot; to the M-21 crew.&lt;ref&gt;Peebles 1999, p. 125.&lt;/ref&gt; A second launch took place on 27 April 1966; the D-21 reached its operational altitude of {{convert|90000|ft|m|0|abbr=on}} and speed of over {{convert|3.3|Mach|90000|0}}, though it was lost due to a hydraulic pump failure after a flight of over {{convert|1200|nmi|mi km|abbr=on}}. The Air Force's interest in the program continued and more D-21s were ordered after the second launch.&lt;ref name=Donald_p155/&gt;  A third flight took place on 16 June with the D-21 flying {{convert|1550|nmi|mi km|abbr=on}} through its complete flight profile, though its camera hatch was not released due to an electronics failure.&lt;ref name=gg_p108&gt;Goodall and Goodall 2002, p. 108.&lt;/ref&gt;

The fourth and final launch from an M-21 on 30 July ended in disaster. Unlike the three previous launches this one was performed straight and level, not in an [[outside loop]] to assist in the separation of the drone from the aircraft. The D-21 suffered engine problems and struck the M-21's tail after separation, leading to the destruction of both aircraft. The two crew ejected and landed at sea. The pilot, Bill Park, survived, but the Launch Control Officer, Ray Torick, drowned.&lt;ref name=gg_p108/&gt;&lt;ref name=Landis_p24-5&gt;Landis and Jenkins 2005, pp. 24–25.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:B-52 with D-21.jpg|thumb|A modified D-21 carried on the wing of a [[Boeing B-52 Stratofortress|B-52]]|alt=]]
Following the accident, Johnson suggested launching the D-21 from the very large [[Boeing B-52 Stratofortress]] bomber, and adding a solid rocket booster to get it up to speed.&lt;ref name=Landis_p25-6&gt;Landis and Jenkins 2005, pp. 25–26.&lt;/ref&gt; The drone was modified by adding attachment points on its spine to mate with the carrying pylon on the B-52 and its belly attachment points were adapted to accommodate the rocket booster necessary to increase its speed and allow its ramjet to operate. Its vertical stabilizer was increased in size by approximately 20%. The modified drone version was designated ''D-21B'' (there was no ''-21A''). Two B-52Hs were modified to carry a pair of drones each by means of two large underwing pylons that replaced the smaller pylons used for the [[AGM-28 Hound Dog]] cruise missiles. The [[tail gunner]]'s and [[electronic warfare]] officer's stations were replaced with two launch control stations. Command and [[telemetry]] systems were added, and high-speed cameras were installed to track the drones as they separated from the pylons. The launch control officer on the B-52H could communicate with the D-21Bs, and could make it self-destruct.&lt;ref&gt;Goodall and Goodall 2002, pp. 109, 113, 117.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:D-21 Booster Launch.jpg|thumb|left|A D-21B being launched, illustrating the size of the booster relative to the drone.|alt=]]
The [[solid-fuel rocket|solid-fuel booster]] was both larger and heavier than the drone; it was {{convert|44|ft|4|in|m|sigfig=3}} long and weighed {{convert|13286|lb|kg|sigfig=3}}. It had a folding [[Vertical stabilizer|tail fin]] on the bottom to stabilize it while the rocket was firing. The booster had a burn time of 87 seconds and a thrust of {{convert|27300|lbf|kN}}.&lt;ref&gt;Peebles 1999, p. 127.&lt;/ref&gt; During ground handling everyone within {{convert|25|ft|m|sigfig=2}} was required to wear anti-static straps to prevent any [[electrostatic discharge|discharge of static electricity]] that might ignite the booster.&lt;ref&gt;Goodall and Goodall 2002, pp. 115–116.&lt;/ref&gt;

The first attempted launch of a D-21B was on 28 September 1967, but the drone fell off the B-52's launch pylon due to a stripped nut on the pylon before the aircraft reached its intended launch point. Johnson admitted that the incident was &quot;very embarrassing&quot;. Three more launches were performed from November 1967 through January 1968. None were completely successful, so Johnson ordered his team to conduct a thorough review before renewing launch attempts.&lt;ref&gt;Peebles 1999, p. 129.&lt;/ref&gt; The next launch was on 10 April 1968. It also failed as the engine did not ignite. On 16 June the D-21B finally made a completely successful flight; it flew at the specified altitude and course for its full range, and the hatch was recovered.&lt;ref name=gg_p118&gt;Goodall and Goodall 2002, p. 118.&lt;/ref&gt; The next two launches were failures, followed by another successful flight in December. A test in February 1969 to check the inertial navigation system with an actual mission profile was a failure. The next two flights in May and July succeeded.&lt;ref&gt;Miller 1995, p. 141.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Operational history==
[[File:B-52 with two D-21s.jpg|thumb|The same B-52 photographed from farther away, showing both drones.|alt=]]

Four operational missions with the D-21B took place under the codename of ''Senior Bowl''. These were conducted over the People's Republic of China from 9 November 1969 to 20 March 1971 to spy on the [[Lop Nor]] nuclear test site. The USAF's 4200th Support Squadron, based at [[Beale Air Force Base]], California, flew the missions, usually from [[Andersen Air Force Base]] in [[Guam]].&lt;ref&gt;Goodall and Goodall 2002, pp. 112, 118.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Chinese never spotted the D-21B. The first one failed to turn around and continued straight on, crashing somewhere in the Soviet Union.&lt;ref name=CIA_513A&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.lazygranch.com/images/cia/jac/jac37s.jp2 |title= Interview with James A. Cunningham, Jr. (Director of Development Projects Division) |publisher=CIA |date= 4 October 1983}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another test flight was conducted on 20 February 1970 in a successful attempt to correct any problems. The second operational mission, however, was not until 16 December 1970. The D-21B reached Lop Nor and back to the recovery point, but the hatch had a partial parachute failure and was lost at sea with its photographs.&lt;ref name=gg_p118/&gt;

During the third operational mission, on 4 March 1971, the D-21B flew to Lop Nor and returned, and released the hatch, which deployed its parachute, but the [[Mid-air retrieval|midair recovery]] failed and the hatch fell into the water. The [[destroyer]] that tried to retrieve the hatch  ran it down and it sank. The fourth, and last, operational flight of the D-21B was on 20 March 1971. It was lost over China on the final segment of the route over China's [[Yunnan province]];&lt;ref&gt;Peebles 1999, p. 131.&lt;/ref&gt; wreckage was found by local authorities. In 2010, after being in the junkyard of [[China Aviation Museum]] for years, the wreckage was moved to the exhibition area.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.airforceworld.com/others/D21-mach-3-supersonic-reconnaissance-plane-crashed-in-china.html &quot;Lockheed D-21B No.&amp;nbsp;527 now in China Aviation Museum&quot;], 29 August 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 23 July 1971, the D-21B program was canceled due to its poor success rate, the introduction of a new generation of photo reconnaissance [[satellite]]s, and President [[Richard Nixon]]'s rapprochement with China.&lt;ref&gt;Peebles 1999, pp. 133–34.&lt;/ref&gt;  A total of 38 D-21 and D-21B drones had been built, 21 of which were expended in launches. The remaining 17 were initially stored at [[Norton Air Force Base]], California, then moved to the [[Davis-Monthan Air Force Base]] &quot;boneyard&quot; near [[Tucson, Arizona]],&lt;ref name=Landis_p28&gt;Landis and Jenkins 2005, p. 28.&lt;/ref&gt; in 1976 and 1977. With the base open to the public, the D-21 drones were quickly spotted and photographed. The Air Force called them GTD-21Bs with the GT standing for Ground Training.&lt;ref&gt;Peebles 1999, p. 132.&lt;/ref&gt;

The fate of the D-21 that had disappeared on the first operational flight was finally revealed in February 1986 when an official from the CIA returned a panel to [[Ben Rich]] that he had been given by a Soviet [[KGB]] agent. The drone had self-destructed over Siberia and the Soviets had recovered the wreckage.&lt;ref&gt;Peebles 1999, p. 134.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Tupolev]] design bureau [[reverse-engineered]] the wreck and produced plans for a Soviet copy, named the ''Voron'' (Raven), but it was never built.&lt;ref&gt;Gordon and Rigamant 2005, pp. 325–27.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the late 1990s [[NASA]] considered using a D-21 to test a hybrid &quot;[[rocket-based combined cycle]]&quot; engine, which operates as a ramjet or rocket, depending on its flight regime. Ultimately NASA used a derivative of the agency's [[NASA X-43|X-43A]] hypersonic test vehicle for the experiments.&lt;ref&gt;Landis and Jenkins 2005, pp. 28–29.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aircraft on display==
[[File:D21-070308.jpg|thumb|D-21 on display at the Blackbird Airpark, Air Force [[Plant 42]], [[Palmdale, California]] |alt=]]
[[File:MD-21 Blackbird rearview.jpg|thumb|A close-up rear view of D-21 on M-21 at the [[Museum of Flight]] in Seattle |alt=]]
[[File:Lockheed D21a and M21.jpg|thumb|[[SR-71]] and D-21 at the [[Pima Air &amp; Space Museum]], Tucson, Arizona |alt=]]

* [[309th Aerospace Maintenance and Regeneration Group|Aerospace Maintenance and Regeneration Group (AMARG)]] located on [[Davis-Monthan AFB]], Tucson, Arizona (D-21 #530&lt;ref name=Pace_p64&gt;Pace 2004, p. 64.&lt;/ref&gt; and two more&lt;ref&gt;Google and Bing Maps imagery as of 26 May 2012&lt;/ref&gt;)
* Blackbird Airpark, [[Palmdale, California]] (D-21B #525)&lt;ref name=Pace_p64/&gt;
* [[Chinese Aviation Museum]], Beijing, China (D-21 #527)&lt;ref&gt;[https://secure.flickr.com/photos/zaruka/4917830245/in/set-72157624660623125/ &quot;Lockheed D-21 No.&amp;nbsp;527 SR-71 Drone&quot;]. ''flickr.com'', 5 August 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Evergreen Aviation Museum]], [[McMinnville, Oregon]] (GTD-21B #534)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.evergreenmuseum.org/#/aircraft-exhibits/military-aircraft/support-aircraft|title=Support Aircraft |publisher=Evergreen Aviation Museum |accessdate=15 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Grissom Air Museum]], [[Grissom Air Reserve Base]], Peru, Indiana (GTD-21B #528)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.grissomairmuseum.com/?page_id=341|title=Lockheed GTD-21 Tagboard Drone |publisher=Grissom Air Museum|accessdate=15 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[March Field Air Museum]], [[March Air Reserve Base]], [[Riverside, California]] (D-21B #537)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.marchfield.org/d21drone.htm|title=Lockheed D-21B (#537) Drone |publisher=March Field Air Museum |accessdate=15 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Museum of Aviation (Warner Robins)|Museum of Aviation]], [[Robins Air Force Base]], [[Georgia (U.S. state)|Georgia]] (GTD-21B #538)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.museumofaviation.org/D21.php|title=Lockheed D-21B Unmanned Aerial Vehicle (UAV) |publisher=Museum of Aviation |accessdate=5 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Museum of Flight]], [[Seattle]], Washington (D-21 No.&amp;nbsp;510 mounted on remaining M-21 #60-6940)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.museumofflight.org/aircraft/lockheed-d-21b-drone |title=Lockheed D-21B Drone |publisher=The Museum of Flight |accessdate=5 April 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[National Museum of the United States Air Force]], [[Wright-Patterson Air Force Base]], [[Ohio]] (D-21B #524)&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.nationalmuseum.af.mil/factsheets/factsheet_print.asp?fsID=396&amp;page=1 |title=U.S. Air Force Fact Sheet Lockheed D-21B |publisher=National Museum of the US Air Force|accessdate=2 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Pacific Coast Air Museum]], [[Sonoma County, California]] (D-21B #522) &lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.pressdemocrat.com/article/20090704/ARTICLES/907049953?p=1&amp;tc=pg |title=Cold War drone comes to Sonoma County |date=July 4, 2009 |author=Bob Norberg |work=Press Democrat}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Pima Air &amp; Space Museum]] (adjacent to [[Davis-Monthan AFB]]), [[Tucson, Arizona]] (D-21B #533) &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pimaair.org/collection-detail.php?cid=151 |title=Lockheed D-21B |publisher=Pima Air &amp; Space Museum |accessdate=15 March 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Specifications (D-21)==
;D-21A and D-21B without booster
*'''[[Wingspan]]:''' 19&amp;nbsp;ft 1/4 in (5.79 m)
*'''Length:''' 42&amp;nbsp;ft 10 in (12.8 m)
*'''Height:''' 7&amp;nbsp;ft 1/4 in (2.14 m)
*'''Launch weight:''' 11,000&amp;nbsp;lb (5,000&amp;nbsp;kg)
*'''Maximum speed:''' Mach 3.35 (2,210&amp;nbsp;mph, 1,920 knots, 3,560&amp;nbsp;km/h)
*'''Service ceiling:''' 95,000&amp;nbsp;ft (29,000 m)
*'''Range:''' 3,000&amp;nbsp;nmi, 3,450&amp;nbsp;mi, 5,550&amp;nbsp;km
*'''Engine:''' 1 x [[Marquardt RJ43|Marquardt RJ43-MA-20S4]] [[ramjet]], 1,500&amp;nbsp;lbf (6.67&amp;nbsp;kN)

Sources: Pace,&lt;ref&gt;Pace 2004, p. 63.&lt;/ref&gt; Landis &amp; Jenkins,&lt;ref name=Landis_p23-25&gt;Landis and Jenkins 2005, pp. 23–25.&lt;/ref&gt; Donald&lt;ref name=Donald_p154-5&gt;Donald 2003, pp. 154–55.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Aircontent
|see also=
|related=
* [[Lockheed A-12]]
* [[Lockheed YF-12]]
* [[Lockheed SR-71 Blackbird]]

|similar aircraft=
|lists=
* [[List of military aircraft of the United States]]
* [[List of Lockheed aircraft]]
}}

==References==

===Citations===
{{Reflist|30em}}

===Bibliography===
* {{cite book |title=Black Jets |editor=Donald, David |publisher=AIRtime Publishing|location=Norwalk, Connecticut |year=2003 |chapter=Lockheed's Blackbirds: A-12, YF-12 and SR-71 |isbn=1-880588-67-6}}
* {{cite journal |last=Goodall |first=James C. and Nora D. |year=2002 |title=Senior Bowl–the Lockeed D-21 |journal=International Air Power Review |publisher=AIRtime Publishing |location=Norwalk, Connecticut |volume=3 |pages=106–119 |issn=1473-9917}}
* {{cite book|last=Gordon|first=Yefim|author2=Rigamant, Vladimir |title=OKB Tupolev: A History of the Design Bureau and its Aircraft|publisher=Midland Publishing|location=Hinckley, England|year=2005|isbn=1-85780-214-4}}
* {{cite book |last=Landis |first=Tony R. |author2=Dennis R. Jenkins  |title=Lockheed Blackbirds |publisher=Specialty Press |location=North Branch, Minnesota |year=2005 |edition=Revised |series=Warbird Tech |volume=10 |isbn=1-58007-086-8}}
* {{cite book|last=Miller|first=Jay|title=Lockheed Martin's Skunk Works|publisher=Midland Publishing|location=Leicester, England|year=1995|edition=Revised|isbn=1-85780-037-0}}
* {{cite book|last=Pace|first=Steve |title=Lockheed SR-71 Blackbird |publisher=Crowood Press |location=Swindon |year=2004 |isbn=1-86126-697-9}}
* {{cite book|last=Peebles|first=Curtiss|title=Dark Eagles: A History of Top Secret U.S. Aircraft Programs|publisher=Presidio Press|location=Novato, California|year=1999|edition=Revised|isbn=0-89141-696-X}}
* {{cite book|last=Rich |first=Ben |author2=Janos, Leo  |title=Skunk Works |publisher=Little, Brown &amp; Company|location=Boston |year=1996 |isbn=0-316-74300-3}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|D-21}}
* [http://www.wvi.com/~sr71webmaster/M21_Crash.htm Loss of M-21 and D-21, including video of successful launches and the midair collision]
*[http://www.designation-systems.net/dusrm/app4/d-21.html Directory of U.S. Military Rockets and Missiles]
*[http://muller.lbl.gov/TRessays/04_Weapons_Precise_Destru.htm Weapons of Precise Destruction]
*[http://www.airforceworld.com/others/D21-mach-3-supersonic-reconnaissance-plane-crashed-in-china.html Photos of Lockheed D-21B No.&amp;nbsp;527 in China Aviation Museum, Beijing]

{{Lockheed}}
{{Good article}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2011}}

[[Category:Lockheed aircraft|D-021]]
[[Category:United States military reconnaissance aircraft 1960–1969]]
[[Category:Unmanned military aircraft of the United States]]
[[Category:Single-engined jet aircraft]]
[[Category:Ramjet-powered aircraft]]
[[Category:Tailless delta-wing aircraft]]
[[Category:Parasite aircraft]]
[[Category:Stealth aircraft]]
[[Category:Black projects]]
[[Category:Composite aircraft]] &lt;!-- M21 with D.21 --&gt;</text>
      <sha1>ngl7nboop8sbk0uup4vxke1s4sp2i68</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
