<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Nguyễn Văn Nhung</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>10591031</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738465242</id>
      <parentid>730636449</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-09T03:24:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SCFoxJD</username>
        <id>15336816</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="14838">{{Vietnamese name|Nguyễn|Nguyen|Nhung}}
{{Infobox military person
|name=Nguyễn Văn Nhung 
|birth_date=1919 or 1920
|death_date= 31 January 1964
|image= 
|birth_place= [[French Indochina]]
|death_place= [[Ho Chi Minh City|Saigon, South Vietnam]]
|nickname=
|allegiance=[[South Vietnam]]
|branch=[[French Army]] (1944-49)&lt;br&gt;[[Vietnamese National Army]] (1949-55)&lt;br&gt;[[Army of the Republic of Vietnam]] (1955-63)
|serviceyears=
|rank=[[Major]]
|commands=
|unit=
|battles=[[First Indochina War]]&lt;br&gt;[[Arrest and assassination of Ngo Dinh Diem|Ngô Đình Diệm]], [[Ngô Đình Nhu]] and [[Lê Quang Tung]]
|laterwork=Aide-de-camp and bodyguard of General [[Dương Văn Minh]], military hitman who assassinated or executed 50 people}}

Major '''Nguyễn Văn Nhung''' (1919 or 1920 &amp;ndash; 31 January 1964) was an officer in the [[Army of the Republic of Vietnam]] (ARVN). After joining the [[French Army]] in 1944 during the [[French Indochina|colonial era of Vietnam]], he soon met and became the ''[[aide-de-camp]]'' and bodyguard of [[Dương Văn Minh]], and spent the rest of his career in this role as Minh rose up the ranks to become a general. Nhung and Minh later transferred to the French-backed [[Vietnamese National Army]] (VNA) during the [[First Indochina War]] and he became an officer; the VNA then became the ARVN after the creation of the Republic of Vietnam ([[South Vietnam]]). A soft-spoken man, Nhung was a professional military [[hitman]] who was reputed to have etched a line on his [[revolver]] for each of his killings, and ended the lives of 50 people during his career.&lt;ref&gt;Hammer, p. 298.&lt;/ref&gt;

Nhung was best known for his role in the [[1963 South Vietnamese coup|November 1963 ''coup d'état'']] led by Minh that ousted President [[Ngô Đình Diệm]] from office. At the end of the coup, Nhung - having shot Colonel [[Lê Quang Tung]], the loyalist commander of the [[Army of the Republic of Vietnam Special Forces]] at a grave at [[Tan Son Nhut Air Base|Tân Sơn Nhứt Air Base]] the day before - executed Diệm and his brother [[Ngô Đình Nhu]]. An investigation led by General [[Trần Văn Đôn]], another coup plotter, determined that Nhung had repeatedly stabbed and shot the Ngô brothers while escorting them back to military headquarters after having arrested them. It was widely believed that Minh had ordered Nhung to execute the Ngô brothers. Following [[Nguyễn Khánh]]'s successful [[1964 South Vietnamese coup|January 1964 coup]] against Minh's [[military junta]], Nhung died in mysterious circumstances, the only rebel fatality in the regime change.

==Early career==
Nhung was born in either 1919 or early 1920.&lt;ref name=n1/&gt; At the time, Vietnam was a French colony within [[French Indochina]]; and, in 1944, Nhung joined the French Army, where he soon met [[Dương Văn Minh]], who became his superior for the next two decades. Nhung would spend most of his career as Minh's ''aide-de-camp'' and bodyguard. He was described as a quiet and slightly built man who smoked a pipe.&lt;ref name=n1/&gt; Following the end of World War II, the French set up the [[State of Vietnam]], an associated state within the [[French Union]], and created the [[Vietnamese National Army]] (VNA), and both Minh and Nhung transferred to the VNA, where they were trained and commissioned as officers. As of November 1963, Nhung had risen to the rank of captain.&lt;ref name=n1/&gt;

==Tung assassination==
[[File:Ngo Dinh Diem - Thumbnail - ARC 542189.png|thumb|right|Ngô Đình Diệm, the President of South Vietnam.|alt=A portrait of a middle-aged man, looking to the left in a half-portrait/profile. He has chubby cheeks, parts his hair to the side and wears a suit and tie.]]

On 1 November 1963, a group of ARVN generals, led by Minh, orchestrated a coup against President [[Ngô Đình Diệm]]. The plotters summoned a group of ARVN officers to the Joint General Staff headquarters at [[Tan Son Nhut Air Base|Tân Sơn Nhứt Air Base]], on the pretext that they were going to attend a lunch meeting.&lt;ref name=&quot;j408&quot;&gt;Jones, p. 408.&lt;/ref&gt; Among those invited was the loyalist commander of the [[Army of the Republic of Vietnam Special Forces]], Colonel [[Lê Quang Tung]]. At 13:30 ([[UTC]] 06:30), General [[Trần Văn Đôn]] announced that a coup was taking place. Most of the officers rose to applaud, but Tung did not, refusing to join the coup. He was taken away by Nhung, all the while shouting, “Remember who gave you your stars!”&lt;ref name=&quot;j408&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;encyc&quot;&gt;Tucker, p. 227.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ks&quot;/&gt;

At 16:45, Tung was forced at gunpoint to talk to Diệm on the phone, telling the president that he had ordered his special forces to surrender. Minh then ordered Nhung to execute the Diệm loyalist. Tung had failed to convince the president to surrender and still commanded the loyalty of his men. The other generals had little sympathy for Tung, because the special forces' commander had disguised his men in regular army uniforms and framed the generals for the [[Xá Lợi Pagoda raids]] in August.&lt;ref name=&quot;j414&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hammer, p. 290.&lt;/ref&gt; The generals were well aware of the threat that Tung posed; they had discussed his elimination during their planning,&lt;ref&gt;Karnow, p. 310.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jones, p. 325.&lt;/ref&gt; having contemplated waging an offensive against his special forces.&lt;ref&gt;Jones, p. 388.&lt;/ref&gt; At nightfall, Nhung took Tung, and his brother and deputy, Major Lê Quang Triệu,&lt;ref name=&quot;encyc&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ks&quot;&gt;Karnow, p. 321.&lt;/ref&gt; with their hands tied, to a jeep and drove them to the edge of the air base. Forced to kneel over two freshly dug holes, the brothers were shot into their graves and buried.&lt;ref name=&quot;j414&quot;&gt;Jones, p. 414.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Diệm and Nhu assassination==
{{see also|1963 South Vietnamese coup|Arrest and assassination of Ngô Đình Diệm}}
[[File:LBJ nhu.jpg|thumb|right|Ngô Đình Nhu ''(pictured)'' shaking hands with United States Vice President [[Lyndon B. Johnson]].|alt=Tall Caucasian man standing in profile at left in a white suit and tie shakes hands with a smaller black-haired Asian man in a white shirt, dark suit and tie.]]
By the next morning, the loyalist forces had collapsed. Diệm and his younger brother and chief adviser, [[Ngô Đình Nhu]], agreed to surrender, and coup plotter Đôn promised them safe passage out of the country.&lt;ref&gt;Karnow, p. 322.&lt;/ref&gt; In the meantime, Minh left Joint General Staff (JGS) headquarters and travelled to [[Gia Long Palace]] in a sedan, accompanied by Nhung. He arrived at the palace at 08:00 in full military uniform to supervise the arrest of Diệm and Nhu for the surrender ceremony.&lt;ref name=&quot;j418&quot;/&gt;

However, the Ngô brothers were not there&amp;mdash;they had escaped from [[Gia Long Palace]] via a secret tunnel to a safehouse in [[Cholon]] the previous night.&lt;ref name=&quot;j418&quot;&gt;Jones, p. 418.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hammer, p. 293.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;k323&quot;&gt;Karnow, p. 323.&lt;/ref&gt; Diệm and Nhu had communicated with the generals via a direct phone link from the safehouse to the palace, giving the false impression that they were still besieged.&lt;ref name=&quot;k323&quot;/&gt; Having been informed of Diệm and Nhu’s whereabouts, Minh dispatched a group of officers and troops&amp;mdash;which included Nhung&amp;mdash;to arrest them. He was aware that the brothers had left the safehouse to go to St. Francis Xavier's Church. Led by General [[Mai Hữu Xuân]], the officers took an [[M113 armored personnel carrier]] (APC), four jeeps, and several soldiers to Cholon. As they left, Minh gestured to Nhung with two fingers, taken to be an order to shoot the brothers.&lt;ref name=&quot;k323&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jones, pp. 416-17.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Diem dead.jpg|right|thumbnail|200px|The corpse of [[Ngô Đình Diệm]] in the back of an armoured personnel carrier|alt=Middle-aged black-haired man lies face half-down on the floor, covered on his face and dark suit and trousers with blood. His hands are behind his back.]]
The soldiers arrived at the church and promptly arrested the brothers, tying them with their hands behind their backs. After the arrest, Nhung and Major [[Dương Hiếu Nghĩa]] sat with Diệm and Nhu inside the APC, and the [[convoy]] departed for Tân Sơn Nhứt. They stopped at a railroad crossing on the return trip where, by all accounts, the brothers were assassinated. An investigation by Đôn later determined that Nghĩa had shot the brothers at [[point-blank range]] with a [[semi-automatic firearm]] and that Nhung sprayed them with bullets before repeatedly stabbing their bodies with a knife.&lt;ref name=&quot;k326&quot;&gt;Karnow, p. 326.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the journey back, Nghĩa gave his account of the assassinations to military headquarters: “As we rode back to the Joint General Staff headquarters, Diệm sat silently, but Nhu and the captain [Nhung] began to insult each other. I don’t know who started it. The name-calling grew passionate. The captain had hated Nhu before. Now he was charged with emotion.”&lt;ref name=&quot;j429&quot;/&gt; When the convoy reached a train crossing, Nghĩa said that Nhung “lunged at Nhu with a bayonet and stabbed him again and again, maybe fifteen or twenty times. Still in a rage, he turned to Diệm, took out his revolver and shot him in the head. Then he looked back at Nhu, who was lying on the floor, twitching. He put a bullet into his head too. Neither Diệm nor Nhu ever defended themselves. Their hands were tied.”&lt;ref name=&quot;j429&quot;/&gt;

Đôn and other officers were stunned when the corpses arrived at JGS headquarters. Đôn confronted Minh in his office, and while they were remonstrating, Xuân entered the room. Unaware of Đôn's presence, Xuân snapped [[At attention|to attention]] and stated in French, ''“Mission accomplie”''.&lt;ref name=&quot;j429&quot;&gt;Jones, p. 429.&lt;/ref&gt; Despite Đôn's investigation,&lt;ref name=&quot;k326&quot;/&gt; no one was ever charged with the killings.&lt;ref&gt;Jones, p. 180.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Death==
{{see also|1964 South Vietnamese coup}}
Following the coup, Nhung's commanding officer, General Minh, became the President of South Vietnam, ruling through a [[military junta]] known as the Military Revolutionary Council.&lt;ref name=&quot;pp&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=The Overthrow of Ngo Dinh Diem, May–November, 1963|series=[[Pentagon Papers]]|publisher=[[Daniel Ellsberg]]|url=http://www.mtholyoke.edu/acad/intrel/pentagon2/pent6.htm|pages=201–76|accessdate=2008-06-10}}&lt;/ref&gt; After three months of rule, which was criticised for its lack of direction,&lt;ref&gt;Shaplen, p. 213.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=k&gt;Karnow, pp. 350-54.&lt;/ref&gt; General [[Nguyễn Khánh]] deposed Minh in a bloodless coup before dawn on 30 January 1964. Minh was briefly put under [[house arrest]],&lt;ref name=k/&gt; and the next day, reports surfaced that Nhung was dead, the only fatality in the coup or its aftermath.&lt;ref name=n1/&gt;

There was initially confusion as various conflicting reports of Nhung's demise surfaced, one source telling journalists that Nhung lived in a cottage within the grounds of Minh's villa and shot himself outside his house.&lt;ref name=n1/&gt; These informants speculated that Nhung committed suicide to avoid having to live to see Minh being demoted or humiliated.&lt;ref name=n1/&gt; The time of this incident was reported to be 21:00.&lt;ref name=n3&gt;{{cite news|author=Grose, Peter|work=[[The New York Times]]|date=1964-09-04|title=Crisis in Vietnam: How It Developed|page=1}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=n4&gt;{{cite news|author=Butterfield, Fox|work=[[The New York Times]]|date=1971-11-04|title=Man Who Sheltered Diem Recounts '63 Episode|page=5}}&lt;/ref&gt; Other reports at the time said that Nhung was found dead as a result of strangulation at the Joint General Staff headquarters. According to variations of this line, Nhung either hanged himself in custody or was murdered by an unknown hand.&lt;ref name=n5&gt;{{cite news|author=Shaplen, Robert|work=[[The New York Times]]|date=1972-05-14|title=The Cult of Diem|page=SM16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

More recently, historians have come to believe that Khánh ordered that Nhung be liquidated and that the earlier reports were deliberately false material disseminated by Khánh through his subordinates. According to this now-established account, one of Khánh's men took Nhung to the garden of a Saigon villa and forced him to kneel, before executing him with a single gunshot to the back of the head. Nhung's death led to protests among the Saigon public, who took the killing to be a signal that the remaining members of Diệm's regime would be reinstated to positions of authority.&lt;ref name=&quot;d&quot;&gt;Karnow, pp. 354-55.&lt;/ref&gt;

Nhung was buried on 1 February, the day after his death, in the presence of family and friends, at Gia Đính cemetery.&lt;ref name=n1&gt;{{cite news|author=Grose, Peter|work=[[The New York Times]]|date=1964-02-02|title=Diem's death laid to Saigon Major|page=14}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nhung's death was never formally investigated by an independent body and the official line of suicide continued to be propagated.&lt;ref name=n4/&gt;

Minh was said to have been deeply affected by the loss of his long-time aide, and it was reported that the general erected an altar dedicated to Nhung's memory in his office, with the major's portrait on it.&lt;ref name=n3/&gt; Shortly after the coup, Khánh made Minh the figurehead head of state under American advice, hoping that the presence of the popular general would help to unify the armed forces, but Minh made little attempt to help Khánh, partly because of resentment over the loss of his aide.&lt;ref name=n3/&gt;

== References ==
=== Citations ===
{{Reflist|20em}}

=== Sources ===
* {{cite book |title=A Death in November |authorlink=Ellen Hammer |first=Ellen J.|last=Hammer |year=1987 |publisher=E. P. Dutton |ISBN = 0-525-24210-4 |location=New York City}}
* {{cite book |first=Howard |last=Jones |year=2003 |title= Death of a Generation |publisher=Oxford University Press |ISBN = 0-19-505286-2 |location=New York City}}
* {{cite book |title=Vietnam: A history |first=Stanley |last=Karnow |authorlink=Stanley Karnow |year=1997 |publisher=Penguin Books |ISBN = 0-670-84218-4 |location=New York City}}
* {{cite book |first=Robert |last=Shaplen |title=The lost revolution: Vietnam 1945&amp;ndash;1965  |year=1965 |publisher=André Deutsch |location=London}}
* {{cite book |title = Encyclopedia of the Vietnam War |first = Spencer C. |last=Tucker |year=2000 |publisher=ABC-CLIO |ISBN = 1-57607-040-9 |location = Santa Barbara, California}}
{{Buddhist crisis}}

{{good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Nguyen, Van Nhung}}
[[Category:1964 deaths]]
[[Category:Murder in 1963]]
[[Category:Deaths by firearm in Vietnam]]
[[Category:Assassinated military personnel]]
[[Category:Vietnamese anti-communists]]
[[Category:South Vietnamese military personnel of the Vietnam War]]
[[Category:Vietnamese assassins]]
[[Category:Assassins of heads of state]]
[[Category:Date of birth unknown]]
[[Category:Place of birth missing]]
[[Category:Year of birth uncertain]]</text>
      <sha1>8kx85zieyvmsm5855vi5exeayi3fpgu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
