<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Operation Paravane</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>11384647</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749254561</id>
      <parentid>749188907</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-13T09:17:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Nick-D</username>
        <id>415269</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Planning */ tweak</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="46595">{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Operation Paravane
| partof      = [[World War II]]
| image       = [[File:British Avro Lancaster bomber over Kaafjord during Operation Paravane.jpg|300px|alt=Black and white photo of a four-engined aircraft viewed from above while flying over a narrow body of water|A British Lancaster bomber over Kaafjord during Operation Paravane]]
| caption     = A British Lancaster bomber over Kaafjord during Operation Paravane
| date        = 15 September 1944
| place       = [[Kåfjorden (Alta)|Kaafjord]], Norway
| coordinates = 
| map_type    = 
| map_relief  = 
| latitude    = 
| longitude   = 
| map_size    = 
| map_marksize = 
| map_caption = 
| map_label   = 
| territory   = 
| result = British victory
| status =
| combatant1 = {{flagu|United Kingdom}}
| combatant2 = {{flagcountry|Nazi Germany|1935}}
| combatant3  = 
| commander1 = {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Colin McMullen|C.C. McMullen]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[James Brian Tait|Willie Tait]]
| commander2 =  {{flagicon|Nazi Germany|1935}} [[Rudolf Peters]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany|1935}} [[Wolf Junge]]{{sfn|Bishop|2012|pp=339, 341}}
| commander3  = 
| units1      = 
| units2      = 
| units3      = 
| strength1   = 
| strength2   = 
| strength3   = 
| casualties1 = 11 killed
| casualties2 = 1 battleship heavily damaged&lt;br&gt;5 killed, 15 wounded
| casualties3 = 
| notes       = 
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Norwegian Campaigns (1941 - 1945)}}
}}
'''Operation Paravane''' was a British air raid of [[World War II]] that inflicted heavy damage on the [[German battleship Tirpitz|German battleship ''Tirpitz'']]. The attack was conducted on 15 September 1944 by 21 [[Royal Air Force]] [[heavy bomber]]s, which flew from an airfield in the north of the [[Soviet Union]]. The battleship was struck by one bomb, and further damaged by several near misses. This damage rendered ''Tirpitz'' unfit for combat, and she could not be repaired as it was no longer practical for the Germans to sail her to a major port.

The attack on 15 September followed a series of raids conducted against ''Tirpitz'' by [[Royal Navy]] aircraft carriers between April and August 1944 that sought to sink or disable the battleship at her anchorage in [[Kåfjorden (Alta)|Kaafjord]] in the far north of Norway, so that she no longer posed a threat to Allied convoys travelling to and from the Soviet Union. While the first of these raids was successful, the other attacks failed due to shortcomings with the [[Fleet Air Arm]]'s strike aircraft and the formidable German defences. As a result, the task of attacking the battleship was transferred to the RAF's [[RAF Bomber Command|Bomber Command]]. [[Avro Lancaster]] bombers from the Command's two elite squadrons flew to their staging airfield in the Soviet Union on the night of 11/12 September, and attacked on 15 September using heavy bombs and air-dropped mines. All of the British aircraft returned to base, though one of the Lancasters later crashed during its flight back to the United Kingdom.

Following Operation Paravane, the German Navy's commander decided to use ''Tirpitz'' as a static artillery battery at the town of [[Tromsø]]. The Allies were unable to confirm the extent of the battleship's damage, and conducted two further heavy bomber raids against her in late 1944. ''Tirpitz'' was sunk with heavy loss of life on 12 November during the second of these attacks.

==Background==
{{see also|List of Allied attacks on the German battleship Tirpitz}}
From early 1942, ''Tirpitz'' posed a significant threat to the [[Arctic convoys of World War II|Allied convoys]] transporting supplies through the [[Norwegian Sea]] to the Soviet Union. Stationed in [[fjord]]s on the Norwegian coast, the battleship was capable of overwhelming the close-escort forces assigned to the Arctic convoys or breaking out into the North Atlantic.{{sfn|Ellis|1999|pp=294–295}} To counter this threat, the Allies needed to keep a powerful force of warships with the British [[Home Fleet]], and [[capital ship]]s accompanied most convoys part of the way to the Soviet Union.{{sfn|Bennett|2012|p=9}}{{sfn|Faulkner|Wilkinson|2012|p=109}}

[[Royal Air Force]] (RAF) heavy bombers conducted a series of unsuccessful raids on ''Tirpitz'' shortly after the battleship arrived in Norway from Germany in January 1942. ''Tirpitz'' was initially based at [[Fættenfjord]] near [[Trondheim]], which lay within range of British bombers flying from Scotland.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|pp=14–16}} The first raid took place on 30 January, and involved nine [[Handley Page Halifax]] and seven [[Short Stirling]] bombers. Due to cloud over the target area, only one of the bombers sighted ''Tirpitz'' and none inflicted any damage. One Halifax crashed into the sea on its way back to Scotland, but its crew were rescued.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|pp=16–17, 170}} The next raid on Fættenfjord took place on 30 March, with the attacking force comprising 33 Halifaxes. However, the operation was again frustrated by heavy clouds over the target area and none of the aircrew sighted ''Tirpitz''. Four of the Halifaxes were shot down, and two others crashed while returning to base.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|p=27}} Another attack was mounted by 30 Halifaxes and 11 [[Avro Lancaster]]s on the night of 27/28 April. While ''Tirpitz'' was located and attacked by the aircraft of the first wave, no damage was inflicted and five heavy bombers were lost.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|pp=31–33, 170}} The final raid in this series took place the next night, and involved 21 Halifaxes and 12 Lancasters. The attackers found ''Tirpitz'' covered in a protective smokescreen, and the battleship again escaped damage; two British aircraft were destroyed.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|pp=33–34, 170}} 
[[File:The Royal Navy during the Second World War A22634.jpg|thumb|left|upright=1.2|alt=Black and white photograph of a World War II-era warship in a small bay with a steep and snow-covered shoreline. Clouds of smoke are being blown from the shoreline towards the ship.|A British aerial reconnaissance photograph of ''Tirpitz'' moored at Kaafjord in northern Norway. The artificial smoke generators on the shores of the fjord have not yet obscured her.]]

While plans for further heavy bomber attacks on ''Tirpitz'' were developed throughout 1942, none took place.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|p=43}} One of the options considered during this period was to stage the bombers through a base in the northern Soviet Union, but this was judged impractical as little was known about the suitability of Soviet airfields for heavy bombers at the time.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|pp=46–47}} Two squadrons of [[RAF Coastal Command]] [[Handley Page Hampden]] torpedo bombers operated from [[Severomorsk|Vaenga]] in northern Russia during mid-September 1942 to counter ''Tirpitz'' or any other German warships which attempted to attack Allied convoys, but these aircraft did not make contact with the enemy.{{sfn|Herington|1954|pp=295–297}}

Further plans for air attacks on ''Tirpitz'' were developed during 1943, but none eventuated. During 1942 and 1943 British inventor [[Barnes Wallis]] attempted to develop a version of his &quot;[[bouncing bomb]]&quot; concept for use against ''Tirpitz'' alongside the larger weapons which were successfully used to attack several German dams during [[Operation Chastise]] on 16/17 May 1943.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|p=51}}  [[No. 618 Squadron RAF|No. 618 Squadron]] was formed in April 1943 equipped with [[de Havilland Mosquito]]s to execute this attack, but trials of the &quot;Highball&quot; bouncing bombs during the year were unsuccessful and the plan was abandoned in September.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=618 Squadron|url=http://www.raf.mod.uk/history/618squadron.cfm|website=Historical Structure of the Royal Air Force|publisher=Royal Air Force|accessdate=30 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|pp=51–52}} In the meantime, ''Tirpitz'' was transferred to a new base at [[Kåfjorden (Alta)|Kaafjord]] in the far north of Norway in late May 1943.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|p=52}} This anchorage was well protected, with the defences including equipment capable of rapidly generating an artificial smokescreen as well as a large number of anti-aircraft guns located in shore batteries and warships.{{sfn|Tactical, Torpedo and Staff Duties Division (Historical Section)|2012|p=135}} During June 1943 consideration was given to attacking the battleship with [[United States Army Air Forces]] [[Boeing B-17 Flying Fortress]] heavy bombers flying from the United Kingdom and landing in the Soviet Union, before making another attack on their return flight. However, such a mission was judged to be impractical by the RAF as it was expected that German fighter aircraft would heavily attack the bombers and ''Tirpitz'' would be covered by a smokescreen by the time they arrived over the target area.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|p=53}} The only attack made against ''Tirpitz'' by land-based aircraft prior to September 1944 was a small raid conducted by 15 Soviet bombers on the night of 10/11 February 1944 which did not inflict any damage on the battleship.{{sfn|Bishop|2012|p=295}}

The Royal Navy repeatedly attacked ''Tirpitz'' at Kaafjord from September 1943 until August 1944. On 23 September 1943 the crews of two British midget submarines succeeded in penetrating the defences around the battleship during [[Operation Source]], and placed explosive charges in the water beneath her. This attack caused extensive damage to ''Tirpitz'', putting her out of service for six months.{{sfn|Woodman|2004|p=340}} Further midget submarine attacks were considered infeasible, and an air raid designated [[Operation Tungsten]] was conducted by Royal Navy aircraft carriers as repairs to the battleship neared completion on 3 April 1944. ''Tirpitz'' did not suffer heavy damage in this operation, but was placed out of action for several additional months while repairs were completed.{{sfn|Bennett|2012|pp=14–17}}{{sfn|Garzke|Dulin|1985|p=267}} The Home Fleet sortied to attack Kaafjord on a further four occasions between April and July; all but the last of these operations were frustrated by bad weather, and the [[Operation Mascot]] raid on 17 July did not inflict any damage on ''Tirpitz''.{{sfn|Roskill|1961|pp=156, 170}} Four further carrier attacks targeting ''Tirpitz'' were undertaken between 22 and 29 August during [[Operation Goodwood (naval)|Operation Goodwood]], but again resulted in only minor damage to the battleship.{{sfn|Roskill|1961|pp=159–161}}

==Planning==
{{Location map+ | Russia Northwestern Federal District|relief=1
|caption = The location of Kaafjord in northern Norway and Yagodnik in the Soviet Union
| places =
  {{Location map~ | Russia Northwestern Federal District
    | label = Kaafjord
    | lat_deg = 69.9353
    | lon_deg = 23.0454 }}
  {{Location map~ | Russia Northwestern Federal District
    | label = Yagodnik
    | lat_deg = 64.402778
    | lon_deg = 40.888611 }}
}}
The failure of the Royal Navy raids conducted between April and August 1944 was attributed by senior Royal Navy officers to shortcomings with the [[Fleet Air Arm|Fleet Air Arm's]] main attack aircraft, the [[Fairey Barracuda]]. While Operation Tungsten succeeded because the Germans were taken by surprise, during the subsequent raids the slow speed of the Barracudas gave Kaafjord's defenders time to cover the area with artificial smoke before incoming raids arrived over the target area. Moreover, the Barracudas were unable to carry bombs large enough to significantly damage ''Tirpitz'' when hits were achieved.{{sfn|Roskill|1961|pp=156, 161}} As a result, before and after Operation Goodwood, further consideration was given to using Mosquitos to attack the battleship; under initial plans developed in mid-August these aircraft would have been launched from aircraft carriers, attacking ''Tirpitz'' with {{convert|2000|lb|kg|adj=on}} or {{convert|4000|lb|kg|adj=on}} armour-piercing bombs before landing in northern Russia.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|pp=86–87}} These proposals came to nothing as the Supreme Allied Commander of the Allied Expeditionary Force General [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]] was unwilling to release any Mosquitos in July,{{#tag:ref|Eisenhower was involved in this decision as [[RAF Bomber Command]] was under his command at the time to support the [[Operation Overlord|invasion of Normandy]].{{sfn|Bishop|2012|p=316}}|group=Note}} and in August the Mosquitos were also judged to be too slow to successfully reach Kaafjord from aircraft carriers before it was covered by smoke.{{sfn|Roskill|1961|p=156}}{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|p=88}}

In August [[RAF Bomber Command]], which controlled the force's heavy bombers, began developing plans to strike ''Tirpitz'' at Kaafjord. In a meeting held on 28 August between the commander of RAF Bomber Command, Air Chief Marshal [[Sir Arthur Harris, 1st Baronet|Sir Arthur Harris]], and Vice-Chief of the Air Staff Air Marshal [[Douglas Evill]] to discuss the feasibility of dispatching Mosquitos against Kaafjord, Harris stated that he had a plan to attack the battleship with Lancaster bombers ready.{{sfn|Bishop|2012|pp=317, 319}} Under this plan, 24 Lancasters were to depart from a base in the far north of Scotland, bomb ''Tirpitz'' and return to an airstrip in the [[Shetland Islands]]. If the return trip was not judged feasible, the bombers would instead land at [[Murmansk]] in northern Russia before returning to the United Kingdom. Bomber Command's staff had contacted Soviet officials about the latter element of the plan, and concluded that it would be feasible. Due to the complex nature of the mission Bomber Command's two elite special duties units, [[No. 9 Squadron RAF|No. 9]] and [[No. 617 Squadron RAF|No. 617 Squadrons]], would conduct the attack. This proposal was viewed favourably, and was approved by Eisenhower's headquarters on 5 September.{{sfn|Bishop|2012|p=319}}

[[No. 5 Group RAF|No. 5 Group]] was assigned responsibility for planning the attack on ''Tirpitz'' in late August.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|p=89}} The group's staff officers judged that it was essential for the raid to surprise Kaafjord's defenders so that the battleship was not covered in smoke by the time the Lancasters arrived over the region. As the seaward approaches to the fjord were covered by a comprehensive radar network, the planners decided that the attack force should approach the region overland from the south-east and at a high speed to limit the defenders' warning time to eight minutes or less.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|p=95}} Due to the difficulty of damaging the heavily armoured battleship, the main weapon selected for this operation was the [[Tallboy (bomb)|tallboy bomb]], which was the largest bomb then in service with the RAF and capable of penetrating well protected targets.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|p=92}} In addition some of the bombers were to be armed with &quot;Johnnie Walker&quot; (commonly called &quot;JW&quot;) [[Naval mine|mines]] which were designed to be dropped from aircraft near ships and move through the water by rapidly diving and surfacing until they struck their target.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|pp=92–93}} While the Tallboy had been successfully used by No. 617 Squadron against tunnels and other facilities, the mines had not seen combat and Harris and some other senior RAF officers doubted that they would prove effective.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|pp=92, 94}}
[[File:Royal Air Force Bomber Command, 1942-1945. CH15363.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Black and white photo of a large bomb being hoisted. Two men wearing military uniforms are standing below the bomb, and steadying it with their hands.|A Tallboy bomb being hoisted from a bomb dump prior to being used in a raid during 1944.]]

As test flights conducted by No. 617 Squadron proved that it was not possible to make a return trip to Kaafjord from Scotland and an evaluation of the main airstrip in the Shetlands determined that it was unsuitable for Lancasters, No. 5 Group's staff officers judged that it would be necessary for the aircraft to refuel in the Soviet Union. Detailed investigation of the air strips near Murmansk found that they were at best marginal for heavy bombers and had almost no accommodation or aircraft servicing facilities. Moreover, the air strips were vulnerable to attack from fighters operating from nearby German bases. Instead, it was decided that the attack force should instead fly over northern Sweden and Finland after raiding Kaafjord and refuel at [[Yagodnik]] airstrip, which was located on an island near [[Arkhangelsk]]. This plan was accepted by the [[Air Ministry]] on 6 September.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|pp=95–96}} [[Soviet Naval Aviation]] offered to attack German fighter bases at the same time as the British bombers arrived over the target area, but No. 5 Group rejected this proposal and requested that Soviet aircraft not fly near Kaafjord to avoid alerting the Germans.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|p=97}}

The operation order setting out how the raid was to be conducted was issued by No. 5 Group on 7 September. It stated that Kaafjord was believed to be protected by 16 heavy and 16 light [[Anti-aircraft warfare|anti-aircraft guns]], as well as ''Tirpitz''{{'}}s guns, and that it took the defenders ten minutes to cover the battleship with a smokescreen.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|pp=97–98}} The attack force was to be organised into two groups. Force A, comprising twelve Lancasters from No. 9 Squadron and an equal number from No. 617 Squadron armed with a single Tallboy each, was to continue to Yagodnik after bombing. Force B was to be made up of six Lancasters from each of the squadrons armed with twelve JW mines each and return directly to either Scotland or the Shetland Islands. A Lancaster from the RAF Film Unit, which was attached to [[No. 463 Squadron RAAF]], would accompany Force B and also return to the United Kingdom after the bombers completed their attack. It was intended that the attack would be conducted in daylight, and that the Lancasters would assemble into formations near Kaafjord before attacking. If the fjord was found to be covered in cloud or smoke, Force A was ordered to not drop its expensive bombs and continue onto Yagodnik. Force B was directed to drop the JW mines regardless of cloud or smoke cover as long as an aiming point could be identified. The entire attack group was to maintain strict [[radio silence]].{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|p=99}} Two [[No. 511 Squadron RAF|No. 511 Squadron]] [[Consolidated B-24 Liberator]] transport aircraft were assigned to carry maintenance personnel and supplies from the United Kingdom to Yagodnik, and a Mosquito fitted for photo reconnaissance tasks from [[No. 540 Squadron RAF|No. 540 Squadron]] would scout ahead of the attack force.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|p=101}} All aircrew were briefed on this plan on either 8 or 9 September.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|p=98}} Group Captain [[Colin McMullen|C.C. McMullen]], the commander of No. 9 Squadron's home base, was appointed the overall leader of the detachment and No. 617 Squadron's commanding officer Wing Commander [[James Brian Tait|&quot;Willy&quot; Tait]] was selected to lead the strike force.{{sfn|Bishop|2012|p=331}}{{sfn|Brown|1977|p=41}}

To provide weather reports and damage assessments from Kaafjord, agents on the ground were needed, with the last radio group in the area having [[Extraction (military)|exfiltrated]] in May 1944. The first attempt at re-establishing a presence near ''Tirpitz'' occurred in August 1944, when a Norwegian [[Secret Intelligence Service]] (SIS) agent was despatched to the nearby village of [[Alta (town)|Alta]].{{#tag:ref|During World War II, the British [[Secret Intelligence Service]] cooperated with exiled Norwegian authorities in despatching more than 100 radio transmitters with Norwegian operators to German-occupied Norway. The first transmitter became operational on 10 June 1940, the same day [[Norwegian Campaign|regular fighting]] ceased in Norway. Located almost exclusively along the coast, the SIS agents primarily reported on shipping movements. In all, some 200 Norwegian SIS agents operated clandestinely in occupied Norway, supported by around 2,000 local helpers. Of the people involved, 26 agents and at least 9 locals lost their lives, either by being killed in action with German troops, being executed, or dying as a consequence of captivity.{{sfn|Nøkleby|1995|pp=371–373}}|group=Note}} The agent infiltrated with a radio transmitter codenamed &quot;Sinding&quot;  from [[Sweden during World War II|neutral Sweden]], but only managed to begin transmissions to the United Kingdom on 22 September, too late for the preparation stage for the operation.{{sfn|Nøkleby|1988|p=112}} In a second attempt at establishing an agent group in the area, the Norwegian SIS agents [[Knut Moe]] and [[Anton Arild]] were dropped by parachute into the wilderness between Kaafjord and Alta on 8 September by an American [[Operation Carpetbagger]] B-24 Liberator. During the drop the agents became separated from most of their equipment, with the exception of the radio transmitter. Without weapons and equipment, the agents were forced to relocate to the village of [[Bossekop]], where Moe's mother lived. The radio transmitter operated by the SIS team, codenamed &quot;Aslaug&quot;, was operational by 13 September, sending weather reports to the United Kingdom every other hour.{{sfn|Hafsten|Larsstuvold|Olsen|Stenersen|2005|pp=261–262}}{{sfn|Nøkleby|1988|p=112–113}} In addition to reporting on the weather, Moe and Arild radioed assessments of the damage ''Tirpitz'' had suffered in the air attacks prior to Operation Paravane.{{sfn|Pedersen|1982|p=114}} Local contacts helped the agents in spying on ''Tirpitz'' before and after the 15 September attack.{{sfn|Ulstein|1992|p=94}} By the time of the attack, Moe and Arild had established an [[observation post]] overlooking ''Tirpitz''{{'}}s anchorage in Kaafjord.{{sfn|Nøkleby|1988|p=113}}

==Preparations==
The attack force was placed on alert to launch what had been designated Operation Paravane on 8 September. As good weather was vital for the operation, the airmen waited at their home bases over the next two days while forecasts proved unfavourable.{{sfn|Bishop|2012|pp=328–329}} Over this period, the Air Ministry, No. 5 Group and British military liaison officers in the USSR continued to work with the relevant Soviet headquarters to finalise the arrangements for Force A's flight from Norway to Yagodnik.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|p=100}}

Further forecasts indicated that weather conditions at Kaafjord were changing rapidly, and during the morning of 11 September Harris judged that it would not be feasible to launch the bombers from Scotland with confidence that Kaafjord would be free of cloud by the time they arrived. Accordingly, he decided to change the plans for the operation, with all of the bombers now flying to Yagodnik first and mounting the attack from that airfield.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|p=100}}{{sfn|Bishop|2012|p=329}} Harris ordered the attack force to depart that afternoon, before advising the Air Ministry or Soviets of the change in plans.{{sfn|Bishop|2012|p=329}}

Both British bomber squadrons began to take off at 5{{nbsp}}pm local time.{{sfn|Bishop|2012|p=330}} Of the 38 aircraft assigned to the attack forces, 26 were armed with Tallboys and the remainder with JW mines. The Film Unit Lancaster carried three RAF cameramen as well as an [[Associated Press]] journalist and a radio reporter from the [[BBC]].{{sfn|Bishop|2012|p=330}} The Liberators departed just before the bombers, carrying McMullen, spare parts and maintenance personnel. The No. 540 Squadron Mosquito left the next day.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|p=101}} Despite not being notified of the new plan until after all of the Lancasters were airborne, the Soviet military quickly agreed to the changed arrangements.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|p=100}}
[[File:A No 617 Squadron Lancaster which crashed in the USSR during Operation Paravane in 1944.jpg|thumb|left|alt=A black and white photo of a large monoplane aircraft with four propeller engines on muddy ground. The aircraft's port-side landing gear is not working, and it is lying at a steep angle with a tarpaulin over its nose.|A No. 617 Squadron Lancaster which made a crash landing near the settlement of Kegostrov during the unit's flight to the USSR]]

The Lancasters' flight to Yagodnik proved difficult. After departing their home bases, the 39 aircraft flew north to the Shetlands before turning east. During the early stages of the flight one of the No. 9 Squadron Lancasters was forced to dump its Tallboy into the North Sea after it became decoupled from its mounting; the bomber subsequently returned to base.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|p=101}} The remainder of the aircraft passed over neutral Sweden where the aircrew, most of whom had only conducted night flying over countries observing [[Blackout (wartime)|blackouts]], were pleased to see towns lit up.{{sfn|Nichol|2015|p=198}} After crossing the [[Gulf of Bothnia]] the Lancasters continued over Finland towards the USSR. Several aircraft were fired on by Swedish, Finnish and Soviet anti-aircraft defences, but only one suffered any damage.{{sfn|Nichol|2015|p=198}}

Despite pre-departure forecasts of good weather, the force encountered thick clouds after entering Finnish airspace which continued for the remainder of the flight. These conditions made navigation difficult, and forced the pilots to fly at a low altitude so that they could use features on the ground to determine their location.{{sfn|Bishop|2012|p=331}} Only 26 of the Lancasters were able to locate Yagodnik and land there during the morning of 12 September, with the other 13 touching down at other airfields or crash landing in open spaces.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|p=106}} Six of the later aircraft were written off, and two of the seven which eventually reached Yagodnik were too badly damaged to be used in operations.{{sfn|Webster|Frankland|1961|p=193}} Despite the number of crashes, none of the airmen on board these aircraft were injured.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|p=107}} McMullen recorded that it was &quot;extraordinary that so few crashes occurred&quot; given the adverse circumstances, and that the majority of the aircraft dispatched could have been destroyed.{{sfn|Bishop|2012|p=332}}

After being concentrated at Yagodnik, the attack force was readied to strike Kaafjord. The Soviet personnel at the airfield provided considerable assistance, but the process of refuelling the aircraft could not be completed until 13 September due to inadequate facilities. During this period the ground crew also repaired some of the damaged bombers, including with parts salvaged from the aircraft which had been written off.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|p=107}}{{sfn|Bishop|2012|pp=332–333}} The British officers and senior non-commissioned officers were accommodated in a boat, and all other personnel slept in overcrowded underground huts. Both the boat and the huts were infested with [[bed bug]]s, and almost all of the airmen were bitten before the accommodation was fumigated by the detachment's medical officer.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|pp=108–109}}

By the morning of 14 September, 26 Lancasters from the attack forces and the Film Unit aircraft were ready; 20 of the bombers were armed with Tallboys and the remainder with JW mines. The No. 540 Squadron Mosquito took off bound for Kaafjord at 2:10{{nbsp}}am, but the planned departure of the bombers at 8:00{{nbsp}}am was cancelled when it returned to Yagodnik at 6:45 and reported that conditions over the target area were unsuitable.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|p=107}} For the remainder of the day the Soviets provided hospitality which included a formal lunch, a [[Association football|football]] tournament and a film that night.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|pp=107–108}} However, some of the Allied airmen were disturbed to see [[political prisoner]]s being beaten by overseers while conducting forced labour.{{sfn|Nichol|2015|p=207}} Work on repairing the damaged Lancasters also continued on 14 September, and an additional Tallboy-armed aircraft was ready by the next morning.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|p=111}}

The plans for the raid were also adjusted while No. 9 and No. 617 Squadrons were waiting at Yagodnik. The Lancasters were to take off together, and fly at low altitude until they reached the border between Finland and the USSR to avoid detection by German radar stations located around [[Kirkenes]]. The Force A aircraft would then climb to around {{convert|20000|ft|m}} and the six Force B bombers to {{convert|16000|ft|m}}. Three Lancasters from No. 9 Squadron would proceed ahead of the main body to determine wind conditions over Kaafjord. When the main body reached a position around {{convert|60|mi|km}} from the fjord, at which point the British expected that the Germans would have detected the bombers, the Lancasters would move into attack formations and commence their bombing run. It was decided that all of the aircraft would attack simultaneously, with Force A flying in four groups of five aircraft, approaching Kaafjord from the south and dropping their Tallboys from altitudes between {{convert|18000|ft|m}} and {{convert|14000|ft|m}}. Force B was to fly in two lines abreast, pass over the fjord from south-east to north-west, and release the JW mines from between {{convert|12000|ft|m}} and {{convert|10000|ft|m}}.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|pp=109–111}}

==Attack==
The Mosquito reconnoitred Kaafjord again in the morning of 15 September, and at 7{{nbsp}}am Yagodnik time reported that conditions were suitable for an attack.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|p=111}} The 27 bombers and Film Unit Lancaster began taking off shortly afterwards. The force flew in a loose formation and the journey to northern Norway went as planned, though six Lancasters were forced to abort and return to Yagodnik.{{sfn|Bishop|2012|pp=335–336}}{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|p=119}} Despite passing near several German bases, the British force was undetected and no German fighters were airborne over Kaafjord at the time of the attack.{{sfn|Nichol|2015|p=208}}

Kaafjord's defenders detected the Lancasters approximately ten minutes before they arrived, and the protective smokescreen was beginning to form when the attack commenced at 10:55{{nbsp}}am [[Greenwich Mean Time|GMT]].{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|p=112}} Only the first group of Lancasters, led by Tait, were able to aim their bombs at ''Tirpitz'' before she was obscured by smoke. It is believed that the bomb dropped from Tait's aircraft struck the battleship, and the other bombs dropped by this group landed in the water nearby.{{sfn|Brown|1977|p=41}} All of the other Force A aircraft with bombs aimed their Tallboys at the anti-aircraft gunfire rising from the ship; a total of 17 of the weapons were dropped.{{sfn|Webster|Frankland|1961|p=194}}{{sfn|Bishop|2012|p=338}} Several of the Lancasters made more than one pass over the target area as their bomb aimers sought to locate ''Tirpitz'' or technical problems prevented their Tallboy from being dropped on the initial pass.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|pp=113–114}}

Force B commenced its attack after the Tallboy Lancasters had completed theirs so that the shock waves from bomb explosions did not prematurely set off the JW mines. As none of the Force B aircrew were able to spot ''Tirpitz'' due to the smokescreen, they dropped the mines on the battleship's estimated position.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|pp=113–114}} These weapons did not cause any damage.{{sfn|Roskill|1961|p=162}} The smokescreen over Kaafjord prevented the Allied aircrew from being able to assess the results of their bombing, though several large spouts of water and explosions were observed.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|pp=113–114}} Tait was also pleased to see a column of black smoke rising through the smokescreen.{{sfn|Bishop|2012|p=338}} However, some of the bombs and mines landed up to a mile from the battleship.{{sfn|Brown|1977|p=41}} ''Tirpitz''{{'}}s anti-aircraft guns and a further 98 guns located in nearby shore batteries and warships fired on the bombers throughout the attack. However, only four Lancasters suffered any damage.{{sfn|Zetterling|Tamelander|2009|p=293}}{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|p=120}}

All of the Lancasters had completed their attacks by 11:07{{nbsp}}am GMT, and the 21 bombers began the return journey to Yagodnik.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|p=115}} The Force A aircraft which had not been able to bomb brought their expensive Tallboys back. This flight proved uneventful, and all 27 Lancasters landed at Yagodnik in the evening.{{sfn|Bishop|2012|p=338}} The Film Unit aircraft flew directly to the United Kingdom, and arrived at its home station after a fifteen-and-a-half hour flight; this was the longest operational Lancaster mission of World War II.{{sfn|Nichol|2015|p=211}}

The No. 540 Squadron Mosquito conducted a reconnaissance sortie over Kaafjord on the afternoon of 15 September, arriving at about 1:30{{nbsp}}pm GMT. Its crew found that the fjord was covered with cloud and smoke. They could only briefly see ''Tirpitz'', but reported that no damage was evident to the battleship, which remained afloat.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|p=112}} The Mosquito conducted further reconnaissance sorties on 16 September, but the fjord was completely obscured on all occasions.{{sfn|Zetterling|Tamelander|2009|p=293}} McMullen considered launching a second attack, but decided against doing so as only two Tallboys and one load of JW mines were available.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|p=112}}

==Aftermath==

''Tirpitz'' was rendered unfit for combat by Operation Paravane. The Tallboy bomb that struck the battleship passed through the [[Forecastle|foredeck]] and hull, and exploded in the water on the starboard side of her [[Bow (ship)|bow]]. This damage wrecked the bow, and left the battleship's forward compartments flooded with 2,000 tons of water. The explosions of several other Tallboys in the water near ''Tirpitz'' also buckled some of her hull plates and [[Bulkhead (partition)|bulkheads]]. The battleship's casualties were not heavy, with five men killed and fifteen wounded.{{sfn|Bishop|2012|p=339}} The damage was assessed as needing nine months' worth of work to repair.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|p=121}} After reporting on the damage, ''Tirpitz''{{'}}s commanding officer, [[Captain at sea|''Kapitän zur See'']] [[Wolf Junge]], recommended to the German Navy's high command that the battleship be removed from service.{{sfn|Garzke|Dulin|1985|p=268}}

The attack force returned to the United Kingdom in several groups. Tait led 16 Lancasters out of Yagodnik in the evening of 16 September; most of these aircraft flew over southern Finland, Sweden and Denmark. One of the Lancasters went off course and crashed on a mountain near [[Nesbyen]] in Norway, resulting in the death of the eleven airmen aboard,{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|pp=115–116}} the only Allied casualties of Operation Paravane.{{sfn|Zetterling|Tamelander|2009|p=294}} Nine other Lancasters departed on 17 September, followed by five the next day, one on 19 September and two on 21 September. The six other Lancasters at Yagodnik had been judged to be damaged beyond repair, and were handed over to the Soviets. The Mosquito, which had been damaged by anti-aircraft fire during a sortie over Kaafjord, returned once repairs were complete on 26 September. The two Liberators were the final aircraft to depart, and flew out of Yagodnik carrying McMullen on 27 September.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|pp=116–117}}

Following the attack, the British intelligence services sought to determine the extent of ''Tirpitz''{{'}}s damage. During late September Norwegian SIS agents in the Kaafjord area reported that the battleship had been struck by a bomb and appeared damaged.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|pp=117–118}} German radio signals which were intercepted and decoded on 25 and 29 September also stated that ''Tirpitz'' had suffered a single hit from a large bomb.{{sfn|Hinsley|1984|p=277}} Photographs taken by the No. 540 Squadron Mosquito and a Soviet aircraft on 20 September indicated that the bow of the ship was damaged, though it was not possible to determine how badly.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|pp=117–118}} Drawing on this evidence, the Royal Navy's Naval Intelligence Division concluded on 30 September that ''Tirpitz'' had &quot;almost certainly&quot; been struck by a Tallboy and may have been further damaged by near misses, and that the damage to the ship may have been &quot;considerable&quot; and rendered her unable to put to sea. A report from a Norwegian agent on 31 September was more specific, stating that ''Tirpitz'' had suffered a direct hit which had opened a {{convert|17|m|ft|adj=on}} gash on her bow. Further agent reports in early October provided little further new evidence.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|p=118}} By late October, with no major German warships left in Kaafjord, the agents operating the &quot;Aslaug&quot; transmitter left the area, sending their last transmission to the United Kingdom on 22 October. Moe and Arild made their way on foot across the [[Finnmarksvidda]] plateau to [[Kautokeino]] and from there through Finland to [[Karesuando]] in Sweden, arriving on 5 December.{{sfn|Christensen|1990|pp=254–255}}{{sfn|Ulstein|1992|p=469}} The agents carried out the march without resupplies of food, as Operation Carpetbagger had ceased using Soviet airbases after a B-24 Liberator was accidentally shot down by a Soviet fighter during a follow-up operation to [[Finnmark]] shortly after the insertion of Moe and Arild.{{sfn|Rørholt|Thorsen|1990|pp=399–400}}

A meeting with [[Grand admiral|''Großadmiral'']] [[Karl Dönitz]], the commander of the German Navy, was held in Berlin on 23 September to discuss the damage to ''Tirpitz''. Dönitz was informed that it would take nine months to repair the ship, with all the work needing to be done at Kaafjord. As Soviet forces were also rapidly advancing towards northern Norway, Dönitz judged that it would not be feasible to either return the ship to ocean-going service or retain her at Kaafjord. Instead, he decided to use ''Tirpitz'' as a floating [[artillery battery]] to defend the town of [[Tromsø]]. Dönitz also expressed a hope that retaining the ship in commission would &quot;continue to tie down enemy forces and by her presence&amp;nbsp;... confound the enemies' intentions&quot;.{{sfn|Sweetman|2000|p=121}}{{sfn|Bishop|2012|pp=340–341}} The commander of the German Navy's task force in northern Norway, ''[[Konteradmiral]]'' [[Rudolf Peters]], was accordingly directed to anchor ''Tirpitz'' at a location near Tromsø where the water was shallow enough to prevent the battleship from sinking completely if she suffered further damage.{{sfn|Bishop|2012|pp=341}}

As the intelligence available to them was not conclusive, the Allies believed that ''Tirpitz'' still posed a potential threat.{{sfn|Zetterling|Tamelander|2009|p=295}} Accordingly, No. 9 and No. 617 Squadrons conducted two further attacks on the battleship after she moved to Tromsø on 15 October; these operations were more straightforward to conduct than Operation Paravane as the port was within the range of Lancasters flying from airfields in northern Scotland.{{sfn|Garzke|Dulin|1985|p=268}}{{sfn|Bennett|2012|p=19}} The first raid, [[Operation Obviate]], took place on 29 October but caused only minor damage to the battleship. During the subsequent attack conducted on 12 November, [[Operation Catechism]], ''Tirpitz'' was struck by several Tallboy bombs and capsized with heavy loss of life among her crew.{{sfn|Bennett|2012|pp=19–21}}

==References==

===Footnotes===
{{Reflist|group=Note}}

===Citations===
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

===Works consulted===

*{{cite book|last=Bennett|first=G.H.|title=Hunting Tirpitz: Naval Operations Against Bismarck's Sister Ship|year=2012|publisher=University of Plymouth Press|location=Plymouth, Devon|isbn=978-1-84102-310-6|editor=Bennett, G.H.|chapter=Introduction|pages=7–25|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Bishop|first=Patrick|title=Target Tirpitz|year=2012|publisher=Harper Press|location=London|isbn=978-0-00-743119-9|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Brown|first=David|title=Tirpitz: The Floating Fortress|year=1977|publisher=Arms and Armour Press|location=London|isbn=0-85368-341-7|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Christensen |first=Dag |authorlink= |title=Den skjulte hånd: historien om Einar Johansen - britenes toppagent i Nord-Norge under krigen |url=http://urn.nb.no/URN:NBN:no-nb_digibok_2007090401009 |publisher=Damm |location=Oslo |year=1990 |isbn=82-517-9982-1 |language=Norwegian |ref=harv|trans-title=The Hidden Hand: The story of Einar Johansen - the top agent of the British in northern Norway during the war}}
*{{cite book|last=Ellis|first=John|title=One Day in a Very Long War: Wednesday 25th October 1944|year=1999|publisher=Pimlico|location=London|isbn=0-7126-7465-9|edition=Pimlico|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last1=Faulkner|first1=Marcus|title=War at Sea: A Naval Atlas, 1939–1945|year=2012|publisher=Naval Institute Press|location=Annapolis, Maryland|isbn=978-1-59114-560-8|last2=Wilkinson|first2=Peter|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last1=Garzke|first1=William H.|last2=Dulin|first2=Robert O.|title=Battleships: Axis and Neutral Battleships in World War II|year=1985|publisher=Naval Institute Press|location=Annapolis, Maryland|isbn=978-0-87021-101-0|oclc=|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last1=Hafsten |first1=Bjørn |last2=Larsstuvold |first2=Ulf |last3=Olsen |first3=Bjørn |last4=Stenersen |first4=Sten |title=Flyalarm – luftkrigen over Norge 1939–1945 |edition=2nd, revised |publisher=Sem &amp; Stenersen Forlag |location=Oslo| year=2005 |isbn=82-7046-074-5 |language=Norwegian|ref=harv|trans-title=Air Alert - the Air War over Norway 1939-1945}}
*{{cite book|last1=Herington|first1=John|title=Air War Against Germany and Italy, 1939–1943|date=1954|publisher=Australian War Memorial|location=Canberra|url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070211/|series=[[Australia in the War of 1939–1945]]. Series 3 – Air. Volume III|oclc=569627837|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Hinsley|first=F.H.|title=British Intelligence in the Second World War: Its Influence on Strategy and Operations. Volume Three, Part I|year=1984|publisher=Her Majesty's Stationery Office|location=London|isbn=0-11-630935-0|display-authors=etal|series=[[History of the Second World War]]|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last1=Nichol|first1=John|title=After the Flood: What the Dambusters Did Next|date=2015|publisher=William Collins|location=London|isbn=978-0-00-810084-1 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Nøkleby |first=Berit |authorlink=Berit Nøkleby |title=Pass godt på Tirpitz! - norske radioagenter i Secret Intelligence Service 1940–1945 |edition= |publisher=Gyldendal |location=Oslo | year=1988 |isbn=82-05-17705-8 |url=http://urn.nb.no/URN:NBN:no-nb_digibok_2013062608017 |language=Norwegian|ref=harv|trans-title=Look well after Tirpitz! - Norwegian radio agents in the Secret Intelligence Service 1940-1945}}
* {{cite encyclopedia |first=Berit |last=Nøkleby |authorlink= | encyclopedia=[[Norsk krigsleksikon 1940–1945]] |title=Secret Intelligence Service, SIS |editor=[[Hans Fredrik Dahl|Dahl]] |editor2=[[Guri Hjeltnes|Hjeltnes]] |editor3=[[Berit Nøkleby|Nøkleby]] |editor4=[[Nils Johan Ringdal|Ringdal]] |editor5=[[Øystein Sørensen|Sørensen]] |url=http://urn.nb.no/URN:NBN:no-nb_digibok_2010113005006 |accessdate= | year=1995 |publisher=Cappelen |location=Oslo |isbn=82-02-14138-9 |language=Norwegian|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Pedersen |first=Gunnar |authorlink= |title=Militær motstand i nord 1940–45 : jakten på Tirpitz, Arnøytragedien, Operasjon MARTIN og SEPALS |edition= |publisher=Universitetsforlaget |location=Tromsø | year=1982 |isbn=82-00-06328-3 |url=http://urn.nb.no/URN:NBN:no-nb_digibok_2016052707010 |language=Norwegian|ref=harv|trans-title=Military resistance in the north from 1940 to 1945: The Hunt for Tirpitz, the Arnøy tragedy, Operation MARTIN and SEPALS}}
* {{cite book |last1=Rørholt |first1=Bjørn |authorlink=Bjørn Rørholt |last2=Thorsen |first2=Bjarne |authorlink2=Bjarne Thorsen |year=1990 |title=Usynlige soldater: nordmenn i Secret Service forteller |pages= |publisher=Aschehoug |location=Oslo |isbn=82-03-16046-8 |url=http://urn.nb.no/URN:NBN:no-nb_digibok_2007110500050 |language=Norwegian|ref=harv|trans-title=Invisible Soldiers: Norwegians in the Secret Service relate}}
*{{cite book|last=Roskill|first=S.W.|title=The War at Sea 1939–1945. Volume III: The Offensive Part II|year=1961|publisher=Her Majesty's Stationery Office|location=London|oclc=59005418|series=History of the Second World War|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Sweetman|first=John|title=Tirpitz: Hunting the Beast: Air Attacks on the German Battleship, 1940–44|date=2000|publisher=Naval Institute Press|location=Annapolis, Maryland|isbn=1-55750-822-4|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Tactical, Torpedo and Staff Duties Division (Historical Section)|title=Hunting Tirpitz: Naval Operations Against Bismarck's Sister Ship|year=2012|publisher=University of Plymouth Press|location=Plymouth, United Kingdom|isbn=978-1-84102-310-6|editor=Bennett, G.H.|chapter=Naval Aircraft Attack on the Tirpitz (Operation 'Tungsten') 3 April 1944|origyear=1944|pages=133–177|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Ulstein |first=Ragnar |authorlink=Ragnar Ulstein |title=Etterretningstjenesten i Norge 1940–45 |volume=3 |url=http://urn.nb.no/URN:NBN:no-nb_digibok_2014051906143 |publisher=Cappelen |location=Oslo |year=1992 |isbn=82-02-13822-1 |language=Norwegian |ref=harv|trans-title=The Intelligence Service in Norway 1940-1945}}
*{{cite book|last1=Webster|first1=Charles|last2=Frankland|first2=Noble|title=The Strategic Air Offensive Against Germany, Volume III: Victory|date=1961|publisher=Her Majesty's Stationery Office|location=London|oclc=614956318|series=History of the Second World War|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Woodman|first=Richard|title=The Arctic Convoys: 1941–1945|year=2004|publisher=John Murray|location=London|isbn=0-7195-6617-7|edition=Paperback|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last1=Zetterling|first1=Niklas|last2=Tamelander|first2=Michael|title=Tirpitz: The Life and Death of Germany's Last Super Battleship|year=2009|publisher=Casemate|location=Philadelphia|isbn=978-1-935149-18-7|ref=harv}}

{{coord|69.9353|23.0454|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Paravane}}
[[Category:Aerial operations and battles of World War II]]
[[Category:Soviet Union–United Kingdom relations]]
[[Category:Military operations of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Aerial operations and battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:1944 in Norway]]
[[Category:Alta, Norway]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1944]]</text>
      <sha1>gx09tkwroiqgllepf39uilyzg5yp0qs</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
