<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Operation Sky Monitor</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>21557540</id>
    <revision>
      <id>731276237</id>
      <parentid>623229323</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-07-24T08:31:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ewen</username>
        <id>3610</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13530">{{operational plan
|name = Operation Sky Monitor
|partof =the [[NATO intervention in Bosnia]]
|image= [[File:Boeing E-3A Sentry, NATO - Airborne Early Warning Force JP7067257.jpg|300px|A NATO E-3 Sentry, the aircraft type used for monitoring in Operation Sky Monitor]]
|caption = A NATO E-3 Sentry, the aircraft type used for monitoring in Operation Sky Monitor
|objective = Monitoring of no-fly zone over Bosnia
|date = October 16, 1992 &amp;ndash; April 12, 1993
|executed_by = [[Allied Forces Southern Europe]]
}}
{{Campaignbox NATO intervention in Bosnia}}

'''Operation Sky Monitor''' was a [[NATO]] mission to monitor unauthorized flights in the airspace of [[Bosnia-Herzegovina]] during the [[Bosnian War]].  The operation began in response to [[United Nations Security Council Resolution 781]], which established a ban on the use of military aircraft in Bosnian airspace, and requested the aid of member states in monitoring compliance.  Beginning on October 16, 1992, NATO monitored violations of the [[no-fly zone]] using [[E-3 Sentry]] [[NAEW]] aircraft based in [[Germany]], [[Italy]], [[Greece]], and the [[United Kingdom]].  The operation documented more than 500 violations of the no-fly zone by April 1993.&lt;ref name=&quot;beale19&quot; /&gt;   In response to this high volume of unauthorized flights, the Security Council passed [[United Nations Security Council Resolution 816|Resolution 816]], which authorized NATO to enforce the no-fly zone, and engage violators.  In response, NATO deactivated Sky Monitor on April 12, 1993, transferring its forces to the newly established [[Operation Deny Flight]].

==Background==
On September 25, 1991, at the beginning of the [[Yugoslav wars]], the [[United Nations Security Council]] issued [[United Nations Security Council Resolution 713|Resolution 713]], which established &quot;a general and complete embargo on all deliveries of weapons and military equipment to Yugoslavia&quot;, with the goal of reducing violence and bloodshed throughout the country.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url= http://www.nato.int/IFOR/un/u910925a.htm | title = Resolution 713|accessdate = 2009-06-11|work = United Nations Security Council Resolutions}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In May, the Security Council reaffirmed the embargo in [[United Nations Security Council Resolution 757|Resolution 757]], and added a provision for a naval force to monitor compliance with the embargo.  In resolution 757, the Council also called on states to &quot;deny permission to any aircraft to take off, land in or overfly their territory if it is destined to land in or had taken off from the territory of the Federal Republic of Yugoslavia&quot;, setting the precedent for later anti-air measures.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title = Resolution 757| url = http://www.nato.int/IFOR/un/u920530a.htm|accessdate = 2009-06-11|work = United Nations Security Council Resolutions}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In response to resolution 757, NATO began to perform its first operations on behalf of the United Nations on July 16, 1992 with [[Operation Maritime Monitor]], which monitored violations of Security Council Resolutions by ships.  As a part of Maritime Monitor, NATO dispatched [[E-3 Sentry]] [[airborne early warning]] aircraft to the region to monitor sea traffic.  These aircraft flew more than 200 missions over the course of the operation.&lt;ref name = &quot;globalsecurity&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title = Operation Maritime Monitor | url = http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/ops/maritime_monitor.htm | work = GlobalSecurity.org|accessdate = 2009-06-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On October 9, 1992, the Security Council passed resolution 781.  In the resolution, the Security Council expressed concern about the use of aircraft by the belligerents in the [[War in Bosnia]] and established a formal &quot;ban on military flights in the airspace of Bosnia and Herzegovina&quot;. It also called upon member states to help the United Nations Protection Force ([[UNPROFOR]]) in monitoring &quot;compliance with the ban on military flights&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title = Resolution 781 | url = http://www.ohr.int/other-doc/un-res-bih/pdf/s92r781e.pdf|accessdate = 2009-06-11|work = United Nations Security Council Resolutions}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Shortly thereafter, on October 15, NATO aircraft operating under Maritime Monitor began monitoring flights over Bosnia for the UN.  The essential goal of this mission was to conduct surveillance in order to determine whether or not the various parties in the conflict were respecting the UN no-fly zone.   The next day, October 16, Operation Sky Monitor officially began when NATO planes expanded their monitoring with flight paths over the Adriatic.&lt;ref name =&quot;AFSOUTH&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title = JFC Naples/AFSOUTH, 1951-2009: OVER FIFTY YEARS WORKING FOR PEACE AND STABILITY | url = http://www.afsouth.nato.int/JFCN_Factsheets/JFC_Naples_history.html | author = Allied Joint Force Command Naples|accessdate = 2009-06-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Operation==
During Operation Sky Monitor, aircraft operated in two &quot;orbits&quot;, one over the [[Adriatic]] established on October 16, and a second one over [[Hungary]], established with the permission of the Hungarian government on October 31.&lt;ref name = &quot;AFSOUTH&quot; /&gt;  Both of these orbits operated 24 hours a day, providing constant surveillance of Bosnian airspace.&lt;ref name = &quot;8squadron&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title = No 8 Squadron Comes Home | url =  http://8squadron.co.uk/history_1991-present.php|accessdate = 2009-06-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The first flight over Hungary on October 31 was an important milestone in NATO history as it was the &quot;first operational mission in a former [[Warsaw Pact]] nation&quot; for the alliance.&lt;ref name = &quot;voellger&quot;&gt;{{cite journal| title = NATO airborne early warning force Balkan operations | first = Gary | last = Voellger | journal = NATO's Nations and Partners for Peace |date=January 1999|issue = 2|pages = 28–32 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Even more significantly, Hungary agreed that if a NATO aircraft were attacked in its airspace, the [[Hungarian Air Force]] would provide support with [[Mikoyan-Gurevich MiG-21]] fighters.&lt;ref name = &quot;8squadron&quot;/&gt;  This support never became necessary, but it marked another important milestone, actual military cooperation between NATO and the former Warsaw Pact.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title = Hungary Assists NATO Monitoring in Bosnia | work = Jane's Defence International | date = March 1993}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The monitoring aircraft of Sky Monitor were initially drawn from the NATO Airborne Early Warning squadron based at [[NATO Air Base Geilenkirchen]] in Germany, but [[Aviano Air Base]] in Italy, [[Preveza]] in Greece, and [[Trapani]] in Italy were all used as forward operating bases.  As the operation expanded, the British [[No. 8 Squadron RAF]] and the French E-3F squadron at [[Avord Air Base]] were also used.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title = Details/Information for Canadian Forces (CF) Operation SKY MONITOR | accessdate = 2009-06-13 | url =http://www.cmp-cpm.forces.gc.ca/dhh-dhp/od-bdo/di-ri-eng.asp?IntlOpId=213&amp;CdnOpId=251 | publisher = National Defence and Canadian Forces}}&lt;/ref&gt;  All of these NATO forces fell under the authority of [[Allied Forces Southern Europe]], commanded by Admiral [[Jeremy Boorda]] of the [[United States Navy]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title = Deny Flight and Deliberate Force: An Effective Use of Airpower | first = Kurt | last = Miller | publisher = US Army Command and General Staff College | url = http://handle.dtic.mil/100.2/ada331766}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Eleven NATO countries provided personnel or aircraft for the operation: Belgium, Canada, Denmark, Germany, Greece, Italy, the Netherlands, Norway, Portugal, 
Turkey, and the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| title = Interoperability of U.S. and NATO Allied Air Forces: Supporting Data and Case Studies|first = Eric | last = Larson | publisher = [[RAND]] | year = 2003}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The rules of engagement for Sky Monitor were very restrictive.  Because the purpose of the operation was to monitor, rather than prevent, unauthorized flights, participating aircraft were only authorized to use force in self-defense.  Furthermore, under the rules of engagement, NATO forces were directed to take evasive action if attacked rather than engage an opponent if at all possible.  As a result of the strict rules of engagement, no NATO forces were engaged in combat during Operation Sky Monitor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title = Deliberate Force: A Case Study in Effective Air Campaigning | chapter = Chariots of Fire: Rules of Engagement in Operation Deliberate Force | first = Ronald | last = Reed | publisher = Air University Press | editor = Robert Owen | isbn = 1-58566-076-0| page = 396}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sky Monitor documented many violations of the no-fly zone, the most significant of which came in March 1993, when [[Republika Srpska|Serb]] aircraft bombed two Muslim villages.  This violation, the first &quot;combat violation&quot; of the no-fly zone, led to calls for NATO to actively enforce the zone, rather than just monitoring compliance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title = U.N. Moving to Toughen Yugoslav Flight Ban | first = Paul | last = Lewis | work = The New York Times | date = March 19, 1993 | url = http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFDF163AF93AA25750C0A965958260&amp;scp=71&amp;sq=NATO+bosnia&amp;st=nyt}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Results==
At the beginning of April 1993, NATO had documented more than 500 violations of the no-fly zone over Bosnia, including violations from all sides in the conflict.&lt;ref name=&quot;beale19&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title = Bombs over Bosnia: The Role of Airpower in Bosnia-Herzegovina|first = Michael | last = Beale | publisher = [[Air University Press]] | year = 1997|page = 19}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Out of these numerous violations, however, NATO documented only one that it considered a &quot;combat mission&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title = NATO Agrees to Enforce Flight Ban Over Bosnia Ordered by U.N. | first = Alan | last = Riding | work = The New York Times | date = April 3, 1993 | url = http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D9163DF930A35757C0A965958260&amp;scp=2&amp;sq=NATO+bosnia&amp;st=nyt}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Although most of the violations were not combat missions, NATO had decided even before the end of Sky Monitor that the UN ban was ineffective.  On December 18, 1992, the NATO members voted to enforce the no-fly zone with military force if requested by the United Nations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title = CONFLICT IN THE BALKANS; NATO Offers Support | first = Elaine | last = Sciolono | work = The New York Times | date = December 18, 1992 | url = http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFD81238F93BA25751C1A964958260&amp;scp=29&amp;sq=NATO+bosnia&amp;st=nyt}}&lt;/ref&gt;  This escalation of NATO involvement also gained the crucial backing of US President-elect [[Bill Clinton]] in December, when he told the press that he had &quot;been in favor of enforcing the no-fly zone for some time.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title = Clinton Urges Stronger U.S. Stand On Enforcing Bosnia Flight Ban | first = Elaine | last = Sciolono | work = The New York Times | date = December 12, 1992 | url = http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DB1E3FF931A25751C1A964958260&amp;scp=52&amp;sq=NATO+bosnia&amp;st=nyt}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Deny Flight F-15.jpg|left|thumb|A [[US Air Force]] [[F-15C]] takes off on a sortie to enforce the no-fly zone during [[Operation Deny Flight]]]]
The UN called for NATO to use force in response to the &quot;blatant violations of the ban on military flights in the airspace of Bosnia and Herzegovina&quot; with [[United Nations Security Council Resolution 816|Security Council Resolution 816]] on March 31, 1993.  The resolution authorized UN member states to &quot;take all necessary measures&quot; in order &quot;to ensure compliance&quot; with the no-fly zone.&lt;ref name = &quot;unscres816&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ohr.int/other-doc/un-res-bih/pdf/816e.pdf  |title= Resolution 816 |accessdate=2009-02-17 |work=United Nations Security Council Resolutions |publisher= UN Security Council |date= }}&lt;/ref&gt;  As a result of this new resolution, NATO deactivated Sky Monitor, and began [[Operation Deny Flight]] on April 12, 1993.  Under Deny Flight, NATO forces continued to monitor and document unauthorized flights, but they were also authorized to enforce the zone and engage violators if necessary.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title = Bombs over Bosnia: The Role of Airpower in Bosnia-Herzegovina|first = Michael | last = Beale | publisher = [[Air University Press]] | year = 1997 | page = 20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Operation Sky Monitor was the first of many NATO air operations in the Balkans, including the more significant [[Operation Deliberate Force]] and [[Operation Allied Force]].  Sky Monitor was also NATO's first out of area air operation, and one of its first collaborative missions with the United Nations. Thus, it set the precedent for future NATO-UN cooperation, based on a model where NATO forces would use their superior technical expertise to assist the UN in pursuing its broader mission.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title =Armed Peacekeepers in Bosnia | first = Robert | last = Baumann | publisher = Combat Studies Institute Press | isbn = 1-4289-1020-4 | year = 2004| page = 64}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Sky Monitor also affected military policy, as it proved the utility of the [[E-3 Sentry]], NATO's principal aircraft in the operation, for monitoring missions under a wide variety of circumstances.  Thus, the E-3 became an important part of NATO's planning for later operations.&lt;ref name = &quot;voellger&quot; /&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

{{good article}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Sky Monitor}}
[[Category:Bosnian War]]
[[Category:Humanitarian military operations]]
[[Category:No-fly zone operations]]
[[Category:Military operations of the Bosnian War]]
[[Category:NATO intervention in the former Yugoslavia]]</text>
      <sha1>n5l96n3gtb7xnfeqot3aen9w1tqc8jo</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
