<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Organization of the Luftwaffe (1933–45)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2431156</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749252367</id>
      <parentid>745654670</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-13T09:02:39Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[User:AnomieBOT/docs/TemplateSubster|Substing templates]]: {{ill}}. See [[User:AnomieBOT/docs/TemplateSubster]] for info.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="82026">{{Infobox military unit
|unit_name= [[Luftwaffe]]
|image=
&lt;gallery mode=packed heights=150&gt;
File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1978-106-25, Deutsche Luftwaffe.jpg|Luftwaffe formations in 1937|alt=Three lines of aircraft fly in arrow
File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-03127, Berlin, Parade am Tag der Luftwaffe.jpg|Luftwaffe day parade in front of the [[Reichsluftfahrtministerium|Reich Air Ministry]], 1 March 1939.|alt=Soldiers with rifles and helmets march along a road past a reviewing party and guard of honor
&lt;/gallery&gt;
|caption=
|dates= 15 May 1933
|country= [[Nazi Germany]]
|allegiance= {{Flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Nazi Germany]]
|branch= [[Air Force]]
|type=
|role=
|size=
|command_structure=
|garrison=
|garrison_label=
|nickname=
|patron=
|motto=
|colors=
|colors_label=
|march=
|mascot=
|equipment=
|equipment_label=
|battles=[[Invasion of Poland]],&lt;br /&gt;[[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]],&lt;br /&gt;[[Battle of Britain]],&lt;br /&gt;[[Defence of the Reich]],&lt;br /&gt;[[Unternehmen Bodenplatte]]
|anniversaries=25 March 1933
|decorations=
|battle_honours=
|disbanded=8 May 1945
|flying_hours=
|website=
&lt;!-- Commanders --&gt;
|commander1= [[Reichsmarschall]] [[Hermann Göring]]
|commander1_label= Oberbefehlshaber der Luftwaffe
|commander2= [[Generalfeldmarschall]] [[Robert Ritter von Greim]]
|commander2_label=Oberbefehlshaber der Luftwaffe
|notable_commanders=
&lt;!-- Insignia --&gt;
|identification_symbol=
|identification_symbol_label=
|identification_symbol_2=
|identification_symbol_2_label=
|identification_symbol_3=
|identification_symbol_3_label=
|identification_symbol_4=
|identification_symbol_4_label=
&lt;!-- Aircraft --&gt;
|aircraft_attack=[[Messerschmitt Bf 109]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Focke-Wulf Fw 190]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Henschel Hs 129]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Junkers Ju 87]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Focke-Wulf Ta 152]]
|aircraft_bomber=[[Junkers Ju 87]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Junkers Ju 88]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Heinkel He 111]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Heinkel He 177]]&lt;br /&gt;(strategic bomber)&lt;br /&gt;[[Dornier Do 17]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Dornier Do 217]]
|aircraft_strategic_bomber=
|aircraft_electronic=
|aircraft_fighter= [[Messerschmitt Bf 109]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Messerschmitt Bf 110]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Focke-Wulf Fw 190]]
|aircraft_interceptor=[[Heinkel He 162]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Messerschmitt Me 163]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Messerschmitt Me 262]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Focke-Wulf Ta 152]]
|aircraft_patrol=[[Focke-Wulf Fw 200]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Blohm &amp; Voss Bv 138]]
|aircraft_recon=[[Henschel Hs 126]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Focke-Wulf Fw 189]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Fieseler Fi 156]]
|aircraft_trainer=[[Arado Ar 96]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Klemm Kl 35]]
|aircraft_transport=[[Gotha Go 244]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Junkers Ju 52]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Messerschmitt Me 323]]
}}

Between 1933 and 1945, the '''organization of the Luftwaffe''' underwent several changes. Originally, the German military high command, for their air warfare forces, decided to use an organizational structure similar to the army and navy, treating the aviation branch as a strategic weapon of war. Later on, during the period of rapid rearmament, the [[Luftwaffe]] was organized more in a geographical fashion.

Under the terms of the [[Treaty of Versailles]] (1919), Germany was prohibited from having an air force, with the former [[German Empire]]'s ''[[Luftstreitkräfte]]'' disbandment in 1920. German pilots were secretly trained for military aviation, first in the Soviet Union during the late 1920s, and then in Germany in the early 1930s. In Germany, the training was done under the guise of the German Air Sports Association ({{lang-de|Deutscher Luftsportverband}} (DLV)) at the Central Commercial Pilots School ({{lang-de|Zentrale der Verkehrs Fliegerschule}} (ZVF)).

The [[Luftwaffe|formation of the German air arm]] was openly announced in February 1935, with [[Reichsmarschall]] [[Hermann Göring]] as its Commander-in-Chief ({{lang-de|Oberbefehlshaber der Luftwaffe}}), in blatant defiance of the Versailles Treaty. Initial plans were for long-term growth of the Luftwaffe over a period of five years with the intention of using the Luftwaffe as a strategic force. These plans were changed several times, especially after the June 1936 death of [[Walther Wever (general)|Walter Wever]] and the succession of [[Ernst Udet]]. The focus and role of the Luftwaffe became one of ground support for the German Army during its Lightning War ({{lang-de|[[Blitzkrieg]]}}) campaigns. Göring, using his political capital, was able to get significant resources allocated to the Luftwaffe, more so than the army ({{lang-de|[[German Army (Wehrmacht)|Heer]]}}) or the navy ({{lang-de|[[Kriegsmarine]]}}). This made the Luftwaffe one of the most powerful force in Europe during its initial years. Partly due to its ground support role, the Luftwaffe was reorganized in a fashion similar to the army units, with one unit controlling a specific area. Each Luftwaffe unit was self-contained and had complete control over all aspects of Luftwaffe forces in that area.

Before becoming head of the Luftwaffe, Göring was Interior Minister of Prussia. In this position he had formed his own army, starting from a 400 men police department to regiment size. When Göring took over the Luftwaffe, he brought the regiment along with him to the Luftwaffe and created his own ground forces in the form of [[Luftwaffe Field Division]]s and Paratrooper Regiments ({{lang-de|[[Fallschirmjäger]]}}) under the Luftwaffe. He eventually included a tank regiment ([[Fallschirm-Panzer Division 1 Hermann Göring|Fallschirm-Panzer Division]]), [[Flak corps|''Flak'' units]] and a signals regiment ({{lang-de| Luftnachrichten Regiment}}) under the Luftwaffe umbrella.
{{TOC limit}}
==Formation and expansion==
{{Main article|Luftwaffe}}
[[File:Regulation WW II Upperwing Balkenkreuz.png|upright|thumb|The emblem of WWII German armed forces was the bar cross, ({{lang-de|Balkenkreuz}}) seen in its Luftwaffe upper-wing &quot;narrow-flank&quot; form|alt=Image of the emblem of the German Armed forces of WWII, the Iron Cross ({{lang-de|Balkenkreuz}})]]
During the 1930s and 1940s, air power had not matured enough to be considered a dominant weapon of war. Unlike the other two forces, air power did not have past experience to draw upon. This resulted in the air force having to learn from experience rather than the classroom. There were no cohesive ideas for the organization of a structured, modern air force. One train of thought subordinated the air force to the army in support of land operations and to the navy for maritime tasks. It would be staffed by soldiers or sailors trained to fly.&lt;ref name=Lepage09p16&gt;Lepage, (2009) p. 16&lt;/ref&gt;

The second theory envisioned a centralized, well organized air force to be used as a weapon of war, like the army and navy. German aviators from World War I, followed this thought process. Since they had the backing of the German political leadership, this is how the Luftwaffe was originally conceived and formed. Following the tradition of putting a soldier in charge of the army and a sailor in charge of the navy, an aviator was designated to lead the Luftwaffe: ''Reichsmarschall'' Herman Göring, also the cabinet minister for aviation. Göring formed a Luftwaffe high Command ({{lang-de|[[Oberkommando der Luftwaffe]]}}) for operational management.&lt;ref name=Lepage09p16/&gt;

Within the German air force leadership, the general opinion was that the Luftwaffe was a tactical rather than a strategic air force. Hence, in order to support the various army groups, the Luftwaffe was organized in similar fashion to the army. Its units had a flexible composition with sub-units being added or removed when necessary. These sub-units tended to be semi-autonomous and highly mobile. This offered the flexibility required to support the ground units.&lt;ref name=DenisLepage09p17&gt;Lepage, (2009) p. 17&lt;/ref&gt;

From the start of the [[Spanish Civil War]], the Luftwaffe was in action continuously without the time for rest or training. [[German occupation of Czechoslovakia|Multiple political acts]] and the consequent need for a show of strength forced the Luftwaffe to be in a perpetual state of readiness. This did not allow time for organizational strategy. Göring complicated the hierarchy by bringing the paratrooper ({{lang-de|[[Fallschirmjäger]]}}) and [[Flak corps]] (anti-aircraft units) under his command. Due to his political differences with the army leadership, he raised his own police force as Prussian Minister of the Interior.&lt;ref&gt;Not to be confused with Göring's formation of the [[Gestapo]], the political secret state police force in Prussia. McNab, Chris, (2009) ''The SS: 1923–1945'', pp. 150, 162.&lt;/ref&gt; This later became the Paratroop Tank Corps ({{lang-de|Fallschirmjägerpanzerkorps}}).&lt;ref name=Buell02p14&gt;Buell, Griess, Bradley and Dice, (2002) p. 14&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Ruffner.90.3&gt;Ruffner, (1990) pp. 3–4&lt;/ref&gt;

By September 1939, the Luftwaffe had a total of 4,000 aircraft and 400,000 personnel. This strength had grown to 1,700,000 by 1941. In total, 571,000 of these were in anti-aircraft units and another 18 percent were in the signals branch. Only 36 percent or 588,000 comprised air-crew, but this also included the aircraft maintenance personnel. At the end of the war on 8 May 1945, more than 97,000 air-crew would be reported dead, wounded or missing.&lt;ref name=Ruffner.90.3/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;SteadmanChappell02pp67&quot;/&gt;

==Organizational levels==
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-H27413, Berlin, Reichsluftfahrtministerium.jpg|thumb|The ''Reichsluftfahrtministerium'', or Reich Air Ministry on [[Leipziger Strasse]] in [[Berlin]] in 1938|alt=Photo of the Reich Air Ministry in Berlin.]]
All aspects of aviation including the Luftwaffe, came under the control of the ''[[Reichsluftfahrtministerium]]'' (RLM), the Reich Air Ministry. Since the Luftwaffe was one of the three armed forces, it came under the Commander in Chief of the Armed Forces from a military command point of view ({{lang-de|[[Oberkommando der Wehrmacht]]}}) (OKW).&lt;ref name=&quot;Uswd95p15&quot;&gt;United States War Dept., (1995) p. 15&lt;/ref&gt;

Göring was the cabinet minister of aviation ({{lang-de|Reichsminister der Luftfahrt}}) during most of this period. He also served as the Commander in Chief of the Luftwaffe ({{lang-de|Oberbefehlshaber der Luftwaffe}}). As a cabinet minister, he was responsible for civil aviation and all aspects of aircraft manufacturing and supply. Operationally, the Luftwaffe command was shared by the [[Inspector of Combat Flight]] ({{lang-de|General der Kampfflieger}}) and the [[Inspector of Fighters]] ({{lang-de|General der Jagdflieger}}) along with the [[State Secretary for Aviation|Secretary of State for Aviation]].&lt;ref name=Uswd95&gt;United States War Dept., (1995) p. 591&lt;/ref&gt;

The German air force was divided into three operational branches:
* Flying Troops
* Anti-Aircraft Artillery
* Air Signal Troops

These three branches were further divided into sub-branches such as Paratroops, air engineering, air medical corps and air-crew. Since the Luftwaffe was organized in a geographical fashion rather than on a strategic functional basis, it had an independent administrative as well as an operational command structures. Each geographical area had its own supply and maintenance corps. For this reason, any aviation units moving within that geographical area did not need to carry its own maintenance staff. This allowed for a great deal of mobility within the Luftwaffe.&lt;ref name=&quot;Uswd95p15&quot;/&gt;

===Strategic===
[[File:Luftwaffe Organization.jpg|thumb|right|400px|Luftwaffe Organization Chart during this period.&lt;ref name=&quot;Uswd95p15&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Navalpress05p14&quot;/&gt;|alt=An organization chart for the Luftwaffe Organization during WWII.]]
Strategically, all three German military forces were part of a single service called, &quot;The Defensive Power&quot; ({{lang-de|Die Wehrmacht}}; from {{lang-de|wehren}}([[Verb]]), to defend; and {{lang-de|die Macht}}, the Power, Might) controlled by the ''{{lang|de|[[Oberkommando der Wehrmacht]]}}'' (OKW); the head of the OKW was part of the Cabinet. Within the OKW, each service was headed by its own operational command:
* Commander in Chief of the Army ({{lang-de|[[Oberkommando des Heeres]]}})
* Commander in Chief of the Air Force ({{lang-de|[[Oberkommando der Luftwaffe]]}})
* Commander in Chief of the Navy ({{lang-de|[[Oberkommando der Kriegsmarine]]}})&lt;ref name=&quot;Uswd95p15&quot;/&gt;

The top levels of control of the Luftwaffe resided with the RLM, the German Air Ministry and its operational branch, the ''[[Oberkommando der Luftwaffe]]'' (OKL), or Air Force High Command. These institutions together were responsible for the direction of research, production and overall maintenance of aircraft.&lt;ref name=&quot;Uswd95p15&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Navalpress05p14&quot;&gt;Frieser and Greenwood, (2005) p. 14&lt;/ref&gt;

As head of the Luftwaffe, Göring was responsible for the overall war effort and for the resources sent to a particular region. As a cabinet minister, he was able to get significant resources and personnel allocated to the Luftwaffe compared to other branches of the armed forces. In 1945, close to the end of the war, [[Robert Ritter von Greim]] replaced Göring as Commander in Chief.&lt;ref name=Lepage09pp216&gt;Lepage, (2009) pp. 2, 16&lt;/ref&gt;

===Operational===
{{Main article|German Air Fleets in World War II}}
The OKL, as the operational branch of the RLM, had complete control over unit movements, formation and personnel transfers. It had a strength of 25,000 personnel in 1939. On an operational level, the Luftwaffe was divided into air fleets ({{lang-de|Luftflotten}}), not entirely unlike the nearly contemporary [[United States Army Air Corps]] and (after late June 1941) [[USAAF]] [[numbered air force]]s. Each air fleet was responsible for a particular geographic region. They were self-contained units equipped with all types of aircraft and their own supply elements, maintenance staff, administration and legal departments.&lt;ref name=Robertstedman02p5&gt;Stedman and Chappell, (2002) p. 5&lt;/ref&gt;

At the start of the war the Luftwaffe had four ''Luftflotten'', each responsible for roughly a quarter of Germany. As the war progressed, three more were created as the areas under German rule expanded. ''[[Luftflotte 5]]'' was created in 1940 to direct operations in [[Norway]] and [[Denmark]]. The commander of each ''Luftflotte'' was responsible for all fighter as well as support operations within that region. A fighter leader ({{lang-de|Jagdführer}}) (Jafü) was responsible for fighter operations within that region and reported to the commander.&lt;ref name=Robertstedman02p5/&gt;

Each ''Luftflotte'' in turn was divided into many air districts ({{lang-de|Luftgaue}}) and air corps ({{lang-de|Fliegerkorps}}). The purpose of a ''Luftgau'' was to provide administrative and logistical support to each airfield, whereas the ''Fliegerkorps'' controlled all operational matters. The ''Luftgau'' headquarters command consisted of one ''[[Generalmajor]]'' and a staff of 50 to 100 officers. Each ''Fliegerkorps'' would have a number of units under its command. These were usually several wings ({{lang-de|Geschwader}}), but sometimes also specialized squadrons ({{lang-de|Staffeln}}) and battle groups ({{lang-de|Kampfgruppen}}).&lt;ref name=Robertstedman02p5/&gt;

===Tactical===
Each ''Geschwader'' within the ''Fliegerkorps'' was roughly the size of an [[Royal Air Force|RAF]] [[Wing (air force unit)|wing]], with about 90 to 120 aircraft under its command. These numbers varied as sub-units were added or removed. Each wing had a particular task (such as fighter, bomber, or transport duties) and were mostly equipped with aircraft appropriate to that task. Other types of aircraft were also sometimes attached.&lt;ref name=Robertstedman02pp56&gt;Stedman and Chappell, (2002) pp. 5, 6&lt;/ref&gt;

A ''Geschwader'' was commanded by a ''[[Geschwaderkommodore]]'', with the [[Military rank|rank]] of either a [[major]], [[Lieutenant Colonel|lieutenant colonel]] ({{lang-de|[[Oberstleutnant]]}}) or [[colonel]] ({{lang-de|[[Oberst]]}}). The unit also had other staff officers with administrative duties such as the {{lang-de|[[adjutant]]}}), technical and operations officers. These were usually (although not always), experienced [[Aircrew member|aircrew]] still flying on operations. Other specialist staff were [[navigation]], [[Military communications|signals]] and [[Military intelligence|intelligence]] personnel. A [[headquarters]] [[Flight (military unit)|flight]] or ({{lang-de|[[Stab (Luftwaffe designation)|Stabschwarm]]}}) was attached to each ''Geschwader''.&lt;ref name=&quot;SteadmanChappell02pp67&quot;&gt;Stedman and Chappell, (2002) pp. 6–7&lt;/ref&gt;

==Strategic level: ''Oberkommando der Luftwaffe''==
{{Main article|Oberkommando der Luftwaffe}}
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-1988-0106-501, von Blomberg. 40-jähriges Militärjubiläum.jpg|thumb|War minister and OKW commander [[Werner von Blomberg|Blomberg]] followed by the three armed forces chiefs inspecting a parade in honor of Blomberg's birthday in 1937|alt=Werner von Blomberg inspects a parade in his honor on his birthday. Soldiers with Guns stand to attention.]]

The OKW was the highest in the military command structure. It was responsible for the co-ordinated effort of the three military arms. It was headed by [[Wilhelm Keitel]] after he took over from war minister  [[Werner von Blomberg]] in 1938. Since the head of the Luftwaffe, Göring, was also a cabinet minister, any Luftwaffe operational orders would come from Hitler to him, who would pass them on to Luftwaffe leaders, bypassing the OKW.&lt;ref&gt;United States War Dept., (1995) pp. 15, 591&lt;/ref&gt;

On 5 February 1944, through the efforts of [[Günther Korten]] and [[Karl Koller (general)|Karl Koller]], the Luftwaffe High Command ({{lang-de|Oberkommando der Luftwaffe}}) (OKL), was formed. Colonel General ({{lang-de|''[[Generaloberst]]''}}) [[Hans Jeschonnek]] was appointed Chief of Staff of the OKL. This created a military command out of the all encompassing Reich Air Ministry (RLM), controlling all aspects of aviation. The OKL covered general as well as operational staff of the Luftwaffe. The following parts of the Luftwaffe were under its command:&lt;ref name=&quot;Navalpress05p14&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Caldwell and Muller, (2007) pp. 145, 298&lt;/ref&gt;
* The General Staff
* Operational Staff
* Weapons Inspectorates
* Inspector of Fighters ({{lang-de|[[General der Jagdflieger]]}})
* Supply and equipment
* A Signals Division&lt;ref name=&quot;Navalpress05p14&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=caldwell02p145&gt;Caldwell and Muller, (2007) p. 145&lt;/ref&gt;

The other components, such as armament and aircraft manufacturing remained under the control of the RLM.&lt;ref name=&quot;caldwell02p145&quot;/&gt;

The OKL was led by the Chief of the General Staff. It was strategically divided into eight directorates ({{lang-de|Abteilungen}}) numbered consecutively. The directorates were:
* Operations Directorate
* Organization Directorate
* Training Directorate
* Troop Movement Directorate
* Intelligence Directorate
* Equipment and Supply Directorate
* Historical Archives Directorate
* Personnel Management Directorate

There were also 17 Inspectorates:
* Luftwaffe Inspection ({{lang-de|Luftwaffen Inspektion}}) 1 – Reconnaissance
* ''Luftwaffen Inspektion'' 2 – Bombers and Dive Bombers ([[General der Kampfflieger]])
* ''Luftwaffen Inspektion'' 3 – Fighter, Destroyer, Ground Support and Weaponry ([[General der Jagdflieger]])
* ''Luftwaffen Inspektion'' 5 – Air safety and equipment
* ''Luftwaffen Inspektion'' 6 – Motor vehicles
* ''Luftwaffen Inspektion'' 7 – Signal communications ([[General der Nachrichtentruppe]])
* ''Luftwaffen Inspektion'' 8 – Naval aircraft (Disbanded in 1942)
* ''Luftwaffen Inspektion'' 9 – Pilot training schools
* ''Luftwaffen Inspektion'' 10 – Troop service and training
* ''Luftwaffen Inspektion'' 11 – Parachute and air-landing forces
* ''Luftwaffen Inspektion'' 12 – Navigation
* ''Luftwaffen Inspektion'' 13 – Air Defense (Under the control of the Secretary of State for Aviation)
* ''Luftwaffen Inspektion'' 14 – Medical
* ''Luftwaffen Inspektion'' 15 – Air Defense zones
* ''Luftwaffen Inspektion'' 16 – Air sea rescue services under the umbrella of Sea Rescue Service {{lang-de|[[Seenotdienst]]}}.
* ''Luftwaffen Inspektion'' 17 – Construction troops and prisoners of war (Under the control of the Secretary of State for Aviation)
* ''Luftwaffen Inspektion'' 18 – Luftwaffe field units&lt;ref name=Uswd95p1188&gt;United States War Department, (1995) pp. 37, 188&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Boog, Krebs and Vogel, (2006) pp. xxvii, 237&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Nielsen, (1968) pp. 81, 260&lt;/ref&gt;

==Operational level==
Six ''Luftkreise'' (Air Service Commands) were established on 1 April 1934. These were each the size of an Air Corps and were basic territorial units of the Luftwaffe following its geographical organization. Their headquarters were as given in the table:&lt;ref name=Mitcham07p12&gt;Mitcham, (2007-a) p. 12&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition, Luftkreis VII was established on 12 October 1937 with its headquarters at Braunschweig, and is shown incorporated into the above-mentioned table &lt;ref&gt;'Luftwaffe Colours - Kampfflieger Vol1 (Bombers of the Luftwaffe 1933-1940 (Smith &amp; Creek) ISBN 1-903223-42-3, p21&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable floatleft&quot;
|+ ''Luftkreise'' Headquarters.&lt;ref name=Mitcham07p12/&gt;
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | ''Luftkreis''
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Headquarters
|-
| ''Luftkreis I''|| [[Königsberg]]
|-
| ''Luftkreis II'' || [[Berlin]]
|-
| ''Luftkreis III'' || [[Dresden]]
|-
| ''Luftkreis IV'' || [[Münster]]
|-
| ''Luftkreis V'' || [[München]]
|-
| ''Luftkreis VI'' (sea) || [[Kiel]]
|-
| ''Luftkreis VII'' || [[Braunschweig]]
|-
|}

Each ''Luftkreis'' was led by a ''Höherer Fliegerkommandeur'' (Senior Air Commander) in charge of all aviation units within its area. These included, two or three ''Luftgaukommandos'' (administrative commands), a signals command, a medical battalion and a procurement and supply group. Their area of operations also included civilian airfields and Civil Air Defense. The following year, all the replacement battalions in that area also came under their control. In 1936, these were extended to regiment size or ''Fliegerersatzregimente''. From 1935–36, Flak units in the area also came under their command.&lt;ref name=Mitcham07p12/&gt;

Hermann Göring and [[Erhard Milch]] appointed retired army lieutenant generals to lead each ''Luftkreis''. These were [[Hans Halm]], [[Edmund Wachenfeld]] and [[Leonhard Kaupisch]]. They were promoted to ''[[General der Flieger]]''. A retired navy officer, [[Konrad Zander]], was similarly promoted and put in charge of ''Luftkreis'' VI supporting the naval units. Two Luftwaffe officers, Colonel [[Hugo Sperrle]] and Major General [[Karl Schweickhard]] were put in charge of the remaining two ''Luftkreise'' without being promoted.&lt;ref name=Mitcham07p12/&gt;

Operationally, the Luftwaffe organization underwent changes in July 1938. ''Luftkreise'' were consolidated into three Luftwaffengruppenkommandos (Airforce Group Commands). As a result, on 1 August 1938, ''Luftwaffenkommando Ostpreußen'' (Airforce Command East Prussia) replaced ''Luftkreis'' 1. This change also rendered the three digit ''Geschwader'' identifiers meaningless. From 1 November 1938, ''Geschwader'' identifiers were changed universally. The third digit of the Unit Identifier was replaced with the same digit as its parent ''Luftwaffengruppenkommando''. For example, all units under ''Luftwaffengruppenkommando 1'' (headquartered in Berlin), had the third digit of their identifiers replaced with a '1'. For units under ''Luftwaffengruppenkommando Ostpreußen'', the third digit was replaced with a zero.&lt;ref name=weal03p10&gt;Weal, (2003) p. 10&lt;/ref&gt;

By the end of April 1939, another ''Luftwaffengruppenkommando'' was added. All four ''Luftwaffengruppenkommando'' were renamed ''Luftflotte'' (Air Fleets). Geschwaders under each ''Luftflotte'', were re-numbered sequentially. Each ''Luftflotte'' received a batch of 25. For example, ''Luftflotte 1'' Geschwaders were numbered 0–25, ''Luftflotte 2'' Geschwaders became 26–50 and so on.&lt;ref name=weal03p10/&gt;

===''Luftgaue''===
Within the Air Ministry, for administration purposes, the Luftwaffe was organized into ''Luftgaue'' (Air Districts), based on the army's ''[[Military district (Germany)|Wehrkreis]]'' (&quot;military districts&quot;). A ''Luftgau'' was responsible for all administrative activities, such as training, administration, maintenance, air defense, signals, recruitment and reserve personnel.

The ''[[Generalmajor]]'' leading the ''Luftgau-kommando'' of each ''Luftgau'' reported to the Air Ministry.

Those ''Luftgaue''  established within Germany were numbered non-consecutively with Roman numerals.&lt;ref name=DenisLepage09p17/&gt;&lt;ref name=uswd95p597&gt;United States War Dept., (1995) p. 597&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Div col|&quot;cols&quot;=2}}
* [[Luftgau I]] ([[Königsberg]])
* [[Luftgau II]] ([[Stettin]])
* [[Luftgau III]] ([[Berlin]])
* [[Luftgau IV]] ([[Dresden]])
* [[Luftgau V]] ([[Stuttgart]])
* [[Luftgau VI]] ([[Münster]])
* [[Luftgau VII]] ([[Munich]])
* [[Luftgau VIII]] ([[Breslau]])
* [[Luftgau IX]] ([[Weimar]])
* [[Luftgau X]] ([[Hamburg]])
* [[Luftgau XI]] ([[Hanover]])
* [[Luftgau XII]] ([[Giessen]]/[[Wiesbaden]])
* [[Luftgau XIII]] ([[Nuremberg]])
* [[Luftgau XIV]] ([[Koblenz]])
* [[Luftgau XVII]] ([[Vienna]])
{{Div col end}}
''Luftgaue'' were also established as required in [[occupied Europe]] and were named after their location, e.g. ''Luftgau Belgien-Nordfrankreich'' was headquartered in Brussels and responsible for Belgium and northern France.

Each ''Luftgau'' had its own section for the following matters:
* Operations
* Adjutant
* Legal
* Administration
* Signals
* Supply
* Restricted flying areas

These sections were numbered in Arabic numerals followed by a ''Luftgau'' designator. For example, section 3 of ''Luftgau VI'' would be designated '3/VI'. Flying units used the services of a ''Luftgau through'' ''Flughafenbereichkommandanturen'' (Airfield Regional Commands). Each ''Luftgau'' usually had five such commands. Each regional command was divided into five or more ''Einsatzhafenkommandanturen'' (Operational Airfield Commands). The operational commands were located at the airfields where it serviced the flying units.&lt;ref name=uswd95p597/&gt;

===''Luftflotte''===
{{further|German Air Fleets in World War II}}
[[File:Chef einer Luftflotte Version 2.svg|thumb|upright|Flag of the Chief of a ''Luftflotte''|alt=Image of the Flag of a Chief of Luftflotte.]]
Operationally under the OKL, all Luftwaffe units were organized into ''Luftflotte'', which were equivalent to an army group. Its size and number of subordinated units, was flexible and changed depending on need. The ''Luftflotten'' were created according to the geographical area. As the Wehrmacht occupied new territories, new ''Luftflotten'' were created. Each ''Luftflotte'', had an adjutant or staff officer assisting the commanding officer. Although a ''Luftflotte'' could be moved from one area to another by the RLM, the ''Luftflotte'' had absolute control over all aspects of aviation in that area, including ground operations. This also included legal, administration, signals and supply work. They were essentially divided into operational or administrative commands. The signal services consisted of three ''Luft-Nachrichtenregimenter'' (signals regiments) in a ''Luftflotte''. There was also a ''Fliegerabwehrkanone'' ([[Anti-aircraft warfare|Flak]]) unit.&lt;ref name=DenisLepage09p17/&gt;&lt;ref name=Uswd95p592&gt;United States War Dept., (1995) p. 592&lt;/ref&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; ; text-align:left&quot;
|+ ''Luftflotte'' and their areas of operation.&lt;ref name=DenisLepage09p17/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;SteadmanChappell02pp67&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Bower98p119&gt;Bower, (1998) p. 119&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;G.Bernage, F.de Lannoy - Dictionnaire Historique - La Luftwaffe 1939-1945- Editions Heimdal&lt;/ref&gt;
! scope=&quot;col&quot; style=&quot;width:150px;&quot;| ''Luftflotte''
! scope=&quot;col&quot; style=&quot;width:150px;&quot;| Original Headquarters Location
! scope=&quot;col&quot; style=&quot;width:150px;&quot;| Area of Operations
! scope=&quot;col&quot; style=&quot;width:300px;&quot;| Major Campaigns
|-
|[[Luftflotte 1]] ||[[Berlin]] || [[Northern Germany|North]] and [[Eastern Germany|East Germany]] || [[Invasion of Poland]], North Russia
|-
|[[Luftflotte 2]] ||[[Braunschweig]] ||Northwest Germany||1939–40 [[Western Front (World War II)|Western Front]], [[Battle of Britain]], [[European Russia|Central Russia]], [[Italy]], [[North African Campaign|North Africa]], [[Mediterranean, Middle East and African theatres of World War II|Mediterranean Campaign]].
|-
|[[Luftflotte 3]]{{ref label|Note1|a|a}} ||[[München]]|| Southwest Germany||1939 Western Front, Battle of Britain, [[Invasion of Europe]].
|-
|[[Luftflotte 4]] ||[[Wien]]|| Southeast Germany||Invasion of Poland, [[Balkans Campaign (World War II)|Balkans Campaign]], South Russia, [[Hungary]] and [[Slovakia]].
|-
|[[Luftflotte 5]] ||[[Hamburg]]|| [[Norway]], [[Finland]] and Northern Russia||[[Arctic convoys of World War II|The Arctic Convoys]] and Northern Russia.
|-
|[[Luftflotte 6]] ||[[Smolensk]]|| [[European Russia|Central Russia]] || Invasion of Poland, [[Protectorate of Bohemia and Moravia|Bohemia-Moravia]], [[Invasion of Yugoslavia|Slovakia and Croatia]].
|-
|Luftwaffen-Befehlshaber Mitte (Renamed ''[[Luftflotte Reich]]'' in 1944)||[[Berlin]]|| [[Defense of the Reich|Home Air Defense]]||[[Occupation of Denmark]], [[East Prussia]], [[Channel islands#World War II|Channel Islands]], [[Operation Doomsday|Liberation of Norway]] and [[Hungary]].
|-
|[[Luftflotte 10]] ||[[Berlin]]||Replacement and training units (from July 1944)||
|}

===''Fliegerkorps'' and ''Fliegerdivision''===
A ''Luftflotte'' was operationally divided into one or more ''Fliegerkorps'' (&quot;Air Corps&quot;) of varying size, depending on its area of operations. They were responsible for all operational matters such as deployment, air traffic, ordnance and maintenance. A ''Fliegerkorps'' could potentially be loaned out to another ''Luftflotte'' depending on the nature of the operation. There were a total of 13 ''Fliegerkorps''.&lt;ref name=DenisLepage09p17/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;uswd95p594&quot;&gt;United States War Dept., (1995) p. 594&lt;/ref&gt;

Similar to the ''Luftflotte'', each ''Fliegerkorps'' had its own geographical area of operations. It consisted of several Geschwader along with Reconnaissance ''Gruppen'' (Groups). The Geschwader could be either fighter or bomber units. Depending on the nature or purpose of the ''Fliegerkorps'', it would have only bomber or fighter units. Similar to the ''Luftflotte'', a ''Fliegerkorps'' also had an adjutant as well as other departments. However, it did depend on the parent ''Luftflotte'' for administrative and supply purposes. The ''Fliegerkorps'' were numbered consecutively in Roman numerals.&lt;ref name=DenisLepage09p17/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;uswd95p594&quot;/&gt; During the initial organization of the ''Luftwaffe'', it was divided into ''Fliegerdivisionen''. However, during later reorganizations, most of these were replaced by the ''Fliegerkorps''. Some remained in operation on the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]].&lt;ref name=&quot;uswd95p594&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Denislepage09p18&gt;Lepage, (2009) p. 18&lt;/ref&gt;

A ''Jagdkorps'' was a more specialized version of a ''Fliegerkorps'' with limited responsibility to fighter command only. A ''Jagd-Division'' was subordinated to a ''Jagdkorps'' but specialized in fighter operations. Jagd-Divisionen (fighter divisions) were active at one point or other during this period. Together the fighter force of Luftwaffe was also called Jagdwaffe.&lt;ref name=&quot;uswd95p594&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Denislepage09p18/&gt;

The Luftwaffe also had specialist divisions for testing new aircraft as well as captured allied machines. It was initially unnumbered and simply called the ''Lehrdivision'' (Instruction Division) but in later years several ''Erprobungskommando'' were created to test specific new aircraft. Along with the aircraft, it was also responsible for testing anti-aircraft defenses and air signals equipment. The staff of this division was required to have prior combat experience. The ''Lehr'' units in this division were usually made part of operational units, receiving help from them for testing under combat conditions. This division did not undertake the testing of experimental aircraft. As the war went on, some of the units under its command were used for operational purposes.&lt;ref name=&quot;uswd95p594&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Denislepage09p18/&gt;

==Tactical level==

===''Geschwader''===
In the Luftwaffe the largest mobile and autonomous unit was the ''Geschwader''. A ''Geschwader'' was the equivalent of a [[Wing (military aviation unit)|Wing]] in the [[United States Army Air Forces]] (USAAF). It would be used for different purposes such as bombing, interception (both single and twin engine), ground attack and reconnaissance. A ''Geschwader'' would be named, based on its purpose.&lt;ref name=Mitcham07p12/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;uswd95p594&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Denislepage09p18/&gt;&lt;ref name =stedman02p6&gt;Stedman and Chappell, (2002) p. 6&lt;/ref&gt; There were several ''Geschwader'' with the same purpose. They would be named with an Arabic numeral following the word. It was also customary to give an additional title to a ''Geschwader'' in honor of a distinguished person. For example, ''[[Jagdgeschwader 2]]'' was named ''Jagdgeschwader 2 Richthofen'' in honor of [[Manfred von Richthofen]].&lt;ref name=Denislepage09p18/&gt;&lt;ref name =stedman02p6/&gt;

Each ''Geschwader'' was commanded by a ''[[Geschwaderkommodore]]''. This person usually had the rank of ''[[Oberst]]'' (equivalent to colonel), ''[[Oberstleutnant]]'' (lieutenant colonel) or major. He had a small staff along with an [[adjutant]] (Staff Officer) for operational as well as for administrative purposes. There would be a ''[[Stabschwarm]]'' (staff flight) of four aircraft including the Geschwaderkommodore's aircraft. Typically there were three ''Gruppen'' (groups) under each ''Geschwader'' and sometimes a fourth or even a fifth ''gruppe'' was added to single engine fighter ''geschwader''. On several occasions, [[day fighter]] ''Geschwader'' or ''Jagdgeschwader'' were formed with four ''Gruppe'' strength from start.&lt;ref name=Mitcham07p12/&gt;&lt;ref name=uswd95p594/&gt;&lt;ref name=Denislepage09p18/&gt;&lt;ref name =stedman02p6/&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|+ Types of Geschwader and their purpose.&lt;ref name=Denislepage09p18/&gt;
|-
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Purpose
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Name
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Abbreviation
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Examples
|-
| Fighter
| ''Jagdgeschwader''
| JG
| [[JG 52]], [[JG 27]]
|-
| Bomber
| ''Kampfgeschwader ''
| KG
| [[KG 4]], [[KG 30]]
|-
| Dive-bomber
| ''Sturzkampfgeschwader''
| StG
| [[StG 2]], [[Sturzkampfgeschwader 77|StG 77]]&lt;br /&gt;(to October 1943)
|-
| Transport aircraft
| ''Transportgeschwader'' (1943–45)
| TG
| TG 1, TG 4
|-
| Advanced Training
| ''Lehrgeschwader''
| LG
| [[LG 1]], [[LG 2]]
|-
| Glider
| ''Luftlandegeschwader''
| LLG
| LLG 1, LLG 2
|-
| Night Fighter
| ''Nachtjagdgeschwader''
| NJG
| [[NJG 3]], [[NJG 11]]
|-
| Ground attack
| ''Schlachtgeschwader''
| SchlG, since October 1943 SG&lt;br/&gt;(also replacing the old StG prefix)
| [[SG 2]], [[SG 1]]
|-
| Fast bomber
| ''Schnellkampfgeschwader''
| SKG
| SKG 10, SKG 210
|-
| Heavy fighter
| ''Zerstörergeschwader''
| ZG
| [[ZG 26]], [[ZG 76]]
|}
* ''Jagdgeschwader (JG)'' – A day fighter ''Geschwader'' (literally &quot;hunting wing&quot;), typically equipped with the [[Messerschmitt Bf 109]] or [[Focke-Wulf Fw 190|Fw 190]] flying in the fighter or [[Ground-attack aircraft|fighter-bomber]] roles.
* ''Nachtjagdgeschwader (NJG)'' – A [[night fighter]] ''Geschwader'', typically flying [[Lichtenstein radar|radar]]-equipped [[heavy fighter]]s such as the Messerschmitt Bf 110 or [[Junkers Ju 88|Ju 88]] against [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] bombers.
* ''Zerstörergeschwader (ZG)'' – ''[[Zerstörer]]'' (literally &quot;destroyer&quot;, as in naval [[destroyer]]). These units were usually equipped with twin-engined [[heavy fighter]]s such as the [[Messerschmitt Bf 110|Bf 110]] or [[Messerschmitt Me 410|Me 410 ''Hornisse'']].
* ''Schlachtgeschwader'' (''SchlG'', since 1943 ''SG'') – ''Schlacht'' ([[German language|German]]: &quot;strike&quot;)  These were [[Ground-attack aircraft|ground attack]] or [[close air support]] ''Geschwader'', initially equipped with the biplane [[Hs 123]], later with [[Hs-129]], fighter-bomber variants of [[Bf 109]], and [[Focke-Wulf Fw 190#Attack versions|ground-attack variants of Fw 190]].
* ''Sturzkampfgeschwader'' (''StG''; ''Stuka Geschwader'') – [[dive bomber]] ''Geschwader'' equipped mainly with [[Ju 87]]; on 18 October 1943, most of them were re-designated ''Schlachtgeschwader'' (''SG'').&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|pages=40–41|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=UPNzp8-i63EC&amp;lpg=PA40&amp;pg=PA40|title=Focke-Wulf Fw 190 Aces of the Russian Front|isbn=9781855325180|author1=Weal|first1=John|date=1995-09-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''Kampfgeschwader (KG)'' – literally ''combat wing'', primarily a medium bomber unit, with typical aircraft being the [[Heinkel He 111|He 111]] and the Junkers Ju 88.
* ''Lehrgeschwader (LG)'' – a ''Geschwader'' created to test new equipment under operational conditions and to evaluate new tactics. Personnel from a unit of this type could fly several types of aircraft.
* ''Transportgeschwader (TG)'' – typical aircraft being the [[Junkers Ju 52|Ju 52/3m]] or the [[Messerschmitt Me 323|Me 323]]. The &quot;TG&quot; designation was a result of the reorganization of the transport branch in 1943. These units were previously designated ''KG zbV'' (''Kampfgeschwader zur besonderen Verwendung'' or &quot;combat ''Geschwader'' for special purposes&quot;).
* ''Kampfschulgeschwader (KSG)'' – a Bomber Training School ''Geschwader''.
* ''Luftlandegeschwader (LLG)'' – a Glider Geschwader for the ''[[Fallschirmjäger]]'' or Paratroops.
* ''Schnellkampfgeschwader (SKG)'' – [[fast bomber]] wing. Two units equipped with single- or twin-engine fighter bombers and used for ground-attack or hit-and-run missions over the [[United Kingdom]]. Later absorbed by other units or re-designated as Schlachtgeschwader.

As the war progressed, the various sub-units of each numbered ''Geschwader'' operated separately and often on totally different fronts or theaters of war.&lt;ref name=Denislepage09p18/&gt;

===''Gruppe''===
The ''Gruppe'' was the basic autonomous unit in the Luftwaffe, in both administration and strategic use, much the same as in the American air forces of that time. Each ''Gruppe'' would have a ''[[Stab (Luftwaffe designation)|Stabschwarm]]'' (&quot;Staff flight&quot;) of three aircraft. The ''Gruppe'' would be commanded by a ''[[Gruppenkommandeur]]'', that would be a ''major'' or ''[[Hauptmann]]''. He would have a small staff including administration, operations, medical and technical officers. A ''Gruppe'' usually occupied one airfield. ''Gruppen'' from the same ''Geschwader'' typically occupied adjacent airfields. Each would have an air signals platoon, mechanical and administrative personnel. There was also a trained fire-fighting crew doubling as police officers and staffed by the [[SS]].&lt;ref name=Denislepage09p18/&gt;

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-356-1805-24A, Frankreich, Flugzeug Ju 88.jpg|thumb|A [[Junkers Ju 88|Junkers Ju 88 A-4]] of 2./Küstenfliegergruppe 106, being loaded with bombs, 1942. Note the condition of the ''Balkenkreuz''.|alt=Junkers JU 88 displaying the Balkenkreuz.]]
As with the ''Geschwader'' combat wing formation, the ''Gruppe'' included staff officers tasked with additional administrative duties, usually an adjutant, technical, medical and operations officers. These officers were usually (though not always), experienced [[Aircrew member|aircrew]] or pilots appointed from the operational cadre within the unit.

''Gruppen'' organized within a combat wing were designated with [[Roman numeral]]s: I, II, III and IV. This would be combined with the abbreviated ''Geschwader'' designation – for example, the second ''Gruppe'' of ''Jagdgeschwader'' 11 would be designated II./JG 11. Each ''Gruppe'' in turn consisted of three ''Staffeln'' (squadrons). In total, each group had thirty to forty aircraft including the ''Gruppenstab''. A ''Gruppe'' was often transferred from one ''Geschwader'' to another. After a transfer they would be re-designated. For example, ''Gruppe II'' of ''Jagdgeschwader 3'', II./JG 3 was transferred to ''Jagdgeschwader 1'' as ''Gruppe I'' and was re-designated I./JG 1. In the case of bomber Geschwaders, an ''Ergänzungsgruppe'' (training group) might be attached to a ''Geschwader'' as the fifth ''Gruppe'' and designated 'V' (Roman numeral 5).&lt;ref name=SteadmanChappell02pp67/&gt;&lt;ref name=Denislepage09p18/&gt;

Although all ''Gruppen'' in a ''Geschwader'' performed the same role, they were not always equipped with the same aircraft. This was more prevalent in fighter ''Geschwader'', but did occur in bomber units as well. Some groups of a fighter ''Geschwader'' would be equipped with Messerschmitt Bf 109s, while others would be equipped with Focke-Wulf Fw 190s. Among the bomber ''Geschwaders'', some ''Gruppen'' would be equipped with [[Dornier Do 17]]s while others would have either Heinkel He 111s or Junkers Ju 88s.&lt;ref name=Denislepage09p18/&gt;

There were several types of ''Gruppen'' acting in specialized autonomous roles, many centered around either reconnaissance or maritime-involved duties. They were:

So-named ''Aufklärungsgruppe'' [[Aerial reconnaissance|reconnaissance]] units existed in two basic forms for the Luftwaffe in World War II:
* ''Aufklärungsgruppe (F)'' – a long range reconnaissance ''Gruppe''. It was later changed to ''Fernaufklärungsgruppe'' (FAGr), from ''Fern'', the German word for &quot;far&quot;;
* ''Aufklärungsgruppe (H)'' were units initially attached to the army (''Heer''). They provided tactical and photo reconnaissance and were later re-designated ''Nahaufklärungsgruppe'' (NAGr), from ''Nah'' (near). Typical aircraft were Messerschmitt Bf 109s, Bf 110s and Hs 126s, although a wide range of aircraft types were used, including the STOL-capable [[Fieseler Fi 156]], and the twin-engined [[Focke-Wulf Fw 189]].
* ''Fernaufklärungsgruppe (FAGr)'' – The later designation for ''Aufklärungsgruppe (F)'' involved with long-range reconnaissance duties.
* ''Nahaufklarungsgruppe (NAGr)'' – The later designation for ''Aufklärungsgruppen (H)'' or army reconnaissance group.

Maritime-involved ''Gruppe''-sized units of the Luftwaffe involved:
* ''Bordfliegergruppe (BFGr)'' – (literally &quot;onboard aircraft group&quot;). [[Arado Ar 196]] seaplanes on battleships and cruisers.
* ''Küstenfliegergruppe (KuFlGr)'' (German: &quot;coastal aircraft group&quot;) a coastal reconnaissance ''Gruppe''. These units fulfilled a similar role to [[RAF Coastal Command]] and were usually equipped with floatplanes such as the [[Heinkel He 115]] and [[flying boat]]s like the [[Dornier Do 18]] as well as land-based bombers such as the Dornier Do 17. These units were also used to attack shipping.
* ''Minensuchgruppe (MSGr)'' – (literally &quot;minesearch group&quot;). Junkers Ju-52s, or rarely [[Blohm und Voss BV 138|Bv 138 flying boats]] fitted with [[Degaussing|large electromagnetic rings]] that were designed to sweep oceanic minefields of magnetically-triggered [[sea mines]].
* ''Seeaufklärungsgruppe (SAGr)'' –  a ''Gruppe'' for maritime reconnaissance.
* ''Trägergruppe (TrGr)'' – (literally &quot;Carrier group&quot;). They consisted of Junkers Ju 87C (Stukas) and [[Messerschmitt Bf 109 variants#Bf 109T &quot;Trägerflugzeug&quot; (carrier aircraft)|Bf 109 T]] aircraft for the planned [[German aircraft carrier Graf Zeppelin|German aircraft carrier ''Graf Zeppelin'']]. It was disbanded in 1940 after the carrier project was scrapped.

Other types of ''Gruppe''-sized units of various types existed within the Luftwaffe structure as well:
* ''Ergänzungsgruppe (ERgGr)'' – Supplemental groups that were attached to a ''Geschwader'' for replacing lost aircraft and training.
* ''Erprobungsgruppe (ErpGr)'' – a specialized ''Gruppe'', much like the similar ''[[Erprobungskommando]]'' units, for field testing new models and on occasions captured Allied aircraft, and often bearing the [[List of RLM aircraft designations|RLM airframe number]] of the aircraft design they were meant to test.
* ''Nachtschlachtgruppe (NSGr)'' – a night ground attack group. Predominantly used in anti-personnel and anti-tank roles.

Each ''Gruppe'' comprised three or four ''Staffeln'', but by late 1944 a fourth ''Staffel'' was usually added to fighter units, making the established strength of the unit approximately 65 to 70 aircraft, although during the war years operational strength tended to fluctuate greatly. Personnel strength varied between 35 and 150 aircrew, and 300 to 500 ground personnel.&lt;ref name=Denislepage09p18/&gt;

During the mid-war years a fourth ''Gruppe'' was introduced in many ''Geschwader'', initially as an [[Operational Conversion Unit|operational training unit]] for new aircrew. However, these ''Gruppen'' soon became additional front-line units, performing the same tasks as their sister formations, while new ''Ergänzungseinheiten'', or operational training units, were formed and took up their tasks.&lt;ref name=Weal.2006.12&gt;Weal (2006), p. 12.&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Staffel''===
A ''Staffel'' was the equivalent of a squadron. It usually had twelve aircraft but some had as few as five or six aircraft due to losses, while others had as many as 16. It would be led by a ''[[Staffelkapitän]]'' ranking Hauptmann, [[Oberleutnant]] or sometimes [[Leutnant]]. ''Staffeln'' were numbered consecutively in Arabic numerals within a ''Geschwader'' irrespective of the ''Gruppe'' they came under. The ''Staffel'' designation would be similar to that of the ''Gruppe'' except for the Arabic numerals. For example, ''Staffel 6'' of ''Jagdgeschwader 27'' would be designated 6./JG 27. The ''Staffeln'' of ''Gruppe I'' would be numbered 1, 2 and 3. Those of ''Gruppe II'' would be numbered 4, 5 and 6. This was continued for the rest of the groups.

When a ''Staffel'' was transferred from one group to another or from one ''Geschwader'' to another, it would be re-designated accordingly.&lt;ref name=SteadmanChappell02pp67/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lepage, (2009) pp. 18, 19, 48–50&lt;/ref&gt; For example, ''Gruppe II'' of ''Jagdgeschwader 3'', II./JG 3 was transferred to ''Jagdgeschwader 1'' as ''Gruppe I'' and was re-designated I./JG 1., this caused its three ''Staffeln'' originally named 4./JG 3, 5./JG 3, 6./JG 3 to be renumbered to 1./JG 1, 2./JG 1 and 3./JG 1.

The ''Staffel'' usually had a few vehicles allocated to it, and a mobile ''Fliegerhorstkompanie'' (air station company) to carry out minor repairs. These were usually named after and attached to a ''Geschwader''. The number of ground staff varied depending on its type, with about 150 for a fighter unit and 80 in a bomber unit – a smaller number of personnel were required in the bomber units as many of the servicing functions were carried out by attached units provided by the local ''Luftgau'' or &quot;Air District&quot;.&lt;ref name=Denislepage09p18/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Stedman and Chappell, (2002) p. 7&lt;/ref&gt;

The service test units often known as ''Erprobungskommando'' could also be of ''Staffel'' or ''Gruppe'' organizational size, as well as existing outside of any such &quot;set&quot; unit size as a group or squadron - the [[Heinkel He 177]] was service-tested by a ''Staffel''-sized unit, known as ''Erprobungsstaffel 177''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Heinkel He 177-277-274 |last= |first= |authorlink= |authors=Griehl, Manfred and Dressel, Joachim |year=1998 |publisher=Airlife Publishing |location=Shrewsbury, England |isbn= |page= |pages=55, 56, 58 |url= |accessdate=September 2, 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There were a few types of ''Staffeln'' acting in specialized autonomous, or semi-autonomous roles, if integrally attached to a ''Gruppe'' or ''Geschwader'' for differing duties from the main unit. Some of these were:
* ''Jagdbomberstaffel (Jabo)'' – a fighter-bomber ''Staffel'', within a ''Gruppe''. Predominantly refers to a ground attack squadron. It was made more prominent by [[Heinz Knoke]] with air-to-air bombing of Allied bombers.
* ''Luftbeobachtungstaffel'', later ''[[Wettererkundungsstaffel]]'' (Weku or Wekusta)'' – a ''Staffel'' meant for meteorological findings.&lt;ref name=SteadmanChappell02pp67/&gt;
* ''Zerstörerstaffel'', as the northernmost-based of all Luftwaffe day fighter wings, [[JG 5]] in northern Norway, had one attached to it [[JG 5#Staffelkapitäne|as its 13th ''Staffel'']].

After the mid 1942 successes of [[Operation Barbarossa]], Soviet VVS nocturnal [[Harassing fire|harassment bomber]] units such as the [[Night Witches]], used obsolete [[Polikarpov Po-2]] biplanes against the invading Germans. The Luftwaffe began to set up their own nocturnal harassment Staffel-sized forces known as ''Störkampfstaffeln''. Eventually ''Gruppe''-sized ''Nachtschlachtgruppen'' were used for the same general purpose as the Soviet units. The Luftwaffe's own harassment aviation units also used similarly obsolete aircraft, but of German design. The [[Heinkel He 46]], [[Arado Ar 66]], [[Focke-Wulf Fw 56]] and even the standard training biplane, the [[Gotha Go 145]], were all deployed in their efforts at attempting to emulate the success of the Soviets.

A few specialized ''Staffel'' sized units existed within the Luftwaffe for such specialized tasks as weather observation ''[[Wettererkundungsstaffel]]n'', (contracted to ''Wekusta''), specialized weaponry (a so-called ''Staffel 92'' was meant to be equipped with the cannon-armed [[Junkers Ju 88|Ju 88P]]-series of bomber destroyer fighters) and even outside the actual Luftwaffe, such as [[Focke-Wulf Fw 187#Operational history|aircraft factory-operated]] defense ''Staffeln'', at least one of which even operated the [[Me 262]] late in the war.

====''Schwarm'', ''Rotte'' and ''Kette''====
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Flugformation Rotte.jpg|Rotte
File:Flugformation Kettenkeil.jpg|Kette
&lt;/gallery&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
A ''Staffel'' was divided into three ''Schwärme'' (singular: ''Schwarm'', &quot;swarm&quot;), or [[flight (military unit)|flights]], consisting of four to six aircraft.

A fighter ''Schwarm'' was divided into two ''{{lang|de|Rotten}}'' (singular: ''Rotte'', &quot;pack&quot;) which was a pair of aircraft. The ''Rotte'' was the basic fighting unit, consisting of a leader and a wingman.

A bomber ''Schwarm'' was divided into a ''Kette'' (&quot;chain&quot;) of three aircraft flying in a [[Vic formation|&quot;V&quot; formation]].&lt;ref&gt;Lepage, (2009) p. 19&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Weal, (2006) p. 30&lt;/ref&gt;

===Air combat tactics ===
{{Main article|Finger-four}}
[[File:Four Finger Squadron.PNG|thumb|left|upright=1.4|Finger-four formation adopted by the Luftwaffe. Note the color coded flights.|alt=Pattern depicting Finger Four formation technique of the Luftwaffe.]]
During the Spanish Civil War, Luftwaffe aces [[Werner Mölders]] and [[Günther Lützow]] created a new formation strategy for fighter wings. It had two aircraft flying in a loose pair called a 'Pack' ({{lang-de|Rotte}}). Two pairs constituted a flight ({{lang-de|Schwarm}}). The four aircraft were flown in what was called the &quot;Finger-four&quot; formation. These aircraft were spread apart so that each pilot was offered maximum visibility. This arrangement was so successful that Soviet pilots in the Spanish Civil War followed the same technique. However, on returning home, they had to revert to the standard &quot;V&quot; formation. [[Douglas Bader]], the British pilot, was the first [[RAF]] leader to adopt the &quot;Finger four&quot; formation in 1940. Japan also adopted{{citation needed|date=January 2011}}&lt;!--not according to Sakai in ''Samurai''--&gt; the &quot;Finger four&quot; in World War II.&lt;ref name=Bickers96p150&gt;Bickers, (1996) p. 150&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Boyne, (2003) p. 192&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Buell02p77&gt;Buell, Griess, Bradley and Dice, (2002) p. 77&lt;/ref&gt; However, the [[Finnish Air Force]] claims to have used &quot;finger-four&quot; already in 1935.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.century-of-flight.net/Aviation%20history/WW2/fin_force.htm Finnish Air Force&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sci.fi/~fta/FAFhist.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:North American P-51 Mustang.JPG|thumb|The [[USAAF]] adopted the &quot;finger four&quot; formation by the time the Mustang saw squadron service.]]
In this formation, where each aircraft flew in positions similar to the fingers of an open hand (hence the name), the leader ({{lang-de|Rottenführer}}) was at the front, while on his left wingtip was his partner from the ''Rotte''. The other ''Rotte'' was on the right wingtip of the leader. The partner in the second ''Rotte'' being on the right wingtip of his partner. The ''Rotte'' fighting pair also added to its flexibility, as a ''Schwarm'' could easily break into two ''Rotte'' pairs without losing its fighting ability. The ''Rottenführer'' could attack enemy aircraft, leaving his wingman to watch for the enemy. It was much more flexible than the rigid three-aircraft &quot;Vic&quot; formation the RAF used at the start of the war. In the ''Schwarm'' the aircraft had plenty of space to maneuver, so they were free to scan the horizon for enemy aircraft rather than focusing on maintaining a close formation. This flexibility became apparent to the RAF during the [[Battle of Britain]].&lt;ref name=Bickers96p150/&gt;&lt;ref name=Buell02p77/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gray, (2007) p. 69&lt;/ref&gt;

==Ground combat forces==

===Anti-aircraft units===
Luftwaffe controlled the bulk of German anti-aircraft artillery (commonly called ''Flak'') since the 1930s. The smallest tactical unit of anti-aircraft artillery was a [[artillery battery|battery]] ({{lang-de|Batterie}}).&lt;ref&gt;The ''Batterie'' and ''Abteilung'' unit organization followed the German field artillery practice. Normally, the German Army (''Heer'') anti-aircraft units were called ''Batterie'' as well, except the units of anti-aircraft machine guns which were called ''Kompanie'', in the infantry style.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=w&gt;Westermann, ''Flak German Anti-aircraft Defenses 1914–1945''; pp. 36, 44, 90.&lt;/ref&gt; Battery usually had four to six guns.&lt;ref name=w/&gt; The larger unit was a [[battalion]] (''Flak-Abteilung''), composed of three to five gun batteries and a searchlight battery. Battalions would be &quot;light&quot; (''leichte''), &quot;mixed&quot; (''gemischte''), or &quot;heavy&quot; (''schwere''), referring to the size of guns in their batteries.&lt;ref name = Ruffner.90.40&gt;Ruffner, (1990) pp. 40, 45&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = Mitcham.07.323&gt;Mitcham, (2007-b) p. 323&lt;/ref&gt; Flak guns in use were in two light calibers and three heavy calibers – light 20&amp;nbsp;mm and [[3.7 cm FlaK 43|37 mm]]; and the heavy 88&amp;nbsp;mm, [[10.5 cm FlaK 38|105 mm]], and [[12.8 cm FlaK 40|128 mm]].

The battalions were variously organized into [[regiment]]s (''Flak-Regimenter''), [[brigade]]s (''Flak-Brigaden'' e.g. ''Flak-Brigade XIX''), [[Division (military)|divisions]] (''Flak-Divisionen'', e.g. ''27. Flak-Division'') and [[flak corps]] (''Flakkorps''), although the hierarchy was neither very strict or very stable throughout the history.

Over the course of the war, the continuous attacks by first RAF, then [[United States Army Air Forces|USAAF]] bombers on German cities led to increases in the number of flak units deployed in Germany. Late in the war, AA units were bolstered by the use of foreigners and German youths.&lt;ref name = Ruffner.90.40/&gt;&lt;ref name = Windrow.72.18&gt;Windrow, (1972) p. 18&lt;/ref&gt; There were a total of 29 flak divisions.{{When|date=July 2011}} Each division generally consisted of five flak regiments, one searchlight regiment, three motorized flak transport battalions, one communications battalion, and supply troops. The number of transport battalions varied depending on location and need of transport of the divisions. The first of these was formed in Berlin on 1 July 1938 as the Air Defense Command (''Luftverteidigungskommando'') but later renamed as 1st. Flak Division.&lt;ref name = Mitcham.07.323/&gt;

===Paratroops===
{{Main article|Fallschirmjäger}}
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1979-128-35, Ramcke, Kurt Student, Hans Kroh.jpg|thumb|right|''Fallschirmjäger'' commander [[Kurt Student]] with [[Hermann-Bernhard Ramcke]] and [[Hans Kroh]] in 1941|alt=A photo of paratroop commander Kurt Studentfollowed by Hermann-Bernhard Ramcke and Hans Kroh in 1941]]
One of the unique characteristics of the Luftwaffe (as opposed to independent air forces of other nations), was the possession of an organic [[paratrooper]] force; the ''[[Fallschirmjäger]]''. These were established in 1938. They saw action in their proper role during 1940–1941, most notably in the capture of the Belgian Army [[Fort Eben-Emael|fortress at Eben–Emael]] and the [[Battle of the Netherlands]] in May 1940. They also took part in the [[Battle of Crete|invasion of Crete]] in May 1941. More than 4,000 ''Fallschirmjäger'' were killed during the Crete operation. Consequently, these forces were only used for smaller-scale operations, such as the successful rescue of [[Benito Mussolini]], the then-deposed dictator of Italy, in 1943. Fallschirmjäger formations were used as standard infantry in all theaters of the war.&lt;ref name=Taylor.74.95/&gt;

===Armored Paratroop Division===
{{Main article|Fallschirm-Panzer Division 1 Hermann Göring|Fallschirm-Panzergrenadier Division 2 Hermann Göring}}
As the Prussian Minister of the Interior, Göring formed an elite police force in early 1933. It consisted of 400 men with its headquarters in Berlin. After several name changes within the following six months, it was named the ''Landespolizeigruppe General Göring''. During the next two years, it grew to become the ''Regiment General Göring''. After the formation of the Luftwaffe was announced, Göring transferred this unit to the German air arm. At that time, it consisted of the following units:&lt;ref name=&quot;Williamson and Andrew 2003 pp. 3–5&quot;&gt;Williamson and Andrew, (2003) pp. 3–5&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''Regimentstab'' (Headquarters Staff)
* ''Musikkorps'' (Military Band)
* I and II Jäger-Batallionen
* 13. Kradschützen-Kompanie
* 15. Pionier-Kompanie
* Reiterzug
* Nachrichtenzug&lt;ref name=&quot;Williamson and Andrew 2003 pp. 3–5&quot;/&gt;

In late 1937, volunteers for the Paratroop Corps were combined in the ''I.Jäger–Battalion''. This along with the ''15. Pionier-Kompanie'' formed the ''IV. Fallschirmschützen-Battalion''. They still remained part of the ''Regiment Hermann Göring'' until March 1938. In March they were renamed  ''I./FallschirmJäger-Regiment 1''. In late 1939, the regiment had expanded even further and consisted of the following units:&lt;ref name=&quot;Williamson and Andrew 2003 pp. 3–5&quot;/&gt;
* Regimentstab
* Musikkorps
* Stabsbatterie''
* I. (Schwere) Flak-Abteilung (Heavy Anti-Aircraft Artillery Battalion)
* II. (Leichte) Flak-Abteilung (Light Anti-Aircraft Artillery Battalion)
* III.Scheinwerfer-Abteilung (Searchlight Battalion)
* IV.(Leichte) Flak-Abteilung
* WachBattalion
** Reiterschwadron (Mounted Squadron)
** 9.Wach-Kompanie
** 10.Wach-Kompanie
** 11.Wach-Kompanie
* Reserve Scheinwerfer-Abteilung
* Ersatz-Abteilung
* (Schwere) Eisenbahn Flak-Batterie (Heavy Rail mounted Flak Battery)
* (Leichte) Flak-Batterie (Light Flak Battery)&lt;ref name=&quot;Williamson and Andrew 2003 pp. 3–5&quot;/&gt;
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-2006-0128, Oskar Bauer.jpg|upright|thumb|[[Oskar Bauer]], commander of the II. Division of Flak-Regiment 4 in May, 1942|alt=A photo of Oskar Bauer, commander of the II. Division of Flak Regiment 4]]
On 1 October 1944, the division was expanded to become the ''FallschirmPanzerkorps Hermann Göring''. In order to achieve this, another division called ''[[Fallschirm-Panzergrenadier Division 2 Hermann Göring]]'' was formed. This was staffed by fresh recruits from both the army and the Luftwaffe.&lt;ref name=Taylor.74.95/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Williamson and Andrew, (2003) pp. 13–15&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ruffner, (1990) p. 3&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Williamson and Andrew, (2003) p. 3&lt;/ref&gt;

===Field Division===
{{Main article|Luftwaffe Field Division}}
In early 1942, in the east, the Luftwaffe formed seven ''Feldregimenter der Luftwaffe'' (&quot;Luftwaffe Field Regiments&quot;). These were predominantly formed from volunteer or surplus Luftwaffe personnel. Their goal was to maintain airfield security against [[Soviet partisans|Soviet Partisan activity]]. Each regiment consisted of four battalions. Each battalion consisted of three light companies and one heavy company. They also had a headquarters company and one signals platoon. The heavy company operated twelve 20&amp;nbsp;mm cannon and four 88&amp;nbsp;mm dual-purpose guns. There was also an anti-tank battalion. It had two companies equipped with nine [[5 cm PaK 38]] and one company equipped with captured Russian [[7.62 cm Infanteriegeschütz L/16.5|7.62 cm guns]]. Due to a lack of training in ground combat skills, these regiments were limited to defensive operations. Although intended to act as a single unit, the divisions were separated and served with army or with ''Fallschirmjäger'' units. While in the field, these units were tactically under the command of the army but administratively still under Luftwaffe control. Within the Luftwaffe, they came under the control of ''XIII. Fliegerkorps''.&lt;ref name=Taylor.74.95&gt;Taylor and Mayer, (1974) p. 95&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ruffner, (1990) pp. 3, 6–11, 14&lt;/ref&gt;

Administratively, these units came under the control of four Luftwaffe Field Corps numbered I, II, III and IV. Each was commanded by ''General Der Luftwaffe'' (&quot;General of the Airforce&quot;) Headquarters. The strength of a Luftwaffe Field Division was half that of an army infantry division. It did have a mixed Flak battalion and an artillery battalion. The composition of the artillery battalion varied.&lt;ref&gt;Ruffner, (1990) p. 10&lt;/ref&gt; The mixed flak [[battalion]] ({{lang-de|Abteilung}}) was formed as a part of the Luftwaffe Field Division. It had one heavy [[Artillery battery|battery]] with three [[2 cm FlaK 30|20 mm]] cannons and four [[8.8 cm FlaK 18/36/37/41|88 mm]] guns along with twenty-seven [[2 cm FlaK 30|20 mm anti-aircraft guns]]. It had a headquarters staff as well as signals support troops.&lt;ref name = Ruffner.90.10&gt;Ruffner, (1990) pp. 10–11&lt;/ref&gt;

The Luftwaffe Field Division had a minimal administrative staff along with logistical support personnel in pioneer, medical and supply companies along with maintenance and other staff. Although the division gave the impression of strength, the reality was that it was barely the size of an army [[brigade]]. As of 28 October 1943, the 1. Luftwaffe Field Division reported an effective strength of 6,429 consisting of Officers, [[Non-commissioned officer|NCOs]] and enlisted men. But the fighting strength was only 2,779.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ruffner, 1990 p. 11&quot;&gt;Ruffner, (1990) p. 11&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the army was short of manpower, Göring blocked the transfer of surplus Luftwaffe personnel to be trained for the army and instead increased the number of field divisions. Besides the lack of training and combat experience of the Luftwaffe commanders, the army had to supply equipment to these units. Instead of being used on quieter sections of the various fronts to relieve army units for use elsewhere, they were put into action where the Germans were hard pressed and suffered accordingly.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ruffner, 1990 p. 11&quot;/&gt;

==Identification markings and camouflage schemes==

===Identification markings===
{{refimprove section|date=May 2014}}
[[File:FW 190 F.jpg|thumb|left|The Smithsonian's faithfully-restored Fw 190F, showing both forms of ''Balkenkreuz'' in &quot;low-visibility&quot; flanks-only form]]
[[Military aircraft insignia|Aircraft markings]] were used to distinguish friend from foe. There were several changes in identification markings from 1935 until the end of the war in 1945. From 1933 to 1935, civilian aircraft were painted with a bright red horizontal band with a black ''[[Hakenkreuz]]'' (swastika) in a white circle superimposed, shown only on the vertical stabilizer. From 1936, the ''[[Balkenkreuz]]'' (national cross with four equal arms), basically inherited from the early spring 1918 period of ''Luftstreitkräfte'' service when it first appeared in World War I, was applied in black and white, with somewhat different proportions (one-quarter as wide as its length from end-to-end) than the WW I-period insignia, and without the white border outlining the &quot;ends&quot; of the cross, the white borders forming four right-angled &quot;flanks&quot; around the central black core cross. It was painted on the fuselage about halfway between the wing and the tail and on the upper and lower sides of each wing. The flanks came in two regulation dimension formats, with much narrower flanks before July 1939 used in all six positions on an airframe — a wider-flanked variation, for use underneath wings and on the fuselage sides, came into use from July 1939 onwards. This helped in immediate identification.

[[File:Bf109C LegionCondor2.jpg|thumb|A Bf 109C of the [[Condor Legion]] with St Andrew's Crosses on the wings and tail|alt=An image of Bf109C aircraft in service of the Condor Legion. It displays the St. Andrew's cross painted on wings and tail.]]
During the Spanish Civil War, where the Luftwaffe participated through the [[Condor Legion]], aircraft were repainted with a white [[Cross of Burgundy flag|Andrea's Cross]] in a black circle. The tail was all white with Andrea's Cross on the rudder. In Germany itself, the ''Balkenkreuz'' was once again used as the national insignia on the fuselage and wings in six locations, initially with a very narrow set of four white &quot;flanks&quot;, which were widened around 1938–39, with the usual ''Hakenkreuz'' on the vertical tail surfaces, usually on the fixed fin, but sometimes instead on the rudder (as done on some [[Arado Flugzeugwerke|Arado]]-designed aircraft) and on airframe designs that either had a small fin or one braced with struts. Medical aircraft were painted with a red cross on a white circular background. Later on in the war when camouflage was more necessary, the ''Balkenkreuz'' had only a white or black outline in a &quot;low-visibility&quot; format, consisting only of the four right-angle &quot;flanks&quot; that had previously bordered the now-absent central black core cross of the ''Balkenkreuz'',&lt;ref name=denislepage09p4850&gt;Lepage, (2009) pp. 48–50&lt;/ref&gt; with the ''Hakenkreuz'' also frequently being done with a white or black border only, omitting the central black shape.
[[File:Regulation WW II Underwing Balkenkreuz.png|thumb|left|150px|The July 1939-onwards &quot;wide&quot; version of the ''Balkenkreuz'', used under wings and on fuselage sides during WW II]]

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-674-7766-31A, Flugzeug Heinkel He 177.jpg|thumb|right|A Heinkel He 177 bomber with the upper-wing style standardized ''Balkenkreuz'' on the fuselage, and with flat black undersurfaces and fuselage sides.]]  Production examples of the [[Heinkel He 177]], however, curiously most often came from the [[Heinkel]] and subcontracting [[Arado Flugzeugwerke|Arado]] factories with a set of ''Balkenkreuz'' insignia, most often the upper-wing narrow flank variant used as standard for all Luftwaffe aircraft, in all six positions throughout its deployment in the war, as was regulation before July 1939 for the entire Luftwaffe — these were often displayed without the outermost black &quot;flanks&quot;, seemingly making the existing white &quot;flanks&quot; appear to be even thinner than regulation, which through photogrammetric examination of some examples, make the stroke width of the white &quot;flanks&quot; on some He 177 airframes as narrow as 1/80th the length of the core cross from end to end,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Griehl |first1=Manfred |last2=Dressel |first2=Joachim |title=Heinkel He 177 – 277 – 274 |url= |accessdate= |year=1998 |publisher=Airlife Publishing |location=Shrewsbury, UK |isbn=1-85310-364-0 |page=107 |quote=As measured in CAD software, in photogrammetric mode, of a photo of the He 177 V31 airframe}}&lt;/ref&gt; only one-quarter as wide as the 1/20th regulation width called for on the upper wing ''Balkenkreuz'' regulation dimensions.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.luftarchiv.de/index.htm?/flugzeugbau/kenungen.htm |title=Luftarchiv.de - Kennzeichen - Allgemein, Abb.4 |author=Bert Hartmann |date= |work= |publisher=Luftarchiv.de |accessdate=November 21, 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Sometimes the wide-flanked underwing ''Balkenkreuz'' would be substituted for the narrow-flank version on some He 177A aircraft, and was already in use on many He 177As in that position.

Until 1935, civilian aircraft only had a registration painted on. This was usually the letter D (for ''Deutschland'') [[Aircraft registration#Pre-1928 allocations|national identification letter in use from before 1928]], followed by three or four numbers. After 1935, military planes carried, on the fuselage, an alphanumeric four-character ''Geschwaderkennung'' code with the ''Balkenkreuz'' after the first two characters, always consisting of one letter and one number in a unique combination for a specific ''Geschwader'' or ''Gruppe''. The third letter always designated the individual aircraft ID within a ''Staffel'', while the fourth letter designated the ''Staffel'' itself within the larger ''Geschwader'' or ''Gruppe'' unit it belonged to.&lt;ref name=denislepage09p4850/&gt;

===Camouflage schemes===
[[File:ME-110G-2 at RAF Hendon.jpg|thumb|right|A museum-preserved Bf 110G night fighter with its accurate light base-color nocturnal camouflage, also bearing &quot;wave-mirror&quot; irregular gray lines]]
In the Luftwaffe, there were centralized regulations on field camouflage patterns. In practice, these were either amended or ignored. Units in various areas used their own way of painting the aircraft excepting the ''Geschwaderkennung'' alphanumeric  unit identifiers. Units in the very northern parts of Europe used pale blue wavy lines on a gray background. Night units of both fighters and bombers tended to color their aircraft completely black with a light brown or light gray pattern. This changed in early 1942: night fighters were painted a light gray on the upper surfaces and fuselage/nacelle sides, with light blue undersides, then over-sprayed with either irregular dark gray spots or irregular dark gray lines over all their upper surfaces. The irregular lines were meant to match the intricate patterns of ocean waves (usually called &quot;wave-mirror&quot; camouflage) as seen from the air, especially for interceptions of RAF night bombers over the North Sea.  The nighttime skies over Germany usually had some light from either [[moonlight]] or even from [[Skyglow|city lights reflecting upwards into the skies]], making a light base color effective for night fighters against sometimes cloudy or foggy skies below the night fighters' usual combat altitudes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Price |first=Alfred |date=1967 |title=Aircraft in Profile No.148 — The Junkers Ju 88 Night Fighters |url=http://www.scribd.com/doc/103258739/aircraft-profile-no-148-the-junkers-ju-88-night-fighters |location=Leatherhead, Surrey, UK |publisher=Profile Publications Ltd. |pages=16 |isbn= |accessdate=March 29, 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Reconnaissance and maritime aircraft operating over the North Sea tended to paint the underside light blue and the top side in a dark gray or dark green to resemble the sea. By 1943, as economic conditions tightened, front line units used captured allied paint where available. Central control over camouflage relaxed even further.
[[File:He 219 Rumpf 3.jpg|thumb|left|Heinkel He 219 fuselage in museum with later flat black undersurfaces]]
Later-deployed examples of both night fighters defending the Reich, and Heinkel He 177 heavy bombers used for night raids over England such as with [[Operation Steinbock]], often returned to using flat black undersurfaces replacing the light blue previously used during the mid-war years, while retaining the skyglow-based light gray base color/darker gray &quot;wave-mirror&quot; irregular lines or irregular splotches on the upper surfaces. With units disbanding and reforming frequently, intricate patterns became less common. Dark green became more or less the standard. With deteriorating conditions and scarce supplies, various motley color schemes were used. This changed only for those day fighter and &quot;destroyer&quot; units that flew as part of the [[Defense of the Reich]]  (''Reichsverteidigung'') campaign. Later in 1944 these units adopted the pattern of a distinct color band, or two-colored bands, around the aft fuselage, with each ''Geschwader'' usually having their own unique combination.&lt;ref name=denislepage09p4850/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Weal, (2003) p. 8&lt;/ref&gt;

====Day fighter units====
Single engine fighter units used [[Chevron (insignia)|chevrons]] to represent the pilot's rank or seniority. Bars, points or crosses to represent the ''Gruppe'' to which it belonged, and a number representing the ''Jagdgeschwader'' were also utilized. The ''Geschwaderkommodore'' of a fighter wing was represented by two chevrons and a vertical bar. The ''Gruppenkommandeur'' was represented by two chevrons; while a ''Gruppe'' Technical Officer would have a single chevron and a circle. The ''Geschwader'' abbreviation such as JG 11, ZG 110 was also applied. For a staff pilot, there would be a thick black line all around the aircraft. Some day fighter units also used geometric patterns of alternating black and white horizontal stripes on the engine cowling, or [[checkerboard]] patterns, also on the cowling. During the Defense of the Reich campaign, there was a general adoption of a system of colored rear fuselage bands, with unique combinations assigned to each ''Jagdgeschwader'' engaged in the campaign. Use of these colored fuselage bands was generally abandoned by mid-1944. At one point, a color scheme that painted the rudder in white, similar to what had been done during the [[North African Campaign]], was trialled for units dedicated to Defense of the Reich duties,&lt;ref name=denislepage09p4850/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Weal, (1996) p. 52&lt;/ref&gt; which also included the aforementioned ''Reichsverteidigung'' wing-code rear fuselage stripes for each individual ''Jagdgeschwader''.

The unofficial way to represent one's unit was the unit badge. These were solely at the discretion of the commanding officer, so badges of all shapes, sizes and subjects appeared. On the Eastern Front, they were officially banned in later years as they provided intelligence to the enemy.&lt;ref&gt;Weal, (2003) p. 48&lt;/ref&gt;

====Remaining units====
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-433-0881-13A, Flugzeug Junkers Ju 88.jpg|thumb|right|A photo of a Ju 88A displaying the ''Geschwaderkennung'' of [[Stab (Luftwaffe designation)|''Geschwaderstab'']]/[[LG 1]]]]
''Geschwaders'', other than day fighters, during the war usually bore a four-character identification code, starting with a two-character alphanumeric ''{{Interlanguage link multi|Geschwaderkennung|de}}'' (a code unique to each ''Geschwader'') to the left of the national ''Balkenkreuz'' marking and two letters to the right, signifying the individual aircraft's letter within its ''Staffel'' as the third letter and the ''Staffel''-designating letter within the ''Geschwader'' as the fourth and last letter. The full four-character code was usually shown on the fuselage sides, sometimes with the individual aircraft letter repeated under the wings. ''Gruppe'' and ''Staffel''-sized units could also have their own unique codes of this type, most often used for reconnaissance and maritime aviation groups and ''Wekusta'' weather observation squadrons, with ''Staffel'' sized units using the four-character alphanumeric code almost always using an &quot;H&quot; as the fourth and last character. Late in the war, the first two characters of the ''Geschwaderkennung'' code (designating the ''geschwader'') were depicted on the fuselage sides in a much reduced size, possibly as a &quot;low-visibility&quot; security measure. The code tended (though not always), to be omitted altogether by 1945.&lt;ref name=denislepage09p4850/&gt;

==See also==
* [[List of RLM paint designations]]
* [[RLM aircraft designation system]]
* [[RLM numbering system for gliders and sailplanes]]
* [[Stab (Luftwaffe designation)]]

==Notes==

===Footnotes===
* {{note label|Note1|a|a}}By [[D-Day]] in June 1944, ''Luftflotte 3'', had units under it, scattered all over [[France]]. [[10th Air Corps (Germany)|X. ''Fliegerkorps]]'' was transferred from [[Greece]] to [[Angers]], France in March 1944. It acquired the assets of ''[[Fliegerführer Atlantik]]''.&lt;ref name=Bower98p119/&gt;

===Citations===
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
{{Refbegin|2}}
* {{Cite book| last=Bickers | first=Richard Townshend | year=1996 | title=Von Richthofen: The Legend Evaluated |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=P7oUgaPNOngC |publisher=[[Naval Institute Press]] | isbn=1-55750-571-3 |ref=Bickers96 |page=892}}
* {{Cite book| last=Boog | first=Horst |author2=Gerhard Krebs |author3=Vogel Detlef | year=2006 | title=Germany and the Second World War: Volume VII: The Strategic Air War in Europe and the War in the West and East Asia, 1943–1944/5 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=rVVeO4B985wC |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] | isbn=1-55750-571-3 |ref=Bickers96 |page=172}}
* {{Cite book| last=Bower | first=Charles F. | year=1998 | title=World War II in Europe: The Final Year | publisher=[[Palgrave Macmillan]] | isbn=0-312-21133-3 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=yfnEdIFlh2AC |ref=Charlesbower98 | page=321}}
* {{Cite book| last=Boyne | first=Walter J. | year=2003 | title=The Influence of Air Power Upon History | publisher=[[Pelican Publishing Company]] | isbn=1-58980-034-6 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=X-YiU-PJ0ogC |ref=Walterboyne03 | page=447}}
* {{Cite book| last=Buell | first=Thomas |author2=Thomas E. Griess |author3=John H. Bradley |author4=Jack W. Dice| year=2002 | title=The Second World War: Europe and the Mediterranean | publisher=[[Square One Publishers]] | isbn=0-7570-0160-2 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=HP3-9NNz71sC |ref=Thomasbuell02 | page=448}}
* {{Cite book| last=Caldwell | first=Donald |author2=Richard Muller| year=2007 | title=The Luftwaffe Over Germany: Defense of the Reich | publisher=MBI Publishing Company | isbn=1-85367-712-4 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZDLNaRbHD7gC |ref=Donaldcaldwell07 | page=304}}
* {{Cite book| last=Frieser | first=Karl-Heinz |author2=John T. Greenwood| year=2005 | title=The Blitzkrieg Legend: The 1940 campaign in the West |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=7Y0MxdP-ws4C |publisher=[[Naval Institute Press]] | isbn=1-59114-294-6 |ref=Navalpress05 |page=507}}
* {{Cite book| last=Gray | first=Stephen Roberts | year=2007 | title=Rampant Raider: an A-4 Skyhawk pilot in Vietnam |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=8Ysr-aBOMIIC |publisher=[[Naval Institute Press]] | isbn=1-59114-342-X |ref=Gray07 |page=284}}
* {{Cite book| last=Lepage | first=Jean Denis G. G.| year=2009 | title=Aircraft of the Luftwaffe 1935–1945: An Illustrated History |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=hdQBTcscxyQC |publisher=[[McFarland &amp; Company]] | isbn=0-7864-3937-8 |ref=Lepage09 |page=402}}
* {{Cite book| last=Mitcham | first=Samuel W. | year=2007 | title=Eagles of the Third Reich: Men of the Luftwaffe in World War II |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=_HkHU5RJJekC |publisher=[[Stackpole Books]] | isbn=0-8117-3405-6 |ref=Mitcham07 |page=346}}
* {{Cite book| last=Mitcham | first=Samuel W. | year=2007 | title=German Order of Battle: 291st–999th Infantry divisions, named infantry divisions, and special divisions in World War II |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Zz_hX4wmEKAC |publisher=[[Stackpole Books]] | isbn=978-0-8117-3437-0 |ref=Mitcham07-2 |page=375}}
* {{Cite book| last=Nielsen| first=Andreas | year=1968 | title=The German Air Force General Staff Issue 173 of USAF historical studies, German Air Force in World War 2 Series |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=HW0FfrEwc_8C |publisher=[[Ayer Publishing]] | isbn=0-405-00043-X |ref=Mitcham07 |page=265}}
* {{Cite book|last=Ruffner|first=Kevin Conley|year=1990|title=Luftwaffe Field Divisions 1941–45|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=sS7Ofv-4regC|publisher=[[Osprey Publishing]]|isbn=1-85532-100-9|ref=Ruffner90 |page=48}}
* {{Cite book| last=Stedman | first=Robert |author2=Mike Chappell| year=2002 | title=Luftwaffe Air &amp; Ground Crew 1939–45 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=agsYY4SqtcUC |publisher=[[Osprey Publishing]] | isbn=1-84176-404-3 |ref=Robertstedman02 |page=48}}
* {{Cite book| last=Taylor | first=Alan John Percivale |author2=Sydney L. Mayer| year=1974 | title=History of World War II |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=73lwQgAACAAJ&amp;dq=ISBN0706403991&amp;cd=1 |publisher=[[Octopus Books]] | isbn=0-7064-0399-1 |ref=Taylor74 |page=286}}
* {{Cite book| last=United States War Department | year=1995 | title=Handbook on German Military Forces | publisher=[[LSU Press]] | isbn=0-8071-2011-1 |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=b3W1tiuHzcoC |ref=Uswd95 |page=635}}
* {{Cite book| last=Weal | first=John | year=1996 | title=Focke-Wulf FW 190 Aces of the Western Front | publisher=[[Osprey Publishing]] | isbn=1-85532-595-0 |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=iblZ2Nvdj1EC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false |ref=Johnweal96 |page=96}}
* {{Cite book| last=Weal | first=John | year=2003 | title=Jagdgeschwader 27 ''Afrika'' | publisher=[[Osprey Publishing]] |isbn=1-84176-538-4 |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=MwOcPfei6-MC|ref=Johnweal03 |page=128}}
* {{Cite book| last=Weal | first=John | year=2006 | title=Bf 109 Defence of the Reich Aces | publisher=[[Osprey Publishing]] | isbn=1-84176-879-0 |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=AnOx0_wamhgC|ref=Johnweal06 |page=96}}
* {{Cite book| last=Williamson | first=Gordon|authorlink=Gordon Williamson (writer) |author2=Stephen Andrew| year=2003 |series=Men-At-Arms | title=The Hermann Göring Division, |volume=385 | publisher=[[Osprey Publishing]] | isbn=1-84176-406-X |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=mMc9tLaOGzsC|ref=Williamson03 |page=48}}
* {{Cite book|last=Windrow| first=Martin | year=1972 | title=Luftwaffe Airborne and Field Units|publisher=[[Osprey Publishing]] | isbn=978-0-85045-114-6 |url = https://books.google.com/books?id=_ROQlcEseqAC|ref=Martinwindrow72 |page=40}}
{{Refend}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2010}}

{{Good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Organization Of The Luftwaffe (1933-1945)}}
[[Category:Luftwaffe]]
[[Category:Organizational structures of contemporary air forces]]</text>
      <sha1>7etj8er6pw9go9cho7r8je2u0cst4tf</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
