<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>RAAF area commands</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>47262498</id>
    <revision>
      <id>730149022</id>
      <parentid>729469757</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-07-17T01:59:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lightlowemon</username>
        <id>10246337</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Post-war organisation and supersession */clean up using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="28639">{{good article}}
[[File:RAAFAreaCommands1944.png|thumb|upright=1.8|right|alt=Map of Australia showing state borders, with RAAF area command boundaries superimposed|RAAF area command boundaries in 1944]]
'''Area commands''' were the major operational and administrative formations of the [[Royal Australian Air Force]] (RAAF) between 1940 and 1954. Established in response to the outbreak of World War&amp;nbsp;II, they underpinned the Air Force's geographically based command-and-control system for the duration of the conflict and into the early years of the [[Cold War]], until being superseded by a functional control system made up of [[RAAF Home Command|Home]], [[RAAF Training Command|Training]], and [[RAAF Maintenance Command|Maintenance Commands]].

The area commands and their responsibilities evolved over time according to changing circumstances. The RAAF established four commands to begin with in 1940–41: [[Southern Area Command (RAAF)|Southern Area]], [[Central Area Command (RAAF)|Central Area]], [[Western Area Command (RAAF)|Western Area]], and [[Northern Area Command (RAAF)|Northern Area]]. They oversaw almost all operations, training and maintenance within their boundaries. A concession to functional control occurred in mid-1941, when the Air Force formed two [[Group (military aviation unit)|groups]] that assumed the training role of the southern and eastern states; Central Area itself was disbanded and most of its units taken over by Northern and Southern Areas, and the newly formed No.&amp;nbsp;2 (Training) Group. The area structure was further revised in 1942, following the outbreak of the [[Pacific War]]. Northern Area was split into [[North-Eastern Area Command (RAAF)|North-Eastern Area]] and [[North-Western Area Command (RAAF)|North-Western Area]], and a new command, [[Eastern Area Command (RAAF)|Eastern Area]], was created, making a total of five commands. The same year, the RAAF formed two functional groups that assumed the maintenance role of the area commands;  the latter focussed on operations until the end of hostilities. A new area command covering RAAF units in New Guinea, [[Northern Command (RAAF)|Northern Command]], was formed in 1944 and dissolved soon after the war.

By the early 1950s, most operational units were based within Eastern Area Command, most  Air Force training was controlled by Southern Area Command, and maintenance was the responsibility of Maintenance Group. The area command structure was no longer considered appropriate for delivering the concentration of force necessary for combat, and the Federal government decided to replace it with a functional command-and-control system. In 1953, Eastern Area Command was re-formed as Home Command (controlling operations), Southern Area Command was re-formed as Training Command, and Maintenance Group was re-designated Maintenance Command. The three remaining area commands ceded their authority to the functional commands in 1954, and were disbanded by the end of 1956.

==History==

===Origin and purpose===
[[File:Caf goble.jpg|thumb|right|upright|Air Vice Marshal Goble, who proposed a functional command system for the RAAF in 1940|alt=Portrait of man in dark military uniform with pilot's wings on chest, wearing peaked cap with two rows of braid]]
On the eve of World War&amp;nbsp;II, the RAAF comprised twelve flying [[Squadron (aviation)|squadrons]], two aircraft depots and a flying school, situated at five air bases.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephens pp. 111–112&quot;&gt;Stephens, ''The Royal Australian Air Force'', pp. 111–112&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Gillison pp. 66–67&quot;&gt;Gillison, [https://static.awm.gov.au/images/collection/pdf/RCDIG1070476--1-.pdf ''Royal Australian Air Force'', pp. 66–67]&lt;/ref&gt; An air force of this size did not require large-scale operational formations such as [[Wing (military aviation unit)|wings]], [[Group (military aviation unit)|groups]], or commands, as all units could be directly administered and controlled by RAAF Headquarters in [[Melbourne]]. With the [[Military history of Australia during World War II|onset of war]] in September 1939, the Australian Air Board decided to implement a decentralised form of command, commensurate with an envisioned increase in manpower and units.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephens pp. 111–112&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Pathfinder121&quot;&gt;{{cite magazine |title = Organising for War: The RAAF Air Campaigns in the Pacific | magazine = Pathfinder|issue=  121| date = October 2009| url = http://airpower.airforce.gov.au/Publications/Details/403/121-Organising-for-War-The-RAAF-Air-Campaigns-in-the-Pacific.aspx|publisher=Air Power Development Centre|accessdate=10 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The RAAF's initial move in this direction was to create Nos.&amp;nbsp;1 and 2 Groups in November 1939, the former based in Melbourne to control units in [[Victoria (Australia)|Victoria]], and the latter in [[Sydney]] to control units in [[New South Wales]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Gillison pp. 66–67&quot;/&gt;

In January 1940, the [[Chief of Air Force (Australia)|Chief of the Air Staff]], Air Vice Marshal [[Stanley Goble|Jimmy Goble]], proposed organising the RAAF along functional lines with Home Defence, Training, and Maintenance Commands, but the Federal government did not take up this plan.&lt;ref&gt;Gillison, [https://static.awm.gov.au/images/collection/pdf/RCDIG1070724--1-.pdf ''Royal Australian Air Force'', pp. 90–91]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ashworth, ''How Not to Run an Air Force'', p. 24&lt;/ref&gt; Goble was replaced in February by a [[Royal Air Force]] (RAF) officer, Air Chief Marshal [[Charles Burnett (RAF officer)|Sir Charles Burnett]], who focussed on rapid expansion of the RAAF to meet the needs of the [[British Commonwealth Air Training Plan|Empire Air Training Scheme]] and believed that Australia's huge land mass would make a functional command system unwieldy. He proceeded to reorganise the Air Force into a geographically based &quot;area&quot; system.&lt;ref&gt;Ashworth, ''How Not to Run an Air Force'', p. 26&lt;/ref&gt; The roles of each area command were the same: [[Anti-aircraft warfare|air defence]]; protection of adjacent [[sea lane]]s; and [[aerial reconnaissance]]. Each area was led by an [[Air Officer Commanding]] (AOC) who was responsible for the administration and operations of all bases and units within his boundary.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pathfinder121&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Gillison pp. 91–92&quot;&gt;Gillison, [https://static.awm.gov.au/images/collection/pdf/RCDIG1070724--1-.pdf ''Royal Australian Air Force'', pp. 91–92]&lt;/ref&gt; Exceptions to this policy included aircraft depots and the [[Central Flying School RAAF|Central Flying School]] that trained flying instructors, as their range of responsibilities crossed area boundaries and therefore came under the direct control of RAAF Headquarters.&lt;ref&gt;Ashworth, ''How Not to Run an Air Force'', pp. xx, 30&lt;/ref&gt; The static area system was primarily defensive in nature, but considered well suited to training new pilots, who could be instructed at flying schools and mentored through their initial squadron postings, all within the same geographical region.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gillison pp. 91–92&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ashworth, ''How Not to Run an Air Force'', p. 1&lt;/ref&gt;

===Evolution and control===
{{multiple image
| align     = right
| direction = vertical
| header    = 
| width     = 280

| image1    = RAAFAreaCommands1940.png
| alt1      = Map of Australia showing state borders, with RAAF area command boundaries superimposed
| caption1  = The four area commands as planned in February 1940

| image2    = RAAFAreaCommands1941.png
| alt2      = Map of Australia showing state borders, with RAAF area command boundaries superimposed
| caption2  = The three area commands as at December 1941

| image3    = Jones-Bostock-Burnett AWM 012249.jpg
| alt3      = Informal half portrait of three men in dark military uniforms
| caption3  = Air Chief Marshal Burnett (right), who instituted the RAAF's area command system in 1940–41, with Air Vice Marshals Jones (left) and Bostock (centre), pictured in May 1942, when Jones took over as Chief of the Air Staff
|alt=Informal half portrait of three men in dark military uniforms
}}
The RAAF planned four area commands initially: [[Southern Area Command (RAAF)|Southern Area]], covering all units in Victoria, [[Tasmania]], [[South Australia]] and the southern [[Riverina]] district of New South Wales; [[Central Area Command (RAAF)|Central Area]], covering units in New South Wales except southern Riverina and the north of the state; [[Western Area Command (RAAF)|Western Area]], covering units in [[Western Australia]]; and [[Northern Area Command (RAAF)|Northern Area]], covering units in northern New South Wales, [[Queensland]], [[Northern Territory]] and [[Territory of Papua|Papua]]. The first two commands established, in March 1940, were Southern Area, which essentially took over the role and headquarters of No.&amp;nbsp;1 Group in Melbourne, and Central Area, which evolved from No.&amp;nbsp;2 Group in Sydney. Western and Northern Areas eventually followed in January and May 1941, respectively; pending their formation, units in Queensland were temporarily controlled by Central Area Command, and those in Western Australia, Northern Territory and Papua came under the direct control of RAAF Headquarters.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gillison pp. 91–92&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ashworth pp. 27–29&quot;&gt;Ashworth, ''How Not to Run an Air Force'', pp. 27–29&lt;/ref&gt;

By mid-1941, RAAF Headquarters had determined to form training units in the southern and eastern states into semi-geographical, semi-functional groups separate to the area commands. This led to the establishment in August of [[No. 1 Training Group RAAF|No.&amp;nbsp;1 (Training) Group]] in Melbourne, covering Victoria, Tasmania and South Australia, and [[No. 2 Training Group RAAF|No.&amp;nbsp;2 (Training) Group]] in Sydney, covering New South Wales and Queensland.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gillison p. 112&quot;&gt;Gillison, [https://static.awm.gov.au/images/collection/pdf/RCDIG1070724--1-.pdf ''Royal Australian Air Force'', p. 112]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ashworth pp. xx, 38&quot;&gt;Ashworth, ''How Not to Run an Air Force'', pp. xx, 38&lt;/ref&gt; Central Area was then disbanded and its responsibilities &quot;divided as convenient&quot;, according to the [[Australia in the War of 1939–1945|official history of the war]], between Southern Area, Northern Area, and No.&amp;nbsp;2 (Training) Group.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gillison p. 112&quot;/&gt; Western Area retained responsibility for training, as well as operations and maintenance, within its boundaries.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ashworth pp. xx, 38&quot;/&gt;

With the outbreak of the [[Pacific War]] in December 1941, Northern Area was split the following month into [[North-Western Area Command (RAAF)|North-Western]] and [[North-Eastern Area Command (RAAF)|North-Eastern Areas]], to counter distinct Japanese threats to Northern Australia and New Guinea, respectively.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephens pp. 111–112&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gillison, [https://static.awm.gov.au/images/collection/pdf/RCDIG1070486--1-.pdf ''Royal Australian Air Force'', p. 311]&lt;/ref&gt; Southern Area was also considered appropriate for subdivision owing to its size, so [[Eastern Area Command (RAAF)|Eastern Area]] was established in May 1942 to take over control of operational units in New South Wales and southern Queensland. These arrangements stabilised the number of area commands at five.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ashworth pp. xxi, 134–135&quot;&gt;Ashworth, ''How Not to Run an Air Force'', pp. xxi, 134–135&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gillison, [https://static.awm.gov.au/images/collection/pdf/RCDIG1070516--1-.pdf ''Royal Australian Air Force'', p. 478]&lt;/ref&gt; Of necessity, the two northerly commands were primarily responsible for bombing and air defence, while the other commands focussed on maritime patrol and anti-submarine warfare.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephens pp. 144–145&quot;&gt;Stephens, ''The Royal Australian Air Force'', pp. 144–145&lt;/ref&gt; Further convergence of command-and-control responsibilities along semi-geographical, semi-functional lines took place between June and September 1942, when authority over maintenance units was transferred from the area commands to the newly formed [[No. 4 Group RAAF|No.&amp;nbsp;4 (Maintenance) Group]] in Melbourne and [[No. 5 Group RAAF|No.&amp;nbsp;5 (Maintenance) Group]] in Sydney.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ashworth pp. xxi, 134–135&quot;/&gt; Some finetuning of the area boundaries occurred in August: as well as the Northern Territory, North-Western Area was given responsibility for the portion of Western Australia north of a line drawn south-east from [[Yampi Sound]] to the Northern Territory border, and part of Queensland adjacent to the [[Barkly Tableland]].&lt;ref&gt;Gillison, [https://static.awm.gov.au/images/collection/pdf/RCDIG1070519--1-.pdf ''Royal Australian Air Force'', p. 588]&lt;/ref&gt;

Until 1942, RAAF Headquarters exercised complete operational and administrative control over the area commands. In April that year, Allied Air Forces (AAF) Headquarters was established under General [[Douglas Macarthur]]'s [[South West Pacific Area (command)|South West Pacific Area]] (SWPA), with operational authority over all RAAF combat infrastructure, including the area commands.&lt;ref&gt;Gillison, [https://static.awm.gov.au/images/collection/pdf/RCDIG1070516--1-.pdf ''Royal Australian Air Force'', p. 473]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Air War Against Japan ch.01 pp. 15-16&quot;&gt;Odgers, [https://static.awm.gov.au/images/collection/pdf/RCDIG1070530--1-.pdf ''Air War Against Japan'', pp. 15–16]&lt;/ref&gt; In September the new AAF commander, Major General [[George Kenney]], formed the majority of his US flying units into [[Fifth Air Force]], and most of their Australian counterparts into [[RAAF Command]], led by Air Vice Marshal [[William Bostock|Bill Bostock]].&lt;ref&gt;Gillison, [https://static.awm.gov.au/images/collection/pdf/RCDIG1070519--1-.pdf ''Royal Australian Air Force'', pp. 585–588]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Air War Against Japan ch.01 pp. 4-6&quot;&gt;Odgers, [https://static.awm.gov.au/images/collection/pdf/RCDIG1070530--1-.pdf ''Air War Against Japan'', pp. 4–6]&lt;/ref&gt; Bostock exercised control of Australian air operations through the area commands, although RAAF Headquarters continued to hold overarching administrative authority, meaning that Bostock and his area commanders were ultimately dependent on the Chief of the Air Staff, Air Vice Marshal [[George Jones (RAAF officer)|George Jones]] in Melbourne, for supplies and equipment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephens pp. 144–145&quot;/&gt;

To help overcome the static nature of the area command system, in September 1942 the RAAF created a large mobile formation known as [[No. 9 Operational Group RAAF|No.&amp;nbsp;9 (Operational) Group]], a self-contained tactical air force that could keep pace with Allied advances north through New Guinea and towards Japan. By April 1944, No.&amp;nbsp;9 Group had become a garrison force in New Guinea and lost its mobile function to No.&amp;nbsp;10 (Operational) Group (later the [[Australian First Tactical Air Force]]). No.&amp;nbsp;9 Group was therefore re-formed as a dedicated area command covering air units in New Guinea; Bostock had recommended calling it Northern Area, before RAAF Headquarters settled on [[Northern Command (RAAF)|Northern Command]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephens144&quot;&gt;Stephens, ''The Royal Australian Air Force'', pp. 144, 168&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Odgers182&quot;&gt;Odgers, [https://static.awm.gov.au/images/collection/pdf/RCDIG1070561--1-.pdf ''Air War Against Japan'', pp. 182–183, 198–200]&lt;/ref&gt; In August that year, RAAF Headquarters proposed to disband the training and maintenance groups formed in 1941–42 and return their functions to the control of the area commands, but no action was taken.&lt;ref&gt;Ashworth, ''How Not to Run an Air Force'', pp. 227–229&lt;/ref&gt; The same month, the Air Board recommended carving a new Central Area Command out of Eastern Area, which it considered too large to be controlled by one headquarters. This proposed Central Area would have been responsible for units in southern Queensland but the [[War Cabinet]] deferred its decision, as it had when a similar concept was raised in October 1943.&lt;ref&gt;Ashworth, ''How Not to Run an Air Force'', pp. pp. 214–217, 227–228&lt;/ref&gt;

Near the end of the war, [[No. 11 Group RAAF|No.&amp;nbsp;11 Group]] was formed as a &quot;static command&quot; headquartered on [[Morotai]] in the [[Dutch East Indies]], using elements of Northern Command and the First Tactical Air Force; this freed the latter from garrison duties following the [[Borneo campaign (1945)|liberation of Borneo]].&lt;ref&gt;Ashworth, ''How Not to Run an Air Force'', p. xxiii&lt;/ref&gt; In recommending the Morotai garrison's establishment, Bostock explained that while it shared the static characteristic of an area command, it differed in that the area commands were part of the permanent structure of the Air Force and situated within the borders of Australia's mainland and overseas territories, whereas the new formation was a temporary wartime measure, headquartered on foreign territory.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://recordsearch.naa.gov.au/SearchNRetrieve/Interface/ViewImage.aspx?B=670344&amp;S=1|title=RAAF organisation|date=1943–45|publisher=[[National Archives of Australia]]|pages=18–23|accessdate=20 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Post-war organisation and supersession===
[[File:RAAFAreaCommands1947.png|thumb|upright=1.28|right|The area commands in 1947; these boundaries remained in place until superseded in 1953–54|alt=Map of Australia showing state borders, with RAAF area command boundaries superimposed]]
Following the end of the Pacific War in August 1945, SWPA was dissolved and RAAF Headquarters in Melbourne again assumed full control of all its operational formations, including the area commands.&lt;ref&gt;Ashworth, ''How Not to Run an Air Force'', p. 262&lt;/ref&gt; Nos.&amp;nbsp;1 and 2&amp;nbsp;(Training) Groups, and No.&amp;nbsp;5 (Maintenance) Group in Sydney, were disbanded between January and March 1946.&lt;ref name=DVA&gt;{{cite web|url=http://clik.dva.gov.au/history-library/part-3-order-battle/ch-2-order-battle-air-force/s-2-headquarters|title=Order of Battle&amp;nbsp;– Air Force&amp;nbsp;– Headquarters|publisher=[[Department of Veterans' Affairs (Australia)|Department of Veterans' Affairs]]|accessdate=12 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Northern Command, having been re-designated Northern Area in December 1945, was disbanded in February 1947. The other area commands continued to function with essentially the same boundaries as during the war, except that North-Western Area no longer covered the Dutch East Indies.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephens pp. 111–112&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=DVA/&gt;

By the 1950s, a geographically based area command system was considered outmoded, and calls came to replace it with a system based on function.&lt;ref name=&quot;Helson pp. 252–254&quot;&gt;Helson, ''Ten Years at the Top'', pp. 252–254&lt;/ref&gt; With hindsight, the area commands were judged adequate for the organisation of the Air Force in the early years of World War&amp;nbsp;II, but not for the rapid response times and concentration of force necessary to properly prepare for attacks on Australia following the start of the Pacific War, nor for conducting offensive operations from 1943 onwards.&lt;ref&gt;Ashworth, ''How Not to Run an Air Force'', p. 277&lt;/ref&gt;  Air Marshal Jones, who had retained his position as Chief of the Air Staff (CAS) following the war, resisted pressure to replace the area structure. He was persuaded by his staff to set up a conference to discuss the possibility of change, but participation by the CAS, who had been satisfied with the wartime structure, and the area commanders themselves, whose positions were on the line, was half-hearted at best.&lt;ref name=&quot;Helson pp. 252–254&quot;/&gt; Jones did suggest reducing the number of area commands to three (Northern Area to cover Queensland and the Northern Territory, Eastern Area to cover New South Wales, and Southern Area to encompass Western Australia, South Australia, Victoria and Tasmania) as part of a much larger proposal to restructure the post-war RAAF, but this never eventuated.&lt;ref&gt;Helson, ''Ten Years at the Top'', p. 257&lt;/ref&gt;

The Federal government retired Jones in 1952 and replaced him with an RAF officer, Air Marshal [[Donald Hardman]], who was well versed in the functional command system employed in Britain.&lt;ref name=&quot;Helson pp. 252–254&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Pathfinder&quot;&gt;{{cite magazine |title = Sir Donald Hardman’s Reorganisation of the RAAF| magazine = Pathfinder|issue=  106| date = March 2009| url = http://airpower.airforce.gov.au/Publications/Details/380/106-Sir-Donald-Hardmans-Reorganisation-of-the-RAAF.aspx|publisher=Air Power Development Centre|accessdate=10 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Hardman believed that restructuring the Air Force would remove inefficiencies and duplication, and permit commanders greater autonomy, allowing more effective concentration of strength in a potential combat situation. He declared that the RAAF was &quot;the one force that could quickly strike for Australia's and the Commonwealth's defence in South East Asia&quot;. To this end he identified three major functions: operations, covering home defence and mobile task forces; training, including all permanent, reserve and [[national service]] recruitment and instruction; and maintenance, responsible for supply, equipment and other logistical services. The three functions  were duly constituted in October 1953 as [[RAAF Home Command|Home]], [[RAAF Training Command|Training]], and [[RAAF Maintenance Command|Maintenance Commands]], respectively.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pathfinder&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Solo&quot;&gt;Stephens, ''Going Solo'', pp. 73–76, 462–463&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Caf hardman.jpg|thumb|right|upright|Air Marshal Hardman, who instituted the RAAF's functional command system|alt=Portrait of man in light-coloured military uniform with pilot's wings on chest, wearing peaked cap with two rows of braid]]
Home Command was re-formed from the existing Eastern Area Command, which was considered a ''de facto'' operational organisation owing to the preponderance of such forces within its boundaries. Training Command was re-formed from Southern Area Command, as it was already the hub of training services, controlling those in New South Wales and Queensland as well as Victoria and South Australia. Maintenance Command was re-formed from the extant Maintenance Group headquarters in Melbourne. The transition to a functional system was completed in February 1954, when the three new commands assumed control of all operations, training and maintenance from Western, North-Western, and North-Eastern Area Commands.&lt;ref name=&quot;Solo&quot;/&gt; These three area commands remained in existence, but only as &quot;remote control points&quot; for Home Command.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article23429331 |title=Battle 'nerve-centre' goes north RAAF fighting control shifted from here |newspaper=[[The Argus (Melbourne)|The Argus]] |location=Melbourne |date=21 May 1954 |accessdate=10 July 2015 |page=5}}&lt;/ref&gt; North-Western Area Command was disbanded in June 1955, Western Area Command in November 1956, and North-Eastern Area Command in December 1956.&lt;ref name=DVA/&gt;

===Aftermath===
The functional commands established in 1953–54 were revised in 1959. Home Command was renamed Operational Command, and Training and Maintenance Commands merged to become [[RAAF Support Command|Support Command]].&lt;ref&gt;Stephens, ''Going Solo'', pp. 76–77&lt;/ref&gt; Operational Command was renamed [[RAAF Air Command|Air Command]] in 1987, and three years later Support Command split into [[RAAF Logistics Command|Logistics Command]] and Training Command.&lt;ref name=&quot;Oxford150&quot;&gt;Dennis et al, ''The Oxford Companion to Australian Military History'', pp. 150–151&lt;/ref&gt; In 1997, logistics management became the responsibility of Support Command (Air Force), the RAAF component of the Defence-wide Support Command Australia (later subsumed by the [[Defence Materiel Organisation]]).&lt;ref&gt;Stephens, ''The Royal Australian Air Force'', p. 307&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://uat.defence.gov.au/AnnualReports/97-98/dar98pr6.pdf|title=Program 6: Support Command|work=Defence Annual Report 1997–98|page=224|date=1998|publisher=[[Department of Defence (Australia)|Department of Defence]]|accessdate=10 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Horner, ''Making the Australian Defence Force'', pp. 278–279&lt;/ref&gt; Training Command was re-formed as [[Air Force Training Group RAAF|Air Force Training Group]], a [[Force Element Group|force element group]] under Air Command, in 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.airforce.gov.au/About_us/Structure_of_the_RAAF/Air_Command/Air_Force_Training_Group/?RAAF-hq2wskEcYXfEfqWNOvO1s4mdhi2R+mo+ |title=Air Force Training Group|publisher= [[Royal Australian Air Force]]|accessdate=10 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Air Command thus became the sole command-level organisation in the RAAF.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.airforce.gov.au/organisation/aircommand/index.htm |title=Air Command |publisher=Royal Australian Air Force |accessdate=10 July 2015 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080720065652/http://www.airforce.gov.au/organisation/aircommand/index.htm |archivedate=20 July 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Summary of area commands formed==
The RAAF raised eight area commands over the course of World War&amp;nbsp;II, and five of them continued to operate into the 1950s:

{|class=&quot;wikitable plainrowheaders sortable&quot; style=&quot;width:65%;&quot;
|-
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Command
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Formation
! scope=&quot;col&quot; | Supersession/disbandment
! scope=&quot;col&quot; class=&quot;unsortable&quot; | Re-formed as
|-
| [[Southern Area Command (RAAF)|Southern Area Command]] || {{center|1940}} || {{center|1953}} || [[RAAF Training Command|Training Command]]
|-
| [[Central Area Command (RAAF)|Central Area Command]] || {{center|1940}} || {{center|1941}} ||  
|-
| [[Western Area Command (RAAF)|Western Area Command]] || {{center|1941}} || {{center|1954/1956}} || 
|-
| [[Northern Area Command (RAAF)|Northern Area Command]] || {{center|1941}} || {{center|1942}} || North-Eastern Area Command&lt;br /&gt;North-Western Area Command
|-
| [[North-Eastern Area Command (RAAF)|North-Eastern Area Command]] || {{center|1942}} || {{center|1954/1956}} || 
|-
| [[North-Western Area Command (RAAF)|North-Western Area Command]] || {{center|1942}} || {{center|1954/1955}} || 
|-
| [[Eastern Area Command (RAAF)|Eastern Area Command]] || {{center|1942}} || {{center|1953}} || [[RAAF Home Command|Home Command]]
|-
| [[Northern Command (RAAF)|Northern Command]] || {{center|1944}} || {{center|1947}} || Northern Area (in 1945)
|}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
*{{cite book | year = 2000| title = How Not to Run an Air Force! Volume One&amp;nbsp;– Narrative| url = http://airpower.airforce.gov.au/Publications/Details/241/How-Not-To-Run-An-Air-Force-Volume-1.aspx| last = Ashworth | first=Norman| publisher = RAAF Air Power Studies Centre | location = Canberra | isbn =978-0-642-26550-0}}
*{{cite book|last=Dennis| first=Peter|author2=Grey, Jeffrey|author3= Morris, Ewan|author4= Prior, Robin| year=2008| origyear=1995| title=The Oxford Companion to Australian Military History| location=South Melbourne| publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|isbn=978-0-19-551784-2}}
*{{cite book|last=Gillison | first=Douglas |year=1962| title=Australia in the War of 1939–1945: Series Three (Air) Volume I&amp;nbsp;– Royal Australian Air Force 1939–1942 | location=Canberra| publisher=[[Australian War Memorial]]|url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070209/| isbn=|oclc=2000369}}
*{{cite thesis | degree =Ph. D| author = Helson, Peter | title = Ten Years at the Top | publisher = [[University of New South Wales]] | location=Sydney|year = 2006 | url = http://handle.unsw.edu.au/1959.4/38729|oclc=225531223}}
*{{cite book|last=Horner|first=David|authorlink=David Horner|title=The Australian Centenary History of Defence Volume IV: Making the Australian Defence Force|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Melbourne|year=2001|isbn=978-0-19-554117-5}}
*{{cite book|last=Odgers | first=George |authorlink=George Odgers|origyear=1957| year=1968| title=Australia in the War of 1939–1945: Series Three (Air) Volume II&amp;nbsp;– Air War Against Japan 1943–1945 | location=Canberra| publisher=Australian War Memorial|  url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070210/| isbn=|oclc=246580191}}
*{{cite book|last=Stephens| first=Alan| year=1995| title=Going Solo: The Royal Australian Air Force 1946–1971|location=Canberra|publisher=Australian Government Publishing Service|url=http://airpower.airforce.gov.au/Publications/Details/214/Going-Solo-The-Royal-Australian-Air-Force-19461971.aspx|isbn=978-0-644-42803-3}}
*{{cite book|last=Stephens| first=Alan|origyear=2001|year=2006| title=The Royal Australian Air Force: A History| location=London| publisher=Oxford University Press|isbn=978-0-19-555541-7}}

{{RAAF area commands}}

[[Category:RAAF commands]]
[[Category:Organizational structures of contemporary air forces]]</text>
      <sha1>7f7kygnb4x8xdiu6n1fzdi02l5e1ko6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
