<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Revolt of the Comuneros</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2358320</id>
    <revision>
      <id>747648713</id>
      <parentid>747616361</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-03T15:31:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>SnowFire</username>
        <id>120807</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>rvt. again, per majority of sources.  There wasn't really any revolutionary activity going on between October &amp; February.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="73577">{{for|other revolts by this name|Comunero (disambiguation)}}
{{good article}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|image=[[File:Comuneros.jpg|alt=Two men and a priest stand in the center, overseeing the proceedings. A dead body lies on the ground; a man triumphantly lifts up his severed head in the background. A bearded man with hands bound is being brought forward to be executed next.|300px]]
|caption=''Execution of the Comuneros of Castile'', by [[Antonio Gisbert]] (1860)
|conflict=Revolt of the Comuneros
|date= April 16, 1520&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; October 25, 1521&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;
|place=[[Crown of Castile]]
|result=Decisive royalist victory
|combatant1= [[List of people associated with the Revolt of the Comuneros#Comuneros|Comuneros rebels]]
|combatant2= [[List of people associated with the Revolt of the Comuneros#Royalists|Royalist Castilians]]
|commander1=[[Juan López de Padilla|Juan de Padilla]],&lt;br/&gt;[[Juan Bravo (rebel)|Juan Bravo]],&lt;br/&gt;[[Francisco Maldonado]],&lt;br/&gt;[[Antonio de Acuña]],&lt;br/&gt;[[Pedro Téllez-Girón, 3rd Count of Ureña|Pedro Girón]],&lt;br/&gt;[[María Pacheco]]
|commander2=[[Charles V, Holy Roman Emperor]]; &lt;br/&gt;[[Pope Adrian VI|Adrian of Utrecht]], regent of Castile; &lt;br/&gt;[[Íñigo Fernández]], [[Constable of Castile]]; &lt;br/&gt;[[Fadrique Enríquez]], [[Admiral of Castile]]
|notes=&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;February 3, 1522 is also used as an end date; see [[#Revolt of February 1522|1522 revolt]].
}}
[[File:Fachada de la iglesia conventual de San Pablo (Valladolid).jpg|thumb|right|275px|alt=A tall stone building, topped with a cross.|[[San Pablo Church]] in [[Valladolid]], seat of a Cortes held in 1518.  Protests emerged when the Flemish adviser [[Jean de Sauvage]] was named its president, presaging later troubles.]]
The '''Revolt of the Comuneros''' ({{lang-es|Guerra de las Comunidades de Castilla}}, &quot;War of the Communities of Castile&quot;) was an uprising by citizens of [[Crown of Castile|Castile]] against the rule of [[Charles V, Holy Roman Emperor|Charles V]] and his administration between 1520 and 1521. At its height, the rebels controlled the heart of Castile, ruling the cities of [[Valladolid]], [[Tordesillas]], and [[Toledo, Spain|Toledo]].

The revolt occurred in the wake of political instability in the [[Crown of Castile]] after the death of Queen [[Isabella I of Castile|Isabella I]] in 1504.  [[Joanna of Castile|Joanna the Mad]], Isabella's daughter, inherited the throne with her [[Duke of Burgundy#House of Habsburg (1482–1780)|Burgundian]] husband [[Philip I of Castile|King Philip I]].  However, Philip died two years into their reign, and their son Charles was only six years old.  Due to his youth and Joanna's mental instability, Castile was ruled by the nobles and her father, [[Ferdinand II of Aragon|King Ferdinand II of Aragon]], as a regency. After Ferdinand's death in 1516, the sixteen-year-old Charles was proclaimed king of both Castile and [[Kingdom of Aragon|Aragon]].  Charles had been raised in the [[Burgundian Netherlands|Netherlands]] with little knowledge of [[Castilian language|Castilian]].  He arrived in Spain in October 1517 accompanied by a large retinue of Flemish nobles and clerics.  These factors resulted in mistrust between the new king and the Castilian social elites, who could see the threat to their power and status.

In 1519, Charles was elected [[Holy Roman Emperor]].  He departed for Germany in 1520, leaving the Dutch cardinal [[Adrian of Utrecht]] to rule Castile in his absence.  Soon, a series of anti-government riots broke out in the cities, and local city councils (''Comunidades'') took power.  The rebels chose Charles' own mother, Queen Joanna, as an alternative ruler, hoping they could control her madness.  The rebel movement took on a radical [[manorialism|anti-feudal]] dimension, supporting peasant rebellions against the landed nobility.  On April 23, 1521, after nearly a year of rebellion, the reorganized supporters of the emperor struck a crippling blow to the comuneros at the [[Battle of Villalar]].  The following day, rebel leaders [[Juan López de Padilla|Juan de Padilla]], [[Juan Bravo (rebel)|Juan Bravo]], and [[Francisco Maldonado]] were beheaded.  The army of the comuneros fell apart.  Only the city of Toledo kept alive the rebellion, until its surrender in October 1521.

The character of the revolution is a matter of historiographical debate.  According to some scholars, the revolt was one of the first modern revolutions, notably because of the anti-noble sentiment against social injustice and its basis on ideals of democracy and freedom.  Others consider it a more typical rebellion against high taxes and perceived foreign control.  From the 19th century onwards, the revolt has been mythologized by various Spaniards, generally liberals who drew political inspiration from it.  Conservative intellectuals have traditionally adopted more pro-Imperial stances toward the revolt, and have been critical of both the motives and the government of the comuneros.  With [[Spanish transition to democracy|the end of Franco's dictatorship]] and the establishment of the [[Autonomous communities of Spain|autonomous community]] of [[Castile and León]], positive commemoration of the ''Comunidades'' has grown.  April 23 is now celebrated as [[Castile and León Day]], and the incident is often referred to in [[Castilian nationalism]].

==Origins==
[[File:Bernaerd van Orley 004.jpg|thumb|left|alt=A young Charles V.|A 1516 portrait of [[Charles V, Holy Roman Emperor|King Charles I of Castile and Aragon]], later Holy Roman Emperor Charles V, by [[Bernard van Orley]].  Charles would rule one of the largest empires in European history&amp;mdash;through his father [[Philip I of Castile|Philip]], [[Kingdom of Burgundy|Burgundy]] and [[Burgundian Netherlands|the Netherlands]]; through his mother [[Joanna of Castile|Joanna]], Castile, Aragon, and [[Kingdom of Naples|Naples]]; and through his grandfather [[Maximilian I, Holy Roman Emperor|Maximilian]] and his election in 1519 as Holy Roman Emperor, Germany, Austria, and much of Northern Italy.]]
Discontent had been brewing for years before the Revolt of the Comuneros. The second half of the 15th century saw profound political, economic, and social changes in Spain.  Economic growth created new urban industries and offered a route to power and wealth not tied to the aristocracy.  Support from these urban elites was critical to [[Catholic Monarchs|Ferdinand and Isabella's]] centralization of power, and they acted as a counterweight to the landed aristocracy and the clergy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Halp10&quot;&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt;

However, with [[Isabella I of Castile|Queen Isabella I]]'s death in 1504, this alliance between the national government and the budding middle class faltered.&lt;ref name=&quot;Halp10&quot; /&gt;  The Castilian government decayed with each successive administration, becoming rife with corruption.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 113.&lt;/ref&gt;  King [[Philip I of Castile|Philip I]] ruled for a mere two years; he was replaced by [[Francisco Jiménez de Cisneros|Archbishop Cisneros]] as regent for a short time, and then by Isabella's widower [[Ferdinand II of Aragon|Ferdinand]] who ruled from Aragon.&lt;ref name=&quot;hal151&quot;&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 151.&lt;/ref&gt;  Ferdinand's claim to continue ruling Castile as regent was somewhat tenuous after Isabella's death, but no plausible alternatives existed as the sovereign, their widowed daughter [[Joanna of Castile|Joanna]], was mentally unfit to reign on her own.&lt;ref name=&quot;hal151&quot; /&gt;  The landed nobility of Castile took advantage of the weak and corrupt [[Council of Castile|Royal Council]] to illegally expand their territory and domain with private armies while the government did nothing.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 66.&lt;/ref&gt;  In response, the towns signed mutual defense pacts, relying on each other rather than the national government.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 93.&lt;/ref&gt;

The budgets of both Castile and Aragon had been in poor condition for some time.  The government had [[Alhambra Decree|expelled the Jews]] in 1492 and the [[Morisco|Muslims of Granada]] in 1502, moves that undercut lucrative trades and businesses.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 147.  The [[silk]] industry is held up as particularly relevant, as the Moors had been deeply involved in it; more generally, many Muslim converts to Christianity who had not been expelled still emigrated from 1500 onward.&lt;/ref&gt;  Ferdinand and Isabella had been forced to borrow money to pay troops during and after the [[Reconquista#Granada War|Reconquista]], and Spanish military obligations had only increased since then.&lt;ref name=&quot;hal147&quot;&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 147.&lt;/ref&gt;  A large number of troops were required to maintain stability in recently conquered [[Emirate of Granada|Granada]], threatened by revolt from the maltreated [[morisco]]s (former Muslims who had converted to Christianity) and frequent [[Barbary pirate|naval raids]] from Muslim nations along the Mediterranean.&lt;ref name=&quot;hal163&quot;&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 163.&lt;/ref&gt;  Additionally, Ferdinand had [[Spanish conquest of Iberian Navarre|invaded and occupied the Iberian part of Navarre]] in 1512, and forces were required to garrison it against Navarrese revolts and French armies.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 145.&lt;/ref&gt;  Very little money was left to pay for the royal army in Castile proper, let alone service foreign debts.  The corruption in the government since Isabella's death only made the budget shortfalls worse.&lt;ref name=&quot;hal147&quot; /&gt;

===Succession of Charles===
In 1516, Ferdinand died.  The remaining heir was Ferdinand and Isabella's grandson [[Charles V, Holy Roman Emperor|Charles]], who became King Charles I of both [[Crown of Castile|Castile]] and [[Kingdom of Aragon|Aragon]] in [[co-regency]] with his mother Joanna.  Charles was brought up in [[Flanders]], the homeland of his father Philip, and barely knew Castilian.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Lyn64|Lynch 1964]], p. 36.&lt;/ref&gt;  The people greeted him with skepticism, but also hoped he would restore stability.  With the arrival of the new king in late 1517, [[List of people associated with the Revolt of the Comuneros#Royal Council and Advisers|his Flemish court]] took positions of power in Castile; young Charles only trusted people he knew from the [[Burgundian Netherlands|Netherlands]].  Among the most scandalous of these was the appointment of the twenty-year-old [[William de Croÿ (archbishop)|William de Croÿ]] as [[Archbishop of Toledo]].  The Archbishopric was an important position; it had been held by [[Francisco Jiménez de Cisneros|Archbishop Cisneros]], the former regent of the country.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 126.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lynch38&quot; /&gt;  Six months into his rule, discontent openly simmered among rich and poor alike.  Even some monks began to agitate, denouncing the opulence of the royal court, the Flemish, and the nobility in their sermons.  One of the first public protests involved placards posted in churches, which read:

{{quote|You, land of Castile, very wretched and damned are you to suffer that as noble a kingdom as you are, you will be governed by those who have no love for you.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Die77|J. L. Díez 1977]], p. 7.  &quot;Tú, tierra de Castilla, muy desgraciada y maldita eres al sufrir que un tan noble reino como eres, sea gobernado por quienes no te tienen amor.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;}}

With the unrest growing, Charles' paternal grandfather [[Maximilian I, Holy Roman Emperor|Holy Roman Emperor Maximilian I]] died in 1519.  A new election had to be held to choose the next emperor.  Charles campaigned aggressively for the post, vying with [[Francis I of France|King Francis I of France]] to bribe the most [[prince-elector]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;sea50&quot;&gt;[[#Sea28|Seaver 1928]], p. 50.&lt;/ref&gt;  Charles I won the election, becoming Emperor Charles V and cementing the power of the [[House of Habsburg]].  He prepared to head to Germany to take possession of his new domains in the Holy Roman Empire.&lt;ref name=&quot;sea50&quot; /&gt;

===New taxes: The Cortes of Santiago and Corunna===
Charles had already stressed the treasury to its limit with his extravagant Flemish court, and over 1 million [[gold florin]]s were spent in bribes for the election.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lynch38&quot;&gt;[[#Lyn64|Lynch 1964]], p. 38.&lt;/ref&gt;  Taxes{{Ref label|A|note a|none}} had to be raised to cover the debt, but  any new taxes must be approved by the ''[[Cortes Generales#History of the Cortes|Cortes]]'' (Castile's own parliamentary body).  Thus, in late March 1520, Charles convened the Cortes in [[Santiago de Compostela]].  Charles ensured the Cortes would only have limited power, and further attempted to stack the Cortes with pliable representatives he could bribe.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lynch38&quot; /&gt;  Support for the opposition only increased in response, and the representatives demanded that their grievances be heard first before any new tax was granted.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hal159&quot;&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 159.&lt;/ref&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
A group of clerics soon circulated a statement in protest of the king.  It argued three points: any new taxes should be rejected; Castile should be embraced and the foreign Empire rejected; and if the king did not take into account his subjects, the ''Comunidades'' themselves should defend the interests of the kingdom.&lt;ref name=&quot;Perez39&quot;&gt;[[#Per01|Pérez 2001]], p. 39&amp;ndash;40.&lt;/ref&gt; It was the first time where the word ''comunidades'' (communities, communes) was used to signify the independent populace, and the name would stick to the councils later formed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Perez39&quot; /&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;
At this point, most of the members of the Cortes in Santiago intended to vote against the king's requested duties and taxes, even with the Cortes stacked with royalists.  In response, Charles decided to suspend the Cortes on April 4.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Sea28|Seaver 1928]], p. 75.&lt;/ref&gt;  He convened them again in [[A Coruña|Corunna]] &lt;!--See talk page for why Corunna is used, not A/La Coruña.--&gt; on April 22, this time getting his program passed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lynch38&quot; /&gt;  On May 20, he embarked for Germany, and left as regent of his Spanish possessions his former tutor, [[Adrian of Utrecht]] (better known as the future Pope Adrian VI).&lt;ref&gt;[[#Sea28|Seaver 1928]], p. 77&amp;ndash;79.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Beginnings of the Revolt==

===Rebelliousness in Toledo===
[[File:Toledo Skyline Panorama, Spain - Dec 2006.jpg|thumb|300px|alt=A cityscape; two tall buildings dominate the view, the Alcázar and the Cathedral.|Toledo, home of the first ''Comunidad'']]
[[File:Juan de Padilla.gif|thumb|175px|alt=A bearded man wearing a feathered cap, armor, and sash.|[[Juan López de Padilla]], leader of the ''Comunidad'' of Toledo]]
In April 1520, [[Toledo, Spain|Toledo]] was already unstable.  The city council had been at the forefront of protests against Charles' bid to become Holy Roman Emperor.  They decried the short-term expenses that would be borne by [[Crown of Castile|Castile]] and questioned the role of Castile in this new political framework, given the possibility that the land would become a mere imperial province.&lt;ref name=&quot;Perez39&quot; /&gt;  The situation erupted when the royal government summoned the most radical of the city councilors away from the city, intending to send back more easily controllable replacements on a royal salary.  The order came on April 15; one day later, as the councilors prepared to leave, a large crowd opposed to the departure rioted and drove out the royal administrators instead.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 160.&lt;/ref&gt;  A citizen's committee was elected under the leadership of [[Juan López de Padilla]] and [[Pero Laso de la Vega]], naming themselves a ''Comunidad''.  On April 21, the remaining administrators were driven from the fortifications of the [[Alcázar of Toledo]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 161, and [[#Sea28|Seaver 1928]], p. 87.  [[#Per01|Pérez 2001]] lists the final fall as happening on May 31; this is (almost certainly) referring to the formal capture of the Alcázar.  The defending forces had long since left by then.&lt;/ref&gt;

Following Charles' departure to Germany, the riots multiplied in the cities of [[Geography of Spain#The Inner Plateau and associated mountains|central Castile]], especially after the arrival of legislators who had voted &quot;yes&quot; to the taxes Charles had asked for.  [[Segovia]] had some of the earliest and most violent incidents; on May 30, a mob of woolworkers murdered two administrators and the city's legislator who had voted in favor.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt;  Incidents of a similar size occurred in cities such as [[Burgos]] and [[Guadalajara, Spain|Guadalajara]], while others, such as [[León, Spain|León]], [[Ávila, Spain|Ávila]], and [[Zamora, Spain|Zamora]], suffered minor altercations.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Per01|Pérez 2001]], p. 50&amp;ndash;52.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Proposals to other cities===
With widespread discontent circulating, on June 8 Toledo's council suggested to cities with a vote in the Cortes to hold an emergency meeting.  They proffered five goals:
# Cancel the taxes voted in the Cortes of Corunna.
# A return to the local-controlled ''[[#endnote Anone|encabezamiento]]'' system of taxation.
# Reserve official positions and church [[benefice]]s for Castilians.
# Prohibit money from leaving the kingdom to fund foreign affairs.
# Designate a Castilian to lead the kingdom in the absence of the king.&lt;ref name=&quot;perez53&quot;&gt;[[#Per01|Pérez 2001]], p. 53&amp;ndash;54.&lt;/ref&gt;

These claims, especially the first two, spread quickly through society.&lt;ref name=&quot;perez53&quot; /&gt;  Ideas began to circulate of replacing the king; Toledo's leaders floated the possibility of turning the cities of Castile into independent [[City-state|free cities]], similar to [[Republic of Genoa|Genoa]] and other [[Repubbliche Marinare|Italian republics]].&lt;ref name=&quot;perez53&quot; /&gt;  Competing proposals suggested keeping the monarchy, but dethroning Charles.  They proposed that he be replaced by either his mother Queen Joanna or his Castilian-born brother [[Ferdinand I, Holy Roman Emperor|Ferdinand]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Hal159&quot; /&gt;  With these ideas, the revolt shifted from a simple protest against taxes to a broader revolution.  Many cities, while not quite in outright revolt, stopped sending taxes to the Royal Council and began to self-govern.&lt;ref name=&quot;hal164&quot;&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 164.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Expansion of the Revolt==

===Blockade of Segovia===
[[File:AcueductoSegovia edit1.jpg|thumb|alt=A stone aqueduct bordered by a modern road and smaller houses.|Segovia, the city of the first armed clash between the comuneros and the royalists]]
The situation moved closer to armed conflict on June 10.  [[Rodrigo Ronquillo]] had been sent to Segovia by the [[Council of Castile|Royal Council]] to investigate the recent murder of Segovia's legislator, but Segovia refused him entry.  Unable to besiege a city of 30,000 with only a small force, Ronquillo instead set out to blockade foodstuffs and other supplies from entering Segovia.  The people of Segovia, led by militia leader and noble [[Juan Bravo (rebel)|Juan Bravo]], rallied around the ''Comunidad''.  Segovia requested aid against Ronquillo's army from the ''Comunidades'' of Toledo and Madrid.  The cities responded by sending their militias, captained by [[Juan López de Padilla|Juan de Padilla]] and [[Juan Zapata]], who won in the first major confrontation between the forces of the king and the rebels.&lt;ref name=&quot;hal163&quot;/&gt;

===The Junta of Ávila===
Other cities now followed the lead of Toledo and Segovia, deposing their governments.  A revolutionary Cortes, {{lang|es|''La Santa Junta de las Comunidades''}} (&quot;Holy Assembly of the Communities&quot;),{{Ref label|B|note b|none}} held its first session in [[Ávila, Spain|Ávila]] and declared itself the legitimate government deposing the Royal Council.  Padilla was named Captain-General, and troops were assembled.  Still, only four cities sent representatives at first: Toledo, Segovia, Salamanca, and Toro.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 166.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Burning of Medina del Campo===
[[File:Medinapano03.jpg|thumb|alt=A stone castle, surrounded by an empty moat.|The ''[[Castillo de la Mota]]'' of [[Medina del Campo]]]]
Faced with the situation in Segovia, Regent and Cardinal [[Adrian of Utrecht]] decided to use the royal artillery, located in nearby [[Medina del Campo]], to take Segovia and defeat Padilla.  Adrian ordered his commander [[Antonio de Fonseca]] to seize the artillery.&lt;ref name=&quot;hal165&quot;&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 165.&lt;/ref&gt;  Fonseca arrived on August 21 in Medina, but encountered heavy resistance from the townspeople, as the city had strong trade links to Segovia.  Fonseca ordered the setting of a fire to distract the resistance, but it grew out of control.  Much of the town was destroyed, including a [[Franciscan]] monastery and a trade warehouse containing goods valued at more than 400,000 [[ducat]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;sea129&quot; /&gt;  Fonseca had to withdraw his troops, and the event was a public relations disaster for the government.&lt;ref name=&quot;sea129&quot;&gt;[[#Sea28|Seaver 1928]], p. 129.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Halp6&quot; /&gt;  Uprisings throughout Castile occurred, even in cities that previously had been neutral such as Castile's capital, [[Valladolid]].  The establishment of the ''Comunidad'' of Valladolid caused the most important core of the [[Geography of Spain#The Inner Plateau and associated mountains|Iberian plateau]] to declare for the rebels, upending the stability of the government.  New members now joined the Junta of Ávila and the Royal Council looked discredited; Adrian had to flee to [[Medina de Rioseco]] as Valladolid fell.&lt;ref name=&quot;Halp6&quot;&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt;  The royal army, with many of its soldiers unpaid for months, started to disintegrate.&lt;ref name=&quot;hal165&quot; /&gt;

===The Junta of Tordesillas===
[[File:Johanna I van Castilië.JPG|thumb|right|alt=A lady with a long, thin face wearing red robes and a hood in the style of a nun.|[[Joanna the Mad]], officially the Queen and co-regent of Castile with her son Charles, actually had no power whatsoever]]
The comunero army now properly organized itself, integrating the militias of Toledo, Madrid, and Segovia.  Once told of Fonseca's attack, the comunero forces went to Medina del Campo and took possession of the artillery that had just been denied to Fonseca's troops.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Per01|Pérez 2001]], p. 60.&lt;/ref&gt;  On August 29, the comuneros' army arrived at [[Tordesillas]] with the goal of declaring [[Joanna of Castile|Queen Joanna]] the sole sovereign.  The Junta moved from Ávila to Tordesillas at the Queen's request and invited cities that had not yet sent representatives to do so.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Sea28|Seaver 1928]], p. 164.&lt;/ref&gt;  A total of thirteen cities were represented in the Junta of Tordesillas: [[Burgos]], [[Soria]], [[Segovia]], [[Ávila, Spain|Ávila]], [[Valladolid]], [[León, Spain|León]], [[Salamanca]], [[Zamora, Spain|Zamora]], [[Toro, Zamora|Toro]], [[Toledo, Spain|Toledo]], [[Cuenca, Spain|Cuenca]], [[Guadalajara, Spain|Guadalajara]], and [[Madrid]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 167.&lt;/ref&gt;  The only invited cities that failed to attend were the four Andalusian cities: [[Seville]], [[Granada]], [[Córdoba, Spain|Cordova]], and [[Jaén, Spain|Jaén]].  Since most of the kingdom was represented at Tordesillas, the Junta renamed itself the {{lang|es|''[[Cortes Generales|Cortes y Junta General del Reino]]''}} (&quot;General Assembly of the Kingdom&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;[[#Per01|Pérez 2001]], p. 61.  In the spelling of the time, it was rendered ''Cortes e Junta General del Reyno''.&lt;/ref&gt;  On September 24, 1520, the mad Queen, for the only time, presided over the Cortes.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Sea28|Seaver 1928]], p. 147.&lt;/ref&gt;

The legislators met with Queen Joanna and explained the purpose of the Cortes: to proclaim her sovereignty and restore lost stability to the kingdom.  The next day, September 25, the Cortes issued a declaration pledging to use arms if necessary and for the whole to aid any one city that was threatened.  On September 26, the Cortes of Tordesillas declared itself the new legitimate government and denounced the Royal Council.  Oaths of self-defense were taken by all the cities represented over the week, finishing by September 30.  The revolutionary government now had structure and a free hand to act, with the Royal Council still ineffective and confused.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 179.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Scope of the rebellion===
[[File:Escultura en bronce de Juan de Padilla, obra del escultor toledano Julio Martín de Vidales.jpg|thumb|right|Bronze sculpture of Juan de Padilla in Toledo]]
The comuneros were strong in the [[Geography of Spain#The Inner Plateau and associated mountains|central plateau of the Iberian Peninsula]], as well as scattered other places such as [[Murcia]].  The rebels sought to propound their revolutionary ideas to the rest of the kingdom, but without much success.  There were few attempts at rebellion elsewhere, such as in [[Galicia (Spain)|Galicia]] to the northwest or in [[Andalusia]] to the south.&lt;ref name=&quot;perez146&quot;&gt;[[#Per01|Pérez 2001]], p. 146&amp;ndash;147.&lt;/ref&gt;  ''Comunidades'' in the south were set up in [[Jaén, Spain|Jaén]], [[Úbeda]], and [[Baeza]], unique in Andalusia, but with time they were drawn back into the royalists.  Murcia stayed with the rebel cause, but did not coordinate much with the Junta, and the rebellion there had a character closer to the nearby [[Revolt of the Brotherhoods]] in [[Kingdom of Valencia|Valencia]] in [[Crown of Aragon|Aragon]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Per01|Pérez 2001]], p. 155.&lt;/ref&gt;  In [[Extremadura]] to the southwest, the city of [[Plasencia]] joined the  ''Comunidades'', but this was undermined by the close proximity of other royalist cities such as [[Ciudad Rodrigo]] and [[Cáceres, Spain|Cáceres]].&lt;ref name=&quot;perez146&quot; /&gt;  A close correlation can be drawn between poor economic fortunes over the previous twenty years and the rebellion; central Castile suffered from agricultural failure and other setbacks under the Royal Council, while Andalusia was relatively prosperous with its maritime trade.  Andalusia's leadership also feared that in the instability of a civil war, the [[Moriscos]] of Granada would likely revolt.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 183, 205.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{wide image|ComunerosCityControl.svg|760px|alt=Map of Spain with cities colored by affiliation; see text for details.|3=The rebels were strongest in the central plateau of Spain; the royalists controlled Andalusia in the South and Galicia in the North.  Aragon was distracted by the [[Revolt of the Brotherhoods]], and [[Spanish conquest of Iberian Navarre|Navarre was occupied]] by Castilian troops who guarded against the return of the [[Henry II of Navarre|Navarrese king]] and the French.  Rebel cities are in purple; Royalist cities are in green; cities with both elements present or that vacillated are in both colors.}}

==Popular and governmental response==
[[File:Hadrian VI.jpg|thumb|right|alt=A middle-aged man in red and white clerical vestment.|[[Adrian of Utrecht]], future Pope Adrian VI, was considered an effective regent despite the difficult situation.  He spearheaded the recruitment of nobility to the royalist side, and two Castilian co-regents were appointed to lessen the appearance of foreign control.]]

===Turning of the nobles===
The growing success of the comuneros emboldened people to accuse members of the old government of complicity with royal abuses.  The protests attacked the landed nobility as well, many of whom had illegally taken property during the reign of the regents and weak kings after Isabella's death.  In [[Dueñas, Palencia|Dueñas]], the Count of Buendía's vassals revolted against him on September 1, 1520, encouraged by rebel monks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Halp185&quot; /&gt;  This uprising was followed by others of a similar anti-feudal nature.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Per01|Pérez 2001]], p. 65.&lt;/ref&gt;  The leadership of the comuneros was forced to take a stance on these new rebellions; reluctant to openly endorse them, the Junta initially denounced them but did nothing to oppose them.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Sea28|Seaver 1928]], p. 306.&lt;/ref&gt;  The dynamics of the uprising thus changed profoundly, as it could now jeopardize the status of the entire [[Manorialism|manorial system]].  The nobles had previously been somewhat sympathetic to the cause due to their loss of privileges to the central government.  However, these new developments lead to a dramatic drop in support for the comuneros from aristocrats, who were frightened by the more radical elements of the revolution.&lt;ref name=&quot;Halp185&quot;&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 185.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Response of Charles V===
At first, Charles seemed not to grasp the magnitude of the revolt.  He continued to demand payments from Castile; with the government of Castile still in arrears, Cardinal Adrian found it impossible to secure any new loans.&lt;ref name=&quot;hal164&quot; /&gt;  A letter from Cardinal Adrian on August 25 warned Charles of the severity of the situation:

{{quote|Your Highness is making a great error if you think that you will be able to collect and make use of this tax; there is no one in the Kingdom, not in Seville or Valladolid or any other city who will ever pay anything of it; all the grandees and members of the council are amazed that Your Highness has scheduled payments from these funds.&lt;ref name=&quot;hal164&quot; /&gt;|[[Adrian of Utrecht]]}}

Once he realized that a full-fledged revolution was underway, Charles responded vigorously.  Through Cardinal Adrian, he undertook new policy initiatives, such as canceling the taxes granted in the Cortes of Corunna.  Most important was the appointment of two new Castilian co-regents: the [[Constable of Castile]], [[Íñigo Fernández]], and the [[Admiral of Castile]], [[Fadrique Enríquez]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Sea28|Seaver 1928]], p. 155&amp;ndash;156.&lt;/ref&gt;  This negated two of the most salient complaints of the rebels.  In addition, Adrian approached the nobles to convince them that their best interests lay with the king.  The Royal Council was re-established in the fief of Admiral Enríquez, [[Medina de Rioseco]], which enabled the Council to be nearer to the revolting cities and reassure skeptical supporters.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Sea28|Seaver 1928]], p. 163.&lt;/ref&gt;  While the royal army was still in tatters, many high nobles maintained their own well-trained mercenary armies&amp;mdash;armies that with the revolt's recent radicalization would now fight for the king.&lt;ref name=&quot;Halp6&quot; /&gt;

==Organization, funding, and diplomacy==
The first political defeats of the comuneros came in October 1520.  The comuneros' attempt to use Queen Joanna for legitimacy did not bear fruit, as she blocked their initiatives and refused to sign any edicts.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 156.&lt;/ref&gt;  In turn, dissenting voices inside the comuneros now began to be heard, especially in [[Burgos]].  The wavering position of Burgos was soon known to the royalists, and the Constable of Castile negotiated with Burgos's government.  The Royal Council granted a number of significant concessions to Burgos in exchange for them leaving the Junta.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Sea28|Seaver 1928]], p. 215.&lt;/ref&gt;

Following this incident, the Royal Council hoped that other cities would imitate Burgos and leave the comuneros peacefully.  Valladolid, the former seat of royal power, was considered especially likely to turn, but too many supporters of the king had left city politics and lost their influence.  It remained rebel-controlled.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Sea28|Seaver 1928]], p. 179.&lt;/ref&gt;  The Admiral of Castile continued his campaign to try to convince the comuneros to return to the royal government and thereby avoid a violent suppression.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Sea28|Seaver 1928]], p. 192&amp;ndash;195.&lt;/ref&gt;  This attitude concealed a great shortage of funds on the royal side.&lt;ref name=&quot;hal181&quot;&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 181.&lt;/ref&gt;

During October and November 1520, both sides accepted that a military conclusion would soon be necessary and actively devoted themselves to fundraising, recruiting soldiers, and training their troops.  The comuneros organized their militias in the major cities and levied new taxes on the countryside; they also took measures aimed at eliminating waste, routinely auditing their treasurers and dismissing those thought to be corrupt.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 170.&lt;/ref&gt;  The royal government, which had lost much of its revenue due to the revolt, sought loans from [[Portugal]] and from conservative Castilian bankers, who saw reassuring signs in the switch of the allegiance of Burgos.&lt;ref name=&quot;hal181&quot; /&gt;

==Battle of Tordesillas==
{{main|Military history of the Revolt of the Comuneros#Battle of Tordesillas}}

===Leadership disputes===
[[File:BattleofTordesillas.PNG|thumb|right|310px|alt=Map of army maneuvers.  The comunero army heads north to Villabrágima, then west, leaving the way open for the royal army to march south from Medina de Rioseco to Tordesillas.|The royal army, commanded by the [[Íñigo Fernández|Constable of Castile]]'s son, the [[Pedro IV Fernández de Velasco|Count of Haro]], consisted of 6,000 infantry, 2,100 cavalry, and 12&amp;ndash;15 artillery pieces.  [[Pedro Téllez-Girón, 3rd Count of Ureña|Pedro Girón]]'s rebel force was larger but slower, with 10,000 infantry, 900 cavalry, and 13 artillery pieces.  The rebels' deficiency in cavalry would hurt them throughout the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;seaver200&quot; /&gt;]]
Gradually, both the city of Toledo and its leader [[Juan López de Padilla|Juan de Padilla]] lost influence within the Junta, though Padilla retained popularity and prestige among the commoners.  Two new figures emerged within the ''Comunidades'', [[Pedro Téllez-Girón, 3rd Count of Ureña|Pedro Girón]] and [[Antonio Osorio de Acuña]].  Girón was one of the most powerful nobles who supported the comuneros; his rebellion is thought to originate from Charles' refusal to grant Girón the prestigious [[Dukes of Medina Sidonia|Duchy of Medina-Sidonia]] a year prior to the war.  Antonio de Acuña was the [[Roman Catholic Diocese of Zamora in Spain|Bishop of Zamora]].  Acuña was also the head of the ''Comunidad'' in Zamora and the leader of its army, which included more than 300 priests.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Per01|Pérez 2001]], p. 75.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Alfonso Guilarte&quot;&gt;[[#Gui83|Guilarte 1983]].&lt;/ref&gt;

On the royalist side, the nobles could not agree on what tactics to use.  Some preferred to directly challenge the rebels in combat, while others such as the Constable of Castile favored continued waiting and the building of defensive fortifications.  The Admiral of Castile preferred negotiations and exhausting all the possible peaceful options first.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Lyn64|Lynch 1964]], p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt;   Patience, however, began to run thin; armies were expensive to maintain once assembled.  In late November 1520, both armies took positions between Medina de Rioseco and Tordesillas, and a confrontation was inevitable.&lt;ref name=&quot;perez78&quot;&gt;[[#Per01|Pérez 2001]], p. 78.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Royal capture===
With Pedro Girón in command, the army of the comuneros advanced on [[Medina de Rioseco]], following the orders of the Junta.  Girón established his headquarters in [[Villabrágima]], a town merely {{convert|8|km|mi}} from the royalist army.  The royalists occupied nearby villages to cut communication lines back to other comuneros.&lt;ref name=&quot;perez78&quot; /&gt;

This situation continued until December 2, when Girón, apparently thinking the royal army would remain entrenched,{{Ref label|C|note c|none}} moved his forces west to the small town of [[Villalpando]].&lt;ref name=&quot;hal189&quot;&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 189&lt;/ref&gt;  The town surrendered the next day without resistance, and the troops began looting the estates in the area.  However, with this movement, the comuneros left the path to Tordesillas completely unprotected. The royal army took advantage of the blunder, marching by night on December 4 and occupying Tordesillas the next day.  The small rebel garrison was overwhelmed.&lt;ref name=&quot;seaver200&quot;&gt;[[#Sea28|Seaver 1928]], p. 200&amp;ndash;202.&lt;/ref&gt;

Seizure of Tordesillas marked a serious defeat for the comuneros, who lost [[Joanna of Castile|Queen Joanna]] and with her their claim to legitimacy. In addition, thirteen representatives of the Junta were imprisoned, though others fled and escaped.&lt;ref name=&quot;hal189&quot; /&gt;  Morale fell among the rebels, and much angry criticism was directed towards Pedro Girón for his maneuvering of the troops out of position and for his failure to attempt to retake Tordesillas or capture Medina de Rioseco.  Girón was obliged to resign from his post and withdrew from the war.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Sea28|Seaver 1928]], p. 206.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Events of December and January==

===Reorganization of the comuneros===
Following the loss of Tordesillas, the comuneros regrouped in [[Valladolid]].  The Junta reconvened on December 15, but with only eleven cities represented, down from a height of fourteen.  Soria and Guadalajara's representatives did not return, and Burgos had left earlier.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Per70|Pérez 1970]], p. 262.  Note that the original Junta of Tordesillas had thirteen cities represented, not fourteen; Murcia joined later.&lt;/ref&gt;  Valladolid would be the third capital of the rebels, after Ávila and Tordesillas.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Per01|Pérez 2001]], p. 95&lt;/ref&gt;

The situation was somewhat worse for the army, with a large number of desertions in Valladolid and Villalpando.  This forced the rebels to intensify their recruitment drives, especially in Toledo, Salamanca, and Valladolid itself.  With these new recruits and the arrival of Juan de Padilla to Valladolid, the rebel military apparatus was rebuilt and morale bolstered.  At the beginning of 1521, the comuneros prepared for an all-out war, despite disagreements within the movement.  Some suggested seeking a peaceful resolution, while others favored continuing the war.  Those who favored war were divided between two tactics: occupy [[Simancas]] and [[Torrelobatón]], a less ambitious proposal defended by [[Pero Laso de la Vega]]; or lay siege to Burgos, a tactic favored by Padilla.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Per01|Pérez 2001]], p. 99&lt;/ref&gt;

===Military initiatives in Palencia and Burgos===
[[File:Burgos Santa Maria Arc.jpg|thumb|300px|alt=An ornate stone gate with statues.|[[Arco de Santa María]] in [[Burgos]], one of the few cities loyal to the king on the Iberian plateau]]

In the far north of Castile, the rebel army began a series of operations conducted by [[Antonio Osorio de Acuña|Antonio de Acuña]], bishop of Zamora.  They received orders from the Junta on December 23 to try and raise a rebellion in [[Palencia (province)|Palencia]].  They were tasked with expelling royalists, collecting taxes on behalf of the Junta, and creating an administration sympathetic to the comuneros cause. Acuña's army made a series of raids into the area around [[Dueñas, Palencia|Dueñas]], raising more than 4,000 ducats and inspiring the peasantry.  He returned to Valladolid in early 1521, then came back to Dueñas on January 10 to begin a major offensive against the nobles of [[Tierra de Campos]].  The nobles' land and holdings were completely devastated.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alfonso Guilarte&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;perez105&quot; /&gt;

In mid-January, Pedro de Ayala, Count of Salvatierra, joined the comuneros and organized an army of about two thousand men who set about raiding the north of Castile.&lt;ref name=&quot;seaver294&quot;&gt;[[#Sea28|Seaver 1928]], p. 294&lt;/ref&gt;  Nearby, Burgos awaited the fulfillment of the pledges made by Cardinal Adrian after they had joined the royalist cause two months prior.  The slow response led to dissatisfaction and uncertainty in the city.  Ayala and Acuña, aware of this situation, decided to besiege Burgos, Ayala from its north and Acuña from its south.  They also sought to undermine the defenses by encouraging a revolt of the inhabitants of Burgos.&lt;ref name=&quot;perez105&quot;&gt;[[#Per01|Pérez 2001]], p. 105&lt;/ref&gt;

===Royalist response===
Still in Germany, Charles V issued the Edict of Worms on December 17, 1520 (not to be confused with the [[Edict of Worms]] of May 25, 1521, against [[Martin Luther]]), which condemned 249 prominent ''Comunidad'' members.  For secular rebels, the punishment was death; clergy were to receive lighter penalties.  Similarly, the edict also declared that those who supported the ''Comunidades'' were traitors, disloyal, rebels, and infidels.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.cervantesvirtual.com/historia/CarlosV/7_1_14.shtml |title=Texto íntegro del Edicto de Worms |publisher=Cervantes Virtual Library |date=1520-12-17 |accessdate=2008-07-20 |language=Spanish }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Royal Council's next move was the occupation of [[Ampudia]] in Palencia, a town loyal to the Count of Salvatierra.  The Junta sent Padilla to meet Acuña; their combined force besieged the royal army at [[Torremormojón|the castle of Mormojón]].  The royal army slipped away by nightfall, and Mormojón was forced to pay tribute to avoid being pillaged.  Ampudia was recovered by the rebels the next day, January 16.&lt;ref name=&quot;seaver228&quot;&gt;[[#Sea28|Seaver 1928]], p. 228, and [[#Per01|Pérez 2001]], p. 104.  The two accounts disagree on the amount of Mormojón's tribute: Seaver says 1,500 ducats, and Pérez 2,000.&lt;/ref&gt;

Meanwhile, the rebellion in Burgos scheduled for January 23 was a failure due to poor coordination with the besieging army; it started two days early and was easily crushed. The comuneros of Burgos had to surrender, and this was the last rebellion to be seen in Castile.&lt;ref name=&quot;perez105&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;seaver228&quot; /&gt;

==Rebel campaigns of early 1521==

===Padilla's decision on the rebels' next move===
[[File:Castillo de Torrelobatón (torre del homenaje).jpg|thumb|alt=A stone tower at the corner of the defensive walls.|The taking of the [[Castle of Torrelobatón]], built in the 13th century, provided a much-needed victory for the comuneros.  The castle was renovated in 2007 and is now a tourist site.]]
After abandoning the siege of Burgos due to the failure of its revolt, Padilla decided to return to Valladolid, while Acuña opted to resume his skirmishing and harassment of noble properties around Tierra de Campos. With this series of actions, Acuña intended to destroy or occupy the homes of the prominent nobles.  The rebels now set themselves completely against the [[manorialism|manorial system]].  This would be one of the strongest features of the second phase of the rebellion.&lt;ref name=&quot;seaver228&quot; /&gt;

After the recent setbacks suffered by the comuneros, Padilla realized that they needed a victory to raise morale.  He decided to take [[Torrelobatón]] and its castle.  Torrelobatón was a stronghold halfway between Tordesillas and Medina de Rioseco, and was very close to Valladolid.  Taking it would grant the rebels an excellent fortress for launching military operations and remove a threat on Valladolid.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Sea28|Seaver 1928]], p. 248.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Battle of Torrelobatón===
On February 21, 1521, the [[Military history of the Revolt of the Comuneros#Battle of Torrelobatón|siege of Torrelobatón]] began.  Outnumbered, the town nevertheless resisted for four days, thanks to its walls.  On February 25, the comuneros entered the town and subjected it to a massive looting spree as a reward to the troops.  Only churches were spared.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Sea28|Seaver 1928]], p. 251.&lt;/ref&gt;  The castle resisted for another two days. The comuneros then threatened to [[hanging|hang]] all of the inhabitants, at which point the castle surrendered.  The defenders did secure an agreement to spare half of the goods inside the castle, thus avoiding further looting.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Per01|Pérez 2001]], p. 107.  &quot;Los asaltantes amenzaron con ahorcar a todos los inhabitantes si no se rendía.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

The victory in Torrelobatón lifted the spirits of the rebel camp while worrying the royalists about the rebel advance, exactly as Padilla hoped.  The faith of the nobles in Cardinal Adrian was again shaken, as he was accused of having done nothing to avoid losing Torrelobatón.  The Constable of Castile began to send troops to the Tordesillas area to contain the rebels and prevent any further advances.&lt;ref name=&quot;perez110&quot;&gt;[[#Per01|Pérez 2001]], p. 110.&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the renewed enthusiasm among the rebels, a decision was made to remain in their positions near Valladolid without pressing their advantage or launching a new attack.  This caused many of the soldiers to return to their home communities, tired of waiting for salaries and new orders.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Per01|Pérez 2001]], p. 109.&lt;/ref&gt;  This was a problem the comunero forces had throughout the war; they possessed only a small number of full-time soldiers, and their militias were constantly &quot;dissolving and recruiting.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Sea28|Seaver 1928]], p. 319.&lt;/ref&gt;  A serious attempt to negotiate a peaceful end to the war was tried again by the moderates, but was undercut by extremists of both sides.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Sea28|Seaver 1928]], p. 278.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the north, after the failure of the siege of Burgos in January, the Count of Salvatierra resumed his campaign.  He set off to cause an uprising in [[Merindades]], the homeland of the Constable of Castile, and besieged [[Medina de Pomar]] and [[Frías (Burgos)|Frías]].&lt;ref name=&quot;seaver294&quot; /&gt;

===Acuña's southern campaign===
{{main|Military history of the Revolt of the Comuneros#Acuña's campaign, March–April}}
[[File:Iglesia de la Virgen de Altagracia, Mora (Toledo).jpg|thumb|A stone tower.  Crosses can be seen in the windows.|The Church of the Virgin of Highest Grace in [[Mora, Spain|Mora]], completely reconstructed after royalist troops set fire to it while 50 refugees took shelter inside.  The royalist commander [[Antonio de Zúñiga|Prior Zúñiga]] denied responsibility.&lt;ref name=&quot;seaver333&quot; /&gt;]]
[[William de Croÿ (archbishop)|William de Croÿ]], the young Flemish [[Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Toledo|Archbishop of Toledo]] appointed by Charles, died in January 1521 in [[Worms, Germany]].  In Valladolid, the Junta proposed to [[Antonio de Acuña]] that he submit himself as a candidate for the seat.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alfonso Guilarte&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;perez114&quot; /&gt;

Acuña departed for Toledo in February with a small force under his command.  He traveled south, declaring his impending claim on the archdiocese to every village as he passed.  This raised enthusiasm among the commoners, who received him with cheers, but aroused suspicion in the aristocracy.  They feared Acuña might attack their holdings as he did in [[Tierra de Campos]].  The [[Diego López Pacheco|Marquis of Villena]] and [[Diego Hurtado de Mendoza y Luna|Duke of Infantado]] contacted Acuña and persuaded him to sign a pact of mutual neutrality.&lt;ref name=&quot;perez114&quot;&gt;[[#Per01|Pérez 2001]], p. 114&amp;ndash;115.&lt;/ref&gt;

Acuña soon had to confront [[Antonio de Zúñiga]], who had been appointed commander of the royalist army in the Toledo area.  Zúñiga was a [[prior]] in the [[Knights of St. John]], who maintained a base in Castile at the time.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Per01|Pérez 2001]], p. 116&lt;/ref&gt;  Acuña received information that Zúñiga was in the area of [[Corral de Almaguer]], and pursued battle with him near [[Tembleque]].  Zúñiga drove the rebel forces off, and then launched a counterattack of his own between [[Lillo, Spain|Lillo]] and [[El Romeral]], inflicting a crushing defeat on Acuña.  Acuña, a relentless self-promoter, tried to minimize the loss and even claimed that he had emerged victorious from the confrontation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alfonso Guilarte&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;seaver332&quot;&gt;[[#Sea28|Seaver 1928]], p. 332.&lt;/ref&gt;

Undaunted, Acuña continued into Toledo.  He appeared at the [[Zocodover Plaza]] in the heart of the city on March 29, 1521, [[Good Friday]].  The crowd gathered around him and took him directly to the cathedral, claiming the archbishop's chair for him.&lt;ref name=&quot;Alfonso Guilarte&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;seaver333&quot;&gt;[[#Sea28|Seaver 1928]], p. 333&amp;ndash;334.&lt;/ref&gt; The next day he met with [[María Pacheco]], wife of Juan de Padilla and ''de facto'' leader of the Toledo ''Comunidad'' in her husband's absence.  A brief rivalry emerged between the two, but it was resolved after mutual attempts at reconciliation.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Per01|Pérez 2001]], p. 120.&lt;/ref&gt;

Once settled in the [[archdiocese of Toledo]], Acuña began to recruit any men he could find, enlisting soldiers from fifteen to sixty years old.  After royalist troops burned the town of [[Mora, Spain|Mora]] on April 12, Acuña returned to the countryside with roughly 1,500 men under his command.  He moved into [[Yepes]], and from there conducted raids and operations against royalist-controlled rural areas.  He first attacked and pillaged [[Villaseca de la Sagra]], then faced Zúñiga again in an inconclusive battle near the [[Tagus river]] in [[Illescas, Toledo|Illescas]].&lt;ref name=&quot;perez122&quot;&gt;[[#Per01|Pérez 2001]], p. 122.&lt;/ref&gt;  Light skirmishing near Toledo would continue until news of Villalar ended the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;perez122&quot; /&gt;

==Battle of Villalar==
{{main|Battle of Villalar}}
[[File:BatallaDeVillalar.jpg|right|thumb|300px|alt=Soldiers and cannon on the battlefield; an officer on a white horse points to direct his men.|A 19th century work by [[Manuel Picolo López]] depicting the [[Battle of Villalar]]]]
In early April 1521, the royalist side moved to combine their armies and threaten Torrelobatón.  The [[Constable of Castile]] moved his troops (including soldiers recently transferred from the defense of Navarre) southwest from Burgos to meet with the [[Fadrique Enríquez|Admiral]]'s forces near Tordesillas.&lt;ref name=&quot;perez110&quot; /&gt;  Meanwhile, the comuneros reinforced their troops at Torrelobatón, which was far less secure than the comuneros preferred.  Their forces were suffering from desertions, and the presence of royalist artillery would make Torrelobatón's castle vulnerable.  [[Juan López de Padilla|Juan de Padilla]] considered withdrawing to [[Toro, Spain|Toro]] to seek reinforcements in early April, but wavered.  He delayed his decision until the early hours of April 23, losing considerable time and allowing the royalists to unite their forces in [[Peñaflor de Hornija|Peñaflor]].&lt;ref name=&quot;seaver324&quot;&gt;[[#Sea28|Seaver 1928]], p. 324&amp;ndash;325.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;perezorig313&quot;&gt;[[#Per70|Pérez 1970]], p. 313&amp;ndash;314.&lt;/ref&gt;

The combined royalist army pursued the comuneros. Again, the royalists had a strong advantage in cavalry, with their army consisting of 6,000 infantry and 2,400 cavalry against Padilla's 7,000 infantry and 400 cavalry.  Heavy rain slowed Padilla's infantry more than the royalist cavalry and rendered the primitive firearms of the rebels' 1,000 [[arquebusiers]] nearly useless.&lt;ref name=&quot;seaver324&quot; /&gt;  Padilla hoped to reach the relative safety of Toro and the heights of [[Vega de Valdetronco]], but his infantry was too slow.  He gave battle with the harrying royalist cavalry at the town of Villalar.  The cavalry charges scattered the rebel ranks, and the battle became a slaughter.  There were an estimated 500&amp;ndash;1,000 rebel casualties and many desertions.&lt;ref name=&quot;perezorig313&quot; /&gt;

The three most important leaders of the rebellion were captured: [[Juan López de Padilla|Juan de Padilla]], [[Juan Bravo (rebel)|Juan Bravo]], and [[Francisco Maldonado]].  They were beheaded the next morning in the Plaza of Villalar, with a large portion of the royalist nobility present.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Per01|Pérez 2001]], p. 111.&lt;/ref&gt;  The remains of the rebel army at Villalar fragmented, with some attempting to join Acuña's army near Toledo and others deserting.  The rebellion had been struck a crippling blow.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 204.&lt;/ref&gt;

==End of the war==
After the Battle of Villalar, the towns of [[Old Castile|northern Castile]] soon succumbed to the king's troops, with all its cities returning their allegiance to the king by early May.  Only Madrid and Toledo kept their ''Comunidades'' alive.&lt;ref name=&quot;seaver339&quot; /&gt;

===Resistance of Toledo===
[[File:Doña María Pacheco después de Villalar (Museo del Prado).jpg|thumb|right|300px|alt=A woman rests her head in her hand while sitting at a table; a knight in armor and others stand by having told her the bad news.|[[María Pacheco]] receives notice of the death of her husband at Villalar.  The painting is a 19th-century work by [[Vicente Borrás]].]]

The first news of Villalar arrived in Toledo on April 26, but was largely ignored by the local ''Comunidad''. The magnitude of the defeat became apparent in a few days, after the first survivors began arriving in the city and confirmed the fact that the three rebel leaders had been executed.  Toledo was declared in mourning over the death of Juan de Padilla.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Per01|Pérez 2001]], p. 123.&lt;/ref&gt;

After the death of Padilla, [[Antonio de Acuña|Bishop Acuña]] lost popularity in favour of [[María Pacheco]], Padilla's widow.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Per01|Pérez 2001]], p. 128.&lt;/ref&gt;  People began to suggest negotiating with the royalists, seeking to avoid further suffering in the city.  The situation looked even worse after the surrender of Madrid on May 11.&lt;ref name=&quot;seaver339&quot;&gt;[[#Sea28|Seaver 1928]], p. 339.&lt;/ref&gt;  The fall of Toledo seemed only to be a matter of time.&lt;ref name=&quot;seaver339&quot; /&gt;

However, one ray of hope remained for the rebels.  Castile had withdrawn some of its troops from occupied [[Kingdom of Navarre|Navarre]] to fight the comuneros, and [[Francis I of France|King Francis I of France]] used the opportunity to [[Spanish conquest of Iberian Navarre#1521 French invasion|invade with support from the Navarrese]].  The royalist army was forced to march on Navarre to respond rather than besiege Toledo.  Acuña left Toledo to travel to Navarre, but he was recognized and caught.  It is disputed whether he was seeking to join the French and continue fighting, or was simply fleeing.&lt;ref name=&quot;seaver336&quot;&gt;[[#Sea28|Seaver 1928]], p. 336.&lt;/ref&gt;

María Pacheco took control of the city and the remains of the rebel army, living in the [[Alcázar of Toledo|Alcázar]], collecting taxes, and strengthening defenses.  She requested the intervention of her uncle, the respected [[Diego López Pacheco|Marquis of Villena]], to negotiate with the Royal Council, hoping he would be able to obtain better concessions.  The Marquis eventually abandoned the negotiations, and María Pacheco took on personal negotiations with [[Antonio de Zúñiga|Prior Zúñiga]], the commander of the besieging forces.  Her demands, though somewhat galling to honor, were ultimately minor, such as guaranteeing the property and reputation of her children.&lt;ref name=&quot;seaver346&quot;&gt;[[#Sea28|Seaver 1928]], p. 346&amp;ndash;347.&lt;/ref&gt;

Still concerned about the French, the royal government gave in.  With the support of all parties, the surrender of Toledo was orchestrated on October 25, 1521.  Thus, on October 31 the comuneros left the Alcázar of Toledo and new officials were appointed to run the city.  The truce guaranteed the freedom and property of all the comuneros.&lt;ref name=&quot;seaver346&quot; /&gt;

===Revolt of February 1522===
The new administrator of Toledo restored order and brought the city back under royal control.  However, he also provoked former comuneros.&lt;ref name=&quot;Perez131&quot;&gt;[[#Per01|Pérez 2001]], p. 131.&lt;/ref&gt;  María Pacheco continued her presence in the city and refused to hand over all the hidden weapons until Charles V personally signed the agreements reached with the Order of St. John.  This unstable situation came to an end on February 3, 1522, when the generous terms of the surrender were annulled.   Royal soldiers filled the city and the administrator ordered Pacheco's execution.&lt;ref name=&quot;Perez131&quot; /&gt;  Riots broke out in protest.  The incident was temporarily remedied thanks to the intervention of María de Mendoza, the sister of María Pacheco.  Another truce was granted, and while the former comuneros were defeated, the distraction was exploited by María Pacheco to escape to Portugal disguised as a farmer.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Sea28|Seaver 1928]], p. 348.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Pardon of 1522===
Charles V returned to Spain on July 16, 1522.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Sea28|Seaver 1928]], p. 350.&lt;/ref&gt;  Acts of repression and retaliation against former comuneros did occur, but only sporadically.  Embarrassingly large numbers of important people had supported the comuneros, or at least were suspiciously slow to declare allegiance to the king, and Charles thought it unwise to press the issue too much.&lt;ref name=&quot;haliczer212&quot;&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 212.&lt;/ref&gt;

Back in Valladolid, Charles declared a [[Pardon|general pardon]] on November 1.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Per01|Pérez 2001]], p. 136.&lt;/ref&gt;  The pardon gave amnesty to everyone involved in the revolt with the exception of 293 comuneros, a small figure given the huge number of rebels.  Both Pacheco and Bishop Acuña were among the 293 excluded from the pardon.  More pardons were issued later, after pressure from the Cortes; by 1527, the repression was completely at end.  Of the 293, 23 were executed, 20 died in prison, 50 purchased amnesty, and 100 were pardoned later.  The fates of the rest are unknown.&lt;ref name=&quot;haliczer212&quot; /&gt;

==Aftermath==
[[María Pacheco]] successfully escaped to Portugal, where she lived in exile the remaining ten years of her life.  [[Antonio de Acuña|Bishop Acuña]], captured in Navarre, was stripped of his ecclesiastical standing and executed after he killed a guard while trying to escape.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Sea28|Seaver 1928]], p. 357.&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Pedro Téllez-Girón, 3rd Count of Ureña|Pedro Girón]] received a pardon conditional on him going into exile to [[Oran#Spanish period|Oran]] in North Africa, where he served as a commander against the Moors.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Sea28|Seaver 1928]], p. 354.&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Joanna of Castile|Queen Joanna]] was locked in Tordesillas by her son.  She would remain there for thirty-five years, the rest of her life.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Sea28|Seaver 1928]], p. 359.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Charles V, Holy Roman Emperor|Emperor Charles V]] would go on to rule one of the largest and most sprawling empires in European history.  As a consequence, Charles was nearly constantly at war, fighting [[Italian War of 1521–1526|France]], [[War of the League of Cognac|England]], the [[Sack of Rome (1527)|Papal States]], the [[Ottoman–Habsburg wars|Ottoman Turks]], the [[Spanish conquest of the Aztec Empire|Aztecs]], the [[Spanish conquest of the Inca Empire|Incas]], and the Protestant [[Schmalkaldic War|Schmalkaldic League]] during his reign.  Spain would provide the bulk of the Habsburgs' armies and financial resources over this period.  Charles placed Castilians in high governmental positions in both Castile and the Empire at large, and generally left the administration of Castile in Castilian hands.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lynch46&quot; /&gt;  In that sense, the revolt could be considered successful.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lynch46&quot;&gt;[[#Lyn64|Lynch 1964]], p. 46.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some of the reforms of [[Isabella I of Castile|Isabella I]] which reduced noble power were reversed as a price for luring the nobility to the royalist side.  However, Charles understood that noble encroachment of power had helped cause the revolt, and embarked upon a new reform program.  Unpopular, corrupt, and ineffective officials were replaced; judicial functions of the [[Council of Castile|Royal Council]] were limited; and local courts were revitalized.&lt;ref name=&quot;Halp213&quot; /&gt;  Charles also adjusted the membership of the Royal Council; its [[Antonio de Rojas|hated president]] was replaced, the aristocracy's role reduced, and more gentry were added to it.&lt;ref name=&quot;Halp213&quot;&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 213.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Lyn64|Lynch 1964]], p. 48.&lt;/ref&gt;  Realizing that the urban elite needed to have a stake in the royal government once more, Charles gave many of them positions, privileges, and government salaries.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 218.  The program was called &quot;Stewards and gentlemen,&quot; and about 400 well-paid positions were handed out.&lt;/ref&gt;  The Cortes, while not as important as the comuneros had hoped, nevertheless maintained its power; it was still required to approve new taxes and could advise the king.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 220.&lt;/ref&gt;  Charles also discouraged his officials from using overly coercive methods, after seeing his heavy-handed treatment of the Cortes of Corunna backfire.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 223.&lt;/ref&gt;  If anything, the co-option of the middle class worked too well; when Charles' successor [[Philip II of Spain|King Phillip II]] demanded a ruinously large tax increase in the 1580s, the Cortes was too dependent on the Crown for money to effectively resist policies that would wreck the economy.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 227.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Later influence==
[[File:El Empecinado de Goya.jpeg|thumb|right|alt=A soldier in a 19th-century military uniform.|[[Juan Martín Díez]], &quot;''El Empecinado''&quot; (&quot;The Undaunted&quot;), who tried to rehabilitate the reputation of the comuneros in 1821]]
The revolt, fresh in the memory of Spain, is referenced in several literary works during [[Spanish Golden Age|Spain's Golden Age]].  [[Don Quixote]] references the rebellion in a conversation with [[Sancho Panza|Sancho]], and [[Francisco de Quevedo]] uses the word &quot;comunero&quot; as a synonym for &quot;rebel&quot; in his works.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Cervantes |first=Miguel de |authorlink=Miguel de Cervantes |title=Don Quixote de la Mancha |url=http://users.ipfw.edu/jehle/cervante/dqfj4.htm |accessdate=2008-09-27 |publisher=Rodolfo Schevill and Adolfo Bonilla; digital form and editing by Fred F. Jehle |language=Spanish |chapter=Volume 2, Chapter 43 |page=61 |year=1615 |isbn=0-394-90892-9 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Per01|Pérez 2001]], p. 236.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 18th century, the comuneros were not held in high regard by the [[Spanish Empire]].  The government was not amenable to encouraging rebellions, and only used the term to condemn opposition.  In the [[Revolt of the Comuneros (Paraguay)|Revolt of the Comuneros in Paraguay]], the rebels did not take the name willingly; it was only meant to disparage them as traitors.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Colonial History of Paraguay: The Revolt of the Comuneros, 1721-1735 |last=López |first=Adalberto |year=2005 |publisher=Transaction Publishers |isbn=0-87073-124-6|page=12 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Another [[Revolt of the Comuneros (New Granada)|Revolt of the Comuneros in New Granada]] (modern Colombia) was similarly unrelated to the original except in name.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= Military reform and society in New Granada, 1773-1808 |last=Kuethe |first=Allan J. |authorlink=Allan J. Kuethe |year=1978 |publisher=University Presses of Florida |pages=79–101 |isbn= 0-8130-0570-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

At the beginning of the 19th century, the image of the comuneros began to be rehabilitated by scholars such as Manuel Quintana as precursors of freedom and martyrs against [[Absolutism (European history)|absolutism]].&lt;ref&gt;[[#Per01|Pérez 2001]], p. 238.&lt;/ref&gt;  The decline of Castilian liberty was linked to the later decline of Spain.&lt;ref name=&quot;nietoviahal&quot;&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 7.  Haliczer is citing [[#Nie73|Gutiérrez Nieto 1973]], p. 57&amp;ndash;58 for Quintana's views; p. 84 for Danvila's views; and p. 98 for Marañón's views.&lt;/ref&gt;  The first major commemorative event came in 1821, the third [[wikt:centenary|centenary]] of the [[Battle of Villalar]].  [[Juan Martín Díez]], a nationalistic liberal military leader who had fought in the [[Peninsular war#Guerrilla war|resistance against Napoleon]], led an expedition to find and exhume the remains of the three leaders executed in 1521.  Díez praised the comuneros on behalf of the [[Trienio Liberal|liberal government in power at the time]], likely the first positive governmental recognition for their cause.  This view was challenged by conservatives who viewed a centralized state as modern and progressive, especially after the anarchy and fragmentation of the [[Glorious Revolution (Spain)|1868 Revolution in Spain]].&lt;ref name=&quot;nietoviahal&quot; /&gt;  [[Manuel Danvila]], a conservative government minister, published the six-volume ''Historia critica y documentada de las Comunidades de Castilla'' from 1897&amp;ndash;1900, one of the most important works of scholarship on the revolt.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Sea28|Seaver 1928]], p. 376.&lt;/ref&gt;  Drawing on collected original sources, Danvila emphasized the fiscal demands of the comuneros, and cast them as traditionalist, reactionary, medieval, and feudal.&lt;ref name=&quot;nietoviahal&quot; /&gt;  Though a liberal, intellectual [[Gregorio Marañón]] shared the dim view of the comuneros that again prevailed in Spain; he cast the conflict as one between a modern, progressive state open to beneficent foreign influence against a conservative, reactionary, and xenophobic Spain hypersensitive to religious and cultural deviance with an insistence on spurious racial purity.&lt;ref name=&quot;nietoviahal&quot; /&gt;

[[File:Monolito-villalar.jpg|thumb|left|alt=People celebrating.|A floral offering at Villalar, on [[Castile and León Day]], April 23, 2006]]

[[Francisco Franco|General Franco]]'s government from 1939&amp;ndash;1975 also encouraged an unfavorable interpretation of the comuneros.&lt;ref name=&quot;clavero&quot; /&gt;  According to approved historians such as [[José María Pemán]], the revolt was fundamentally an issue of petty [[Nationalisms and regionalisms of Spain|Spanish regionalism]], something which Franco did his best to discourage.  Additionally, the comuneros did not properly appreciate Spain's &quot;imperial destiny.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Nie73|Gutiérrez Nieto 1973]], p. 96.  Nieto is referring to Pemán's ''Breve Historia a España'', p. 208&amp;ndash;211.&lt;/ref&gt;

Since the mid-twentieth century, others have sought more materialist reasons for the revolt.  Historians such as [[José Antonio Maravall]] and [[Joseph Pérez]] portray the developing revolt as alliances of different social coalitions around shifting economic interests, with the &quot;industrial bourgeoisie&quot; of artisans and woolworkers combining with the intellectuals and the low nobility against the aristocrats and the merchants.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 8.  Haliczer is citing [[#Per70|Pérez 1970]], p. 19.&lt;/ref&gt;  Maravall, who views the revolt as one of the first modern revolutions, especially stresses the ideological conflict and intellectual nature of the revolt, with features such as the first proposed written constitution of Castile.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Hal81|Haliczer 1981]], p. 8.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Pendón gigante en la Plaza Mayor de Villalar.jpg|thumb|right|alt=People at a celebration holding a huge purple flag.  Others wave different flags, such as the Cross of Burgundy or the modern flag of Castile and León.|The April 23, 2007 gathering at Villalar.  Villalar was renamed [[Villalar de los Comuneros]] in 1932, under the liberal [[Second Spanish Republic|Second Republic]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cadenaser.com/espana/articulo/20000-personas-celebran-villalar-fiesta/csrcsrpor/20040423csrcsrnac_12/Tes |title=20.000 personas celebran en Villalar la fiesta de Castilla y León |accessdate=2008-11-12 |publisher=[[Cadena SER]] |language=Spanish |date=2004-04-23 }}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
With [[Spanish transition to democracy|Spain's transition to democracy]] following Franco's death, celebration of the comuneros started to become permissible again.  On April 23, 1976, a small ceremony was held clandestinely in Villalar; only two years later, in 1978, the event had become a huge demonstration of 200,000 in support of Castilian autonomy.&lt;ref name=&quot;clavero&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |last=González Clavero |first=Mariano |year=2002 |title=Fuerzas políticas en el proceso autonómico de Castilla y León: 1975-1983 |journal=Biblioteca Virtual Miguel de Cervantes |language=Spanish |pages=337–342 |url=http://www.cervantesvirtual.com/FichaObra.html?Ref=12030&amp;portal=33 |accessdate=2008-11-12 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[Autonomous communities of Spain|autonomous community]] of [[Castile and León]] was created in response to public demand in 1983, and it recognized April 23 as an [[Castile and León Day|official holiday]] in 1986.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.boe.es/g/es/bases_datos/doc.php?coleccion=iberlex&amp;id=1986/90009&amp;codmap |title=Ley por la que se declara Fiesta de la Comunidad de Castilla y León el día 23 de abril |accessdate=2008-10-18   |date=1986-04-17 |publisher=[[Boletín Oficial del Estado]] |location=Madrid |language=Spanish }}&lt;/ref&gt;  Similarly, each February 3 since 1988 has been celebrated by the [[Castilian nationalism|Castilian nationalist]] party [[Tierra Comunera]] in Toledo.  The celebration highlights the roles of [[Juan López de Padilla|Juan de Padilla]] and [[María Pacheco]], and is done in memory of the rebellion in 1522, the last event of the war.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url = http://www.tierracomunera.org/es/contenido/?iddoc=6043 |title = Toledo celebra el XX Homenaje a los Comuneros |publisher=[[Tierra Comunera]] |accessdate = 2008-07-25 |language=Spanish }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[List of people associated with the Revolt of the Comuneros]]
* [[Military history of the Revolt of the Comuneros]]
* [[Revolt of the Brotherhoods]]
* [[Spanish conquest of Iberian Navarre]]
* [[Italian War of 1521–1526]]

==Footnotes==
{{refbegin}}

&lt;ol type=&quot;a&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;{{Note label|A|a|none}} This article uses the term &quot;tax&quot; to encompass a variety of revenue-raising methods the government used.  Briefly, ''servicios'' were flat monetary grants paid to the treasury; the ''encabezamiento'' was a portion of the sales tax towns collected sent to the government; and the ''cruzada'' (&quot;crusade&quot;) was a special and semi-voluntary contribution that counted as an [[indulgence]] and was generally used for war against the Muslims.  Charles wanted to abolish the lenient ''encabezamiento'' and return to an older and harsher system of direct royal control of tolls, pasturage fees, and the like.  He also requested large ''servicios'' at the Cortes he held.  Part of the revenue problem the government had was that income from the ''cruzada'' had fallen greatly since the [[Reconquista]] had finished in 1492.&lt;ref name=&quot;hal147&quot; /&gt;
&lt;li&gt; {{Note label|B|b|none}} ''[[wikt:junta|Junta]]'', meaning &quot;Congress&quot; or &quot;Assembly,&quot; did not yet have the negative connotation of &quot;Oligarchical military dictatorship&quot; in the 16th century.
&lt;li&gt; {{Note label|C|c|none}} There exists a theory that [[Pedro Téllez-Girón, 3rd Count of Ureña|Girón]]'s errors were in fact an intentional betrayal of the comuneros.  Considering his moderate stance and later pardon by the government, historians such as [[#Sea28|Seaver]] consider this possible, but unlikely.&lt;ref name=&quot;seaver200&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

==References==
* This article incorporates text translated from the [[Spanish Wikipedia]] article [[:es:Guerra de las Comunidades de Castilla|''Guerra de las Comunidades de Castilla'']], licensed under the {{srlink|Wikipedia:Text of the GNU Free Documentation License|GFDL}}.
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

===Bibliography===
English language sources:{{refbegin}}

* {{cite book |last=Haliczer |first=Stephen |authorlink=Stephen Haliczer |title=The Comuneros of Castile: The Forging of a Revolution, 1475-1521 |year=1981 |publisher=[[University of Wisconsin Press]] |location=Madison, Wisconsin |isbn=0-299-08500-7 |ref=Hal81 }}
* {{cite book |last=Lynch |first=John |authorlink=John Lynch (historian) |title=Spain under the Habsburgs |volume=(vol. 1) |year=1964 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=New York |isbn= |ref=Lyn64 }}
* {{cite book |last=Miller |first=Townsend |title=The Castles and the Crown |year=1963 |publisher=Coward-McCann |location=New York |isbn= |ref=Mil63 }}
* {{cite book |last=Seaver |first=Henry Latimer |title=The Great Revolt in Castile: A Study of the Comunero Movement of 1520-1521 |origyear=1928 |year=1966 |publisher=Octagon Books |location=New York |ref=Sea28 }}
{{refend}}
Spanish and other language sources:{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book |last=Díez |first=José Luis |title=Los Comuneros de Castilla |year=1977 |publisher=Editorial Mañana |location=Madrid |language= Spanish |isbn=84-7421-025-9 |oclc=4188611 |ref=Die77 }}
* {{cite book |title=El obispo Acuña: Historia de un comunero |last=Guilarte |first=Alfonso María |year=1983 |publisher=Ambito |location=Valladolid |language=Spanish |isbn=84-86047-13-7 |ref=Gui83}}
* {{cite book |last=Maravall |first=José Antonio |authorlink=José Antonio Maravall |title=Las comunidades de Castilla: Una primera revolución moderna |date= |year=1963 |publisher=Revista de Occidente |location=Madrid |language=Spanish |isbn= |oclc=2182035 |ref=Mar63 }}
* {{cite book |last=Gutiérrez Nieto |first=Juan Ignacio |title=Las comunidades como movimiento antiseñorial: La formación del bando realista en la Guerra Civil Castellana de 1520-1521 |year=1973 |publisher=Editorial Planeta |location=Barcelona |language=Spanish |oclc= 	862423  |ref=Nie73 }} &lt;!-- Alphabetizing this under &quot;Nieto&quot; not &quot;Gut-&quot; here.--&gt;
* {{cite book |last=Pérez |first=Joseph |authorlink=Joseph Pérez |title=La révolution des &quot;Comunidades&quot; de Castille, 1520-1521 |origyear=1970 |year=1998 |publisher=Institut d'études ibériques et ibéro-américaines de l'Université de Bordeaux |location=Bordeaux |language=French |isbn=84-323-0285-6 |ref=Per70 }}
* {{cite book |title=Los Comuneros |last=Pérez |first=Joseph |authorlink=Joseph Pérez |year=2001 |publisher=La Esfera de los Libros, S.L. |location=Madrid |language=Spanish |isbn=84-9734-003-5 |ref=Per01 }}
{{refend}}

{{SpanishRevoltsAgainstCharlesI }}

[[Category:1520s conflicts]]
[[Category:1520s in Spain]]
[[Category:Wars involving Spain]]
[[Category:Revolutions in Spain]]
[[Category:16th-century rebellions]]
[[Category:Charles V, Holy Roman Emperor]]
[[Category:Rebellions in Spain]]</text>
      <sha1>d4z8j3wrzicb4czdamrr6caece9vvde</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
