<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Roman–Parthian War of 58–63</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>17843642</id>
    <revision>
      <id>747764768</id>
      <parentid>747685915</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-04T07:02:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cplakidas</username>
        <id>613068</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>rv - only article title is bolded</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="36592">{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Roman–Parthian war over Armenia
|image= 
|caption=
|partof=the [[Roman–Parthian Wars]]
|date= 58–63 AD
|place=[[Kingdom of Armenia (antiquity)|Armenia]]
|territory=Minor gains for the Roman [[client state]]s
|result=[[Treaty of Rhandeia]]&lt;br&gt;[[Arsacid Dynasty of Armenia|Arsacids]] established on Armenian throne as Roman clients
|combatant1={{flag|Roman Empire}}&lt;br&gt;Roman Vassals:&lt;br&gt;[[Sophene]], [[Lesser Armenia]],&lt;br&gt;[[Caucasian Iberia|Iberia]], [[Commagene]], [[Pontus]]
|combatant2={{flagicon|Armenia}} [[Kingdom of Armenia (antiquity)|Kingdom of Armenia]]&lt;br&gt;[[Parthian Empire]]
|commander1=[[Gnaeus Domitius Corbulo]]&lt;br&gt;[[Tigranes VI of Armenia]]&lt;br&gt;[[Lucius Caesennius Paetus]] 
|commander2=[[Tiridates I of Armenia]]&lt;br&gt;[[Vologases I of Parthia]]
|strength1=
|strength2=
|casualties1=
|casualties2=
}}
{{Campaignbox Roman-Parthian Wars}}
{{Campaignbox Armenian Wars}}
{{History of Armenia|expanded=age2}}
The '''Roman–Parthian War of 58–63''' was fought between the [[Roman Empire]] and the [[Parthian Empire]] over control of [[Kingdom of Armenia (antiquity)|Armenia]], a vital [[buffer state]] between the two realms. Armenia had been a Roman client state since the days of Emperor [[Augustus]], but in 52/53, the Parthians succeeded in installing their own candidate, [[Tiridates I of Armenia|Tiridates]], on the Armenian throne.

These events coincided with the accession of [[Nero]] to the imperial throne in Rome, and the young emperor decided to react vigorously. The war, which was the only major foreign campaign of his reign, began with rapid success for the Roman forces, led by the able general [[Gnaeus Domitius Corbulo]]. They overcame the forces loyal to Tiridates, installed their own candidate, [[Tigranes VI of Armenia|Tigranes VI]], on the Armenian throne, and left the country. The Romans were aided by the fact that the Parthian king [[Vologases I of Parthia|Vologases]] was embroiled in the suppression of a [[Hyrcania#Arsacid era|series of revolts]] in his own country. As soon as these had been dealt with, however, the Parthians turned their attention to Armenia, and after a couple of years of inconclusive campaigning, inflicted a heavy defeat on the Romans in the [[Battle of Rhandeia]].

The conflict ended soon after, in an effective stalemate and a formal compromise: a Parthian prince of the [[Arsacid Dynasty of Armenia|Arsacid]] line would henceforth sit on the Armenian throne, but his nomination had to be approved by the [[Roman emperor]].&lt;ref name=Bivar85&gt;Bivar (1968), p. 85&lt;/ref&gt; This conflict was the first direct confrontation between Parthia and the Romans since [[Crassus]]' [[Battle of Carrhae|disastrous expedition]] and [[Mark Antony]]'s [[Antony's Parthian War|campaigns]] a century earlier, and would be the first of a long series of wars between Rome and Iranian powers over Armenia (see [[Roman–Persian Wars]]).&lt;ref name=Bivar80&gt;Bivar (1968), p. 80&lt;/ref&gt;

== Background ==
Ever since the expanding [[Roman Republic]] and the [[Parthian Empire]] had come into contact in the mid-1st century BC, there had been friction between the two great powers over the control of the various states lying between them. The largest and most important of these was the [[Kingdom of Armenia (antiquity)|Kingdom of Armenia]]. In 20 BC, [[Augustus]] succeeded in establishing a Roman [[protectorate]] over the country, when [[Tigranes III]] was enthroned as king of Armenia. Roman influence was secured through a series of Roman-sponsored kings until 37 AD, when a Parthian-supported candidate, [[Orodes of Armenia|Orodes]], assumed the throne. The Roman-supported king, [[Mithridates of Armenia|Mithridates]], recovered his throne with the support of Emperor [[Claudius]] in 42 AD,&lt;ref name=Bivar76&gt;Bivar (1968), p. 76&lt;/ref&gt; but was deposed in 51 AD by his nephew [[Rhadamistus]] of [[Caucasian Iberia|Iberia]]. His rule quickly became unpopular however, and this gave the newly crowned king [[Vologases I of Parthia]] the opportunity to intervene.&lt;ref name=Bivar79&gt;Bivar (1968), p. 79&lt;/ref&gt; His forces quickly seized the two capitals of Armenia, [[Artaxata]] and [[Tigranocerta]], and put his younger brother [[Tiridates I of Armenia|Tiridates]] on the throne. The onset of a bitter winter and the outbreak of an epidemic forced the Parthians forces to withdraw, allowing Rhadamistus to retake control of the country.&lt;ref name=Bivar79&gt;Bivar (1968), p. 79&lt;/ref&gt; His behavior towards his subjects, however, was even worse than before, and they rose in rebellion against him. Thus in 54 AD Rhadamistus fled to his father's court in Iberia, and Tiridates re-established himself in Armenia.&lt;ref name=Bivar80/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 12#50|XII.50–51]]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the same year, in Rome, Emperor [[Claudius]] died and was succeeded by his stepson [[Nero]]. The Parthian encroachment in an area regarded as lying within the Roman sphere of influence worried the Roman leadership, and was widely seen as a major test of the new emperor's ability.&lt;ref name=Annales-xiii-6&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 13#6|XIII.6]]&lt;/ref&gt; Nero reacted vigorously, appointing [[Gnaeus Domitius Corbulo]], a general who had distinguished himself in [[Germania]] and now served as governor of [[Asia (Roman province)|Asia]], to supreme command in the East.&lt;ref&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 13#7|XIII.7–8]]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Diplomatic maneuvers and preparations ==
[[File:Roman East 50-en.svg|thumb|right|300px|Armenia and the Roman East in ca. 50 AD, before the outbreak of the war.]]
Corbulo was given control over two provinces, [[Cappadocia (Roman province)|Cappadocia]] and [[Galatia (Roman province)|Galatia]] (modern-day central [[Turkey]]), with [[propraetor]]ial  and later [[proconsul]]ar authority or ''[[imperium]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Goldsworthy (2007), p. 309&lt;/ref&gt; Although Galatia was considered a good recruiting-ground and Cappadocia had a few units of [[Roman auxiliaries|auxiliaries]], the bulk of his army came from [[Syria (Roman province)|Syria]], where half the garrison of four [[Roman legion|legions]] and several units of auxiliaries was transferred to his command.&lt;ref name=Annales-xiii-8&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 13#8|XIII.8]]&lt;/ref&gt;

Initially, the Romans hoped to resolve the situation by diplomatic means: Corbulo and [[Gaius Durmius Ummidius Quadratus|Ummidius Quadratus]], the governor of Syria, both sent embassies to Vologases, proposing that he give up hostages, as was customary during negotiations, to ensure good faith.&lt;ref&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 13#9|XIII.9]]&lt;/ref&gt; Vologases, himself preoccupied by the revolt of his son [[Vardanes II of Parthia|Vardanes]] which forced him to withdrew his troops from Armenia, readily complied.&lt;ref&gt;Bivar (1968), p. 81&lt;/ref&gt; A period of inactivity ensued, while the Armenian issue remained in limbo. Corbulo used this lull to restore his troops' discipline and combat readiness, which had diminished in the peaceful garrisons of the East.&lt;ref&gt;Goldsworthy (2007), p. 311&lt;/ref&gt; According to Tacitus, Corbulo discharged all who were old or in ill health, kept the entire army under canvas in the harsh winters of the [[Anatolian plateau]] to acclimatize them to the snows of Armenia, and enforced a strict discipline, punishing deserters by death. At the same time however, he took care to be constantly present amongst his men, sharing their hardships.&lt;ref&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 13#35|XIII.35]]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the meantime, Tiridates, backed by his brother, refused to go to Rome, and even engaged in operations against those Armenians whom he deemed were loyal to Rome.&lt;ref name=Annales-xiii-37&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 13#37|XIII.37]]&lt;/ref&gt; Tension mounted and finally, in the early spring of 58, war broke out.

== Outbreak of the war &amp;mdash; The Roman offensive ==
Corbulo had placed a large number of his auxiliaries in a line of forts near the Armenian frontier under a former ''[[primus pilus]]'', Paccius Orfitus. Disobeying Corbulo's orders, he used some newly arrived auxiliary cavalry ''[[Ala (Roman military)|alae]]'' to stage a raid against the Armenians, who appeared to be unprepared. In the event, his raid failed, and the retreating troops even spread their panic amongst the garrisons of the other forts.&lt;ref name=Annales-xiii-36&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 13#36|XIII.36]]&lt;/ref&gt; It was an inauspicious start for a campaign, and Corbulo severely punished the survivors and their commanders.&lt;ref name=&quot;Annales-xiii-36&quot;/&gt;

Having drilled his army for two years Corbulo, despite this misadventure, was ready. He had three legions at his disposal ([[Legio III Gallica|III ''Gallica'']] and [[Legio VI Ferrata|VI ''Ferrata'']] from Syria and [[Legio IV Scythica|IV ''Scythica'']]),&lt;ref&gt;Goldsworthy (2007), p. 312&lt;/ref&gt; to which were added a large number of auxiliaries and allied contingents from Eastern client kings like [[Aristobulus of Chalcis|Aristobulus]] of [[Lesser Armenia]] and [[Polemon II of Pontus]]. The situation was furthermore favorable to the Romans: Vologases faced a serious revolt by the [[Hyrcania]]ns in the region of the [[Caspian Sea]] as well as incursions of [[Dahae]] and [[Sacae]] nomads from [[Central Asia]], and was unable to support his brother.&lt;ref name=Annales-xiii-37/&gt;

The war thus far had featured mostly skirmishing along the Roman–Armenian border. Corbulo tried to protect the pro-Roman Armenian settlements from attack, and simultaneously retaliated against the Parthians' supporters. Given that Tiridates avoided confrontation in a pitched battle, Corbulo divided his force, so that they could attack several places simultaneously, and instructed his allies, Kings [[Antiochus IV of Commagene|Antiochus IV]] of [[Commagene]] and [[Pharsman I of Iberia|Pharasmanes I]] of [[Caucasian Iberia|Iberia]] to raid Armenia from their own territories. In addition, an alliance was concluded with the [[Mushki|Moschoi]], a tribe living in northwestern Armenia.&lt;ref name=&quot;Annales-xiii-37&quot;/&gt;

Tiridates reacted by sending envoys to ask why he was under attack, since hostages had been given. To this, Corbulo reiterated the demand to seek the recognition of his crown from Nero.&lt;ref name=&quot;Annales-xiii-37&quot;/&gt; Eventually, the two sides agreed on a meeting. Tiridates announced that he would bring 1,000 men to the meeting, implying that Corbulo should bring the same number of men &quot;in peaceful fashion, without breastplates and helmets&quot;. Tacitus suggests that Tiridates intended to overwhelm the Romans, as the Parthian cavalry would be superior to an equal number of Roman infantry in any case.&lt;ref name=Annales-xiii-38&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 13#38|XIII.38]]&lt;/ref&gt; At any rate, in a show of force Corbulo decided to take with him the larger part of his force, not only IV ''Ferrata'', but also 3,000 men from III ''Gallica'' plus the auxiliaries.&lt;ref name=Annales-xiii-38/&gt; Tiridates also appeared at the agreed site, but, seeing the Romans in full battle array, and in turn distrusting their intentions, he did not come closer and withdrew during the night.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 13#39|XIII.39]]&lt;/ref&gt; Tiridates then resorted to a tactic that had worked well a century earlier against [[Antony's Parthian War|Mark Antony]]: he sent forces to raid the Roman army's supply route, which stretched over the mountains back to [[Trabzon|Trapezus]] in the Black Sea. They failed however, since the Romans had taken care to secure the mountain routes by a series of forts.&lt;ref&gt;Goldsworthy (2007), p. 314&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Fall of Artaxata ===
[[File:Roman-Parthian War 58-60.svg|thumb|right|300px|Operations during the first two years of the war: Corbulo's invasion and conquest of Armenia.]]
Corbulo now resolved to directly attack Tiridates' fortified strongholds. Not only were they instrumental in controlling the surrounding country and sources of revenue and soldiers, but in addition, a threat to them might force Tiridates to risk a pitched battle, since, in the words of historian A. Goldsworthy, &quot;a king who could not defend communities loyal to him [...] lost prestige.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Goldsworthy (2007), p. 315&lt;/ref&gt; Corbulo and his subordinates successfully stormed three of these forts, including Volandum (possibly modern [[Iğdır]]),&lt;ref name=&quot;Southern301&quot;&gt;Southern (2007), p. 301&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;the strongest of all in that province&quot; according to Tacitus, within a day with minimal casualties, and massacred their garrisons. Terrified by this display of Roman might, several towns and villages surrendered, and the Romans prepared to move against the northern Armenian capital, [[Artaxata]].&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;/&gt;

This forced Tiridates to confront the Romans with his army, as they approached Artaxata. The Roman force, reinforced by a ''[[vexillatio]]'' of [[Legio X Fretensis|X ''Fretensis'']], marched in a [[infantry square|hollow square]], with the legions supported by auxiliary horsemen and foot archers. The Roman soldiers were under strict orders not to break formation, and despite repeated probing attacks and [[Parthian shot|feigned retreats]] by the Parthian horse archers, they held together until nightfall.&lt;ref&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 13#40|XIII.40]]&lt;/ref&gt; During the night, Tiridates withdrew his army, abandoning his capital; its inhabitants promptly surrendered and were allowed to leave unmolested, but the city was torched, since the Romans could not spare sufficient men for garrisoning it.&lt;ref&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 13#41|XIII.41]]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Fall of Tigranocerta ===
In 59, the Romans marched to the south, towards [[Tigranocerta]], Armenia's second capital city. On their way, Corbulo's men punished those who withstood or hid from them, while leniency was shown to those who surrendered.&lt;ref&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 14#23|XIV.23]]&lt;/ref&gt; In the harsh, dry terrain of northern [[Mesopotamia]], the army suffered from lack of provisions, especially water, until they reached the more fertile areas near Tigranocerta. During that time, a plot to murder Corbulo was uncovered and suppressed. Several Armenian nobles who had joined the Roman camp were implicated and executed.&lt;ref&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 14#24|XIV.24]]&lt;/ref&gt; According to a story provided by [[Frontinus]], when the Roman army arrived at Tigranocerta, they launched the severed head of one of the conspirators into the city. By chance, it landed right where the city council was assembled; they immediately decided to surrender the city, which was consequently spared.&lt;ref&gt;[[Frontinus]], ''Strategemata'', [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Frontinus/Strategemata/2*.html#9 II.9.5]&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly after, an attempt by the Parthian army under king Vologases to enter Armenia was blocked by Verulanus Severus, the commander of the auxiliaries.&lt;ref name=Annales-xiv-26&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 14#26|XIV.26]]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Romans were now in control of Armenia, and they promptly installed its new king, [[Tigranes VI of Armenia|Tigranes VI]], the last descendant of the [[List of Kings of Cappadocia|Cappadocian royal house]], in Tigranocerta. Some outlying western parts of Armenia were also ceded to the Roman vassals. Corbulo left 1,000 legionaries, three auxiliary [[Cohort (military unit)|cohort]]s and two cavalry ''alae'' (ca. 3-4,000 men) behind to support the new monarch, and retired with the rest of his army to Syria, whose governorship he now (in 60 AD) assumed as a reward for his success.&lt;ref name=&quot;Annales-xiv-26&quot;/&gt;

== Parthian counterattack ==
[[File:ParthianHorseman.jpg|thumb|200px|right|Relief depicting a Parthian horse-archer. Highly skilled and mobile, they formed the backbone of the Parthian army. In combination with the heavy [[cataphract]] cavalry they formed a very effective force  that had already annihilated a Roman army at [[Battle of Carrhae|Carrhae]].&lt;ref&gt;Goldsworthy (2007), pp. 305–306&lt;/ref&gt;]]
The Romans were well aware that their victory was still fragile, and that as soon as the Parthian king had dealt with the Hyrcanian rebellion, he would turn his attention to Armenia. Despite Vologases' reluctance to risk an all-out conflict with Rome, in the end, he was forced to act when Tigranes raided the Parthian province of [[Adiabene]] in 61. The enraged protests of its governor [[Monobaz II|Monobazus]], and his pleas for protection, could not be ignored by Vologases, whose prestige and royal authority were at stake.&lt;ref&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 15#1|XV.1]]&lt;/ref&gt; Vologases therefore hastily concluded a treaty with the Hyrcanians so as to be free to campaign against Rome, and called an assembly of the grandees of his realm. There he publicly reaffirmed Tiridates' position as king of Armenia by crowning him with a [[Diadem (personal wear)|diadem]]. In order to reinstall his brother on the Armenian throne, the Parthian king assembled a force of picked cavalry under Monaeses, complemented by infantry from Adiabene.&lt;ref&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 15#2|XV.2]]&lt;/ref&gt;

In response, Corbulo sent the legions IV ''Scythica'' and [[legio XII Fulminata|XII ''Fulminata'']] to Armenia, while he detailed the three other legions under his command (III ''Gallica'', VI ''Ferrata'' and XV ''Apollinaris'') to fortify the line of the river [[Euphrates]], fearing that the Parthians might invade Syria. At the same time, he petitioned Nero to appoint a separate legate for Cappadocia, with the responsibility for conducting the war in Armenia.&lt;ref&gt;Goldsworthy (2007), pp. 318–319&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Parthian siege of Tigranocerta ===
Monaeses meanwhile entered Armenia and approached Tigranocerta. Tigranes had taken care to gather supplies, and the city was well-fortified and garrisoned with Romans and Armenians alike. The siege was largely undertaken by the [[Adiabene|Adiabenian]] contingent, since the Parthians, being cavalrymen, were unskilled and unwilling to engage in siegework.&lt;ref&gt;Goldsworthy (2007), p. 319&lt;/ref&gt; The Parthian assault failed, and was driven back with loss by a successful Roman sally.&lt;ref&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 15#4|XV.4]]&lt;/ref&gt; At this point, Corbulo sent an envoy to Vologases, who had encamped with his court at [[Nisibis]], near Tigranocerta and the Roman–Parthian border. The failed siege and a shortage of fodder for his cavalry forced Vologases to agree to withdraw Monaeses from Armenia.&lt;ref&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 15#5|XV.5]]&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time however, the Romans too left Armenia, something that, according to Tacitus, raised suspicions of Corbulo's motives: some whispered that he had reached an agreement of mutual withdrawal with the Parthians, and that he was unwilling to risk his reputation by renewing hostilities against them.&lt;ref name=Annales-xv-6&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 15#6|XV.6]]&lt;/ref&gt; At any rate, a truce was arranged and a Parthian embassy was dispatched to Rome. The negotiations failed to reach an agreement, and war was resumed in the spring of 62.&lt;ref name=Annales-xv-7&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 15#7|XV.7]]&lt;/ref&gt;

In the meantime, the asked-for legate for Cappadocia had arrived, in the person of [[Lucius Caesennius Paetus]], the [[Roman consul|consul]] of the previous year (61 AD). The army was divided between him and Corbulo, with IV ''Scythica'', XII ''Fulminata'', the newly arrived [[legio V Macedonica|V ''Macedonica'']] and the auxiliaries from Pontus, Galatia and Cappadocia going to Paetus, while Corbulo retained III ''Gallica'', VI ''Ferrata'' and X ''Fretensis''. Because of their antagonism for glory, the relations between the two Roman commanders were strained from the beginning.&lt;ref name=&quot;Annales-xv-6&quot;/&gt; It is notable that Corbulo kept the legions he had spent the past few years campaigning with, and gave his colleague, who after all was expected to conduct the main campaign, the more inexperienced units.&lt;ref&gt;Goldsworthy (2007), p. 320&lt;/ref&gt; The total Roman force arrayed against the Parthians was nevertheless considerable: the six legions alone totaled some 30,000 men. The exact number and disposition of auxiliary units is unclear, but there were seven cavalry ''[[Ala (Roman military)|alae]]'' and seven infantry [[Cohort (military unit)|cohorts]] in Syria alone, comprising a force of 7-9,000 troops.&lt;ref&gt;Sartre (2005), p. 61&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Battle of Rhandeia ===
[[File:VologasesI.JPG|thumb|right|200px|Gold coin of [[Vologases I of Parthia|Vologases I]], King of Parthia.]]
Paetus nonetheless appeared confident of victory, and followed the Parthian declaration of war and capture of Tigranocerta with his own invasion of Armenia,&lt;ref name=Annales-xv-8&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 15#8|XV.8]]&lt;/ref&gt; while Corbulo remained at Syria, further strengthening the fortifications in the Euphrates frontier.&lt;ref name=Annales-xv-9&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 15#9|XV.9]]&lt;/ref&gt; Paetus had only two legions with him, IV ''Scythica'' and XII ''Fulminata'',&lt;ref name=&quot;Annales-xv-7&quot;/&gt; and advanced towards Tigranocerta. A few minor forts were taken, but a lack of supplies forced him to withdraw westwards for the winter.&lt;ref name=&quot;Annales-xv-8&quot;/&gt;

The Parthians had originally intended to invade Syria, but Corbulo put on a convincing display of military might, building a strong flotilla of ships equipped with [[catapult]]s and a bridge over the Euphrates, which allowed him to establish a foothold on the Parthian shore. Therefore, the Parthians abandoned their plans for Syria, and turned their attention towards Armenia.&lt;ref name=&quot;Annales-xv-9&quot;/&gt; There, Paetus had dispersed his forces and granted extended leaves to his officers, so that he was taken unawares at the Parthian advance. Upon learning of it, he initially advanced to meet Vologases, but after a reconnaissance detachment was defeated, he panicked and withdrew hastily. Paetus sent his wife and son to safety in the fortress of [[Arsamosata]], and tried to block the Parthian advance by occupying the passes of the [[Taurus mountains]] with detachments from his army.&lt;ref name=Annales-xv-10&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 15#10|XV.10]]&lt;/ref&gt; In so doing, however, he further dispersed his forces, which were then defeated in detail by the Parthians. Roman morale plunged and panic set in among the army, which was now besieged in a series of hastily erected [[castra|camps]] near Rhandeia. Paetus, who appears to have fallen into desperate inactivity, sent urgent messages to Corbulo to come to his rescue.&lt;ref name=Annales-xv-11&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 15#11|XV.11]]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Roman-Parthian War 61-63.svg|thumb|left|300px|Operations during the final years of the war: the raids of Tigranes into Parthian territory provoked a Parthian counterattack, which culminated in the surrender of the Roman army of L. Caesennius Paetus.]]
Corbulo in the meantime had been aware of the danger faced by his colleague, and put part of his forces on readiness; but he did not march to join Paetus, and some accused him of delaying in order to reap more glory from rescuing him.&lt;ref name=&quot;Annales-xv-10&quot;/&gt; Nevertheless, when the calls for assistance arrived, he responded quickly and marched forth with half of the Syrian army, carrying many provisions laden on camels. He soon met dispersed men of Paetus' army, and managed to rally them around his force.&lt;ref&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 15#12|XV.12]]&lt;/ref&gt; But before he could arrive to the rescue, Paetus had capitulated: the Parthians, aware that relief was nearing, increasingly harassed the Romans, until Paetus was forced to send a letter to Vologases to seek terms.&lt;ref&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 15#13|XV.13–14]]&lt;/ref&gt; The subsequent treaty was humiliating: not only would the Romans leave Armenia and surrender all forts they held, but they also agreed to build a bridge over the nearby [[Arsanias]] river over which Vologases could pass in triumph, sitting atop an elephant.&lt;ref name=&quot;cassiusdio-lxii-21&quot;&gt;Cassius Dio, ''Historia Romana'' [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Cassius_Dio/62*.html#21 LXII.21]&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, the Roman army was liberally plundered by the Armenians, who took even the Romans' weapons and clothes without facing any resistance. Still worse, according to rumors reported by Tacitus, the Romans were made to [[Wiktionary:pass under the yoke|pass under the yoke]], a gesture of ultimate humiliation in Roman eyes.&lt;ref&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 15#14|XV.14–15]]&lt;/ref&gt;

The two Roman forces met on the banks of the Euphrates near [[Melitene]], amidst scenes of mutual grief;&lt;ref&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 15#16|XV.16]]&lt;/ref&gt; while Corbulo lamented the undoing of his achievements, Paetus tried to convince him to attempt to reverse the situation by invading Armenia. Corbulo however refused, claiming that he did not have the authority to do so, and that either way the army was too worn out to be able to campaign effectively.&lt;ref name=Annales-xv-17&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 15#17|XV.17]]&lt;/ref&gt; In the end, Paetus retired to Cappadocia and Corbulo to Syria, where he received envoys from Vologases, who demanded that he evacuate his bridgehead over the Euphrates. In turn, Corbulo demanded the Parthian evacuation of Armenia. Vologases agreed to this, and both sides withdrew their forces, leaving Armenia once again masterless but ''de facto'' under Parthian control, until a Parthian delegation could travel to Rome.&lt;ref name=&quot;Annales-xv-17&quot;/&gt;

== Corbulo's return and peace settlement ==
Rome, meanwhile, appears to have been largely unaware of the real situation in Armenia. Tacitus acidly records that &quot;trophies for the Parthian war and arches were erected in the center of the [[Capitoline hill]]&quot; by decree of the [[Roman Senate|Senate]], even while the war was not yet decided.&lt;ref&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 15#18|XV.18]]&lt;/ref&gt; Whatever illusions the Roman leadership had, they were shattered by the arrival of the Parthian delegation to Rome in the spring of 63. Their demands, and the subsequent interrogation of the centurion who accompanied them, revealed to Nero and the Senate the true extent of the disaster, which Paetus had concealed in his dispatches.&lt;ref name=Annales-xv-25&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 15#25|XV.25]]&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, in the words of Tacitus, the Romans decided to &quot;accept a dangerous war over a disgraceful peace&quot;; Paetus was recalled, and Corbulo placed again in charge of the campaign into Armenia, with extraordinary ''imperium'' which placed him above all other governors and client rulers in the East. Corbulo's post as governor of Syria was entrusted to [[Cestius Gallus|Gaius Cestius Gallus]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Annales-xv-25&quot;/&gt;

Corbulo reordered his forces, withdrawing the defeated and demoralized IV ''Scythica'' and XII ''Fulminata'' legions to Syria, leaving X ''Fretensis'' to guard Cappadocia, and leading his veteran III ''Gallica'' and VI ''Ferrata'' to Melitene, where the invasion army was to be assembled. To these he also added V ''Macedonica'', which had remained in Pontus throughout the previous year and not been tainted by the defeat, the newly arrived [[legio XV Apollinaris|XV ''Apollinaris'']], and large numbers of auxiliaries and contingents of the client kings.&lt;ref&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 15#26|XV.26]]&lt;/ref&gt;

After his army crossed the Euphrates, following a route opened up by [[Lucullus]] over a hundred years before, he received envoys from Tiridates and Vologases. At the approach of such a large force, and aware of Corbulo's ability as a general, the two Arsacids were anxious to negotiate. Indeed, Corbulo, no doubt on instructions from Nero, reiterated the old Roman position: if Tiridates would accept his crown from Rome, then renewed war could be averted.&lt;ref&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 15#27|XV.27]]&lt;/ref&gt; Tiridates readily agreed to negotiations, and Rhandeia, the scene of last year's Roman defeat, was agreed upon as a meeting place. To the Armenians, this place was intended as a reminder of their strength, while Corbulo agreed to it because there he hoped to expunge the earlier disgrace, by peace or war.&lt;ref name=&quot;cassiusdio-lxii-22&quot;&gt;Cassius Dio, ''Historia Romana'' [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Cassius_Dio/62*.html#22 LXII.22]&lt;/ref&gt; Once there, Corbulo put Paetus' son, who served under him as a legate, in charge of a party that was to gather the remains of the Roman soldiers and ensure them a proper burial. On the agreed day, both Tiridates and Corbulo, each accompanied by 20 horsemen, met between the two camps.&lt;ref&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 15#28|XV.28]]&lt;/ref&gt; Tiridates agreed to travel to Rome and seek confirmation of his crown from Nero. In sign of this agreement, a few days later, both armies put on a display, arrayed in full parade gear. Tiridates approached the Roman camp, where a statue of the Emperor Nero had been erected upon a raised platform, and placed his royal diadem at its feet in submission.&lt;ref&gt;Tacitus, ''Annales'' [[wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 15#29|XV.29]]&lt;/ref&gt;

== Aftermath ==
[[File:Nero closedJanus.jpg|thumb|200px|Celebratory ''[[As (coin)|as]]'' struck in 66, showing the gates of the Temple of Janus closed as a symbol of universal peace. It would not last long: in the same year, the [[First Jewish–Roman War|Jewish Revolt]] broke out, and many of the units involved in the Armenian War would be deployed against the Jewish rebels.]]

In 66, Tiridates [[Tiridates I of Armenia#Visiting Rome|visited Rome]] to receive his crown and was lavishly received by Nero, who used the occasion to boost his own popularity. He ordered the gates of the [[Temple of Janus (Roman Forum)|Temple of Janus]] to be shut, thus declaring that peace reigned throughout the Roman Empire.&lt;ref&gt;Shotter (2005), p. 39&lt;/ref&gt;

Nero celebrated this peace as a major achievement: he was hailed as ''[[imperator]]'' and held a [[Roman triumph|triumph]],&lt;ref name=&quot;cassiusdio-lxii-23&quot;&gt;Cassius Dio, ''Historia Romana'' [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Cassius_Dio/62*.html#23.4 LXII.23.4]&lt;/ref&gt; although no new territory had been won, and the peace reflected a compromise rather than a true victory. For although Rome could prevail militarily in Armenia, politically, she had no genuine alternatives to the Arsacid candidacy on offer for the Armenian throne.&lt;ref&gt;Wheeler (2007), p. 242&lt;/ref&gt; Armenia would henceforth be ruled by an Iranian dynasty, and despite its nominal allegiance to Rome, it would come under increasing Parthian influence.&lt;ref name=Bivar85&gt;Bivar (1968), p. 85&lt;/ref&gt; In the judgment of later generations, &quot;Nero had lost Armenia&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;[[Festus (historian)|Festus]], ''[http://www.roman-emperors.org/festus.htm Breviarium]'', XX.1&lt;/ref&gt; and although the Peace of Rhandeia ushered in a period of relatively peaceful relations that would last for 50 years, Armenia would continue to be a constant bone of contention between the Romans, the Parthians, and their [[Sassanid Empire|Sassanid]] successors.&lt;ref&gt;Farrokh (2007), p. 150&lt;/ref&gt; For the short term however, the peace that Nero secured was kept by both sides, even while the bulk of Rome's eastern forces was involved in the suppression of the [[First Jewish–Roman War|Jewish Revolt]].&lt;ref&gt;Shotter (2005), pp. 40–41&lt;/ref&gt;

As for Corbulo, he was honoured by Nero as the man who had brought this &quot;triumph&quot; to be, but his popularity and influence with the army made him a potential rival. Together with the involvement of his son-in-law Lucius Annius Vinicianus in a foiled plot against Nero in 66, Corbulo became suspect in the eyes of the emperor.&lt;ref&gt;Shotter (2005), pp. 69–70&lt;/ref&gt; In 67, while journeying in Greece, Nero ordered him to be executed; upon hearing of this, Corbulo committed suicide.&lt;ref name=&quot;cassiusdio-lxiii-17&quot;&gt;Cassius Dio, ''Historia Romana'' [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Cassius_Dio/62*.html#63-17 LXIII.17.5–6]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Shotter (2005), p. 72&lt;/ref&gt;

The war had also demonstrated to the Romans that the defensive system in the East, as put in place by Augustus, was no longer adequate. Thus the following years saw a major reorganization of the Roman East: the client kingdoms of Pontus and Colchis (in 64 AD), [[Cilicia]], [[Commagene]] and [[Lesser Armenia]] (in 72 AD) were made into Roman provinces, the number of legions in the area increased, and Roman presence in the Caucasian client states of [[Caucasian Iberia|Iberia]] and [[Caucasian Albania|Albania]] strengthened, with the aim of strategically encircling Armenia.&lt;ref&gt;Wheeler (2007), p. 243&lt;/ref&gt; Direct Roman control was extended to the entire line of the Euphrates, marking the beginning of the Eastern ''[[limes]]'' that would survive until the [[Muslim conquests]] of the 7th century.

== References ==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

== Sources ==

=== Primary sources ===
*[[File:wikisource-logo.svg|15px]] [[Tacitus]], ''[[Annals (Tacitus)|Annales]]''. [[:Wikisource:The Annals (Tacitus)|Translation based on Alfred John Church and William Jackson Brodribb (1876)]].
*[[Cassius Dio]], ''Historia Romana''. [http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Cassius_Dio/62*.html#23 Loeb Classical Library edition (1925)]

=== Secondary sources ===
*{{cite book |title=The Cambridge History of Iran |last=Bivar|first=H.D.H |editor=William Bayne Fisher |editor2=Ilya Gershevitch |editor3=Ehsan Yarshater |editor4=R. N. Frye |editor5=J. A. Boyle |editor6=Peter Jackson |editor7=Laurence Lockhart |editor8=Peter Avery |editor9=Gavin Hambly |editor10=Charles Melville |year=1968 |publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=0-521-20092-X |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Ko_RafMSGLkC&amp;pg=PA124&amp;dq=Severus,+Ardashir&amp;ei=_EQTSPaZBJHCyQS03tSBCA&amp;sig=2KtkBSoqidkjzcqEuJRCX_OUl2w#PPR7,M1|chapter=The Political History of Iran under the Arsacids: Continuation of conflict with Rome over Armenia}}
*{{cite book |title=Shadows in the Desert: Ancient Persia at War |last=Farrokh |first=Kaveh |isbn=1-84603-108-7|year=2007|publisher=Osprey Publishing|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=p7kltwf9yrwC&amp;dq=Lazica,+545&amp;source=gbs_summary_s&amp;cad=0|chapter=Parthia from Mark Antony to the Alan Invasions}}
*{{cite book |title=In the name of Rome: The men who won the Roman Empire |last=Goldsworthy |first=Adrian |isbn=978-0-7538-1789-6|year=2007|publisher=Phoenix|chapter=Imperial legate: Corbulo and Armenia}}
*{{cite book |title=The Middle East Under Rome |last=Sartre |first=Maurice |coauthors=translated by: Porter, Catherine &amp; Rawlings, Elizabeth |isbn=978-0-674-01683-5 |year=2005 |publisher=Harvard University Press }}
* {{cite book | last=Shotter | first=David | title=Nero (Second Edition) | year=2005 | publisher=Routledge | location = London and New York | isbn=0-415-31942-0}}
* {{cite book | last=Southern | first=Pat | title=The Roman Army: A Social and Institutional History | year=2007 | publisher=Oxford University Press | isbn=978-0-19-532878-3}}
* {{cite book | last=Wheeler | first=Everett L. | title=A Companion to the Roman Army | chapter=The Army and the ''Limes'' in the East | editor=Gardiner, Robert | year=2007 | publisher=[[Blackwell Publishing]] Ltd. | isbn=978-1-4051-2153-8}}

{{Ancient Roman Wars}}
{{good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Roman-Parthian War of 58-63}}
[[Category:1st-century conflicts]]
[[Category:Roman–Parthian Wars]]
[[Category:Wars involving the Roman Empire|Parthia]]
[[Category:58 in the Roman Empire]]
[[Category:59 in the Roman Empire]]
[[Category:60 in the Roman Empire]]
[[Category:61 in the Roman Empire]]
[[Category:62 in the Roman Empire]]
[[Category:63 in the Roman Empire]]
[[Category:1st century in Iran]]
[[Category:1st century in Armenia]]</text>
      <sha1>tsm9h31eqlz4l53x6efdysod7elwws3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
