<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Rudolf Frank</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>30763305</id>
    <revision>
      <id>735501457</id>
      <parentid>732923525</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-21T05:11:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ÄDA - DÄP</username>
        <id>16734816</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>clean up using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="31032">{{good article}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2014}}
{{Use American English|date=October 2014}}
{{Infobox military person
|name=Rudolf Frank
|birth_date=19 August 1920
|death_date={{death date and age|1944|4|27|1920|8|19|df=y}}
|image=File:Rudolf Frank.jpg
|alt=The head and upper body of a young man, shown in semi-profile. He wears a peaked cap and military uniform with various military decorations, at his neck, an Iron Cross displayed at the front of his white shirt collar.
|caption=Frank as ''Oberfeldwebel''
|birth_place=[[Karlsruhe]]-Grünwinkel, Germany
|death_place=near [[Eindhoven]], Netherlands
|placeofburial=[[Ysselsteyn]], Netherlands&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;(Block Z—Row 6—Grave 149)&lt;/small&gt;
|allegiance={{flag|Nazi Germany}}
|branch={{Luftwaffe}}
|serviceyears=1939–44
|rank=''[[Leutnant]]'' (posthumously)
|unit=[[Nachtjagdgeschwader 3|NJG 3]]
|commands=
|battles=World War II
*[[Defense of the Reich]]{{KIA}}
|awards=[[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves]] (posthumously)
|laterwork=}}

'''Rudolf Frank''' (19 August 1920 – 27 April 1944) was a German ''[[Luftwaffe]]'' [[military aviation|military aviator]] during World War II, a [[night fighter]] [[fighter ace|ace]] credited with 45 enemy aircraft shot down in 183 combat missions. All of his victories were claimed over the [[Western Front (World War II)|Western Front]] in nocturnal [[Defense of the Reich]] missions against the [[Royal Air Force]]'s [[RAF Bomber Command|Bomber Command]].

Born in [[Karlsruhe]]-Grünwinkel, Frank volunteered for military service in the ''Luftwaffe'' of the [[Third Reich]] in 1939 after finishing school. Following flight training, he was posted to [[Nachtjagdgeschwader 3|''Nachtjagdgeschwader'' 3]] (NJG 3—3rd Night Fighter Wing) in 1941. He was awarded the [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross]] on 6 April 1944 following his 42nd aerial victory. Three weeks later, on 27 April 1944, he and his crew attacked an [[Avro Lancaster]], which exploded and fatally damaged their own aircraft. Frank ordered his crew to [[parachute|bail out]] but was unable to save himself.  He received [[Posthumous recognition|posthumous]] promotion to ''[[Leutnant]]'' (second lieutenant) and was awarded the [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves]].

==Early life and career==
Frank was born on 19 August 1920 in [[Karlsruhe]]-Grünwinkel in what was the [[Republic of Baden]] of the [[Weimar Republic]]; Grünwinkel is now a borough located in the southwest suburbs of Karlsruhe. Frank was the older of two sons of a [[shoemaking|shoemaker]]. He attended the ''[[Volksschule]]'' ([[elementary school]]) in Grünwinkel from 1926 to 1930, when he was enrolled in the ''Realgymnasium''—a secondary school built on the mid-level ''[[Realschule]]''—where he attained his ''[[Mittlere Reife]]'' (school leaving certificate) in 1939.&lt;ref&gt;Schumann 2014, p. 2.&lt;/ref&gt;

Even as a boy, Frank had wanted to become a pilot. World War II had begun on 1 September 1939 and he volunteered for military service in the ''[[Luftwaffe]]''. Following his basic military training, he took flying instruction at the pilot school in [[Zeltweg Air Base|Zeltweg]]. Here he qualified to fly the [[Bücker Bü 131]], [[Bücker Bü 133|Bü 133]] and [[Bücker Bü 181|Bü 181]], the [[Klemm Kl 35]], the [[Arado Ar 66]], [[Arado Ar 68|Ar 68]] and [[Arado Ar 96|Ar 96]], the [[Focke-Wulf Fw 58]], and the [[Junkers W 34]] and [[Junkers Ju 52]].&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;Flight training in the Luftwaffe progressed through the levels A1, A2 and B1, B2, referred to as A/B flight training. A training included theoretical and practical training in aerobatics, navigation, long-distance flights and [[deadstick landing|dead-stick landings]]. The B courses included high-altitude flights, instrument flights, night landings and training to handle the aircraft in difficult situations. For pilots destined to fly multi-engine aircraft, the training was completed with the Luftwaffe Advanced Pilot's Certificate (''Erweiterter Luftwaffen-Flugzeugführerschein''), also known as C-Certificate.&lt;/ref&gt; In October 1940 he transferred to ''Nachtjagdschule'' 1 (1st Night Fighter School) at [[Schleißheim]] near [[Munich]], formerly the ''Zerstörerschule'' 1 (ZS 1—1st Destroyer School). There he specialized as a night fighter pilot in the 2nd Squadron under the command of ''[[Staffelkapitän]]'' (squadron leader) ''[[Oberleutnant]]'' (First Lieutenant) [[Günther Specht]].&lt;ref&gt;Schumann 2014, pp. 2–5.&lt;/ref&gt;

==World War II==
Frank was posted to the 1. ''Ergänzungsstaffel ''(1st Supplemental Training Squadron) of [[Nachtjagdgeschwader 3|''Nachtjagdgeschwader'' 3]] (NJG 3—3rd Night Fighter Wing) on 5 February 1941.&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;For an explanation of ''Luftwaffe'' unit designations, see [[Organization of the Luftwaffe (1933–1945)|Organization of the ''Luftwaffe'' during World War II]].&lt;/ref&gt; The unit was stationed at [[Stuttgart]]-Echterdingen (now [[Stuttgart Airport]]). Initially he flew with radio operator (''Bordfunker'') ''Gefreiter'' (Private) Willimowski before [[Hans-Georg Schierholz]] was assigned as his permanent radio operator. Frank and Schierholz had already formed a crew at the ''Nachtjagdschule'' 1 at Schleißheim. The two were then assigned to 1. ''[[Organization of the Luftwaffe (1933–1945)#Staffel|Staffel]]'' (1st Squadron) of NJG 3 stationed at [[Vechta]]. 1. ''Staffel'' was under the command of ''Staffelkapitän'' ''Oberleutnant'' Walter Milius. This unit was equipped with the C-variant of the [[Messerschmitt Bf 110]] [[heavy fighter]].&lt;ref&gt;Schumann 2014, p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt; Both Frank and Schierholz were promoted to the rank of ''Gefreiter'' on 1 March 1941.&lt;ref&gt;Schumann 2014, p. 8.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Night fighter pilot===
Frank and Schierholz flew Bf 110 C-4 &quot;L1+GH&quot; on their first operational combat mission on 9 May 1941, without success. They flew their second mission on 12 May and another nine missions before claiming their first aerial victory during the night of 3/4 July. The mission started at 22:45 from [[Oldenburg]] and intercepted a [[Royal Air Force]] (RAF) [[Vickers Wellington]] at 00:54, which crashed {{Convert|10|km|mi|abbr=off|sp=us}} north of [[Berge, Lower Saxony|Grafeld]]/Oldenburg. For this achievement, Frank and Schierholz were awarded the [[Iron Cross]] 2nd Class ({{Lang|de|''Eisernes Kreuz 2. Klasse''}}). On 15 July, they claimed their second victory, a [[Handley Page Halifax]] that they shot down at 01:05 northwest of [[Meppen]]. The victory was, however, credited to the [[Anti-aircraft warfare|anti-aircraft artillery]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann p9&quot;&gt;Schumann 2014, p. 9.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-659-6436-12, Flugzeug Messerschmitt Me 110.jpg|thumb|left|Messerschmitt Bf 110 G-4 of NJG 3 similar to those flown by Frank.|alt=A twin engine propeller driven aircraft in flight.]]
By 13 August 1941, Frank had flown 20 night fighter missions. For this achievement, he was awarded the [[Front Flying Clasp of the Luftwaffe]] for Night Fighters in Bronze ({{Lang|de|''Frontflugspange für Nachtjäger in Bronze''}}) and was promoted to ''[[Unteroffizier]]'' (sergeant). He was credited with his second victory on 15 September 1941, a Wellington shot down at 23:30 northwest of Meppen. This was also his last claim in 1941. He achieved his third victory, a [[Handley Page Hampden]] he shot down at 21:03 on 21 January 1942 near Berge in northeast [[Lingen, Germany|Lingen]]. Five days later he claimed an [[Armstrong Whitworth Whitley]] Mk V, shot down at 20:36 west of [[Quakenbrück]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann p9&quot;/&gt;

Frank was awarded the Iron Cross 1st Class ({{Lang|de|''Eisernes Kreuz 1. Klasse''}}) on 15 April 1942 and two months later, on 18 June 1942, the Front Flying Clasp of the Luftwaffe for Night Fighters in Silver ({{Lang|de|''Frontflugspange für Nachtjäger in Silber''}}). On 30 June 1942 at 01:29, he and Schierholz took off from Vechta on their 64th combat mission. While attacking a British bomber, either a Wellington or Halifax, their aircraft was hit by the defensive fire from the [[tail gunner|tail gun]] position at 02:40. With both radiators destroyed, they [[parachute|bailed out]] from their aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;Schumann 2014, p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt;

Frank's ''[[Luftwaffe Organization#Gruppe|Gruppe]]'' (group) relocated to [[Rheine]] in [[Westphalia]] on 28 July 1942, when he flew further missions with [[Dornier Do 217]] J &quot;D5+G5&quot;, a night fighter variant of the Do 217. He claimed a Wellington shot down at 02:05 on 14 September 1942; it crashed in the vicinity of [[Osnabrück]], and was his only victory while flying a Do 217. On this mission, the Dornier suffered engine problems and Frank made a [[forced landing]] at [[Bad Zwischenahn]], damaging the aircraft. He ended the year 1942 with seven confirmed victories to his credit.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann p13&quot;&gt;Schumann 2014, p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Lichtenstein FuG 202 Viestimuseo 2.JPG|thumb|right|''Lichtenstein'' [[cathode-ray]] tubes:&lt;br /&gt;{{*}}The left tube indicated other aircraft ahead as bumps.&lt;br /&gt;{{*}}The center tube indicated range to a specific target and whether they were higher or lower.&lt;br /&gt;{{*}}The right tube indicated whether the target was to left or right.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hinchliffe p56&quot;&gt;Hinchliffe 1999, p. 56.&lt;/ref&gt;|alt=An electrical device with three round displays, cables and control knobs.]]
The first victory Frank claimed in 1943 occurred on 3 March. Again flying a Bf 110, he shot down a [[Short Stirling]] south of [[Delmenhorst]]. Contact with three other enemy bombers did not lead to any victories. Frank flew further missions in Do 217 &quot;D5+LK&quot; on a target practice mission on 9 April 1943. The right [[landing gear]] collapsed during the landing, causing 10% damage to the aircraft. Three days later he made an error during the landing approach, crashing Do 217 &quot;D5+IK&quot; and causing 30% damage. Frank avoided an official reprimand for either crash.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann p13&quot;/&gt;

On 1 April 1943, Frank and Schierholz were transferred to the 2. ''Staffel'' of NJG 3, which was located at [[Wittmundhafen Air Base|Wittmundhafen]]. Here they underwent conversion training to the [[Junkers Ju 88]] C-6, which was designed for long-distance night fighter operations.&lt;ref&gt;Schumann 2014, p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt; While Frank was training, his old unit was relocated to [[Gilze-Rijen Air Base|Gilze-Rijen]] in the Netherlands. His unit also received the newer G-version of the Bf 110; these were equipped with [[Lichtenstein radar|SN-2 ''Lichtenstein'' radar]]. When Frank and Schierholz returned from conversion training, they were assigned Bf 110 G-4 &quot;D5+CH&quot; to fly as their personal aircraft. They claimed a Lancaster(ED810) near [[Antwerp]] on 15 June 1943. Two days later, on 17 June, they intercepted and shot down three more Lancasters from a force returning from a mission against [[Cologne]]. The three Lancasters came down within 41 minutes of each other over the [[Scheldt Estuary]].&lt;ref&gt;Schumann 2014, p. 16.&lt;/ref&gt;

Frank claimed his 13th victory, a Wellington, on 22 June. While attempting another attack, both radiators were shot out and the crew was again forced to bail out. On 4 July they shot down a Halifax bomber north of Antwerp; this was his 14th victory overall.&lt;ref&gt;Schumann 2014, pp. 16–17.&lt;/ref&gt; The unit relocated to [[Juvincourt Airfield|Juvincourt]], France, on 16 July 1943. Frank was awarded the [[Ehrenpokal der Luftwaffe|Honor Goblet of the Luftwaffe]] ({{Lang|de|''Ehrenpokal der Luftwaffe''}}) on 9 August 1943. Now flying Ju 88 C-6 &quot;D5+EK&quot;, again from Wittmundhafen, he claimed three aircraft shot down on 24 August 1944, but only received credit for the Short Stirling shot down at 00:47 over [[Berlin]]. Following his 110th operational mission, he was awarded the Front Flying Clasp of the Luftwaffe for Night Fighters in Gold ({{Lang|de|''Frontflugspange für Nachtjäger in Gold''}}) on 18 August 1943.&lt;ref&gt;Schumann 2014, p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt;

Around this time in 1943, the two-man Bf 110 crew was augmented by a third member, sometimes referred to as ''Bordmechaniker'' ([[Flight engineer|air mechanic]]) or ''Bordschütze'' ([[air gunner]]). On 31 August, Frank shot down two British bombers, a Halifax northwest of [[Venlo]] and a Lancaster east of [[Diepholz]], during separate combat missions. On 2 September, his aircraft was hit in the right engine by enemy fire and he was forced to belly-land the Ju 88 &quot;D5+DK&quot; at [[Wilhelmshaven]], suffering 20% damage to the aircraft. He claimed his 20th victory on the night of 23/24 September 1943. He added two more victories and on 17 October 1943 received the [[German Cross]] in Gold ({{Lang|de|''Deutsches Kreuz in Gold''}}). The next day his aircraft was hit by German anti-aircraft artillery and Frank was forced to make a landing at Vechta on one engine. He was posted to the 3. ''Staffel'' on 14 December and ended the year with 26 aerial victories to his credit.&lt;ref&gt;Schumann 2014, p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt; A British [[Intruder (air combat)|intruder]] night-fighter shot Frank and his crew down over Berlin in a Junkers Ju 88 C-6, &quot;D5+HP&quot;, on 24 December 1943, but they all managed to bail out unharmed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann p19&quot;&gt;Schumann 2014, p. 19.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross===
Frank claimed his first victories of 1944, a Lancaster and a Wellington, on 21 January 1944 near [[Magdeburg]]. Having been promoted to ''[[Feldwebel]]'' (staff sergeant), Frank was assigned to the ''[[Stab (Luftwaffe designation)|Stab]]'' (headquarters unit) of NJG 3, under the command of ''[[Geschwaderkommodore]]'' (Wing Commander) ''[[Oberstleutnant]]'' (Lieutenant Colonel) [[Helmut Lent]]. Frank's previous 6. ''Staffel'' had been transferred to [[Nachtjagdgeschwader 1]] (NJG 1—1st Night Fighter Wing), where it continued operations under the designation of 12. ''Staffel''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann p19&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-668-7168-05A, Reichsgebiet, Leitstand der 4. Flakdivision.jpg|thumb|left|''Luftwaffenhelferinen'' helped plot the course of enemy bombers.|alt=A group of young women, wearing headsets, sitting in an auditorium, controlling projectors.]]
On 20 February 1944, between 01:53 to 05:04, Frank became an &quot;[[Aviators who became ace in a day|ace-in-a-day]]&quot;, shooting down five Lancaster bombers on their way to attack [[Leipzig]]. He was sent on a mission against intruding [[de Havilland Mosquito]] night-fighters on 7 March, but did not achieve any victories. He claimed his next victories on 22 March, a Lancaster shot down near Osnabrück and a Halifax near [[Gütersloh]]. On the same mission, while attacking a third bomber, his Messerschmitt Bf 110 &quot;D5+BL&quot; was damaged. An [[incendiary bomb]], probably released by the bomber, penetrated the right wing and damaged the engine. Frank managed to bring the aircraft down at Gießen.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann p19&quot;/&gt;

Three more bombers shot down on 25 March took Frank's total to 39 aerial victories. The ''Luftwaffe'' had its most successful night of the war on 30 March 1944. The entire night-fighter force was credited with the destruction of 132 enemy aircraft that night; Frank, who was credited with a further three bombers, brought his total to 42.&lt;ref&gt;Schumann 2014, pp. 19, 21.&lt;/ref&gt; For this achievement ''[[Oberfeldwebel]]'' (Senior Staff Sergeant) Frank was awarded the [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross]] ({{Lang|de|''Ritterkreuz des Eisernen Kreuzes''}}) on 6 April 1944. The presentation was made by ''Generalleutnant'' [[Joseph Schmid]], commander of the [[1st Fighter Corps (Germany)|I. Jagdkorps]], at his headquarters in [[Braunschweig Airport|Braunschweig-Waggum]] on 10 April 1944. Frank then went on a short vacation at home with his wife Lisa, a ''[[Luftwaffenhelfer]]in'' (female air force helper).&lt;ref&gt;Schumann 2014, pp. 21–22.&lt;/ref&gt;

Following his vacation, Frank claimed two victories on 23 April 1944, a Halifax shot down at 02:11 north of [[Geldern]] and, later that day, a Short Stirling at 23:47 over [[Lolland]]. The Stirling was on a [[Minelayer|minelaying]] operation.&lt;ref&gt;Schumann 2014, p. 23.&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|The story and fate of [[No. 76 Squadron RAF|No. 76 Squadron]] Halifax ''MZ578''/MP-I is described by the former crew-member, Tom Wingham, in his book &quot;''Halifax Down!: On the Run from the Gestapo, 1944''&quot;.|group=&quot;Note&quot;}}

===Death and posthumous honors===
Frank was assigned Junkers Ju 88 (''Werknummer'' 751 095—factory number) on 17 April 1944. He never flew this aircraft operationally. Ten days later, on the night of 26/27 April, he and his crew of radio operator ''Oberfeldwebel'' Schierholz and air mechanic ''Feldwebel'' Heinz Schneider took off in Messerschmitt Bf 110 G-4 &quot;D5+CL&quot; (''Werknummer'' 720074) from Vechta. The mission was to intercept incoming bombers heading for the [[Ruhr Area]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann p32&quot;&gt;Schumann 2014, p. 32.&lt;/ref&gt;

The crew spotted and attacked an Avro Lancaster bomber over the vicinity of [[Eindhoven]] in the Netherlands. The bomber, severely hit by cannon fire at 01:58, exploded and became Frank's 45th and last aerial victory. Debris from the Lancaster tore off the Messerschmitt's right wing and Frank lost control of the aircraft. He gave the order to bail out. Schierholz and Schneider parachuted to safety but Frank failed to get out in time. He was killed when the Bf 110 crashed at [[Heeze]], {{Convert|9|km|mi|sp=us}} southeast of Eindhoven.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann p32&quot;/&gt;

Frank was buried at the [[Ysselsteyn German war cemetery|German War Cemetery]] [[Ysselsteyn]] (Block Z—Row 6—Grave 149) at [[Venray]].&lt;ref&gt;Schumann 2014, p. 42.&lt;/ref&gt; The funeral was attended by his parents, his crew Schierholz and Schneider, his ''[[Gruppenkommandeur]]'' ''Hauptmann'' [[Werner Husemann]], the fighter operations leader for the Holland and Ruhr area ''Generalleutnant'' [[Walter Grabmann]], and ''Generalmajor'' Ernst Exss, the airfield sector commander.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann p32&quot;/&gt;

On 20 July 1944, Frank was posthumously awarded the [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves]] ({{Lang|de|''Ritterkreuz des Eisernen Kreuzes mit Eichenlaub''}}), the 531st soldier or officer of the [[Wehrmacht]] to receive this award. On 27 April Lent submitted a request to the I. Jagdkorps, recommending Frank for a promotion to ''[[Leutnant]]'' (second lieutenant). The commander of the [[2nd Fighter Division (Germany)|2nd Fighter Division]] ''Generalmajor'' [[Max Ibel]] as well as Schmid were supportive of the request. Frank was posthumously promoted ''Leutnant'', backdated to 1 April 1944.&lt;ref&gt;Schumann 2014, p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aerial victory credits==
Frank was credited with 45 aerial victories claimed in 183 combat missions.&lt;ref&gt;Obermaier 1986, p. 68.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;For a list of ''Luftwaffe'' night fighter aces see [[List of German World War II night fighter aces]].&lt;/ref&gt;

{{legend2|#e3d9ff|This and the ♠ ([[Ace of spades]]) indicates those aerial victories which made Frank an ace-in-a-day, a term which designates a fighter pilot who has shot down five or more airplanes in a single day. |border=1px solid #AAAAAA}}

&lt;center&gt;
{| class=&quot;wikitable plainrowheaders&quot; style=&quot;text-align:right;&quot;
|-
! colspan=&quot;7&quot; | Chronicle of aerial victories&lt;ref&gt;Schumann 2014, p. 43.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
!scope=&quot;col&quot;| Victory
!scope=&quot;col&quot; style=&quot;width:130px&quot;| Date
!scope=&quot;col&quot;| Time
!scope=&quot;col&quot;| Type
!scope=&quot;col&quot;| Location
!scope=&quot;col&quot;| Unit
!scope=&quot;col&quot;| Serial No./Squadron No.
|-
! colspan=&quot;7&quot; | – Messerschmitt Bf 110 C-4 L1+GH –
|-
| 1
| 4 July 1941
| 00:54
| [[Vickers Wellington]]
| {{Convert|10|km|mi|abbr=on|sp=us}} north of [[Berge, Lower Saxony|Grafeld]]/[[Oldenburg]]
|
|
|-
| —
| 15 July 1941
| 01:05
| [[Handley Page Halifax]]
| northwest of [[Meppen]]
|
|
|-
! colspan=&quot;7&quot; | – Messerschmitt Bf 110 D-3 L1+DH –
|-
| 2
| 15 September 1941
| 23:30
| Vickers Wellington
| northwest of Meppen
|
|
|-
! colspan=&quot;7&quot; | – Messerschmitt Bf 110 E-2 D5+EH –
|-
| 3
| 21 January 1942
| 21:03
| [[Handley Page Hampden]]
| near [[Berge, Lower Saxony|Berge]] (northeast [[Lingen, Germany|Lingen]])
|
|
|-
! colspan=&quot;7&quot; | – Messerschmitt Bf 110 E-2 D5+HH –
|-
| 4
| 26 January 1942
| 20:36
| [[Armstrong Whitworth Whitley]]
| west of [[Quakenbrück]]
|
|
|-
| 5
| 3 July 1942
| 01:45
| Vickers Wellington
| {{Convert|5|km|mi|abbr=on|sp=us}} north of [[Cloppenburg]]
|
|
|-
| 6
| 3 July 1942
| 02:13
| Vickers Wellington
| {{Convert|20|km|mi|abbr=on|sp=us}} southwest of [[Vechta]]
|
|
|-
! colspan=&quot;7&quot; | – Dornier Do 217 J D5+GH –
|-
| 7
| 14 September 1942
| 03:42
| Vickers Wellington
| {{Convert|10|km|mi|abbr=on|sp=us}} east of Lingen
|
|
|-
! colspan=&quot;7&quot; | – Messerschmitt Bf 110 C-2 D5+BH –
|-
| 8
| 3 March 1943
| 22:22
| [[Short Stirling]]
| south of [[Delmenhorst]]
|
|
|-
! colspan=&quot;7&quot; | – Messerschmitt Bf 110 G-4 D5+CH –
|-
| 9
| 15 June 1943
| 01:24
| [[Avro Lancaster]] III
| [[Antwerp]]
| [[No. 50 Squadron RAF|No. 50 Squadron]]
| ''ED810''/VN-Z&lt;ref&gt;Chorley 1996, p. 186.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 10
| 17 June 1943
| 00:58
| Avro Lancaster
| [[Scheldt Estuary]]
|
|
|-
| 11
| 17 June 1943
| 01:18
| Avro Lancaster
| Scheldt Estuary
|
|
|-
| 12
| 17 June 1943
| 01:39
| Avro Lancaster
| Scheldt Estuary
|
|
|-
| 13
| 22 June 1943
| 01:24
| Vickers Wellington
| {{Convert|20|km|mi|abbr=on|sp=us}} east of Antwerp
|
|
|-
! colspan=&quot;7&quot; | – Messerschmitt Bf 110 G-4 D5+BH –
|-
| 14
| 4 July 1943
| 01:06
| Handley Page Halifax
| north of Antwerp
|
|
|-
! colspan=&quot;7&quot; | – Junkers Ju 88 C-6 D5+EK –
|-
| 15
| 24 August 1943
| 00:47
| Short Stirling
| [[Berlin]]
|
|
|-
| 16
| 31 August 1943
| 03:43
| Handley Page Halifax
| northwest of [[Venlo]]
|
|
|-
| 17
| 31 August 1943
| 23:28
| Avro Lancaster
| east of [[Diepholz]]
|
|
|-
! colspan=&quot;7&quot; | – Junkers Ju 88 C-6 D5+DK –
|-
| 18
| 6 September 1943
| 00:14
| Four-engined bomber
| [[Saargebiet]]
|
|
|-
! colspan=&quot;7&quot; | – Junkers Ju 88 C-6 D5+LK –
|-
| 19
| 22 September 1943
| 23:35
| Handley Page Halifax
| [[Hanover]]
|
|
|-
! colspan=&quot;7&quot; | – Junkers Ju 88 C-6 D5+KK –
|-
| 20
| 23 September 1943
| 23:42
| Avro Lancaster
| [[Mannheim]]
|
|
|-
! colspan=&quot;7&quot; | – Junkers Ju 88 C-6 D5+LK –
|-
| 21
| 3 October 1943
| 21:56
| Handley Page Halifax
| northwest of [[Bad Zwischenahn]]
|
|
|-
| 22
| 8 October 1943
| 00:16
| Vickers Wellington
| {{Convert|30|km|mi|abbr=on|sp=us}} north of [[Norderney]]
|
|
|-
! colspan=&quot;7&quot; | – Junkers Ju 88 C-6 D5+IK –
|-
| 23
| 18 November 1943
| 23:12
| Avro Lancaster
| east of Lingen
|
|
|-
! colspan=&quot;7&quot; | – Junkers Ju 88 C-6 D5+AK –
|-
| 24
| 26 November 1943
| 22:22
| Avro Lancaster
| west of Quakenbrück
|
|
|-
! colspan=&quot;7&quot; | – Junkers Ju 88 C-6 D5+IK –
|-
| 25
| 26 November 1943
| 23:30
| Avro Lancaster
| east of [[Papenburg]]
|
|
|-
| 26
| 16 December 1943
| 21:49
| Avro Lancaster
| east of [[Dümmer]]
|
|
|-
! colspan=&quot;7&quot; | – Junkers Ju 88 C-6 D5+IP –
|-
| 27
| 21 January 1944
| 22:57
| Avro Lancaster
| [[Magdeburg]]
|
|
|-
| 28
| 21 January 1944
| 23:19
| Vickers Wellington
| Magdeburg
|
|
|-
! colspan=&quot;7&quot; | – Messerschmitt Bf 110 G-4 D5+HL –
|-
| 29
| 15 February 1944
| 19:58
| Four-engined bomber
| south of [[Wismar]]
|
|
|-
| style=&quot;background:#e3d9ff&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; | 30♠
| 20 February 1944
| 01:53
| Avro Lancaster
| northwest of Delmenhorst
|
|
|-
| style=&quot;background:#e3d9ff&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; | 31♠
| 20 February 1944
| 02:21
| Avro Lancaster
| south of [[Bremen]]
|
|
|-
| style=&quot;background:#e3d9ff&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; | 32♠
| 20 February 1944
| 02:48
| Avro Lancaster
| east of [[Celle]]
|
|
|-
| style=&quot;background:#e3d9ff&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; | 33♠
| 20 February 1944
| 04:33
| Avro Lancaster
| west of Vechta
|
|
|-
| style=&quot;background:#e3d9ff&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; | 34♠
| 20 February 1944
| 05:04
| Avro Lancaster
| north of Meppen
|
|
|-
! colspan=&quot;7&quot; | – Messerschmitt Bf 110 G-4 D5+BL –
|-
| 35
| 22 March 1944
| 21:38
| Avro Lancaster
| north of [[Osnabrück]]
|
|
|-
| 36
| 22 March 1944
| 21:54
| Handley Page Halifax
| west of [[Gütersloh]]
|
|
|-
! colspan=&quot;7&quot; | – Messerschmitt Bf 110 G-4 D5+CL –
|-
| 37
| 25 March 1944
| 00:22
| Avro Lancaster
| northwest of [[Essen, Lower Saxony|Essen]] in [[Oldenburg]]
|
|
|-
| 38
| 25 March 1944
| 00:39
| Avro Lancaster
| north of Quakenbrück
|
|
|-
| 39
| 25 March 1944
| 01:04
| Four-engined bomber
| south of Papenburg
|
|
|-
| 40
| 31 March 1944
| 00:01
| Avro Lancaster
| west of [[Vogelsberg]]
|
|
|-
| 41
| 31 March 1944
| 00:18
| Avro Lancaster
| north of [[Fulda]]
|
|
|-
| 42
| 31 March 1944
| 00:57
| Handley Page Halifax
| [[Rhön]]
|
|
|-
! colspan=&quot;7&quot; | – Messerschmitt Bf 110 G-4 D5+PL –
|-
| 43
| 23 April 1944
| 02:11
| Handley Page Halifax III
| north of [[Geldern]]
| [[No. 76 Squadron RAF|No. 76 Squadron]]
| ''MZ578''/MP-I&lt;ref&gt;Chorley 1997, p. 179.&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
! colspan=&quot;7&quot; | – Messerschmitt Bf 110 G-4 D5+CL –
|-
| 44
| 23 April 1944
| 23:30
| Short Stirling III
| Isle [[Lolland]]
|
|
|-
| 45
| 27 April 1944
| 01:58
| Avro Lancaster III
| east of [[Eindhoven]]
|
|
|}
&lt;/center&gt;

==Awards and decorations==
* [[Aviator badge]]
* [[Iron Cross]] (1939)
** 2nd Class (4 July 1941)&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann pii&quot;&gt;Schumann 2014, p. ii.&lt;/ref&gt;
** 1st Class (15 April 1942)&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann pii&quot;/&gt;
* [[Ehrenpokal der Luftwaffe]] on 9 August 1943 as ''[[Unteroffizier]]'' and pilot&lt;ref&gt;Patzwall 2008, p. 79.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Front Flying Clasp of the Luftwaffe]]
** in Silver (18 June 1942)&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann pii&quot;/&gt;
** in Gold (14 January 1944)&lt;ref name=&quot;Schumann pii&quot;/&gt;
* [[German Cross]] in Gold on 17 October 1943 as ''[[Unteroffizier]]'' in the 2./''Nachtjagdgeschwader'' 3&lt;ref&gt;Patzwall &amp; Scherzer 2001, p. 119.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves]]
** Knight's Cross on 6 April 1944 as ''[[Feldwebel]]'' and pilot in the 2./''Nachtjagdgeschwader'' 3&lt;ref name=&quot;Scherzer p315&quot;&gt;Scherzer 2007, p. 315.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fellgiebel 2000, p. 184.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Von Seemen 1976, p. 130.&lt;/ref&gt;
** 531st Oak Leaves on 20 July 1944 as ''[[Oberfeldwebel]]'' and pilot in the 2./''Nachtjagdgeschwader'' 3&lt;ref name=&quot;Scherzer p315&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fellgiebel 2000, p. 85.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Von Seemen 1976, p. 47.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{reflist|group=&quot;Note&quot;}}

==References==

===Citations===
{{Reflist|25em}}

===Bibliography===
{{Refbegin}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Chorley
  |first=W. R.
  |year=1996
  |title=Royal Air Force Bomber Command Losses of the Second World War: Aircraft and crew losses: 1943
  |location=Leicester
  |publisher=Midland Counties Publications
  |isbn=978-0-904597-90-5
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Chorley
  |first=W. R.
  |year=1997
  |title=Royal Air Force Bomber Command Losses of the Second World War: Aircraft and crew losses: 1944
  |location=Leicester
  |publisher=Midland Counties Publications
  |isbn=978-0-904597-91-2
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Fellgiebel
  |first=Walther-Peer
  |authorlink=Walther-Peer Fellgiebel
  |year=2000
  |origyear=1986
  |title=Die Träger des Ritterkreuzes des Eisernen Kreuzes 1939–1945 — Die Inhaber der höchsten Auszeichnung des Zweiten Weltkrieges aller Wehrmachtteile
  |trans_title=The Bearers of the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross 1939–1945 — The Owners of the Highest Award of the Second World War of all Wehrmacht Branches
  |language=German
  |location=Friedberg, Germany
  |publisher=Podzun-Pallas
  |isbn=978-3-7909-0284-6
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Hinchliffe
  |first=Peter
  |year=1999
  |title=Schnaufer: Ace of Diamonds
  |location=Brimscombe Port, UK
  |publisher=Tempus
  |isbn=978-0-7524-1690-8
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Obermaier
  |first=Ernst
  |year=1989
  |title=Die Ritterkreuzträger der Luftwaffe Jagdflieger 1939 – 1945
  |trans_title=The Knight's Cross Bearers of the Luftwaffe Fighter Force 1939 – 1945
  |language=German
  |location=Mainz, Germany
  |publisher=Verlag Dieter Hoffmann
  |isbn=978-3-87341-065-7
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last1=Patzwall
  |first1=Klaus D. 
  |last2=Scherzer
  |first2=Veit 
  |year=2001
  |title=Das Deutsche Kreuz 1941 – 1945 Geschichte und Inhaber Band II
  |trans_title=The German Cross 1941 – 1945 History and Recipients Volume 2
  |language=German
  |location=Norderstedt, Germany
  |publisher=Verlag Klaus D. Patzwall
  |isbn=978-3-931533-45-8
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Patzwall
  |first=Klaus D. 
  |year=2008
  |title=Der Ehrenpokal für besondere Leistung im Luftkrieg
  |trans_title=The Honor Goblet for Outstanding Achievement in the Air War
  |language=German
  |location=Norderstedt, Germany
  |publisher=Verlag Klaus D. Patzwall
  |isbn=978-3-931533-08-3
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Scherzer
  |first=Veit
  |year=2007
  |title=Die Ritterkreuzträger 1939–1945 Die Inhaber des Ritterkreuzes des Eisernen Kreuzes 1939 von Heer, Luftwaffe, Kriegsmarine, Waffen-SS, Volkssturm sowie mit Deutschland verbündeter Streitkräfte nach den Unterlagen des Bundesarchives
  |trans_title=The Knight's Cross Bearers 1939–1945 The Holders of the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross 1939 by Army, Air Force, Navy, Waffen-SS, Volkssturm and Allied Forces with Germany According to the Documents of the Federal Archives
  |language=German
  |location=Jena, Germany
  |publisher=Scherzers Militaer-Verlag
  |isbn=978-3-938845-17-2
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Schumann
  |first=Ralf
  |year=2014
  |title=Ritterkreuzträger Profile Nr. 13 Rudolf Frank — Eichenlaubträger der Nachtjagd
  |trans_title=Knight's Cross Profiles Nr. 13 Rudolf Frank — Oak Leaves Bearer of the Night Fighter Force
  |language=German
  |publisher=UNITEC-Medienvertrieb
  |oclc=883388135
  |id={{ASIN| B00JQ4TPDO | country=de| date=16 June 2014}}
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Von Seemen
  |first=Gerhard
  |year=1976
  |title=Die Ritterkreuzträger 1939–1945 : die Ritterkreuzträger sämtlicher Wehrmachtteile, Brillanten-, Schwerter- und Eichenlaubträger in der Reihenfolge der Verleihung : Anhang mit Verleihungsbestimmungen und weiteren Angaben
  |trans_title=The Knight's Cross Bearers 1939–1945 : The Knight's Cross Bearers of All the Armed Services, Diamonds, Swords and Oak Leaves Bearers in the Order of Presentation: Appendix with Further Information and Presentation Requirements
  |language=German
  |location=Friedberg, Germany
  |publisher=Podzun-Verlag
  |isbn=978-3-7909-0051-4
}}
{{Refend}}

===Further reading===
{{Refbegin}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Wingham
  |first=Tom
  |year=2009
  |title=Halifax Down!: On the Run from the Gestapo, 1944
  |location=London
  |publisher=Grub Street
  |isbn=978-1-906502-39-3
}}
{{Refend}}

{{KCwithOL}}
{{Knight's Cross recipients of NJG 3}}
{{Top German World War II night fighter aces}}
{{Subject bar
| portal1=Aviation
| portal2=Biography
| portal3=Military of Germany
| portal4=World War II
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Frank, Rudolf}}
[[Category:1920 births]]
[[Category:1944 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Karlsruhe]]
[[Category:Luftwaffe pilots]]
[[Category:German World War II flying aces]]
[[Category:German military personnel killed in World War II]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Gold German Cross]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves]]
[[Category:Burials at Ysselsteyn German war cemetery]]
[[Category:People from the Republic of Baden]]</text>
      <sha1>ngibc7ny1gn7h1rlymgvdgn45djjy9a</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
