<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Rupert Downes</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>11926402</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748582255</id>
      <parentid>735406923</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-09T00:29:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dl2000</username>
        <id>917223</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>en-AU</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="35980">{{Use Australian English|date=November 2016}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2011}}
{{Infobox military person
|name=Rupert Downes
|birth_date=10 February 1885
|death_date= {{Death date and age|1945|3|5|1885|2|10|df=yes}}
|birth_place=[[Mitcham, South Australia|Mitcham]], South Australia
|death_place=near [[Cairns]], Queensland
|image=Rupert Downes.jpg
|caption=Major General Rupert Downes
|alt=Head and shoulders of man in uniform with high collar and peaked cap.
|nickname=
|allegiance={{flagicon|Australia}}  [[Australia]]
|branch=[[File:Australian Army Emblem.JPG|25px]] [[Australian Army]]
|serviceyears=1901 – 1903&lt;br /&gt;1908 – 1945
|rank=[[Major General (Australia)|Major General]]
|commands=2nd Light Horse Field Ambulance&lt;br /&gt;3rd Light Horse Field Ambulance
|servicenumber=VX57673
|battles=First World War:
* [[Battle of Gallipoli]]
* [[Sinai and Palestine Campaign]]
Second World War
|awards=[[Companion of the Order of St Michael and St George]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Venerable Order of Saint John|Knight of Grace of the Venerable Order of Saint John]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Volunteer Decoration]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Mentioned in Despatches]] (4)
|relations= Son of [[Major Downes]]
}}

[[Major General (Australia)|Major General]] '''Rupert Major Downes''' [[Companion of the Order of St Michael and St George|CMG]], [[Venerable Order of Saint John|KStJ]], [[Volunteer Decoration|VD]], [[Fellow of the Royal Australasian College of Surgeons|FRACS]] (10 February 1885 – 5 March 1945) was an Australian soldier, general, surgeon and historian in the first half of the 20th century. Downes attended the [[University of Melbourne]], graduating with his medical degrees in 1907. He returned to the university to pursue a [[Doctor of Medicine]] degree, which was awarded in 1911.

The son of British Army officer [[Major Downes|Major Francis Downes]],&lt;ref name=&quot;adb&quot;/&gt; Downes joined the Army as a trumpeter while he was still at school. He was commissioned as a [[Captain (land and air)|captain]] in the [[Royal Australian Army Medical Corps|Australian Army Medical Corps]] in 1908, and joined the [[First Australian Imperial Force]] (AIF) in 1914 as its youngest [[lieutenant colonel]]. He served in the [[Battle of Gallipoli|Gallipoli campaign]], and was appointed Assistant Director of Medical Services (ADMS) of the newly formed [[ANZAC Mounted Division]] in 1916, which he combined with the post of ADMS AIF Egypt. In 1917, he became Deputy Director of Medical Services (DDMS) of the [[Desert Mounted Corps]]. After the war, he wrote articles on medical aspects of the [[Sinai and Palestine Campaign]], and the section on the campaign for the [[Official History of Australia in the War of 1914–1918|official history]].

Returning to Australia, Downes became an honorary consulting surgeon at the [[Royal Children's Hospital, Melbourne]] and [[Royal Victorian Eye and Ear Hospital]], and honorary surgeon at [[Monash Medical Centre|Prince Henry's Hospital]]. He became a foundation fellow of the [[Royal Australasian College of Surgeons|College of Surgeons of Australasia]] in 1927, and president of the Victorian branch of the [[British Medical Association]] in 1935. He lectured on [[medical ethics]] at the University of Melbourne, writing the course textbook. He was also Victorian State Commissioner of the St. John Ambulance Brigade, which he led for 25 years, and was president of the St John Ambulance Association for eight years.

In 1934 Downes became Director General of Medical Services, the Australian Army's most senior medical officer, with the rank of major general. He oversaw the construction of major military hospitals in the capital cities. In 1944 he accepted a commission to edit the medical series volumes of the Official History of [[Australia in the War of 1939–1945]] but was never able to do so as he was killed in a plane crash in 1945.

==Education and early life==
Rupert Major Downes was born on 10 February 1885 in [[Mitcham, South Australia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;adb&quot;&gt;{{Australian Dictionary of Biography |last= Hill |first= A. J. |authorlink= Alec Hill |year= 1981 |id= A080356b |title= Downes, Rupert Major  (1885–1945) |accessdate=5 November 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was the youngest of fifteen children of [[Colonel (United Kingdom)|Colonel]] Major Francis Downes—a [[British Army]] officer—and his wife Helen Maria, formerly Chamberlin, only five of whom survived to adulthood.{{sfn|Howie-Willis|2008|p=13}} After service in the [[Crimean War]],{{sfn|Howie-Willis|2008|p=10}} Colonel Francis Downes served as commandant of the [[Colonial forces of Australia|Colonial forces]] of South Australia and [[Victoria (Australia)|Victoria]] and retired with the rank of major general in the [[Australian Army]] in 1902.{{sfn|Howie-Willis|2008|pp=15–20}}

[[File:Opening of the first parliament.jpg|thumb|left|300px|[[Tom Roberts]]' painting of the opening of the first parliament in 1901. Downes is in the white helmet, behind the Duke of Cornwall and York's legs.{{sfn|Howie-Willis|2008|p=29}}|alt=Painting of a group of people stand on a stage, we a sea of people looking on. A man in a naval uniform stands at the front of the stage. Behind him are two women in mourning black.]]
Rupert was educated at [[Haileybury, Melbourne]] as a boarding student. In March 1901, at the age of 16, he joined the Victorian Horse Artillery (St Kilda Battery), a part-time volunteer militia unit, as a trumpeter. In May 1901 he served in this capacity at the opening of the inaugural [[Parliament of Australia]] by [[George V of the United Kingdom|The Duke of Cornwall and York]] at the [[Royal Exhibition Building]].{{sfn|Howie-Willis|2008|pp=26-29}} In 1903, Downes became a medical student at the [[University of Melbourne]]. A good result in his first year examinations earned him a residential scholarship to [[Ormond College (University of Melbourne)|Ormond College]], and he graduated with the double degree of [[Bachelor of Medicine, Bachelor of Surgery|Bachelor of Medicine and Bachelor of Surgery]] (MBBS) in 1907.{{sfn|Howie-Willis|2008|pp=32–34}}

Soon after graduation, Downes enlisted in the [[Australian Army Reserve|Militia]]. He was commissioned as a [[Captain (land and air)|captain]] in the [[Royal Australian Army Medical Corps|Australian Army Medical Corps]] on 1 July 1908 and was promoted to major on 26 March 1913.&lt;ref name=&quot;list&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Australian Army|1945}}&lt;/ref&gt; He served his [[Residency (medicine)|residency]] at [[Royal Melbourne Hospital|Melbourne Hospital]] and became a [[general practitioner]] in [[Malvern, Victoria]], but soon returned to the university to pursue a doctorate. His [[Doctor of Medicine]] (MD) thesis, entitled &quot;The anatomical relations of the Thymus, especially considered in regard to thymic death with an account of cases of abnormality&quot;, was accepted in 1911. He also did the coursework for a [[Master of Surgery]] (MS), and this degree was conferred in 1912.{{sfn|Howie-Willis|2008|pp=37–38}}

Downes married Doris Mary Robb on 20 November 1913 at St John's Church, [[Toorak, Victoria]]. They had three children: Rosemary Major, born in 1914;{{sfn|Howie-Willis|2008|p=32}} Valerie Major, born in March 1918;{{sfn|Howie-Willis|2008|p=44}} and John Rupert Major, born in 1922.{{sfn|Howie-Willis|2008|p=226}}

==First World War==
Downes joined the [[First Australian Imperial Force]] (AIF) on 2 October 1914, assuming command of the 2nd Light Horse Field Ambulance with the rank of [[lieutenant colonel]]&lt;ref name=&quot;list&quot; /&gt;—making him the youngest officer of that rank in the AIF at the time. Soon after his taking command, the unit was renamed the 3rd Light Horse Field Ambulance.&lt;ref name=&quot;adb&quot; /&gt; After training at the [[Broadmeadows, Victoria|Broadmeadows]] Army Camp near Melbourne, the unit embarked for [[Egypt]] on the transport ''Chilka'' on 2 February 1915.{{sfn|Howie-Willis|2008|p=59}}

The 3rd Light Horse Field Ambulance departed [[Alexandria]] for [[Battle of Gallipoli|Gallipoli]] on 17 May 1915.{{sfn|Howie-Willis|2008|p=85}} It moved to [[Lemnos]] in June, where it operated a hospital, but returned to [[ANZAC Cove]] for the [[Battle of Sari Bair|August offensive]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Howie-Willis 2008 p=90&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Howie-Willis|2008|p=90}}&lt;/ref&gt; Downes missed this operation, as he remained on Lemnos supervising the hospital until he returned to Anzac on 11 August.&lt;ref name=&quot;Howie-Willis 2008 p=90&quot;/&gt; He remained with his unit until 13 November, when he departed for Lemnos and then Egypt.&lt;ref name=&quot;Howie-Willis 2008 p=101&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Howie-Willis|2008|p=101}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Desert Mounted Corps HQ Staff.jpg|thumb|right|300px|upright|Lieutenant General Sir Harry Chauvel (front and centre) with his Desert Mounted Corps Headquarters. Colonel Downes is immediately behind and to the right of Chauvel|alt=About thirty soldiers and two dogs pose on the steps of a building beneath a pair of arches]]
After the evacuation of Gallipoli, Downes was appointed Assistant Director of Medical Services (ADMS) of the newly formed [[ANZAC Mounted Division]] on 15 March 1916. He was given the temporary rank of [[colonel]], before substantive promotion on 20 February 1917. Downes combined this post with that of ADMS AIF Egypt from 6 September 1916.&lt;ref name=&quot;list&quot; /&gt; Downes therefore had to travel back and forth to Cairo. In November 1916, a Deputy ADMS was appointed to assist him.{{sfn|Downes|1930|pp=646–647}}

Medically speaking, the health of the Anzac Mounted Division was remarkably good,{{sfn|Downes|1930|pp=598–599}} but the [[Sinai Peninsula]] still had its challenges—especially for medical officers unfamiliar with conditions in the Middle East. The [[Battle of Romani]] revealed the importance of transportation in an area with few roads.{{sfn|Downes|1930|pp=582–585}} A poorly organised casualty  evacuation effort caused a great deal of preventable hardship and suffering for the wounded, and resulted in a number of avoidable deaths.{{sfn|Downes|1930|p=580}}  An inquiry into the matter was held after the battle,  at which Downes was called to testify.{{sfn|Howie-Willis|2008|pp=133-135}} The Commander in Chief if the [[Egyptian Expeditionary Force]] (EEF), General Sir [[Archibald Murray]], declined to assign blame to any individual, but implemented the inquiry's recommendations for improving the casualty evacuation process.{{sfn|Downes|1930|p=580}}

There was also the heat, and the problem of supplying adequate quantities of [[potable water]]. Diseases included [[cholera]], [[typhus]] and [[bilharzia]]. To combat these, Downes obtained the services of the Lieutenant Colonel [[Charles James Martin (scientist)|Charles James Martin]], {{sfn|Howie-Willis|2008|p=138}} and created the Anzac Field Laboratory to investigate these diseases.{{sfn|Downes|1930|p=651}} As a result of aggressively tackling the problem, Downes reduced rates of disease among Australian and New Zealand troops well below those of British troops serving alongside them. Martin advanced the notion that heat exhaustion and heat stroke were not the result of defective evaporation, as had previously been believed, but simply a matter of failing to drink enough water. He in turn converted Downes to the belief that &quot;provided water is available in adequate amount the heat mechanism of the body can defy all ordinary climatic ranges of temperature even under conditions of hard work.&quot;{{sfn|Downes|1930|pp=600–602}} With so many people and horses, sanitation was a challenge, and discipline in this area was initially slack, as it had been with disastrous results at Gallipoli. Downes took measures to improve the situation.{{sfn|Downes|1930|pp=600–611}} Although not normally one to engage in disputes, Downes repeatedly clashed with the British medical officers of the EEF, especially the DMS EEF, Colonel Alfred &lt;!-- Ernest Conquer --&gt; Keble, whose attitudes Downes regarded as endangering his troops.{{sfn|Howie-Willis|2008|pp=143, 164}}

Doris travelled to Egypt to visit her husband in March 1917. By June, Rupert was becoming increasingly immersed in preparations for the [[Third Battle of Gaza]] and Doris, who had become pregnant during her visit, decided to return home.&lt;ref name=&quot;Howie-Willis 2008 p=101&quot;/&gt; On her return journey to Australia in June 1917, her ship, the [[Peninsular and Oriental Steam Navigation Company|P&amp;O]] liner ''Mongolia'' struck a [[Naval mine|mine]] and was sunk in the Indian Ocean with the loss of 23 lives.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=P&amp;O Line |url=http://www.theshipslist.com/ships/lines/pando.html |publisher=Swiggum |accessdate=19 May 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Doris spent 11 hours in a crowded lifeboat, before being rescued by a passing steamer, which took her to [[Bombay]]. From there she eventually made her way back to Australia via Singapore and [[Batavia, Dutch East Indies|Batavia]].{{sfn|Howie-Willis|2008|p=102}} In 1918 Doris was appointed an [[Officer of the Order of the British Empire]] (OBE) for her volunteer work among soldiers' families as secretary of the Friendly Union of Soldiers' Wives and Mothers.&lt;ref&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue=30935|supp=yes|startpage=11772|date=4 October 1918|accessdate=2 August 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Howie-Willis|2008|p=155}}

On 10 August 1917, Downes became Deputy Director of Medical Services (DDMS) of the [[Desert Mounted Corps]], while still retaining the post of ADMS AIF Egypt.&lt;ref name=&quot;list&quot; /&gt; He was therefore answerable to three superiors—to [[Lieutenant General (Australia)|Lieutenant General]] [[Harry Chauvel]], the commander of the Desert Mounted Corps and AIF Egypt; to Major General [[Neville Howse]], the DMS AIF in London; and to the new British DMS EEF, Major General [[William Travers Swan]].{{sfn|Downes|1930|pp=647–650}} As the EEF advanced into Palestine, the major medical problem remained transportation. During the operations in the Es Salt area, Downes experimented with the delivery of drugs and medical supplies by air.{{sfn|Downes|1930|pp=693–694}} In the Jordan valley in 1918, however, Downes was confronted with an epidemic of [[malaria]] and vigorous preventative and prophylactic efforts were required in order to bring it under control.{{sfn|Downes|1930|pp=705–713}}

In October 1918, with victory near, Downes was confronted by his most serious medical crisis. [[Damascus]] contained over 3,000 sick and wounded Turkish soldiers, many of them in appalling condition.{{sfn|Downes|1930|p=729}} Downes appointed the DADMS of the Australian Mounted Division, Major W. Evans, as Principal Medical Officer of Damascus, and gave him orders to organise the medical arrangements, bury the dead and provide care for the living.{{sfn|Downes|1930|p=731}} The task was made more difficult by the poor communications and transport shortages, which hampered the delivery of supplies and evacuation of the hospitals; by shortages of medical units; and by the actions of Lieutenant Colonel [[T. E. Lawrence]], who was more concerned with establishing the political authority of [[Hussein bin Ali, Sharif of Mecca]] over Damascus.{{sfn|Downes|1930|pp=732–735}} At this point the Desert Mounted Corps itself began to experience epidemic diseases, particularly of [[bronchopneumonia]], [[cholera]] and [[malaria]], putting the medical services under enormous pressure. Through extraordinary measures, including the diversion of lighthorsemen and motor vehicles to medical units, Downes managed to evacuate the sick to [[Beirut]], and the crisis abated.{{sfn|Downes|1930|pp=736–741}}

For his service in the [[Sinai and Palestine Campaign]], Downes was [[mentioned in despatches]] four times,&lt;ref&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue=29845|supp=yes|startpage=11807|date=1 December 1916|accessdate=2 August 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue=30474|supp=yes|startpage=804|date=12 January 1918|accessdate=1 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue=31138|supp=yes|startpage=1164|date=22 January 1919|accessdate=1 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue=31383|supp=yes|startpage=7189|date=5 June 1919|accessdate=1 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; and was appointed a [[Companion of the Order of St Michael and St George]] on 1 January 1918.&lt;ref&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue=30450|supp=yes|startpage=6|date=1 January 1918|accessdate=2 August 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue=30514|supp=yes|startpage=1802|date=5 February 1918|accessdate=2 August 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; His citation read:
{{quote|In addition to his duties as ADMS Australian and New Zealand Mounted Division, Colonel Downes has carried out those of A.D.M.S., Australian Imperial Force in Egypt for many months. He has shown considerable administrative ability and has placed Australian A.M.C. matters on a much better footing than they were when he took over the appointment.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Honours and Awards – R M Downes |url=http://www.awm.gov.au/cms_images/AWM28/2/360/0010.pdf |publisher=[[Australian War Memorial]] |accessdate=1 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Interwar years==
Returning to Australia, Downes was discharged from the AIF, but remained in the Army as a reservist. He became an honorary consulting surgeon at the [[Royal Children's Hospital, Melbourne]] and [[Royal Victorian Eye and Ear Hospital]], and honorary surgeon at [[Monash Medical Centre|Prince Henry's Hospital]].&lt;ref name=&quot;adb&quot; /&gt; He was a founding fellow of the [[Royal Australasian College of Surgeons|College of Surgeons of Australasia]] in 1927, and became president of the Victorian branch of the [[British Medical Association]] in 1935.&lt;ref name=&quot;adb&quot; /&gt; He established a reputation as one of Melbourne's leading [[Pediatrics|paediatric surgeons]],{{sfn|Howie-Willis|2008|p=236}} but found himself in disagreement with certain medical practices then in vogue. In a 1922 paper published in the ''Medical Journal of Australia'', he examined 100 cases of [[tonsillectomy]] in children, and concluded that the majority of them were unnecessary. It would be another four decades before the medical profession in Australia accepted this.{{sfn|Howie-Willis|2008|p=228}} He lectured on [[medical ethics]] at the University of Melbourne from the late 1930s until his death in 1945,{{sfn|Howie-Willis|2008|p=233}} and wrote a course textbook on the subject, entitled ''Medical Ethics'', which was published in 1942.{{sfn|Downes|Anderson|1942}}

In addition to his medical writings, Downes wrote a book-length section on the Sinai and Palestine campaign for Volume I of the [[Official History of Australia in the War of 1914–1918|''Official History of the Australian Army Medical Services in the War of 1914–1918'']]{{sfn|Downes|1930|pp=547–713}} in the late 1920s under the direction of Medical Series editor Graham Butler. The two men had discussed the prospect during a visit Butler made to Egypt in 1918 to inspect the medical records of the AIF, and again in France in 1919. Downes published an article in the ''Journal of the British Army Medical Corps'' entitled &quot;The Tactical Employment of the Medical Services in a Cavalry Corps&quot; in 1926, which was expanded into one of the chapters of the Official History. Downes' manuscript proved too long for the proposed book, and was extensively edited by Butler before it was published in 1930.{{sfn|Howie-Willis|2008|pp=227–229}} Downes was instrumental in supporting Butler's Medical Series and helped obtain the funding necessary to complete the project.{{sfn|O'Keefe|1988|pp=29–30}}

Downes was chairman of the Masseurs' Registration Board, a councillor of the Victorian division of the [[Australian Red Cross]], and chairman of the Red Cross National Council. He was Victorian State Commissioner of the [[St. John Ambulance]] Brigade for 25 years. He was also president of the St John Ambulance Association for eight years, and chairman of the Victorian Civil Ambulance Service from 1937 to 1938.&lt;ref name=&quot;adb&quot; /&gt; In 1930, he was appointed a Commander of the [[Venerable Order of Saint John]],&lt;ref&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue=33618|startpage=3956|date=24 June 1930|accessdate=20 May 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; and later became a Knight of Grace of the order in 1937.&lt;ref&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue=34356|startpage=2|date=1 January 1937|accessdate=20 May 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, Doris became an Officer of the Order of Saint John,&lt;ref&gt;{{LondonGazette|issue=34356|startpage=4|date=1 January 1937|accessdate=20 May 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; in recognition for her fund raising efforts for the Victorian branch. She also later served as a member of its council from 1942 to 1953. Downes was instrumental in persuading the various state branches to come together as a national organisation, arguing that without a national body, the organisation would be eclipsed by the Red Cross.{{sfn|Howie-Willis|2008|pp=242-245}}

In 1930, Downes' son John, then in his first year as a boarder at [[Geelong Grammar School]], fell seriously ill with [[meningitis]]. Despite the best efforts of two eminent medical practitioners, Dr Keith Fairley and Dr Reginald Webster, John succumbed to [[Bacteremia|toxaemia]] and died in 1933, at the age of 10. The failure of modern medicine to save his son affected Downes deeply, and led him to abandon his medical career in favour of a military one.{{sfn|Howie-Willis|2008|pp=251-253}}

[[File:Medical Officers 1936.png|thumb|left|300px|Army Medical officers participate in a training exercise in the southern highlands of New South Wales in April 1936. Downes is front row, centre.|alt=A group of men in suits pose for a picture.]]
Downes remained in the Army throughout the inter-war period. He became a colonel in the [[Royal Australian Army Medical Corps|Australian Army Medical Corps]] on 8 January 1920. He was DDMS of the 3rd Military District (Victoria) from 1 July 1921 to 26 June 1933, and Officer in Charge of [[Voluntary Aid Detachment]]s from 1 July 1921 to 15 March 1940.&lt;ref name=&quot;list&quot; /&gt; He also served as head of the medical services of the [[Royal Australian Air Force]] (RAAF). Although the RAAF had become a separate service in 1921, the [[Minister for Defence (Australia)|Minister for Defence]] decided in 1927 that the Army's Director General of Medical Services  should be responsible for the administration of the RAAF's medical services. In this capacity, Downes was answerable to the Air Board.{{sfn|Walker|1961|pp=173–181}} In addition, he was honorary surgeon to the [[Governor General of Australia]] from 1 July 1927 to 30 June 1931.&lt;ref name=&quot;list&quot; /&gt;

On 20 August 1934 Downes became Director General of Medical Services (DGMS), a full-time post and the Army's most senior medical officer.&lt;ref name=&quot;list&quot; /&gt; His priority was a recruiting campaign to increase the number of medical professionals in the Army. {{sfn|Howie-Willis|2008|p=263}} The [[Munich Agreement|Munich Crisis]] caused people to believe that another war was imminent, and an Army-wide recruiting campaign led by Major General Sir [[Thomas Blamey]] doubled the size of the Army from 35,000 in 1938 to 70,000 in 1939.{{sfn|Long|1952|p=26}} Downes' efforts at recruiting were far more modest. In 1934, there were 299 part-time officers in the AAMC; by 1939 there were 394, and increase of only 32 per cent. This included 320 medical practitioners, 37 dentists and 13 pharmacists.{{sfn|Howie-Willis|2008|p=263}} Downes was acutely aware that a large Army would require mobilisation of the country's doctors, and pushed for all doctors to be prepared for either military service or direction by civil authorities. He presided over a major effort to stockpile drugs and medical equipment required for a mobilisation. With the help of the [[Department of Health and Ageing|Department of Health]] and the [[Commonwealth Serum Laboratories]], most of this was delivered by July 1939.{{sfn|Walker|1953|pp=14–20}}

In 1939, Downes began a tour of military and other medical centres in [[India]], the Middle East, the United Kingdom, France, the United States and Canada.&lt;ref name=&quot;Walker, p. 20&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Walker|1953|p=20}}&lt;/ref&gt; While in London, he arranged for Doris and Valerie to be formally presented to the [[George VI of the United Kingdom|King]] and [[Elizabeth Bowes-Lyon|Queen]] at [[Buckingham Palace]] by Ethel Bruce, the wife of [[Stanley Bruce]], the [[Australian High Commissioner to the United Kingdom]].{{sfn|Howie-Willis|2008|p=279}} Downes foresaw a major war, fought in the islands to the north of Australia. While in London, he took steps to obtain the services as consultants of two eminent Australian physicians, the surgeon Sir [[Thomas Dunhill (surgeon)|Thomas Dunhill]] and [[Neil Hamilton Fairley]], an expert on tropical diseases.{{sfn|Walker|1953|p=32}} The outbreak of the Second World War caused Downes to curtail the North American leg of his tour, and return to Australia in October 1939.&lt;ref name=&quot;Walker, p. 20&quot; /&gt;

==Second World War==
[[File:Vasey Funeral AWM087410.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Generals Simpson, Blamey, and Morshead pay their respects at the military funeral service for Generals Vasey and Downes in Cairns.|alt=A group of soldiers in shirt sleeves stand at attention.]]
Downes, in his role as DGMS, pressed for the construction of major military hospitals in the capital cities. He argued that, after the war, they should be handed over to the Repatriation Commission for the care of sick and disabled ex-service personnel. Despite strong opposition on the grounds of cost, Downes won his case in October 1940. Time soon vindicated his judgement; and today the major military hospitals in the state capital cities, the [[Concord Repatriation General Hospital]] in Sydney, the [[Austin Hospital, Melbourne|Austin Hospital]] in Melbourne and [[Greenslopes Private Hospital]] in [[Brisbane]] remain his greatest legacy.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Walker|1953|pp=78–81}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In late 1940, medical units in the Middle East were experienced &quot;precarious and at times acute&quot; shortages of medicals stores. Units were sent to the Middle East as fully equipped as was possible, with the expectation that the British Army would make up the difference, but British policy was that all possible sources had to be exploited before any demands could be made on the United Kingdom's sources. [[General (Australia)|General]] Sir [[Thomas Blamey]], the Commander in Chief of the AIF, recognised this as something that had to be negotiated between the two governments,&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Walker|1953|pp=333–339}}&lt;/ref&gt; but medical officers in the Middle East blamed the Medical Services in Australia—and therefore Downes—for the situation. The Minister of the Army, [[Percy Spender]] decided to pay a visit to the Middle East to see the situation for himself but before he did so, he resolved that Downes should become Director of Medical Services, AIF (Middle East). On arrival in the Middle East with the [[Chief of Army (Australia)|Chief of the General Staff]], Lieutenant General [[Vernon Sturdee]], Spender found that Blamey had already appointed Major General [[Samuel Burston]] to that post. This came as a surprise to them as they had not realised that Blamey had the authority to make such an appointment; but on seeing the situation for himself, Spender confirmed Burston's appointment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Howie-Willis, pp. 305-309&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Howie-Willis|2008|pp=305–309}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On returning to Australia, Spender appointed Major General F. A. Maguire as DGMS and Downes was appointed to the newly created post of Inspector General of Medical Services (IGMS).&lt;ref name=&quot;Howie-Willis, pp. 305-309&quot; /&gt; As IGMS, Downes toured extensively—he visited all the Australian states and overseas locations where Australian troops had been sent, including Papua and New Guinea, Malaya, the Middle East and North Africa, as well as the Netherlands East Indies (Indonesia), India and East Africa.&lt;ref name=&quot;adb&quot; /&gt; When Blamey reorganised the Army on his return to Australia in 1942, he appointed Burston as Director General of Medical Services. Downes became DMS of the [[Second Army (Australia)|Second Army]] on 6 April 1942. He joined the [[Second Australian Imperial Force|Second AIF]] as a major general on 27 June 1942,&lt;ref name=&quot;list&quot; /&gt; receiving the AIF serial number VX57673.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.ww2roll.gov.au/Veteran.aspx?serviceId=A&amp;veteranId=465312 |title=WW2 Nominal Roll |publisher=[[Australian War Memorial]] |accessdate=23 May 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Death and legacy==
Downes held this post until 22 August 1944. Due to the run-down of the Army, the Second Army, always mainly a paper organisation, increasingly had less and less to do. Now nearly sixty, he then accepted an invitation to write the medical history series of the [[Australia in the War of 1939–1945|official history of Australia in the war]]. As part of this, in March 1945, he decided to accompany Major General [[George Alan Vasey]] to New Guinea, where Vasey's [[6th Division (Australia)|6th Division]] had encountered an [[Quinacrine|atabrine]]-resistant strain of [[malaria]] in the [[Aitape-Wewak campaign]]. On 5 March 1945, the RAAF [[Lockheed Hudson]] aircraft they were travelling in crashed into the sea about {{convert|400|yd}} from Machans Beach, just north of the mouth of the [[Barron River (Queensland)|Barron River]] near [[Cairns]]. Downes and Vasey were killed along with all nine other Australian service personnel on board. Their bodies were recovered and buried in Cairns War Cemetery with full military honours. Downes was survived by Doris, Valerie and Rosemary. A memorial service was held at [[St Paul's Cathedral, Melbourne]] on 9 March 1945.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Howie-Willis|2008|pp=349–356}}&lt;/ref&gt; He became the third most senior Australian officer to die in the Second World War, after General Sir [[Brudenell White]], who died in the [[Canberra air disaster, 1940|Canberra air disaster]] in 1940,&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Long|1952|pp=89–90}}&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Lieutenant General]] [[Henry Wynter]], who died on 7 February 1945.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Long|1952|p=8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Downes' papers are in the [[Australian War Memorial]].&lt;ref&gt;Downes papers, AWM 3DRL/0518&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Royal Australasian College of Surgeons]] established the triennial Rupert Downes Memorial Lecture in his honour. The subject of the Lecture is &quot;related to some aspect or aspects of military surgery, medical equipment (military and civil), the surgery of children, neurosurgery, general surgery, medical ethics or medical history; these being subjects in which Downes was particularly interested&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Rupert Downes Memorial Lecture and Medal |url=http://www.surgeons.org/racs/about-the-college/awards,-lectures-and-prizes/lectures-and-prizes#rupert_downes |publisher=[[Royal Australasian College of Surgeons]] |accessdate=6 August 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Rupert Downes Memorial Lectures==
* 1950 Major General [[Samuel Burston]] ''Some Medical Aspects of Atomic Warfare''
* 1954 A.S. Walker ''The Following Wind of History''
* 1957 F.K. Norris ''Be Strong and of Good Courage''
* 1961 Sir Albert Coates ''The Doctor in the Services''
* 1965 D. Waterson ''Œsophageal Replacement in Pædiatric Surgery''
* 1970 J.H. Louw ''The Scientific Method in Surgery''
* 1972 H.E. Beardmore ''Pædiatric Surgery – Yesterday, Today, and Tomorrow, and Tomorrow, and Tomorrow''
* 1976 P.P. Rickham ''Nephroblastoma – a New Look at an Old Problem''
* 1978 C.M. Gurner ''Military Medical Preparedness''
* 1980 D.G. Hamilton ''One Hundred Years of Pædiatric Surgery in Sydney''
* 1983 G.B. Ong ''The Trifacetted Nature of Surgery in Hong Kong''
* 1988 B.A. Smithurst ''Distinguished Australian Military Surgeons''
* 1990 Patricia K. Donahoe ''The Development of Tumour Inhibitors''
* 1994 General Sir [[Phillip Bennett]] ''Medical Aspects of Australia’s Defence''
* 1996 Professor Averil Mansfield ''Arterio-Venous Malformations and their Treatment''
* 1998 D. Trunkey ''I am Giddy, Expectation Whirls me Round''
* 2000 A. Wyn Beasley ''Of Scurvy and Shipwreck – the Dutch Discovery of Australasia''
* 2002 Colonel D. Beard ''The Music of Warfare''
* 2005 Robert Pearce ''Trust me, Claudius''
* 2008 Professor [[Arthur Li]] ''Ethics and standards''
* 2011 Major General John Pearn ''Pro patria et spe gentis''

Source: {{cite web |title=Rupert Downes Memorial Lecture and Medal |url=http://www.surgeons.org/member-services/scholarships-awards-lectures-prizes/lectures-and-prizes/lecturers-and-prize-recipients/#rdml |publisher=[[Royal Australasian College of Surgeons]] |accessdate=6 January 2014 }}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
*{{cite journal
 | last = Australian Army
 | journal=The Army List of Officers of the Australian Military Forces 
 | publisher=Australian Army
 | location = Melbourne
 | year = 1945
 | oclc = 220688670 
 | ref = harv
}}
*{{cite book
 | last = Downes
 | first = Rupert M.
 | authorlink = Rupert Downes
 | contribution = The Campaign in Sinai and Palestine
 | title = Gallipoli, Palestine and New Guinea
 | volume = Volume I
 | url = https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1069845/
 | year = 1930 
 | series = [[Official History of Australia in the War of 1914-1918|Official History of the Australian Army Medical Services, 1914–1918]]
 | publisher=Australian War Memorial
 | location = Canberra
 | oclc = 156690674
 | ref = harv
 }}
*{{cite book
 | last = Downes
 | first = Rupert M.
 | authorlink = Rupert Downes
 | last2 = Anderson
 | first2 = A. V. M.
 | title = Medical Ethics
 | publisher=W. Ramsay
 | year = 1942
 | location = Melbourne
 | isbn = 
 | oclc = 37101595
 | ref = harv
}}
*{{cite book
 | last = Howie-Willis
 | first = Ian
 | title = Surgeon and General: A Life of Major General Rupert Downes 1885–1945
 | publisher=Australian Military History Publications
 | year = 2008
 | location = Loftus, New South Wales
 | isbn = 978-0-9804753-3-3
 | oclc = 271862033
 | ref = harv
}}
* {{cite book
 | last = Long 
 | first = Gavin 
 | authorlink = Gavin Long 
 | title = To Benghazi 
 | url = https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070200/
 | work=[[Australia in the War of 1939–1945]] Series 1 – Army
 | year = 1952
 | publisher=Australian War Memorial
 | location = Canberra
 | oclc = 3134176
 | ref = harv
}}
* {{cite journal
 | last= O'Keefe
 | first = Brendan
 | title = Butler's Medical Histories
 | pages = 25–34 
 | journal=Journal of the Australian War Memorial 
 | publisher=Australian War Memorial
 | location=Canberra
 
 | issue = 12
 | date = April 1988
 | issn = 0729-6274
 | ref = harv
}}
* {{cite book
 | url = https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070219/
 | title = Middle East and Far East
 | volume = Volume II 
 | last = Walker 
 | first = Allan S.
 | year = 1953
 | work=[[Australia in the War of 1939–1945]] Series 5 – Medical 
 | publisher=Australian War Memorial
 | location = Canberra
 | oclc = 19769283
 | ref = harv
}}
* {{cite book
 | url = https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070221/
 | title = Medical Services of the Royal Australian Navy and Royal Australian Air Force with a section on women in the Army Medical Services
 | volume = Volume IV 
 | last = Walker 
 | first = Allan S.
 | year = 1961
 | work=[[Australia in the War of 1939–1945]] Series 5 – Medical 
 | publisher=Australian War Memorial
 | location = Canberra
 | accessdate =1 April 2009
 | oclc = 4059171
 | ref = harv
}}

{{Good Article}}
{{Australian Generals of World War II}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Downes, Rupert}}
[[Category:1885 births]]
[[Category:1945 deaths]]
[[Category:Accidental deaths in Queensland]]
[[Category:Australian generals]]
[[Category:Australian medical doctors]]
[[Category:Australian military historians]]
[[Category:Australian military personnel killed in World War II]]
[[Category:Australian military personnel of World War I]]
[[Category:Australian military personnel of World War II]]
[[Category:Companions of the Order of St Michael and St George]]
[[Category:Knights of Grace of the Order of St John]]
[[Category:Melbourne Medical School alumni]]
[[Category:Victims of aviation accidents or incidents in Australia]]
[[Category:People educated at Haileybury, Melbourne]]
[[Category:20th-century Australian historians]]
[[Category:Fellows of the Royal Australasian College of Surgeons]]</text>
      <sha1>0f4pivevf8jsmwnid89r660wra8h87q</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
