<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Serbian State Guard</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5218056</id>
    <revision>
      <id>743024627</id>
      <parentid>743024538</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-07T09:13:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Peacemaker67</username>
        <id>15690513</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Books */ added authorlink</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22200">{{good article}}
{{Infobox military unit
|unit_name= Serbian State Guard&lt;br&gt;''Srpska državna straža'' (SDS)
|image= 
|caption=
|dates=1942–45
|allegiance={{flagicon image|S Flag.svg}} [[Government of National Salvation]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Nazi Germany]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon image|Chetniks Flag.svg}} [[Chetniks]] (1944–45)
|country=
|branch=
|type=[[Paramilitary]] [[gendarmerie]]
|role=Anti-[[Yugoslav Partisans|Partisan]] operations
|size=25,000–36,000
|command_structure=
|garrison=
|garrison_label=
|nickname=''Nedićevci''
|patron=
|motto=
|colors=
|colors_label=
|march=
|mascot=
|equipment=
|equipment_label=
|battles=[[World War II in Yugoslavia]]
|anniversaries=
|decorations=
|battle_honours=
&lt;!-- Commanders --&gt;
|commander1=
|commander1_label=
|commander2=
|commander2_label=
|commander3=
|commander3_label=
|notable_commanders=[[Dragomir Jovanović]]&lt;br&gt;[[Milan Kalabić]]
}}

The '''Serbian State Guard''' ({{lang-sh|Srpska državna straža or SDS, Српска државна стража}}; {{lang-de|Serbische Staatsgarde}}) was an auxiliary [[paramilitary]] force used to impose law and order within the [[Territory of the Military Commander in Serbia]] during the [[Nazi Germany|German]] [[military occupation]] of the [[Kingdom of Yugoslavia]] in [[World War II]]. It was formed from two former Yugoslav [[gendarmerie]] regiments, was created with the approval of the German military authorities, and for a long period was controlled by the [[SS and Police Leader|Higher SS and Police Leader]] in the Territory. It was also known as the '''Nedićevci''' after the leader of the Serbian pro-[[Axis powers|Axis]] puppet government, General [[Milan Nedić]], who eventually gained control of its operations. It assisted the Germans in imposing one of the most brutal occupation regimes in occupied Europe and helped guard and execute prisoners at the [[Banjica concentration camp]] in [[Belgrade]]. Its leaders and much of the [[wikt:rank and file|rank and file]] were sympathetic to the [[Chetnik]] movement of [[Draža Mihailović]], and it was purged by the Germans on several occasions for that reason. In October 1944, as the [[Red Army]] closed on Belgrade, the SDS was transferred to Mihailović's control by a member of the fleeing Nedić administration, but it quickly disintegrated during its withdrawal west, with only a small number of former SDS members being captured by the [[British Army during the Second World War|British]] near the [[Kingdom of Italy|Italian]]-Yugoslav border in May 1945.

==History==

===Background===
Following the [[Axis powers|Axis]] [[Invasion of Yugoslavia|invasion, occupation and dismantling of Yugoslavia]] in April 1941, the [[Wehrmacht]] established the [[Territory of the Military Commander in Serbia]]{{sfnm|Hehn|1971|1p=350|Pavlowitch|2002|2p=141|ps=, official name of the occupied territory.}} under a [[Martial law|military government]] of [[military occupation|occupation]]. The territory included most of [[Serbia proper]], with the addition of the [[Kosovo|northern part of Kosovo]] (around [[Kosovska Mitrovica]]), and the [[Banat (1941–1944)|Banat]].{{sfn|Tomasevich|2001|pp=63–64}} It was the only area of the partitioned [[Kingdom of Yugoslavia]] in which the German occupants established a military government, to exploit the key rail and [[Danube|riverine transport]] routes that passed through it, and its valuable resources, particularly [[non-ferrous metal]]s.{{sfn|Tomasevich|2001|p=64}} The Military Commander in Serbia appointed Serbian [[puppet government]]s to &quot;carry on administrative chores under German direction and supervision&quot;.{{sfn|Tomasevich|2001|p=177}} On 29 August 1941, the Germans appointed the [[Government of National Salvation]] (''Vlada Nacionalnog Spasa'', Влада Националног Спаса) under General [[Milan Nedić]], to replace the short-lived Commissioner Administration.{{sfn|Tomasevich|2001|p=179}}

===Formation===
[[File:Territory Of The German Military Commander In Serbia 1941-44.png|thumb|Map of the Territory of the Military Commander in Serbia. The five battalions of the SDS were based in Belgrade, Kraljevo, Niš, Valjevo and Zaječar.]]
The Serbian State Guard (or SDS) was established by Nedić on the basis of an understanding he reached with the German Military Commander in Serbia, ''[[General of the Artillery (Germany)|General der Artillerie]]'' (Lieutenant General) [[Paul Bader]], and the [[SS and Police Leader|Higher SS and Police Leader]] in Serbia, ''SS-[[Obergruppenführer]] und [[General (Germany)|Generalleutnant]] der Polizei'' (SS-General of Police) [[August Meyszner]],{{sfn|Cohen|1996|p=39}} regarding the maintenance of law and order in the occupied territory. It was formed on 10 February 1942 from two former Yugoslav gendarmerie regiments, ''Drinski'' and ''Dunavski'',{{sfn|Thomas|Mikulan|1995|p=21}} but the law formally creating the force was not issued by Nedić until 2 March 1942. The SDS took over the role and functions of the gendarmerie, and was initially commanded by Stevan Radovanović.{{sfn|Ramet|Lazić|2011|p=24}} Sources vary on the strength of the SDS. The Germans initially set a maximum strength of 17,000, but the SDS quickly reached a strength of 18,500.{{sfn|Cohen|1996|p=39}} Initially the SDS included four groups, the Rural Police (''poljska straža''), the Municipal Police (''gradska straža''), the Frontier (or Border) Guard (''granična straža''), and the Village Guard (''seljačka straža'').{{sfn|Thomas|Mikulan|1995|p=21}}{{sfn|Tomasevich|2001|p=183}} The SDS was equipped using arms and ammunition captured by the Germans from throughout Europe, and was organised as a largely static force split across five regions (''oblasts''): [[Belgrade]], [[Kraljevo]], [[Niš]], [[Valjevo]] and [[Zaječar]], with one [[battalion]] per region. Each region was further divided into three districts (''okrugs''), each of which included one or more SDS [[Company (military unit)|companies]].{{sfn|Thomas|Mikulan|1995|p=21}} A branch of the SDS was created specifically for service in the Banat, and was known as the Banat State Guard. It was formed from the region's German minority (or ''[[Germans of Yugoslavia|Volksdeutsche]]''), and in March 1942 numbered less than one thousand.{{sfn|Tomasevich|2001|p=206}}

Nedić intended that the SDS would not only maintain law and order and guard the borders, but also monitor the people's requirements and offer assistance and protection in areas such as &quot;health care, cultural, educational and economic life&quot;.{{sfn|Antić|2012|p=22}} The SDS was royalist and was rapidly infiltrated by Chetniks loyal to [[Draža Mihailović]]. It also lacked sufficient officers,{{sfn|Pavlowitch|2008|p=58}} and although it had some initial successes, it never developed into an effective military force.{{sfn|Thomas|Mikulan|1995|p=21}}{{sfn|Tomasevich|1975|pp=109–110}} Meyszner took overall control of the SDS three days after its formation, a decision which was strongly opposed by Nedić.{{sfn|Ramet|Lazić|2011|p=24}}

===Operations===
Along with other collaborationist military and paramilitary units, the SDS was used against the [[Yugoslav Partisans|Partisans]] operating within the Territory. In late 1941, prior to the formation of the SDS, the Serbian gendarmerie had participated in the German-led [[Operation Uzice]], which drove the Partisans and Chetniks from the Užice area.{{sfn|Pavlowitch|2008|p=63}} The SDS routinely executed captured Partisans,{{sfn|Cohen|1996|p=39}}{{sfn|Ramet|2006|p=130}} and frequently took and murdered hostages in towns and villages. The SDS also included former members of the gendarmerie that had assisted German troops to round up hostages to be shot at both Kraljevo and [[Kragujevac massacre|Kragujevac]] in October 1941. In July 1941, the [[Banjica concentration camp]] had been established in the suburbs of Belgrade.{{sfn|Ramet|Lazić|2011|p=24}} It was initially guarded by both the [[Gestapo]] and the SDS, but sole responsibility was eventually transferred to the SDS, who behaved sadistically and violently towards the inmates.{{sfn|Antić|2012|p=31}} Survivors of the camp stated that executions at the camp were carried out by both the [[Belgrade Special Police]] and the SDS, and that those executed included children.{{sfn|Haskin|2006|p=29}} A total of 3,849 people were killed at the camp before it was closed on 3 October 1944.{{sfn|Ramet|Lazić|2011|p=29}} The SDS became increasingly unpopular with the population as time went on.{{sfn|Antić|2012|p=18}} Despite their limited independence, the SDS actively engaged in dehumanising [[Jews]], [[Romani (people)|Roma]] and communist [[Serbs]], and in killing people from those groups or delivering them to the Germans for execution. They engaged in the execution of hostages both under Gestapo or Wehrmacht control and at their own initiative.{{sfn|Antić|2012|pp=32–34}} The SDS clashed with other collaborationist formations at times, specifically [[Dimitrije Ljotić]]'s [[Serbian Volunteer Corps (World War II)|Serbian Volunteer Corps]] (''Srpski dobrovoljački korpus'' or SDK), and the [[Pećanac Chetniks]] loyal to ''[[vojvoda]]'' [[Kosta Pećanac]].{{sfn|Ramet|Lazić|2011|pp=29–30}}

In March 1942, Nedić suggested to the Germans that the SDK and Pećanac Chetniks be incorporated into the SDS and that he take control of the force, but this idea was firmly rejected.{{sfn|Ramet|Lazić|2011|pp=32–33}} In mid-1942, Meyszner appointed [[Dragomir Jovanović]], the German-approved mayor and chief of police of Belgrade, as chief of Serbian State Security, which included responsibility for the SDS.{{sfn|Cohen|1996|p=39}} The Germans considered that Radovanović was a Mihailović sympathiser, so in June 1942 he was replaced by [[Colonel]] Borivoje Jonić, the brother of Nedić's minister of education, [[Velibor Jonić]]. In July 1942 the SDS consisted of 15,000–20,000 men.{{sfn|Ramet|Lazić|2011|pp=24–25}} In August and September 1942, Nedić again tried to have the SDS placed under his command, and the German refusal to do so contributed to him tendering his resignation. Nedić had threatened to resign several times previously for similar reasons, but on this occasion the Germans took it more seriously and offered him an audience with [[Adolf Hitler]]. On that basis, Nedić remained at his post.{{sfn|Ramet|Lazić|2011|pp=32–33}} In October 1942, the Border Guard was transferred to the Ministry of Finance.{{sfn|Cohen|1996|p=39}} Also in 1942, the Gestapo arrested some SDS officers suspected of having links with Mihailović, and by the end of 1942 the Germans had purged the SDS in an attempt to eliminate those who sympathised with Mihailović.{{sfn|Pavlowitch|2008|pp=98–99}} One of the senior SDS officers arrested by the Gestapo during the purge was [[Lieutenant Colonel]] [[Milan Kalabić]], the prefect of [[Požarevac]], and father of one of Mihailović's unit commanders, [[Nikola Kalabić]]. The elder Kalabić had been passing information, arms and ammunition to Mihailović's Chetniks. In October 1943, Milan Kalabić was executed by the Germans along with other Chetnik commanders and men.{{sfn|Tomasevich|2001|p=215}}   
[[File:Stjepan Stevo Filipović.jpg|thumb|upright|left|Partisan fighter [[Stjepan Filipović|Stjepan &quot;Stevo&quot; Filipović]] shouting &quot;[[Death to fascism, freedom to the people|Death to fascism, freedom to the People!]]&quot; seconds before his execution by a Serbian State Guard unit in Valjevo on 22 May 1942.]]
By 1943, most of the rank and file of the SDS was sympathetic to Mihailović's Chetniks,{{sfn|Pavlowitch|2008|pp=185 &amp; 199}} and SDS units were regularly being &quot;disarmed&quot; by them, sometimes even staging mock battles to disguise transfers of much needed weapons and ammunition to Mihailović's forces.{{sfn|Pavlowitch|2008|pp=96–97 &amp; 183}}{{sfn|Tomasevich|2001|p=216}} Jovanović himself provided financial assistance to Mihailović from his own discretionary funds.{{sfn|Cohen|1996|p=40}} In April 1943, units of the SDS were praised by German commanders for their fighting against the Partisans near [[Bijeljina]] in eastern [[Bosnia (region)|Bosnia]].{{sfn|Cohen|1996|p=57}} In June 1943, the Germans rounded up and executed 1,139 Serb civilians under suspicion that they had been collaborating with the resurgent Partisans. The SDS were involved in these crimes, and throughout 1943 were actively involved in committing atrocities against Serbian civilians.{{sfn|Ramet|Lazić|2011|p=37}} After many delays, on 18 September 1943 Nedić met with Hitler in [[Berlin]] and was promised that he would be given command of the SDS and the SDK. Upon his return to Belgrade, Nedić called upon the Military Commander in Serbia, ''[[General of the Infantry (Germany)|General der Infanterie]]'' [[Hans Felber]], to make arrangements for the transfer of command, but Felber advised him that he had received no orders to do so. It was not until 2 November 1943 that Nedić was finally given command of both the SDS and SDK.{{sfn|Ramet|Lazić|2011|pp=33–34}} In late 1943 the SDS reached its maximum strength of 36,716 men.{{sfn|Tomasevich|2001|p=183}} By February 1944, the SDS leadership were avoiding any direct confrontations with Mihailović's Chetniks.{{sfn|Pavlowitch|2008|p=226}}

In the spring and summer of 1944, the SDS had declined to a strength of around 24,000–25,000 men.{{sfn|Pavlowitch|2008|p=228}} With the return of the Partisans to Serbia proper, the SDS began to incur serious casualties. For example, between 15 March and 15 August 1944, the SDS lost 157 men killed, 107 wounded and 26 missing.{{sfn|Tomasevich|1975|p=344}} By August 1944, SDS units were responding to Mihailović's call for a general mobilisation by defecting openly to his Chetniks.{{sfn|Pavlowitch|2008|pp=231–232}}

===Withdrawal and capture===
Three days after the fall of the Nedić regime on 6 October 1944, Felber transferred the command of the SDS to General Miodrag Damjanovič, the head of Nedić's secretariat and a principal confidant of Mihailović within Nedić's administration. Damjanovič immediately placed himself and the remaining 6,500 troops of the SDS under Mihailović's command. The SDS was then renamed the &quot;Serbian Shock Corps (''Srpski udarni korpus'' or SUK) of the Yugoslav Army in the Homeland&quot; once again under the command of Radovanović and it joined the withdrawal of other Chetnik formations towards the [[Sandžak]] region then into northeastern Bosnia. This arrangement resulted in a difficult and uneasy alliance which began to disintegrate under the pressures of the withdrawal.{{sfn|Tomasevich|1975|p=421}}

In the last days of December 1944, the SUK participated, along with other Chetnik formations, in an unsuccessful attempt to capture the Partisan-held city of [[Tuzla]] in northeastern Bosnia. This failure and mutual recriminations between Mihailović's Chetniks and the SUK resulted in the effective disintegration of the SUK. By mid-January 1945, 5,000 former SDS members had rejoined the Germans, with some returning to Serbia to take advantage of [[Josip Broz Tito]]'s amnesty. Most were transported to Austria where they were used in labour battalions under the direction of [[Organisation Todt]], but about 1,500 were allowed to move to the Ljubljana Gap area, where they could join other collaborationist forces, such as the SDK or the Chetnik formations of [[Momčilo Đujić]] or [[Dobroslav Jevđević]]. Mihailović was not concerned about their departure, describing the former SDS troops as the &quot;worst troops in the world&quot;.{{sfn|Tomasevich|1975|pp=435–436}}

The remnants of the SDS/SUK and Mihailović's Chetniks remained under the overall command of Damjanovič as part of the Chetnik Šumadija Division. These Chetniks had been under the command of the [[Schutzstaffel|SS]] since 12 December 1944.{{sfn|Ramet|2006|p=130}}{{sfn|Cohen|1996|p=60}} They crossed the river [[Soča]] and surrendered to the [[British Army during the Second World War|British]] near the Italian-Yugoslav border on 5 May 1945. Fortunately for them, they were interned as [[prisoners of war]] and other than a few senior officers, were not repatriated to Yugoslavia to face trial.{{sfn|Pavlowitch|2008|p=265}}

==Uniform and journal==
The SDS wore either the 1940 pattern olive green uniform of the Royal Yugoslav Army, or the earlier [[Kingdom of Serbia]] pattern which was a green-grey in the case of officers, and a greyish-ochre colour for enlisted ranks. These were obtained from stores secured during the invasion.{{sfn|Thomas|Abbott|2010|p=34}} The ''Review of the Serbian State Guard'' (''Glasnik Srpske Državne Straže'') was the official gazette of the SDS, published from 1942 to the end of 1943. The journal was edited by Jonić, and contributors included Nedić and [[Milan Aćimović]].{{sfn|Stambolija|2011|p=141}}

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

{{commons category|Serbian State Guard}}

==References==

===Books===
* {{cite book
  | last = Antić
  | first = Ana
  | chapter = Police Force Under Occupation: Serbian State Guard and Volunteers' Corps in the Holocaust
  | editor-last = Horowitz
  | editor-first = Sara R.
  | title = Back to the Sources: Re-examining Perpetrators, Victims and Bystanders
  | pages = 13–36
  | publisher = Northwestern University Press
  | location = Evanston
  | year = 2012
  | isbn = 978-0-8101-2862-0
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=FYJS1xt5SPoC&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Cohen
  | first = Philip J.
  | authorlink = Philip J. Cohen
  | title = Serbia's Secret War: Propaganda and the Deceit of History
  | publisher = Texas A&amp;M University Press
  | location = College Station
  | year = 1996
  | isbn = 978-0-89096-760-7
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=C21t6bdyv3cC&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | first = Jeanne M.
  | last = Haskin
  | title = Bosnia and Beyond: The &quot;Quiet&quot; Revolution That Wouldn't Go Quietly
  | publisher = Algora Publishing
  | location = New York
  | year = 2006
  | isbn = 978-0-87586-428-0
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=lgc-XDvNWzoC&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | first = Stevan K.
  | last = Pavlowitch
  | author-link = Stevan K. Pavlowitch
  | title = Serbia: The History Behind the Name
  | publisher = C. Hurst &amp; Co. Publishers
  | location = London
  | year = 2002
  | isbn = 978-1-85065-476-6
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=0_3Wt46vBv8C&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Pavlowitch
  | first = Stevan K.
  | year = 2008
  | title = Hitler's New Disorder: The Second World War in Yugoslavia
  | publisher = Columbia University Press
  | location = New York
  | isbn = 978-1-85065-895-5
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=R8d2409V9tEC&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Ramet
  | first = Sabrina P.
  | authorlink = Sabrina P. Ramet
  | year = 2006
  | title = The Three Yugoslavias: State-Building and Legitimation, 1918–2005
  | publisher = Indiana University Press
  | location = Bloomington
  | isbn = 978-0-253-34656-8
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=FTw3lEqi2-oC&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Ramet
  | first1 = Sabrina P.
  | last2 = Lazić
  | first2 = Sladjana
  | chapter = The Collaborationist Regime of Milan Nedić
  | editor1-last = Ramet
  | editor1-first = Sabrina P.
  | editor2-last = Listhaug
  | editor2-first = Ola
  | title = Serbia and the Serbs in World War Two
  | pages = 17–43
  | publisher = Palgrave Macmillan
  | location = London
  | year = 2011
  | isbn = 0230278302
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Thomas
  | first1 = Nigel
  | last2 = Mikulan
  | first2 = Krunoslav
  | title = Axis Forces in Yugoslavia 1941–45
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=A8X6UH58dlgC
  | publisher = Osprey Publishing
  | year = 1995
  | location = New York
  | isbn = 978-1-85532-473-2
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Thomas
  | first1 = Nigel
  | last2 = Abbott
  | first2 = Peter
  | title = Partisan Warfare 1941–45
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=z1CNJitx5RkC&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | publisher = Osprey Publishing
  | year = 2010
  | location = Wellingborough
  | isbn = 978-0-85045-513-7
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Tomasevich
  | first = Jozo
  | authorlink = Jozo Tomasevich
  | year = 1975
  | title = War and Revolution in Yugoslavia, 1941–1945: The Chetniks
  | publisher = Stanford University Press
  | location = Stanford
  | isbn = 978-0-8047-0857-9
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=yoCaAAAAIAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Tomasevich
  | first = Jozo
  | year = 2001
  | title = War and Revolution in Yugoslavia, 1941–1945: Occupation and Collaboration
  | publisher = Stanford University Press
  | location = Stanford
  | isbn = 978-0-8047-3615-2
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=fqUSGevFe5MC&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | ref = harv
  }}

===Journals===
* {{cite journal
  | last= Hehn
  | first= Paul N.
  | year = 1971
  | title = Serbia, Croatia and Germany 1941–1945: Civil War and Revolution in the Balkans
  | journal = Canadian Slavonic Papers
  | volume = 13
  | issue = 4
  | pages = 344–373
  | publisher = University of Alberta
  | jstor = 40866373
  | ref = harv
  }}
* {{cite journal
  | last = Stambolija
  | first = Nebojša
  | title = 'Glasnik srpske državne straže' - opšte informacije i tematska analiza sadržaja
  | journal = Istorija 20. veka
  | year = 2011
  | volume = 29
  | issue = 1
  | pages = 141–150
  | language = Serbo-Croatian
  | ref = harv
  }}

{{Yugoslav Axis collaborationism |state=collapsed}}
{{Factions in the Yugoslav Front}}

[[Category:Serbia under German occupation|State Guards, Serbian]]
[[Category:Military units and formations established in 1942]]
[[Category:Military units and formations disestablished in 1945]]
[[Category:The Holocaust in Yugoslavia]]
[[Category:1942 establishments in Yugoslavia]]
[[Category:Collaboration during World War II]]

[[zh:南斯拉夫祖國軍]]</text>
      <sha1>4rko0kjsilbskibj7so4zfh5ydfkqyw</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
