<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Siege of Kimberley</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>12141983</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749814132</id>
      <parentid>741092371</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-16T08:20:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lord Eastfarthing</username>
        <id>11187569</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Cleaned up using [[WP:AutoEd|AutoEd]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="46971">{{Use South African English|date=May 2012}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2012}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Siege of Kimberley
| partof      = the [[Second Boer War]]
| image       = [[File:RML2.5inchMountainGunDefenceOfKimberley.jpg|300px|alt=Three artillery men crouch behind a small 2.5&amp;nbsp;inch &quot;Screw Gun&quot; employed in the defence of Kimberley]]
| caption     = British [[RML 2.5 inch Mountain Gun]] employed in the defence of Kimberley during the Second Boer War
| date        = {{Start date|1899|10|14|df=y}}&amp;nbsp;– {{Start date|1900|02|15|df=y}}
| place       = [[Kimberley, Northern Cape|Kimberley]], [[Cape Colony]] (present-day South Africa)
| coordinates = {{Coord|28|44|S|24|45|E |type:event_region:ZA |display=inline,title}}
| casus       =
| territory   =
| result      = British Victory
| combatant1  = {{flagcountry|United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland}}
| combatant2  = {{Plainlist|
* {{flag|South African Republic}}
* {{flag|Orange Free State}}
}}
| commander1  = {{Plainlist|
* {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} Lt Col [[Robert Kekewich]]
* {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Cecil Rhodes]]&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;Rhodes was a civilian ''de facto'' commander&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[John French, 1st Earl of Ypres|Major-General John French]]
}}
| commander2  = {{Plainlist|
* {{flagicon|Orange Free State}} Commandant Cornelius Wessels
* {{flagicon|Orange Free State}} General I. S. Ferreira
* {{flagicon|South African Republic}} General [[Piet Cronjé]]
}}
| strength1   = &gt;1,600
| strength2   = 3,000–6,500&lt;ref name=&quot;Peddle&quot;&gt;Peddle, 1977&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;Several guns
| casualties1 = 42 killed&lt;br /&gt;135 wounded&lt;ref name=&quot;THW-7-24&quot;&gt;Amery ''et al'', p. 24&lt;/ref&gt;
| casualties2 = Heavy
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Second Boer War}}
}}

The '''Siege of Kimberley''' took place during the [[Second Boer War]] at [[Kimberley, Northern Cape|Kimberley]], [[Cape Colony]] (present-day South Africa), when [[Boer]] forces from the [[Orange Free State]] and the [[South African Republic|Transvaal]] besieged the diamond mining town.  The Boers moved quickly to try to capture the British enclave when war broke out between the British and the two Boer republics in October 1899.  The town was ill-prepared, but the defenders organised an energetic and effective improvised defence that was able to prevent it from being taken.

[[Cecil Rhodes]], who had made his fortune in the town, and who controlled all the mining activities, moved into the town at the onset of the siege.  His presence was controversial, as his involvement in the [[Jameson Raid]] made him one of the primary protagonists behind war breaking out.  Rhodes was constantly at loggerheads with the military, but he was nonetheless instrumental in organising the defence of the town.  The Boers shelled the town with their superior artillery in an attempt to force the garrison to capitulate.  Engineers of the [[De Beers]] company manufactured a one-off gun named [[Long Cecil]], however the Boers soon&amp;nbsp;countered with a much larger siege gun that terrified the residents, forcing many to take shelter in the [[Big Hole|Kimberley Mine]].

The British military had to change its strategy for the war as public opinion demanded that the sieges of Kimberley, [[Siege of Ladysmith|Ladysmith]] and [[Siege of Mafeking|Mafeking]] be relieved before the Boer capitals were assaulted. The first attempt at relief of Kimberley under [[Paul Methuen, 3rd Baron Methuen|Lord Methuen]] was stopped at the battles of [[Battle of Modder River|Modder River]] and [[Battle of Magersfontein|Magersfontein]].  The 124-day siege was finally relieved on 15&amp;nbsp;February 1900 by a cavalry division under [[John French, 1st Earl of Ypres|Lieutenant-General John French]], part of a larger force under [[Frederick Roberts, 1st Earl Roberts|Lord Roberts]].  The battle against the Boer general [[Piet Cronjé]] continued at [[Battle of Paardeberg|Paardeberg]] immediately after the town itself was relieved.

==Background==
South Africa was initially a Dutch colony after the [[Dutch East India Company]] set up a shipping station at the [[Cape of Good Hope]] in 1652.&lt;ref&gt;Morris &amp; Linnegar 2004, p. 39&lt;/ref&gt;  In 1815, Britain captured the territory at the [[Battle of Blaauwberg]],&lt;ref&gt;Morris &amp; Linnegar 2004, p. 58&lt;/ref&gt; setting the scene for an influx of English [[1820 Settlers|settlers]]&lt;ref&gt;Morris &amp; Linnegar 2004, p. 73&lt;/ref&gt; who were culturally at odds with the existing Dutch population, notably with respect to issues such as the [[Slavery Abolition Act 1833|abolition of slavery]].  Many Dutch farmers elected to move away from British influence into the hinterland, which resulted in a mass migration known as the [[Great Trek]].&lt;ref&gt;Morris &amp; Linnegar 2004, p. 95&lt;/ref&gt;  As people moved inland, prospecting for minerals started; in the 1870s, the [[Kimberley, Northern Cape#History|discovery of diamonds]] in the area of present-day Kimberley was followed a decade later by the [[Witwatersrand Gold Rush|discovery of gold in the Witwatersrand]].&lt;ref&gt;Morris &amp; Linnegar 2004, p. 108&lt;/ref&gt;  The discoveries led to a massive influx of ''[[Uitlander]]s'' (Dutch for &quot;foreigners&quot;) into the Boer republics of the Orange Free State and Transvaal.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ralph26&quot;&gt;Ralph 1900, p. 26&lt;/ref&gt;

Tensions soon started rising between the British Empire and the two Boer republics.  The causes of the war were complex, with contributing factors including the Boers' desire for independence, the prize of the rich gold fields, [[Scramble for Africa|British colonial expansionist ambitions in Africa]], perceived ill-treatment of British [[expatriate]]s working in the Boer republics, the [[First Boer War]] and a failed British-organised uprising in the form of the [[Jameson Raid]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Ralph26&quot;/&gt;  Discussions broke down in October 1899 when the British ignored a Boer [[ultimatum]] to stop concentrating forces on the borders of the Boer republics.&lt;ref&gt;Ralph 1900, p. 33&lt;/ref&gt;

Prior to the onset of the [[Second Boer War]], Kimberley was the second biggest settlement in the [[Cape Colony]],&lt;ref&gt;Morris &amp; Linnegar 2004, p. 110&lt;/ref&gt; centre of diamond mining operations of the De Beers Mining Company, and the source of 90% of the world's diamonds.&lt;ref&gt;Fremont-Barnes, p. 18&lt;/ref&gt;  The town had a population of 40,000, of which 25,000 were white.&lt;ref name=&quot;AsheIntro&quot;&gt;Ashe, Introduction, p. 17&lt;/ref&gt; It was the only British outpost in the far north east of the colony, located just a few kilometres from the borders of the Boer republics of the Transvaal and Orange Free State; [[Cape Town]] was {{convert|1041|km}} away by rail, while [[Port Elizabeth]] was {{convert|780|km}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;AsheIntro&quot;/&gt;  The closest Boer settlements were [[Jacobsdal]] to the south and [[Boshof]] to the east.

==Preparation==
The De Beers company was concerned about the defence of Kimberley some years before the outbreak of the war, particularly its vulnerability to attack from the neighbouring Orange Free State.  In 1896, an arms depot was formed, a plan of defence sent to the authorities and a local defence force set up.  As it began to look more likely that war would break out, the nervous citizens of Kimberley appealed to the premier of the Cape Colony, [[William Philip Schreiner]], for additional protection, but he did not believe the town to be under serious threat and declined to arm it further.&lt;ref name=&quot;handbook&quot;/&gt;  His reply to an appeal for arms in September 1899 stated: &quot;There is no reason whatever for apprehending that Kimberley is or will be in any danger of attack and your fears are therefore groundless.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Mitchell265&quot;&gt;Michell (1900), p. 265&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Robert Kekewich.jpg|thumb|left|upright|alt=Portraint of Lt. Col. Robert Kekewich|Lt Col Robert Kekewich]]
The town next appealed to the High Commissioner, this time with more success.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mitchell265&quot;/&gt;  On 4 October 1899, Major Scott-Turner was permitted to summon volunteers to join the town guard and raise the Diamond Fields Artillery.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mitchell267&quot;/&gt;  Three days later, the town was placed under the command of [[Robert Kekewich|Colonel Robert Kekewich]] of the 1st Battalion, [[Loyal Regiment (North Lancashire)]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Peddle&quot;/&gt; and secured against a ''[[coup de main]]'', but not against sustained siege.&lt;ref name=&quot;handbook&quot;/&gt;

Colonel Kekewich's troops consisted of four [[Company (military unit)|companies]] of the Loyal North Lancashire Regiment, some [[Royal Engineers]], six [[RML 2.5 inch Mountain Gun|RML 2.5 inch mountain guns]] and two machine guns. Also at his disposal were 120&amp;nbsp;men of the Cape Police (recalled from various outposts along the railway line), 2,000&amp;nbsp;[[irregular military|irregular troops]], the Kimberley Light Horse, and a battery of obsolete seven-pounder guns. Eight [[Maxim gun|Maxim machine guns]] were mounted on [[redoubt]]s built atop [[tailings|tailing heaps]] around the town.&lt;ref name=&quot;Peddle&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Conan-Doyle, Chapter VIII&lt;/ref&gt;

Cecil John Rhodes, the founder of De Beers, was contemplating moving into the town.  The citizens feared that his presence there, given his prominent role in the [[Jameson Raid|breakdown of Anglo-Boer relations]] leading up to the war, would antagonise the Boers.  Consequently, the mayor of Kimberley, as well as various associates of Rhodes, tried to discourage him.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mitchell267&quot;&gt;Michell (1900), pp. 267–269&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Le Sueur, p. 237&lt;/ref&gt; However, Rhodes ignored the advice and moved into the town just prior to the onset of the siege, very narrowly evading capture when the Boer ultimatum expired at 5&amp;nbsp;pm on 11&amp;nbsp;October while he was still ''en route''.  It was a calculated move to raise the political stakes and thereby force the government to divert war resources to lifting the siege.  Since most of the resources in the garrison were owned by De Beers, Rhodes inevitably became an important factor in the defence organised by Colonel Robert Kekewich. As head of the mining company that owned most of the assets in the town, the military felt that Rhodes proved to be more of a hindrance as he did not cooperate fully with them;&lt;ref&gt;Jourdan, p. 108&lt;/ref&gt; civil and military authorities were not always working together, especially after the death of the second in command of the garrison, Major Scott-Turner.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mitchell267&quot;/&gt;  The military took the following view of Rhodes:&lt;ref name=&quot;handbook&quot;&gt;A Handbook of the Boer War&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Cquote|Rhodes had come into his own Kimberley and for the first time he was not master in it. He found himself a sterilized dictator acting in an atmosphere too tenuous to support his vitality but sufficient to preserve it from extinction. He was subject to the authority of the military commandant, a galling position for a distinguished statesman who had not a high opinion of the professional capacity of the British officer.}}

Kekewich decided to include the neighbouring municipality of Beaconsfield as well as the outlying suburb of Kenilworth inside the {{convert|22|km|mi|adj=on}} defensive perimeter he established around the town.&lt;ref name=&quot;Peddle&quot;/&gt;  Rhodes sponsored the raising of a new regiment called the Kimberley Light Horse,&lt;ref name=&quot;Saunders27&quot;&gt;Saunders, pp. 27–28&lt;/ref&gt; but Lord Methuen advised Kekewich that &quot;Rhodes is to leave Kimberley the day after I arrive.  Tell him he is not to interfere in military matters.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller183&quot;&gt;Miller, p. 183&lt;/ref&gt;

==Siege==
{{Location map+|South Africa|float=right|width=260|alt=Map of South Africa showing the location of Kimberley and other places mentioned in the article|caption=|places=
{{Location map~|South Africa |label=Kimberley|lat={{Decdeg|28|44|31|S}}|long={{Decdeg|24|46|19|E}}|position=left|mark=red_pog.svg|marksize=8}}
{{Location map~|South Africa |label=Kraaipan|lat={{Decdeg|26|17|49|S}}|long={{Decdeg|25|18|23|E}}|position=left|mark=red_pog.svg|marksize=5}}
{{Location map~|South Africa |label=Mafeking|lat={{Decdeg|25|51|00|S}}|long={{Decdeg|25|38|00|E}}|position=top|mark=red_pog.svg|marksize=5}}
{{Location map~|South Africa |label=Cape Town|lat={{Decdeg|33|51|00|S}}|long={{Decdeg|18|25|00|E}}|position=right|mark=red_pog.svg|marksize=5}}
{{Location map~|South Africa |label=Port&amp;nbsp;Elizabeth|lat={{Decdeg|33|57|00|S}}|long={{Decdeg|25|36|00|E}}|position=top|mark=red_pog.svg|marksize=5}}
{{Location map~|South Africa |label=Bloemfontein|lat={{Decdeg|29|06|00|S}}|long={{Decdeg|26|13|00|E}}|position=bottom|mark=red_pog.svg|marksize=5}}
{{Location map~|South Africa |label=Ladysmith|lat={{Decdeg|28|33|00|S}}|long={{Decdeg|29|47|00|E}}|position=top|mark=red_pog.svg|marksize=5}}
{{Location map~|South Africa |label=Pretoria|lat={{Decdeg|25|44|00|S}}|long={{Decdeg|28|11|00|E}}|position=right|mark=red_pog.svg|marksize=5}}
}}
[[File:Kimberley-ticket.jpg|thumb|right|alt=Soup ration ticket from the Siege of Kimberley with the text &quot;Kimberley Siege Soup: Town Hall Depot: Two Pints&quot;|Soup [[rationing|ration]] ticket from the Siege of Kimberley]]
The conflict at Kimberley started on 14 October 1899.  [[Robert Baden-Powell, 1st Baron Baden-Powell|Colonel Baden-Powell]], anticipating the inevitable onset of hostilities, encouraged all the women and children to leave the town.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ashe3&quot;&gt;Ashe, pp. 3–4&lt;/ref&gt;  Some civilians left in a special train, escorted as far as [[Vryburg]] by an [[armoured train]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Phelan13&quot;&gt;Phelan, p. 13&lt;/ref&gt;  On the return journey, the armoured train was captured in the first action of the war between Kimberley and [[Mafeking]] at [[Battle of Kraaipan|Kraaipan]] by Boers under the command of fighting general [[Koos de la Rey|De la Rey]], the hero of the western Transvaal.  On 12&amp;nbsp;October, the [[Jacobsdal]] Commando severed the railway line at the bridge over the [[Modder River]] south of Kimberley,&lt;ref name=&quot;Wilson&quot;&gt;Wilson, p. 53&lt;/ref&gt; whereafter the Boers entrenched themselves in the hills at Spytfontein.&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;Spytfontein is located immediately south of Kimberley at {{Coord|-28.882230|24.683372 |format=dms |type:landmark_region:ZA |name=Spytfontein}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Phelan13&quot;/&gt;  Meanwhile, the [[Boshof]] Commando severed the railway line {{convert|16|km|mi|-1}} north of the town at Riverton Road, then shut off the primary water supply at Riverton on the [[Vaal River]].&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;Riverton is located north of Kimberley on the Vaal River at {{Coord|28|30|51|S|24|42|2|E |type:landmark_region:ZA |name=Riverton}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ashe3&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wilson&quot;/&gt;  For the first time, water in the mines became more precious than the diamonds in them. On 14&amp;nbsp;October the Boers cut the telephone line to the Cape.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ralf266&quot;&gt;Ralf, pp. 267–275&lt;/ref&gt;  [[Heliograph]] and [[dispatch rider]]s consequently had to make hazardous journeys through Boer lines to the Orange River and then to Cape Town and Port Elizabeth.  On 15 October, [[martial law]] was declared in the town.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis, p. 269&lt;/ref&gt;

The cattle that usually grazed on the outskirts of the town presented a problem; if they were left, they would be lost to the Boers, but if they were slaughtered, the meat would perish quickly in the summer heat.  The De Beers chief engineer, [[George Labram]], provided a solution by building an industrial refrigeration plant underground in the Kimbeley mine to preserve the meat.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.atlanticlibrary.org/Newspapers/MLRecord/MLR09151906.pdf |title=An American Engineer |accessdate=22 July 2009 |date=15 September 1906 |publisher=May's Landing |location=Atlantic City |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110725022634/http://www.atlanticlibrary.org/Newspapers/MLRecord/MLR09151906.pdf |archivedate=25 July 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Boer commander, Commandant Cornelius Wessels, presented Kekewich with an ultimatum on 4 November, demanding the town's surrender.&lt;ref name=&quot;CD-18&quot;/&gt;  Kekewich replied the same day, stating: &quot;...you are hereby invited to effect the occupation of this town as an operation of war by the employment of the military forces under your command.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Heberden, 1976&lt;/ref&gt;  When the siege of Kimberley itself began in earnest on 6&amp;nbsp;November, the situation favoured an attack. The Boers were in control of the railway from the [[Orange River]] to Mafeking, while arms and ammunition were in short supply in Kimberley.  On 7&amp;nbsp;November, the Boers started shelling the town.&lt;ref&gt;Ashe, p. 32&lt;/ref&gt;  Communication with the outside world was not seriously impeded however.  The Boer strategy was not to attack the town in a full battle, but rather to wait for the defenders to capitulate, all the time wearing them down with shelling.&lt;ref name=&quot;J. Lee Thompson 2007 153&quot;&gt;Thompson, p. 153&lt;/ref&gt;  The defenders tried to send the large contingent of migrant native labourers that was working in the mines home, but twice the Boers drove them back into the town in an apparent attempt to put pressure on the limited food and water supply.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ralf266&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Long Cecil.jpg|thumb|alt=The &quot;Long Cecil&quot; gun in the workshops of the De Beers company showing a large gun on a carriage with a workman casually looking on in the background.|Long Cecil gun in the workshops of [[De Beers]]]]
Rhodes had his own agenda, which differed from the greater war goal of redressing wrongs in the Transvaal that had [[Second Boer War#Escalation and war|triggered]] the conflict.  He used his position and influence to demand relief of the siege vociferously in both the press and directly of the government.&lt;ref name=&quot;Saunders27&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;J. Lee Thompson 2007 153&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gilman, 1976&lt;/ref&gt;  However, Kekewich was a more cool-headed man, and was careful to let the authorities in Cape Town know that the situation was by no means desperate and that he would be able to hold out for several weeks.&lt;ref name=&quot;handbook&quot;/&gt;  The feud between the two men escalated when the ''Diamond Fields Advertiser'', the local newspaper which was under Rhodes' control, ignored the military censor and printed information that compromised the military.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/commons/1900/mar/22/siege-of-kimberley-mr-rhodes-and-colonel|title=Siege of Kimberley—Mr. Rhodes and Colonel Kekewich|work=[[Hansard]]|publisher=[[Parliament of the United Kingdom]]|date=22 March 1900|accessdate=29 August 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/commons/1901/jun/11/censorship-diamond-fields-advertiser-mr#S4V0097P0_19010611_HOC_64|title=Censorship—Diamond Fields Advertiser—Mr. Rhodes and Col. Kekewich|work=[[Hansard]]|publisher=[[Parliament of the United Kingdom]]|date=11 June 1901|accessdate=29 August 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Kekewich obtained permission from his superior to place Rhodes under arrest if necessary.&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;Magnus says Lord Kitchener granted permission to arrest Rhodes, while Van Haresveldt says it was Lord Roberts.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Magnus, p. 162&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Van Hartesveldt, p. 19&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gardner, pp. 170–171&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Long Tom en route to Kimberley.jpg|thumb|alt=Boer Long Tom gun packed for travel on board a train with the barrel removed from the carriage.|left|Boer Long Tom gun ''en route'' to Kimberley]]
The food and water supply was managed closely by the military authorities.  Rationing was imposed as the food supply dwindled, with the inhabitants eventually resorting in the final states of the siege to eating horse meat.  Vegetables could not be grown easily because of a shortage of water.  The scarcity of vegetables took the hardest toll on the poorest people, notably the 15,000-strong indigenous population; a local doctor suggested that they eat [[aloe]] leaves to avoid contracting [[scurvy]],&lt;ref&gt;Ashe, p. 80&lt;/ref&gt; while Rhodes organised a [[soup kitchen]].&lt;ref&gt;Jourdan, pp. 114–115&lt;/ref&gt;

On 25 November, the British garrison launched an attack on the Boer [[redoubt]] at Carter's Ridge, west of the town.  Kekewich's men held the belief that the action would assist Methuen's relief column at [[Battle of Magersfontein|Magersfontein]] by keeping more Boers occupied at Kimberley.  A detachment of 40 members of Cape Police and Light Horse under the command of Major Scott-Turner of the [[Black Watch]] set out at midnight and completely surprised their enemy in the early hours of the morning.  Thirty-three Boers were captured at the cost of four killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;CD-18&quot;&gt;Conan-Doyle, Chapter 18&lt;/ref&gt;  Scott-Turner tried to repeat the successful raid three days later, but it was a disaster for the British the second time round, with Scott-Turner amongst those killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;CD-18&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=980CE2DD1538E433A25754C0A9649D94689ED7CF|work=New York Times|date=7 December 1899|title=Hard Fight at Kimberley; Major Scott-Turner Killed Leading a Fierce Sortie|accessdate=23 August 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Le Rire issue 276 1900-02-17 cph.3b48494.jpg|thumb|upright|Contemporary French caricature of Rhodes, showing him trapped in Kimberley during the Second Boer War, seen emerging from a tower clutching papers with a champagne bottle behind his collar.]]
The engineers of Rhodes' company, under Chief Mechanical Engineer George Labram were instrumental in the defence of the town.  They manufactured fortifications, an armoured train, a watch tower, shells, and a gun, known as ''[[Long Cecil]]'', for the defenders in order to supplement their inadequate weapons.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ashe85&quot;&gt;Ashe, p. 85&lt;/ref&gt;  ''Long Cecil'' was rifled with a bore of {{convert|100|mm|in}} capable of propelling a {{convert|13|kg|lb|adj=on}} shell {{convert|6000|m|yards}}.&lt;ref&gt;Ashe, p. 113&lt;/ref&gt;  The gun was completed on 21&amp;nbsp;January 1900, and successfully test fired against a previously untouchable Boer position north of the town.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ashe150&quot;&gt;Ashe, p. 150&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jourdan, p. 121&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Rhodes message.jpg|thumb|right|alt=Rhodes' message to residents stating: &quot;Sunday. I recommend women and children who desire complete shelter to proceed to Kimberley and De Beers shafts. They will be lowered at once in the mines from 8 O'clock throughout the night. Lamps and guides will be provided. C.J. Rhodes&quot;|Rhodes' message to the residents of Kimberley, offering shelter in the Kimberley Mine]]
The Boers countered on 7&amp;nbsp;February with a much heavier 100-pounder named [[155 mm Creusot Long Tom|&quot;Long Tom&quot;]]; it had been disabled by British saboteurs at [[Siege of Ladysmith|Ladysmith]], before being repaired at Pretoria, and brought to Kimberley.&lt;ref&gt;De Souza, p. 82&lt;/ref&gt;  In addition to having larger shells than any of the siege guns used up to that point, its longer range meant that it could also target any location in Kimberley.  The town's inhabitants had become accustomed to shelling by smaller guns and were to some extent able to take shelter and to carry on their daily lives.  The new gun immediately changed the status quo, as terrified residents were no longer able to find sanctuary anywhere at ground level.&lt;ref name=&quot;handbook&quot;/&gt;  Rhodes published a notice inviting people to take shelter in the Kimberley Mine in order to avoid its lethal shelling.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jourdan122&quot;&gt;Jourdan, p. 122&lt;/ref&gt;  Fortunately for the defenders, the gun did not use [[smokeless powder]], so observers were able to give residents up to 17&amp;nbsp;seconds warning to take cover when a shell was incoming.&lt;ref&gt;Jourdan, p. 123&lt;/ref&gt;  Labram was the most notable civilian casualty, when he was killed within a week of the end of the siege, ironically by a Boer shell from the Long Tom gun brought to counter his own gun.&lt;ref name=&quot;Jourdan122&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Phelan, p. 162&lt;/ref&gt;  Kekewich arranged a full [[military funeral]] for him, which was well attended, but took place after dark for safety reasons;&lt;ref&gt;Williams, p. 655&lt;/ref&gt; the procession was targeted by Boer shelling with the help of a traitor inside the town who lit the area with a flare.&lt;ref&gt;Ashe, p. 199&lt;/ref&gt;

The Boers [[siege|besieged]] the town for 124&amp;nbsp;days, shelling it on most days, except Sundays.&lt;ref name=&quot;Saunders27&quot;/&gt;  Shelling abated somewhat during the [[Battle of Magersfontein]] when the Boer siege guns were temporarily brought to bear there.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ralf266&quot;/&gt;  Throughout the siege, Kekewich mounted numerous armed [[reconnaissance]] missions outside the town's defences, sometimes using the armoured train.  Some of these engagements were fierce, with casualties on both sides, however they did not change the status quo.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ralf266&quot;/&gt;  In January 1900, the local Boer command passed from Commandant Wessels to General Ignatius S. Ferreira.&lt;ref&gt;De Wet, Chapter VII&lt;/ref&gt;
{{clear}}

==Relief==
[[File:Major-General Sir J.D.P. French.jpg|thumb|upright|alt=Portrait of Major-General French|right|Major-General Sir J.D.P. French, whose cavalry division lifted the siege.]]
The British commander-in-chief in South Africa, General Sir [[Redvers Buller]] initially planned to march with a single large force on the Boer capitals of [[Bloemfontein]] and [[Pretoria]].  However public opinion demanded relief of the sieges of Kimberley, Ladysmith and Mafeking—pressure that was attributable in part to Rhodes' presence in Kimberley and lobbying in London.&lt;ref name=&quot;Miller183&quot;/&gt;  Buller therefore had to change his plans and divide his forces:&lt;ref&gt;Gooch, p. 15&lt;/ref&gt; Lord Methuen was sent north by the [[War Office]] in December 1899 with the objective of relieving Kimberley and Mafeking, while Buller himself went to Natal.&lt;ref&gt;Thompson, p. 157&lt;/ref&gt; On 1 December 1899, communications were established between Methuen's relief column and the defenders in the town.&lt;ref&gt;Williams, p. 638&lt;/ref&gt; However, Methuen's advance ground to a halt after the Boers inflicted heavy casualties on his force at the [[Battle of Modder River]] and defeated him resoundingly at the [[Battle of Magersfontein]].  These, and other defeats elsewhere, came to be called &quot;[[Black Week]]&quot; by the British. Thus, for two of the four months of the siege, the 10,000 British troops at Modder River who were within {{convert|12|mi|km}} of the town, were unable to reach it.&lt;ref&gt;Danes, p. 431&lt;/ref&gt;

Field Marshal [[Frederick Roberts, 1st Earl Roberts|Lord Roberts]] replaced Buller as British Commander-in-Chief in South Africa in January 1900.  Within a month Roberts assembled 30,000 infantry, 7,501 cavalry and 3,600 mounted infantry, together with 120 guns, in the area between the Orange and Modder Rivers.&lt;ref name=&quot;CC&quot;/&gt;  The largest British mounted division ever assembled was created under the command of [[John French, 1st Earl of Ypres|Major-General John French]] through the amalgamation of virtually all the cavalry in the area.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ralph261&quot;&gt;Ralph 1900, p. 261&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Goldman73&quot;&gt;Goldman, pp. 73–75&lt;/ref&gt;  News of the shelling by the Boer Long Tom gun had reached Lord Roberts, whose parting words to his officers on 9 February were that &quot;You must relieve Kimberley if it costs you half your forces.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Goldman73&quot;/&gt;

Piet Cronjé believed that Roberts would attempt to attack him in a flanking manoeuvre from the west,&lt;ref name=&quot;Cassar47&quot;&gt;Cassar, pp. 47–49&lt;/ref&gt;  and that the advance would largely continue as before along the railway line.&lt;ref&gt;Fremont-Barnes, p. 56&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Goldman, pp. 70–72&lt;/ref&gt;  With this mind, Roberts ordered Methuen to advance with the 1st Division on 11&amp;nbsp;February in a feint movement on [[Magersfontein]], while General Sir [[Hector MacDonald]] led the [[Highland Brigade (Scottish)|Highland Brigade]] {{convert|20|mi|km}}west to Koedoesberg,&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;Koedoesberg is at {{coord|28|55|0|S|24|25|0|E |name=Koesdoesberg |type:landmark_region:ZA}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ralph261&quot;/&gt; thereby encouraging Cronjé's forces to believe that the attack would occur there. However, the bulk of the force initially headed south to Graspan,&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;Graspan is located south of Kimberley at {{coord|29|19|8|S|24|26|51|E|name=Graspan |type:landmark_region:ZA}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ralph261&quot;/&gt; then east deep into the Orange Free State with the cavalry division guarding the British right flank by securing [[Ford (crossing)|drifts]] across the [[Riet River]].  On 13&amp;nbsp;February, Roberts activated the second part of his plan, that involved French's cavalry separating from the slower main force and piercing forward quickly by swinging northwards, just east of [[Jacobsdal]], to cross the Modder River at Klip Drift.&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;Klipdrif is south-east of Kimberley on the Modder River at {{coord|29|3|24|S|24|51|43|E |name=Klip Drift |type:landmark_region:ZA}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:French's Cavalry at Klip Drift.jpg|thumb|alt=French's cavalry at Klip Drift on the Modder River, showing men, horses and guns crossing the river.|left|French's cavalry crossing the Modder River after charging to Klip Drift on their way to Kimberley]]
As French's column neared the Modder River on 13 February, a force of about 1,000&amp;nbsp;Boers made contact with his right flank.&lt;ref&gt;Goldman, p. 79&lt;/ref&gt;  French wheeled his right and center brigades towards their enemy, thereby allowing the brigade on the left to hold course for Klip Drift, while giving the enemy the false impression that he was headed for Klipkraal Drift.&lt;ref&gt;Cassar, p. 47&lt;/ref&gt;  The whole force then wheeled left at the last minute and charged the Klip Drift crossing at full gallop. The Boers at Klip Drift, who were taken completely by surprise, left their camp and provisions behind, which French's exhausted men and horses were glad to seize.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ralph262&quot;&gt;Ralf, p. 262&lt;/ref&gt;  Although speed was important, the cavalry had to wait for the infantry to catch up to secure the lines of communication before moving forward to relieve Kimberley.  The cavalry's route had taken them deep inside the Free State over Cronjé's [[line of communication]], thereby cutting off any Boer forces who did not immediately fall back. Meanwhile, Roberts led the main force in an easterly direction with the objective of capturing the Boer capital of Bloemfontein.&lt;ref name=&quot;CC&quot;&gt;Coulthard-Clark, pp. 66–68&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Roberts Enters Kimberley.jpg|thumb|upright|alt=Lord Robert's entry into Kimberley, showing jubilant crowds outside the town hall as Roberts takes the salute on horseback|right|Lord Roberts entering Kimberley in February 1900 following the lifting of the siege]]
French's flanking manoeuvre took a very high toll on horses and men in the blazing summer heat, with about 500 horses either dying en route or no longer fit to ride.&lt;ref&gt;Cassar, p.48&lt;/ref&gt;  When Cronjé became aware of French's cavalry on his left flank at Klip Drift, he concluded that the British were trying to draw him eastwards away from his prepared defences.  He despatched 900&amp;nbsp;men with guns to stop the British push northwards.  French's men set out from Klip Drift at 9:30&amp;nbsp;am on 15&amp;nbsp;February on the last stage of their journey to Kimberley, and were soon engaged by the Boer force sent to block them.  Rifle fire came from the river in the east while artillery shells rained from the hills in the north west; the route the Kimberley lay straight ahead through the crossfire, so French ordered a bold cavalry [[Charge (warfare)|charge]] down the middle.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cassar47&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Chisholm, p. 75&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Goldman, pp. 82–84&lt;/ref&gt;  As waves of horses galloped forward, the Boers poured down fire from the two sides. However, the speed of the attack, screened by a massive cloud of dust, proved successful and the Boer force was defeated. British casualties during this day's fighting were five dead and ten wounded, with approximately 70 horses lost through exhaustion.&lt;ref name=&quot;CC&quot;/&gt; However, the route to Kimberley was open; by that evening, General French and his men passed through the recently abandoned Boer lines, and relieved the town of Kimberley after some initial difficulty in convincing the defenders via heliograph that they weren't Boers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cassar47&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Phelan, pp. 195–197&lt;/ref&gt;  The cavalry had covered {{convert|120|mi|km}} in four days at the height of summer to reach the town.&lt;ref&gt;Ashe, p. 230&lt;/ref&gt;  When French arrived in town, he snubbed Kekewich, the local military authority, by presenting himself to Rhodes instead.&lt;ref&gt;Robbins, 2001&lt;/ref&gt;

French's men did not have much opportunity to relax when they reached the town, as they were roused during their first night in the town first to make yet another dash to try to capture the Long Tom gun&lt;ref&gt;Jourdan, p. 126&lt;/ref&gt; and, in the early hours of 17 February, to cut off Cronjé's main force, who had abandoned Magersfontein and were heading east towards Bloemfontein along the Modder River.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cassar47&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Goldman98&quot;&gt;Goldman, p.98-105&lt;/ref&gt;  Kitchener directed French to cut off the Boers' escape; of French's original strength of 5,000, only 1,200 of his cavalrymen were still fit, while the horses were depleted.  At first light, the cavalry headed towards the Boer dust clouds; soon they were overlooking a whole valley full of Boers, with cattle, 400&amp;nbsp;wagons and women and children in tow.  The surprise was complete when the British started shelling the Boer column just as it started crossing the Modder River at Paardeberg Drift, causing considerable confusion and panic.&lt;ref name=&quot;Goldman98&quot;/&gt;  Cronjé elected to sit tight rather than escape, giving French the opportunity to summon reinforcements before the Boers realised how small and depleted the force was that was harassing them.  The [[Battle of Paardeberg]] ensued over the next week, resulting in the defeat of Cronjé, but at the expense of a considerable amount of British blood.&lt;ref&gt;Goldman, Chapter IV&lt;/ref&gt;
{{clear}}

==Aftermath==
[[File:Kimberley Star.jpg|thumb|left|[[Kimberley Star]]]]
On 17 February, Kekewich was promoted to the rank of full [[colonel (United Kingdom)|colonel]] while French was promoted to [[Major General (United Kingdom)|major general]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://query.nytimes.com/mem/archive-free/pdf?_r=1&amp;res=9903E6DC113BEE33A2575BC1A9649C946197D6CF|work=New York Times|date=17 February 1900|accessdate=29 August 2009|title=French and Kekewich Promoted | format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;  &lt;!-- Both officers saw further action in the war.  --&gt;A number of medals were issued to combatants, notably the [[Kimberley Star]], which was instituted by Mayor H.A. Oliver. Since the medal was not an official one, it could not be worn with military uniforms. The official awards for the siege and relief of Kimberley were, respectively, the &quot;DEFENCE OF KIMBERLEY&quot; and &quot;RELIEF OF KIMBERLEY&quot; clasps to the [[Queen's South Africa Medal]].&lt;ref&gt;Johnson, pp. 159–160&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Duxbury, 1972&lt;/ref&gt;

The British established a [[concentration camp]] at Kimberley to hold [[internment|interned]] Boer women and children.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Sessional Papers By Great Britain Parliament |publisher=House of Commons |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=7jBFAAAAMAAJ |year=1902|accessdate=23 August 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; A memorial outside the Newton Dutch Reformed Church commemorates those that died in the camp.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kimberley.co.za/tourism/historical/tripintothepast/|title=Kimberley, The Capital of the Northern Province|accessdate=3 September 2009|publisher=City of Kimberley Tourism|date=9 March 2009 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20080723020440/http://www.kimberley.co.za/tourism/historical/tripintothepast/ |archivedate = 23 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Dead Memorial, Kimberley.jpg|thumb|upright|The Honoured Dead Memorial in Kimberley|right|alt=The Honoured Dead Memorial, a tall, brown sandstone building with multiple Grecian-type pillar and the ''Long Cecil'' gun at its base]]
The [[Honoured Dead Memorial]], a sandstone edifice commissioned by [[Cecil Rhodes]] and designed by [[Sir Herbert Baker]], was erected to commemorate the defenders who fell during the Siege.&lt;ref name=&quot;Roberts338&quot;&gt;Roberts, p. 338&lt;/ref&gt; Twenty-seven soldiers are entombed in the memorial, which was made from stone quarried in the [[Matopo Hills]] in Zimbabwe.  It bears an inscription by [[Rudyard Kipling]]:&lt;ref name=&quot;Roberts338&quot;/&gt;  &quot;This for a charge to our children in sign of the price we paid, The price that we paid for freedom that comes unsoiled to your hand; Read, revere and uncover, here are the victors laid, They who died for their City, being sons of the land&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Westby-Nunn p. 399&lt;/ref&gt; [[Long Cecil]], the gun manufactured in the [[De Beers]] workshops during the Siege, is mounted on the [[stylobate]] (facing the [[Free State (South African province)|Free State]]), surrounded by shells from the Boer [[155 mm Creusot Long Tom|Long Tom]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Roberts338&quot;/&gt;

The Sanatorium Hotel, in which Cecil Rhodes stayed during the siege, is the present-day site of the [[McGregor Museum]].  The stone that he used to mount his horse is still in the gardens, while the story of the siege is covered extensively in the permanent exhibitions of the museum.&lt;ref&gt;Maylam, p. 56&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!-- No reliable reference available...
The town of [[Wesselsbron]] in the Orange Free State is named in honour of the Boer commander, Cornelius Wessels.--&gt;

==See also==
* [[Kimberley Regiment]]
* [[Kimberley Star]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|group=&quot;Note&quot;|2}}

==References==

===Citations===
{{reflist|2}}

===Bibliography===
* {{cite book |title=A Handbook of the Boer War With General Map of South Africa and 18 Sketch Maps and Plans |url=http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/15699 |publisher=[[Gale and Polden]] Ltd |location=London and Aldershot |year=1910}}
* {{cite book|title=The Times History of the War in South Africa, 1899–1902 |location=London|publisher=S. Low, Marston and company, ltd |url=https://archive.org/details/timeshistoryofwa06ameriala|author=[[Leo Amery|Amery, LS]]; [[Robert Erskine Childers|Erskine Childers]]; G.P. Tallboy &amp; Basil Williams|year=1900}}
* {{cite book |url=https://archive.org/details/besiegedbyboers00ashegoog |title=Besieged by the Boers; A Diary of Life and Events in Kimberley During the Siege|author=Ashe, E. Oliver |publisher=Doubleday, Page &amp; Co |location=New York |year=1900}}
* {{cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ijcjfpJH6JoC |title=The Tragedy of Sir John French |author=Cassar, George H. |publisher=University of Delaware Press |year=1985 |isbn=0-87413-241-X}}
* {{cite book |author=Coulthard-Clark, Chris |title=Where Australians Fought—The Encyclopaedia of Australia's Battles |publisher=Allen and Unwin |location=Sydney |year=1998 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=RiMVHQAACAAJ |isbn=978-1-86448-611-7}}
* {{cite book |url=https://archive.org/details/cassellshistory00danegoog |author=Danes, Richard |publisher=Cassells |year=1903 |title=Cassell's History of the Boer War, 1899–1902 (1903)}}
* {{cite book|title=A Question of Treason|author1=De Souza |author2=Francis Hugh |publisher=Kiaat Creations|year=2004|isbn=0-620-32030-3|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=_3SfxrH82Z8C}}
* {{cite book|authorlink=Christiaan de Wet|first=Christiaan|last=De Wet|title=Three Years War|publisher=Charles Scribner's Sons|location=New York|year=1902|url=http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/18794|isbn=0-947020-03-9}}
* {{cite journal|url=http://samilitaryhistory.org/vol023gd.html|title=Queen's South Africa Medal With 10 Bars|last=Duxbury|first=G.R.|journal=Military History Journal|volume= 2| issue =  3|date=June 1972|accessdate=28 August 2009}}
* {{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=h9wbSjpIMPwC|title=The Boer War 1899–1902|first=Gregory|last=Fremont-Barnes|publisher=Osprey Publishing|year=2003|isbn=1-84176-396-9}}
* {{cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=T9UKAQAAIAAJ |title=The Lion's Cage |first=Brian|last=Gardner |year=1969 |publisher=Barker |isbn=0-213-76477-6}}
* {{cite journal|publisher=South African Military History Society|url=http://samilitaryhistory.org/vol033eg.html|journal=Military History Journal|volume= 3| issue =  3/4|title=Should the Strategy of Lord Roberts be Judged by the Victory at Paardeberg or by the Subsequent Delay at Bloemfontein?|first=Ernest|last=Gilman|date=June 1976|accessdate=23 August 2009}}
* {{cite book|title=With General French and the Cavalry in South Africa|year=1902|last=Goldman|first=Charles Sydney|publisher=Macmillan and co.|location=London|url=https://archive.org/details/withgeneralfren00goldgoog}}
* {{cite book|title=The Boer War: Direction, Experience, and Image|first=John|last=Gooch|publisher=Routledge|year=2000|isbn=0-7146-5101-X|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=yPFeGjE2MH4C}}
* {{cite journal |url=http://samilitaryhistory.org/vol035wh.html |title=The Diary of a Doctor's Wife (Part 2) |volume= 3| issue =  5 |journal=Military History Journal |author=Heberden, Winifred |publisher=The South African Military History Society |date=June 1976|accessdate=23 August 2009}}
* {{cite book|url=https://archive.org/details/medalcollectorgu00johniala|title=The Medal Collector; A Guide to Naval, Military, Air-force and Civil Medals and Ribbons|year=1921|author=Johnson, Stanley Currie|publisher=H. Jenkins|location=London}}
* {{cite book|author=Jourdan, Philip|publisher=John Lane Company|year=1911|title=Cecil Rhodes, His Private Life|url=https://archive.org/details/cecilrhodeshisp00jourgoog}}
* {{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=W4EwAAAAIAAJ|title=Good-bye Dolly Grey: The story of the Boer War|author=Kruger, Rayne|year=1960|publisher=Lippincott}}
* {{cite book|title=Cecil Rhodes; The Man and His Work|year=1913|author=Le Sueur, Gordon|publisher=J. Murray|location=London|url=https://archive.org/details/cecilrhodesmanhi00lesurich}}
* {{cite book|title=Kitchener: Portrait of an Imperialist|first=Sir Philip Montefiore|last=Magnus|publisher=J. Murray|year=1958|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=aQ0rAAAAIAAJ|location=London}}
* {{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=VbD_mokWhL8C|title=The Cult of Rhodes: Remembering an Imperialist in Africa|first=Paul|last=Maylam|publisher=New Africa Books|year=2005|isbn=0-86486-684-4}}
* {{cite book|title=The Life of the Right Hon. Cecil John Rhodes, 1853–1902 (1910)|author=Michell, Lewis, ()|volume=Volume 2|publisher=E. Arnold|location=London|url=https://archive.org/details/lifeofrthoncecil02michuoft}}
* {{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=kRjryHqRiygC&amp;pg=PA183|title=Lord Methuen and the British Army: Failure and Redemption in South Africa|first=Stephen M.|last=Miller|year=1999|isbn=0-7146-4904-X|publisher=Cass|location=London}}
* {{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=57gyw36xwk8C|title=Every Step of the Way: The Journey to Freedom in South Africa|publisher=Ministry of Education|year=2004|isbn=0-7969-2061-3 |author1=Morris, Michael  |author2=John Linnegar |lastauthoramp=yes }}
* {{cite journal |url=http://samilitaryhistory.org/vol041dp.html |volume= 4| issue =  1 |title=Long Cecil: The Gun Made in Kimberley During the Siege |author=Peddle, Colonel D.E. |publisher=The South African Military History Society |journal=Military History Journal |date=June 1977|accessdate=23 August 2009}}
* {{cite book |url=http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/13777 |title=The Siege of Kimberley |author=Phelan, T. |year=1913 |location=Dublin|publisher=M.H. Gill &amp; Son, Ltd}}
* {{cite book |url=https://archive.org/details/towardspretoriar00ralp|author=Ralph, Julian |publisher=Frederick A. Stokes company |year=1900 |title=Towards Pretoria; A Record of the War Between Briton and Boer, to the Relief of Kimberley}}
* {{cite book|title=The siege of Kimberley and the battle of Magersfontein|author=Robbins, David|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=wPlyAAAAMAAJ|publisher=Ravan Press|year=2001|isbn=0-86975-532-3}}
* {{cite book|title=Kimberley: Turbulent CIty|author=Roberts, Brian|year=1976|isbn=0-949968-62-5|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ON71wM6U0ZMC|publisher=D. Philip in association with the Historical Society of Kimberley and the Northern Cape|location=Cape Town}}
* {{cite book |title=Mafeking Memories|author1=Saunders, Frederick  |author2=Phillip Thurmond Smith  |lastauthoramp=yes |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Xfgmh34g0vcC |year=1995 |accessdate=2 July 2008 |publisher=Fairleigh Dickinson University Press |isbn=0-8386-3635-7}}
* {{cite journal |url=http://www.americanheritage.com/articles/magazine/ah/1981/3/1981_3_48.shtml |title=George Labram |author=Snow, Richard F. |journal=American Heritage |volume= 32| issue = 3 |date=Apr–May 1981|accessdate=23 August 2009}}
* {{cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=PDMcYymUie8C&amp;pg=PA131 |title=Forgotten Patriot |author=Thompson, J. Lee |publisher=Fairleigh Dickinson Univ Press |year=2007 |isbn=0-8386-4121-0}}
* {{cite book|title=The Boer War: Historiography and Annotated Bibliography|volume=Volume 24 of Bibliographies of Battles and Leaders|first=Fred R.|last=Van Hartesveldt|publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group|year=2000|isbn=0-313-30627-3|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=AzY28y1teF4C}}
* {{cite book|title=A Tourist Guide to the Anglo-Boer War, 1899-1902|first=Tony|last=Westby-Nunn|publisher=Westby-Nunn Publishers|year=2000|isbn=978-0620249782|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=FQMwAQAAIAAJ&amp;redir_esc=y}}
* {{cite book|url=https://archive.org/details/diamondminesofso00willrich|title=The Diamond Mines of South Africa; Some Account of Their Rise and Development|last=Williams|first=Gardner Fred|publisher=The Macmillan Company|location=London|year=1902}}
* {{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=5UEKAQAAIAAJ|title=With the Flag to Pretoria: A History of the Boer War of 1899–1900|first=Herbert Wrigley|last=Wilson|publisher=Harmsworth Brothers, limited|year=1900}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=30FCAAAAIAAJ |title=Pioneer, Soldier and Politician |first=David|last=Harris |year=1931 |publisher=S. Low, Marston &amp; Co., ltd.}}
* {{cite book|title=Days of Horror During the Siege of Kimberley, 1899–1990|first=Carl|last=Meyer|publisher=Kimberley Africana Library under the auspices of the Friends of the Library|year=1999|isbn=978-0-620-24573-9|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=dKYrGQAACAAJ}}
* {{cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=PBCSAAAAIAAJ |title=The Boer War |year=1979 |first=Thomas|last=Pakenham |publisher=Random House |isbn=0-380-72001-9|authorlink=Thomas Pakenham (historian)}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
* [http://www.uq.edu.au/~mlwham/banjo/with_french_to_kimberley.html With French to Kimberley] poem by [[Banjo Paterson]]
* [http://www.britishbattles.com/great-boer-war/kimberley.htm The Siege of Kimberley] at BritishBattles.com
* [http://wasfu-man-kimberleysiege.blogspot.com/ Henry Symonds' Kimberley Siege Letter]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Siege Of Kimberley}}
[[Category:1899 in the Cape Colony]]
[[Category:1900 in the Cape Colony]]
[[Category:Battles of the Second Boer War|Kimberly, Siege of]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1899]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1900]]
[[Category:Histories of cities in South Africa]]
[[Category:Kimberley, Northern Cape]]
[[Category:Sieges of the Second Boer War]]
[[Category:Cavalry charges|Relief of Kimberley]]</text>
      <sha1>0gu7q62y6uwo4klowz2hdzymjhfyqww</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
