<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Skanderbeg's Italian expedition</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>26666514</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745803575</id>
      <parentid>744455993</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-23T11:39:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>http&amp;rarr;https for [[Google Books]] and [[Google News]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="38540">{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Skanderbeg's Italian expedition
|image= [[File:Skanderbeg expedition in Italy (1460-1462)2.svg|290px|alt= A map showing the routes taken Skanderbeg and his subordinates across the Adriatic Sea to Southern Italy.]]
|caption=[[Skanderbeg]]'s voyage to Italy. The northern route was taken by Skanderbeg himself whereas the southern was taken by his subordinates. 
|partof=the Neapolitan war of succession (1459–1464)
|date=1460–1462
|place=Southern Italy
|result=[[Ferdinand I of Naples|Ferdinand]] regains most of his lost territories
|combatant1=[[File:Coa Kastrioti Family.svg|18px]] [[League of Lezhë]] &lt;br/&gt; [[File:Emblem of the Papacy SE.svg|18px]] [[Papal States]] &lt;br/&gt;{{flag|Kingdom of Naples|1442}}&lt;br/&gt; [[File:Flag of the Duchy of Milan (1450).svg|18px]] [[Duchy of Milan]]
|combatant2=[[File:Blason duche fr Anjou (moderne).svg|18px]] [[House of Valois-Anjou|House of Anjou]] &lt;br/&gt; [[File:Blason fam it Orsini.svg|18px]] [[Principality of Taranto]] &lt;br/&gt; Pro-Angevin Italian nobles
|commander1=[[File:Coa Kastrioti Family.svg|18px]] [[Skanderbeg]] &lt;br/&gt; [[File:Coa Kastrioti Family.svg|18px]] [[Constantine Kastrioti]] &lt;br/&gt; [[File:Emblem of the Papacy SE.svg|18px]] [[Pius II]] &lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|Kingdom of Naples|1442}} [[Ferdinand I of Naples]] &lt;br/&gt; [[File:Flag of the Duchy of Milan (1450).svg|18px]] [[Alessandro Sforza]]
|commander2=[[File:Blason duche fr Anjou (moderne).svg|18px]] [[René d'Anjou]] &lt;br/&gt; [[File:Blason duche fr Anjou (moderne).svg|18px]] [[John II, Duke of Lorraine|Jean d'Anjou]] &lt;br/&gt; [[File:Blason duche fr Anjou (moderne).svg|18px]] [[Jacopo Piccinino]] &lt;br/&gt; [[File:Blason fam it Orsini.svg|18px]] [[Giovanni Antonio del Balzo Orsini|Giovanni Orsini]]
|strength1=
|strength2=
|casualties1=
|casualties2=
}}
{{Ottoman-Albanian Wars}}

'''Skanderbeg's Italian expedition''' (1460–1462) was undertaken to aid his ally [[Ferdinand I of Naples]], whose rulership was threatened by the [[House of Valois-Anjou|Angevin Dynasty]]. [[George Kastrioti Skanderbeg]] was the ruler of Albania ({{lang-la|dominus Albaniae}}) who had been leading a rebellion against the [[Ottoman Empire]] since 1443 and allied himself with several Western European monarchs in order to consolidate his domains. In 1458, [[Alfonso V of Aragon]], ruler of [[Kingdom of Sicily|Sicily and Naples]] and Skanderbeg's most important ally, died, leaving his illegitimate son, Ferdinand, on the Neapolitan throne; [[René d'Anjou]], the French [[List of Counts and Dukes of Anjou|Duke of Anjou]], laid claim to the throne. The conflict between René's and Ferdinand's supporters soon erupted into a civil war. [[Pope Calixtus III]], of Spanish background himself, could do little to secure Ferdinand, so he turned to Skanderbeg for aid.

In 1457, Skanderbeg had achieved his most famous victory over the Ottoman Empire at [[Battle of Ujëbardha|Albulena]] (Ujëbardha), which was received with great enthusiasm throughout [[Italy]]. In order to repay Alfonso for the financial and military assistance given to him years before, Skanderbeg took up the pope's pleas to help out Alfonso's son by sending a military expedition to Italy. Before leaving, Skanderbeg tried to negotiate a ceasefire with Sultan [[Mehmed II]], the [[Fall of Constantinople|conqueror of Constantinople]], to ensure his domain's safety. Mehmed had not declared a truce and he was still sending his armies against [[Kingdom of Bosnia|Bosnia]] and the [[Despotate of Morea|Morea]]. It was not until 1459, after Mehmed's conquest of [[Serbian Despotate|Serbia]], that Mehmed not only declared a truce, but also a three-year ceasefire with Skanderbeg. This gave Skanderbeg his opportunity to send his men to Italy.

Due to fears of an approaching Ottoman army, Skanderbeg first sent his nephew, [[Constantine Kastrioti|Constantine]], with 500 cavalry to [[Barletta]]. They were incorporated into Ferdinand's forces to combat his Angevin rivals. They held back their enemy for a year, but did not gain much ground until Skanderbeg arrived in September 1461. Before reaching Italy, Skanderbeg visited [[Republic of Ragusa|Ragusa]] ([[Dubrovnik]]) to convince its [[rector (politics)|rector]]s to help fund his campaign. Meanwhile, his men landed in Italy and Angevin forces lifted their siege on Barletta. Upon arriving, Skanderbeg continued to pursue his ally's enemies with great success. Ferdinand's adversaries thus began to retreat from his territories and Skanderbeg went back to Albania; a troop of his men stayed until Ferdinand managed to finally defeat the pretenders to his throne at the [[Battle of Orsara]], although it is not known if Skanderbeg's men participated.

==Background==

In 1456, Skanderbeg's ally, [[Janos Hunyadi]], died, and his son, [[Mathias Corvinus]], was crowned [[King of Hungary]]. Hunyadi had been an advocate for an offensive war against the Ottoman Empire, whereas the Hungarian nobility and his son promoted a defensive war.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri359&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=359}}&lt;/ref&gt; The next year, however, [[Skanderbeg|George Kastrioti Skanderbeg]] defeated a sizable Ottoman force at the [[Battle of Albulena]] (Ujëbardha). Rome had been desperately waiting for such a victory after the [[Siege of Belgrade (1456)|Siege of Belgrade]], as [[Pope Calixtus III]] had wanted to assure himself of the feasibility of a crusade before declaring one.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri357&quot;/&gt; Calixtus thus named Skanderbeg the Captain-General of the [[Roman Curia|Curia]]; to secure the pope's interests, Skanderbeg sent twelve Turkish [[Prisoner of war|prisoners of war]] that had been captured at Albulena to [[Rome]]. Despite seeing his forces defeated the year before, Sultan [[Mehmed II]] prepared another force to be sent into Albania. The country had been obstructing his ambitions for empire in the West and he grew restless to defeat Skanderbeg.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri357&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=357}}&lt;/ref&gt; Skanderbeg sent delegations to several Western European states to convince them to stop fighting each other and unite for Calixtus' crusade.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri358&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=358}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Italian situation===
[[File:Gjergj Kastrioti.jpg|thumb|left|upright=0.9|Portrait of Skanderbeg in the [[Uffizi]], [[Florence]] |alt= A portrait of Skanderbeg, the ruler of Albania who led a war against the Ottoman Empire.]]

On 27 September 1458, [[Alfonso V of Aragon]], Skanderbeg's most important and helpful ally after the stipulation of the [[Treaty of Gaeta]], died.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri359&quot;/&gt; In 1448, as gesture of friendship with Alfonso, Skanderbeg sent a detachment of Albanian troops commanded by General Demetrios Reres to [[Crotone]] to quell a rebellion against Alfonso.&lt;ref name=Nasse24&gt;{{harvnb|Nasse|1964|p=24}}&lt;/ref&gt; The next year, many of these men were allowed to settle four villages in [[Sicily]] which Alfonso controlled.&lt;ref name=Nasse25&gt;{{harvnb|Nasse|1964|p=25}}&lt;/ref&gt; Upon hearing of his ally's death, Skanderbeg sent emissaries to the new King of Naples, [[Ferdinand I of Naples|Ferdinand I]], to give condolence for his father's death, but also to congratulate him on his accession to the throne of Naples.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri359&quot;/&gt; The succession was not without turbulence, however: [[René d'Anjou]] laid claim to the throne since his family had controlled Naples before [[Crown of Aragon|Aragon]] had taken control of it, and also because Ferdinand was Alfonso's [[Legitimacy (law)|illegitimate son]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri359&quot;/&gt; The Southern Italian nobility, many of [[House of Valois-Anjou|Angevin]] background, supported René d'Anjou over the Aragonese Ferdinand.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri359&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Setton231&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Setton|1978|p=231}}&lt;/ref&gt; Among them was [[Giovanni Antonio del Balzo Orsini]], the Prince of [[Taranto]], and [[Jacopo Piccinino]], a famed ''[[condottieri]]'' who had been invited by the Angevins. [[Francisco Sforza]], the Duke of Milan, who was wary of a French presence in Italy, sided with Ferdinand and sent his nephew, [[Alessandro Sforza]], to command his army in southern Italy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt307&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schmitt|2009|p=307}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pope Calixtus, a Spaniard who wished to see his compatriot in control of Naples, was in no position to help the weak Ferdinand, so he turned to Skanderbeg for help.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri359&quot;/&gt; However, by that time, Piccinino and his men had conquered all of southern Italy except [[Naples]], [[Capua]], [[Aversa]], [[Gaeta]], [[Troia, Apulia|Troia]], and [[Barletta]], where Ferdinand was besieged.&lt;ref name=&quot;Franco321&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Franco|1539|p=321}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Skanderbeg had received much aid from Ferdinand's father, Alfonso, and was still a vassal of the Crown of Aragon, so he felt the need to repay the Crown.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri360&quot;/&gt; He accepted the pope's pleas to go to Italy and aid Ferdinand. Skanderbeg's stated reasoning was twofold: he wanted to remain loyal to his ally and he wanted to prevent an Angevin takeover of Naples since they had maintained friendly relations with the Turks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri360&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=360}}&lt;/ref&gt; Skanderbeg also feared that if the Angevins took Naples, they would turn to Albania where they had previously maintained a [[Kingdom of Albania (medieval)|kingdom]]. On the other hand, before undertaking any action against the Angevins, he took measures to soften relations with [[Republic of Venice|Venice]]. Seeing that Southern Italy was locked in conflict, Venice no longer feared an Aragonese-Albanian alliance and the Senate decided to take a friendlier approach in Albanian-Venetian relations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri360&quot;/&gt; Meanwhile, Pope Calixtus III had died and was succeeded by [[Pope Pius II]]. Sensing that war would soon begin, Pius tried to convince Giovanni Orsini, Ferdinand's main rival, to settle his differences with the King.&lt;ref name=&quot;Setton231&quot;/&gt; The French King, [[Louis XI]], took up the Angevin stance and, in the hopes of convincing Pius to allow the French takeover of Naples, proposed the repeal of the [[Pragmatic Sanction of Bourges]] which undermined the pope's power and he even declared that he would be willing to lend 70,000 men for the planned papal crusade. Pius, however, was wary of insincerity and disregarded these proposals.&lt;ref name=&quot;Setton232&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Setton|1978|p=232}}&lt;/ref&gt; A further effort to deter Skanderbeg's landing was made by [[Sigismondo Pandolfo Malatesta|Sigismondo Malatesta]], the Lord of [[Rimini]] and Italy's most feared petty tyrant, who had tried to invite Mehmed to Italy with a detailed map of the Adriatic if Ferdinand sent for the Albanian.&lt;ref name=&quot;Babinger201&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Babinger|1978|p=201}}&lt;/ref&gt; The manuscript, however, never reached the sultan and fell into Pius' hands.&lt;ref name=&quot;Babinger202&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Babinger|1978|p=202}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Albanian situation===
[[File:Pintoricchio 014.jpg|thumb|right|upright=0.9|Pius II: fresco located in the 'Piccolomini library' in the [[Siena Cathedral|Duomo of Siena]] |alt= A fresco of Pope Piuss II, one of Skanderbeg's main supporters.]]

Constant news of Ottoman campaigns against [[Kingdom of Bosnia|Bosnia]] and [[Despotate of Morea|Morea]] but not against Albania seemed to suggest to Skanderbeg that Mehmed II had been considering an armistice with Skanderbeg. The latter took advantage of this lull in the fighting by preparing for his voyage to Italy and by securing his northern frontiers from a possible attack by Skanderbeg's elusive ally in northern Albania, [[Lekë Dukagjini]], who had been trying to expand his realm by reaching an agreement with the Turks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri360&quot;/&gt; In order to curb his ambitions, Skanderbeg seized Shat Fortress and presented it as a gift to Venice.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri361&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=361}}&lt;/ref&gt; Skanderbeg then established an alliance with Venice against Dukagjini, while Dukagjni was strengthening his Turkish alliance.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=362}}&lt;/ref&gt; The new pope issued a [[papal bull|bull]] against Dukagjini, giving him fifteen days to break his alliance with the Ottomans and to reconcile with Skanderbeg, or be subject to [[interdict]]ion; Dukagjini conceded and chose the former option. He then reestablished his alliance with Skanderbeg and Venice and accepted all of its losses.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri363&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=363}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Pius II continued to support Skanderbeg, but did not provide him as much financial aid as Calixtus had since he believed that Skanderbeg's military skill and his soldiers' aptitude for battle were enough to hold back the Turkish armies. However, the pope still considered Skanderbeg's assistance essential for his plans for an anti-Ottoman crusade.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri364&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=364}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1459, after Mehmed II completed his conquest of [[Serbian Despotate|Serbia]], Ottoman envoys appealed for a three-year armistice between Skanderbeg's Albania and the [[Ottoman Empire]]. The sultan's purpose was to distance Skanderbeg from the pope's crusade as he believed the crusade's only hope for success was Skanderbeg. In order to give Albania a break from fifteen years of continuous Ottoman invasion, Skanderbeg considered accepting the proposal but he had to get the pope's approval.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri364&quot;/&gt; Pius did not allow such an agreement and began to doubt Skanderbeg's loyalty.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri365&quot;/&gt; As the Ottomans were operating in the Western Balkans, Pius feared that the Ottoman soldiers would break the truce and pour into Albania.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt309&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schmitt|2009|p=309}}&lt;/ref&gt; In order to regain the pope's trust, Skanderbeg did not agree to the peace.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri365&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=365}}&lt;/ref&gt; Skanderbeg, nevertheless, was disappointed by Rome's response and he responded by not participating in the [[Council of Mantua (1459)|Council of Mantua]] which was held to plan the future crusade.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri366&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=366}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Council ended in failure, signifying that Skanderbeg would receive no help from the West. He thus sent ambassadors to the pope saying that he would only be willing to land in Italy if a ceasefire with the Turks were arranged, something which Rome soon allowed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri368&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=368}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Before sending his men to Italy, [[Republic of Ragusa|Ragusa]] (Dubrovnik) was to receive Skanderbeg's envoy on 9 June 1460. He requested the city's support for the transport of his  warriors to southern Italy over the [[Adriatic Sea|Adriatic]]. Venice was not consulted since they pursued their own interests in Italy, whereas Ragusa held close economic relations with the Crown of Aragon. Meanwhile, Skanderbeg sent Martin Muzaka to Rome where he presented Pius with Skanderbeg's plans, and Pius in turn notified Ferdinand. Pius then ordered Venice to guard the Albanian coastline.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt308&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schmitt|2009|p=308}}&lt;/ref&gt; Skanderbeg then decided to send a troop of his men while he remained in Albania.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt309&quot;/&gt; In mid-June 1461, Skanderbeg agreed to a ceasefire with Mehmed who used this time to finally conquer [[Empire of Trebizond|Trebizond]] ([[Trabzon]]) in the northeastern part of modern [[Turkey]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt316&quot;/&gt; The truce was agreed to last for three years.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=369}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==First landings==
On 17 September 1460, Skanderbeg sent 500 cavalry to Barletta in [[Apulia]] under the command of his nephew, [[Constantine Kastrioti|Constantine]], who at the time was 22 or 23 years old. The battles for the Crown of Naples up to that point had been minor with not much more than one-thousand troops per belligerent. Ferdinand's Neapolitan army as a whole stood at 7,000 men. The addition of 500 Albanian cavalry, even though they were not [[cuirass]]ed like their Italian counterparts, increased his force's effectiveness.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt309&quot; /&gt; By this time, Ferdinand had lost most of his territory, and was left with some fortresses in Apulia and the area surrounding [[Naples]]. The Angevins were swiftly approaching Naples and Ferdinand prepared a counteroffensive. He first secured what he had by putting Roberto del Balzo Orsini in command, but Orsini's incompetence held up the Neapolitan army. By this time, Skanderbeg's men had already arrived, and Ferdinand commenced his offensive. Albanian light-cavalry warfare was first noted here for its swiftness and effectiveness where they were reported to travel {{convert|30|-|40|mi|km}} per day as opposed to the Italian cavalry which could only travel {{convert|10|-|12|mi|km}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri376&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=376}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Albanians were encouraged by Ferdinand to fight in their traditional manner and to raid the territory; Ferdinand informed Francisco Sforza that the Albanians had been devastating Apulia and taking whatever loot they could.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt315&quot; /&gt; These events worried the Angevins and prompted Giovanni Orsini to try to stop Skanderbeg from pouring his men into Italy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt309&quot; /&gt; René d'Anjou had been particularly surprised by Skanderbeg's action since he believed that he had never offended the Albanian.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt310&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Noli124&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Noli|1947|p=124}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Orsini–Skanderbeg correspondence===
{{quote box
|title=
|quote= &quot;The Prince of Taranto wrote me a letter, a copy of which, and the reply I made him, I am sending to Your Majesty. I am very surprised that His Lordship should think to turn me from my intention by his brusque words, and I should like to say one thing: may God guard Your Majesty from ill and harm and danger, but however things may turn out I am the friend of virtue and not fortune.&quot;
|source= Skanderbeg's letter to Ferdinand I of Naples.&lt;ref&gt;Translated version provided by {{harvnb|Hodgkinson|1999|pp=163–164}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|align= right 
|width= 260px 
|bgcolor= #c6dbf7  
}}

Giovanni Orsini was the Prince of [[Taranto]] and Ferdinand's fiercest rival. He had been, however, Alfonso's faithful ally and had developed an admiration for Skanderbeg and his campaigns in Albania.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri373&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=373}}&lt;/ref&gt; After Skanderbeg had sided with his rival, Orsini allied with the Angevins and refused to recognize Ferdinand as King of Naples.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt310&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schmitt|2009|p=310}}&lt;/ref&gt; He then sent a letter to convince Skanderbeg to pull his men out of Italy arguing that Ferdinand's fortunes were hopeless, that Skanderbeg's fame would die out after his supposed debacle, and that an alliance with René would be much more rewarding than an alliance with Ferdinand. Skanderbeg's letter in response, dated to 10 October 1460, stated that he was not a ''[[condottieri]]'' looking for fortune, but a mature man looking to help his ally.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri373&quot; /&gt; Furthermore, he sent another letter to Ferdinand assuring him his loyalty.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri375&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=375}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hodgkinson163164&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Hodgkinson|1999|pp=163–164}}&lt;/ref&gt; Another letter was sent to Pius assuring him that the Albanians were fit for battle in Italy, something the Italian rulers did not believe.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt312&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schmitt|2009|p=312}}&lt;/ref&gt; The letters elucidate Skanderbeg's political motives behind his Italian expedition, presenting himself as a noble ally, and also illustrate the influence of the [[Renaissance]] in Skanderbeg's court.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt313&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|pp=372–373}}&lt;/ref&gt; They also served a psychological purpose to intimidate Ferdinand's rivals: Skanderbeg compared himself to [[Pyrrhus of Epirus]] of antiquity who marched into Italy to defend the Greek city-states from Roman expansion.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt313&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schmitt|2009|p=313}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Neapolitan counteroffensive===
By October 1460, Ferdinand was able to recapture his western territories from [[Capua]] to [[Benevento|Beneventum]]. In his eastern frontier, however, his enemies remained at large. The most dangerous among them was Piccinino.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri376&quot; /&gt; Piccinino had undertaken the task of blocking papal and Neapolitan troops en route to Apulia. Since Roberto Orsini, the man left in charge of the east and Giovanni Orsini's brother who had remained loyal to Ferdinand, was deemed incompetent, Ferdinand invited Constantine to Naples, offering him a leading role in an operation against Piccinino.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri377&quot; /&gt; Along with Constantine's cavalry, Francesco del Balzo, the Duke of [[Andria, Apulia|Andria]] who had remained loyal to Ferdinand, managed to defeat [[Ercole d'Este]] in [[Gargano]]. They then had control over the custom-duties gathered there which brought 30,000 [[ducat]]s annually from which most of Piccinino's pay came.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt316&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schmitt|2009|p=316}}&lt;/ref&gt; The fighting continued for three months after which Constantine and Ferdinand were able to regain some lost territory. Piccinino prepared his own counteroffensive, along with Giovanni Orsini's men, laying siege to the main castles. A fierce battle soon erupted over [[Venosa]] on 28 May 1461 where the Albanian cavalry took part. Ferdinand abandoned the city and fled back to Apulia. Near [[Troia, Apulia|Troia]], he met Skanderbeg's ambassador, Gjokë Stres Balsha, who informed him that Skanderbeg was ready to land in Italy as soon as the proper [[galley]]s were provided.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri377&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=377}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Skanderbeg's expedition==

===Preparations and Ragusan voyage===
Before leaving for Italy, Skanderbeg needed to accumulate the appropriate finances. Pius ordered the Diocese of Dalmatia to give a third of what it had raised for the forthcoming crusade to Skanderbeg. The pope also ordered 1,000 [[Florin (Italian coin)|florin]]s to be given to Skanderbeg from the Vatican's funds. The Ragusan banks held this amount, but due to the threat of an Ottoman invasion, they refused to continue funding the crusade;&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri379&quot; /&gt; [[Stjepan Vukčić Kosača|Stefan Vukčić]] of [[Principality of Zeta|Zeta]] warned that the Ottomans would soon move into [[Dalmatia]] and Albania.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt315&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schmitt|2009|p=315}}&lt;/ref&gt; They were thus reluctant to fund Skanderbeg's expedition to Italy.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri379&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=379}}&lt;/ref&gt; Due to issues of finance and the lack of large ships (he had, however, received several smaller ships to transport his troops), Skanderbeg's arrival was delayed while Ferdinand was under siege in Barletta. Before the siege began, however, Ferndinand sent four galleys to the Albanian shores where Skanderbeg and his men were waiting.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri379&quot; /&gt; Skanderbeg had meanwhile sent an unnamed captain to his eastern frontiers to guard against an Ottoman attack and left his wife, [[Donika Kastrioti|Donika]], in charge of his affairs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Franco322&quot; /&gt;

[[File:Map of Ragusa.jpg|thumb|left|upright=1.2|Map of the [[Republic of Ragusa]] |alt= A map of the Republic of Ragusa which Skanderbeg visited before setting foot in Italy.]]

A Venetian ambassador on his way from [[Constantinople]] reported that Skanderbeg had assembled 1,000 cavalry and 2,000 infantry along with several papal and Neapolitan ships at ''Capo-di-Lachi'' ({{lang-al|Kepi i Lagjit}}) near modern-day [[Kavajë]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|pp=379–380}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Noli127&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Noli|1947|p=127}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was still awaiting a supply of grain and two Neapolitan ships, however, so he continued to wait. On 21–22 August 1461, the four galleys sent by Ferdinand arrived. He boarded soon thereafter but he did not send his entire force directly to Apulia. He sent Gjokë Balsha (who had returned from Italy) with 500 cavalry and 1,000 infantry to the besieged Ferdinand, whereas Skanderbeg himself went to Ragusa to convince its rectors there to give him his needed funds. Balsha's men landed in Barletta on 24 August 1461. The Angevin forces, among whom was Giovanni Orsini, feared that Skanderbeg himself was the leader of this force, so they lifted the siege of Barletta immediately. Balsha then informed Ferdinand that Skanderbeg would arrive after his voyage to Ragusa.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri380&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=380}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ferdinand felt that Skanderbeg's personal involvement was essential and began to worry when he did not come in two days, as Balsha had promised.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri381&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=381}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Skanderbeg reached Ragusa on 24 August 1461 along with the [[Pal Engjëlli]], the [[Archbishop of Dyrrachium|Archbishop of Durrës]]. His men stayed on the ships anchored in the harbor while he went into the city. Due to papal pressure, the Ragusans had reconsidered Skanderbeg's requests.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri381&quot; /&gt; His fame was visible when he walked through the city-gates and the population poured into the streets to see him. He had been greeted with a ceremony and a tour of the city inspecting its [[Walls of Dubrovnik|walls]] and weaponry. He then received the financial sum he had come for.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri382&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=382}}&lt;/ref&gt; His men were also supplied with food for their coming campaign.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt317&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schmitt|2009|p=317}}&lt;/ref&gt; His popularity allowed him to be well-kept by the Ragusans where the largest Albanian community outside of Albania was present. On 29 August 1461, Skanderbeg set off for Apulia, but a storm forced him to anchor off a Dalmatian island. On 3 September 1461, Skanderbeg finally reached Barletta.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri383&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=383}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Skanderbeg in Italy===
[[File:Skanderbeg disembarking with his troops in Italy.png|thumb|244x244px|Skanderbeg disembarking in Italy - Engraving by Jost Amman 1587]]
Even though they lifted the siege of Barletta upon seeing Skanderbeg's approaching men the week before, Angevin forces remained active.&lt;ref name=&quot;Franco322&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Franco|1539|p=322}}&lt;/ref&gt; Once Skanderbeg arrived, Ferdinand put him in command of the fortress of Barletta whereas the King himself went to [[Ariano Irpino]]. Once left in command of the fortress, Skanderbeg moved against Ferdinand's rivals. Among them were Giovanni Orsini, Jean d'Anjou (the Duke of [[Calabria]]), Piccinino, and Francesco del Balzo.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri383&quot;/&gt; They had stationed themselves in Andria, where the Albanian assaults continued. The Albanian cavalry's light armament, swift horses and loose ranks allowed them to quickly overcome the more heavily armed Italian cavalry, which fought in tight formations. In one of their operations, an Albanian warrior captured Alois Minutulo, the lord of the Castle of [[Monte Sant'Angelo]] who was imprisoned in the Fortress of Barletta.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri383&quot;/&gt; Three years later, Ferdinand would present Skanderbeg with the castle as a token of his gratitude.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt318&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schmitt|2009|p=318}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Ferdinand's opponents, under Piccinino's main command, tried to open battle with Skanderbeg, but due to the combined strength of Albanian and Neapolitan forces, they withdrew from the Andrian fields to [[Acquaviva delle Fonti]]. News of Piccinino's retreat reached Venice who sent a message to [[Francisco Sforza]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri383&quot;/&gt; Skanderbeg then marched to [[Taranto]], where Giovanni Orsini was prince. Orsini tried again to dissuade Skanderbeg from marching against him, but Ferdinand was wary of Orsini's faithfulness, so Skanderbeg continued raiding Orsini's territory.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri384&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=384}}&lt;/ref&gt; He split his army into three parts, one under [[Moisi Arianit Golemi]], the other under [[Vladan Gjurica]], and the last under his command. He led attacks against Ferdinand's enemies in three directions without halt, thoroughly exhausting them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Franco324&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Franco|1539|p=324}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the month of October, Skanderbeg continued to pillage Orisini's territory from his bases at Barletta and Andria since the Angevins were not present; Ferdinand meanwhile mopped up in [[Calabria]], where he recaptured [[Cosenza]] and [[Castrovillari]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt319&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schmitt|2009|p=319}}&lt;/ref&gt; At this point, Orsini asked Skanderbeg for a truce which the Albanian rejected. On 27 October, Skanderbeg reported that he had captured the town of [[Gesualdo, Campania|Gisualdo]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt320&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schmitt|2009|p=320}}&lt;/ref&gt; Piccinino then asked Skanderbeg to discontinue his campaign which Skanderbeg exuberantly accepted, believing that peace was near.&lt;ref name=&quot;Franco324&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Monte sant'angelo castle old.jpg|thumb|The Castle of Monte Sant'Angelo in an early 20th-century photograph |alt= An old photograph of the Castle of Monte Sant'Angelo which was afterwards awarded to Skanderbeg by Ferdinand.|left]]

Piccinino, however, did not seek to maintain the agreement as one of his deserters reported.&lt;ref name=&quot;Franco324&quot;/&gt; Upon learning this, Skanderbeg decided to open battle with Piccinino's men. After feeding his men and preparing his horses, Skanderbeg set off by moonlight for the Angevin camp. He found the place empty, however, since one of Piccinino's men had already informed Piccinino on the Albanians' intentions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Franco325&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Franco|1539|p=325}}&lt;/ref&gt; Skanderbeg then returned to Barletta where he was reinforced by Ferdinand and his men. He then split his army into two, one under Alessandro Sforza's command, the other under his, and he approached Troia. Jean d'Anjou and Piccinino were stationed in [[Lucera]], however, eight miles from Troia. Knowing that battle would come between Troia and Lucera, Skanderbeg set out by night to capture Seggiano, a mountain lying between the two cities, where he stationed some of his men to protect it. Thence, his men could find refuge in case of defeat.&lt;ref name=&quot;Franco325&quot;/&gt; Piccinino had the same objective in mind and set out to capture the mountain, but instead met Skanderbeg's men. He thus kept his men in order for the coming battle. The next day, the two armies met. The battle lasted until dusk, but Jean's men suffered a serious defeat and he was forced to flee. Piccinino then retreated from his campaigns.&lt;ref name=&quot;Franco325&quot;/&gt; He went northwards where he joined Sigismondo Malatesta and 200 of his men to launch assaults on the papal state.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt322&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schmitt|2009|p=322}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Skanderbeg's next task was to recapture [[Trani]], the second most important point in Apulia, aside from Barletta. He succeeded in capturing the commander of the garrison, Fuscia de Foxa, who had rebelled against Ferdinand. Fuscia was outside the walls of Trani with sixteen men when Skanderbeg saw him and surrounded him and then tried to convince him to abandon Orsini, whereby Fuscia refused for pecuniary reasons.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri386&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=386}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt321&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schmitt|2009|p=321}}&lt;/ref&gt;  On the morning of 28 December 1461, with Fuscia's pleas, Gracciani, the vice-commander of the garrison, surrendered Trani. Both Fuscia and Gracciani, however, refused to hand over the garrison's munitions. Skanderbeg threatened to imprison them if they did not surrender what they were asked to, forcing the two to hand over Trani's stores.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri386&quot;/&gt; After weeks of marauding, Skanderbeg and his Aragonese colleagues joined Alessandro Sforza's men.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt322&quot;/&gt; They then yielded all of the fortresses that they had recaptured to Ferdinand.&lt;ref name=&quot;Franco326&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Franco|1539|p=326}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
Seeing that their fortunes were dwindling, Ferdinand's rivals tried to settle for peace with Francisco Sforza. Ferdinand sent Skanderbeg as an intermediary where Giovanni Orsini and Piccinino offered peace if paid 150,000 and 110,000 ducats respectively, something that Ferdinand refused.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri386&quot;/&gt; This was one of Skanderbeg's last personal actions in Italy. He stayed in Apulia for another month until January 1462 when he returned to Albania, leaving his soldiers in Italy. His reason for leaving Italy is not clear, but it is believed that at that time Mehmed was preparing his campaign against Hungary, something which could be turned against Albania. On his return route, he again visited Ragusa, where he was likewise welcomed as a hero.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri386&quot;/&gt; He wanted to set off for Albania immediately, but bad weather forced him to stay.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt323&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schmitt|2009|p=323}}&lt;/ref&gt; He was offered supplies by the Ragusan Rectors, suggesting that he wished to continue to Albania via land, but instead, after ten days in Ragusa, he sailed by ship to Albania. Before leaving, he purchased grain from Sicily for his soldiers in Apulia.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri387&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=387}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The war over the Crown of Naples continued for several more months after Skanderbeg left. It is not known if Albanian warriors fought in the ensuing battles. In August 1462, Ferdinand achieved a decisive victory at [[Orsara di Puglia|Orsara]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri387&quot;/&gt; Skanderbeg's expedition made him famous throughout Italy. In his book, ''De Bello Neapolitano'' ({{lang-en|The Neapolitan War}}), [[Iovianus Pontanus]] sees the Albanian landing as essential to Ferdinand's victory: their quick maneuvering and swift assaults virtually immobilized the Italian warriors.&lt;ref name=&quot;Frasheri388&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|p=388}}&lt;/ref&gt; Skanderbeg's expedition succeeded in lifting the Siege of Barletta, capturing Trani through a ruse, forcing the Angevins to turn from an offensive to a defensive strategy, and devastating the land to the point where its inhabitants and Giovanni Orsini were forced to submit to Ferdinand, even allowing Ferdinand to safely attend the wedding of Antonio Piccolomini, Pius II's nephew.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Frashëri|2002|pp=389–390}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, the campaign was instrumental in securing the Neapolitan kingdom for Ferdinand.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Setton|1978|pp=231–232}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For his services, Ferdinand awarded Monte Sant'Angelo to Skanderbeg where many of his men soon settled.&lt;ref name=&quot;Schmitt324&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Schmitt|2009|p=324}}&lt;/ref&gt; They settled fifteen villages in the rolling landscapes to the east of Taranto.&lt;ref name=Nasse25/&gt; His return to Albania was greeted as a triumph by his followers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Noli131&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Noli|1947|p=131}}&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the jubilation, however, Skanderbeg began to prepare for war. On 7 July 1462, the Turkish army resumed its campaigns in Albania. The first major engagement was at [[Battle of Mokra (July 1462)|Mokra]] on 7 July 1462.&lt;ref name=&quot;Francione158&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Francione|2003|p=158}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the following [[Skanderbeg's Macedonian campaign|Macedonian campaign]] in August of the same year, Skanderbeg defeated three Ottoman armies in one month.&lt;ref name=&quot;Francione159&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Francione|2003|p=159}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 27 April 1463, Skanderbeg and Mehmed signed a new peace treaty,&lt;ref name=&quot;Hodgkinson188&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Hodgkinson|1999|p=188}}&lt;/ref&gt; but later, on 9 September 1463, Skanderbeg signed an alliance with Venice which had been preparing for war against the Ottomans.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hodgkinson190&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Hodgkinson|1999|p=190}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 12 October 1463, Pius grew confident enough to declare his crusade against the Ottoman Turks which Skanderbeg joined.&lt;ref name=&quot;Francione165&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Francione|2003|p=165}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Mehmed II's first Albanian campaign]]
*[[Wars in Lombardy]]
*[[Ottoman-Venetian War (1463-1479)]]
*[[Italian Wars]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|colwidth=25em}}

==References==
* {{citation|last=Babinger|first=Franz|year=1978|title=Mehmed the Conqueror and His Time|publisher=Princeton University Press|location=Princeton, N.J.|isbn=0-691-01078-1}}
* {{citation|page= |title=Skënderbeu, një hero modern: (Hero multimedial) |first=Gennaro |last=Francione |year=2006 |trans-title=Skanderbeg, a modern hero (Hero multimedia)  |editor1-first=Donika |editor1-last=Aliaj |others=Translated by Tasim Aliaj |isbn=99927-38-75-8 |location=[[Tirana|Tiranë, Albania]] |publisher=Shtëpia botuese &quot;Naim Frashëri&quot; |origyear=2003 |url=http://www.bksh.al/adlib/scripts/wwwopac.exe?DATABASE=books&amp;OPAC_URL=/adlib/expert/index_al.html&amp;LANGUAGE=1&amp;%250=33427&amp;LIMIT=50 |language=Albanian}}
* {{citation|last=Franco|first=Demetrio|year=1539|title=Comentario de le cose de' Turchi, et del S. Georgio Scanderbeg, principe d' Epyr|location=Venice|publisher=Altobello Salkato|isbn=99943-1-042-9}}
* {{citation|last=Frashëri|first=Kristo |title=Gjergj Kastrioti Skënderbeu: jeta dhe vepra, 1405–1468|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=vwR3PQAACAAJ&amp;dq=kristo+frasheri+skenderbeu&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=vD6aTMPAFoPGlQeau_HZDw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCsQ6AEwAA|year=2002 |publisher=Botimet Toena|location=Tiranë|language=Albanian|isbn=99927-1-627-4}}
* {{citation|last=Hodgkinson|first=Harry|title=Scanderbeg: From Ottoman Captive to Albanian Hero|year=1999|publisher=Centre for Albanian Studies|location=London|isbn=978-1-873928-13-4}}
* {{Citation|last=Nasse|first=George Nicholas|title=The Italo-Albanian Villages of Southern Italy|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=VjArAAAAYAAJ|year=1964|publisher=National Academies|location=Washington D.C.|oclc=476226177}}
* {{citation|last=Noli|first=Fan Stilian|year=1947|title=George Castroiti Scanderbeg (1405–1468)|publisher=International Universities Press|location=New York|oclc=732882}}
*{{citation|last=Schmitt|first=Oliver Jens|authorlink=Oliver Jens Schmitt|year=2009|title=Skënderbeu|publisher=K&amp;B|location=Tiranë|isbn=978-99956-667-5-0}}
*{{citation|last=Setton|first=Kenneth Meyer|authorlink=Kenneth Setton|year=1978|title=The Papacy and the Levant, 1204-1571|location=Philadelphia|publisher=DIANE Publishing|isbn=978-0-87169-127-9}}

==External links==
* [https://books.google.com/books?id=P3wKAAAAMAAJ&amp;printsec=titlepage&amp;source=gbs_summary_r&amp;cad=0 ''George Castriot, Surnamed Scanderbeg, King of Albania''] by [[Clement Clarke Moore]] - See Book X (pp.&amp;nbsp;298–315) for a description of Skanderbeg's Italian expedition
* [http://grecicousins.com/41.html Skanderbeg's Expedition in Italy] - Excerpt from ''Appunti Di Storia Cronologica Di Greci'' by Sacerdote Gerado Conforti (1922)

{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2011}}
{{Good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Skanderbeg's Italian Expedition}}
[[Category:Warfare by Skanderbeg]]
[[Category:Wars involving the Papal States]]
[[Category:Military history of Italy]]
[[Category:1460s in the Papal States]]</text>
      <sha1>cqes1p9s90uu9e3m3h3xa3eimta006h</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
