<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>SMS Schwaben</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>15061596</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750911897</id>
      <parentid>750875292</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-22T05:23:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Yobot</username>
        <id>7328338</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Description */[[WP:CHECKWIKI]] error fixes using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20680">{| {{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
| Ship image   = [[File:Bundesarchiv DVM 10 Bild-23-61-16, Linienschiff &quot;SMS Wittelsbach&quot;.jpg|300px]]
| Ship caption = SMS ''Schwaben''{{'}}s sister ship ''Wittlesbach''
}}
{{Infobox ship career
| Hide header = 
| Ship country = [[German Empire]]
| Ship flag = {{shipboxflag|German Empire|naval}}
| Ship name = ''Schwaben''
| Ship namesake = [[House of Swabia]]
| Ship builder = [[Kaiserliche Werft Wilhelmshaven]]
| Ship laid down = 15 September 1900
| Ship launched = 19 August 1901
| Ship christened = [[Charlotte of Schaumburg-Lippe|Queen Charlotte of Württemberg]]
| Ship commissioned = 13 April 1904
| Ship struck = 8 March 1921
| Ship fate=Scrapped in 1921
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
| Hide header = 
| Header caption = 
| Ship class = {{sclass-|Wittelsbach|battleship|0}} [[pre-dreadnought battleship]]
| Ship displacement = {{convert|12798|MT|LT|abbr=on|0}}
| Ship length = {{convert|126.8|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
| Ship beam = {{convert|22.8|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
| Ship draft = {{convert|7.95|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
| Ship power = {{convert|14000|PS|ihp kW|lk=on|abbr=on|0}}
| Ship propulsion = 3 shafts, [[triple expansion engine]]s
| Ship speed = {{convert|18|kn|lk=in}}
| Ship range = {{convert|5000|nmi|lk=in}}; {{convert|10|kn}}
| Ship complement =*  30 officers
* 650 enlisted men
  
| Ship armament =*  4 × {{convert|24|cm|in|1|abbr=on}} guns (40 cal.)
* 18 × {{convert|15|cm|in|1|abbr=on}} guns
* 12 × {{convert|8.8|cm|in|1|abbr=on}} guns
*  6 × {{convert|45|cm|in||abbr=on}} [[torpedo tube]]s
  
| Ship armor =* [[Belt armor|Belt]]:    {{convert|100|to|225|mm|in|abbr=on}}
* [[Gun turret|Turrets]]: {{convert|250|mm|in|abbr=on}}
* Deck:    {{convert|50|mm|in|abbr=on}}
  
| Ship notes = 
}}
|}

'''SMS ''Schwaben''''' (&quot;His Majesty's Ship ''[[Swabia]]''&quot;){{efn|name=SMS|}} was the fourth ship of the {{sclass-|Wittelsbach|battleship|4}} of [[pre-dreadnought]] [[battleship]]s of the [[Kaiserliche Marine|German Imperial Navy]]. ''Schwaben'' was built at the [[Kaiserliche Werft Wilhelmshaven|Imperial Dockyard]] in [[Wilhelmshaven]]. She was laid down in 1900, and completed in April 1904, at the cost of 21,678,000 [[German gold mark|marks]]. Her [[sister ship]]s were {{SMS|Wittelsbach||2}}, {{SMS|Zähringen||2}}, {{SMS|Wettin||2}} and {{SMS|Mecklenburg||2}}; they were the first capital ships built under the [[German Naval Laws|Navy Law of 1898]], championed by [[Admiral]] [[Alfred von Tirpitz]]. ''Schwaben'' was armed with a main battery of four {{convert|24|cm|sp=us|adj=on}} guns and had a top speed of {{convert|18|kn}}.

''Schwaben'' spent the majority of her career as a gunnery training ship from 1904 to 1914, though she frequently participated in the large scale fleet exercises during this period. After the start of [[World War I]] in August 1914, the ship was mobilized with her sisters as the IV Battle Squadron. She saw limited duty in the North Sea as a guard ship and in the Baltic Sea against Russian forces. The threat from British submarines forced the ship to withdraw from the Baltic in 1916. For the remainder of the war, ''Schwaben'' served as an engineering training ship for navy cadets. She was retained by the [[Reichsmarine]] after the war and reactivated from 1919 until June 1920, serving as a depot ship for F-type [[Minesweeper (ship)|minesweepers]] in the Baltic. The ship was stricken from the navy list in March 1921 and sold for scrapping in that year.

== Description ==
{{main article|Wittelsbach-class battleship}}
[[File:Wittelsbach class linedrawing.png|thumb|left|Line-drawing of the ''Wittelsbach'' class]]

''Schwaben'' was {{convert|126.8|m|ftin|abbr=on}} [[length overall|long overall]] and had a [[beam (nautical)|beam]] of {{convert|22.8|m|ftin|abbr=on}} and a [[Draft (hull)|draft]] of {{convert|7.95|m|ftin|abbr=on}} forward. The ship was powered by three 3-cylinder vertical [[triple expansion engine]]s that drove three screws. Steam was provided by six [[water-tube boiler|water-tube]] and six cylindrical coal-fired boilers. ''Schwaben''{{'}}s powerplant was rated at {{convert|14000|PS|ihp kW|lk=on|0}}, which generated a top speed of {{convert|18|kn}}. She had a crew of 30&amp;nbsp;officers and 650&amp;nbsp;enlisted men.{{sfn|Gröner|pp=16–17}}

''Schwaben''{{'}}s armament consisted of a main battery of four 24&amp;nbsp;cm (9.4&amp;nbsp;in) SK L/40 guns in twin [[gun turret]]s,{{efn|name=gun nomenclature}} one fore and one aft of the central [[superstructure]].{{sfn|Hore|p=67}} Her secondary armament consisted of eighteen 15&amp;nbsp;cm (5.9&amp;nbsp;inch) SK L/40 guns and twelve 8.8&amp;nbsp;cm (3.45&amp;nbsp;in) SK L/30 quick-firing guns. The armament system was rounded out with six {{convert|45|cm|in||abbr=on}} torpedo tubes, all submerged in the hull; one was in the bow, one in the stern, and the other four were on the [[broadside]]. Her [[armored belt]] was {{convert|225|mm|sp=us}} thick in the central portion that protected her magazines and machinery spaces, and the [[deck (ship)|deck]] was {{convert|50|mm|abbr=on}} thick. The main battery turrets had {{convert|250|mm|abbr=on}} of armor plating.{{sfn|Gröner|p=16}}

== Service history ==
''Schwaben''{{'}}s keel was laid 15 September 1900, at the [[Kaiserliche Werft Wilhelmshaven|Imperial Dockyard]] in [[Wilhelmshaven]], under construction number 27. She was ordered under the contract name &quot;G&quot;, as a new unit for the fleet.{{sfn|Gröner|p=16}} The vessel was a member of the first class of battleships built under the direction of Admiral [[Alfred von Tirpitz]], the State Secretary of the ''[[Reichsmarineamt]]'' (RMA&amp;mdash;Imperial Navy Office), according to the terms of the [[German Naval Laws|Navy Law of 1898]].{{sfn|Herwig|p=43}} ''Schwaben'' was launched on 19 August 1901; during the launching ceremony, [[William II of Württemberg|King Wilhelm II of Württemberg]] gave a speech and his wife [[Charlotte of Schaumburg-Lippe|Queen Charlotte of Württemberg]] christened the ship.{{sfn|Hildebrand Röhr &amp; Steinmetz|p=140}} She was commissioned on 13 April 1904, the last ship of her class to enter active service.{{sfn|Gröner|p=17}} The ship's cost totaled 21,678,000 [[German gold mark|marks]].{{sfn|Gröner|p=16}}

There was a dispute over where ''Schwaben'' should be assigned after her commissioning in April 1904. Admiral [[Hans von Koester]], the fleet commander, wanted the ship to be assigned to the active duty squadron, but  Tirpitz wanted to use the new battleship as a training vessel, since the Training Squadron only possessed cruisers and obsolescent ships. Tirpitz won the debate, and so ''Schwaben'' was to replace the ancient [[ironclad warship|ironclad]] [[frigate]] {{SMS|Friedrich Carl|1867|2}} in the Training Squadron. There, she was to serve as a torpedo training ship. On 18 May, ''Schwaben'' departed Wilhelmshaven and passed through the [[Skagerrak]] to the [[Baltic Sea]], arriving in [[Kiel]] on 22 May.{{sfn|Hildebrand Röhr &amp; Steinmetz|p=140}}

While on [[sea trials]], she struck an uncharted [[shoal]] off the northern tip of the island of [[Fehmarn]]. The impact damaged a {{convert|30|m|sp=us|adj=on}} length of the ship's hull and holed it in several places. After repairs were completed, she resumed her trials, which lasted until the end of 1904. The trials were interrupted by the annual autumn maneuvers, during which ''Schwaben'' joined the active fleet in the [[North Sea]]. On 11 January 1905, she was formally assigned to the Training Squadron, but as an artillery training ship to replace the old vessel {{SMS|Mars|1877|2}}.{{sfn|Hildebrand Röhr &amp; Steinmetz|p=140}} The ship was based in [[Sonderburg]] in the Baltic, along with the armored cruisers {{SMS|Prinz Heinrich||2}} and {{SMS|Prinz Adalbert|1901|2}}, and several other training ships.{{sfn|''Germany''|p=1049}} She began an annual routine of gunnery training in the western Baltic that was interrupted only by yearly gunnery drills with the entire [[High Seas Fleet]] in October. During these fleet exercises, ''Schwaben'' was supported by the tender {{SMS|Ulan||2}}. ''Schwaben'' also went into drydock from the end of October to the middle of December every year for periodic maintenance.{{sfn|Hildebrand Röhr &amp; Steinmetz|p=140}}

''Schwaben'' participated in exercises in the [[Swinemünde]] Bay in April and May 1906, and the annual fleet gunnery drills took place off [[Helgoland]] in August. Her annual overhaul was completed early, in November. In March 1907, ''Schwaben'' participated in gunnery training with the fleet. She joined the [[flagship]] of the Reserve Squadron, the [[coastal defense ship]] {{SMS|Frithjof||2}}, for maneuvers off the coast of [[Farther Pomerania]] in July. The following month, ''Schwaben'' served as the flagship of ''[[Vizeadmiral]]'' (Vice Admiral) [[Hugo Zeye]] for a training squadron during the fleet maneuvers in the North Sea. Directly after the conclusion of the fleet maneuvers in mid-September, ''Schwaben'' participated in fleet gunnery drills off Helgoland. The year was concluded with an overhaul in the Imperial Dockyard in Wilhelmshaven.{{sfn|Hildebrand Röhr &amp; Steinmetz|p=141}}

In 1908, the training ships based in the Baltic were placed under the command of Rear Admiral [[Hugo von Pohl]],{{sfn|''The German Fleet''|p=10}} who would go on to command the High Seas Fleet in 1915 during [[World War I]].{{sfn|Tarrant|p=43}} That year followed the same pattern as the previous year, but ''Schwaben'' did not participate in the autumn fleet maneuvers. She instead remained at Sonderburg and [[Als (island)|Alsen]] during the exercises. In 1909, after the autumn maneuvers, ''Schwaben'' was assigned as the flagship of the Reserve Fleet, again under the command of Admiral Zeye. During her yearly overhaul at the Imperial Dockyard in Wilhelmshaven, her guns were fitted with new motors produced in Germany to test their reliability over foreign-manufactured motors. The tests proved to be successful. While steaming in the [[Flensburg Firth]] on 10&amp;ndash;12 December, she had to assist the training ship {{SMS|Württemberg|1878|2}} in heavy fog.{{sfn|Hildebrand Röhr &amp; Steinmetz|p=141}}

In 1910, after the normal training routine in the first half of the year, ''Schwaben'' was assigned to the [[III Battle Squadron]] of the High Seas Fleet for the autumn maneuvers, which lasted from 19 August to 11 September. She served in this role to replace the battleships {{SMS|Kurfürst Friedrich Wilhelm||2}} and {{SMS|Weissenburg||2}}, which had been sold to the Ottoman Empire just before the start of the maneuvers. On 14 October, she joined up with the battleship {{SMS|Elsass||2}} and steamed through the [[Kaiser Wilhelm Canal]] to Kiel for her yearly overhaul at the [[Kaiserliche Werft Kiel|Imperial Dockyard]] there. These repairs lasted until 4 January 1911. ''Schwaben'' served in the III Battle Squadron during the autumn maneuvers again in 1911.{{sfn|Hildebrand Röhr &amp; Steinmetz|p=141}} By 1911, the eight {{sclass-|Nassau|battleship|5}} and {{sclass-|Helgoland|battleship|4}}es of [[dreadnought battleship]]s had entered service;{{sfn|Gardiner &amp; Gray|pp=145&amp;ndash;146}} these ships were assigned to the [[I Battle Squadron]], which displaced the newer pre-dreadnoughts of the {{sclass-|Deutschland|battleship|5}} and {{sclass-|Braunschweig|battleship|4}}es to the [[II Battle Squadron|II]] and III Battle Squadrons.{{sfn|Staff|pp=11&amp;ndash;14}} As a result, ''Schwaben'' was decommissioned in Wilhelmshaven on 30 December 1911 and assigned to the Reserve Division in the North Sea. She was placed back in service briefly from 9 to 12 May 1912 to move to Kiel. ''Schwaben'' returned to service again to participate in the autumn maneuvers from 14 August to 28 September, as the flagship of then-''[[Konteradmiral]]'' (Rear Admiral) [[Maximilian von Spee]].{{sfn|Hildebrand Röhr &amp; Steinmetz|p=141}}

===World War I===
[[File:North and Baltic Seas, 1911.png|thumb|Map of the North and Baltic Seas in 1911]]
After the outbreak of World War I in August 1914, ''Schwaben'' and the rest of her class were mobilized to serve in the IV Battle Squadron, under the command of Vice Admiral Ehrhard Schmidt.{{sfn|Scheer|p=15}} After it reached full combat readiness, the Squadron was employed both as a defense force in the [[German Bight]]&amp;mdash;usually stationed in the mouth of the [[Elbe]]&amp;mdash;and for operations in the Baltic.{{sfn|Hildebrand Röhr &amp; Steinmetz|p=141}} Starting on 3 September, the IV Squadron, assisted by the [[armored cruiser]] {{SMS|Blücher||2}}, conducted a sweep into the Baltic. The operation lasted until 9 September and failed to bring Russian naval units to battle.{{sfn|Halpern|p=185}} In May 1915, IV Squadron, including ''Schwaben'', was transferred to support the German Army in the Baltic Sea area.{{sfn|Scheer|pp=90–91}} ''Schwaben'' and her sisters were then based in Kiel.{{sfn|Halpern|p=192}} During this period, she served as the flagship of the second command admiral of the Squadron, ''Konteradmiral'' Alberts.{{sfn|Hildebrand Röhr &amp; Steinmetz|p=141}}

On 6 May, the IV Squadron ships were tasked with providing support to the assault on [[Liepāja|Libau]]. ''Schwaben'' and the other ships stood off [[Gotland]] in order to intercept any Russian cruisers that might try to intervene in the landings, which the Russians did not attempt. On 10 May, after the invasion force had entered Libau, the British submarines {{HMS|E1}} and {{HMS|E9}} spotted the IV Squadron, but were too far away to make an attack.{{sfn|Halpern|p=192}} The increasingly active British submarines forced the Germans to employ more destroyers to protect the capital ships. As a result, ''Schwaben'' and her sisters were not included in the German fleet that [[Battle of the Gulf of Riga|assaulted the Gulf of Riga]] in August 1915, due to the scarcity of escorts.{{sfn|Halpern|p=197}} On 29 August, ''[[Kapitän zur See]]'' (Captain at Sea) Walter Engelhardt replaced Alberts aboard ''Schwaben''. She was then used as a guard ship in Libau, starting on 24 September. On 10&amp;ndash;11 November, ''Schwaben'', her sisters {{SMS|Wittelsbach||2}} and {{SMS|Wettin||2}}, and ''Prinz Heinrich'' left Libau, bound for Kiel.{{sfn|Hildebrand Röhr &amp; Steinmetz|p=141}}

By late 1915, the increasing threat from British submarines in the Baltic convinced the German navy to withdraw the elderly ''Wittelsbach''-class ships from active service.{{sfn|Herwig|p=168}} On 20 November ''Schwaben'' steamed to Wilhelmshaven, where she replaced {{SMS|Kaiser Karl der Grosse||2}} as a training ship for engineers, a role she held for the remainder of the war.{{sfn|Gröner|p=17}}{{sfn|Hildebrand Röhr &amp; Steinmetz|pp=141&amp;ndash;142}} After the [[Battle of Jutland]] on 31 May&amp;nbsp;– 1 June, in which ''Schwaben'' did not take part, Rear Admiral [[Franz von Hipper]], the commander of the German [[battlecruiser]] squadron,{{sfn|Tarrant|p=287}} sent his four surviving battlecruisers to dock for repairs. Hipper made ''Schwaben'', which was stationed in Wilhelmshaven, his temporary command ship while his force was being repaired.{{sfn|Raeder|p=77}} In 1916, ''Schwaben'' was partially disarmed; the four 24&amp;nbsp;cm guns were removed, her battery of 15&amp;nbsp;cm guns was reduced to six weapons, and only four 8.8&amp;nbsp;cm guns were left aboard.{{sfn|Hildebrand Röhr &amp; Steinmetz|p=142}}

===Postwar service===
The ship was briefly retained by the [[Reichsmarine]] after the war, and was reactivated for service on 1 August 1919.{{sfn|Hildebrand Röhr &amp; Steinmetz|p=142}} According to Articles 182 and 193 of the [[Treaty of Versailles]], Germany was obliged to keep sufficient vessels in commission to sweep mines from large areas in the North and Baltic Seas.{{refn|[[s:Treaty of Versailles 1919|Treaty of Versailles]] Section II: Naval Clauses, Articles 182 and 193.}} ''Schwaben'' was therefore converted into a [[depot ship]] for F-type minesweepers to assist in meeting Germany's treaty obligations,{{sfn|Gardiner &amp; Gray|p=141}} which entailed removal of her remaining weaponry and construction of platforms to hold the minesweepers. She was assigned to the 6th Baltic Minesweeping Half-Flotilla, though this service did not last long, as the minesweeping work was completed by 19 June 1920. The old battleship was stricken from the naval register on 8 March 1921. She was sold for 3,090,000&amp;nbsp;marks and broken up for scrap that year in Kiel-Nordmole.{{sfn|Gröner|p=17}}{{sfn|Hildebrand Röhr &amp; Steinmetz|p=142}}

== Notes ==

'''Footnotes'''

{{notes
| notes =

{{efn
| name = SMS
| &quot;SMS&quot; stands for &quot;''[[Seiner Majestät Schiff]]''&quot; ({{lang-de|link=no|His Majesty's Ship}}).
}}

{{efn
| name = gun nomenclature
| In Imperial German Navy gun nomenclature, &quot;SK&quot; (''Schnelladekanone'') denotes that the gun is quick firing, while the L/40 denotes the length of the gun. In this case, the L/40 gun is 40 [[Caliber (artillery)|calibers]], meaning that the gun is 40 times as long as it is in diameter. See: {{harvnb|Grießmer|p=177}}.
}}

}}

'''Citations'''

{{reflist|20em}}

== References ==

{{portal|Battleships}}

'''Books'''

* {{cite book
  | editor1-last = Gardiner
  | editor1-first = Robert
  | editor2-last = Gray
  | editor2-first = Randal
  | year = 1985
  | title = Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships: 1906–1921
  | publisher = Naval Institute Press
  | location = Annapolis
  | isbn = 978-0-87021-907-8
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Gardiner &amp; Gray}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Grießmer
  | first = Axel
  | year = 1999
  | language = German
  | title = Die Linienschiffe der Kaiserlichen Marine
  | trans-title=The Battleships of the Imperial Navy
  | publisher = Bernard &amp; Graefe Verlag
  | location = Bonn
  | isbn = 978-3-7637-5985-9
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Grießmer}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Gröner
  | first = Erich
  | year = 1990
  | title = German Warships: 1815–1945
  | publisher = Naval Institute Press
  | location = Annapolis
  | isbn = 978-0-87021-790-6
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Gröner}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Halpern
  | first = Paul G.
  | year = 1995
  | title = A Naval History of World War I
  | publisher = Naval Institute Press
  | location = Annapolis
  | isbn = 978-1-55750-352-7
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Halpern}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Herwig
  | first = Holger
  | year = 1998
  | origyear = 1980
  | title = &quot;Luxury&quot; Fleet: The Imperial German Navy 1888–1918
  | publisher = Humanity Books
  | location = Amherst
  | isbn = 978-1-57392-286-9
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Herwig}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last1 = Hildebrand
  | first1 = Hans H.
  | last2 = Röhr
  | first2 = Albert
  | last3 = Steinmetz
  | first3 = Hans-Otto
  | year = 1993
  | title = Die Deutschen Kriegsschiffe (Volume 7)
  | trans-title=The German Warships
  | language = German
  | publisher = Mundus Verlag
  | location = Ratingen
  |asin=B003VHSRKE |asin-tld=de
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Hildebrand Röhr &amp; Steinmetz}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Hore
  | first = Peter
  | year = 2006
  | title = The Ironclads
  | publisher = Southwater Publishing
  | location = London
  | isbn = 978-1-84476-299-6
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Hore}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Raeder
  | first = Erich
  | title = My Life
  | year = 1960
  | publisher = United States Naval Institute
  | location = Annapolis
  | oclc = 883168
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Raeder}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Scheer
  | first = Reinhard
  | year = 1920
  | title = Germany's High Seas Fleet in the World War
  | publisher = Cassell and Company
  | location = London
  | oclc = 2765294
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Scheer}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Staff
  | first = Gary
  | year = 2010
  | title = German Battleships: 1914–1918 (1)
  | publisher = Osprey Books
  | location = Oxford
  | isbn = 978-1-84603-467-1
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Staff}}
  }}
* {{cite book
  | last = Tarrant
  | first = V. E.
  | year = 2001
  | origyear = 1995
  | title = Jutland: The German Perspective
  | publisher = Cassell Military Paperbacks
  | location = London
  | isbn = 978-0-304-35848-9
  | ref = {{sfnRef|Tarrant}}
  }}

'''Journals'''

* {{cite journal
  | title = Germany
  | year = 1911
  | journal = Proceedings
  | volume = 37
  | pages = 1044–1050
  | publisher = United States Naval Institute
  | location = Annapolis
  | ISSN = 0041-798X
  | ref = {{sfnRef|''Germany''}}
  }}
* {{cite journal
  | title = The German Fleet
  | year = 1908
  | journal = The Navy
  | volume = 
  | pages = 10–11
  | publisher = Navy Publishing Co.
  | location = Washington D.C.
  | oclc = 7550453
  | ref = {{sfnRef|''The German Fleet''}}
  }}

{{Wittelsbach class battleship}}

{{Good Article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Schwaben}}
[[Category:Wittelsbach-class battleships]]
[[Category:1901 ships]]</text>
      <sha1>9ns16xg7da1v131mtue0srvw2o4dqff</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
