<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>SMS Seeadler</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3534408</id>
    <revision>
      <id>739892181</id>
      <parentid>739633655</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-17T18:42:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mdnavman</username>
        <id>7061136</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* External links */ Added template.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22174">{{About|the long range cruiser|the World War I commerce raider|SMS Seeadler (1888)}}
{{Good article}}
{|{{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
|Ship image=[[File:SMS Seeadler cropped.jpg|300px]]
|Ship caption=SMS ''Seeadler'' at New York, 1893
}}
{{Infobox ship career
|Hide header=
|Ship country=[[German Empire]]
|Ship flag={{shipboxflag|German Empire|naval}}
|Ship name=''Seeadler''
|Ship namesake=[[White-tailed eagle]] (haliaeetus albicilla)
|Ship builder=[[Kaiserliche Werft Danzig]]
|Ship laid down= 1890 
|Ship launched=2 February 1892 
|Ship commissioned=17 August 1892
|Ship struck=
|Ship fate=Exploded at [[Wilhelmshaven]] 19 April 1917 while being used as a mine hulk
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
|Hide header=
|Header caption=
|Ship class={{sclass-|Bussard|cruiser|0}} [[unprotected cruiser]]
|Ship type=
|Ship displacement={{convert|1864|MT|abbr=on}}
|Ship length={{convert|82.60|m|ft|abbr=on|0}}
|Ship beam={{convert|12.70|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
|Ship draft={{convert|4.42|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
|Ship propulsion= 3-cylinder triple expansion engines, 2 screws
|Ship speed={{convert|16.9|kn|km/h}}
|Ship range={{convert|2950|nmi|km|-1|abbr=on}} at {{convert|9|kn|km/h}}
|Ship complement=*9 officers
*152 enlisted men
|Ship armament=*8 × {{convert|10.5|cm|in|abbr=on}} SK L/35 guns
*5 × revolver cannon
*2 × {{convert|35|cm|in|abbr=on}} [[torpedo tube]]s
|Ship notes=
}}
|}

'''SMS ''Seeadler''''' (&quot;His Majesty's Ship ''Sea Eagle''&quot;){{efn|name=SMS|}} was an [[unprotected cruiser]] of the {{sclass-|Bussard|cruiser|4}}, the third member of a class of six ships built by the German ''[[Kaiserliche Marine]]'' (Imperial Navy). Her sister ships included {{SMS|Bussard||2}}, the [[lead ship]], along with {{SMS|Falke||2}}, {{SMS|Condor||2}}, {{SMS|Cormoran|1892|2}}, and {{SMS|Geier||2}}. ''Seeadler'' was built at the [[Kaiserliche Werft Danzig|''Kaiserliche Werft'']] (Imperial Shipyard) in [[Danzig]] in late 1890, launched in February 1892, and commissioned in August of that year. Intended for colonial service, ''Seeadler'' was armed with a main battery of eight {{convert|10.5|cm|adj=on|sp=us}} guns and had a top speed of {{convert|15.5|kn}}.

''Seeadler'' spent almost her entire career abroad. Following her commissioning, she joined the [[protected cruiser]] {{SMS|Kaiserin Augusta||2}} in 1893 on a visit to the [[United States]] for the 400th anniversary of [[Christopher Columbus]]'s discovery of the Americas. She thereafter went to [[German East Africa]], where she was stationed until 1898. She returned to Germany briefly for a modernization in 1898&amp;ndash;1899, before being assigned to the South Seas Station in [[German New Guinea]]. During her tour in the Pacific, she participated in the suppression of the [[Boxer Rebellion]] in [[Qing China]] in 1900. Her assignment in the Pacific was interrupted by the 1905 [[Maji-Maji Rebellion]] in German East Africa, which prompted the German Navy to send ''Seeadler'' there.

''Seeadler'' remained in East Africa for the next nine years, returning to Germany finally in January 1914. She had spent over thirteen years abroad since her 1899 modernization, the longest period of continuous overseas service of any major German warship. After arriving in Germany, she was decommissioned. She was not mobilized after the outbreak of [[World War I]] in August 1914, being too old to be of any fighting value. She was instead used as a mine storage [[hulk (ship)|hulk]] outside [[Wilhelmshaven]]. On 19 April 1917, her cargo of mines exploded and destroyed the ship, though there were no casualties. Her wreck was never raised for scrapping.

==Design==
{{Main|Bussard-class cruiser}}
[[File:SMS Geier.jpg|thumb|left|Illustration of the ''Bussard''-class cruiser {{SMS|Geier||2}}]]
''Seeadler'' was {{convert|82.60|m|ft|sp=us|0}} [[length overall|long overall]] and had a [[beam (nautical)|beam]] of {{convert|12.70|m|ftin|abbr=on}} and a [[draft (hull)|draft]] of {{convert|4.42|m|ftin|abbr=on}} forward. She displaced {{convert|1864|MT|abbr=on}} at full combat load. Her propulsion system consisted of two horizontal 3-cylinder triple-expansion [[steam engine]]s powered by four coal-fired cylindrical boilers. These provided a top speed of {{convert|16.9|kn|abbr=on}} and a range of approximately {{convert|2950|nmi|lk=in}} at {{convert|9|kn|abbr=on}}. She had a crew of 9 officers and 152 enlisted men.&lt;ref name=G97&gt;Gröner, p. 97&lt;/ref&gt;

The ship was armed with eight [[10.5 cm SK L/35|10.5&amp;nbsp;cm SK L/35]] quick-firing (QF) guns in single pedestal mounts, supplied with 800&amp;nbsp;rounds of ammunition in total. They had a range of {{convert|10800|m|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=G97/&gt; Two guns were placed side by side forward, two on each [[broadside]], and two side by side aft. The gun armament was rounded out by five [[Hotchkiss gun|revolver cannon]].&lt;ref name=G253&gt;Gardiner, p. 253&lt;/ref&gt; She was also equipped with two {{convert|35|cm|abbr=on}} [[torpedo tube]]s with five torpedoes, both of which were mounted on the deck.&lt;ref name=G97/&gt;

==Service history==
[[File:SMS Kaiserin Augusta SMS Seeadler 1890s.jpg|thumb|''Seeadler'' (right) with {{SMS|Kaiserin Augusta||2}} in [[Hampton Roads]]]]
''Seeadler'' ([[White-tailed eagle|sea eagle]])&lt;ref name=HRS151&gt;Hildebrand, Röhr, &amp; Steinmetz, p. 151&lt;/ref&gt; was laid down at the [[Kaiserliche Werft Danzig|''Kaiserliche Werft'']] (Imperial Shipyard) in [[Danzig]] in late 1890. She was launched on 2 February 1892, originally named ''Kaiseradler'' ([[Eastern imperial eagle]]). The shipyard director, ''[[Kapitän zur See]]'' (Captain) Aschmann, gave the launching speech. She was completed by 27 June 1892, when she was commissioned into the [[Imperial German Navy]]. The ship was renamed on 17 August when she was commissioned, since [[Kaiser Wilhelm II]] decided to rename his first [[yacht]] [[SMY Hohenzollern|''Kaiseradler'']] instead. ''Seeadler'' began her [[sea trials]] the same day. On 25 October, she was accidentally rammed by the armored [[corvette]] {{SMS|Bayern|1878|2}} in [[Kiel]], but she suffered only light damage. Her trials lasted until 17 November; she formally entered service with the fleet on 15 March 1893.&lt;ref name=G253/&gt;&lt;ref name=G98&gt;Gröner, p. 98&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=HRS152&gt;Hildebrand, Röhr, &amp; Steinmetz, p. 152&lt;/ref&gt;

After her commissioning, ''Seedadler'' was slated to replace {{SMS|Schwalbe||2}} in the East African Station in [[German East Africa]]. But first, ''Seeadler'' and the [[protected cruiser]] {{SMS|Kaiserin Augusta||2}} conducted a goodwill visit to the United States, a belated celebration of the 400th anniversary of [[Christopher Columbus|Columbus's]] first voyage across the Atlantic. The ships left Kiel on 25 March, but due to a mistaken estimate for the amount of coal that would be necessary to cross the Atlantic, ''Seeadler'' ran out of fuel while en route. ''Kaiserin Augusta'' took the cruiser under tow to [[Halifax Regional Municipality|Halifax]], where she refilled her coal bunkers. The two cruisers reached [[Hampton Roads]] on 18 April.&lt;ref name=HRS152/&gt; Ships from nine other navies, including the [[US Navy]], arrived for a major celebration in New York harbor that was reviewed by [[Grover Cleveland]], the [[President of the United States]].&lt;ref&gt;Sondhaus, p. 206&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Northrop, pp. 195&amp;ndash;197&lt;/ref&gt; ''Seeadler''&lt;nowiki/&gt;'s yacht-like appearance attracted particular attention.&lt;ref name=HRS152/&gt;

===Deployment to East Africa===
After the conclusion of the festivities in the United States, ''Seeadler'' steamed back across the Atlantic to the [[Azores]], before proceeding into the [[Mediterranean Sea]] and then into the [[Red Sea]]. There, she met ''Schwalbe'' at [[Aden]] on 20 June. ''Seeadler'' proceeded to [[Bombay]], India, for routine maintenance that lasted from 3 July to 21 August. The cruiser finally arrived on station on 2 September when she dropped anchor in [[Zanzibar]] and met the survey ship {{SMS|Möwe|1879|2}}, the other vessel on the East Africa Station. On 9 September both ships went to [[Kilwa Kisiwani|Kilwa]]; a group of slave traders had attacked the small police force detachment stationed there. The colonial army, the ''[[Schutztruppe]]'' (protection force), was unavailable to reinforce the police troops, and so ''Seeadler'' and ''Möwe'' bombarded the slavers and neutralized the threat.&lt;ref name=HRS152/&gt;

[[File:Deutsch Ost-Afrika,1892.jpg|thumb|upright|left|Contemporary map of [[German East Africa]]]]
''Seeadler'' proceeded to [[Lourenço Marques]] in Portuguese [[Moçambique]]. A rebellion in the Portuguese colony threatened German nationals residing in the city; ''Seeadler'' evacuated the civilians and took them to Zanzibar, where they arrived on 15 November. During this period, ''Möwe'' was transferred to [[German New Guinea]], and ''Seeadler''{{'}}s [[sister ship]]s {{SMS|Condor||2}} and {{SMS|Cormoran|1892|2}} arrived in German East Africa. ''Condor'' was to reinforce ''Seeadler'' and ''Cormoran'' was to continue on to the Pacific, but the latter remained in the area temporarily to strengthen the German naval force in the region. This was done both to observe the damage to German economic interests in Moçambique and as a show of force to prevent British encroachment on [[Delagoa Bay]], which was the only supply port for the independent [[South African Republic|Transvaal]]. In January 1895, ''Condor'' took over ''Seeadler''{{'}}s role on the East African coast.&lt;ref name=HRS152/&gt;

On 10 January, ''Seeadler'' departed for Bombay, where her boilers were repaired in a major overhaul. Workers from the [[Kaiserliche Werft Kiel|''Kaiserliche Werft'']] in Kiel were sent to do the work. ''Seeadler'' was back in service by May, and on 18 May she departed Bombay, arriving in East Africa on 31 May. ''Cormoran'' was meanwhile detached from East Africa and allowed to continue to the Pacific.&lt;ref&gt;Hildebrand, Röhr, &amp; Steinmetz, pp. 152&amp;ndash;153&lt;/ref&gt; The rest of the year was uneventful for ''Seeadler'', though she became briefly involved in political developments in East Africa. The British [[Jameson Raid]] into the Transvaal in December 1895 threatened some 15,000 German nationals in the Transvaal, along with the investment of 500&amp;nbsp;million [[German gold mark|gold marks]] in the country. The German governor considered ordering ''Seeadler'' to contribute a landing force to protect the German consul in [[Pretoria]], the capital of the Transvaal, but the defeat of the Jameson Raid rendered the plan redundant. ''Seeadler'' nevertheless remained in East Africa while tensions cooled. In mid-February 1896, she went to [[Cape Town]] for her yearly overhaul.&lt;ref name=HRS153&gt;Hildebrand, Röhr, &amp; Steinmetz, p. 153&lt;/ref&gt;

After completing her repairs, ''Seeadler'' was ordered to [[German South-West Africa]] on 28 April to assist the ''Schutztruppe'' in suppressing a local rebellion. The ship was tasked with interrupting the shipment of weapons from British arms dealers to the rebels. ''Seeadler'' thereafter proceeded to [[Swakopmund]] on 5 May; she was joined there by the [[gunboat]] {{SMS|Hyäne||2}}. The two ships sent forces ashore to defend the city. At the end of the month, ''Seeadler'' returned to East Africa. On 2 October, she steamed to Zanzibar to take the deposed Sultan [[Khalid bin Barghash of Zanzibar|Khalid bin Barghash]] to Dar es Salaam following the brief [[Anglo-Zanzibar War]]. On 20 December, ''Seeadler'' was again called to Lourenço Marques after the German consul Graf von Pfeil was attacked by Portuguese colonial police. ''Condor'' joined her there on 2 January 1897 to strengthen the show of force. ''Seeadler'' thereafter proceeded to Cape Town for her yearly overhaul.&lt;ref name=HRS153/&gt;

The following two years proceeded uneventfully. In January 1898, ''Seeadler'' again returned to Cape Town for an overhaul before being ordered to return to Germany on 3 May. She left Dar es Salaam three days later and arrived in Aden on 31 May. There she met ''Schwalbe'', which was replacing her in East Africa. ''Seeadler'' returned to Kiel on 26 June, and she was placed out of service on 9 July for a major overhaul in Danzig. The work was done at the ''Kaiserliche Werft'', and the changes included removing the main mast and cutting down her rigging to a topsail [[schooner]] rig.&lt;ref&gt;Hildebrand, Röhr, &amp; Steinmetz, pp. 153&amp;ndash;154&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gröner, pp. 97&amp;ndash;98&lt;/ref&gt; On 3 October 1899, ''Seeadler'' was recommissioned and was ordered to replace her sister {{SMS|Falke||2}} on the South Seas Station in German New Guinea. She departed Kiel on 19 October and stopped in [[Tangiers]] on 27&amp;ndash;28 October to force restitution from the Moroccan government for damage to German interests. ''Seeadler'' then proceeded to Germany's south-Pacific colonies, arriving on 15 November.&lt;ref name=HRS154&gt;Hildebrand, Röhr, &amp; Steinmetz, p. 154&lt;/ref&gt;

===Deployment to the Pacific===
[[File:SMS Seeadler.png|thumb|''Seeadler'', {{c.|1899}}]]
Following her arrival in the Pacific, ''Seeadler'' first went to the [[Admiralty Islands]] on 18 January 1900 in response to the murder of European businessmen by natives there. Starting on 30 January, she took a cruise to tour the German holdings in the area that lasted for several weeks. Stops included the [[Caroline Islands]] and the [[Mariana Islands]], both of which had been recently purchased from Spain. In May, a cruise to [[German Samoa]] followed; there she met ''Cormoran''. The two ships then toured the islands with the governor of German Samoa, [[Wilhelm Solf]], and the Samoan chief, [[Mata'afa Iosefo]], aboard ''Seeadler''. In July 1900, following the outbreak of the [[Boxer Rebellion]] in [[Qing China]] the previous year, ''Seeadler'' was sent from the South Seas Station to assist in the Western suppression of the Boxers. She arrived in [[Tsingtau]] in the [[Kiautschou Bay concession]] and joined the ships of the [[German East Asia Squadron|East Asia Squadron]]. She spent the following months off Chinese harbors with the [[armored cruiser]] {{SMS|Fürst Bismarck|1897|2}} and the protected cruiser {{SMS|Hertha||2}}.&lt;ref name=HRS154/&gt;

On 24 April 1901, ''Seeadler'' was ordered to steam to the island of [[Yap]] in the Carolines to assist the stranded [[Norddeutscher Lloyd]] postal steamer {{SS|München}}. A pair of [[tugboat]]s had managed to pull the steamer free by the time ''Seeadler'' arrived on 3 May, though the cruiser's crew assisted with repairs to the ship's damaged hull. ''Seeadler'' thereafter returned to East Asia and resumed her patrols of Chinese harbors, though during this period she also visited Japanese harbors as well. These duties lasted until the end of 1902.&lt;ref name=HRS154/&gt; During ''Seeadler''{{'}}s operations in China, her crew suffered only one casualty from enemy action.&lt;ref&gt;''Sundries'', p. 547&lt;/ref&gt; On 2 January 1903, her sister {{SMS|Bussard||2}} arrived to take her place in East Asian waters, allowing ''Seeadler'' to return to the South Seas Station. ''Seeadler'' underwent a periodic overhaul in [[Uraga, Kanagawa|Uraga]], outside [[Tokyo]], Japan, from 3 August to 14 September.&lt;ref name=HRS154/&gt;

Following the outbreak of the [[Russo-Japanese War]] in February 1904, ''Seeadler'' was recalled to Tsingtau to be prepared for any possible hostilities involving Germany.&lt;ref name=HRS154/&gt; During this period, ''Cormoran'' was replaced by ''Condor''; the two cruisers were joined by ''Seeadler''{{'}}s old consort from East Africa, the survey vessel ''Möwe''.&lt;ref&gt;''Naval Notes'', 1904, p. 1079&lt;/ref&gt; In early 1905, ''Seeadler'' conducted goodwill visits to the [[Philippines]] and the [[Dutch East Indies]] (now [[Indonesia]]), before returning to Tsingtau in April. On 28 June, with the Russo-Japanese War winding down following the decisive Japanese victory at the [[Battle of Tsushima]], ''Seeadler'' was detached from the East Asia Squadron, permitting her return to the South Seas Station. While en route to her station area, ''Seeadler'' received an order to return to Africa during a stop at [[Pohnpei|Ponape]] on 20 August. Her presence was necessary there to help put down a major uprising, the [[Maji Maji Rebellion]], that had broken out in July. ''Seeadler'' ran aground twice, at [[Labuan]] and [[Singapore]], on her way to East Africa, but neither incident resulted in damage to the ship. She arrived in Dar es Salaam on 1 October.&lt;ref name=HRS154/&gt;

===Return to East Africa===
[[File:SMS Seeadler Daressalam1907-14.jpg|thumb|left|''Seeadler'' in [[Dar es Salaam]] during her second deployment]]
In mid-October 1905, ''Seeadler'' sent a landing party ashore at [[Samanga]] to protect the coastal telegraph line there. By mid-December, she had returned to Dar es Salaam, before proceeding to Kilwa on 17 January 1906. The cruiser was back in Dar es Salaam on 24 January. Another overhaul at Cape Town followed from 10 February to 16 March. By this time, the situation in East Africa had calmed, and the [[light cruiser]] {{SMS|Thetis||2}}, which had also been sent to suppress the Maji-Maji uprising, was sent back to Germany. ''Seeadler'' nevertheless remained in the region, and was formally assigned to the East Africa Station in early 1907.&lt;ref name=HRS154/&gt; In October 1907, then-''[[Korvettenkapitän]]'' (Lieutenant Commander) [[Hugo Meurer]] served as the ship's commanding officer. He would hold the position until June 1909.&lt;ref name=HRS151/&gt;

In 1908, ''Seeadler'' was joined by ''Bussard'' on the East Africa Station.&lt;ref&gt;''Naval Notes'', 1908, p. 710&lt;/ref&gt; From 18 February to 18 March, ''Seeadler'' underwent another overhaul at Cape Town. She thereafter proceeded to German South-West Africa, stopping in [[Walvis Bay]] and Swakopmund.&lt;ref&gt;Hildebrand, Röhr, &amp; Steinmetz, pp. 154&amp;ndash;155&lt;/ref&gt; There, she cruised with the gunboat {{SMS|Panther||2}} in March and early April. On 18 April, she was back in Dar es Salaam. Another period of dockyard repairs followed from 12 to 26 September, this time in Bombay. The rest of 1908 continued uneventfully for ''Seeadler'', as did the next few years. The only significant event came in early November 1911, when ''Seeadler'' pulled the [[Hamburg-Bremen-Afrika Linie]] steamer {{SS|Irmgard}} free after she ran aground off [[Quelimane]]. In 1913, the mayor of Cape Town hosted delegations from ''Seeadler'' and the British protected cruiser {{HMS|Hermes|1898|6}}. And at the end of December, the princes [[Prince Leopold of Bavaria|Leopold]] and [[Prince Georg of Bavaria|Georg]] of [[Bavaria]] visited ''Seeadler'' in Dar es Salaam while on an overseas tour.&lt;ref name=HRS155&gt;Hildebrand, Röhr, &amp; Steinmetz, p. 155&lt;/ref&gt;

===Later service===
On 9 January 1914, ''Seeadler'' departed East Africa for the last time, bound for Germany. She had spent nearly thirteen and a half years abroad, the longest uninterrupted period of overseas service of any major German warship. Her replacement, her sister {{SMS|Geier||2}}, had not yet arrived but was en route. ''Seeadler'' stopped in Aden on 22 January, and arrived in Kiel on 18 March. She was then moved to Danzig and decommissioned.&lt;ref name=HRS155/&gt; On 6 May 1914, she was reclassified as a gunboat. After the outbreak of [[World War I]] in August 1914, she was reduced to a [[hulk (ship)|hulk]] for storing [[naval mine]]s since she was no longer fit for active service. She was towed to Wilhelmshaven and anchored in the outer [[roadstead]]. On 19 April 1917, her cargo exploded while she was moored in the [[Jade Bight|Jade]] outside Wilhelmshaven. The explosion destroyed the ship, but there were no casualties; her wreck was never raised.&lt;ref name=G98/&gt;&lt;ref name=HRS155/&gt;

==Notes==
===Footnotes===
{{Notes
| notes =

{{efn
| name = SMS
| &quot;SMS&quot; stands for &quot;''[[Seiner Majestät Schiff]]''&quot; ({{lang-de|link=no|His Majesty's Ship}}).
}}

}}

===Citations===
{{Reflist|colwidth=20em}}

==References==
*{{cite book|editor-last=Gardiner|editor-first=Robert|title=Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships 1860–1905|publisher=Conway Maritime Press|location=Greenwich|year=1979|isbn=0-8317-0302-4}}
*{{cite book|last=Gröner|first=Erich|title=German Warships 1815–1945|year=1990|publisher=Naval Institute Press|location=Annapolis, MD|isbn=0-87021-790-9}}
* {{cite book| last1 = Hildebrand| first1 = Hans H.| last2 = Röhr| first2 = Albert| last3 = Steinmetz| first3 = Hans-Otto| year = 1993| title = Die Deutschen Kriegsschiffe (Volume 7)| publisher = Mundus Verlag| location = Ratingen, DE|asin=B003VHSRKE |asin-tld=de}}
* {{cite journal|title=Naval Notes|pages=1071&amp;ndash;1081|journal=Journal of the Royal United Service Institution|date=June 1904|volume=XLVIII|issue=319|publisher=J. J. Keliher &amp; Co.|location=London, UK|issn=	0035-9289|oclc=723657282|doi=10.1080/03071840409418368}}
* {{cite journal|title=Naval Notes|pages=704&amp;ndash;715|journal=Journal of the Royal United Service Institution|date=June 1908|volume=LII|issue=363|publisher=J. J. Keliher &amp; Co.|location=London, UK|issn=	0035-9289|oclc=723657282|doi=10.1080/03071840809418822}}
*{{cite book|last1=Northrop|first1=Henry Davenport|last2=Banks|first2=Nancy Huston|title=The World's Fair as Seen in One Hundred Days: Containing a Complete History of the World's Columbian Exposition|year=1893|publisher=Ariel Book Co.|location=Philadelphia, PA|oclc=9008669}}
* {{cite book |last=Sondhaus|first=Lawrence|title=Preparing for Weltpolitik: German Sea Power Before the Tirpitz Era|year=1997|publisher=Naval Institute Press|location=Annapolis, MD|isbn=1-55750-745-7}}
* {{cite journal|title=Sundries|pages=545&amp;ndash;550|journal=The United Service Magazine|year=1902|volume=XXV|publisher=William Clowes &amp; Sons|location=London, UK}}

==External links==
* {{Commons category-inline|Seeadler (ship, 1892)|''Seeadler'' (ship, 1892)}}

{{Bussard class cruisers}}
{{April 1917 shipwrecks}}

{{Coord|53|29|N|8|12|E|region:DE-NI_type:landmark_source:kolossus-dewiki|display=title}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Seeadler}}
[[Category:Bussard-class cruisers]]
[[Category:Ships built in Danzig]]
[[Category:1892 ships]]
[[Category:World War I cruisers of Germany]]
&lt;!-- did not serve as a cruiser during World War I --&gt;
[[Category:World War I shipwrecks in the North Sea]]
[[Category:Maritime incidents in 1917]]</text>
      <sha1>19s1zsnib1xrjfq4bgnfr8cddgpz64p</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
