<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>SMS Schlesien</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1628788</id>
    <revision>
      <id>744604317</id>
      <parentid>720115199</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-16T09:17:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* References */http&amp;rarr;https for [[Google Books]] and [[Google News]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25452">{| {{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
| Ship image   = [[File:SMS Schlesien BainNews.jpg|300px]]
| Ship caption = ''Schlesien'' before World War I
}}
{{Infobox ship career
| Hide header = 
| Ship country =[[German Empire]]
| Ship flag ={{shipboxflag|German Empire|naval}} {{shipboxflag|Weimar Republic|naval}} {{shipboxflag|Nazi Germany|naval}}
| Ship name = ''Schlesien''
| Ship namesake = [[Silesia|Schlesien]]
| Ship builder = [[Schichau-Werke|Schichau]], [[Danzig]]
| Ship laid down = 19 November 1904
| Ship launched = 28 May 1906
| Ship commissioned = 5 May 1908
| Ship fate = Mined off [[Swinemünde]] in 1945, scrapped 1949–1956
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
| Hide header = 
| Header caption = 
| Ship class ={{sclass-|Deutschland|battleship}}
| Ship displacement =
*{{convert|13,191|t|LT|abbr=on}} normal
*{{convert|14,218|t|LT|abbr=on}} full load
| Ship length ={{convert|127.60|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
| Ship beam ={{convert|22.20|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
| Ship draft ={{convert|7.70|m|ftin|abbr=on}}
| Ship propulsion ={{convert|13,918|kW|ihp|order=flip|abbr=on}}, three shafts
| Ship speed ={{convert|18.5|kn|lk=in}}
| Ship range ={{convert|4,770|nmi|lk=in|abbr=on}} at {{convert|10|kn}}
| Ship complement = 743
| Ship armament =
*At construction:
**2 × 2 – [[28 cm SK L/40 gun|{{convert|28|cm|in|abbr=on}} SK L/40]] guns
**14 × [[17 cm SK L/40 gun|{{convert|17|cm|in|abbr=on}} SK L/40 gun]]s (casemated)
**22 × [[8.8 cm SK L/45 naval gun|{{convert|8.8|cm|in|abbr=on}} SK L/45 naval gun]]s (casemated)
**6 × {{convert|45|cm|in|abbr=on}} torpedo tubes
*Armament in 1939:
**2 × 2 – [[28 cm SK L/40 gun|{{convert|28|cm|in|abbr=on}} SK L/40]] guns
**2 {{convert|8.8|cm|in|abbr=on}} guns
**4 × {{convert|3.7|cm|in|abbr=on}} guns (2×2)
**22 × {{convert|2|cm|in|1|abbr=on}} cannon
| Ship armor =
*230 mm in belt
*280 mm in turrets
*76 mm in deck
| Ship notes = 
}}
|}

'''SMS ''Schlesien'''''{{efn|name=SMS}} was one of the five {{sclass-|Deutschland|battleship|0}} [[pre-dreadnought]] [[battleship]]s built for the [[Kaiserliche Marine]] between 1904 and 1906. Named after the German province of [[Schlesien]], she was built at the [[Schichau-Werke]] shipyard in [[Danzig]], where she was launched on 28 May 1906. She was commissioned into the navy on 5 May 1908. The ships of her class were already outdated by the time they entered service, being inferior in size, armor, firepower and speed to the revolutionary new battleship {{HMS|Dreadnought|1906|6}}.

After commissioning, ''Schlesien'' was assigned to the I Battle Squadron of the [[High Seas Fleet]]. She served with the fleet throughout the first two years of [[World War I]]; by this time she had been transferred to the II Battle Squadron alongside her four [[sister ship]]s. ''Schlesien'' was present at the [[Battle of Jutland]] on 31 May – 1 June 1916, where she was actively engaged only briefly. After Jutland, she was relegated to guard duties before being withdrawn altogether in 1917, when she became a training ship. The [[Treaty of Versailles]] permitted the German navy to retain eight obsolete battleships, which included ''Schlesien'', to defend the German coast. She saw extensive service with the reorganized [[Reichsmarine]]; in the 1920s and 1930s the ship was rebuilt and eventually converted back into a training ship.

''Schlesien'' saw limited combat during [[World War II]], including the [[invasion of Norway]] in 1940. After the conclusion of the operation, the ship was again given secondary duties. She ended her career as an anti-aircraft ship in the Baltic; in April 1945 ''Schlesien'' steamed to [[Swinemünde]] to restock her ammunition and evacuate wounded soldiers when she struck a mine on 3 May. She sank in shallow water, though much of her superstructure, including her main battery, remained above water. In the remaining days of the war, ''Schlesien'' used her heavy artillery to provide support for retreating German ground troops. After the end of the war, she was broken up, though some parts of the ship remained until the 1970s.

== Construction ==
{{main|Deutschland-class battleship}}
[[File:Deutschland class line-drawing.png|thumb|left|Line-drawing of the ''Deutschland'' class]]

''Schlesien'' was intended to fight in the [[line of battle]] with the other battleships of the [[High Seas Fleet]].{{sfn|Herwig|p=45}} She was laid down on 19 November 1904 at the [[Schichau-Werke|Schichau]] dockyard in [[Danzig]].{{sfn|Staff|p=5}} She was launched on 28 May 1906, and in March 1908 was sent to [[Kiel]], where her fitting out work was completed. She was commissioned for trials on 5 May, though these were interrupted from 6 July to 5 September when the ship was temporarily used as a torpedo trials vessel. ''Schlesien'' joined the fleet after the torpedo trials were completed in September.{{sfn|Staff|p=12}} The British battleship {{HMS|Dreadnought|1906|6}}—armed with ten 12&amp;nbsp;inch (30.5&amp;nbsp;cm) guns—had already been commissioned nearly two years prior, in December 1906.{{sfn|Gardiner &amp; Gray|pp=21–22}} ''Dreadnought''{{'}}s revolutionary design rendered obsolete every ship of the German navy, including the newer ''Schlesien''.{{sfn|Herwig|p=57}}

''Schlesien'' was {{convert|127.60|m|ft|abbr=on}} long, had a beam of {{convert|22.20|m|ft|abbr=on}}, and a draft of {{convert|8.21|m|ft|abbr=on}}. She had a full-load displacement of {{convert|14,218|t|sp=us}}. She was equipped with three-shaft [[triple expansion engine]]s and twelve coal-fired [[water-tube boiler]]s that produced a rated {{convert|13,918|kW|ihp|order=flip|lk=in}} and a top speed of {{convert|18.5|kn|lk=in}}. In addition to being the fastest ship of her class, ''Schlesien'' was the most fuel efficient. At a cruising speed of {{convert|10|kn}}, she could steam for {{convert|4,770|nmi|sp=us|lk=in}}.{{sfn|Gröner|1982|p=44}} She had a standard crew of 35&amp;nbsp;officers and 708&amp;nbsp;enlisted men.{{sfn|Gröner|p=21}}

The ship's primary armament consisted of four [[28 cm SK L/40 gun]]s in two twin turrets;{{efn|name=gun nomenclature}} one turret was placed forward and the other aft. She was also equipped with fourteen {{convert|17|cm|in|abbr=on}} guns mounted in casemates and twenty {{convert|8.8|cm|in|abbr=on}} guns in pivot mounts. The ship was fitted with six {{convert|45|cm|in|abbr=on}} torpedo tubes, all submerged in the hull. One was in the bow, one in the stern, and four on the [[broadside]]. Her [[belt armor|armored belt]] was {{convert|240|mm|abbr=on}} thick [[amidships]] and she had a {{convert|40|mm|abbr=on}} thick armored deck. The main battery turrets had {{convert|280|mm|abbr=on}} thick sides.{{sfn|Gröner|pp=20–21}}

== Service history ==
After commissioning, ''Schlesien'' was assigned to the [[I Battle Squadron]]. Her first year of service, 1909, saw a pattern of fleet maneuvers in the North and Baltic Seas as well as the Atlantic Ocean.{{sfn|Staff|p=14}} Her first cruise into the Atlantic was conducted from 7 July to 1 August. Another round of exercises followed in the autumn.{{sfn|Staff|p=8}} The I Battle Squadron was transferred from Kiel to [[Wilhelmshaven]] in April 1910.{{sfn|Staff|p=14}} The following month, in May 1910, the fleet conducted training maneuvers in the [[Kattegat]], between Norway and Denmark. For the first time, the annual summer cruise went to Norway. Fleet training followed, and a training cruise into the Baltic took place at the end of the year.{{sfn|Staff|p=8}}

On 3 November 1911, ''Schlesien'' was transferred to the [[II Battle Squadron]] with the rest of her sister ships.{{sfn|Staff|p=14}} Training  maneuvers in 1911 and 1912 followed the same pattern as in 1910, with the exception of the summer cruise in 1912; owing to the [[Agadir Crisis]] that year, the cruise only went into the Baltic, rather than to Norway.{{sfn|Staff|p=8}}

=== World War I ===
''Schlesien'' remained with the High Seas Fleet throughout the first two years of the war. At the outbreak of war, the ship was deployed to guard the [[German Bight]]. She then rejoined the High Seas Fleet as part of the battleship support for the battlecruisers that [[Raid on Scarborough, Hartlepool and Whitby|bombarded Scarborough, Hartlepool, and Whitby]] on 15–16 December 1914.{{sfn|Staff|p=14}} During the operation, the German battle fleet of some 12 dreadnoughts and 8 pre-dreadnoughts came to within {{convert|10|nmi|abbr=on}} of an isolated squadron of six British battleships. However, skirmishes between the rival [[destroyer]] screens convinced Admiral [[Friedrich von Ingenohl]] that he was confronted with the entire [[Grand Fleet]], and so he broke off the engagement and turned for home.{{sfn|Tarrant|pp=31–33}} Two resultless fleet advances followed on 17–18 and 21–23 April 1915. Another followed on 17–18 May, and another on 23–24 October.{{sfn|Staff|p=14}}

On 24–25 April 1916, ''Schlesien'' and her sisters joined the dreadnoughts of the High Seas Fleet to support the battlecruisers of the [[I Scouting Group]] on a raid of the English coast.{{sfn|Staff|p=14}} While en route to the target, the battlecruiser {{SMS|Seydlitz||2}} was damaged by a [[naval mine|mine]]. The battlecruisers conducted a short [[Bombardment of Yarmouth and Lowestoft|bombardment of the ports of Yarmouth and Lowestoft]]. Visibility was poor, so the operation was soon called off before the British fleet could intervene.{{sfn|Tarrant|pp=52–54}}

==== Battle of Jutland ====
[[File:Map of the Battle of Jutland, 1916.svg|thumb|Diagram of the Battle of Jutland showing the major movements|alt=The German fleet sailed to the north and met the British fleet sailing from the west; both fleets conducted a series of turns and maneuvers during the chaotic battle.]]
{{main|Battle of Jutland}}

Admiral Scheer immediately planned another foray into the North Sea, but the damage to ''Seydlitz'' delayed the operation until the end of May.{{sfn|Tarrant|p=58}} ''Schlesien'' was the second ship in the IV Division of the II Battle Squadron under the command of Rear Admiral [[Franz Mauve]], positioned at the rear of the German line. ''Schlesien'' was the second to last ship in the German line, followed only by ''Schleswig-Holstein''.{{sfn|Tarrant|p=286}} During the &quot;Run to the North,&quot; Admiral [[Reinhard Scheer]], the commander of the fleet, ordered the fleet to pursue the British V Battle Squadron at top speed. The slower ''Deutschland''-class ships could not keep up with the faster dreadnoughts and quickly fell behind.{{sfn|London|p=73}}

Later on the first day of the battle, the hard-pressed battlecruisers of the I Scouting Group were being pursued by their British opponents. ''Schlesien'' and the other so-called &quot;five-minute ships&quot; came to their aid by steaming in between the opposing battlecruiser squadrons.{{sfn|Tarrant|p=195}} ''Schlesien'' and her sisters could barely make out a target in the darkness. Due to the poor visibility their shooting was ineffective.{{sfn|London|pp=70–71}} The British battlecruisers scored several hits on the German ships; in the brief melee a near miss from a large-caliber gun sprayed shell splinters onto ''Schlesien''{{'}}s decks, killing one man and wounding another.{{sfn|Staff|p=14}} Admiral Mauve ordered an [[Boxing the compass|8-point]] turn to the south, and the British did not follow.{{sfn|London|p=71}}

Late on the 31st, the fleet organized for the night march back to Germany; ''Schlesien'' and ''Schleswig-Holstein'' fell in behind the mauled battlecruisers {{SMS|Von der Tann||2}} and {{SMS|Derfflinger||2}} at the rear of the line.{{sfn|Tarrant|p=240}} British destroyers conducted a series of attacks against the fleet, some of which targeted ''Schlesien''.{{sfn|Staff|p=14}} Regardless, the High Seas Fleet punched through the British destroyer forces and reached [[Horns Rev|Horns Reef]] by 4:00 on 1 June.{{sfn|Tarrant|pp=246–247}} The German fleet reached Wilhelmshaven a few hours later, where the undamaged dreadnoughts of the {{sclass-|Nassau|battleship|5}} and {{sclass-|Helgoland|battleship|4}}es took up defensive positions.{{sfn|Tarrant|p=263}}

=== Inter-war years ===
[[File:Schlesien Panama 2.jpg|thumb|''Schlesien'' in the Panama Canal in 1937]]

Following the German defeat in World War I, the German navy, reorganized as the [[Reichsmarine]], was permitted to retain three of the ''Deutschland''-class battleships: ''Hannover'', ''Schleswig-Holstein'' and ''Schlesien'', along with several of the ''Braunschweig''-class battleships.{{sfn|Williamson, ''Battleships''|pp=5–6}} ''Deutschland'', the oldest and least advanced ship of the class, was instead scrapped in 1922.{{sfn|Gröner|p=22}} ''Schlesien'' and ''Schleswig-Holstein'' were modernized in the 1920s,{{sfn|Williamson, ''Battleships''|p=6}} a process that included replacement of the ships' 17&amp;nbsp;cm guns with {{convert|15|cm|in|abbr=on}} pieces.{{sfn|''Proceedings''|p=1014}} ''Schlesien'' and ''Schleswig-Holstein'' continued in their battleship configuration with the active fleet, while ''Hannover'' was intended to be rebuilt as a target ship, although this never occurred.{{sfn|Gardiner &amp; Gray|p=141}}

''Schleswig-Holstein'' was the flagship of the fleet until 1932 when she was taken in for another reconstruction that converted her into a training vessel.{{sfn|Gardiner &amp; Chesneau|p=222}} As a result, ''Schlesien'' held the position of fleet flagship afterward.{{sfn|Mueller|p=89}} In 1932, [[Wilhelm Canaris]] took command of the ship, a post he held for two years.{{sfn|Kahn|p=229}}{{efn|name=Canaris}} In May 1935, the Reichsmarine was again reorganized as the [[Kriegsmarine]].{{sfn|Williamson, ''Battleships''|p=6}} Shortly after, ''Schlesien'' took part in extensive fleet maneuvers with the new heavy cruiser [[German pocket battleship Deutschland|''Deutschland'']].{{sfn|Williamson, ''Light Cruisers''|p=36}} Later that year, ''Schlesien'' was converted into a training ship.{{sfn|Gardiner &amp; Chesneau|p=222}} Among the modifications were the installation of additional anti-aircraft guns and replacement of the ship's boilers. The newer boilers were more efficient, which allowed fewer of them to be used; the additional space this created was used as crew compartments for the cadets and an instruction room.{{sfn|Gardiner &amp; Chesneau|p=222}}{{sfn|Gröner|p=21}} The crew was also altered; the standard crew had been 35 officers and 708 enlisted men; after the conversion, this was reduced to 29 officers and 559 sailors, supplemented by 214 cadets.{{sfn|Gröner|p=21}} The following year, ''Schlesien'' toured the Americas; in March 1937 the ship stopped in [[Halifax Regional Municipality|Halifax]], Nova Scotia.{{sfn|Edwards, S.|p=68}} Later that year in December, she stopped in [[Mar del Plata]], Argentina.{{sfn|Newton|p=184}} In 1938, the ship visited [[Samaná Bay]] in the [[Dominican Republic]].{{sfn|Leonard &amp; Bratzel|p=78}}

=== World War II ===
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101II-MN-1585-09A, Linienschiffe &quot;Schlesien&quot;, &quot;Schleswig-Holstein&quot;.jpg|thumb|''Schlesien'' (foreground) and ''Schleswig-Holstein'' in [[Westerplatte]] following the occupation of the port]]

During the invasion of Poland in September 1939, ''Schlesien'' initially remained in her training ship role, though she briefly acted as an [[icebreaker]] for [[U-boat]]s.{{sfn|Williamson, ''Battleships''|p=8}} Later in the month, ''Schlesien'' joined her sister ''Schleswig-Holstein'' to bombard Polish positions along the Baltic coast; the bombardments lasted from 25–27 September.{{sfn|Rohwer|p=5}} After the operation, ''Schlesien'' had six of her 15&amp;nbsp;cm guns removed to arm the new surface raider {{ship|German auxiliary cruiser|Pinguin||2}}.{{sfn|Edwards, B.|p=11}} In 1940, ''Schlesien'' took part in [[Operation Weserübung]], the German invasion of Denmark and Norway. ''Schlesien'' operated in Danish waters throughout the operation.{{sfn|Rohwer|p=18}} After the occupations were complete, ''Schlesien'' resumed her ice-breaking duties. In March 1941, ''Schlesien'' escorted mine-layers in the Baltic. After returning from this operation, she was to be converted into a barracks ship in [[Gotenhafen]].{{sfn|Williamson, ''Battleships''|p=8}} On 4 April 1942, ''Schlesien'' departed for Gotenhafen in company with the battleship {{ship|German battleship|Gneisenau||2}} and the icebreaker {{ship|German icebreaker|Castor||2}}.{{sfn|Garzke &amp; Dulin|p=151}}

In mid 1944, ''Schlesien''{{'}}s and ''Schleswig-Holstein''{{'}}s anti-aircraft armaments were considerably strengthened so they could used as air defense ships in the port of Gotenhafen.{{sfn|Williamson, ''Battleships''|p=8}} In April 1945, ''Schlesien'' was moved to [[Swinemünde]] to restock her ammunition supply as well as evacuate 1,000 wounded soldiers from the front.{{sfn|Williamson, ''Battleships''|p=9}} On 3 May she struck a mine at [[Zinnowitz]] outside Swinemünde and beached in shallow water.{{sfn|Slavick|p=233}} Much of the ship remained above water, including her main armament; she was able to provide artillery support for retreating German units.{{sfn|Williamson, ''Battleships''|p=9}} Between 1949 and 1956, the wreck was demolished and then scrapped ''in situ'' by an East German company.{{sfn|Gröner|p=22}}{{sfn|Slavick|p=233}} However, some remains from the ship were still visible in 1970.{{sfn|Gröner|p=22}}

== Footnotes ==

=== Notes ===

{{notes
| notes =

{{efn
| name = SMS
| &quot;SMS&quot; stands for &quot;''[[Seiner Majestät Schiff]]''&quot;, or &quot;His Majesty's Ship&quot; in German.
}}

{{efn
| name = gun nomenclature
| In Imperial German Navy gun nomenclature, &quot;SK&quot; (Schnelladekanone) denotes that the gun is quick loading, while the L/40 denotes the length of the gun. In this case, the L/40 gun is 40 [[Caliber (artillery)|caliber]], meaning that the gun is 40 times long as it is in diameter.
}}

{{efn
| name = Canaris
| Canaris would subsequently be appointed chief of the ''[[Abwehr]]'' and use his position to support the [[German resistance]] during World War II. See {{harvnb|Kahn|pp=229–235}}.
}}

}}

=== Citations ===

{{reflist|25em}}

== References ==

{{portal|Battleships}}

*{{cite book
  | last = Edwards
  | first = Bernard
  | year = 2001
  | title = Beware Raiders!: German Surface Raiders in the Second World War
  | publisher = Naval Institute Press
  | location = Annapolis, MD
  | isbn = 978-1-55750-210-0
  | ref ={{sfnRef|Edwards, B.}}
  }}
*{{cite book
  | last = Edwards
  | first = Suzanne K.
  | year = 2007
  | title = Gus: From Trapper Boy to Air Marshall
  | publisher = General Store Publishing House
  | location = Renfrew, Ontario, CA
  | isbn = 978-1-897113-74-5
  | ref ={{sfnRef|Edwards, S.}}
  }}
*{{cite book
  | editor1-last = Gardiner
  | editor1-first = Robert
  | editor2-last = Gray
  | editor2-first = Randal
  | year = 1985
  | title = Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships, 1906–1921
  | publisher = Naval Institute Press
  | location = Annapolis, MD
  | isbn = 978-0-87021-907-8
  | oclc = 12119866
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=V2r_TBjR2TYC&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | ref ={{sfnRef|Gardiner &amp; Gray}}
  }}
*{{cite book
  | editor1-last = Gardiner
  | editor1-first = Robert
  | editor2-last = Chesneau
  | editor2-first = Roger
  | year = 1980
  | title = Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships, 1922–1946
  | publisher = Naval Institute Press
  | location = Annapolis, MD
  | isbn = 978-0-87021-913-9
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=bJBMBvyQ83EC&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | ref ={{sfnRef|Gardiner &amp; Chesneau}}
  }}
*{{cite book
  | last1 = Garzke
  | first1 = William H.
  | last2 = Dulin
  | first2 = Robert O.
  | title = Battleships: Axis and Neutral Battleships in World War II
  | year = 1985
  | publisher = Naval Institute Press
  | location = Annapolis, MD
  | isbn = 978-0-87021-101-0
  | oclc = 
  | ref ={{sfnRef|Garzke &amp; Dulin}}
  }}
*{{cite book
  | last = Gröner
  | first = Erich
  | year = 1990
  | title = German Warships: 1815–1945
  | publisher = Naval Institute Press
  | location = Annapolis, MD
  | isbn = 978-0-87021-790-6
  | ref ={{sfnRef|Gröner}}
  }}
*{{cite book
  | last = Herwig
  | first = Holger
  | year = 1998
  | origyear = 1980
  | title = &quot;Luxury&quot; Fleet: The Imperial German Navy 1888–1918
  | publisher = Humanity Books
  | location = Amherst, NY
  | isbn = 978-1-57392-286-9
  | oclc = 57239454
  | ref ={{sfnRef|Herwig}}
  }}
*{{cite book
  | last = Kahn
  | first = David
  | year = 2000
  | title = Hitler's Spies: German Military Intelligence in World War II
  | publisher = Da Capo Press
  | location = Cambridge, MA
  | isbn = 978-0-306-80949-1
  | ref ={{sfnRef|Kahn}}
  }}
*{{cite book
  | last1 = Leonard
  | first1 = Thomas M.
  | last2 = Bratzel
  | first2 = John F.
  | year = 2007
  | title = Latin America during World War II
  | publisher = Rowman &amp; Littlefield
  | location = Lanham, MD
  | isbn = 978-0-7425-3741-5
  | ref ={{sfnRef|Leonard &amp; Bratzel}}
  }}
*{{cite book
  | last = London
  | first = Charles
  | year = 2000
  | title = Jutland 1916: Clash of the Dreadnoughts
  | publisher = Osprey Publishing
  | location = Oxford, UK
  | isbn = 978-1-85532-992-8
  | oclc = 
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=geQ6-XpW5fEC&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | ref ={{sfnRef|London}}
  }}
*{{cite book
  | last = Mueller
  | first = Michael
  | year = 2007
  | title = Canaris: The Life and Death of Hitler's Spymaster
  | publisher = Naval Institute Press
  | location = Annapolis, MD
  | isbn = 978-1-59114-101-3
  | oclc = 
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=9WGAexVXyHwC&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | ref ={{sfnRef|Mueller}}
  }}
*{{cite book
  | last = Newton
  | first = Ronald C.
  | year = 1992
  | title = The &quot;Nazi Menace&quot; in Argentina, 1931–1947
  | publisher = Stanford University Press
  | location = Stanford, CA
  | isbn = 978-0-8047-1929-2
  | oclc = 
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=CzOsAAAAIAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover
  | ref ={{sfnRef|Newton}}
  }}
*{{cite book
  | last = Rohwer
  | first = Jürgen
  | authorlink = Jürgen Rohwer
  | year = 2005
  | title = Chronology of the War at Sea, 1939–1945: The Naval History of World War Two
  | publisher = US Naval Institute Press
  | location = Annapolis, MD
  | isbn = 978-1-59114-119-8
  | ref ={{sfnRef|Rohwer}}
  }}
*{{cite book
  | last = Slavick
  | first = Joseph P.
  | year = 2003
  | title = The Cruise of the German Raider Atlantis
  | publisher = Naval Institute Press
  | location = Annapolis, MD
  | isbn = 978-1-55750-537-8
  | ref ={{sfnRef|Slavick}}
  }}
*{{cite book
  | last = Staff
  | first = Gary
  | year = 2010
  | title = German Battleships: 1914–1918 (1)
  | publisher = Osprey Books
  | location = Oxford, UK
  | isbn = 978-1-84603-467-1
  | ref ={{sfnRef|Staff}}
  }}
*{{cite book
  | last = Tarrant
  | first = V. E.
  | year = 2001
  | origyear = 1995
  | title = Jutland: The German Perspective
  | publisher = Cassell Military Paperbacks
  | location = London, UK
  | isbn = 978-0-304-35848-9
  | oclc = 48131785
  | ref ={{sfnRef|Tarrant}}
  }}
*{{cite book
  | last = Williamson
  | first = Gordon
  | year = 2003
  | title = German Battleships 1939–45
  | publisher = Osprey Publishing
  | location = Oxford, UK
  | isbn = 978-1-84176-498-6
  | oclc = 
  | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=z-3w7JSYHD4C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=isbn:9781841764986&amp;cd=1#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false
  | ref ={{sfnRef|Williamson, ''Battleships''}}
  }}
*{{cite book
  | last = Williamson
  | first = Gordon
  | year = 2003
  | title = German Light Cruisers 1939–45
  | publisher = Osprey Publishing
  | location = Oxford, UK
  | isbn = 978-1-84176-503-7
  | oclc = 
  | ref ={{sfnRef|Williamson, ''Light Cruisers''}}
  }}

*{{cite journal
  | title = German Naval Notes
  | year = 1922
  | journal = Proceedings
  | volume = 48
  | pages = 1014–1015
  | publisher = United States Naval Institute
  | location = Annapolis, MD
  | ref ={{sfnRef|''Proceedings''}}
  }}

{{Commons-inline|Schlesien (1906)}}

== Further reading ==
*{{cite journal
  | last = Dodson
  | first = Aidan
  | year = 2014
  | title = Last of the Line: The German Battleships of the Braunschweig and Deutschland Classes
  | journal = Warship 2014
  | pages = 49–69
  | publisher = Conway Maritime Press
  | location = London
  | isbn = 978-1591149231
  | ref ={{sfnRef|Dodson}}
  }}

== Online links ==

*SMS ''Schlesien'' in MaritimeQuest – [http://www.maritimequest.com/warship_directory/germany/battleships/schlesien/schlesien.htm ''Schlesien''{{'}}s gallery, including a photograph in the role of icebreaker]
*''Schlesien'' visit to Argentina – [http://www.lacapitalmdp.com/contenidos/fotosfamilia/fotos/4921 Schlesien's commander pays respect to Mar del Plata's mayor, December 1937]
*''Schlesien'' visit to Argentina – [http://www.lacapitalmdp.com/contenidos/fotosfamilia/fotos/5277 A Mar del Plata's girl makes the military salute with the German naval ensign in the background]

{{Deutschland class battleship}}
{{May 1945 shipwrecks}}
{{Good article}}
{{coord missing|Baltic Sea}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Schlesien}}
[[Category:Deutschland-class battleships]]
[[Category:Ships built in Danzig]]
[[Category:1906 ships]]
[[Category:World War I battleships of Germany]]
[[Category:Battleships of the Kriegsmarine]]
[[Category:World War II battleships of Germany]]
[[Category:World War II shipwrecks in the Baltic Sea]]
[[Category:Maritime incidents in May 1945]]
[[Category:Ships built by Schichau]]
[[Category:Ships sunk by mines]]</text>
      <sha1>jxzcfwnfkulku1rybd6d1tnaplbt7cu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
