<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Southern Rhodesian military involvement in the Malayan Emergency</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>36059181</id>
    <revision>
      <id>687103272</id>
      <parentid>672404274</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-10-23T09:07:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cliftonian</username>
        <id>8019733</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Influence on the Rhodesian Bush War */ ce</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24854">{{Good Article}}
[[File:C Squadron (Rhodesian) SAS, 1953.jpg|thumb|300px|[[Rhodesian Special Air Service|&quot;C&quot; Squadron]], the all-Southern Rhodesian unit of the [[Special Air Service]] (SAS), in Malaya in 1953|alt=A formative black-and-white photograph of military personnel. The men wear khaki shirts and shorts with long, dark-coloured socks. They all wear dark berets.]]
[[Southern Rhodesia]],{{refn|group=n|name=since1980|Renamed Zimbabwe in 1980.{{sfn|Cilliers|1984|p=57}}}} then a [[self-governing colony]] of the United Kingdom, sent two military units to fight with the [[Commonwealth of Nations|Commonwealth]] armed forces in the [[Malayan Emergency]] of 1948–60, which pitted the Commonwealth against the [[Malayan National Liberation Army]] (MNLA), the military arm of the [[Malayan Communist Party]]. For two years, starting in March 1951, white Southern Rhodesian volunteers made up [[Rhodesian Special Air Service|&quot;C&quot; Squadron]] of the [[Special Air Service]] (SAS). The [[Rhodesian African Rifles]], in which black rank-and-filers and [[warrant officers]] were led by white officers, then served in Malaya from 1956 to 1958.

Of the hundreds of Southern Rhodesians who served in Malaya, eight were killed. &quot;C&quot; Squadron, which was formed especially to serve in Malaya, was the first SAS unit from a British colony or [[dominion]]. Several veterans of the conflict, [[Peter Walls]] and [[Ronald Reid-Daly|Ron Reid-Daly]] among them, subsequently held key positions in the [[Rhodesian Security Forces]] during the [[Rhodesian Bush War|Bush War]] of the 1970s.

==Background and outbreak of war==
{{main|Malayan Emergency}}
[[File:Terrorist in Malaya.jpg|thumb|In this 1952 photograph, a communist guerrilla is held at gunpoint following his capture by Commonwealth forces|alt=A scarred and bloodied man of Oriental appearance kneels on the ground. Beside him stands a man with an FN FAL battle rifle. A bayonet is fixed to the end of the rifle.]]
The [[Malayan Emergency]] was a [[guerrilla war]] between the [[Federation of Malaya]]—a protectorate of Britain until August 1957, and part of the [[Commonwealth of Nations]] thereafter&lt;ref name=&quot;malaya1957&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb
|Federation of Malaya Independence Act
|1957}}&lt;/ref&gt;—and the [[Malayan National Liberation Army]] (MNLA), the armed wing of the [[Malayan Communist Party]] (MCP). The MNLA sought to topple the Malayan government and force the British out, while the Commonwealth worked to prevent this.&lt;ref name=arnold131132&gt;{{Harvnb
|Arnold
|Wiener
|2012
|pp=131–132}}&lt;/ref&gt; The conflict had its roots in the Second World War, in which groups of [[Malaysian Chinese|local ethnic Chinese]] fought alongside Britain's limited forces in the country against the occupying [[Imperial Japan]]ese; these Malayan Chinese subscribed to communist political thinking, and called themselves the [[Malayan Peoples' Anti-Japanese Army]].&lt;ref name=binda126127/&gt;

Soon after Japan was defeated, the communist fighters renamed themselves the Malayan National Liberation Army, and began to agitate against British rule. Using the arms that Britain had given them—which they had cached, and then subsequently retrieved—they formed themselves into eight regiments, and began a campaign of [[Maoism|Maoist]]-style rural subversion, their intent being to politicise the villagers and gain popular support, which they could then use to take control of Malayan cities.&lt;ref name=binda126127&gt;{{Harvnb
|Binda
|2007
|pp=126–127}}&lt;/ref&gt; In March 1948, the MCP called on the Malayan people to rise up against the British. Three months later, on 16 June, MNLA guerrillas killed three British rubber plantation managers in [[Perak]] province. The British High Commissioner in Malaya, Sir [[Edward Gent]], declared a [[state of emergency]] two days afterwards, marking the beginning of the [[Malayan Emergency]].&lt;ref name=arnold131132/&gt;

In addition to British and Malayan units and personnel, the Commonwealth forces in Malaya included [[Military history of Australia during the Malayan Emergency|Australians]], [[Military history of New Zealand in Malaysia|New Zealanders]], [[Gurkha]]s, [[Colonial Fiji|Fijians]], [[Nyasaland]]ers, and [[Northern Rhodesia|Northern]] and [[Southern Rhodesia]]ns.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb
|Scurr
|2005
|p=5}}&lt;/ref&gt; Southern Rhodesia had been [[self-governing colony|self-governing]] since 1923. It ran its own affairs in most matters, including defence, but it was still constitutionally bound to [[Government of the United Kingdom|Whitehall]] insofar as foreign affairs were concerned. The Southern Rhodesian government was therefore able to exercise a large degree of independence militarily, though diplomatically it came under the British flag.&lt;ref name=wood9&gt;{{Harvnb
|Wood
|2005
|p=9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==&quot;C&quot; Squadron, Special Air Service (1951–53)==
[[File:Map PeninsularMalaysia.png|thumb|The [[Federation of Malaya]]|alt=A map. See caption.]]

The [[Special Air Service]] (SAS) [[commando]] unit was formed by the [[British Army]] in 1941, during the [[North African Campaign]] of the Second World War. Including some Southern Rhodesians in its ranks, it served for the rest of the conflict, also operating [[Allied invasion of Italy|in Italy]] and on the European [[Western Front (World War II)|Western Front]]. It was disbanded by the British government in October 1945,&lt;ref name=shorttmcbride1920&gt;{{Harvnb
|Shortt
|McBride
|1981
|p=16}}&lt;/ref&gt; and reinstituted in 1950 to serve in the [[Korean War]]. The situation in Korea had changed by the end of its three-month training period, however, and it was sent to Malaya instead. There it was placed under the command of a British officer, Major [[Mike Calvert]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb
|Daily Telegraph
|2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Early the following year, Calvert travelled to Southern Rhodesia on a recruitment visit. Roughly 1,000 white Southern Rhodesians, SAS veterans among them, volunteered to go to Malaya;&lt;ref name=shorttmcbride1920/&gt; from these, about 100 were chosen to form an all-Southern Rhodesian unit.&lt;ref name=binda127/&gt; This was the first SAS squadron from a British colony or [[dominion]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb
|Geraghty
|1980
|p=220}}&lt;/ref&gt; Led by the 24-year-old Temporary Captain [[Peter Walls]], the volunteers arrived in Malaya in March 1951. Walls was promoted to major soon after he and his men disembarked at [[Singapore]].&lt;ref name=rlirawalls/&gt; The SAS already had two Squadrons, &quot;A&quot; and &quot;B&quot;, so the Southern Rhodesians became &quot;C&quot; Squadron,&lt;ref name=binda127&gt;{{Harvnb
|Binda
|2007
|p=127}}&lt;/ref&gt; known more informally as the [[Rhodesian Special Air Service|Rhodesian SAS]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb
|Geraghty
|1980
|pp=220–222, 227}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Engaged largely in [[counter-insurgency]] warfare, the Southern Rhodesians became well-drilled in the relevant principles and doctrines.&lt;ref name=mackenzie66/&gt; They noticeably bolstered the hitherto thinly spread ranks of the SAS in Malaya, and performed strongly in the eyes of their superiors, though British Major C&amp;nbsp;L &quot;Dare&quot; Newell believed that their attitude towards &quot;the aborigines&quot; was colder than that of the British soldiers. Barbara Cole, who wrote a history of the Rhodesian SAS, says by contrast that the Rhodesians became close friends with the Fijians they served alongside, and spent far more time socialising with black and mixed-race soldiers off-duty than their British counterparts did.&lt;ref name=mackenzie66&gt;{{Harvnb
|MacKenzie
|2011
|pp=66–67}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In March 1953, after serving their required two years in Malaya, the men of &quot;C&quot; Squadron returned home.&lt;ref name=rlirawalls&gt;{{Harvnb
|RLI Regimental Association}}&lt;/ref&gt; They were replaced in 1955 by a squadron from New Zealand.&lt;ref name=shorttmcbride1920/&gt; Three members of &quot;C&quot; Squadron—Sergeant O&amp;nbsp;H Ernst, and Corporals J&amp;nbsp;B Davies and V&amp;nbsp;E Visagie—were killed while in Malaya.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb
|Rhodesian Army Association}}&lt;/ref&gt; For his services during the emergency, Walls was awarded an [[Order of the British Empire|MBE]].&lt;ref name=rlirawalls/&gt;

==Rhodesian African Rifles (1956–58)==

===Arrival in Malaya===
[[File:Cameronia.jpg|thumb|[[HMT Cameronia|SS ''Empire Clyde'']], on which most of the [[Rhodesian African Rifles]] travelled to Malaya|alt=An impressive ocean liner on the high seas, billowing steam as it goes]]
Following the departure of &quot;C&quot; Squadron, Southern Rhodesia was uninvolved in Malaya until early 1956, when the 1st Battalion, the [[Rhodesian African Rifles]] (RAR) were tasked to relieve the [[Northern Rhodesia Regiment]] (NRR) in [[Johor]]e province. Originally formed in 1916 as the Rhodesian Native Regiment,&lt;ref name=&quot;binda17&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb
|Binda
|2007
|p=17}}&lt;/ref&gt; the RAR were, by Southern Rhodesian standards, an old and well-tried unit; they fought for Britain [[East African Campaign (World War I)|in East Africa]] during the [[World War I|First World War]],&lt;ref name=binda25/&gt; and contributed to the [[Burma Campaign]] during the Second.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb
|Binda
|2007
|pp=59–77}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|The Rhodesian Native Regiment (RNR) disbanded soon following the end of the First World War in 1918,&lt;ref name=&quot;binda25&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb
|Binda
|2007
|p=25}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the Rhodesian African Rifles (RAR) were formed in 1940.&lt;ref name=binda4142/&gt; Although technically separate, the two shared many traditions and personnel, and were generally considered to be closely linked. The RAR successfully lobbied for permission to emblazon their regimental colours with the RNR's First World War [[battle honour]]s in 1952.&lt;ref name=binda25/&gt;|group=&quot;n&quot;}} The regiment's black soldiers and [[warrant officers]], led by white officers, came from both [[Mashonaland]] and [[Matabeleland]], with [[Shona people|Mashona]]s in the majority.&lt;ref name=binda4142&gt;{{Harvnb
|Binda
|2007
|pp=41–42}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Royal Australian Regiment]] was also present in Malaya, so to prevent confusion the Rhodesian African Rifles' acronym was temporarily changed to &quot;RhAR&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb
|Abbott
|Botham
|1986
|p=14}}&lt;/ref&gt; The regiment's advance party, made up of officers, [[non-commissioned officer]]s (NCOs) and warrant officers, left the Southern Rhodesian capital [[Harare|Salisbury]] by air on 13 February 1956. Their tortuous route took them through [[Moi Air Base|Nairobi]], [[RAF Khormaksar|Aden]], [[RAF Mauripur|Karachi]], and [[Bandaranaike International Airport|RAF Negombo]] (in [[Ceylon]]). After touching down in Singapore, the RhAR's advance party travelled to [[Kluang]] in Johore, where they spent three weeks in jungle training with the NRR. They then redeployed to [[Batu Pahat]], where they camped with the [[Fiji Infantry Regiment]]. A spirit of camaraderie quickly developed between the Fijian and Southern Rhodesian soldiers. The RhAR officers and NCOs continued their acclimatisation with the local environment over the following weeks, assisted by the Fijians. The rest of the battalion travelled by sea aboard [[HMT Cameronia|SS ''Empire Clyde'']], and reached Singapore on 26 April 1956. Soon after, the RhAR set up headquarters at [[Chaah]], about {{convert|130|km}} north-west of the port city.&lt;ref name=binda127/&gt;

===MNLA and RhAR tactics===
By this stage of the insurgency, the MNLA had largely split into small groups of guerrillas, which existed by basing themselves in a chosen rural area, subverting local villagers and accumulating from them manpower and supplies. The lot of any security forces posted nearby was to play a constant game of hide-and-seek with the communists, whereby the army would indefinitely search for and destroy any base camps and food caches the MNLA set up. The Commonwealth leaders surmised that the MNLA could not possibly resist such a campaign forever, and would, in time, simply give up attempting to regroup.&lt;ref name=&quot;binda127&quot;/&gt;

{{quote box|align=right|width=30%|quote=Our African soldiers are ideally suited to jungle warfare&amp;nbsp;... far superior to the British and Ghurkha troops.|source=&lt;small&gt;Lt-Col Frank Fitzgerald, RhAR second-in-command in Malaya, 1957&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb
|Stapleton
|2011
|p=65}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/small&gt;|quoted=yes}}
In Malaya, the RhAR comprised A, B, C and D Companies, each of which was split into three 32-man platoons. The white lieutenant commanding each platoon carried the weapon of his choice, usually a shotgun or an [[FN FAL]] battle rifle, and acted with the assistance of a black [[platoon sergeant]] and a black warrant officer. Under the lieutenant, three black corporals led a rifle section each. These consisted of the section leader (generally armed with a shotgun), a scout, a [[Bren light machine gun|Bren]] gunner, a [[Sterling submachine gun|Patchett-Sterling]] machine-gunner, and up to seven FN FAL riflemen. When marching through thick jungle, an RhAR patrol moved in single file, with each trooper {{convert|5|m}} behind the man in front. The warrant officer followed close behind the lieutenant, ready to take over command if necessary, with the radio operator and medic with him. The platoon sergeant made up the rear. According to Second Lieutenant [[John Essex-Clark]], an Australian-born officer who led an RhAR platoon in Malaya, these Southern Rhodesian units moved much faster in jungle conditions than those made up of British men. The black Southern Rhodesian soldiers were reportedly naturals when it came to [[Tracking (hunting)|tracking]];&lt;ref name=binda127128&gt;{{Harvnb
|Binda
|2007
|pp=127–128}}&lt;/ref&gt; many of them came from rural backgrounds, and had acquired relevant instincts and skills while growing up.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb
|Stapleton
|2011
|p=192}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===RhAR operations in Malaya===
The RhAR patrolled around Johore from May to September 1956 without major incident.&lt;ref name=binda129&gt;{{Harvnb
|Binda
|2007
|p=129}}&lt;/ref&gt; The rain of the Malayan [[wet season|monsoon season]] seemed endless to many of the battalion's men, and actual sightings of the communists were rare in the extreme. Even when the guerrillas were spotted, they almost invariably fled after a few shots. &quot;We can but hope that the chaps will get a chance of seeing a CT [communist terrorist] for a change,&quot; reported an RhAR officer in August; &quot;they are all as keen as mustard to come to blows with them.&quot;&lt;ref name=stapleton191&gt;{{Harvnb
|Stapleton
|2011
|pp=191–192}}&lt;/ref&gt; So determined were the RhAR's officers and men to come face to face with the enemy that they ambushed around the railway line at [[Bekok]] for seven nights in a row, starting on 30 October 1956. Patrols were led by a different officer each night, but there were no contacts.&lt;ref name=binda130/&gt;

Around this time the British [[Royal Lincolnshire Regiment]], operating in the [[Bahau]] area, about {{convert|200|km}} north-west of Bekok, reported to the RhAR that they had encountered the communist 32 Independent Platoon, led by Hor Lung, which was then heading south-east towards the Palong River. The RhAR therefore redeployed to intercept Hor Lung's men. On 9 November, a half-section of Southern Rhodesians led by Corporal Munyameni sighted 16 pack-laden guerrillas, marching east. On his own initiative, Munyameni attacked, catching the communists by surprise; the insurgents split up and fled, running in all directions. One fighter attempted to hide behind a tree, but was killed by RhAR rifle fire.&lt;ref name=binda130&gt;{{Harvnb
|Binda
|2007
|p=130}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 17 November, the RhAR was withdrawn for a period of [[R&amp;R (military)|rest and recuperation]] (R&amp;R). The battalion's Transport Platoon was ambushed by communist guerrillas as it was returning to base: a shot through the windscreen of one of the two trucks nearly hit its driver, but the convoy was able to escape the ambush without anybody being injured. On 26 November, the RhAR and the [[King's Own Scottish Borderers]] assisted the local police at [[Kelapa Sawit]] in an action called ''Tartan Rock'': the security forces moved into the village and arrested 34 communist sympathisers, most of whom were ethnic Chinese students from the [[National University of Singapore|University of Malaya]] in Singapore. Two days later, the RhAR were back on regular duty.&lt;ref name=binda131&gt;{{Harvnb
|Binda
|2007
|p=131}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Starting in February 1957, the RhAR took part in Operations ''Cobble'' and ''Shoe''. These were &quot;food denial&quot; operations, whereby efforts to deny supplies to the communists were to be redoubled. Patrols around the rubber plantations and the edges of the jungle were intensified. To prevent guerrilla supplies from north of the [[Rompin River]] from reaching the food denial areas to the south, covered by Operation ''Cobble'', an RhAR platoon under Lieutenant David Heppenstall was posted to the area directly south of the river midway through the month. This action lasted from 21 February to 4 April 1957. There were few contacts, and only one communist was killed by Heppenstall's men, but a great deal of intelligence was secured regarding guerrilla organisation and supply routes.&lt;ref name=binda131132&gt;{{Harvnb
|Binda
|2007
|pp=131–132}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Over the next few months, RhAR patrols in the Chaah, [[Labis]], Bekok and [[Sungai Karas]] areas were stepped up to last between 10 and 18 days each, but contacts with the communist forces remained rare. The constant patrols gradually began to take their toll on the insurgents, and guerrillas began to give themselves up increasingly frequently. A contributing factor here was Britain's granting of independence to Malaya within the Commonwealth on 31 August 1957, which dented the motivation of many fighters. Starting in October 1957, the RhAR were tasked to work alongside former MNLA personnel to wipe out any remaining communist forces in the region. The ex-insurgents were supposed to lead the security forces to MNLA camps and resting places, but this strategy was not successful. The RhAR soon developed a low opinion of these ex-MNLA men.&lt;ref name=binda138&gt;{{Harvnb
|Binda
|2007
|p=138}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As it approached the end of its two-year commitment in Malaya, the RhAR continued its patrolling in Johore province without major incident until February 1958, when it returned to Rhodesia.&lt;ref name=binda139140&gt;{{Harvnb
|Binda
|2007
|pp=139–140}}&lt;/ref&gt; Five of the regiment's number had been killed over the previous two years: Corporal Tavengwa, and Privates Joseph, Hunyani, Manuel and Mjikijelwa.&lt;ref name=binda404&gt;{{Harvnb
|Binda
|2007
|p=404}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Influence on the Rhodesian Bush War==
{{main|Rhodesian Bush War|Rhodesian Security Forces}}
[[File:Rhodesian African Rifles, Lake Kariba, December 1976.png|thumb|Two RhAR soldiers in 1976, during the [[Rhodesian Bush War]]|alt=Two black soldiers work together to fix a machine-gun to the side of a vessel.]]
Several veterans of Malaya proceeded to hold key positions in the [[Rhodesian Security Forces]] during the [[Rhodesian Bush War]] of the 1970s, most prominently Walls and another member of &quot;C&quot; Squadron, [[Ronald Reid-Daly|Ron Reid-Daly]].&lt;ref name=cilliers76&gt;{{Harvnb
|Cilliers
|1984
|p=76}}&lt;/ref&gt; Walls reformed the all-white [[Rhodesian Light Infantry]] (RLI) into a commando battalion similar to the SAS [[History of the Rhodesian Light Infantry (1961–1972)|during the mid-1960s]], with Reid-Daly serving under him as regimental sergeant major.&lt;ref name=&quot;binda46&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb
|Binda
|2008
|pp=46, 78–80}}&lt;/ref&gt; After leaving the RLI in 1967, Walls became head of the Rhodesian Army in 1972, and retained this role for the rest of the Bush War.&lt;ref name=rlirawalls/&gt; Reid-Daly, meanwhile, formed and commanded the [[Selous Scouts]] pseudo-guerrilla regiment from 1973.&lt;ref name=binda127/&gt; The Selous Scouts concept was influenced by similar operations conducted by [[Special Branch]] in Malaya.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb
|Cilliers
|1984
|p=120}}&lt;/ref&gt; Both the Rhodesian African Rifles and the Rhodesian SAS endured following Malaya, and served in the Bush War.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb
|Abbott
|Botham
|1986
|pp=14–15, 18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The South African historian Jakkie Cilliers, writing about the Rhodesian Bush War, comments on the gulf between what he calls the &quot;Malaya clique&quot; and those lower-ranking Rhodesian soldiers in the field, the latter of whom underestimated the threat posed by the nationalist campaigns, having not previously encountered an insurgency situation. From the mid-1970s, officers such as Walls attempted to impress upon their contemporaries the similarity between the Rhodesian situation and the one they had experienced in Malaya.&lt;ref name=cilliers76/&gt; Operations in Malaya had been coordinated nationally, while in Rhodesia the Army, [[Rhodesian Air Force|Air Force]] and [[British South Africa Police|Police]] were sometimes at odds with each other. To resolve this the Rhodesians created a supreme body called Combined Operations in 1977, influenced by similar posts in Malaya, with Walls at its head.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb
|Cilliers
|1984
|pp=66–70}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes and references==
;Notes
{{reflist|group=n}}

;References
{{reflist|colwidth=20em}}

;Newspaper articles
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite news
|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/obituaries/1408949/Major-Alastair-McGregor.html
|title=Obituary&amp;nbsp;— Major Alastair McGregor
|work=[[The Daily Telegraph]]
|location=London
|accessdate=19 March 2010
|date=3 October 2002
|ref={{harvid|Daily Telegraph|2002}}}}
{{refend}}

;Online sources
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite web
|title=Roll of Honour: &quot;C&quot; Squadron 22 SAS, One Special Air Service Regiment
|url=http://www.rhodesianforces.org/SASRollofHonour.htm
|publisher=Rhodesian Army Association
|accessdate=9 June 2012
|ref={{harvid|Rhodesian Army Association}}}}
*{{cite web
|title=Vale: Peter Walls
|url=http://www.therli.com/C_RollofHonour_Vale_Peter_Walls.asp
|publisher=Rhodesian Light Infantry Regimental Association
|accessdate=5 June 2012
|ref={{harvid|RLI Regimental Association}}}}
{{refend}}

;Government documents
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite news
|title=Federation of Malaya Independence Act 1957
|url=http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/Eliz2/5-6/60
|date=31 July 1957
|publisher=Government of the United Kingdom
|location=London
|id=1957 Chapter 60 5 and 6 Eliz 2
|ref={{harvid|Federation of Malaya Independence Act|1957}}}}
{{refend}}

;Bibliography
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite book
|title=Modern African Wars: Rhodesia, 1965–80
|last1=Abbott
|first1=Peter
|last2=Botham
|first2=Philip
|location=Oxford
|publisher=[[Osprey Publishing]]
|year=1986
|isbn=978-0-85045-728-5
|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book
|title=Cold War: The Essential Reference Guide
|last1=Arnold
|first1=James R
|last2=Wiener
|first2=Roberta
|year=2012
|location=Santa Barbara, California
|publisher=[[ABC-CLIO]]
|isbn=978-1-61069-004-1
|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book
|title=Masodja: The History of the Rhodesian African Rifles and its forerunner the Rhodesian Native Regiment
|last=Binda
|first=Alexandre
|editor-last=Heppenstall
|editor-first=David
|location=Johannesburg
|publisher=30° South Publishers
|year=2007
|isbn=978-1-920143-03-9
|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book
|title=The Saints: The Rhodesian Light Infantry
|last=Binda
|first=Alexandre
|location=Johannesburg
|publisher=30° South Publishers
|year=2008
|isbn=978-1-920143-07-7
|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book
|title=Counter-Insurgency in Rhodesia
|last=Cilliers
|first=Jakkie
|location=London, Sydney &amp; Dover, New Hampshire
|publisher=Croom Helm
|year=1984
|isbn=978-0-7099-3412-7
|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book
|title=Who Dares Wins: The Story of the Special Air Service, 1950–1980
|last=Geraghty
|first=Tony
|publisher=Arms and Armour Press
|location=London
|year=1980
|isbn=978-0-85368-457-2
|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book
|title=Special Force: The Untold Story of 22nd Special Air Service Regiment
|last=MacKenzie
|first=Alastair
|publisher=[[I.B. Tauris|I B Tauris]]
|location=London &amp; New York
|year=2011
|isbn=978-1-84885-071-2
|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite book
|title=The Malayan Campaign 1948–60
|last=Scurr
|first=John
|publisher=Osprey Publishing
|location=Oxford
|year=2005
|origyear=1981
|isbn=978-0-85045-476-5
|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite book
|title=The Special Air Service
|last1=Shortt
|first1=James
|authorlink1=James Shortt
|last2=McBride
|first2=Angus
|publisher=Osprey Publishing
|location=Oxford
|year=1981
|isbn=0-85045-396-8
|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book
|title=African Police and Soldiers in Colonial Zimbabwe, 1923–80
|last=Stapleton
|first=Timothy
|year=2011
|location=Rochester, New York
|publisher=[[University of Rochester|University of Rochester Press]]
|isbn=978-1-58046-380-5
|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book
|title=So far and no further! Rhodesia's bid for independence during the retreat from empire 1959–1965
|last=Wood
|first=J R T
|year=2005
|location=Victoria, British Columbia
|publisher=[[Trafford Publishing]]
|isbn= 978-1-4120-4952-8
|ref=harv}}
{{refend}}

{{Rhodesian topics}}

{{Use South African English|date=June 2012}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2012}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Malaya, Southern Rhodesia}}
[[Category:Malayan Emergency|Southern Rhodesia]]
[[Category:Military history of Rhodesia]]
[[Category:Wars involving Rhodesia]]</text>
      <sha1>49uj2mbb3mlbz12n6e4on16sdd224pd</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
