<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>STRAT-X</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>34866867</id>
    <revision>
      <id>721655161</id>
      <parentid>692456008</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-05-23T07:44:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>134.223.230.154</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Findings and consequences */  changed to &quot;as of 2016&quot;</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17773">{{Good article}}&lt;!--
{{Image frame|width=215|content=[[File:Robert McNamara at a cabinet meeting, 22 Nov 1967.jpg|100px|alt=Bespectacled man in suit sitting down next to table doing a chopping sign with left hand.]][[File:Maxwell D Taylor official portrait.jpg|115px|alt=Portrait of middle-age man in military uniforms set against a dark background.]]|caption=STRAT-X was initiated in 1966 by the U.S. Secretary of Defense [[Robert McNamara]] ''(left)'' and presided by General [[Maxwell D. Taylor]] ''(right)''.&lt;ref name=G10_53/&gt;}}--&gt;
{{Infobox historical event
  |Event_Name     = STRAT-X 
  |Image_Name     = Maxwell D Taylor official portrait.jpg
  |Imagesize      = 155px
  |alt      = Portrait of middle-age man in military uniforms set against a dark background
  |Image_Caption  = STRAT-X was presided by General [[Maxwell D. Taylor]].&lt;ref name=G10_53/&gt;
  |Thumb_Time     = 
  |AKA            = Strategic-Experimental
  |Participants   = [[U.S. Department of Defense]]&lt;br&gt; [[Institute for Defense Analyses]]&lt;br&gt; [[U.S. Armed Forces]]&lt;br&gt; Military contractors
  |Location       = 
  |Date           = {{Start date|1966|11|01|df=y}} – {{End date|1967|08|}}&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.ssp.navy.mil/about/history_chronology_66-75.shtml|title=About SSP: September 1966 ~ 1975|work=U.S. Navy|publisher=Navy.mi|accessdate=28 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
  |nongregorian   =
  |Deaths        = 
  |Result         = Implementation of several military concepts 
  |URL            = 
}}

'''STRAT-X''', or '''Strategic-Experimental''', was a [[U.S. government]]-sponsored study conducted during 1966 and 1967 that comprehensively analyzed the potential future of the [[Nuclear weapons and the United States|U.S. nuclear deterrent force]]. At the time, the [[Soviet Union]] was making significant strides in [[nuclear weapons delivery]], and also constructing [[anti-ballistic missile]] defenses to protect strategic facilities. To address a potential [[missile gap|technological gap]] between the two [[superpower]]s, [[U.S. Secretary of Defense]] [[Robert McNamara]] entrusted the [[Classified information|classified]] STRAT-X study to the [[Institute for Defense Analyses]], which compiled a twenty-volume report in nine months. The report looked into more than one hundred different weapons systems, ultimately resulting in the [[MGM-134 Midgetman]] and [[LGM-118 Peacekeeper]] [[intercontinental ballistic missile]]s, the {{sclass-|Ohio|submarine}}s, and the [[Trident missile|Trident]] [[submarine-launched ballistic missile]]s, among others. Journalists have regarded STRAT-X as a major influence on the course of U.S. nuclear policy.

==Background==
In the mid-1960s, reports received by U.S. intelligence agencies indicated that the Soviets were planning to deploy large numbers of highly accurate and powerful [[intercontinental ballistic missile]]s (ICBMs).&lt;ref name=G10_52&gt;Grier 2010, p. 52.&lt;/ref&gt; Later, the [[R-36 (missile)|R-36]] ICBM entered service.  Possessing the greatest [[throw weight]] of any ICBM ever at {{Convert|8.8|t|lb}}, the R-36 was larger than the most modern ICBMs in the U.S. arsenal at the time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://fas.org/nuke/guide/russia/icbm/r-36m.htm |title=R-36M / SS-18 SATAN |author= |date=29 July 2000 |work=[[Federation of American Scientists]] |publisher=FAS.org |accessdate=24 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Due to its size, it was able to carry high-yield warheads [[Pre-emptive nuclear strike|capable of destroying]] [[Minuteman missile|Minuteman]] [[Missile launch facility|hardened silos]] (see [[Counterforce]]). This was considered a significant risk to American ICBMs and, as a result, to the United States' nuclear defense strategy by reducing the United States' [[second strike|ability to retaliate with nuclear weapons if attacked]].{{#tag:ref|&quot;First, increasingly numerous ICBMs posed a threat to America's own weapons.&quot;&lt;ref name=G10_52/&gt;|group=&quot;N&quot;}}

At the same time, the Soviets were designing and constructing increasingly sophisticated [[anti-ballistic missile]] defense systems to protect strategically important facilities around Moscow,&lt;ref name=G10_52/&gt; reducing the threat posed by American ICBMs. These developments compelled the [[U.S. Secretary of Defense]], [[Robert McNamara]], to commission a [[Research|study]] to look into ways of improving the survivability of the [[Nuclear weapons and the United States|U.S. nuclear arsenal]].&lt;ref name=G10_52/&gt;{{#tag:ref|&quot;The survivability of U.S. missiles from a Soviet first-strike attack was given particular consideration by the Strat-X participants&amp;nbsp;...&quot;&lt;ref name=P&amp;M_184/&gt;|group=&quot;N&quot;}}

According to Graham Spinardi in his book ''From Polaris to Trident'' (1994), STRAT-X was a response by the [[U.S. Department of Defense]]'s Deputy Director of Defense Research and Engineering, Lloyd Wilson, to the [[U.S. Air Force]]; the service was demanding a large ICBM called the [[BGM-75 AICBM|WS-120A]]. Spinardi suggests that STRAT-X was allowed to proceed so it could terminate the study for such a missile.&lt;ref&gt;Spinardi 1994, p. 113.&lt;/ref&gt; Funding for the WS-120A would not be released by Secretary McNamara, and plans for such a missile were canceled in 1967.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.designation-systems.net/dusrm/m-75.html |title=BGM-75 AICBM |first=Andreas |last=Parsch |year=2003 |work=Directory of U.S. Military Rockets and Missiles |publisher=Designation-systems.net |accessdate=1 June 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Study==
The study was named &quot;STRAT-X&quot; in order not to reveal its intentions, and also to eliminate partiality towards [[Nuclear triad|sea-, air- or land-based systems]]. It was conducted by the Research and Engineering Support Division of the independent and non-profit [[Institute for Defense Analyses]] (IDA), which had conducted a study in early 1966 titled &quot;Pen-X&quot;, upon which STRAT-X was based.&lt;ref name=FAS_ULMS&gt;{{cite web |url=https://fas.org/nuke/guide/usa/slbm/ssbn_ulms.htm |title=ULMS |author= |date=30 May 1997 |work=[[Federation of American Scientists]] |publisher=FAS.org |accessdate=24 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; STRAT-X was chaired by President of the IDA, General [[Maxwell D. Taylor]], while the institution's Fred Payne presided over STRAT-X's &quot;working&quot; panel. The panel also included executives from major independent corporations and [[defense contractor]]s such as [[Boeing]], [[Booz Allen Hamilton]], [[Thiokol]] and [[TRW Inc.|TRW]].&lt;ref name=G10_53&gt;Grier 2010, p. 53.&lt;/ref&gt; The Advisory Committee members were mostly [[military officers]], including [[United States Navy|U.S. Navy]] [[Rear Admirals]] George H. Miller and Levering Smith.&lt;ref name=FAS_ULMS/&gt;
{{Quote box|quote=&quot;The systems to be analyzed need not be limited to those recommended by the services, and the STRAT-X study group is encouraged to examine system concepts unrestrained by considerations of potential management problems or political influences.&quot;|source=&lt;small&gt;Extract from a memo from the [[Assistant Secretary of Defense for Research and Engineering|Director of Defense Research and Engineering]] to the IDA&lt;ref name=G10_53/&gt;&lt;/small&gt;|align=left|width=40%}}

On 1 November 1966, McNamara signed an order authorizing STRAT-X, officially initiating the study. During STRAT-X, the working panel was &quot;encouraged to examine system concepts unrestrained by considerations of potential management problems or political influences.&quot;&lt;ref name=G10_53/&gt; The Secretary wanted new ideas about &quot;path-breaking&quot; weapons systems that were either offensive or [[Self-defense|defensive]] in nature, unhindered by defense bureaucracy, which had the potential to stifle innovation.&lt;ref name=G10_53/&gt; Sea-, land- and air-based missile systems were investigated, but [[Strategic bomber|manned bombers]] and orbital systems were not. The group was also asked to consider the cost effectiveness of all systems, as well to predict possible [[Brinkmanship (Cold War)|Soviet responses]]. To meet this requirement, a series of documents were written from the perspective of the [[Minister of Defence (Soviet Union)|Soviet Minister of Defense]] General [[Andrei Grechko]], complete with [[Anti-capitalism|anti-capitalistic]] statements and a prediction of the eventual triumph of [[socialism]].&lt;ref name=G10_53/&gt;&lt;ref name=WP.com/&gt; In the end, a twenty-volume report covered no fewer than 125 different ideas for missile systems, nine of which were reviewed in great detail.&lt;ref name=FAS_ULMS/&gt;&lt;ref name=WP.com&gt;{{cite web |url=http://nsarchive.wordpress.com/2010/01/06/the-strat-x-report-and-its-impact/ |title=The STRAT-X Report and Its Impact |author=Burr, William |date=6 January 2010 |work=[[National Security Archive]] |publisher= |accessdate=24 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=G10_54&gt;Grier 2010, p. 54.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- CHECK UNMATCHED --&gt;

===Findings and consequences===
[[File:Small ICBM Hard Mobile Launcher USAF.jpg|thumb|A Hard Mobile Launcher that was designed to carry the [[MGM-134 Midgetman]] missile&lt;ref name=G10_54/&gt;|alt=Long vehicle in green black and dirt brown camouflage executing a turn on light-colored paved road for camera.]]

Of the nine prospective weapons systems, five were land-based. These were: &quot;Rock Silo&quot;—a system where missiles would be stored in hardened silos of [[granite]] [[bedrock]] in the [[Western United States|Western]] and [[Northern United States]]; &quot;Soft Silo&quot;—a similar system but with easily   and cheaply constructed silos; &quot;Rock Tunnel&quot;—a system where missiles would be transported around in deep underground networks before emerging at launch points; &quot;Soft Tunnel&quot;—a similar tunnel but built more cheaply and easily; and &quot;Land Mobile&quot;—a [[Transporter erector launcher|truck-based system]] where road-transporters traveled at speeds up to {{Convert|35|mph|km/h}} constantly around a dedicated and winding road system in {{Convert|65,000|sqmi|km2}} of public land.&lt;ref name=G10_55&gt;Grier 2010, p. 55.&lt;/ref&gt;

Of the remaining four, three were sea-based. These were: &quot;Canal-Based&quot;—a systems where missiles would be sailed in canals to confuse Soviet [[Military operation plan|military planners]]; &quot;Ship-Based&quot;—a system where ships carrying missile canisters would travel around the world, hiding among other traffic; and &quot;Submarine-Based&quot;—a system where [[ballistic missile submarine]]s would roam the oceans while carrying missile canisters outside their [[pressure hull]]s.&lt;ref name=G10_54/&gt; The single air-based based consideration was the {{anchor|Air Launched ICBM}}&quot;Air Launched ICBM&quot;, which required large aircraft carrying [[Standoff (missile)|standoff ballistic missiles]] to launch their payloads at the Soviet Union.&lt;ref name=G10_54/&gt;

Despite the numerous options investigated during the study, none were fully implemented. Although the STRAT-X &quot;Land Mobile&quot; option resulted in the [[MGM-134 Midgetman]] and [[LGM-118 Peacekeeper]] missiles, the [[Revolutions of 1989|fall of communism]] throughout the late 1980s and early 1990s resulted in the Midgetman being canceled while still a prototype,{{#tag:ref|&quot;The [MGM-134 Midgetman] missile was canceled in 1992, following the collapse of the Berlin Wall and the end of the Cold War.&quot;&lt;ref name=G10_54/&gt;|group=&quot;N&quot;}} while only 50 out of the original 100 Peacekeeper missiles were ever fielded.&lt;ref name=G10_55/&gt; Nevertheless, the study did inspire a number of developments in nuclear weapons delivery systems.&lt;ref name=G10_53/&gt; In October 1974, the U.S. Air Force successfully conducted an air launch of a Minuteman missile from a [[Lockheed C-5 Galaxy|C-5 Galaxy]], demonstrating the credibility of the &quot;Air Launched ICBM&quot; option of STRAT-X.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.af.mil/information/heritage/milestones.asp?dec=1970-1980&amp;sd=01/01/1970&amp;ed=12/31/1989 |title=History Milestones |author= |date= |work=U.S. Air Force |publisher=AF.mil |accessdate=24 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the U.S. Navy then had several classes of [[ballistic missile submarine]]s and [[submarine-launched ballistic missile]] (SLBM) in service, the study placed a significant emphasis on the survivability of SLBMs.&lt;ref&gt;Clearwater 1996, p. 31.&lt;/ref&gt; This resulted in the enormous ''Ohio''-class submarine and the Trident SLBMs which the ''Ohio'' class carried. The study originally called for dedicated slow-moving missile-carrying submarines (instead of converted [[SSN (hull classification symbol)|attack submarines]]) to embark missiles outside their hulls and rely primarily on stealth for survivability. However, Admiral [[Hyman Rickover]], director of the [[Naval Reactors]] office, wanted a boat capable of a burst of high speed in order to affect a safe &quot;getaway&quot; after launching the boat's payload. As a result, the ''Ohio'' class was designed to accommodate enormous nuclear reactors to produce the required speed. ''Ohio''-class submarines carry their missiles inside of their hulls, despite STRAT-X's recommendation.&lt;ref name=G10_55/&gt; ''Ohio''-class submarines and Trident missiles are still in service {{asof|2016|lc=y}}.&lt;!--&lt;ref name=FBMS/&gt;--&gt;
&lt;gallery class=center mode=packed heights=175 caption=&quot;Weapons systems inspired by STRAT-X&quot;&gt;
File:Trident II D-5 launch.gif|alt=Blunt-nosed missile, with its rocket motors fired, splashes huge white waves as it positions itself on an angle for a ballistic firing.|A [[Trident II]] [[submarine-launched ballistic missile]] firing its rocket motors after emerging from the ocean.
File:Midgetman (XMGM-134A).jpg|alt=Portrait photo of missile firing its rocket motors shortly after launch.|An [[MGM-134 Midgetman]] [[intercontinental ballistic missile]] shortly after launch.
File:Peacekeeper missile.jpg|alt=Huge missile with body painted in black rising out of silo during a launch, producing clouds of gas at the silo's opening. In the distant is a coastline.|An [[LGM-118 Peacekeeper]] missile leaving its hardened silo.
File:USS Henry M. Jackson (SSBN-730)2.jpg|alt=Submarine in bay with valleys and snow-capped mountains in the background.|{{USS|Henry M. Jackson|SSBN-730}}, one of the eighteen ''Ohio''-class boats constructed&lt;ref name=FBMS&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.navy.mil/navydata/fact_display.asp?cid=4100&amp;tid=200&amp;ct=4 |title=Fleet Ballistic Missile Submarines&amp;nbsp;– SSBN |author= |date=10 November 2011 |work=U.S. Navy |publisher=Navy.mil |accessdate=24 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=USNF&gt;{{Cite web|title=Guided Missile Submarines&amp;nbsp;– SSGN|url=http://www.navy.mil/navydata/fact_display.asp?cid=4100&amp;tid=300&amp;ct=4|publisher=Navy.mil|work=U.S. Navy|date=10 November 2011|accessdate=25 February 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;
File:MMIII C5 airdrop(Oct 1974).jpg|alt= Sequence of grey-scale photos of transport aircraft releasing a missile from its aft loading door. |A [[Minuteman III]] '''Air Launched ICBM''' test launch from a [[C-5 Galaxy]] in October 1974.
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Legacy==
STRAT-X had far-reaching effects on the development and deployment of U.S. nuclear forces. It was the first time that the strategic requirements of the [[U.S. Armed Forces]] were addressed in a detailed and analytical manner.&lt;ref name=P&amp;M_184&gt;Polmar and Moore 2004, p. 184.&lt;/ref&gt; In a 2002 report by the [[RAND Corporation]], STRAT-X was described as &quot;one of the most influential analyses ever conducted&quot; for the [[U.S. Department of Defense]].&lt;ref name=G10_53/&gt; Journalist Peter Grier, in his [[Air Force Magazine|''Air Force'' magazine]] article &quot;STRAT-X&quot;, described the study as &quot;a wide-ranging look at the future of U.S. weapons that shaped the nuclear triad for decades, and remains a model for such efforts today&quot;.&lt;ref name=G10_53/&gt;&lt;ref name=WP.com/&gt; In 2006, the [[Defense Science Board]] (DFS) noted STRAT-X's introduction of ideas and concepts that resulted in the ''Ohio''-class submarines and small and mobile ICBMs.&lt;ref name=G10_52/&gt; The DFS also attributed the use of air-launched [[cruise missile]]s, particularly those carried by the [[B-52 Stratofortress]], to STRAT-X despite their lack of references in the study.&lt;ref name=G10_55/&gt;

==Footnotes==
'''Notes'''
{{Reflist|group=N}}

'''References'''
{{Reflist|colwidth=33em}}

'''Bibliography'''
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite book |author1=Clearwater, M. John |title=Johnson, McNamara, and the Birth of SALT and the ABM Treaty 1963–1969 |type= |edition= |series= |volume= |date= |year=1996 |month= |origyear= |publisher=Universal-Publishers |location=[[St Leonards, New South Wales]] |oclc= |doi= |isbn=1-58112-062-1 |page= |pages= |chapter= |chapterurl= }}
*{{cite book |author=Grier, Peter |title=Air Force |url=http://www.airforce-magazine.com/Pages/HomePage.aspx |format= |accessdate=24 February 2012 |type=magazine |edition= |series= |volume=93 |date= January 2010 |origyear= |publisher=[[Air Force Association]] |location=Arlington, Virginia |oclc=5169825 |doi= |page= |pages= |chapter=STRAT-X |chapterurl=http://www.airforce-magazine.com/MagazineArchive/Documents/2010/January%202010/0110stratx.pdf |issn=0730-6784 }}
*{{cite book |author1=Polmar, Norman |author2=Moore, Kenneth J. |title=Cold War Submarines: The Design and Construction of U.S. and Soviet Submarines |type= |edition= |series= |volume= |date= |year=2004 |month= |origyear= |publisher=Potomac Books |location=Dulles, Virginia |oclc= |doi= |isbn=1-57488-594-4 |page= |pages= |chapter=The Ultimate Weapon II |chapterurl= }}
*{{cite book |author=Spinardi, Graham |title=From Polaris to Trident: The Development of US Fleet Ballistic Missile Technology |url= |format= |accessdate= |type= |edition= |series= |volume= |date= |year=1994 |month= |origyear= |publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]] |location=[[Cambridge]], United Kingdom |oclc= |doi= |isbn=0-521-41357-5 |page= |pages= |chapter=STRAT-X, ULMS, and Trident I |chapterurl= }}
{{refend}}
{{Portal bar|Cold War|Weapons of mass destruction|Military of the United States}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:STRAT-X}}
[[Category:Nuclear warfare]]
[[Category:Research projects]]</text>
      <sha1>qhyt461q7o5o6qdfuk6xsn47lgiaugh</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
