<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Sukhoi Su-25</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>366696</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749868557</id>
      <parentid>749352747</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-16T16:07:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GreenC bot</username>
        <id>27823944</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>3 {{[[template:webarchive|webarchive]]}} templates date format change per {{[[template:use dmy|use dmy]]}})</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="82703">{{pp-semi-indef|small=yes}}
&lt;!-- This article is a part of [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft]]. Please see [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft/page content]] for recommended layout, and guidelines. --&gt;
{|{{Infobox aircraft begin
 |name= Su-25
 |image= Su-25Ub.JPG
 |caption= A Georgian Su-25UB
}}{{Infobox aircraft type
 |type= [[Close air support]]
 |manufacturer= [[Sukhoi Design Bureau]] &lt;br/&gt;[[Tbilisi Aircraft Manufacturing]] (''former'')
 |designer=
 |first flight= 22 February 1975 (T8)
 |introduced= 19 July 1981
 |retired= 
 |status= In service
 |primary user= [[Russian Air Force]]&lt;!--Limit one (1) primary user. Top 4 users listed in 'primary user' and 'more users' fields based on number of their fleets. --&gt;
 |more users= [[Belarusian Air Force]] &lt;br/&gt;[[Ukrainian Air Force]]&lt;br/&gt;[[North Korean Air Force]] &lt;br/&gt;See ''[[#Operators|Operators]]'' for others &lt;!-- Limit is three (3) in 'more users' field, four (4) total users with primary user (Top 3 users per Flight International, 11–17 November 2008, plus operators link). Please separate with &lt;br/&gt;. --&gt;
 |produced= 1978–present
 |number built= Over 1,000
 |unit cost= {{US$|link=yes}}11&amp;nbsp;million&lt;ref name=&quot;gordondawes&quot; /&gt;
 |developed from=
 |variants with their own articles= [[Sukhoi Su-28]]
}}
|}

The '''Sukhoi Su-25 ''Grach''''' ([[Russian language|Russian]]: &quot;Грач&quot;, meaning [[Rook (bird)|rook]]; [[NATO reporting name]]: &quot;'''Frogfoot'''&quot;) is a single-seat, twin-engine [[jet aircraft]] developed in the [[Soviet Union]] by the [[Sukhoi|Sukhoi Design Bureau]]. It was designed to provide [[close air support]] for the [[Soviet Ground Forces]]. The first prototype made its maiden flight on 22 February 1975. After testing, the aircraft went into series production in 1978 at [[Tbilisi]] in the [[Georgian SSR|Soviet Republic of Georgia]].

Early variants included the Su-25UB two-seat trainer, the Su-25BM for target-towing, and the Su-25K for export customers. Some aircraft were being upgraded to Su-25SM standard in 2012. The Su-25T and the Su-25TM (also known as the Su-39) were further developments, not produced in significant numbers. The Su-25, and the [[Sukhoi Su-34|Su-34]], were the only armoured, fixed-wing aircraft in production in 2007.&lt;ref name=&quot;gordondawes&quot;&gt;Gordon and Dawes 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; Su-25s are in service with [[Russia]], other [[Commonwealth of Independent States|CIS]] states, and export customers.

The type has seen combat in several conflicts during its more than 30 years in service. It was heavily involved in the [[Soviet war in Afghanistan]], flying [[counter-insurgency]] missions against the [[Mujahideen]]. The [[Iraqi Air Force]] employed Su-25s against Iran during the 1980–88 [[Iran–Iraq War]]. Most were later destroyed or flown to Iran in the 1991 [[Gulf War|Persian Gulf War]]. [[Abkhazia]]n [[separatist]]s used Su-25s during the [[War in Abkhazia (1992–1993)|Abkhazian War]] from 1992 to 1993. The [[Military of the Republic of Macedonia|Macedonian Air Force]] used Su-25s against Albanian insurgents in the [[2001 Macedonia conflict]] and, in 2008, [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]] and [[Russia]] both used Su-25s in the [[Russo-Georgian War]]. African states, including the [[Ivory Coast]], [[Chad]], and [[Sudan]] have used the Su-25 in local insurgencies and civil wars.  Recently the Su-25 has seen service in the [[Russian military intervention in the Syrian Civil War|Russian intervention in the Syrian Civil War]].
{{TOC limit|limit=3}}

==Development==
In early 1968, the Soviet Ministry of Defence decided to develop a specialised ''[[shturmovik]]'' armoured assault aircraft in order to provide close air support for the [[Red Army|Soviet Ground Forces]]. The idea of creating a ground-support aircraft came about after analysing the experience of ground-attack (''shturmovaya'') aviation during the 1940s, 1950s, and 1960s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Development&quot;&gt;Gordon and Dawes 2004, pp. 6–7.&lt;/ref&gt; The Soviet fighter-bombers in service or under development at the time ([[Sukhoi Su-7|Su-7]], [[Sukhoi Su-17|Su-17]], [[Mikoyan-Gurevich MiG-21|MiG-21]] and [[Mikoyan-Gurevich MiG-23|MiG-23]]) did not meet the requirements for close air support of the army.&lt;ref name=&quot;Development&quot;/&gt; They lacked essential armour plating to protect the pilot and vital equipment from ground fire and missile hits, and their high flight speeds made it difficult for the pilot to maintain visual contact with a target. Having taken into account these problems, [[Pavel Sukhoi]] and a group of leading specialists in the Sukhoi Design Bureau started preliminary design work in a comparatively short period of time, with the assistance of leading institutes of the Ministry of the Aviation Industry and the Ministry of Defence.&lt;ref&gt;Gordon and Dawes 2004, p. 8.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Russian Air Force Su-25.jpg|thumb|A [[Russian Air Force]] Su-25UB. This version is a two-seater intended for both combat and training.]]

In March 1969, a competition was announced by the [[Soviet Air Force]] that called for designs for a new battlefield close-support aircraft. Participants in the competition were the Sukhoi Design Bureau and the Design Bureaus of [[Yakovlev]], [[Ilyushin]] and [[Mikoyan]].&lt;ref&gt;Gordon and Dawes 2004, p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt; Sukhoi finalised its &quot;T-8&quot; design in late 1968, and began in work on the first two prototypes (T8-1 and T8-2) in January 1972. The T8-1, the first airframe to be assembled, was completed on 9 May 1974. Another source says November 1974. However, it did not make its first flight until 22 February 1975, after a long series of test flights by [[Vladimir Ilyushin]]. The Su-25 surpassed its main competitor in the Soviet Air Force competition, the [[Ilyushin Il-102]], and series production was announced by the Ministry of Defence.&lt;ref&gt;Gordon and Dawes 2004, pp. 23–41.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.sukhoi.org/eng/planes/military/su25k/history/|title=Sukhoi Company (JSC) – Airplanes – Military Aircraft – Su-25К – Historical background|work=sukhoi.org|accessdate=27 April 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During flight-testing phases of the T8-1 and T8-2 prototypes' development, the Sukhoi Design Bureau's management proposed that the series production of the Su-25 should start at Factory No. 31 in [[Tbilisi]], [[Georgian SSR|Soviet Republic of Georgia]], which at that time was the major manufacturing base for the [[MiG-21]]UM &quot;Mongol-B&quot; trainer. After negotiations and completion of all stages of the state trials, the Soviet Ministry of Aircraft Production authorised manufacture of the Su-25 at Tbilisi, allowing series production to start in 1978.&lt;ref name=&quot;Variants&quot;/&gt;

In the late 1980s and early 1990s, several Su-25 variants appeared, including modernised versions, and variants for specialised roles. The most significant designs were the Su-25UB dual-seat trainer, the Su-25BM target-towing variant, and the Su-25T for antitank missions. In addition, an Su-25KM prototype was developed by [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]] in co-operation with Israeli company [[Elbit Systems]] in 2001, but so far this variant has not achieved much commercial success. {{asof|2007}}, the Su-25 was the only armoured aircraft still in production.&lt;ref name=&quot;gordondawes&quot;/&gt;

The [[Russian Air Force]], which operates the largest number of Su-25s, planned to upgrade older aircraft to the Su-25SM variant, but funding shortfalls had slowed the progress; by early 2007 only seven aircraft had been modified.&lt;ref name=&quot;AFM&quot;&gt;&quot;Force report: Russian Air Force.&quot; ''[[Air Forces Monthly]]'', July 2007, pp. 78–86.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Design==

===Overview===
The Su-25 has a conventional [[aerodynamic]] layout with a shoulder-mounted [[trapezoidal wing]] and a traditional [[tailplane]] and [[rudder]]. Several [[metals]] are used in the construction of the [[airframe]]: 60% [[aluminium]], 19% [[steel]], 13.5% [[titanium]], 2% [[magnesium alloy]] and 5.5% other materials.&lt;ref name=&quot;Design2&quot;&gt;Gordon and Dawes 2004, pp. 73–75.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Su-25.jpg|thumb|left|Su-25 at [[Kubinka (air base)|Kubinka air base]] ]]
All versions of the Su-25 have a metal [[cantilever wing]], of [[Swept wing|moderate sweep]], [[Aspect ratio (wing)|high aspect ratio]] and is equipped with high-lift devices. The wing consists of two cantilever sections attached to a central [[torsion box]], forming a single unit with the fuselage. The air brakes are housed in [[Aircraft fairing|fairings]] at the tip of each wing. Each wing has five hardpoints for weapons carriage, with the attachment points mounted on [[load-bearing]] ribs and spars.&lt;ref&gt;Gordon and Dawes 2004, p. 77.&lt;/ref&gt; Each wing also features a five-section [[leading edge slat]], a two-section [[Flap (aircraft)|flap]] and an [[aileron]].

The flaps are mounted by steel sliders and rollers, attached to brackets on the rear spar. The trapezoidal ailerons are near the [[wingtip]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Variants5&quot;&gt;Gordon and Dawes 2004, pp. 79–82.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[fuselage]] of the Su-25 has an [[ellipsoidal]] section and is of semi-[[monocoque]], [[stressed-skin]] construction, arranged as a longitudinal load-bearing framework of [[longeron]]s, beams and stringers, with a transverse load-bearing assembly of frames.&lt;ref name=&quot;Design2&quot;/&gt; The one-piece horizontal [[tailplane]] is attached to the load-bearing frame at two mounting points.&lt;ref name=&quot;Variants5&quot;/&gt;

Early versions of the Su-25 were equipped with two [[R95Sh]] non-afterburning [[turbojet]]s, in compartments on either side of the rear fuselage. The engines, sub-assemblies and surrounding fuselage are cooled by air provided by the [[cold air intake]]s on top of the engine nacelles. A [[drainage]] system collects oil, [[hydraulic fluid]] residues and fuel from the engines after flight or after an unsuccessful start. The engine control systems allows independent operation of each engine.&lt;ref name=&quot;Variants5&quot;/&gt; The latest versions (Su-25T and TM) are equipped with improved R-195 engines.&lt;ref&gt;Gordon and Dawes 2004, p. 111.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Su-25 Nose view - Le Bourget.JPEG|thumb|Nose view of the Su-25]]
The [[cannon]] is in a compartment beneath the cockpit, mounted on a load-bearing beam attached to the cockpit floor and the forward fuselage support structure. The nose is fitted with distinctive twin [[Pitot tube|pitot probes]] and hinges up for service access.&lt;ref name=&quot;Design2&quot;/&gt;

===Cockpit===
The [[aircraft pilot|pilot]] flies the aircraft by means of a [[centre stick]] and left hand [[throttle]]s. The pilot sits on a [[NPP Zvezda|Zvezda]] [[NPP Zvezda K-36|K-36]] ejection seat (similar to the [[Sukhoi Su-27]]) and has standard [[flight instruments]]. At the rear of the [[cockpit]] is a {{convert|6|mm|in|abbr=on}} thick steel headrest, mounted on the rear bulkhead. The cockpit has a bathtub-shaped armoured enclosure of [[welded]] [[titanium]] sheets, with transit ports in the walls. Guide rails for the [[ejection seat]] are mounted on the rear wall of the cockpit.&lt;ref name=&quot;Design2&quot;/&gt;

The canopy hinges open to the right and the pilot enters using the flip-down ladder. Once inside, the pilot sits low in the cockpit, protected by the bathtub assembly, which makes for a cramped cockpit. Visibility from the cockpit is limited, being a trade-off for improved pilot protection. Rearwards visibility is poor, though a [[periscope]] is fitted on top of the canopy to compensate.&lt;ref name=&quot;Goebel&quot;&gt;Goebel, Greg. [http://www.airvectors.net/avsu25.html The Sukhoi Su-25 &quot;Frogfoot&quot;], ''airvectors.net'' website, 1 July 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

On the left-hand rear side of the cockpit, a built-in [[ladder]] provides access to the cockpit, the upper part of the engine nacelles and the wing.

===Avionics===
The base model Su-25 incorporates a number of key [[avionics]] systems. It has no TV guidance but includes a distinctive nose-mounted [[laser rangefinder]], that is thought to provide for laser-based target finding.&lt;ref name=&quot;Goebel&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=su25K&gt;Su-25К specification substituted, taken from [http://www.sukhoi.org/eng/planes/military/su25k/lth/ &quot;Sukhoi Company (JSC) – Airplanes – Military Aircraft – Su-25К – Aircraft performance.&quot;] ''Sukhoi.org.'' Retrieved: 26 January 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; A DISS-7 [[doppler radar]] is used for navigation; the Su-25 can fly at night, in [[Visual meteorological conditions|visual]] and [[instrument meteorological conditions]].

The Su-25 often has radios installed for air-to-ground and air-to-air communications, including an SO-69 identification-friend-or-foe ([[Identification friend or foe|IFF]]) transponder. The aircraft's self-defence suite includes various measures, such as [[Flare (pyrotechnic)|flare]] and [[Chaff (radar countermeasure)|chaff]] dispensers capable of launching up to 250 flares and [[dipole]] chaff. Hostile radar uses are guarded against via an SPO-15 [[radar warning receiver]].

An airtight avionics compartment is behind the cockpit and in front of the forward fuel tank.

The newer Su-25TM and Su-25SM models have an upgraded avionics and weapons suite, resulting in improved survivability and combat capability.&lt;ref name=&quot;Variants7&quot;/&gt;

==Operational history==

===Soviet war in Afghanistan===
{{Main article|List of Soviet aircraft losses during the Soviet–Afghan War}}
The first [[Soviet Air Forces]] Su-25 unit was the 200th Independent Attack Squadron, initially based at [[Sitalcay]] air base in the [[Azerbaijan Soviet Socialist Republic]]. The first eleven aircraft arrived at Sitalchay in May 1981.&lt;ref&gt;[http://sukhoi.org/eng/planes/military/su25k/history/ &quot;Historical background.&quot;] ''Sukhoi.org.'' Retrieved 11 November 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 19 July 1981, the 200th Independent Attack Squadron was reassigned to [[Shindand Airbase]] in western [[Afghanistan]], becoming the first Su-25 unit deployed to that country. Its main task was to conduct air strikes against mountain military positions and structures controlled by the Afghan rebels.&lt;ref name = &quot;Combatservice&quot;&gt;Gordon and Dawes 2004, pp. 133–49.&lt;/ref&gt;  Another Soviet Su-25 unit was the 368th Attack Aviation Regiment, which was formed on 12 July 1984, at Zjovtnevoye in Ukraine.&lt;ref&gt;Rozendaal, Frank, Rene van Woezik and Tieme Festner. 'Bear tracks in Germany: The Soviet Air Force in the former German Democratic Republic: Part 1.&quot; ''[[Air International]]'', October 1992, p. 210.&lt;/ref&gt; It was soon also moved east to conduct operations over Afghanistan.

Over the course of the [[Soviet war in Afghanistan]], Su-25s launched a total of 139 guided missiles of all types against [[Mujahideen#Mujahideen of Afghanistan|Mujahideen]] positions. On average, each aircraft performed 360 sorties a year, a total considerably higher than that of any other combat aircraft in Afghanistan. By the end of the war, nearly 50 Su-25s were deployed at Afghan airbases, carrying out a total of 60,000 sorties. Between the first deployment in 1981 and the end of the war in 1989, 21–23 aircraft were lost in combat operations, with up to 9 destroyed on the ground while parked.&lt;ref name = &quot;Combatservice&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.airvectors.net/avsu25.html|title=The Sukhoi Su-25 &quot;Frogfoot&quot;|work=airvectors.net|accessdate=27 April 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Iran–Iraq War===
The Su-25 also saw combat during the [[Iran–Iraq War]] of 1980–88. The first Su-25s were commissioned by the [[Iraqi Air Force]] in 1987 and performed approximately 900 combat sorties throughout the war, carrying out the bulk of Iraqi air attack missions. During the most intense combat of the war, Iraqi Su-25s performed up to fifteen sorties per day, each. In one recorded incident, an Iraqi Su-25 was shot down by an Iranian, [[MIM-23 Hawk|Hawk]] [[surface-to-air missile]], but the pilot managed to eject. This was the only confirmed, successful Iranian attack against an Iraqi Su-25. After the war, [[Saddam Hussein]] decorated all of the Iraqi Air Force's Su-25 pilots with the country's highest [[Military awards and decorations|military decoration]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Combatservice&quot;/&gt;

===Gulf War===
[[File:Iraqi Su-25 - Gulf War 1991.jpg|thumb|An Iraqi Su-25 destroyed during Operation Desert Storm]]

During the [[Gulf War]] of 1991, the air superiority of the coalition forces was so great that the majority of Iraqi Su-25s did not even manage to get airborne. On 25 January 1991, seven Iraqi Air Force Su-25s fled from Iraq and landed in Iran.&lt;ref name=&quot;Iran&quot;&gt;{{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071008004044/www.janes.co.uk/defence/air_forces/news/jdw/jdw060913_1_n.shtml |date=8 October 2007 |title=&quot;Iran bolsters Su-25 fleet&quot; }}. ''Jane's Defence Weekly'', 13 September 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

On the evening of 6 February 1991, two [[United States Air Force|US Air Force]] [[McDonnell Douglas F-15 Eagle|F-15C Eagle]] fighters of the 53rd Tactical Fighter Squadron, operating from [[Al Kharj Air Base]] in [[Saudi Arabia]], intercepted a pair of Iraqi [[Mikoyan-Gurevich MiG-21|MiG-21s]] and a pair of Su-25s. All four Iraqi aircraft were shot down, with both Su-25s coming down in the desert not far from the Iraqi border with Iran. This was the Iraqi Su-25s' only air combat of the war.&lt;ref name=&quot;Combatservice&quot;/&gt;

===Abkhazian War===
The Georgian government used Su-25s in 1992–93 against Abkhaz [[separatist]]s during the [[War in Abkhazia (1992–1993)|First Abkhazian War]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,979327,00.html &quot;Siege of Sukhumi.&quot;] ''[[Time Magazine]]'', 4 October 1993.&lt;/ref&gt; A [[Georgian Air Force]] Su-25 was shot down over Nizhnaya [[Eshera]] on July 4, 1993 by an [[SA-14]] MANPADS.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ejection-history.org.uk/PROJECT/YEAR_Pages/1993.htm|title=2005|work=ejection-history.org.uk|accessdate=27 April 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Cooper|first=Tom|title=Georgia and Abkhazia, 1992–1993: the War of Datchas|url=http://www.acig.org/artman/publish/article_282.shtml|publisher=ACIG.org|accessdate=18 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===First Chechen War===
{{Main article|First Chechen War}}

Russian Su-25s were employed during the First Chechen War. Together with other Russian Air Force air assets, they achieved air supremacy for Russian Forces, destroying up to 266 Chechen aircraft on the ground. The Air Force's deployed assets performed around 9,000 air sorties, with around 5,300 being strike sorties during the Chechen campaign between 1994 and 1996. The 4th Russian Air Army had 140 [[Su-17]]Ms, [[Su-24]]s and Su-25s in the war zone supported by an [[Beriev A-50|A-50]] AWACS aircraft. The employed munitions were generally unguided S-5, S-8, and S-24 rockets, as well as FAB-250 and FAB-5000 bombs, while only 2.3% of the strikes used precision-guided [[Kh-25]]ML missiles, KAB-500L and KAB-500KR smart bombs when weather conditions were suitable.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.airpower.maxwell.af.mil/airchronicles/apj/apj97/win97/thomas.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; Russian forces were not able to properly take advantage of the achieved air supremacy due to obsolete air tactics that focused the Air Force on useless tasks in this type of war such as Combat Air Patrols.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sras.org/military_learning_between_the_chechen_wars &quot;Military Learning Between the Chechen Wars.&quot;] ''Sras.org.'' Retrieved: 26 January 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;  The Russian air losses were low since no integrated air defense was fielded by the Chechens.&lt;ref name=&quot;civilresearch.org&quot;&gt;[http://www.civilresearch.org/pdf/7.pdf &quot;Caucasian diamond traffic&amp;nbsp;– Part 2.&quot;] ''civilresearch.org.'' Retrieved: 26 January 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 4 February 1995, a Russian Su-25 was shot down by [[ZSU-23-4]] Shilka antiaircraft fire over Belgatoi Gekhi, five kilometers southeast of Grozny. The pilot, Maj. Nikolay Bairov, ejected but died impacting the ground as his parachute did not deploy on time. Another Su-25 piloted by Lt. Col. Evgeny Derkulsky was damaged by ground fire on the same day, but managed to land at [[Mozdok, Republic of North Ossetia–Alania|Mozdok]] air base, where the aircraft was repaired.{{citation needed|date=April 2014}}  On 5 May 1995, another Russian Su-25 was downed near Serzhen-Yurt by [[.50 BMG|12.7 mm]] fire while on a low-altitude patrol. The pilot, Col. Vladimir Sarabeyev, was killed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mashar.free.fr/mil_avi.htm|title=Frontal and Army Aviation in the Chechen Conflict|publisher=|accessdate=4 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 4 April 1996, another Su-25 fell either to a [[FIM-92 Stinger]] missile or to ZSU-23 Shilka fire while either making a reconnaissance flight or attacking the village of Goiskoye. The pilot, Maj. Alexander Matvienko, ejected and was recovered by a friendly helicopter returning to the airbase in [[Khankala]], Grozny.&lt;ref name=&quot;ejection-history.org.uk&quot;&gt;[http://www.ejection-history.org.uk/Aircraft_by_Type/Su_25.htm &quot;Aircraft by type.&quot;] ''Ejection-history.org.uk.'' Retrieved: 26 January 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;  On 5 May 1996, a two-seat Su-25UB was downed with an [[9K34 Strela-3]] MANPADS near the village of Mairtup while on reconnaissance. Both pilots, Col. Igor Sviryidov and Maj. Oleg Isayev, were killed in the crash. It was the fourth Su-25 and fifth Russian aircraft shot down since the start of the war in December 1994.&lt;ref name=&quot;civilresearch.org&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://articles.chicagotribune.com/1996-05-06/news/9605060132_1_chechen-rebels-zelimkhan-yandarbiyev-grozny &quot;Rebels Down Russian Plane In Chechnya.&quot;] ''Chicago Tribune,'' 6 May 1996. Retrieved: 26 January 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Second Chechen War===
{{Main article|Second Chechen War|List of Russian aircraft losses in the Second Chechen War}}

Russian Air Force Su-25s were extensively used during the [[Second Chechen War]] in particular during the first phase when Russian forces were invading the self-proclaimed [[Chechen Republic of Ichkeria]].&lt;ref&gt;Goebel, Greg. [http://www.vectorsite.net/avsu25.html &quot;The Sukhoi Su-25 'Frogfoot'.&quot;] ''Vectorsite.net.''  Retrieved: 26 January 2012. {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070806145244/http://www.vectorsite.net/avsu25.html |date=6 August 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Up to seven Russian Su-25s were lost,&lt;ref name=&quot;civilresearch.org&quot;/&gt; one to hostile fire: on 4 October 1999, a Su-25 was shot down by a MANPADS during a reconnaissance mission over the village of Tolstoy-Yurt killing its pilot. The wings of the aircraft were put on a pedestal in the central square in Grozny.&lt;ref name=&quot;ejection-history.org.uk&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.greatdreams.com/terrruss.htm &quot;Russia/Chechnya – Terrorism Leads To War.&quot;] ''Greatdreams.com.'' Retrieved: 26 January 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ethiopian-Eritrean War===
{{Main article|Ethiopian-Eritrean War}}

Su-25 attack aircraft were used by the [[Ethiopian Air Force]] to strike [[Eritrea]]n targets. On 15 May 2000, An Ethiopian Su-25 was shot down by an [[Eritrean Air Force]] [[Mikoyan MiG-29|MiG-29]], killing the pilot.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.webcitation.org/5nDhCzUZj &quot;Ethiopia.&quot;] ''acig.org.'' Retrieved: 10 August 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

===2001 insurgency in the Republic of Macedonia===
{{Main article|2001 insurgency in the Republic of Macedonia}}

Su-25s were used by the [[Macedonian Air Force]] during the conflict against Albanian separatists. Beginning on 24 June 2001, the aircraft made multiple attack runs against separatist positions. The most successful operation took place on 10 August 2001, in the village of [[Raduša, Republic of Macedonia|Raduša]], when Su-25s attacked Albanian militants who had ambushed and killed 16 Macedonian soldiers over the previous two days.&lt;ref name=&quot;Operators4&quot;&gt;Gordon and Dawes 2004, pp. 100–102.&lt;/ref&gt;

===War in Darfur===
{{Main article|War in Darfur}}

[[Sudan]] has used Su-25s in attacks on rebel targets and possibly civilians in [[Darfur]].&lt;ref name=&quot;reuters.com&quot;/&gt;

===Ivorian-French clashes===
{{Main article|2004 French–Ivorian clashes|First Ivorian Civil War}}

During the [[First Ivorian Civil War|Ivorian Civil War]], Su-25s were used by government forces to attack rebel targets. On 6 November 2004, at least one Ivorian Sukhoi Su-25 attacked a unit of [[France]]'s Unicorn peacekeeping forces stationed in [[Bouaké]] at 1300, killing nine peacekeepers and a U.S. development worker, and wounding 37 soldiers.&lt;ref name=&quot;english.people.com.cn&quot;&gt;[http://english.people.com.cn/200411/08/eng20041108_163089.html &quot;Nine French soldiers killed in Cote d'Ivoire.&quot;] ''People's Daily Online'', 8 November 2004.&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly afterwards, the French military retaliated by attacking the air base in [[Yamoussoukro]] and destroyed the Ivorian air force, including its two Su-25s.&lt;ref name=&quot;France attacks Ivorian airbase.&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/low/world/africa/3988769.stm &quot;France attacks Ivorian airbase.&quot;] ''BBC News'', 6 November 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/3989127.stm &quot;Ivory Coast seethes after attack.&quot;] ''BBC News'', 7 November 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cooper, Tom with Alexander Mladenov. [http://www.acig.org/artman/publish/article_463.shtml &quot;Cote d'Ivoire, since 2002.&quot;] ''ACIG Journal'', 5 August 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

===2008 Russia–Georgia war===
{{Main article|Russo-Georgian War}}
[[File:Su-25 93 red (4524872585).jpg|thumb|A Russian Su-25]]

In August 2008, Su-25s were used by both Georgia and [[Russia]] during the 2008 Russia–Georgia war. Su-25s of the [[Georgian Air Force]] participated in providing air support for troops during [[Battle of Tskhinvali]] and launched bombing raids on targets in [[South Ossetia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;gewarplanes&quot;&gt;&quot;N. Ossetia president: Georgian planes bomb out humanitarian aid convoy for S. Ossetia.&quot; ''[[Interfax]]'', 8 August 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Russian military Su-25s struck Georgian forces in South Ossetia, and undertook air raids on targets in Georgia.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.reuters.com/article/worldNews/idUSL768040420080808?pageNumber=1&amp;virtualBrandChannel=0 &quot;Fighting rages in Georgian separatist capital.&quot;] ''[[Reuters]]'', 8 August 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; The Russian military officially confirmed the loss of three Su-25 aircraft to the Georgian air defense, though the ''Moscow Defense Brief'' suggests four.&lt;ref name= two_more_lost&gt;[http://www.lenta.ru/news/2008/08/11/planes/ &quot;General staff recognized the loss of two more aircraft.&quot;]  [[Russia|RU]]: ''Lenta'', 11 August 2008. Retrieved 11 August 2008. [https://translate.google.com/translate?u=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.lenta.ru%2Fnews%2F2008%2F08%2F11%2Fplanes%2F&amp;sl=ru&amp;tl=en&amp;hl=&amp;ie=UTF-8 English translation].&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Barabanov, Mikhail. [http://www.webcitation.org/5fm4fGQ5j &quot;The August War between Russia and Georgia.&quot;] ''Moscow Defense Brief.'' Retrieved 11 November 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;  Russia estimates that it destroyed three Georgian Su-25s in the war, none confirmed by Georgia.&lt;ref name=two_more_lost/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Pike, John. [http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/world/georgia/af.htm &quot;Georgia Air Force.&quot;] ''Global security'', 10 May 2009. Retrieved: 25 December 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; The three Russian aircraft were reportedly downed by Georgian [[Buk-M1]] air defence units.&lt;ref name=&quot;rapidreaction&quot;/&gt;  Georgian Su-25s were able to operate at night.&lt;ref name=&quot;rapidreaction&quot;&gt;[http://www.iiss.org/EasysiteWeb/getresource.axd?AssetID=20268&amp;type=full&amp;servicetype=Attachment &quot;Russia's rapid reaction.&quot;] ''International Institute for Strategic Studies.'' Retrieved 11 November 2012. {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090726012355/http://www.iiss.org/EasysiteWeb/getresource.axd?AssetID=20268&amp;type=full&amp;servicetype=Attachment |date=26 July 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;  In early August 2008, Russian Su-25s attacked the [[Tbilisi Aircraft Manufacturing]] plant, where the Su-25 is produced, dropping bombs on the factory's airfield.&lt;ref&gt;Nowak, David (for Associated Press). &quot;Russian air raid targets Tbilisi factory; fighting continues to rage in South Ossetia&quot;.] ''Newser'', 10 August 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Iran===
On 1 November 2012, two Iranian Su-25s fired cannon bursts at a [[United States Air Force|USAF]] [[MQ-1 Predator]] drone 16 nautical miles off the Iranian coast. The Iranian government has claimed that the drone violated its airspace.&lt;ref&gt;Stewart, Phil. [http://www.reuters.com/article/2012/11/08/us-usa-iran-drone-idUSBRE8A71C520121108 &quot;Iranian warplanes fired on U.S. drone over Gulf: Pentagon.&quot;] ''Reuters,'' 5 November 2012. Retrieved 11 November 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aljazeera.com/news/middleeast/2012/11/20121182048162355.html &quot;Iranian fighters 'fired on US drone in Gulf' – Middle East.&quot;] ''Al Jazeera English,'' 8 November 2012. Retrieved 11 November 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Starr, Barbara. [http://security.blogs.cnn.com/2012/11/08/first-on-cnn-iranian-jets-fire-on-u-s-drone/?hpt=hp_t1 &quot;First on CNN: Iranian jets fire on U.S. drone.&quot;] ''CNN,'' 8 November 2012. Retrieved 11 November 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

===2014–2015 conflict in Ukraine===
{{Main article|2014 pro-Russian unrest in Ukraine|List of Ukrainian aircraft losses during the Ukrainian crisis}}
Ukrainian armed forces deployed aircraft over insurgent Eastern regions starting in spring 2014.  On 26 May 2014, Ukrainian Su-25s supported Mi-24s helicopters during a military operation to regain control over the airport in Donetsk, during which the Su-25s fired air to ground rockets.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://theaviationist.com/2014/05/27/ukrainian-offensive-donetsk/|title=The Aviationist » Impressive Videos of the Ukrainian Air Strikes on Donetsk |work=The Aviationist |accessdate=4 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 2 July 2014, one Ukrainian Su-25 crashed due to a technical fault.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://lenta.ru/news/2014/07/02/su25/ |title=В Днепропетровске разбился штурмовик Су-25 |last1= |first1= |last2= |first2= |authorlink= |publisher=[[Lenta.ru]] |date=2 July 2014 |website=www.lenta.ru |accessdate=2 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://interfax.com.ua/news/general/211777.html |title=Штурмовик Су-25 разбился в Днепропетровске из-за неисправности, пилот жив |last1= |first1= |last2= |first2= |authorlink= |publisher=[[Interfax-Ukraine]] |date=2 July 2014 |website=www.lenta.ru |accessdate=2 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.kyivpost.com/content/ukraine/su-25-attack-aircraft-crashes-in-dnipropetrovsk-354358.html |title=Su-25 attack aircraft crashes in Dnipropetrovsk |work=KyivPost |accessdate=4 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 16 July 2014, an Su-25 was shot down, with Ukrainian officials stating that a Russian [[MiG-29]] shot it down using a [[R-27 (air-to-air missile)|R-27T]] missile.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.kyivpost.com/content/ukraine/sbu-releases-more-conversations-implicating-russia-in-shooting-down-malaysia-airlines-flight-video-transcript-2-356778.html|title=SBU releases more conversations implicating Russia in shooting down Malaysia Airlines flight (VIDEO, TRANSCRIPT)|work=KyivPost|accessdate=4 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://uacrisis.org/rechnik-rnbo/|title=Spokesman for National Security and Defense Council Information Center: Malaysian Flight MH-17 was outside the range of Ukraine's surface to air defense systems - Ukraine Crisis Media Center - UACRISIS.ORG|work=uacrisis.org|accessdate=27 April 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Russia denied these allegations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Russia Rejects 'Absurd' Accusation Over Downed Ukrainian Jet |url= http://www.rferl.org/content/ukraine-russia-jet-shot-down-blame/25460575.html |website= rferl.org |publisher=Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty |date= |accessdate=20 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 23 July 2014, two Su-25s were shot down in the [[Donetsk]] region of Ukraine. A spokesperson for the [[National Security and Defense Council of Ukraine]] said the aircraft were shot down by missiles fired from Russia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://abcnews.go.com/International/ukraine-jets-downed-missiles-fired-russia/story?id=24674661|title=Ukraine Says Two Jets Downed By Missiles Fired From Russia|first=Aaron|last=Katersky|work=ABC News|date=July 23, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 29 August 2014, a Ukrainian Su-25 was shot down by pro Russian rebels. The Ukrainian authorities said the downing was due to a Russian missile without clarifying if they mean Russian made or fired by Russian forces. The pilot managed to eject safely. On the same day, pro Russian rebels claimed the downing of up to four Su-25s.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.kyivpost.com/content/ukraine/ukrainian-fighter-jet-shot-down-by-russian-missile-in-donbas-362666.html?flavour=mobile|title=Ukrainian fighter jet shot down by Russian missile in Donbas|publisher=|accessdate=4 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aviation-safety.net/wikibase/wiki.php?id=169382|title=ASN Aircraft accident 29-AUG-2014 Sukhoi Su-25M1 08 YELLOW|publisher=|accessdate=4 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 9 February 2015, the pro-Russian forces indirectly acknowledged, for the first time, with a reference to a Ukrainian media source, their use of Su-25 against Ukrainian forces during the [[Battle of Debaltseve|fighting near Debaltsevo]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://rusvesna.su/news/1423482673|title=МОЛНИЯ: Ополчение применило авиацию под Дебальцево — 2 штурмовика СУ-25 нанесли удар по позициям 40-го батальона, — источник|work=rusvesna.su|accessdate=27 April 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===2014 Northern Iraq offensive===
{{Main article|Northern Iraq offensive (June 2014)}}
On 29 June 2014, it was reported that Iraq claimed to have received the first batch of [[second hand]] Su-25s ordered from Russia in order to fight Sunni rebels of the [[Islamic State in Iraq and the Levant]]. An Iraqi defense ministry source claimed the aircraft would be in service &quot;within three to four days&quot;, despite the fact that the Iraqis require technical help and parts to make them operational, and the fact that the Russian made aircraft are incompatible with the Iraqi Air force's inventory of American made [[AGM-114 Hellfire|Hellfire missiles]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-28077273 &quot;Iraq receives Russian fighter jets to fight rebels&quot;]. ''BBC News'', 29 June 2014. Retrieved 29 June 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aljazeera.com/news/middleeast/2014/06/iraq-takes-delivery-russian-fighter-jets-201462944837214478.html &quot;Iraq takes delivery of Russian fighter jets&quot;]. ''Aljazerra.com''. 29 June 2014. Retrieved 29 June 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;  The [[Islamic Revolutionary Guards Corps Air Force]] delivered seven Su-25s on 1 July 2014, the majority of which were ex-Iraqi aircraft from the Gulf War.&lt;ref name=&quot;'Iranian attack jets deployed' to help Iraq fight Isis&quot;/&gt;
They were quickly pushed into combat, performing air raids as early as the beginning of August 2014 and later expanding their area of operation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.businessinsider.com/who-bombed-isis-militants-on-august-7-2014-8?IR=T|title=Who Bombed ISIS Militants On August 7? – Business Insider|date=8 August 2014|work=Business Insider|accessdate=27 April 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://airheadsfly.com/2014/12/26/iraqi-su-25s-debut-in-combat-isis-in-the-north/|title=Iraqi Su-25s debut in combat ISIS in the North|work=AIRheads↑FLY|accessdate=27 April 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Military intervention in Syria===
{{Main article|Military intervention against ISIL}}
In September 2015, it was reported that at least a dozen Su-25 were deployed by Russia to an airfield near [[Latakia]], Syria, to support the Russian forces there who were taking part in the Syrian offensive against [[ISIL]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.unian.info/world/1130803-pentagon-releases-satellite-images-of-russian-aircraft-in-syria.html |title=Pentagon releases satellite images of Russian aircraft in Syria |work=unian.info |accessdate=21 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;  On 2 October 2015, Russian Su-24M and Su-25 attack aircraft destroyed an ISIL command post in the Idlib province, while Su-34 and Su-25 aircraft eliminated an ISIL fortified bunker in the Hama province.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://sputniknews.com/middleeast/20151002/1027936878/russia-airstrikes-syria.html#ixzz3nWco27EA |title=Russian Jets Destroy ISIL Command Post, Bunker in Syria |date=2 October 2015 |website=sputniknews.com |accessdate=21 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;  By 15 March 2016, with the scaling down of Russian presence in Syria, Russian Su-25s had performed over 1,600 sorties in Syria while dropping 6,000 bombs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://tass.ru/en/defense/862862 |title=TASS: Military &amp; Defense - Russia’s Su-25 warplanes dropped 6,000 bombs during operation in Syria |date= 16 March 2016 |work=TASS |accessdate=22 March 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Variants==

===Su-25===
[[File:Su-25 early.JPEG|thumb|Soviet Su-25 in flight]]

The basic version of the aircraft was produced at Factory 31, at Tbilisi, in the [[Georgian SSR|Soviet Republic of Georgia]]. Between 1978 and 1989, 582 single-seat Su-25s were produced in Georgia, not including aircraft produced under the Su-25K export program. This variant of the aircraft represents the backbone of the Russian Air Force's Su-25 fleet, currently the largest in the world.&lt;ref name=&quot;Variants&quot;&gt;Gordon and Dawes 2004, pp. 42–46.&lt;/ref&gt;  The aircraft experienced a number of accidents in operational service caused by system failures attributed to salvo firing of weapons. In the wake of these incidents, use of its main armament, the 240&amp;nbsp;mm [[S-24 rocket|S-24]] rocket, was prohibited. In its place, the [[FAB-500]] 500&amp;nbsp;kg general-purpose high-explosive bomb became the primary armament.&lt;ref name=&quot;Variants&quot;/&gt;

====Su-25K====
The basic Su-25 model was used as the basis for a commercial export variant, known as the Su-25K ('''''K'''omercheskiy''). This model was also built at Factory 31 in [[Tbilisi]], Georgia. The aircraft differed from the Soviet Air Force version in certain minor details concerning internal equipment. A total of 180 Su-25K aircraft were built between 1984 and 1989.&lt;ref name=&quot;Variants&quot;/&gt;

===Su-25UB===
The Su-25UB [[Trainer (aircraft)|trainer]] ('''''U'''chebno-'''B'''oyevoy'') was drawn up in 1977. The first prototype, called &quot;T-8UB-1&quot;, was rolled out in July 1985 and its maiden flight was carried out at the [[Ulan-Ude]] factory airfield on 12 August of that year.&lt;ref name=&quot;Variants&quot;/&gt; By the end of 1986, 25 Su-25UBs had been produced at Ulan-Ude before the twin-seater completed its State trials and officially cleared for service with the Soviet Air Force.&lt;ref&gt;Gordon and Dawes 2004, p. 54.&lt;/ref&gt;{{clarify|reason=How many produced in total?|date=November 2012}}

It was intended for training and evaluation flights of active-duty pilots, and for training pilot cadets at Soviet Air Force [[flying school]]s. The performance did not differ substantially from that of the single-seater. The navigation, attack, sighting devices and weapons-control systems of the two-seater enabled it to be used for both routine training and weapons-training missions.&lt;ref&gt;Gordon and Dawes 2004, pp. 50–51.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Su-25UBK====
[[File:Bulgarian Air Force Sukhoi Su-25UBK Lofting.jpg|thumb|Bulgarian Su-25UBK on take-off]]

From 1986 to 1989, in parallel with the construction of the main Su-25UB combat training variant, the Ulan-Ude plant produced the so-called &quot;commercial&quot; Su-25UBK, intended for export to countries that bought the Su-25K, and with similar modifications to that aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;Gordon and Dawes 2004, p. 56.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Su-25UBM====
The Su-25UBM is a twin seat variant that can be used as an operational trainer, but also has attack capabilities, and can be used for reconnaissance, target designation and airborne control. Its first flight was on 6 December 2008 and it was certified in December 2010. It will enter operational use with the Russian Air Force later. The variant has a Phazotron NIIR Kopyo radar and Bars-2 equipment on board. Su-25UBM's range is believed to be 1,300&amp;nbsp;km and it may have protection against infra-red guided missiles (IRGM), a minimal requirement on today's battle fields where IRGMs proliferate.&lt;ref&gt;Karnozov, Vladimir. [http://www.flightglobal.com/articles/2010/12/20/351105/sukhois-su-25ubm-completes-state-acceptance-trials.html &quot;Sukhoi's Su-25UBM completes state acceptance trials.&quot;] ''flightglobal.com,'' 20 December 2010. Retrieved 30 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

====Su-25UTG====
[[File:Sukhoi Su-25UTG in 2010.jpg|thumb|Su-25UTG carrier-based trainer aircraft at Novofedorovka airbase]]
The Su-25UTG ('''''U'''chebno-'''T'''renirovochnyy s '''G'''akom'') is a variant of the Su-25UB designed to train pilots in takeoff and landing on a land-based simulated carrier deck, with a sloping [[ski-jump]] section and [[Tailhook|arrester wire]]s. The first one flew in September 1988, and approximately 10 were produced.&lt;ref&gt;Gordon and Dawes 2004, p. 59.&lt;/ref&gt;  About half remained in Russian service after 1991; they were used on Russia's sole [[aircraft carrier]], the {{Ship|Russian aircraft carrier|Admiral Kuznetsov||2}}. This small number of aircraft were insufficient to meet the training needs of Russia's carrier air group, so a number of Su-25UBs were converted into Su-25UTGs. These aircraft being distinguished by the alternative designation ''Su-25UBP'' ('''''U'''chebno-'''B'''oyevoy '''P'''alubny'') —the adjective ''palubnyy'' meaning &quot;deck&quot;, indicating that these aircraft have a naval function.&lt;ref name=&quot;Variants4&quot; /&gt;  Approximately 10 of these aircraft are currently operational in the [[Russian Navy]] as part of the 279th Naval Aviation Regiment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Warfare.ru&quot;&gt;[http://www.warfare.ru/?linkid=1611&amp;catid=256 &quot;Russian Military Analysis on Su-25&quot;.] ''warfare.ru.'' Retrieved: 18 June 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Su-25BM===
The Su-25BM ('''''B'''uksirovshchik '''M'''isheney'') is a [[target-towing]] variant of the Su-25 whose development began in 1986. The prototype, designated T-8BM1, successfully flew for the first time on 22 March 1990, at Tbilisi. After completion of the test phase, the aircraft was put into production.&lt;ref name=&quot;Variants4&quot;&gt;Gordon and Dawes 2004, pp. 60–71.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Su-25BM target-tower was designed to provide towed target facilities for training ground forces and naval personnel in ground-to-air or naval surface-to-air missile systems. It is powered by an R-195 engine and equipped with an [[RSDN-10]] long-range [[navigation system]], an analogue of the Western [[LORAN]] system.&lt;ref name=&quot;Variants4&quot;/&gt;

===Su-25T===
The Su-25T ('''''T'''ankovy'') is a dedicated [[antitank]] version, which has been combat-tested with notable success in [[Chechnya]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Variants7&quot;/&gt; The design of the aircraft is similar to the Su-25UB ( unification of 85%). The variant was converted to one-seater, with the rear seat replaced by additional avionics.&lt;ref name=Shock&gt;Bangash 2008, p. 270.&lt;/ref&gt;  It has all-weather and night attack capability. In addition to the full arsenal of weapons of the standard Su-25, the Su-25T can employ the KAB-500Kr [[precision-guided munition|TV-guided]] bomb and the semi-active [[laser-guided]] Kh-25ML.&lt;ref name=&quot;Variants7&quot; /&gt;  Its enlarged nosecone houses the ''Shkval'' optical TV and aiming system with the ''Prichal'' laser rangefinder and target designator. It can also carry ''[[Vikhr]]'' laser-guided, tube-launched missiles, which is its main antitank armament. For night operations, the low-light TV ''Merkuriy'' pod system can be carried under the fuselage. Three Su-25Ts prototypes were built in 1983–86 and 8 production aircraft were built in 1990.&lt;ref name=Donald&gt;Donald 2004, pp. 234–237.&lt;/ref&gt; With the introduction of a definitive Russian Air Force Su-25 upgrade programme, in the form of '''''S'''troyevoy '''M'''odernizirovannyi'', the Su-25T programme was officially canceled in 2000.&lt;ref name=Workhorse/&gt;

===Su-25TM (Su-39)===
[[File:Su-25TM.jpg|thumb|Russian Su-25TM has been built in small numbers. Carries (from tip to fuselage) [[Vympel R-73|R-73]], [[R-77]], 8×[[Vikhr]], [[Kh-29T]], [[Kh-58]]. White dome of ''Kopyo'' radar container is seen below, while two ''Omul'' ECM pods lie beside the aircraft.]]

A second-generation Su-25T, the ''Su-25TM'' (also designated ''Su-39''), has been developed with improved navigation and attack systems, and better survivability. While retaining the built-in ''Shkval'' of Su-25T, it may carry ''Kopyo'' (rus. &quot;Spear&quot;) radar in the container under fuselage, which is used for engaging air targets (with RVV-AE/R-77 missiles) as well as ships (with Kh-31 and Kh-35 antiship missiles). The Russian Air Force has received 8 aircraft as of 2008.&lt;ref name=Shock /&gt;  Some of the improved avionics systems designed for T and TM variants have been included in the ''Su-25SM'', an interim upgrade of the operational Russian Air Force Su-25, for improved survivability and combat capability.&lt;ref name=&quot;Variants7&quot;&gt;Gordon and Dawes 2004, pp. 111–126.&lt;/ref&gt; The Su-25TM, as an all-inclusive upgrade programme has been replaced with the &quot;affordable&quot; Su-25SM programme.&lt;ref name=Workhorse/&gt;

===Su-25SM===
[[File:Sukhoi Su-25SM (1).jpg|thumb|A Sukhoi Su-25SM at the Celebration of the 100th anniversary of Russian Air Force]]

The Su-25SM (''Stroyevoy Modernizirovannyi'') is an &quot;affordable&quot; upgrade programme for the Su-25, conceived by the [[Russian Air Force]] in 2000. The programme stems from the attempted Su-25T and Su-25TM upgrades, which were evaluated and labeled as over-sophisticated and expensive. The SM upgrade incorporates avionics enhancements and airframe refurbishment to extend the Frogfoot's service life by up to 500 flight hours or 5 years.&lt;ref name=Workhorse&gt;{{cite journal|last=Mladenov|first=Alexander|title=Armoured Workhorse|journal=Air Forces Monthly|date=January 2013|issue=298|pages=68–74|accessdate=16 January 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Su-25SM's all-new PRnK-25SM &quot;Bars&quot; navigation/attack suite is built around the BTsVM-90 digital computer system, originally planned for the Su-25TM upgrade programme. Navigation and attack precision provided by the new suite is three times better of the baseline Su-25 and is reported to be within {{convert|15|m|ft|abbr=on}} using satellite correction and {{convert|200|m|ft|abbr=on}} without it.&lt;ref name=Workhorse/&gt;

A new KA1-1-01 Head-Up Display (HUD) was added providing, among other things, double the field of view of the original ASP-17BTs-8 electro-optical sight. Other systems and components incorporated during the upgrade include a Multi-Function Display (MFD), RSBN-85 Short Range Aid to Navigation (SHORAN), ARK-35-1 Automatic Direction Finder (ADF), A-737-01 GPS/GLONASS Receiver, Karat-B-25 Flight Data Recorder (FDR), Berkut-1 Video Recording System (VRS), Banker-2 UHF/VHF communication radio, SO-96 Transponder and a L150 &quot;Pastel&quot; Radar Warning Receiver (RWR).&lt;ref name=Workhorse/&gt;

The R-95Sh engines have been overhauled and modified with an anti-surge system installed. The system is designed to improve the resistance of the engine to ingested powders and gases during gun and rocket salvo firing.&lt;ref name=Workhorse/&gt;

The combination of reconditioned and new equipment, with increased automation and self-test capability has allowed for a reduction of pre- and post-flight maintenance by some 25 to 30%. Overall weight savings are around {{convert|300|kg|lb|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name=Workhorse/&gt;

Su-25SM weapon suite has been expanded with the addition of the [[Vympel R-73]] highly agile air-to-air missile (albeit without helmet mounted cuing and only the traditional longitudinal seeker mode) and the [[S-13 rocket|S-13T]] 130&amp;nbsp;mm rockets (carried in five-round B-13 pods) with blast-fragmentation and armour-piercing warheads. Further, the [[Kh-25]]ML and [[Kh-29]]L Weapon Employment Profiles have been significantly improved, permitting some complex missile launch scenarios to be executed, such as: firing two consecutive missiles on two different targets in a single attack pass. The [[GSh-30-2]] cannon (250-round magazine) has received three new reduced rate-of-fire modes: 750, 375 and 188 Rounds per Minute. The Su-25SM was also given new BD3-25 under-wing pylons.&lt;ref name=Workhorse/&gt;

The eventual procurement programme is expected to include between 100 and 130 kits, covering 60 to 70 percent of the Russian Air Force active single-seat fleet, as operated in the early 2000s.&lt;ref name=Workhorse/&gt;  On 21 February 2012, Air Force spokesman Col. Vladimir Drik said that Russia will continue to upgrade its Su-25 attack aircraft to Su-25SM version, which has a significantly better survivability and combat effectiveness. The Russian Air Force currently had over 30 Su-25SMs in service and plans to modernize about 80 Su-25s by 2020, Drik said.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/world/russia/su-25sm.htm|title=Su-25SM FROGFOOT (SUKHOI)|author=John Pike|work=globalsecurity.org|accessdate=27 April 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Russia_to_field&gt;[http://en.rian.ru/mlitary_news/20120517/173508923.html &quot;Russia to Field New Ground Attack Jet.&quot;] ''RIA Novosti.''  Retrieved: 17 June 2012. {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120520105340/http://en.rian.ru/mlitary_news/20120517/173508923.html |date=20 May 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; By March 2013, over 60 aircraft are to be upgraded.&lt;ref name=Russia_to_field/&gt;&lt;ref name=Arms-TASS-5-2012&gt;[http://www.armstass.su/?page=article&amp;aid=106907&amp;cid=25 {{icon ru}}] Retrieved: 11 November 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; In February 2013, ten new Su-25SMs were delivered to the Air Force southern base,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ria.ru/arms/20130215/923095137.html |title=Около 10 новейших самолетов Су-25СМ3 поступили на авиабазу в ЮВО &amp;#124; РИА Новости |publisher=Ria.ru |date=15 February 2013 |accessdate=5 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ria.ru/arms/20130215/923095137.html |title=Около 10 новейших самолетов Су-25СМ3 поступили на авиабазу в ЮВО &amp;#124; РИА Новости |publisher=Ria.ru |date=15 February 2013 |accessdate=12 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; where operational training is being conducted.&lt;ref name=&quot;autogenerated1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ria.ru/defense_safety/20130304/925693163.html |title=Летчики ЮВО осваивают новейшие Су-25СМ3 в ночное время &amp;#124; РИА Новости |publisher=Ria.ru |date= |accessdate=5 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Since early 2014, the Guards Aviation Division Attack Aviation Regiment of the Southern Military District in the Krasnodar region received 16 advanced Su-25SMs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://vpk-news.ru/news/22673|title=Авиаполк ЮВО получил 16 штурмовиков Су-25СМ3 с начала года – Еженедельник &quot;Военно-промышленный курьер&quot;|work=vpk-news.ru|accessdate=27 April 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Su-25KM===
The Su-25KM ('''''K'''ommercheskiy '''M'''odernizirovannyy''), nicknamed &quot;Scorpion&quot;, is an Su-25 upgrade programme announced in early 2001 by the original manufacturer, [[Tbilisi Aircraft Manufacturing]] in Georgia, in partnership with [[Elbit Systems]] of [[Israel]]. The prototype aircraft made its maiden flight on 18 April 2001 at Tbilisi in full [[Georgian Air Force]] markings.&lt;ref name=&quot;Variants0&quot;&gt;Gordon and Dawes 2004, pp. 103–132.&lt;/ref&gt;

The aircraft uses a standard Su-25 airframe, enhanced with advanced avionics including a [[glass cockpit]], digital [[map]] generator, [[head-mounted display|helmet-mounted display]], computerised weapons system, complete mission pre-plan capability, and fully redundant backup modes. Performance enhancements include a highly accurate navigation system, pinpoint weapon delivery systems, all-weather and day/night performance, [[NATO]] compatibility, state-of-the art safety and survivability features, and advanced onboard debriefing capabilities complying with international requirements.&lt;ref name=&quot;Variants0&quot;/&gt;  It has the ability to use Mark 82 and Mark 83 laser-guided bombs and air-to-air missiles, the short-range [[Vympel R-73]].&lt;ref&gt;{{YouTube|ZAszf4XPTFo|&quot;Su-25KM Scorpion (It is made in Georgia).&quot;}} Retrieved: 30 June 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Su-28===
[[File:Su-25UT Frogfoot 02.jpg|thumb|Sukhoi Su-28 non-combat jet trainer]]

The [[Sukhoi Su-28]] (also designated ''Su-25UT'' – '''''U'''chebno-'''T'''renirovochnyy'') is an advanced basic jet trainer, built on the basis of the Su-25UB as a private initiative by the Sukhoi Design Bureau. The Su-28 is a light aircraft designed to replace the Czechoslovak [[Aero L-39 Albatros]]. Unlike the basic Su-25UB, it lacks a weapons-control system, built-in cannon, weapons hardpoints, and engine armour.&lt;ref&gt;Gordon and Dawes 2004, pp. 56–57.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Other ===
* '''Su-25R''' ('''''R'''azvedchik'') – a tactical [[reconnaissance]] variant designed in 1978, but never built.&lt;ref name=&quot;Variants6&quot;&gt;Gordon and Dawes 2004, pp. 70–72.&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Su-25U3''' ('''''U'''chebnyy '''3'''-myestny'') – also known as the &quot;Russian Troika&quot;, was a three-seat basic trainer aircraft. The project was suspended in 1991 due to lack of funding.&lt;ref name=&quot;Variants6&quot;/&gt;
* '''Su-25U''' ('''''U'''chebnyy'') – a trainer variant of Su-25s produced in Georgia between 1996 and 1998. Three aircraft were built in total, all for the Georgian Air Force.&lt;ref name=&quot;Variants6&quot;/&gt;
* '''Su-25M1/Su-25UBM1''' – Su-25 and Su-25UB exemplars slightly modernized by [[Ukrainian Air Force]], at least nine modernized (eight single-seat and one two-seat). Upgrades include a new navigation system, enhanced survivability, more accurate weapon delivery and other minor changes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ukrainian Air Force&quot;&gt;[http://www.ukrinform.ua/eng/order/?id=183070 &quot;Su-25.&quot;] ''ukrinform.ua.'' Retrieved: 3 August 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
* '''Ge-31''' is an ongoing Georgian program of [[Tbilisi Aircraft Manufacturing]] aiming at producing a renewed version of Su-25 without Russian components and parts.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.kyivpost.com/content/russia-and-former-soviet-union/georgia-starts-assembling-reconfigured-su-25-attack-aircraft-without-russian-components-395461.html|title=Georgia starts assembling reconfigured Su-25 attack aircraft without Russian components|work=KyivPost|accessdate=7 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Operators==
[[File:World operators of the Su-25.png|thumb|upright=1.7|Military operators of the Su-25: {{legend|#1a00ff|Current operator}} {{legend|#ed0017|Former operator}}]]
[[File:Belarus Air Force Sukhoi Su-25 Pichugin-1.jpg|thumb|Belarusian Air Force Su-25]]
[[File:Bulgarian Su-25K Frogfoot.jpg|thumb|[[Bulgarian Air Force]] Su-25 in [[Bezmer Air Base]] 2013]]
[[File:Chad Air Force Sukhoi Su-25 at N'djamena Airport (2).jpeg|thumb|Chad Air Force Su-25 at N'djamena Airport]]
[[File:Sukhoi Su-25K at RIAT-92.jpg|thumb|Czechoslovak Air Force Sukhoi Su-25K at Royal International Air Tattoo 1992]]
[[File:Kazakhstan Air Force Sukhoi Su-25 Pichugin-1.jpg|thumb|Kazakhstan Air Force Su-25]]
[[File:Macedonian Air Force Sukhoi Su-24K Lofting-1.jpg|thumb|Macedonian Air Force Sukhoi Su-25]]
[[File:Peruvian Air Force Sukhoi Su-25 SDLP-1.jpg|thumb|Peruvian Air Force Su-25]]
[[File:Sukhoi Su-25SM (2).jpg|thumb|Russian Air Force Su-25SM]]
[[File:Sudanese Air Force Sukhoi Su-25 Onyshchenko-1.jpg|thumb|Sudanese Air Force Sukhoi Su-25s]]
[[File:Su-25 Turmenistan AF (7105317801).jpg|thumb|Turkmenistan Su-25UB]]
[[File:Ukrainian Air Force Su-25UB with two MiG-29s (9-13) in background.jpg|thumb|Ukrainian Su-25UB]]

;{{ANG}}: [[National Air Force of Angola|People's Air and Air Defence Force of Angola]]. An agreement was reached at the beginning of 1988 between the Soviet Union and Angola that arranged for the delivery of a squadron of Su-25s. The Angolan export agreement comprised 12 single-seat Su-25Ks and two Su-25UBKs trainers. Later, these aircraft were augmented by further deliveries comprising at least three two-seater aircraft.&lt;ref name=&quot;Operators3&quot;/&gt;

;{{ARM}}: [[Armenian Air Force]]. Following the break-up of the Soviet Union, Armenia had no Su-25s in its inventory, but following the start of the [[Nagorno-Karabakh War|conflict in Nagorno-Karabakh]] in 1991–92, the newly independent [[Republic of Armenia]] unofficially acquired a small number of aircraft, including one new Su-25K that was stolen from the Georgian Air Force on 15 November 1993 by Georgian Captain Sergey Zhitnikov and flown to Armenia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://geo-army.ge/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=138&amp;Itemid=8&amp;lang=en |title=History of the Air Forces of Georgia |publisher=Geo-army.ge |date= |accessdate=12 September 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; It operates 5 Su-25, 9 Su-25K and 1 Su-25UBK as of January 2009.&lt;ref name=&quot;awst_20090126&quot;&gt;&quot;World Military Aircraft Inventory&quot;. ''Aerospace Source Book 2009''. [[Aviation Week &amp; Space Technology]], 26 January 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

;{{AZE}}: [[Azerbaijan Air Force]]. Like Armenia, Azerbaijan did not inherit any Su-25s after the collapse of the USSR, but a single aircraft was obtained in April 1992 as a consequence of a pilot defecting from the Russian Air Force base at Sital-Chai. Following the incident, Azerbaijan acquired at least five Su-25s through unofficial channels, and one more aircraft has been obtained as the result of yet another defection, this time from the Georgian Air Force. Other aircraft are believed to have been acquired later, as a 2001 inventory of Azerbaijan aircraft revealed that the Azerbaijan Air Force had three of the type in its inventory, after the reported loss of four Su-25s in combat operations relating to the disputed [[Nagorno-Karabakh]] region.&lt;ref name=&quot;Operators3&quot;&gt;Gordon and Dawes 2004, pp. 89–92.&lt;/ref&gt;

;{{BLR}}: [[Belarus Air Force]]. After the break-up of the Soviet Union, Belarus was the second member state of the [[Commonwealth of Independent States|CIS]], after Russia, to have a significant number of Su-25s. Seventy Su-25s and six Su-25UBs are reported to be operational and are mostly concentrated at Lida air base by 2004.&lt;ref name=&quot;Operators2&quot;/&gt;

;{{BUL}}: [[Bulgarian Air Force]]. Bulgaria was the second [[Warsaw Pact]] country to obtain the Su-25, acquiring its first examples of both Su-25K and the Su-25UBK in 1985. The aircraft were intended to replace the obsolete [[Mikoyan-Gurevich MiG-17|MiG-17F ''Fresco-C'']] which had been the backbone of the Bulgarian Air Force fighter-bomber fleet for many years. Twenty Su-25Ks and three Su-25UBKs were commissioned and were operational at [[Bezmer Air Base]] by 2004.&lt;ref name=&quot;Operators2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pan.bg/view_article-1-21602-Vyzstanovqvat-letatelnata-godnost-na-Su-25-i-Bel-206.html |title=Restore the airworthiness of the Su-25 and Bell-206|accessdate=19 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://pan.bg/view_article-4-22066-FOTOOKO-ZAPOChNA-PREBAZIRANETO-NA-BEZMERCI.html |title=Repair airbase Bezmer. Su25 in airbase Graf Ignatievo to 2015 when Su25 return in airbase Bezmer.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://airforce.mod.bg/bg/?page_id=178|title= Weapons and military equipment}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;{{CHA}}: [[Chadian Air Force]] acquired a total of six aircraft (4 Su-25 and 2 Su-25UB) from Ukraine in 2008.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.milaviapress.com/orbat/chad/index.php &quot;Chadian Air Force/&quot;]''MilAvia Press.com.'' Retrieved: 26 January 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;

;{{COD}}: [[Air Force of the Democratic Republic of the Congo]]. In late 1999, the [[Tbilisi]] Aerospace Manufacturing plant signed a contract with the [[Democratic Republic of Congo]] for the delivery of 10 Su-25Ks to the [[Air Force of the Democratic Republic of the Congo|Force Aerienne Congolaise]]. The deal was reported to be valued at 6 million [[US Dollars]], and the first four aircraft were delivered on board an [[An-124]] in November 1999. The remaining six aircraft were delivered in January 2000.&lt;ref name=&quot;Operators2&quot; /&gt; One aircraft crashed in December 2006 during a routine flight, while another one crashed on 30 June 2007, during a Congolese independence day display.&lt;ref name=&quot;Congo&quot;&gt;{{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081209011026/http://africa.reuters.com/wire/news/usnL30209861.html |date=9 December 2008 |title=&quot;Congolese fighter jet crashes during display.&quot; }} ''Reuters'', 30 June 2007. Retrieved: 17 June 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

;{{CZS}}: [[Czechoslovakian Air Force]]. Passed aircraft on to successor states, in the ratio of 2:1 in favour of the [[Czech Republic]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Operators2&quot;/&gt;

;{{CZE}}: [[Czech Air Force]]. After the dissolution of [[Czechoslovakia]], the Czech Republic acquired twenty-four Su-25Ks and one Su-25UBK. In December 2000, the Czech Su-25s were retired from service and placed in storage at [[Přerov]] air base.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scramble.nl/cz.htm &quot;Czech Su-25s.&quot;], ''Scramble (magazine)''. Retrieved 26 July 2011. {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070210100345/http://www.scramble.nl/cz.htm |date=10 February 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

;{{flag|Equatorial Guinea}}: In 2005, 4 Su 25s including 2 Su-25UB combat trainers were delivered to the Equatorial Guinea Air Corps. The current status of the aircraft is unknown.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.scramble.nl/gq.htm Equatorial Guinea National Guard]&quot;. ''Scramble.nl''. Retrieved: 3 January 2009. {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081021053453/http://www.scramble.nl/gq.htm |date=21 October 2008 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

;{{ETH}}: [[Ethiopian Air Force]]. A pair of Su-25Ts and two Su-25UBK combat trainers were delivered to [[Ethiopia]] in the first quarter of 2000. The twin-seaters were withdrawn from Russian Air Force service and modified in accordance to a special request by the Ethiopian Air Force. Since acquiring the aircraft, the Ethiopians have used them in combat operations against [[Eritrea]]n insurgent groups.&lt;ref name=&quot;Operators2&quot;&gt;Gordon and Dawes 2004, pp. 93–96.&lt;/ref&gt;

;{{GEO}}: [[Georgian Air Force]]. Georgia, home to [[Tbilisi Aircraft Manufacturing]] which produced scores of single-seat Su-25s during the Soviet era, was left with virtually no aircraft following the break-up of the Soviet Union. Only a small number of single-seat Su-25s were actually brought into the inventory of the newly formed Georgian Air Force (now army air force), these aircraft having been left in the factory at the time of Georgian independence. Georgia had nine Su-25s of different variants, with eight of them being Su-25KM &quot;''Scorpion''&quot;s (an upgraded variants of the Su-25 in collaboration with [[Israel]]) as of 2004.&lt;ref&gt;Gordon and Dawes 2004, p. 97.&lt;/ref&gt;
;{{flag|Gambia}}: [[Military of The Gambia#Aircraft inventory|Gambian Army]] – operates one Su-25 as of 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;awst_20070115&quot;&gt;&quot;World Military Aircraft Inventory&quot;, ''2007 Aerospace Source Book''. [[Aviation Week &amp; Space Technology]], 15 January 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;FI_AirForces_2008&quot;/&gt;

;{{IRN}}: [[Islamic Revolutionary Guards Corps Air Force]]. On 21 January 1991, seven Iraqi Su-25s were flown to Iran in an effort to find a temporary safe haven from [[Operation Desert Storm]] attacks on major Iraqi airfields. These aircraft were considered by Iran to be a gift from its former adversary, and were seized by the Iranian military. However, as a result of a lack of spare parts, documentation, and pilot training, these aircraft were not flown by the Islamic Republic of Iran Air Force. Iran has added at least six new examples to its inventory and has since likely restored ex-Iraqi Su-25s to flight status as well.&lt;ref name=&quot;Iran&quot;/&gt; Reports indicate that some of the [[Islamic Revolutionary Guards Corps Air Force|IRGCAF]] aircraft have been transferred back to Iraq in July 2014, to increase the latter's [[Close air support|CAS]] and [[Counter-insurgency aircraft|COIN]] capabilities.&lt;ref name=&quot;'Iranian attack jets deployed' to help Iraq fight Isis&quot;&gt;{{citation|title = 'Iranian attack jets deployed' to help Iraq fight Isis|url = http://www.bbc.com/news/world-middle-east-28125687|publisher = BBC News|author = Jonathan Marcus|date = 2 Jul 2014|accessdate = 2 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;{{IRQ}}: [[Iraqi Air Force]]. During the course of the early phase of the Iran–Iraq War, Iraq approached the Soviet Union with a request to purchase a wide variety of military equipment. As a result, Iraq became the first, non-[[Warsaw Pact]] country to obtain the Su-25K and Su-25UBK combat trainer. It is believed that Iraq received a total of 73 examples, of which four were Su-25UBKs. In January 1998, the Iraqi Air Force still possessed 12 Su-25s, and at least three Su-25Ks were seen in a demonstration over [[Baghdad]] in December 2002. However, the remaining Su-25s were phased out immediately after the [[2003 Invasion of Iraq]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Operators2&quot;/&gt; In 2014, the IQAF signed a deal with Russia and Belarus for the purchase of more examples, with the first five arriving on 28 June 2014.&lt;ref name=&quot;Russian fighter jets arrive in Iraq for fight against rebels&quot;&gt;{{citation|title = Russian fighter jets arrive in Iraq for fight against rebels|url = http://www.haaretz.com/news/middle-east/1.601852|publisher = Haaretz|date = 29 Jun 2014|accessdate = 29 Jun 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Reports indicate that a further seven were delivered from Iran on 1 July 2014, all of which were ex-Iraqi examples from the 1991 Gulf War.&lt;ref name=&quot;'Iranian attack jets deployed' to help Iraq fight Isis&quot;/&gt;

;{{CIV}}: [[Air Force of Ivory Coast]]. In November 2004, nine French soldiers were killed and 23 wounded when two Ivorian Su-25s bombed French positions in [[Bouaké]].&lt;ref name=&quot;english.people.com.cn&quot;/&gt; As a result, [[Military of France|French soldiers]] destroyed the Su-25s on the ground at [[Yamoussoukro]] air base.&lt;ref name=&quot;France attacks Ivorian airbase.&quot;/&gt;

;{{KAZ}}: [[Military of Kazakhstan|Kazakh Air Force]] – received 12 single-seat Su-25s and two Su-25UB trainers in December 1995 as compensatory payment for the return of the [[Tu-95|Tu-95MS &quot;''Bear-H''&quot;]] strategic bombers which had been rapidly flown out of the republic at the time of the collapse of the USSR. The Kazakh Su-25s are located at [[Chimkent]] air base in the south of the country.&lt;ref name=&quot;Operators2&quot;/&gt;

;{{MKD}}: [[Macedonian Air Force]]. The Republic of Macedonia purchased three single-seat Su-25s and one Su-25UB following [[2001 Macedonia conflict|incursions and attacks]] by [[Albanians|Albanian]] insurgents. The aircraft were supplied by Ukrainian authorities after having been withdrawn from Ukrainian Air Force service.&lt;ref&gt;Gordon and Dawes 2004, p. 99.&lt;/ref&gt; The aircraft were retired in 2004, and reportedly sold to Georgia in 2005.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aeroflight.co.uk/waf/fyrm/af/types/su25.htm &quot;Macedonian Air Force, Aircraft Types, Su-25.&quot;] ''aeroflight.co.uk,'' 15 September 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; The sale never happened and they were left near the Skopje airport.{{Citation needed|date=June 2015}}

;{{NIG}}: [[Niger Air Force]] – operated two SU-25s in 2014.&lt;ref&gt;[http://insct.syr.edu/wp-content/uploads/2014/05/Niger_Risk_Assessment_Final.pdf Niger Risk Assessment 2014]&lt;/ref&gt;

;{{PRK}}: [[North Korean Air Force]] – North Korea was the first [[Asia|Asian country]] to obtain the Su-25. In the 1950s, the [[North Korean Air Force]] had accumulated experience operating the Su-25's piston-engined predecessor, the [[Ilyushin Il-10|Ilyushin Il-10 &quot;''Beast''&quot;]]. In the period from the end of 1987 until 1989, the DPRK acquired a total of 32 single-seat Su-25Ks and four Su-25UBKs. The aircraft are based at [[Sunchon Airport]] (20&amp;nbsp;km from [[Pyongyang]]), which features heavily fortified natural hangars equipped with blast-proof doors capable of protecting the aircraft from conventional and [[nuclear explosion]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Operators4&quot;/&gt;

;{{PER}}: [[Peruvian Air Force]]. Peru received 18 Su-25s in late 1998 from Belarus, which refurbished them prior to delivery. The shipment comprised 10 single-seat and eight dual-seat Su-25UB trainers. The aircraft were all built just before the collapse of the Soviet Union and thus represented the final versions of the Soviet Su-25. It is believed that between 1998 and December 2005, at least 25 light aircraft transporting [[cocaine]] had been shot down by the Peruvian Su-25s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Operators4&quot;/&gt; As of February 2013, 18 Su-25s are in service, with only 4 aircraft operational.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/spain-offers-eurofighters-to-peru-381843/ Spain offers Eurofighters to Peru] – Flightglobal.com, 4 February 2013&lt;/ref&gt;

;{{RUS}}: [[Russian Air Force]] – Russia possesses a reduced fleet of Su-25s, which are operated by Attack Regiments. The major variants used are the single-seat Su-25, the twin-seat Su-25UB, and the Su-25BM target-towing version. In addition, the Russian Air Force received a small number of the Su-25T anti-tank variant, which have been tested under combat conditions in [[Chechnya]]. Overall, 286 Su-25s are in service with the Russian Air Force as of 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;Warfare.ru&quot;/&gt; A modernisation programme of single-seat Su-25s to the Su-25SM variant is underway.&lt;ref name=&quot;Operators4&quot;/&gt; The first, modernised Su-25SM was delivered in August 2001.&lt;ref name=&quot;AFM&quot;/&gt; By March 2013, over 60 Su-25SMs were scheduled to be delivered.{{citation needed|date=October 2015}} The modernisation programme is to conclude in 2020 with over 80 examples upgraded.&lt;ref name=Russia_to_field/&gt;
: [[Russian Naval Aviation]] – the Russian Navy operates an adapted version of the Su-25UB two-seat trainer, the Su-25UTG. This is a [[aircraft carrier|carrier]] capable version used to carrier out full deck-landing training aboard the Navy's aircraft carrier.

;{{SVK}}: The [[Slovak Air Force]] received 12 Su-25Ks and one Su-25UBK following the dissolution of Czechoslovakia. The aircraft were based at the Slovak 33rd Air Base in Malacky-Kuchyna. They were sold to Armenia.&lt;ref name=&quot;Operators2&quot;/&gt;

;{{USSR}}: [[Soviet Air Force]]. Passed aircraft on to successor states.

;{{SUD}}: [[Sudanese Air Force]] – had one Su-25 in service as of November 2008.&lt;ref name=&quot;FI_AirForces_2008&quot;&gt;[http://www.flightglobal.com/assets/getasset.aspx?ItemID=26061 &quot;Directory: World Air Forces&quot;]. ''[[Flight International]]'', 11–17 November 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;  Since 2008 it has reportedly obtained 15 aircraft from Belarus.&lt;ref name=&quot;reuters.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.reuters.com/article/idUSTRE69L4ON20101022 &quot;Disputed attack jets seen by U.N. envoys in Darfur.&quot;] ''reuters.com.''&lt;/ref&gt;

;{{TKM}}: [[Military of Turkmenistan|Turkmenistan Air Force]] – Following the downfall of the Soviet Union, the newly independent Republic of Turkmenistan was given 46 Su-25s which had been disassembled for storage in Turkmenistan at that time. In accordance with an agreement between Georgia and Turkmenistan in 1999, the Tbilisi Aerospace Manufacturing corporation refurbished 45 of these aircraft for use by the [[Military of Turkmenistan|Turkmenistan Air Force]] as payment for the delivery of [[natural gas]]. The refurbished aircraft were relocated at Ak-Tepe air base, and a total of 18 operational Su-25s are known to be based there by 2004.&lt;ref name=&quot;Operators4&quot;/&gt;

;{{UKR}}: [[Ukrainian Air Force]]. Ukraine obtained 92 Su-25s of differing variants following the country's independence in the wake of the break-up of the USSR. Currently, the Ukrainian Air Force operates approximately 60 Su-25, Su-25UBs, and Su-25UTGs, which are operated by the 299th Independent Assault Regiment (299 OShAP) based at [[Kulbakino]], [[Mykolaiv Oblast]], and at the 456th Assault Regiment (456 ShAP) at [[Chortkiv]]. Up to 30 Su-25s are reportedly stored at the 4070th Reserve Base. Evidently, three Su-25s sold to Macedonia came from this reserve pool.&lt;ref name=&quot;Operators4&quot;/&gt; Also, Ukrainian Air Force modernized two types of the Su-25, one of them is ''Su-25M1'' and ''Su-25UBM1''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ukrainian Air Force&quot;/&gt;
*[[Ukrainian Naval Aviation]]. Former operator.

;{{UZB}}: Until 1990, a [[Soviet Air Force]] pilot training centre equipped with around 20 Su-25, Su-25UB, and Su-25BM variants was located at [[Chirchik]] air base in Uzbekistan. In 1991, a small number of Su-25s were also located at [[Dzhizak]] air base, but after 1991, all Su-25s in Uzbekistan were concentrated at Chirchik, operated by the 59th Fighter-Bomber Aviation Regiment (59 APIB) of the Soviet Air Force. After the collapse of the Soviet Union, all the Su-25s on the territory of the now independent republic became the property of the new government.&lt;ref name=&quot;Operators4&quot;/&gt;

==Notable accidents==
{{see also|Lists of accidents and incidents involving military aircraft}}

The Su-25 has been involved in the following notable [[aviation accidents and incidents|aviation accidents]].
*An Su-25K of the [[Air Force of the Democratic Republic of the Congo]] disappeared in December 2006 during a routine rebasing operation and no wreckage was ever found.&lt;ref name=&quot;Congo&quot; /&gt;
*Another Congolese Su-25K crashed on 30 June 2007 during an Independence Day display, near the city of [[Kisangani]], killing the pilot. Investigations revealed that the crash was due to an engine failure.&lt;ref name=&quot;Congo&quot; /&gt;
*An Su-25 of the Russian Air Force exploded in mid-air on 20 March 2008 during a live firing exercise over the [[Primorsky Krai]], {{convert|143|km|mi|abbr=on}} from [[Vladivostok]], killing the pilot. Further investigations revealed that the aircraft was downed by a missile accidentally launched by a wingman. After the accident, all Russian Su-25s were grounded until the investigation was concluded.&lt;ref&gt;[http://en.rian.ru/russia/20080326/102255244.html &quot;Su-25 jet 'downed by wingman' in last week's crash.&quot;] ''[[RIA Novosti]]'', 26 March 2008. Retrieved 17 June 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;
{{clear}}

==Specifications (Su-25/Su-25K, late production)==
&lt;div style=&quot;float:right&quot;&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;position: relative; width: 400px;&quot;&gt;
[[File:Su25-kompo-vers2.svg|400px]]
{{Image label|x=0.8 |y=1.35 |scale=150|text='''[[Cannon|1]]'''}}
{{Image label|x=2.6 |y=1.55 |scale=150|text='''[[Air brake (aircraft)|2]]'''}}
{{Image label|x=0.5 |y=0.35  |scale=150|text='''[[Electronic countermeasure|3]]'''}}
{{Image label|x=0.3 |y=1.50 |scale=150|text='''[[Laser sight|4]]'''}}
{{Image label|x=0.53 |y=1.37  |scale=150|text='''[[Avionics|5]]'''}}
{{Image label|x=2.35 |y=0.50 |scale=150|text='''[[Identification friend or foe|6]]'''}}
{{Image label|x=0.48 |y=1.26 |scale=150|text='''[[Identification friend or foe|6]]'''}}
{{Image label|x=0.25 |y=1.38 |scale=150|text='''[[Pitot tube|7]]'''}}
{{Image label|x=2.38 |y=0.47  |scale=150|text='''[[Drogue parachute|8]]'''}}
{{Image label|x=1.35 |y=0.92 |scale=150|text='''[[Fuel tank|9]]'''}}
{{Image label|x=1.6 |y=1.25  |scale=150|text='''[[Chassis|10]]'''}}
{{Image label|x=0.84 |y=1.05  |scale=150|text='''[[Ejection seat|11]]'''}}
{{Image label|x=0.61 |y=1.15 |scale=150|text='''[[Bullet-resistant glass|12]]'''}}
{{Image label|x=0.78 |y=0.95 |scale=150|text='''[[Periscope|13]]'''}}
{{Image label|x=1.78 |y=0.88 |scale=150|text='''[[Turbojet|14]]'''}}
{{Image label|x=1.1 |y=1.15  |scale=150|text='''[[Intake|15]]'''}}
{{Image label|x=0.14 |y=1.40|scale=150|text='''[[Radio navigation|16]]'''}}
{{Image label|x=0.14 |y=1.50  |scale=150|text='''[[Pitot tube|17]]'''}}
{{Image label|x=0.9 |y=1.45 |scale=150|text='''[[Chassis|18]]'''}}
{{Image label|x=0.70 |y=0.90 |scale=150|text='''[[Aircraft canopy|19]]'''}}
{{Image label|x=0.68 |y=1.05  |scale=150|text='''[[Sight (device)|20]]'''}}
{{Image label|x=1.1 |y=1.35 |scale=150|text='''[[Ladder|21]]'''}}
{{Image label|x=1.8 |y=1.05  |scale=150|text='''[[Longeron|22]]'''}}
{{Image label|x=1.35 |y=0.62  |scale=150|text='''[[Flap (aircraft)|23]]'''}}
{{Image label|x=0.85 |y=0.62  |scale=150|text='''[[Leading edge slats|24]]'''}}
{{Image label|x=2.2 |y=0.35 |scale=150|text='''[[Empennage|25]]'''}}
{{Image label|x=0.9 |y=0.35 |scale=150|text='''[[Aileron|26]]'''}}
{{Image label|x=1.88 |y=0.82  |scale=150|text='''[[Infrared countermeasure|27]]'''}}
{{Image label|x=2.3 |y=1.55  |scale=150|text='''[[Radar warning receiver|28]]'''}}
{{Image label|x=2.48 |y=0.61  |scale=150|text='''[[Empennage|29]]'''}}
{{Image label|x=1.8 |y=1.35  |scale=150|text='''[[Hardpoint|30]]'''}}
{{Image label|x=2.1 |y=1.44 |scale=150|text='''[[Starter motor|31]]'''}}
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;NavFrame collapsed&quot; style=&quot;width: 30em&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;NavHead&quot;&gt;Legend&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;NavContent&quot;&gt;
{{col-begin}}
{{col-3}}
*'''1: '''SPM-17A cannon
*'''2: '''Air brakes
*'''3: '''Electronic countermeasures
*'''4: '''Laser Station Maple-PS
*'''5: '''Avionics
*'''6: '''Identification friend or foe system
*'''7: '''Pitot tube
*'''8: '''Drogue parachute
*'''9: '''Fuel tanks
*'''10: '''Main landing gear
*'''11: '''K-36L ejection seat
{{col-3}}
*'''12: '''Bulletproof glass
*'''13: '''Periscope
*'''14: '''Turbojet
*'''15: '''Air intake
*'''16: '''RSBN Short Range Navigation System
*'''17: '''PA-7 Pitot tube
*'''18: '''Front landing gear
*'''19: '''Canopy
*'''20: '''TSA-17 Sight
*'''21: '''Hinged ladder
{{col-3}}
*'''22: '''Longeron
*'''23: '''Flaps
*'''24: '''Leading edge slats
*'''25: '''Empennage, including rudder
*'''26: '''Aileron
*'''27: '''ASO-2V infrared countermeasures
*'''28: '''SPO-15 radar warning receiver
*'''29: '''Tail flaps
*'''30: '''CDD-25 hardpoints
*'''31: '''AAP-60 Starter engines{{sfn|Bedretdinov 2002}}
{{col-end}}
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
[[File:Suchoi Su-25.svg|thumb|upright=1.25|Sukhoi Su-25 line drawing]]

{{Aircraft specifications
&lt;!-- If you do not understand how to use this template, please ask at [[Wikipedia talk:WikiProject Aircraft]].
     Please answer the following questions. --&gt;
|plane or copter?=plane
|jet or prop?=jet
&lt;!-- Now, fill out the specs. Please include units where appropriate (main comes first, alt in parentheses). If an item doesn't apply, like capacity, leave it blank. For additional lines, end your alt units with )&lt;/li&gt; and start a new, fully formatted line with &lt;li&gt;
--&gt;
|ref=Jane's All The World's Aircraft 2003–2004;&lt;ref name=&quot;jawa03 p403-5&quot;&gt;Jackson 2003, pp. 403–405.&lt;/ref&gt; Sukhoi Company (JSC)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Sukhoi Company (JSC) – Airplanes – Military Aircraft – Su-25К – Aircraft performance|url=http://www.sukhoi.org/eng/planes/military/su25k/lth/|accessdate=29 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|crew= one
|length main= 15.53 m{{#tag:ref|Including nose probe||group=nb}}
|length alt= 50 ft 11{{frac|1|2}} in
|span main= 14.36 m
|span alt= 47 ft 1{{frac|1|2}} in
|height main= 4.80 m
|height alt= 15 ft 9 in
|area main= 33.7 m²
|area alt= 323 ft²
|empty weight main= 9,800 kg
|empty weight alt= 21,605 lb
|loaded weight main= 14,440 kg
|loaded weight alt= 31,835 lb
|loaded weight more= (normal take-off weight)
|max takeoff weight main= 19,300 kg
|max takeoff weight alt= 42,549 lb
|engine (jet)= Soyuz/Gavrilov R-195
|type of jet= [[turbojet]]s
|number of jets= 2
|thrust main= 44.18 kN
|thrust alt= 9,921 [[pound-force|lbf]]
|max speed main=Mach 0.82
|max speed alt=975 km/h, 526 knots, 606 mph
|max speed more=at sea level
|range main= 1,000 km
|range alt= 621 miles
|range more= clean at altitude
|combat radius main=
|combat radius alt=
|combat range main=750 km
|combat range alt=405 [[nautical mile|nmi]], 466 miles
|combat range more=at sea level, {{convert|4400|kg|lb|abbr=on}} weapons and two external tanks
|ferry range main=
|ferry range alt=
|ceiling main=7,000 m
|ceiling alt=23,000 ft
|ceiling more=clean, {{convert|5,000|m|ft|abbr=on}} with max weapons
|climb rate main=58 m/s
|climb rate alt=11,400 ft/min
|loading main=
|loading alt=
|g limits= +6.5, -2.0
|thrust/weight=

|guns     = 1 × [[Gryazev-Shipunov GSh-30-2|GSh-30-2 30mm cannon]] with 250 rounds
|bombs    = [[FAB-250]], [[FAB-500]], [[KAB-500]] [[laser-guided bomb]]&lt;ref name=fas&gt;{{cite web|title=Su-25 FROGFOOT Grach (Rook)|url=https://fas.org/man/dod-101/sys/ac/row/su-25.htm|publisher=FAS.org|accessdate=16 November 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|rockets  = [[UV-32-57]] 57 mm or B8M1 80 mm rocket pods, [[S-24 rocket|S-24]] ({{convert|240|mm|in|abbr=on}}) or [[S-25 (rocket)|S-25]] ({{convert|330|mm|in|abbr=on}}) rockets
|missiles = [[Kh-23]] (AS-7), [[AS-9]], [[Kh-25]]L (AS-10), [[Kh-29]] (AS-14) [[air-to-surface missile]]s, [[K-13 (missile)|K-13]] (AA-2) or [[R-60 (missile)|R-60]] (AA-8) [[air-to-air missile]]s
|hardpoints = 11
|hardpoint capacity = {{convert|4,000|kg|lb|abbr=on}}
}}

==See also==
{{Portal|Aviation}}
{{Aircontent
|see also=
|related=
* [[Sukhoi Su-28]]
|similar aircraft=
* [[Fairchild Republic A-10 Thunderbolt II]]
* [[Ilyushin Il-102]]
* [[Northrop YA-9]]
* [[IAR 93]]/[[Soko J-22 Orao]]
|lists=
}}

==References==

===Notes===
{{Reflist|30em|group=nb}}

===Citations===
{{Reflist|30em}}

===Bibliography===
{{Refbegin}}
* Bangash, M.Y.H. [https://books.google.com/books?id=kJSDJkgym-EC&amp;pg=PA270 ''Shock, Impact and Explosion: Structural Analysis and Design.''] Berlin: Springer, 2008. ISBN 978-3-540-77067-1.
* {{Cite book |last=Bedretdinov |first=Ilʹdar |title=Штурмовик Су-25 и его модификации |trans_title=The Su-25 and its modifications |language=Russian |location=Moscow |edition=2nd |publisher=Bedretdinov i Ko |isbn=978-5-901668-01-6 |year=2002 |ref={{harvid|Bedretdinov 2002}}}}
* Donald, David. [https://books.google.com/books?id=2KuPWSj8GEYC ''The Pocket Guide to Military Aircraft and the World's Airforces.''] London: Hamlyn, 2004. ISBN 978-0-681-03185-2.
* Donald, David and Daniel J. March. &quot;Sukhoi Su-25 'Frogfoot'.&quot; ''Modern Battlefield Warplanes''. London: AIRtime Publishing, 2004. ISBN 1-880588-76-5.
* {{Cite book|editor-last=Eden|editor-first=Paul|title=The Encyclopedia of Modern Military Aircraft|location=London|publisher=Amber Books, 2004|year=|isbn=1-904687-84-9|ref={{harvid|Eden|2004}}}}
* Frawley, Gerald. &quot;Sukhoi_Su-25&quot;. ''The International Directory of Military Aircraft, 2002/2003''. Fishwick, Act: Aerospace Publications, 2002. ISBN 1-875671-55-2.
* {{Cite book|last=Gordon|first=Yefim|title=Sukhoi Su-25|location=New York|publisher=IP Media, Inc., 2005|isbn=1-932525-02-5|ref={{harvid|Gordon|2005}}}}
* {{Cite book|last=Gordon|first=Yefim|title=Sukhoi Su-25: The Soviet Union's Tank-Buster|publisher=Midland Publishing, 2008|isbn=1-85780-254-3|ref={{harvid|Gordon|2008}}}}
* Gordon, Yefim and Alan Dawes. ''Sukhoi Su-25 Frogfoot: Close Air Support Aircraft''. London: Airlife, 2004. ISBN 1-84037-353-9.
* Jackson, Paul. ''Jane's All The World's Aircraft 2003–2004''. Coulsdon, UK: Jane's Information Group, 2003. ISBN 0-7106-2537-5.
* Wilson, Stewart. ''Combat Aircraft since 1945''. Fyshwick, Australia: Aerospace Publications, 2000. ISBN 1-875671-50-1.
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons and category|Sukhoi Su-25|Sukhoi Su-25}}
* [http://www.sukhoi.org/eng/planes/military/su25k/ Su-25К at Sukhoi.org]
* [http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/world/russia/su-25.htm Su-25 at GlobalSecurity.org]
* [http://www.warfare.ru/?catid=256&amp;linkid=1611 Su-25 at Russia Military Analysis]
* {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080109073305/http://www.uuaz.ru/eng/su-25ub.htm |date=9 January 2008 |title=Su-25UB Combat Trainer }}

{{Sukhoi aircraft}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2013}}

[[Category:Sukhoi aircraft|Su-25]]
[[Category:Anti-tank aircraft]]
[[Category:Soviet attack aircraft 1970–1979]]
[[Category:Carrier-based aircraft]]
[[Category:1981 introductions]]</text>
      <sha1>opckfirnulz0nxdb9nswl3lybprk8kq</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
