<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Sviatoslav's invasion of Bulgaria</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>26735933</id>
    <revision>
      <id>739514118</id>
      <parentid>725067221</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-15T04:12:56Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bobamnertiopsis</username>
        <id>991839</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Sources */ standardizing journal name</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="31108">{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Sviatoslav's invasion of Bulgaria
| partof      = the [[Rus'–Byzantine War (disambiguation)|Rus'–Byzantine War]]s and [[Byzantine–Bulgarian Wars]]
| image       = [[File:Skylintzes+Byzantine Rus conflict.jpg|250px|alt=Medieval manuscript showing a group of horsemen on the left, armed with maces and lances, pursuing other horsemen who flee to the right]]
| caption     = The Byzantines pursuing the Rus' at Dorostolon, from the ''[[Madrid Skylitzes]]''
| date        = 967/968–971
| place       = [[Moesia]] and [[Thrace]]
| result      = [[Byzantine]] victory over the Rus', formal annexation of Bulgaria, a [[Byzantine conquest of Bulgaria|fifty years Byzantine-Bulgarian war]] until the fall of Bulgaria in 1018
| combatant1  = [[Kievan Rus']],&lt;br/&gt;[[Pechenegs]],&lt;br/&gt;[[Magyars]]
| combatant2  = [[First Bulgarian Empire|Bulgaria]]
| combatant3  = [[Byzantine Empire]]
| commander1  = [[Sviatoslav I of Kiev]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Sveneld|Sphangel]]{{KIA}}(?)&lt;br/&gt;Ikmor{{KIA}}
| commander2  = [[Peter I of Bulgaria]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Boris II of Bulgaria]]
| commander3  = [[John I Tzimiskes]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Bardas Skleros]]
| strength1   = 60,000+ men
| strength2   = ~30,000 men
| strength3   = ~30–40,000 men
| campaignbox = 
{{Campaignbox Russo-Byzantine Wars}}
{{Campaignbox Byzantine-Bulgarian Wars}}
}}
'''Sviatoslav's invasion of Bulgaria''' refers to a conflict beginning in 967/968 and ending in 971, carried out in the eastern [[Balkans]], and involving the [[Kievan Rus']], [[First Bulgarian Empire|Bulgaria]], and the [[Byzantine Empire]]. The Byzantines encouraged the Rus' ruler [[Sviatoslav I of Kiev|Sviatoslav]] to attack Bulgaria, leading to the defeat of the Bulgarian forces and the occupation of the northern and north-eastern part of the country by the Rus' for the following two years. The allies then turned against each other, and the ensuing military confrontation ended with a Byzantine victory. The Rus' withdrew and eastern Bulgaria was incorporated into the Byzantine Empire.

In 927, a peace treaty had been signed between Bulgaria and Byzantium, ending many years of warfare and establishing forty years of peace. Both states prospered during this interlude, but the balance of power gradually shifted in favour of the Byzantines, who made great territorial gains against the [[Abbasid Caliphate]] in the East and formed a web of alliances surrounding Bulgaria. By 965/966, the warlike new Byzantine emperor [[Nikephoros II Phokas]] refused to renew the annual tribute that was part of the peace agreement and declared war on Bulgaria. Preoccupied with his campaigns in the East, Nikephoros resolved to fight the war by proxy and invited the Rus' ruler Sviatoslav to invade Bulgaria.

Sviatoslav's subsequent campaign greatly exceeded the expectations of the Byzantines, who had regarded him only as a means to exert diplomatic pressure on the Bulgarians. The Rus' prince conquered the core regions of the Bulgarian state in the northeastern Balkans in 967–969, seized the Bulgarian tsar [[Boris II of Bulgaria|Boris II]], and effectively ruled the country through him. Sviatoslav intended to continue his drive south against Byzantium itself, which in turn regarded the establishment of a new and powerful Russo-Bulgarian state in the Balkans with great concern. After stopping a Rus' advance through [[Thrace]] at the [[Battle of Arcadiopolis (970)|Battle of Arcadiopolis]] in 970, the Byzantine emperor [[John I Tzimiskes]] led an army north into Bulgaria in 971 and captured [[Preslav]], the capital. After a [[Siege of Dorostolon|three-month siege]] of the fortress of [[Silistra|Dorostolon]], Sviatoslav agreed to terms with the Byzantines and withdrew from Bulgaria. Tzimiskes formally annexed Eastern Bulgaria to the Byzantine Empire. However, most of the country in the central and western Balkans remained in effect outside imperial control; this would lead to the revival of the Bulgarian state in these regions under the [[Cometopuli dynasty]].

== Background ==
[[File:South-eastern Europe c. 910.jpg|thumb|right|300px|The Balkans, ca. 910]]

By the beginning of the 10th century, two powers had come to dominate the [[Balkans]]: the [[Byzantine Empire]] controlled the south of the peninsula and the coasts, and the [[First Bulgarian Empire|Bulgarian Empire]] held the central and northern Balkans. The early decades of the century were dominated by [[Simeon I of Bulgaria|Tsar Simeon]]&amp;nbsp;(r. 893–927), who expanded his empire at Byzantium's expense in a series of wars and secured for himself recognition of his imperial title.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Stephenson|2000|pp=18–23}}&lt;/ref&gt; Simeon's death in May 927 was soon followed by a [[rapprochement]] between the two powers, formalized with a treaty and a marriage alliance later that same year. Simeon's second son and successor, [[Peter I of Bulgaria|Peter I]]&amp;nbsp;(r. 927–969), married [[Eirene Lakapena|Maria]], the granddaughter of the Byzantine emperor [[Romanos I Lekapenos]]&amp;nbsp;(r. 920–944), and his imperial title was recognized. An annual tribute (which the Byzantines termed a subsidy for Maria's upkeep, to save face) was agreed to be paid to the Bulgarian ruler in exchange for peace.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Whittow|1996|p=292}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephenson 2000 23–24&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Stephenson|2000|pp=23–24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The agreement was kept for almost forty years as peaceful relations suited both sides. Bulgaria, despite the barrier formed by the [[Danube]], was still menaced in its northern reaches by steppe peoples, the [[Magyars]] and the [[Pechenegs]]. They launched raids throughout Bulgaria, occasionally reaching Byzantine territory as well. The Byzantine–Bulgarian peace nevertheless meant less trouble from the north, as many Pecheneg raids had been sponsored by the Byzantines. Peter's reign, although lacking the military splendour of Simeon's, was still a &quot;golden age&quot; for Bulgaria, with a flourishing economy and a thriving urban society.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephenson 2000 23–24&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Whittow|1996|pp=292–294}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Runciman|1930|p=184}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Byzantium used the peace to focus its energy on wars against the [[Abbasid Caliphate]] in the East, where a series of campaigns under generals [[John Kourkouas]] and [[Nikephoros II Phokas|Nikephoros Phokas]] greatly expanded imperial territory. At the same time, military reforms created a much more effective and offensively-oriented army.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Whittow|1996|pp=317–326}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Treadgold|1997|pp=479–497}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Byzantines did not neglect the Balkans, working steadily to improve their contacts with the peoples of central and eastern Europe, subtly altering the balance of power in the peninsula. Their [[Crimea]]n outpost of [[Cherson (theme)|Cherson]] maintained trade with the Pechenegs and the emerging power of the [[Kievan Rus']]; Byzantine missionaries led the Christianization of the Magyars; and the Slavic princes of the western Balkans came to once again acknowledge the [[suzerainty]] of the Empire,&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Whittow|1996|pp=293–294}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Stephenson|2000|p=47}}&lt;/ref&gt; particularly after [[Caslav Klonimirovic]] ended Bulgarian control over [[Medieval Serbia|Serbia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Runciman|1930|p=185}}&lt;/ref&gt; These relationships on the periphery of the Bulgarian Empire were an important asset for [[Byzantine diplomacy]]: instigating attacks against Bulgaria by the Pechenegs and the [[Khazars]] was a time-honoured method of applying pressure on the Bulgarians.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Stephenson|2000|pp=30–31}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldon|2001|pp=96–97}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Upon the sudden death of Emperor [[Romanos II]] in 963, Nikephoros Phokas usurped the throne from Romanos' infant sons and became senior emperor as [[Nikephoros II]]&amp;nbsp;(r. 963–969).&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Treadgold|1997|pp=498–499}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nikephoros, a prominent member of the [[Anatolia]]n military aristocracy, also focused mostly on the East, leading his army personally in campaigns that recovered [[Cyprus]] and [[Cilicia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Treadgold|1997|pp=499–501}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thus things stood when a Bulgarian embassy visited Nikephoros in late 965 or early 966 to collect the tribute owed. Nikephoros, his confidence boosted by his recent successes, and deeming the Bulgarian ruler's demand presumptuous, refused to pay, claiming that with Empress Maria's recent death (ca. 963) any such obligations had ceased. He had the envoys beaten and sent them home with threats and insults. He proceeded with his troops to [[Thrace]], where he staged an elaborate parade as a display of military strength and sacked a few Bulgarian border forts.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Stephenson|2000|pp=47–48}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Fine|1991|p=181}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Obolensky128&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Obolensky|1971|p=128}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nikephoros' decision to effect a breach of relations with Bulgaria was also in response to the recent treaty that Peter I had signed with the Magyars. The treaty stipulated that the Magyars would be allowed to pass through the country and raid Byzantium in exchange for halting their raids in Bulgaria.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Zlatarski|1971|p=545}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Anxious to avoid war, Tsar Peter sent his two sons, [[Boris II of Bulgaria|Boris]] and [[Roman of Bulgaria|Roman]], as hostages to [[Constantinople]]. This move failed to appease Nikephoros, but he was not able or willing to campaign against Bulgaria; his forces were engaged in the East, and furthermore, drawing on the Byzantines' past experience, Nikephoros was reluctant to mount an expedition into the mountainous and heavily forested terrain of Bulgaria.&lt;ref name=&quot;Obolensky128&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephenson48&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Stephenson|2000|p=48}}&lt;/ref&gt; Consequently, he resorted to the old Byzantine expedient of calling in a tribe from eastern Europe to attack Bulgaria. In late 966 or early 967,{{cref|a}} he dispatched the ''[[patrikios]]'' [[Kalokyros]], a citizen of Cherson, as his ambassador to [[Sviatoslav I of Kiev|Sviatoslav]], ruler of the [[Kievan Rus'|Rus']]. The Byzantines had long maintained close relations with the Rus', with whom they were bound by [[Rus'–Byzantine Treaty (945)|treaty]]. With promises of rich rewards and, according to [[Leo the Deacon]], a payment of 1,500&amp;nbsp;pounds of gold, the Rus' ruler was induced to attack Bulgaria from the north.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephenson48&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Haldon97&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldon|2001|p=97}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Whittow|1996|pp=260, 294}}&lt;/ref&gt; That Nikephoros should call upon Sviatoslav for aid was unusual, since the Pechenegs were traditionally used for such tasks. The historian A.D. Stokes, who examined the questions surrounding the background and chronology of Sviatoslav's Bulgarian campaign, suggested that this move had a second motive of turning the attention of Sviatoslav, who had recently destroyed the Khazar khanate, away from the Byzantine outpost of Cherson.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Fine|1991|pp=181–182}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Kievan Rus en.jpg|thumb|right|250px|&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;Kievan Rus', mid-10th century&lt;/div&gt;]]

Sviatoslav enthusiastically agreed to the Byzantine proposal. In August 967 or 968, the Rus' crossed the Danube into Bulgarian territory, defeated a Bulgarian army of 30,000 men in the [[Battle of Silistra]],&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Zlatarski|1971|p=553}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Andreev|Lalkov|1996|p=111}}&lt;/ref&gt; and occupied most of the [[Dobruja]]. According to the Bulgarian historian [[Vasil Zlatarski]], Sviatoslav seized 80&amp;nbsp;towns in northeastern Bulgaria. They were looted and destroyed but not permanently occupied. Tsar Peter I suffered an [[epileptic stroke]] when he received news of the defeat.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Zlatarski|1971|pp=554–555}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Rus' wintered at [[Pereyaslavets]],&lt;ref&gt;&quot;It is not my pleasure to be in Kiev, but I will live in Pereyaslavets on the Danube. That shall be the centre of my land; for there all good things flow: gold from the Greeks [Byzantines], precious cloths, wines and fruits of many kinds; silver and horses from the Czechs and Magyars; and from the Rus' furs, wax, honey and slaves.&quot; - Sviatoslav, according to the ''[[Primary Chronicle]]'', {{Harvnb|Stephenson|2000|p=49}}&lt;/ref&gt; while the Bulgarians retreated to the fortress of Dorostolon ([[Silistra]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;Obolensky128&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephenson48&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Whittow|1996|p=260}}&lt;/ref&gt; The next year, Sviatoslav left with part of his army to counter a [[Siege of Kiev (968)|Pecheneg attack]] on his capital at [[Kiev]] (incited either by the Byzantines or, according to the Russian ''[[Primary Chronicle]]'', by the Bulgarians). At the same time, Tsar Peter sent a new embassy to Byzantium, a visit that was recorded by [[Liutprand of Cremona]]. In contrast to their previous reception, this time the Bulgarian envoys were treated with great honour. Nevertheless, Nikephoros, confident of his position, demanded harsh terms: Tsar Peter was to resign and be replaced by Boris, and the two young emperors, Basil and Constantine, were to be married to Bulgarian princesses, daughters of Boris.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Whittow|1996|pp=260, 294–295}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fine182-183&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Fine|1991|pp=182–183}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Peter retired to a monastery, where he died in 969, while Boris was released from Byzantine custody and recognized as Tsar Boris II. For the moment, it appeared that Nikephoros' plan had worked.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fine182-183&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephenson49&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Stephenson|2000|p=49}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, Sviatoslav's brief sojourn into the south awakened in him the desire to conquer these fertile and rich lands. In this intention he was apparently encouraged by the former Byzantine envoy, Kalokyros, who coveted the imperial crown for himself. Thus, after defeating the Pechenegs, he set up viceroys to rule Russia in his absence and turned his sights southward again.&lt;ref name=&quot;Obolensky128&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephenson49&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Whittow|1996|pp=260–261}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Fine|1991|pp=183–184}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:63-manasses-chronicle.jpg|thumb|left|250px|alt=Medieval manuscript showing groups of riders, both lancers and horse-archers, fighting, and trampling over bodies|Sviatoslav's invasion, from the ''[[Manasses Chronicle]]''.]]
In summer 969, Sviatoslav returned to Bulgaria in force, accompanied by allied Pecheneg and Magyar contingents. In his absence, Pereyaslavets had been recovered by Boris II; the Bulgarian defenders put up a determined fight, but Sviatoslav stormed the city. Thereafter Boris and Roman capitulated, and the Rus' rapidly established control over eastern and northern Bulgaria, placing garrisons in Dorostolon and the Bulgarian capital of [[Preslav]]. There Boris continued to reside and exercise nominal authority as Sviatoslav's vassal. In reality he was little more than a figurehead, retained in order to lessen Bulgarian resentment at and reaction to the Rus' presence.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Stephenson|2000|pp=49–51}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Fine|1991|pp=184–185}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sviatoslav appears to have been successful in enlisting Bulgarian support. Bulgarian soldiers joined his army in considerable numbers, tempted partly by the prospects of booty, but also enticed by Sviatoslav's anti-Byzantine designs and probably mollified by a shared Slavic heritage. The Rus' ruler himself was careful not to alienate his new subjects: he forbade his army from looting the countryside or plundering cities that surrendered peacefully.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Fine|1991|pp=185–186}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Thus Nikephoros' scheme had backfired: Instead of a weak Bulgaria, a new and warlike nation had been established at the Empire's northern border, and Sviatoslav showed every intention of continuing his advance south into Byzantium. The emperor tried to get the Bulgarians to resume the war against the Rus', but his proposals were not heeded.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephenson51&quot;/&gt; Then, on 11 December 969, Nikephoros was murdered in a palace coup and succeeded by [[John I Tzimiskes]]&amp;nbsp;(r. 969–976), to whom fell the task of dealing with the situation in the Balkans. The new emperor sent envoys to Sviatoslav, proposing negotiations. The Rus' ruler demanded a huge sum before he would withdraw, insisting that otherwise the Empire should abandon its European territories to him and withdraw to [[Asia Minor]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Haldon97&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Obolensky129&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Obolensky|1971|p=129}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Whittow|1996|pp=261, 295}}&lt;/ref&gt; For the time being, Tzimiskes was preoccupied with consolidating his position and countering the unrest of the powerful Phokas clan and its adherents in Asia Minor. He therefore entrusted the war in the Balkans to his brother-in-law, the [[Domestic of the Schools]] [[Bardas Skleros]], and to the eunuch [[stratopedarch]] [[Peter (stratopedarches)|Peter]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephenson51&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Stephenson|2000|p=51}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldon|2001|pp=97–98}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Whittow295&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Whittow|1996|p=295}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In early 970, a Rus' army, with large contingents of Bulgarians, Pechenegs, and Magyars, crossed the [[Balkan Mountains]] and headed south. The Rus' stormed the city of Philippopolis (now  [[Plovdiv]]), and, according to Leo the Deacon, impaled 20,000 of its surviving inhabitants.&lt;ref name=&quot;Whittow295&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fine186&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Fine|1991|p=186}}&lt;/ref&gt; Skleros, with an army of 10,000–12,000&amp;nbsp;men, [[Battle of Arcadiopolis (970)|confronted]] the Rus' advance near Arcadiopolis (now [[Luleburgaz]]) in early spring 970. The Byzantine general, whose army was considerably outnumbered, used a [[feigned retreat]] to draw the Pecheneg contingent away from the main army into a prepared ambush. The main Rus' army panicked and fled, suffering heavy casualties at the hands of the pursuing Byzantines. The Rus' withdrew north of the Balkan mountain range, which gave Tzimiskes time to deal with internal unrest and to assemble his forces.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephenson51&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldon|2001|p=98}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Byzantine offensive ==
[[File:Lebedev Svyatoslavs meeting with Emperor John.jpg|thumb|right|250px|alt=Man in plain white clothes and alone in a rowboat, arrives on a shore where a group of richly dressed men stand and  await him, among them a crowned man in golden armour|The meeting of Sviatoslav with Emperor John Tzimiskes, painting by [[Klavdy Lebedev]]]]
After being occupied with suppressing the revolt of [[Bardas Phokas the Younger|Bardas Phokas]] throughout the year 970, Tzimiskes marshalled his forces in early 971 for a campaign against the Rus', moving his troops from Asia to [[Thrace]] and gathering supplies and siege equipment. The [[Byzantine navy]] accompanied the expedition, tasked with carrying troops to effect a landing in the enemy's rear and to cut off their retreat across the Danube.&lt;ref name=&quot;Obolensky129&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldon|2001|pp=98–99}}&lt;/ref&gt; The emperor chose Easter week of 971 to make his move, catching the Rus' completely by surprise: The passes of the Balkan mountains had been left unguarded, either because the Rus' were busy suppressing Bulgarian revolts or perhaps (as A.D. Stokes suggests) because a peace agreement that had been concluded after the battle of Arcadiopolis made them complacent.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fine186&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Haldon99&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldon|2001|p=99}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Stephenson|2000|pp=51–52}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Byzantine army, led by Tzimiskes in person and numbering 30,000–40,000, advanced quickly and reached Preslav unmolested. The Rus' army was defeated in a battle before the city walls, and the Byzantines proceeded to lay siege. The Rus' and Bulgarian garrison under the Rus' noble [[Sveneld|Sphangel]]{{cref|b}} put up a determined resistance, but the city was stormed on 13 April. Among the captives were Boris II and his family, who were brought to Constantinople along with the Bulgarian imperial regalia.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fine186&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Haldon99&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephenson52&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Stephenson|2000|p=52}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Treadgold509&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Treadgold|1997|p=509}}&lt;/ref&gt; The main Rus' force under Sviatoslav withdrew before the imperial army towards Dorostolon on the Danube. As Sviatoslav feared a Bulgarian uprising, he had 300 Bulgarian nobles executed, and imprisoned many others. The imperial army advanced without hindrance; the Bulgarian garrisons of the various forts and strongholds along the way surrendered peacefully.&lt;ref name=&quot;Haldon99&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stephenson52&quot;/&gt;

As the Byzantines neared Dorostolon, they came upon the Rus' army, which had deployed on a field before the city, ready for battle. After a long and bitter struggle, the Byzantines won the day when Tzimiskes ordered his heavy [[cataphract]] cavalry to advance. The Rus' quickly broke ranks and fled inside the fortress.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldon|2001|pp=99–100}}&lt;/ref&gt; The subsequent [[siege of Dorostolon]] lasted for three months, during which the Byzantines blockaded the city by land and sea and the Rus' attempted several sallies. Three pitched battles were fought, all of which ended in Byzantine victories. After the final and particularly savage battle in late July, the Rus' were forced to capitulate. According to Byzantine chroniclers, by that time only 22,000 out of an army of originally 60,000 remained.&lt;ref name=&quot;Treadgold509&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldon|2001|pp=100–104}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tzimiskes and Sviatoslav met and agreed to a peace treaty: The Rus' army was allowed to depart, leaving their captives and plunder behind, and their trading rights were re-affirmed in exchange for an oath to never again attack imperial territory. Sviatoslav would not long outlive the peace settlement, as he was slain on his way home in a Pecheneg ambush at the river [[Dnieper]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Haldon|2001|p=104}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Stephenson|2000|p=53}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Aftermath ==
[[File:Tzimiskes returns.jpg|thumb|right|250px|alt=Medieval manuscript showing a procession of a carriage surmounted by an icon, followed by a crowned man on a white horse and two other horsemen|Depiction of Tzimiskes' triumph in the ''[[Madrid Skylitzes]]'': The emperor, on a white horse, follows the wagon with the icon of the Virgin and the Bulgarian regalia, while the Bulgarian tsar Boris II follows further behind.]]
The outcome of the war was a complete Byzantine victory, and Tzimiskes decided to take full advantage. Although he initially recognized Boris II as the legitimate Bulgarian tsar, after the fall of Dorostolon his intentions changed. This became evident during his triumphal return to Constantinople, where the emperor entered the [[Golden Gate (Constantinople)|Golden Gate]] behind a wagon carrying an icon of the [[Virgin Mary]] as well as the Bulgarian regalia, with Boris and his family following behind Tzimiskes. When the procession reached the [[Forum of Constantine]], Boris was publicly divested of his imperial insignia, and at the church of [[Hagia Sophia]], the Bulgarian crown was dedicated to God.&lt;ref name=&quot;Whittow296&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Whittow|1996|p=296}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Stephenson|2000|p=54}}&lt;/ref&gt;

This marked the symbolic end of Bulgaria as an independent state, at least in Byzantine eyes. Byzantine generals were installed in the eastern parts of the country along the Danube. Preslav was renamed Ioannopolis in honour of the emperor, and Dorostolon (or perhaps Pereyaslavets) was renamed Theodoropolis after [[Theodore Stratelates|St. Theodore the Stratelate]], who was believed to have intervened in the final battle before Dorostolon. Tzimiskes reduced the [[Bulgarian patriarchate]] to an archbishopric subject to the [[Patriarch of Constantinople]]. He brought the Bulgarian royal family and many nobles to live in Constantinople and Asia Minor, while the region around Philippopolis was settled with [[Armenians]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Treadgold|1997|pp=509–510}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Stephenson|2000|pp=52–53}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Fine|1991|pp=187–188}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, outside eastern Bulgaria, and there only in the major urban centres, Byzantine control existed only in theory. Tzimiskes, like Nikephoros Phokas, was more interested in the East. With the Rus' threat banished and Bulgaria seemingly pacified, his attention turned to [[Syria]]. No coordinated Byzantine drive to secure the interior of the Balkans was made. As a result, the north-central Balkans and [[Macedonia (region)|Macedonia]], where neither the Rus' nor Tzimiskes' troops had ventured, remained as before in the hands of the local Bulgarian elites.&lt;ref name=&quot;Whittow296&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Fine|1991|p=188}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Obolensky|1971|pp=130–131}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In these areas, a Bulgarian resistance emerged, taking advantage of the Byzantine civil wars after the death of Tzimiskes in 976, led by the four sons of a count (''[[comes]]'') [[Nicholas (komes)|Nicholas]], who became known as the ''[[Cometopuli dynasty|Cometopuli]]'' (&quot;sons of the count&quot;). The most capable amongst them, [[Samuel of Bulgaria|Samuel]], revived the Bulgarian realm, now centered in Macedonia, and was crowned Tsar in 997. A formidable warrior, he led raiding campaigns into Byzantine territory as far south as the [[Peloponnese]], and he engaged the Byzantine emperor [[Basil II]] (r. 976–1025) in a [[Byzantine conquest of Bulgaria|series of wars]] resulting in the final conquest of the Bulgarian state by the Byzantines in 1018.&lt;ref name=&quot;Whittow297&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Whittow|1996|p=297}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Stephenson|2000|pp=58–75}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Obolensky|1971|pp=131–133}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, due to the events of 971, the Byzantines would never regard him as anything other than a rebel against imperial authority, let alone concede the principle of equality enjoyed by the Bulgarian rulers before 971.&lt;ref name=&quot;Whittow297&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Obolensky|1971|p=131}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Notes ==
{{refbegin}}

{{Cnote|a|The chronology of the Byzantine embassy to Kiev and Sviatoslav's invasion and conquest of Bulgaria is uncertain, since the sources disagree with each other. Various interpretations have been offered and different dates are used by modern scholars.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Fine|1991|p=182}}&lt;/ref&gt; For these cases, all alternative dates have been provided in this article.}}
{{Cnote|b|[[John Skylitzes]] names Sphangel or Sphengel as Sviatoslav's second-in-command, with Ikmor as the third most important military leader, while [[Leo the Deacon]] reverses this order. Ikmor was killed in battle in front of Dorostolon. Sphangel is usually identified with [[Sveneld]] from the Russian ''Primary Chronicle''. The Greek chroniclers record that Sphangel was also killed at Dorostolon, but the ''Primary Chronicle'' has Sveneld survive the war and the subsequent Pecheneg ambush which claimed Sviatoslav's life.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Talbot|Sullivan|2005|pp=181, 189, 193}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

{{refend}}

== References ==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

== Sources ==
{{refbegin}}
* {{citation | title = The Bulgarian Khans and Tsars | last1 = Andreev | first1 = Jordan | last2 = Lalkov | first2 = Milcho | year = 1996 | language = Bulgarian | publisher = Abagar | location = Veliko Tarnovo | isbn = 954-427-216-X }}
* {{citation | first = Florin | last = Curta | title = Southeastern Europe in the Middle Ages, 500–1250 | publisher = Cambridge University Press | year = 2006 |location = Cambridge; New York | isbn = 978-0-521-81539-0 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=YIAYMNOOe0YC}}
* {{citation | first = John Van Antwerp | last = Fine | title = The Early Medieval Balkans: A Critical Survey from the Sixth to the Late Twelfth Century | publisher = University of Michigan Press | year = 1991 |location = Ann Arbor| isbn = 978-0-472-08149-3 | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Y0NBxG9Id58C}}
* {{citation | last = Haldon | first = John F. | title = The Byzantine Wars | publisher = Tempus | year=2001 |location = Stroud| isbn=978-0-7524-1795-0}}
* {{citation | last = Hanak | first = Walter K. | contribution = The Infamous Svjatoslav: Master of Duplicity in War and Peace? | title = Peace and War in Byzantium: Essays in Honor of George T. Dennis, S.J. | editor1-first = Timothy S. |editor1-last = Miller | editor2-first = John | editor2-last = Nesbitt | publisher = The Catholic University of America Press | year = 1995 | url = http://deremilitari.org/2014/05/the-infamous-svjatoslav-master-of-duplicity-in-war-and-peace/ |location=Washington, D.C.| isbn = 978-0-8132-0805-3 }}
* {{citation | editor-first = Alexander | editor-last = Kazhdan | editor-link=Alexander Kazhdan | title = [[Oxford Dictionary of Byzantium]] | publisher = Oxford University Press | year = 1991 |location=New York| isbn = 978-0-19-504652-6}}
* {{citation | last= Obolensky | first = Dimitri | authorlink = Dimitri Obolensky | title= The Byzantine Commonwealth: Eastern Europe, 500–1453 | year = 1971 | publisher = Praeger Publishers|location=New York|isbn = 978-0-297-00343-4}}
* {{citation |last = Runciman |first = Steven |authorlink = Steven Runciman |title = A History of the First Bulgarian Empire |publisher = [[George Bell &amp; Sons]] |location = London |oclc = 832687 |year = 1930 }}
* {{citation | last=Stephenson | first=Paul| title=Byzantium's Balkan Frontier: A Political Study of the Northern Balkans, 900–1204  | publisher=Cambridge University Press |year=2000 |location=Cambridge; New York| isbn=0-521-77017-3 | url = https://books.google.com/books?id=ILiOI0UgxHoC}}
* {{citation | last=Stokes | first=A.D. | title=The Background and Chronology of the Balkan Campaigns of Sviatoslav Igorevich | journal=The Slavonic and East European Review | volume=40 | year = 1962 | pages=44–57}}
* {{citation | editor1-first = Alice-Mary | editor1-last = Talbot | editor2-first = Dennis F. | editor2-last = Sullivan  |title = The History of Leo the Deacon: Byzantine Military Expansion in the Tenth Century | publisher = Dumbarton Oaks | year= 2005 | isbn= 978-0-88402-324-1 |location=Washington| url = https://books.google.gr/books?id=RCDsV41k8A0C}}
* {{citation |title=A History of the Byzantine State and Society |last=Treadgold |first=Warren T. |year=1997 |publisher=Stanford University Press | location=Stanford, CA |isbn=0-8047-2630-2 | url =https://books.google.com/books?id=nYbnr5XVbzUC}}
* {{citation |title=The Making of Byzantium, 600–1025 | first=Mark |last=Whittow | publisher=University of California Press |location=Berkeley| year=1996 | isbn=0-520-20496-4}}
* {{citation |last=Zlatarski |first=Vasil |authorlink=Vasil Zlatarski | title=History of the Bulgarian state in the Middle Ages, Volume I. History of the First Bulgarian Empire |url=http://www.promacedonia.org/vz1b/index.html |edition=2nd |chapter=Part II. From the Slavinization of the Country to the Fall of the First Empire (852–1018). |publisher=Nauka i izkustvo |year=1971 |origyear=1927 |location=Sofia|language=Bulgarian |oclc=67080314}}
{{refend}}

{{coord missing|Turkey}}
{{good article}}

[[Category:960s conflicts]]
[[Category:970s conflicts]]
[[Category:10th century in the Byzantine Empire]]
[[Category:10th century in Bulgaria]]
[[Category:Rus'–Byzantine wars]]
[[Category:Wars involving the First Bulgarian Empire]]
[[Category:967 in the Byzantine Empire]]
[[Category:971 in the Byzantine Empire]]</text>
      <sha1>d2hmow98sz95ysevcskppmefnz3rimy</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
