<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Theodor Weissenberger</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>10301408</id>
    <revision>
      <id>737059351</id>
      <parentid>735508156</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-31T14:18:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>89.96.190.231</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="40312">{{good article}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2014}}
{{Use American English|date=December 2014}}
{{Infobox military person
|name=Theodor Weissenberger
|birth_date={{birth date|1914|12|21|df=y}}
|death_date={{death date and age|1950|6|11|1914|12|21|df=y}}
|birth_place=[[Mühlheim am Main]], [[German Empire]]
|death_place=[[Nürburgring]], [[West Germany]]
|image=Theodor Weissenberger.jpg
|alt=Black-and-white portrait of a man wearing a peaked cap and military flight suit with an Iron Cross displayed at his neck.
|caption=Theodor Weissenberger 1944
|nickname=
|allegiance={{flag|Nazi Germany}}
|branch={{Luftwaffe}}
|serviceyears=1936–45
|rank=''[[Major (Germany)|Major]]'' (Major)
|commands=II./[[JG 5]], I./[[JG 5]], I./[[JG 7]], [[JG 7]]
|unit=[[JG 77]], [[JG 5]], [[JG 7]]
|battles=[[World War II]]
*[[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]]
*[[Continuation War]]
*[[Western Front (World War II)|Western Front]]
*[[Invasion of Normandy]]
*[[Defense of the Reich]]
|awards=[[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves]]
|laterwork=[[Auto racing]]}}

'''Theodor Weissenberger''' (21 December 1914 – 11 June 1950) was a German ''[[Luftwaffe]]'' [[military aviation|military aviator]] during [[World War II]] and a [[fighter ace]] credited with 208 enemy aircraft shot down in 375 combat missions. The majority of his victories were claimed near the [[Arctic Ocean]] in the northern sector of the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]], but he also claimed 33 victories over the [[Western Front (World War II)|Western Front]]. He claimed eight of these victories over the [[Allies of World War II|Western Allies]] while flying the [[Messerschmitt Me 262]] jet fighter.

Born in [[Mühlheim am Main]] in the [[German Empire]], Weissenberger, who had been a [[Glider (sailplane)|glider]] pilot in his youth, volunteered for service in the ''Luftwaffe'' of the [[Third Reich]] in 1936. Following flight training, he was posted to the [[heavy fighter]] squadron of [[Jagdgeschwader 77|''Jagdgeschwader'' 77]] (JG 77—77th Fighter Wing) in 1941. He claimed his first aerial victory over Norway on 24 October 1941. After 23 aerial victories as heavy fighter pilot, he received the [[German Cross]] in Gold and was then posted to [[Jagdgeschwader 5|''Jagdgeschwader'' 5]] (JG 5—5th Fighter Wing) in September 1942. There he received the [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross]] on 13 November 1942 after 38 aerial victories.

In June 1943, Weissenberger was appointed ''[[Staffelkapitän]]'' of 7. ''[[Organization of the Luftwaffe (1933–1945)#Staffel|Staffel]]'' of JG&amp;nbsp;5. Following his 112th aerial victory, he was awarded the [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves]] on 2 August 1943. He was appointed ''Staffelkapitän'' of 6. ''Staffel'' in September 1943 and in March 1944 he was given command of II. ''[[Luftwaffe Organization#Gruppe|Gruppe]]'' of JG&amp;nbsp;5 which was operating in [[Defense of the Reich]] missions. In June 1944 he took command of I. ''Gruppe'' of JG&amp;nbsp;5 which defended against the [[Invasion of Normandy]]. Weissenberger claimed 25 aerial victories in this theater, which included his 200th victory on 25 July 1944. 

After conversion training to the Me 262 jet fighter, he was appointed commander of I. ''Gruppe'' of [[Jagdgeschwader 7|''Jagdgeschwader'' 7]] &quot;Nowotny&quot; (JG 7—7th Fighter Wing), the first operational jet fighter wing in the world, in November 1944. Promoted to ''[[Major (Germany)|Major]]'' (major), he took command of JG&amp;nbsp;7 &quot;Nowotny&quot; as a ''[[Geschwaderkommodore]]'' in January 1945, a position he held until the end of hostilities. 

He was killed in a car racing accident on 11 June 1950 at the [[Nürburgring]].

== Early life and career ==
Weissenberger, the son of a [[plant nursery]] owner, was born on 21 December 1914 in [[Mühlheim am Main]] in the [[Grand Duchy of Hesse]] of the [[German Empire]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p277&quot;&gt;Stockert 1997, p. 277.&lt;/ref&gt; He had a brother Otto who also served as a pilot in ''[[Luftwaffe]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p279&quot;&gt;Stockert 1997, p. 279.&lt;/ref&gt; As a [[Glider (sailplane)|glider]] pilot with the [[German Air Sports Association]] ({{lang|de|''Deutscher Luftsportverband''}}), he made his maiden flight on 16 November 1935. On 20 July 1941 he logged his 645th flight as a glider pilot, in total 196 hours and 46 minutes of powerless flight. Most of these flights were made as an instructor over the [[Rhön Mountains]], [[Silesia]] and [[Bavaria]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p277&quot; /&gt;

He joined the military service of the ''Luftwaffe'' with 2./''Flieger-Ersatz-Abteilung'' 14 (2nd Company of Flier Replacement Unit 14) in [[Detmold]] on 19 October 1936. There he was promoted to ''[[Feldwebel]]'' of the [[Military reserve force|Reserves]] on 1 December 1940.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p277&quot; /&gt;

== World War II ==
Weissenberger was posted to a front-line unit on 27 August 1941, almost two years after the start of World War II. His unit, 1.(Z)/[[Jagdgeschwader 77|''Jagdgeschwader'' 77]] (JG 77—77th Fighter Wing) was a ''Zerstörer'' (Z—[[heavy fighter]] or destroyer) ''[[Organization of the Luftwaffe (1933–1945)#Staffel|Staffel]]'' (squadron) flying the twin-engine, up to three-seat, [[Messerschmitt Bf 110]].&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;For an explanation of ''Luftwaffe'' unit designations, see [[Organization of the Luftwaffe (1933–1945)|Organization of the ''Luftwaffe'' during World War II]].&lt;/ref&gt; The unit was stationed in Norway, operating in the [[Murmansk]] area in support of Finnish operations against the Soviet Union during the [[Continuation War]].  Germany regarded its operations in the region as part of its overall war efforts on the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]], and it provided Finland with critical material support and military cooperation. There he flew his first combat mission of the war on 13 September 1941.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p277&quot; /&gt;

=== War on the Arctic Front ===
Weissenberger claimed his first aerial victory, a [[Polikarpov I-153]] [[biplane]] fighter, on 24 October 1941 and was awarded the [[Iron Cross]] 2nd Class ({{lang|de|''Eisernes Kreuz zweiter Klasse''}}) on 6 November 1941. He was promoted to ''[[Oberfeldwebel]]'' of the Reserves on 1 February 1942. During this phase of his military career, he often got into trouble with his superiors regarding his lack of discipline. A few times his comrades had to intervene to save him from punishment. On 24 January 1942, Weissenberger and ''[[Oberleutnant]]'' Max Franzisket flew on a [[Air-to-ground weaponry|ground attack]] mission against the [[Kirov Railway]] line.{{refn|Max Franzisket was the brother of [[Ludwig Franzisket]]. Franzisket was a recipient of the German Cross in Gold and was killed in action on 19 July 1943 on the Eastern Front.&lt;ref&gt;Patzwall &amp; Scherzer 2001, p. 121.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ziefle 2010, p. 117.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=&quot;Note&quot;}} Weissenberger claimed a [[Polikarpov I-18]] shot down at 13:35, roughly {{Convert|4|km|mi|abbr=off|sp=us}} northwest of the railway station of Bojaskoje. At 13:40, he claimed a [[Hawker Hurricane]] shot down, his third aerial victory.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p277&quot; /&gt;

[[File:Me 110.jpg|thumb|right|10.(Z)/JG&amp;nbsp;5 was referred to as the &quot;''Dackelstaffel''&quot;. The Bf&amp;nbsp;110s [[noseart]] emblem was a [[dachshund]] biting a [[Polikarpov I-16]].&lt;ref&gt;Ziefle 2013, p. 131.&lt;/ref&gt;|alt=A painting of a dachshund holding a Soviet aircraft in its mouth.]]
In February 1942 he mostly flew [[escort fighter]] missions for [[Junkers Ju 87]] and [[Junkers Ju 88|Ju 88]] bombers attacking the harbors at Ferosero, [[Polyarny, Murmansk Oblast|Polyarnoye]], present-day Polyarny, and Murmansk. Weissenberger received the Iron Cross 1st Class ({{lang|de|''Eisernes Kreuz erster Klasse''}}) on 17 February 1942. On 25 February he claimed two more Hurricanes shot down at 11:15 and 11:22, his fourth and fifth victories. His ''Staffel'' was redesignated as 10.(Z) of [[Jagdgeschwader 5|''Jagdgeschwader'' 5]] (JG 5—5th Fighter Wing) on 16 March 1942 and subordinated to JG&amp;nbsp;5. In April 1942 he claimed eight victories, three of which were shot down on 15 April during two combat missions west of Murmansk. On 25 April at 7:20 Weissenberger took off at [[Kirkenes]] for an emergency intercept mission against 20 Soviet [[Petlyakov Pe-2]] bombers. He shot down two bombers before his aircraft was hit by the defensive fire. The right engine started burning and he was forced to disengage from the enemy. Returning to the German lines, he made a safe [[belly landing]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p277&quot; /&gt;

Weissenberger became an &quot;[[Aviators who became ace in a day|ace-in-a-day]]&quot; for the first time on 10 May 1942 when he shot down five enemy aircraft, aerial victories 14–18, between 16:45 and 16:57 while on a Ju&amp;nbsp;87 escort mission. These victories were claimed over aircraft of 2 ''Gvardeyskiy Smeshannyy Aviatsionny Polk'' (2 GSAP—2nd Soviet Guards Composite Aviation Division), which lost ten Hurricanes destroyed and three damaged.&lt;ref&gt;Bergström &amp; Mikhailov 2001, pp. 148–149.&lt;/ref&gt; He claimed his 20th victory on 15 May when he shot down a Hurricane {{Convert|4|km|mi|abbr=on|sp=us}} west of Murmansk. In June 1942, JG&amp;nbsp;5 was augmented by another group, VI. ''[[Luftwaffe Organization#Gruppe|Gruppe]]'' (4th Group) under the command of ''[[Hauptmann]]'' Hans Kriegel. This led to a number of ''Staffel'' redesignations. Weissenberger's 10.(Z) ''Staffel'' was renamed as 13.(Z) ''Staffel'' and remained subordinated to JG&amp;nbsp;5. He transferred from the reserve force to active service and was promoted to ''[[Leutnant]]'' (second lieutenant) on 1 July 1942.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p277&quot; /&gt; In early September he was transferred to 6. ''Staffel'' of JG&amp;nbsp;5, now flying the single-engine, single-seat, [[Messerschmitt Bf 109]] fighter. By this date, Weissenberger, as a ''Zerstörer'' pilot, had claimed 23 aerial victories in addition to 15 locomotives, 2 [[Anti-aircraft warfare|FLAK]] installations, a radio station, a railway station and other ground targets destroyed and was awarded the [[German Cross]] in Gold ({{lang|de|''Deutsches Kreuz in Gold''}}) on 8 September 1942.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman p49&quot;&gt;Bowman 2008, p. 49.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Obermaier p58&quot;&gt;Obermaier 1989, p. 58.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p278&quot;&gt;Stockert 2007, p. 278.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross ===
At the time, 6. ''Staffel'' at the time was based in [[Pechenga (urban-type settlement), Murmansk Oblast|Petsamo]], present-day Pechenga in [[Murmansk Oblast]], Russia. Weissenberger took off on his first Bf&amp;nbsp;109 combat mission at 14:00 on 15 September 1942 after he had spent a few days familiarizing himself with the single-engine fighter aircraft. The mission, flown by 10 Bf&amp;nbsp;109 fighters from 6. ''Staffel'', was a [[combat air patrol]] in the vicinity of [[Murmashi]]. The flight encountered enemy aircraft and Weissenberger filed claims over two [[Curtiss P-40 Warhawk]] [[Lend-Lease]] fighters shot down at 14:31 and 14:33. These were his first victories claimed on the Bf&amp;nbsp;109, taking his total to 25 victories. A week later, on 22 September, Weissenberger and 6. ''Staffel'' were again patrolling the airspace near the Soviet airfield at Murmashi. During this mission, he claimed three more aerial victories, over Hurricanes shot down between 14:59 and 15:05.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p278&quot; /&gt;

On 27 September 1942, Weissenberger claimed five victories during the course of two combat missions. During the first mission, he shot down a [[Bell P-39 Airacobra]] at 11:36. On his second mission, which began at 15:00, he encountered a formation of roughly 30 aircraft, claiming four Hurricanes shot down from 15:49 to 15:56, a time space of seven minutes. This &quot;ace-in-a-day&quot; achievement took his total to 33 aerial victories. On 22 October 1942, Weissenberger was tasked with fighter protection for a reconnaissance aircraft. The engine of his [[Focke Wulf Fw 190]] F-4 seized up just west of Murmansk. He managed to nurse his aircraft back to the German lines before [[Parachute|bailing out]]. He was picked up eight hours later by a ''[[Gebirgsjäger]]'' (mountain infantry) patrol and brought back to his ''Staffel''. Following this event he was given one week of rest. He returned to combat on 30 October 1942, and during two combat missions again achieved &quot;ace-in-a-day&quot; status. He claimed three victories on his first mission and two P-40s at 15:00 and 15:06 on his second mission of the day. This took his total to 38 aerial victories and he was honored with the presentation of the [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross]] ({{lang|de|''Ritterkreuz des Eisernen Kreuzes''}}) on 13 November 1942.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p278&quot; /&gt;

Following the winter break, Weissenberger claimed 33 further victories between 6–28 March 1943. Often he achieved multiple victories per day; six claims on 10 March, victories 43 to 48 on 10 March, victories 49 to 53 on 12 March, and numbers 54 to 57 on 13 March. A [[ground attack]] mission against the airfield at [[Salmiyarvi]] on 28 March was his last action of the month. Weissenberger claimed three P-39s shot down during this mission, but was himself hit by [[anti-aircraft artillery|anti-aircraft fire]] and had to make a [[forced landing]]. He was picked up and returned by a [[Fiesler Fi 156]] &quot;Storch&quot;. On 13 April 1943, a flight of five aircraft from 6. ''Staffel'' claimed 18 Soviet aircraft destroyed without loss. Six of the enemy aircraft were credited to Weissenberger, shot down between 17:05 and 17:16. This took his score to 77 aerial victories. On 13 May, he claimed four P-39s destroyed, representing victories 83 to 86, and he was promoted to ''Oberleutnant'' on 1 June 1943.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p279&quot; /&gt;

=== Oak Leaves to the Knight's Cross ===
Weissenberger claimed another five victories on 8 June 1943 north of Murmansk between 17:15 and 17:23. This brought his score to 91 aerial victories and on 15 June he was appointed ''[[Staffelkapitän]]'' (squadron leader) of 7. ''Staffel'' of JG&amp;nbsp;5. In the period 15 June to 4 July, 7. ''Staffel'' claimed 122 aerial victories under his leadership. The heaviest fighting occurred on 22 June over the [[Karelia]] Front, during which his ''Staffel'' claimed 13 victories, of which three were Hurricanes shot down by Weissenberger. A day later, he again claimed three aircraft shot down, comprising victories 95 to 97.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p279&quot; /&gt;

On 4 July 1943, Weissenberger led 7. ''Staffel'' to 16 aerial victories, while providing fighter cover for a departing German naval task force. First, Weissenberger claimed a Pe-2 reconnaissance aircraft shot down at 21:07. A flight of 25 to 30 enemy bombers and torpedo bombers was then spotted at 21:50. Weissenberger claimed an [[Ilyushin Il-2]] &quot;Sturmovik&quot; at 21:54, his 100th aerial victory.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p279&quot; /&gt; He was the 43rd ''Luftwaffe'' pilot to achieve the century mark.&lt;ref&gt;Obermaier 1989, p. 244.&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Staffel'' returned to its airfield at 22:19 without having sustained any losses during the encounter. Weissenberger alone had claimed seven victories during this mission, taking his total to 104 victories.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p280&quot;&gt;Stockert 2007, p. 280.&lt;/ref&gt; On 10 July 1943, this achievement earned him his first mention in the ''[[Wehrmachtbericht]]'', an information bulletin issued by the headquarters of the Wehrmacht.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wehrmachtberichte B2p513&quot;&gt;''Die Wehrmachtberichte 1939–1945 Band 2'', p. 513.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Oak Leaves ceremony August 1943 Rastenburg.jpg|thumb|left|Schröer, Ehrler, Prinz zur Lippe-Weißenfeld, Lent, Meurer, Kirschner and Weissenberger (right) at Rastenburg.|alt=Seven men wearing peaked caps and military uniforms standing in a row.]]
He achieved &quot;ace-in-a-day&quot; status for the fourth time on 25 July 1943, claiming aerial victories numbers 108 to 112. Following his 112th victory, he was awarded the [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves]] ({{lang|de|''Ritterkreuz des Eisernen Kreuzes mit Eichenlaub''}}) on 2 August 1943, the 266th member of the Wehrmacht to be so honored. The presentation was made by [[Adolf Hitler]] at the [[Wolf's Lair]], Hitler's headquarters in [[Rastenburg]], present-day Kętrzyn in Poland. Five other ''Luftwaffe'' officers were presented with awards that day by Hitler, ''Hauptmann'' [[Egmont Prinz zur Lippe-Weißenfeld]], ''Hauptmann'' [[Manfred Meurer]], ''Hauptmann'' [[Heinrich Ehrler]], ''Oberleutnant'' [[Joachim Kirschner]], ''Hauptmann'' [[Werner Schröer]] were also awarded the Oak Leaves, and ''[[Major (Germany)|Major]]'' [[Helmut Lent]] received the Swords to his Knight's Cross with Oak Leaves.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p280&quot; /&gt;

Weissenberger was placed in command of 6. ''Staffel'' on 14 September 1943 and in October and November added five more victories to his score, four of which were achieved on 3 November over the [[Rybachy Peninsula]]. At the end of 1943, II. ''Gruppe'' (2nd Group) was ordered to relocate further south to the front near [[Nevel (town)|Nevel]], [[Leningrad]] and [[Lake Ilmen]]. Relocating from [[Pskov]], 6. ''Staffel'' arrived at their new airfield at [[Idritsa]] on 11 November 1943 and was in action again on 17 November. In January 1944, II. Gruppe was subordinated to [[Luftflotte 2|''Luftflotte'' 2]] (2nd Air Fleet) in the middle sector of the Eastern Front in support of the defensive battles at [[Vitebsk]]. The ''Staffel'' flew combat missions from [[Orsha]] and [[Polotsk]]. Between 10:50 to 10:58 on 1 February 1944, Weissenberger achieved his fifth &quot;ace-in-a-day&quot;, taking his total to 124. On 28 February, he claimed his 140th aerial victory.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p280&quot; /&gt;

At the end of February 1944, II. ''Gruppe'' relocated again to Polotsk and then to Jakobstadt, present-day [[Jēkabpils]] in Latvia, and on 16 March Weissenberger claimed his 141st victory.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p280&quot; /&gt; Among his four victories claimed on 20 March were three Il-2 ground attack aircraft. On 25 March 1944, another &quot;ace-in-a-day&quot; achievement saw his total increase to 153 aerial victories. In late March 1944, II. ''Gruppe'' was transferred to the far north again, and was based at [[Alakurtti (rural locality)|Alakurtti]]. Here they defended against the [[Vyborg–Petrozavodsk Offensive]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p281&quot;&gt;Stockert 2007, p. 281.&lt;/ref&gt;

Weissenberger was appointed ''[[Gruppenkommandeur]]'' (group commander) of II. ''Gruppe'' of JG&amp;nbsp; 5 on 26 March 1944. He claimed three aircraft shot down on 4 April, and four more on 9 April, taking his victories from 159 to 162. At the end of April 1944, II. ''Gruppe'' relocated to Jakobstadt, withdrawing from the Arctic Front for the last time. On 17 May he claimed victories 169 to 172, and the next day shot down three [[Yakovlev Yak-9]]s, taking his total to 175. These were his last victories on the Eastern Front. At the end of May 1944, II. ''Gruppe'' was transferred to [[Defense of the Reich]] duties and was relocated to [[Gardelegen Airfield]] in Germany.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p281&quot; /&gt;

=== Combat on the Western Front ===
Weissenberger was promoted to ''Hauptmann'' on 1 June 1944. On 3 June he arrived in [[Herzogenaurach]] to take over command of I. ''Gruppe'' (1st Group) of JG&amp;nbsp;5. The former ''Gruppenkommandeur'' ''Major'' [[Horst Carganico]] had been killed in a flying accident on 27 May 1944. Three days after Weissenberger took command, the Allied [[invasion of Normandy]] began. To counter the invasion, elements of I./JG&amp;nbsp;5 were transported to France by train that afternoon. The ground personnel were flown on [[Junkers Ju 52]]s to their airfield at [[Montdidier, Somme|Montdidier]], {{Convert|35|km|mi|abbr=on|sp=us}} south of [[Amiens]]. The following day, Weissenberger took I. ''Gruppe'' into combat, achieving &quot;ace-in-a-day&quot; status once again on his first day of combat on the [[Western Front (World War II)|Western Front]]. His 176th victory was over a [[Republic P-47 Thunderbolt]] shot down at 09:05. He claimed two further P-47s shot down 20 minutes later. I. ''Gruppe'' was scrambled again in the afternoon which resulted in aerial combat with roughly 12 P-47s near [[Beauvais]]. During the course of this encounter, which ended at 17:39, Weissenberger claimed two P-47s shot down.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p281&quot; /&gt;

On 8 June the final elements of I. ''Gruppe'' arrived in Montdidier, making the unit complete. In the evening Weissenberger again claimed two P-47s shot down, his 181st and 182nd aerial victories. The airfield at Montdidier came under heavy [[fighter bomber]] attack on 11 June followed by another attack on 12 June resulting in significant damage to the airfield.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p281&quot; /&gt; On 12 June Weissenberger filed a claim for three aerial victories. Together with his wingman, ''[[Unteroffizier]]'' (Sergeant) Alfred Tichy, he took off at 06:00 and during the course of 12 minutes shot down three P-47s. After his first victory, Tichy was [[killed in action]], crashing near [[Évreux]]. At 07:02 Weissenberger shot down his third P-47 of the day but his Bf 109 G-5 was hit in the engine forcing him to bail out near [[Saint-André-de-l'Eure|Saint André]]. The airfield in Montdidier was rendered unserviceable and I. ''Gruppe'' was forced to relocate. It was first moved to [[Péronne, Somme|Péronne]], then to [[Chauny]], a makeshift airfield between [[Noyon]] and [[Tergnier]]. The constant attacks against German airfields forced another move in July 1944, this time to [[Frières-Faillouël|Frières]] in the vicinity of [[Laon]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p282&quot;&gt;Stockert 2007, p. 282.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-2008-1118-501, Theodor Weißenberger.jpg|thumb|right|Weissenberger on 4 October 1944|alt=Black-and-white portrait of a man wearing a peaked cap and military flight suit with an Iron Cross displayed at his neck. He is holding a sheet of paper in his left hand and appears to be talking to a larger audience.]]
II. ''Gruppe'' flew a combat air patrol on 6 July 1944, resulting in the claim of three [[Lockheed P-38 Lightning]]s destroyed. Weissenberger was credited with two of these victories, the first at 08:48 and the second at 08:49, both shot down south of [[Cambrai]]. The next day, the ''Gruppe'' took off heading for the airspace south of [[Rosières-en-Santerre|Rosières]] where they engaged a formation of 15 to 20 P-47s. During this encounter, Weissenberger claimed three victories, numbers 188 to 190. The ''Gruppe'' was given a few days of rest and on 13 July were ordered to operate against enemy fighter bombers attacking German positions in the area [[Rouen]] – [[Bernay, Eure|Bernay]] – Évreux. During this mission, he shot down a [[Hawker Typhoon]] at 18:24 near [[Trouville-la-Haule|Trouville]] and another one two minutes later. They were then tasked with a fighter bomber mission on 14 July, attacking enemy positions near [[Caen]]. After a number of ground [[strafing]] attacks they themselves came under attack of numerous [[Supermarine Spitfire]]s and P-47s. Flying at a height of {{Convert|10|m|ft|abbr=off|sp=us}}, Weissenberger managed to shoot down one Spitfire {{Convert|5|km|mi|abbr=on|sp=us}} south of [[Bayeux]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p282&quot; /&gt;

The commanding general of [[2nd Fighter Corps (Germany)|II. ''Jagdkorps'']] (2nd Fighter Corps), ''[[Generalleutnant]]'' [[Alfred Bülowius]], accompanied by ''[[Oberstleutnant]]'' [[Herbert Ihlefeld]] inspected II. ''Gruppe'' at their airfield in Frières on 15 July 1944. On 17 July, Weissenberger led his ''Gruppe'' on a number of missions in the combat area near Caen without encountering any enemy aircraft. On their last mission of the day, having taken off at 19:00, they encountered enemy fighter bombers near Caen – [[Le Mesnil-Bacley|Le Mesnil]]. During aerial combat, the ''Gruppe'' lost three pilots without any success for themselves. On 19 July 1944, I. ''Gruppe'' was tasked with flying top cover for [[Jagdgeschwader 2|''Jagdgeschwader'' 2]] &quot;Richthofen&quot; and [[Jagdgeschwader 26|''Jagdgeschwader'' 26]] &quot;Schlageter&quot;. During this mission, Weissenberger claimed four aerial victories. At 20:22 he shot down his first Typhoon of the mission north of [[Lisieux]], another Typhoon one minute later and his third at 20:25 northwest of [[Cormeilles, Eure|Cormeilles]]. His fourth victory was over a [[North American P-51 Mustang]], shot down at 20:35 near [[Charleval, Eure|Charleval]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p282&quot; /&gt;

On 25 July 1944, the ''Gruppe'' was again tasked with a combat air patrol mission in the greater Caen area. Weissenberger received the order to take off at 10:30 and at 11:00 they spotted Spitfires in the vicinity of Rouen. In the ensuing aerial encounter at an altitude of {{Convert|3,800|m|ft|abbr=on|sp=us}}, Weissenberger shot down a Spitfire {{Convert|15|km|mi|abbr=on|sp=us}} south of Rouen. This was his 199th aerial victory.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p282&quot; /&gt; Two minutes later, at 11:02, he shot down his 200th opponent. This achievement earned him his second mention in the ''Wehrmachtbericht'' on 26 July 1944. Weissenberger left the ''Gruppe'' on 30 July 1944 and went on vacation to [[Bad Wiessee]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p283&quot;&gt;Stockert 2007, p. 283.&lt;/ref&gt;

His I. ''Gruppe'' was withdrawn from combat and moved to [[Wunstorf]] for a period of rest and conversion training to the Bf&amp;nbsp;109 G-14. The ground personnel were transferred to II. ''Gruppe'' of [[Jagdgeschwader 6|''Jagdgeschwader'' 6]] (JG 6—6th Fighter Wing). Conversion training ended in October 1944 and I. ''Gruppe'' was disbanded shortly after and became III. ''Gruppe'' (3rd Group) of JG 6 on 14 October. On 24 October 1944 Weissenberger was ordered to [[Chojna|Königsberg in der Neumark]], present-day Chojna in Poland. At Königsberg, he was given command of the newly forming I. ''Gruppe'' of [[Jagdgeschwader 7|''Jagdgeschwader'' 7]] &quot;Nowotny&quot; (JG 7—7th Fighter Wing).&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p283&quot; /&gt;

=== Flying the Messerschmitt Me 262 ===
JG&amp;nbsp;7 &quot;Nowotny&quot; was the first operational jet fighter [[Wing (air force unit)|wing]] in the world and was named after [[Walter Nowotny]], who was killed in action on 8 November 1944. Nowotny, a fighter pilot credited with 258 aerial victories and recipient of the [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves, Swords and Diamonds]] ({{lang|de|''Ritterkreuz des Eisernen Kreuzes mit Eichenlaub, Schwertern und Brillanten''}}), had been assessing the [[Messerschmitt Me 262]] [[jet aircraft]] under operational conditions.&lt;ref&gt;Forsyth 2008, pp. 6–10.&lt;/ref&gt; JG&amp;nbsp;7 &quot;Nowotny&quot; was equipped with the Me&amp;nbsp;262, an aircraft which was heavily armed and faster than any [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] fighter. ''[[General der Jagdflieger]]'' (General of the Fighter Force) [[Adolf Galland]] hoped that the Me&amp;nbsp;262 would compensate for the Allies' numerical superiority. On 12 November 1944, the ''[[Oberkommando der Luftwaffe]]'' (OKL—Air Force High Command) ordered JG&amp;nbsp;7 &quot;Nowotny&quot; to be equipped with the Me&amp;nbsp;262. Galland appointed ''[[Oberst]]'' [[Johannes Steinhoff]] as its first ''[[Geschwaderkommodore]]'' (wing commander).&lt;ref&gt;Forsyth 2008, p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Messerschmitt Me 262 at Evergreen Aviation Museum.jpg|thumb|left|An Me 262 of JG 7 similar to those flown by Weissenberger on display at the [[Evergreen Aviation &amp; Space Museum]].|alt=A color photo of a twin engine jet-fighter aircraft standing in a hangar.]]
JG&amp;nbsp;7 &quot;Nowotny&quot; was initially formed with the ''[[Stab (Luftwaffe designation)|Stab]]'' (headquarters unit) and III. ''Gruppe''  at [[Brandenburg an der Havel|Brandenburg]]-[[Havelsee|Briest]] from the remnants of ''[[Kommando Nowotny]]''. I. ''Gruppe'' was created on 27 November from pilots and personnel from II. ''Gruppe'' of [[Jagdgeschwader 3|''Jagdgeschwader'' 3]] &quot;Udet&quot; (JG 3—3rd Fighter Wing) and placed under the command of Weissenberger.&lt;ref&gt;Forsyth 2008, p. 20.&lt;/ref&gt; Weissenberger’s appointed ''Staffelkapitäne'' in I. ''Gruppe'' were ''Oberleutnant'' [[Hans Grünberg]], ''Oberleutnant'' Fritz Stehle, and ''Oberleutnant'' [[Hans Waldmann (fighter pilot)|Hans Waldmann]], commanding 1.–3. ''Staffel'' respectively.&lt;ref&gt;Forsyth 2008, p. 21.&lt;/ref&gt;

On [[New Year's Day]] 1945, Weissenberger married his teenage-love Cilly Vogel in [[Langenselbold]] near [[Hanau]]. [[Best man]] at his [[wedding]] was his former JG&amp;nbsp;5 comrade and friend [[Walter Schuck]].&lt;ref&gt;Schuck 2007, p. 184.&lt;/ref&gt; Schuck succeeded Waldmann as ''Staffelkapitän'' of the 3. ''Staffel'' following the latter's death in a flying accident on 18 March 1945.&lt;ref&gt;Schuck 2007, p. 204.&lt;/ref&gt;

Weissenberger was promoted to ''Major'' on 1 January 1945 and replaced Steinhoff as ''Geschwaderkommodore'' of JG&amp;nbsp;7 &quot;Nowotny&quot; shortly after. Both Galland and Steinhoff, among others, were relieved of their commands in the aftermath of the [[Fighter Pilots' Revolt]] in early 1945.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p283&quot; /&gt;

Under his command, JG&amp;nbsp;7 &quot;Nowotny&quot; achieved some success before the [[end of World War II in Europe]] on 8 May 1945. On 18 March 1945, JG&amp;nbsp;7 &quot;Nowotny&quot; claimed 25 aerial victories over [[Berlin]], among them three [[Boeing B-17 Flying Fortress]]es shot down by Weissenberger.&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;For a list of ''Luftwaffe'' jet aces see [[list of German World War II jet aces]].&lt;/ref&gt; Over all, he achieved eight confirmed victories, seven B-17 bombers and a P-51 fighter, while flying the Me&amp;nbsp;262. Weissenberger survived the war and was credited with a total of 208 aerial victories, including 33 over the Western Front, claimed in 375 combat missions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p283&quot; /&gt;{{refn|According to Obermaier, Weissenberger flew more than 500 combat missions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Obermaier p58&quot; /&gt;|group=&quot;Note&quot;}}

== Later life ==
[[File:Circuit Nürburgring-1967-Nordschleife.svg|thumb|right|The Nürburgring circuit. Weissenberger's accident occurred in the vicinity of Metzgesfeld (upper left corner).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |work=Pro Steilstrecke |title=15. Eifelrennen |url=http://www.pro-steilstrecke.de/eifelrennen/nuerburgring_eifelrennen_1950.htm |language=German |accessdate=22 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;|alt=A map of a race track with various points of interest textually identified.]]
Weissenberger became a motor racing driver after the war, and was killed at the [[Nürburgring]] circuit on 11 June 1950, when his modified [[BMW 328]] single seater ([[Veritas (automobile)|Veritas]]), start number 15, crashed on the first lap of the ''XV [[Eifelrennen]]'', a [[Formula Two]] motor race.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bowman p49&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;For a list of fatal accidents on the Nürburgring see [[list of Nürburgring fatalities]].&lt;/ref&gt;

== Awards ==
Weissenberger received the following awards:
* [[Iron Cross]] (1939 variant)
** 2nd Class  (6 November 1941)&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomas p430&quot;&gt;Thomas 1998, p. 430.&lt;/ref&gt;
** 1st Class (17 February 1942)&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomas p430&quot; /&gt;
* [[Ehrenpokal der Luftwaffe]] on 1 July 1942 as ''[[Oberfeldwebel]]'' and pilot&lt;ref&gt;Patzwall 2008, p. 215.&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|According to Obermaier on 28 May 1942.&lt;ref name=&quot;Obermaier p58&quot; /&gt;|group=&quot;Note&quot;}}
* [[German Cross]] in Gold on 8 September 1942 as ''[[Oberfeldwebel]]'' in the 10.(ZS)/JG 5&lt;ref&gt;Patzwall &amp; Scherzer 2001, p. 504.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves]]
** Knight's Cross on 13 November 1942 as ''[[Leutnant]]'' (war officer) and pilot in the 6./JG 5&lt;ref name=&quot;Scherzer p776&quot;&gt;Scherzer 2007, p. 776.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fellgiebel 2000, p. 441.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Von Seemen 1976, p. 355.&lt;/ref&gt;
** 266th Oak Leaves  on 2 August 1943 as ''[[Oberleutnant]]'' (war officer) and ''[[Staffelkapitän]]'' of the 7./JG 5&lt;ref name=&quot;Scherzer p776&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fellgiebel 2000, p. 70.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Von Seemen 1976, p. 36.&lt;/ref&gt;
* Mentioned twice in the [[Wehrmachtbericht]]

In addition, Weissenberger was also recommended for the [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves and Swords]] ({{lang|de|''Ritterkreuz des Eisernen Kreuzes mit Eichenlaub und Schwertern''}}) by Steinhoff after his 200th aerial victory.  The recommendation was received by the ''Oberkommando der Luftwaffe''/''Luftwaffenpersonalamt'' (OKL/LP—Air Force High Command/Air Force Staff Office) on  29 January 1945, but was declined on 20 February 1945.&lt;ref&gt;Berger 2000, p. 395.&lt;/ref&gt; At the time, 240 aerial victories were required for the Swords to be awarded.&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p283&quot; /&gt;

=== Dates of rank ===
{| style=&quot;background:none;&quot;
|-
| 1 December 1940: || ''[[Feldwebel]]'' (Technical Sergeant) of the [[Military reserve force|Reserves]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p277&quot; /&gt;
|-
| 1 February 1942: || ''[[Oberfeldwebel]]'' (Master Sergeant) of the Reserves&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p277&quot; /&gt;
|-
| 1 July 1942: || ''[[Leutnant]]'' (Second Lieutenant)&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p277&quot; /&gt;
|-
| 1 June 1943: || ''[[Oberleutnant]]'' (First Lieutenant)&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p279&quot; /&gt;
|-
| 1 June 1944: || ''[[Hauptmann]]'' (Captain)&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p281&quot; /&gt;
|-
| 1 January 1945: || ''[[Major (Germany)|Major]]'' (Major)&lt;ref name=&quot;Stockert p283&quot; /&gt;
|}

== Notes ==
{{Reflist|group=&quot;Note&quot;}}

== References ==

=== Citations ===
{{Reflist|25em}}

=== Bibliography ===
{{Refbegin}}
* {{cite book
  |last=Berger
  |first=Florian
  |year=1999
  |title=Mit Eichenlaub und Schwertern. Die höchstdekorierten Soldaten des Zweiten Weltkrieges
  |trans_title=With Oak Leaves and Swords. The Highest Decorated Soldiers of the Second World War
  |language=German
  |location=Vienna, Austria
  |publisher=Selbstverlag Florian Berger
  |isbn=978-3-9501307-0-6
}}
* {{cite book
  |last1=Bergström
  |first1=Christer
  |last2=Mikhailov
  |first2=Andrey
  |year=2001
  |title=Black Cross/Red Star: Air War Over the Eastern Front, Volume II, Resurgence January–June 1942
  |location=Pacifica, California
  |publisher=Pacifica Military History
  |isbn=978-0-935553-51-2
}}
* {{cite book
  |last=Boehme
  |first=Manfred
  |year=1992
  |title=JG 7 The World's First Jet Fighter Unit 1944/1945
  |place=Atglen, PA
  |publisher=[[Schiffer Publishing]]
  |isbn=978-0-88740-395-8
}}
* {{cite book
  |last=Bowman
  |first=Martin
  |year=2008
  |title=P-47 Thunderbolt Vs. Bf 109G/K: Europe 1943–45
  |location=Oxford, UK
  |publisher=[[Osprey Publishing]]
  |isbn=978-1-84603-315-5
}}
* {{cite book
  |last=Fellgiebel
  |first=Walther-Peer
  |authorlink=Walther-Peer Fellgiebel
  |year=2000
  |origyear=1986
  |title=Die Träger des Ritterkreuzes des Eisernen Kreuzes 1939–1945 — Die Inhaber der höchsten Auszeichnung des Zweiten Weltkrieges aller Wehrmachtteile
  |trans_title=The Bearers of the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross 1939–1945 — The Owners of the Highest Award of the Second World War of all Wehrmacht Branches
  |language=German
  |location=Friedberg, Germany
  |publisher=Podzun-Pallas
  |isbn=978-3-7909-0284-6
}}
* {{cite book
  |last1=Forsyth
  |first1=Robert
  |year=2008
  |title=Jagdgeschwader 7 'Nowotny''
  |location=Oxford, UK
  |publisher=Osprey Publishing
  |isbn=978-1-84603-320-9
}}
* {{cite book
  |last=Obermaier
  |first=Ernst
  |year=1989
  |title=Die Ritterkreuzträger der Luftwaffe Jagdflieger 1939–1945
  |trans_title=The Knight's Cross Bearers of the Luftwaffe Fighter Force 1939–1945
  |language=German
  |location=Mainz, Germany
  |publisher=Verlag Dieter Hoffmann
  |isbn=978-3-87341-065-7
}}
* {{cite book
  |last1=Patzwall
  |first1=Klaus D.
  |last2=Scherzer
  |first2=Veit
  |year=2001
  |title=Das Deutsche Kreuz 1941–1945 Geschichte und Inhaber Band II
  |trans_title=The German Cross 1941–1945 History and Recipients Volume 2
  |language=German
  |location=Norderstedt, Germany
  |publisher=Verlag Klaus D. Patzwall
  |isbn=978-3-931533-45-8
}}
* {{cite book
  |last1=Patzwall
  |first1=Klaus D.
  |year=2008
  |title=Der Ehrenpokal für besondere Leistung im Luftkrieg
  |trans_title=The Honor Goblet for Outstanding Achievement in the Air War
  |language=German
  |location=Norderstedt, Germany
  |publisher=Verlag Klaus D. Patzwall
  |isbn=978-3-931533-08-3
}}
* {{cite book
  |last=Scherzer
  |first=Veit
  |year=2007
  |title=Die Ritterkreuzträger 1939–1945 Die Inhaber des Ritterkreuzes des Eisernen Kreuzes 1939 von Heer, Luftwaffe, Kriegsmarine, Waffen-SS, Volkssturm sowie mit Deutschland verbündeter Streitkräfte nach den Unterlagen des Bundesarchives
  |trans_title=The Knight's Cross Bearers 1939–1945 The Holders of the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross 1939 by Army, Air Force, Navy, Waffen-SS, Volkssturm and Allied Forces with Germany According to the Documents of the Federal Archives
  |language=German
  |location=Jena, Germany
  |publisher=Scherzers Militaer-Verlag
  |isbn=978-3-938845-17-2
}}
* {{cite book
  |last=Schuck
  |first=Walter
  |authorlink=Walter Schuck
  |year=2007
  |title=Abschuss! Von der Me 109 zur Me 262 Erinnerungen an die Luftkämpfe beim Jagdgeschwader 5 und 7
  |trans_title=Victory! From the Me 109 to the Me 262 Memories of the Dogfights with Fighter Wing 5 and 7
  |language=German
  |location=Aachen, Germany
  |publisher=Helios Verlags- und Buchvertriebsgesellschaft
  |isbn=978-3-938208-44-1
}}
* {{cite book
  |last=Stockert
  |first=Peter
  |year=1997
  |title=Die Eichenlaubträger 1939–1945 Band 3
  |trans_title=The Oak Leaves Bearers 1939–1945 Volume 3
  |language=German
  |location=Bad Friedrichshall, Germany
  |publisher=Friedrichshaller Rundblick
  |isbn=978-3-932915-01-7
}}
* {{cite book
  |last=Thomas
  |first=Franz
  |year=1998
  |title=Die Eichenlaubträger 1939–1945 Band 2: L–Z
  |trans_title=The Oak Leaves Bearers 1939–1945 Volume 2: L–Z
  |language=German
  |location=Osnabrück, Germany
  |publisher=Biblio-Verlag
  |isbn=978-3-7648-2300-9
}}
* {{cite book
  |last=Von Seemen
  |first=Gerhard
  |year=1976
  |title=Die Ritterkreuzträger 1939–1945 : die Ritterkreuzträger sämtlicher Wehrmachtteile, Brillanten-, Schwerter- und Eichenlaubträger in der Reihenfolge der Verleihung : Anhang mit Verleihungsbestimmungen und weiteren Angaben
  |trans_title=The Knight's Cross Bearers 1939–1945 : The Knight's Cross Bearers of All the Armed Services, Diamonds, Swords and Oak Leaves Bearers in the Order of Presentation: Appendix with Further Information and Presentation Requirements
  |language=German
  |location=Friedberg, Germany
  |publisher=Podzun-Verlag
  |isbn=978-3-7909-0051-4
}}
* {{cite book
  |year=1985
  |title=Die Wehrmachtberichte 1939–1945 Band 2, 1. Januar 1942 bis 31. Dezember 1943
  |trans_title=The Wehrmacht Reports 1939–1945 Volume 2, 1 January 1942 to 31 December 1943
  |language=German
  |location=München, Germany
  |publisher=Deutscher Taschenbuch Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KG
  |isbn=978-3-423-05944-2
}}
* {{cite book
  |year=1985
  |title=Die Wehrmachtberichte 1939–1945 Band 3, 1. Januar 1944 bis 9. Mai 1945
  |trans_title=The Wehrmacht Reports 1939–1945 Volume 3, 1 January 1944 to 9 May 1945
  |language=German
  |location=München, Germany
  |publisher=Deutscher Taschenbuch Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KG
  |isbn=978-3-423-05944-2
}}
* {{cite book
  |last=Ziefle
  |first=Michael
  |year=2013
  |title=Messerschmitt Bf 110: Die Rehabilitierung eines Flugzeuges
  |trans_title=Messerschmitt Bf 110: The Rehabilitation of an Airplane
  |language=German
  |location=Norderstedt, Germany
  |publisher=Books on Demand
  |isbn=978-3-8482-8879-3
}}
{{Refend}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-mil}}
{{succession box
|before=''[[Oberstleutnant]]'' [[Johannes Steinhoff]]
|after=none
|title=Commander of [[Jagdgeschwader 7|''Jagdgeschwader'' 7]] ''Nowotny''
|years=1 January 1945 – 8 May 1945
}}
{{s-end}}

{{KCwithOL}}
{{Knight's Cross recipients of JG 5}}
{{Top German World War II Aces}}
{{German World War II jet aces}}
{{Subject bar
| portal1=Aviation
| portal2=Biography
| portal3=Military of Germany
| portal4=World War II
| portal5=Motorsport
| commons=y
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Weissenberger, Theodor}}
[[Category:1914 births]]
[[Category:1950 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Mühlheim am Main]]
[[Category:Luftwaffe pilots]]
[[Category:German World War II flying aces]]
[[Category:People from the Grand Duchy of Hesse]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Gold German Cross]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross with Oak Leaves]]
[[Category:Military personnel referenced in the Wehrmachtbericht]]
[[Category:German racing drivers]]
[[Category:Formula Two drivers]]
[[Category:Racing drivers killed while racing]]
[[Category:Sport deaths in Germany]]</text>
      <sha1>mt011bee1gfp3s3k5i0gkmlujbxegz0</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
