<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Trương Định</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>13530776</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748270241</id>
      <parentid>748180537</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-07T09:31:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Good Olfactory</username>
        <id>6454287</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>added [[Category:Vietnamese Confucianists]] using [[WP:HC|HotCat]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="46414">{{Use mdy dates|date=June 2012}}
{{Vietnamese name|Trương|Định}}
{{Infobox person
|name=Trương Định&lt;br /&gt;[[wikt:張|張]] [[wikt:定|定]]
|image=Truong Dinh.JPG
|caption=Trương Định, 19th century Vietnamese anti-colonial military commander
|other_names   =Trương Công Định
|birth_date= 1820
|birth_place=[[Bình Sơn District|Bình Sơn]], [[Quảng Ngãi Province|Quảng Ngãi]], Vietnam
|death_date=August 19, {{death year and age|1864|1820}}
|death_place=[[Biên Hòa]], Vietnam
|organization =[[Nguyễn dynasty]]
|religion=[[Confucianism]]
|footnotes=Refused an appointment to a [[mandarin (bureaucrat)|mandarin]] post in [[An Giang Province|An Giang]]
}}
{{Contains Vietnamese text}}

'''Trương Định''' (1820 &amp;ndash; August 19, 1864), sometimes known as '''Trương Công Định''',  was a [[mandarin (bureaucrat)|mandarin]] in the [[Nguyễn dynasty]] of [[Vietnam]] under Emperor [[Tự Đức]]. He is best known for leading a ''guerrilla'' army in southern Vietnam against the [[Conquest of Cochinchina|French invasion]] in defiance of the emperor.&lt;ref&gt;Nghia M. Vo ''Saigon: A History'' 2011 - Page 69 &quot;The best known guerrilla fighter was Trương Định or Trương Công Định. Born in central Vietnam in 1820 or 1821, he moved to Gia Định with his father, a colonel in the royal army, who was transferred there.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; He refused to recognise the 1862 [[Treaty of Saigon]] that ceded Vietnamese territory to France.

The son of a military mandarin from central Vietnam, Định moved south when his father was posted to [[Gia Định]] as the provincial commander. Định grew up to lead a military colony, overseeing the settlement and economic development of his constituency. He gained a reputation for being an able leader and land developer who cared for his people. When France began its invasion of southern Vietnam in 1859, Định organised local militia to reinforce the imperial army. As the regular army units suffered defeats on the battlefield, its remnants joined Định's partisans, and by 1861, he had around 6,000 men under his command. Định built his own resistance base and organised guerrilla attacks against the French. His success led Tự Đức to grant Định command of the southern partisans and to order the regular commanders to coordinate their plans with him. Định's forces quickly gained the respect of the French. They focused on disrupting the French bureaucracy and military posts in addition to the transportation of rice. Their most notable attack was the sinking of ''L'Espérance'' in December 1861.

Amid growing military setbacks, Vietnam signed the Treaty of Saigon in June 1862, losing three southern provinces which became the French colony of [[Cochinchina]]. Tự Đức hoped that by abiding by the treaty, Vietnam could eventually negotiate the future return of the territory. He ordered the partisans to disband, but Định refused to recognise the treaty and disobeyed the monarch, fighting on in defense of his homeland. With the loss of imperial support, Định's forces began to struggle against the superior resources of the French. His men were gradually worn down and, following an ambush, Định committed suicide to avoid being captured.

Vietnamese and French historians have fiercely debated Định's choice to disregard the treaty. The effectiveness of Định's insurgency led French officials to claim that Tự Đức was secretly assisting him, thereby violating the treaty, a pretext the French used to seize three more provinces in 1867. Vietnamese records dispute this, contending that Tự Đức attempted to ensure Định's compliance with the treaty. Định's defiance of the emperor has led historians to debate whether his actions were motivated by a rejection of the monarch's authority or whether he disobeyed in an attempt to help Tự Đức. Định remains widely respected among Vietnamese of all political persuasions. During the [[Vietnam War]], communist historians sought to portray the [[Viet Cong|Việt Cộng]] as Định's modern successor.

== Early years ==
Định was born in the [[Bình Sơn District]] in the [[Quảng Ngãi]] prefecture in [[Quảng Nam Province]] in central Vietnam.&lt;ref&gt;At the time, Quảng Ngãi was a part of Quảng Nam.&lt;/ref&gt; The son of a military mandarin named Trương Cầm, Định went south in the 1830s when his father was posted to [[Gia Định]] as the provincial commander.&lt;ref name=&quot;n426&quot;/&gt; Định enjoyed a reputation among the locals for his martial skills and knowledge of the military classics. He married the daughter of a wealthy resident of [[Tân An]] in nearby [[Dinh Tuong Province]], having moved there after his father's unexpected death. It was likely that he would have returned to central Vietnam if he had not married.&lt;ref&gt;Marr, pp. 30&amp;ndash;31.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;m91&quot;&gt;McLeod, p. 91.&lt;/ref&gt;

Định took advantage of his improved socio-economic status to recruit a group of impoverished people, whom he organised for clearing land and founding a ''đồn điền'' (&quot;military colony&quot;) in [[Gò Công]]. This occurred after Emperor Tự Đức's 1854 order, which granted General [[Nguyễn Tri Phương]] permission to organise southern levies in this manner. In recognition of his achievements, the mandarin authorities gave Định the rank of deputy regimental commander.&lt;ref name=&quot;m31&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;c121&quot;&gt;Chapuis, p. 121.&lt;/ref&gt; His success in developing ''đồn điền'' was attributed to his organisational ability as well as a genuine concern for the welfare of those under his protection, ensuring that they had enough to eat and something to wear.&lt;ref name=&quot;m31&quot;/&gt; He was regarded as energetic, brave and compassionate.&lt;ref name=&quot;n426&quot;&gt;Nguyen, p. 426.&lt;/ref&gt; In gratitude for Định's land development skills, the peasants gave him the middle name '''Công''', which means &quot;great public service&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Nguyen, p. 394.&lt;/ref&gt;

== French invasion in 1859 ==
The process of Vietnam's colonisation began in September 1858 when a Franco-Spanish force landed at [[Da Nang]] in central Vietnam and attempted to proceed to the capital, [[Huế]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Chapuis, p. 48&quot;&gt;Chapuis, p. 48.&lt;/ref&gt; After becoming tied down, they sailed to the less-defended south. The French and Spanish quickly captured the imperial [[Citadel of Saigon]] in February 1859—the fortress's commander committed suicide.&lt;ref name=&quot;m91&quot;/&gt; The citadel was razed and the substantial supplies were confiscated.&lt;ref&gt;Marr, p. 27.&lt;/ref&gt; The leaderless and defeated imperial troops fled in disarray.&lt;ref name=&quot;m91&quot;/&gt; The attacks were ordered by French Emperor [[Napoleon III]]. French diplomats, naval officers, merchants and missionaries had long advocated the expedition. The missionaries wanted the French administration to facilitate their work converting the Vietnamese to Roman Catholicism, while military and business figures saw commercial opportunities in Vietnam. Napoleon's motivations were primarily imperial, strategic and commercial, but he found it convenient to cite &quot;freedom of religion&quot; as his justification for taking action.&lt;ref name=&quot;m88&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Karnow, pp. 84&amp;ndash;88.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title= A History of South-east Asia| first= D. G. E.|last=Hall |location=London| publisher=Macmillan|origyear=1955 |year=1981|page=647|isbn=0-333-24163-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title= South East Asia: Its historical development| first= John F.|last=Cady | publisher=McGraw Hill|location=New York |pages= 414–416| origyear=1964| year=1976|oclc=15002777}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Nguyễn Dynasty was [[Confucian]]ist and had restricted the activity of missionaries. The belief system of Christianity was incompatible with the Confucian belief that the monarch was the &quot;son of heaven&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;m88&quot;&gt;McLeod, p. 88.&lt;/ref&gt;

In response to the razing of the Citadel of Saigon,&lt;ref name=&quot;n267&quot;&gt;Nguyen, p. 267.&lt;/ref&gt; Định organised his local levies into a ''guerrilla'' force that initially numbered between 500 and 1000 men, operating out of [[Thuan Kieu]].&lt;ref name=&quot;m91&quot;/&gt; They were armed with bladed spears, fire lances, knives, sabres, bamboo sticks and swords,&lt;ref name=&quot;m91&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;m31&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;n427&quot;/&gt; trained and on call as necessary. As a local notable who was respected for his leadership and military ability, Định naturally assumed a lead role in the partisan movement that responded to Tự Đức's appeals for popular resistance against European aggression.&lt;ref name=&quot;m91&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;m31&quot;&gt;Marr, p. 31.&lt;/ref&gt; In the initial phase of the conflict, the local militias concentrated on evacuating the populace from areas that had been taken over by the French, while urging those who chose to stay to not cooperate with the Europeans. Snipers were deployed into French areas to assassinate isolated soldiers.&lt;ref name=&quot;n267&quot;/&gt;

In 1861, Định moved his men to [[Tân Hòa, Bà Rịa–Vũng Tàu|Tân Hòa]] sub-prefecture in the [[Gò Công]] area.&lt;ref name=&quot;m91&quot;/&gt; Tan Hoa was an ideal location for a resistance base. It was close to newly formed resistance groups led by [[Nguyễn Trung Trực]], [[Tran Xuan Hoa]] and others in the Gò Công and [[Mỹ Tho]] area, yet was also close to Saigon.&lt;ref name=&quot;m31&quot;/&gt; In February, the French attacked the [[citadel of Ky Hoa]], seizing the fort after two days, along with a large quantity of weapons, artillery and food supplies.&lt;ref&gt;Chapuis, p. 49.&lt;/ref&gt; Having fought at Ky Hoa,&lt;ref name=&quot;l11&quot;/&gt; Định incorporated soldiers from the defeated imperial army into his ranks, because its commander [[Vo Duy Ninh]] had committed suicide.&lt;ref name=&quot;m91&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;c121&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Chapuis, p. 50.&lt;/ref&gt; In May 1861, Admiral [[Léonard Charner]] ordered the dissolution of the ''đồn điền'' of Gò Công. He went about confiscating the land of those Vietnamese who remained loyal to the monarchy, giving it to his collaborators. French impositions against the trade of rice via nearby waterways caused a further backlash from the locals of Gò Công.&lt;ref name=&quot;n424&quot;&gt;Nguyen, p. 424.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1861, the resistance leaders in the Gò Công area delegated Định to travel to [[Biên Hòa]] to seek permission from Imperial Military Commissioner [[Nguyen Ba Nghi]] to &quot;turn around the situation&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;n427&quot;&gt;Nguyen, p. 427.&lt;/ref&gt;

Appointed to the rank of lieutenant colonel,&lt;ref name=&quot;c121&quot;/&gt; Định began to stockpile foodstuffs, manufacture weapons, and recruit forces from the populace with the help of officers from the imperial army.&lt;ref name=&quot;m91&quot;/&gt; His forces grew to around 6,000 men by June 1861. The French began to report that junks from [[Singapore]] and Hong Kong had arrived in Gò Công with shipments of European-made weapons.&lt;ref name=&quot;n427&quot;/&gt; Định's forces began inflicting substantial damage on the European troops, largely because of their intimate knowledge of the terrain, skill in hit-and-run guerrilla tactics, and support from the local villagers.&lt;ref name=&quot;m92&quot;/&gt; Định's men focused on chasing French soldiers around the countryside and attacking military installations that were left undefended as a consequence of their guerrilla pursuit.&lt;ref name=&quot;n430&quot;&gt;Nguyen, p. 430.&lt;/ref&gt; Learning of Định's role in support of the Nguyễn dynasty's call for popular resistance, Tự Đức promoted him to the rank of lieutenant colonel for the Gia Định region. Later in 1861, the imperial regulars were defeated at [[Biên Hòa]],&lt;ref name=&quot;m92&quot;/&gt; and the commanding Vietnamese officers were ordered by the royal authorities to meet Định at Tan Hoa to develop a plan for retaking Biên Hòa. As a result, the number of troops under Định's direct authority grew. Early in 1862, the Nguyễn court granted Định command of all the southern ''nghĩa quân'' (''righteous soldiers''), the term that Huế used for the partisans. Định continued to lead raids on enemy forces from his base in Gò Công.&lt;ref name=&quot;m92&quot;/&gt; Friction developed between the regular army and Định's partisans as to whether to stage aggressive sorties from Tan Hoa, as was Định's strategy, or to bide their time and engage in military buildup.&lt;ref name=&quot;m32&quot;/&gt;

Định's ''nghĩa quân'' quickly earned the respect of the opposing French naval officers. [[Léopold Pallu de la Barrière]], who defended the posts at Gò Công from Định's attacks, was surprised by their ferocity. Unaware of their nationalist feelings, de la Barrière had expected the Vietnamese to live submissively under any ruler that would allow them to sow their crops.&lt;ref name=&quot;m92&quot;/&gt; He wrote:
{{quote|The attack on Gò Công by a group of armed, skillfully led men surprised everyone. We thought that the Annamites were still submerged in fear, that the masses were enslaved, cowardly, the dregs of empire ... incapable of any act of resistance.&lt;ref name=&quot;m92&quot;&gt;McLeod, p. 92.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

He went on to recognise the popular nature of the partisans' efforts, stating that the &quot;centre of resistance was everywhere, infinitely subdivided&quot;;&lt;ref name=&quot;m92&quot;/&gt; he regarded every peasant as a centre of resistance.&lt;ref name=&quot;m92&quot;/&gt;

== Notable attacks ==
[[Image:Nguyen Trung Truc portrait.jpg|left|[[Nguyễn Trung Trực]], one of Trương Định's assistants|thumb]]
From the middle of 1861, Định's Gò Công guerrillas focused on three objectives: to disrupt the newly created French bureaucracy, to disrupt their military outposts and to disrupt the transport of rice to [[Cholon]], the main commercial hub of southern Vietnam.&lt;ref name=&quot;n428&quot;&gt;Nguyen, p. 428.&lt;/ref&gt; The first major attack against the French administration in the area targeted the Gò Công district office on June 22, 1861.&lt;ref name=&quot;n428&quot;/&gt; At 05:00, 600 rebels under the command of [[Do Dinh Thoai]] stormed the military post in the town, engaging the French troops in hand-to-hand combat with lances, bayonets, knives and bamboo sticks. The French were surprised by the attack, losing one soldier and having 100 wounded.&lt;ref name=&quot;n428&quot;/&gt; By the time reinforcements and naval cover had arrived from [[Mỹ Tho]], Định's men had fled.&lt;ref name=&quot;n429&quot;/&gt; Thoai—who had been the district chief until the French invasion—was among the 14 killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;n427&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;n429&quot;&gt;Nguyen, p. 429.&lt;/ref&gt;

On September 27, the guerrillas assassinated the French-installed chief of Gò Công, displaying his severed head in the town market. The chief's servant, who was an informant for Định, aided this operation. The killing had the effect of intimidating the chief's designated successor into submitting to the rebels and ceasing his service for the French.&lt;ref name=&quot;n429&quot;/&gt; In November 1861, Định's men went into the town of [[Mỹ Tho]] to recruit militants and collect food supplies. During this time, they attacked and burned pro-French villages and their leaders.&lt;ref name=&quot;n430&quot; /&gt;

Định's Gò Công insurgents attempted to stop rice from being shipped to Cholon by attacking the French [[lorcha (boat)|lorchas]] and apprehending the trading vessels on the local waterways. A French report in November 1861 noted that shipping had been severely disrupted and restricted, despite high levels of French naval protection. The most notable of the seaborne attacks was the burning of the [[Lorcha (boat)|lorcha]] ''L'Espérance'' on [[Nhat Tao Canal]] on December 10, 1861.&lt;ref name=&quot;n431&quot;&gt;Nguyen, p. 431.&lt;/ref&gt; Around 150 guerrillas commanded by Trực ambushed the vessel, killing some of the crew before burning and sinking the boat.&lt;ref&gt;Nguyen, pp. 432&amp;ndash;433.&lt;/ref&gt; The attack buoyed Vietnamese morale and instilled the belief that they could fight against French naval forces. The sinking earned the specific praise of Emperor Tự Đức, who described the incident as &quot;most outstanding&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Nguyen, pp. 433&amp;ndash;434.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Continued guerrilla campaign ==
[[Image:Phan Thanh Gian.jpg|thumb|right|Phan Thanh Giản]]
However, the overall Vietnamese military performance was not as successful as Định's guerrilla activities. On June 5, 1862, Định broke with the Nguyễn army after the court's plenipotentiary [[Phan Thanh Giản]] and another official, [[Lam Duy Hiep]], signed the [[Treaty of Saigon]]. This agreement ceded the three southern provinces of [[Gia Định Province|Gia Định]], [[Định Tường Province|Định Tường]] and [[Biên Hòa Province|Biên Hòa]] to France; they became the colony of [[Cochinchina]].&lt;ref name=&quot;m32&quot;&gt;Marr, p. 32.&lt;/ref&gt; The treaty was accompanied by financial payments to France, religious concessions to missionaries and commercial opportunities for European merchants.&lt;ref&gt;Karnow, pp. 88&amp;ndash;89.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Chapuis, pp. 49&amp;ndash;51.&lt;/ref&gt; Militarily, the withdrawal of the Nguyễn army deprived the resistance of the logistical support that could be provided by a regular force. It also permitted the French to concentrate their efforts against a single antagonist. Politically, the treaty provided, for those Vietnamese who needed one, a legal basis to collaborate with the French on Cochinchinese soil. As a result, the colonial forces found it easier to recruit militia and administrative personnel among Vietnamese who had been too afraid or too embarrassed to serve the French openly before the 1862 treaty.&lt;ref name=&quot;m93&quot;&gt;McLeod, p. 93.&lt;/ref&gt; Định then allied himself with [[Võ Duy Dương]] to form the [[Movement of Popular Self Defense]] (''Phong Trao Nhan Dan Tu Ve''), creating an operations base in [[Đồng Tháp Province|Đồng Tháp]].&lt;ref name=&quot;c121&quot;/&gt;

The Huế court ordered Định to disband his forces and to accept a high position in [[An Giang Province]].&lt;ref name=&quot;c121&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;l11&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;m32&quot;/&gt; Fearing that they faced extermination at the hands of the French, Định's followers and lieutenants pressed him to remain. Claiming that his followers would not allow him to leave, Định refused his appointment to An Giang,&lt;ref name=&quot;m32&quot;/&gt; instead adopting the title of ''Bình Tây Sát Tà Đại Tướng'' (''Western Pacifying Antiheresy General''). He continued his guerrilla attacks against French patrols and their Vietnamese collaborators. The slogan &quot;Phan-Lâm mái quốc; Triều đình khi dân&quot; (''Phan [Thanh Gian] and Lam [Duy Hiep] sell out the country; the court doesn’t care for the people'') was circulated through the region.&lt;ref name=&quot;m32&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lam, pp. 8&amp;ndash;9.&lt;/ref&gt; From his stronghold at [[Gò Công]], Định exhorted all southern Vietnamese to rise against the occupying regime, an appeal that was well received. In the words of French naval artillery officer Henri de Poyen, by December 1862, &quot;the insurrection had broken out and was rapidly spreading throughout the colony&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;m32&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;m93&quot;/&gt; French commanders were convinced that Định remained in secret contact with Huế and was privately supported by Tự Đức against the terms of the treaty. The French charged that Định possessed a seal of office from Huế.&lt;ref name=&quot;m32&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;m93&quot;/&gt; However, there were reports that Tự Đức had twice ordered the arrest of Định and Dương to ensure their compliance with the treaty.&lt;ref name=&quot;c122&quot;/&gt;

In contrast with many of his scholar-gentry colleagues who lacked a military training, Định was regarded as having a good understanding of the capabilities and limitations of his armed resistance. Định hoped to wear down the French over an extended period by exploiting the constant outbreak of [[malaria]] among the Europeans.&lt;ref name=&quot;m33&quot;/&gt; During the initial phase of the invasion in 1858, the French had suffered heavily from tropical disease.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chapuis, p. 48&quot;/&gt; Định calculated that such illnesses would partly compensate for the inferior weaponry of his forces. He attempted to maintain an administration parallel to the one imposed on the districts by the French admirals. These objectives required a high degree of regional coordination, something that was impossible without the support of the imperial bureaucracy.&lt;ref name=&quot;m33&quot;&gt;Marr, p. 33.&lt;/ref&gt; Định's appeal among the peasantry was attributed to their gratitude for his administration of the ''đồn điền''. Under such a system, he was responsible for assisting them in matters such as clearing land, educating the community, providing health care and mediating disputes. Joining the resistance army was seen as a means of showing trust and gratitude.&lt;ref name=&quot;n406&quot;&gt;Nguyen, p. 406.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Hịch Trương Định'' (''The proclamation of Trương Định''), which was believed to have been written in 1862 or 1863, emphasised such themes.&lt;ref name=&quot;n406&quot;/&gt; It read:

{{Quote box
 | quote  = To all those who can see and hear!&lt;br&gt;
Look at the animals,&lt;br&gt;
The water buffaloes and the horses are deaf and dumb,&lt;br&gt;
But they are grateful to their masters;&lt;br&gt;
The chickens and the dogs only know how to crow and bark,&lt;br&gt;
But they are kind to their masters.&lt;br&gt;
And we who have our feet on the ground, our head under the sky should we harm our people and country!&lt;ref name=&quot;n406&quot;/&gt;
 | source = Trương Định, ''Hịch Trương Định'' (''The proclamation of Trương Định''
 | width  = 50%
 | align  = center
}}

== Death ==
By February 1864, Admiral Bonard had accumulated sufficient reinforcements to attack and seize Định's main strongholds in the Tan Hoa and Gò Công areas. He inflicted heavy casualties on the partisans and forced them to retreat in disarray. Định reorganised his troops and procured more firearms from the local Chinese in order to resume his guerrilla campaign. He attempted to widen his support base by distributing leaflets as far as the regional centres of [[Saigon]] and [[Mỹ Tho]], calling on ''nghĩa quân'' from other provinces to join the common struggle.&lt;ref name=&quot;m33&quot;/&gt; By this time, the French were able to keep Định and the other resistance leaders constantly on the move, aided by a growing network of local informants. In 1863, a famine had broken out, and resistance forces were increasingly unable to find food. With the court providing no practical support, the French gradually wore down the partisans. Định retreated into the marshes of Bien Hoa, where he attempted to reorganise his forces.

On August 19, 1864, with his remaining guerrillas facing serious supply problems and suffering from hunger, Định was betrayed by a former follower and ambushed by French forces. Wounded and facing imminent capture, Định committed suicide.&lt;ref name=&quot;c122&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;m34&quot;/&gt; His 20-year-old son Truong Quyen (1840 &amp;ndash; 1870), attempted with modest success to carry on his father's struggle. A new base was set up in [[Tây Ninh]]. It allowed more room for tactical manoeuvring but still depended on supplies being carried north from Tan Hoa.&lt;ref name=&quot;m34&quot;&gt;Marr, p. 34.&lt;/ref&gt; Quyen was eventually killed and in 1874, long after the southern insurgency had been crushed, Tự Đức granted a monthly allowance in grain and cash to Định's widow Le Thi Thuong, who had returned to her native village in [[Quảng Ngãi]], which at the time was still in independent Vietnamese territory.&lt;ref name=&quot;m34&quot;/&gt; The ration of 20 francs and 60 litres of rice was substantial,&lt;ref name=&quot;c122&quot;&gt;Chapuis, p. 122.&lt;/ref&gt; because the monthly salary of a ninth-rank mandarin was only 18 francs and 48 litres of rice.&lt;ref name=&quot;c135&quot;&gt;Chapuis, p. 135.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Defiance of Huế? ==
The actions of Định in the wake of the [[Treaty of Saigon]] have long been a subject of conjecture. At the time, the French military accused Huế of surreptitiously supporting Định in contravention of the treaty, while Huế denied this, publicly claiming that Định's actions in resisting the French would be counterproductive in attempting to maintain Vietnamese sovereignty.&lt;ref name=&quot;c121&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;McLeod, pp. 89&amp;ndash;90.&lt;/ref&gt;

After the signing of the Treaty of Saigon, the Huế court attempted to regain what it had lost militarily through diplomacy. Vietnamese negotiators sought a reversal of the territorial cession, which they regarded as the most humiliating clause of the treaty.&lt;ref name=&quot;m90&quot;/&gt; In late 1863, the Vietnamese proposed extensive financial, economic, and [[concession (politics)|political concessions]] in exchange for the return of the three provinces. Tự Đức sent Gian to France to seek an audience with Napoleon III. There Gian behaved in a helpless manner in an attempt to gain pity from the French monarch. Gian promised that Vietnam would pay large indemnities for the military conflicts, grant further commercial concessions and a protectorate over all six southern provinces.&lt;ref name=&quot;c301&quot;&gt;Chapuis, pp. 30&amp;ndash;31.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;k90&quot;&gt;Karnow, p. 90.&lt;/ref&gt; Napoleon initially agreed, but the decision was reversed after lobbying from French officers.&lt;ref name=&quot;c301&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;k90&quot;/&gt;

Tự Đức continued to hope that Vietnamese compliance with the treaty would convince France to return the three southern provinces. In the words of Gian, Vietnam's full cooperation with the 1862 treaty was necessary to maintain the possibility of a territorial retrocession. The French officers in Saigon, the capital of Cochinchina, frequently accused the Nguyễn court of violating the treaty by quietly supporting continued resistance. In 1867, they took this as a pretext to seize the other three provinces in southern Vietnam: [[Vĩnh Long Province|Vĩnh Long]], [[Hà Tiên Province|Hà Tiên]] and [[An Giang Province|An Giang]].&lt;ref name=&quot;c122&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;m90&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;k90&quot;/&gt;

The court records of the Nguyễn dynasty in Huế, the ''[[Đại Nam thực lục]]'' (''Veritable Records of the Great South'') dispute the French claims, revealing that the court attempted to prevent illegal guerrilla activity by the likes of Định.&lt;ref name=&quot;m90&quot;&gt;McLeod, p. 90.&lt;/ref&gt; However, in one edict, Định claimed that Tự Đức endorsed his struggle, in an attempt to garner popular support. This fuelled French claims that the guerrillas were periodically traveling between French territory and the adjoining sovereign Nguyễn territory to get supplies from provincial officials.&lt;ref name=&quot;m90&quot;/&gt;

The French officers never produced concrete proof of Huế's support for the southern partisans or of the connivance of Vietnamese officials in the sovereign provinces bordering French-occupied territory. Despite this, they seized the rest of southern Vietnam on the basis that Huế was violating the treaty. Vice-Admiral Bonard, governor of French Cochinchina from 1861 until 1863, asserted:

{{quote|There is no disguising the fact that the peace stipulated by the Treaty [of 1862] has never been faithfully executed by the Huế court. Seeing that it could not withstand a conventional war, the Annamite government organised, openly before the peace, clandestinely and underhandedly afterward, a permanent insurrection in Cochin China.... Quan Dinh [Mandarin Dinh], head of the insurrection at Gò Công, although publicly disavowed by the viceroy of [[Vĩnh Long]] Phan Thanh Gian, who has called on him several times to withdraw so that the peace treaty can be implemented, has absolutely refused to do so. He is thus apparently in a state of rebellion, but the Huế government, which has publicly given him orders that he has disobeyed, supports him clandestinely and supplies him with arms, munitions, and seals.&lt;ref name=&quot;m94&quot;&gt;McLeod, p. 94.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Historians sympathetic to the colonisation reiterated the officers' assertions about the contacts between Huế and the southern partisans. De Poyen wrote that the southern insurgency &quot;was ceaselessly excited and supported by emissaries from Huế, who travelled throughout the country&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;m94&quot;/&gt; Milton Osborne, while noting that evidence was circumstantial, asserted that French charges were probably legitimate:&lt;ref name=&quot;m94&quot;/&gt;

{{quote|The scale of the risings in December 1862 certainly suggests an organised concerted effort, backed by Huế. This judgment, however, is based on inference, not on certain fact. After the failure of the 1862 risings, Huế had little active part in the repeated risings in the South.... Noninvolvement in practical ways did not mean the end of interest, and there seems some reason to accept the French allegations that the sporadic risings against their control of Cochinchina received the clandestine approval of Huế for many years.&lt;ref name=&quot;m94&quot;/&gt;}}

Vietnamese documentation challenges the French assertions. The imperial records, written communications between Gian and Định, and the account of the southern insurgency written by a resistance figure named [[Nguyen Thong]] support the contention that Định's guerrillas operated independently of Huế and in violation of its orders. The imperial records hold that Tự Đức immediately ordered the insurgents to disband, fearing that their actions were an obstacle to his plan of negotiating the return of the lost territory. The records assert that Tự Đức ordered his officials to prevent the insurgents from returning to independent Vietnamese land and to arrest those who did so. Messengers were sent from Huế into the south with the intention of discouraging the insurgents, rather than fomenting resistance.&lt;ref name=&quot;m95&quot;&gt;McLeod, p. 95.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the specific case of Định, the Vietnamese documents record the failed attempts of Gian to persuade him to lay down his arms and accept an administrative post in An Giang. The records assert that his position as head of the resistance was granted by his followers rather than Huế.&lt;ref name=&quot;m96&quot;&gt;McLeod, p. 96.&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly after signing the treaty, the court directed Gian to write to Định, ordering him to respect the agreement and end his resistance. Gian's letter and Định's rebuff show Tự Đức's insistence on abiding by the treaty and the guerrilla chief's staunch refusal to do so. Gian's letter argued that it was illegal and futile to ignore the court's order to cease hostilities. Gian wrote:&lt;ref name=&quot;m96&quot;/&gt;

{{quote|Since the court has signed the peace treaty, you should cease hostilities and not violate the king's orders.... At present, the court's regular forces have all been withdrawn, and the mandarins commanding troops hiding in the mountains and forests have all disbanded their forces. If you alone are to lead your soldiers to the attack, can you be certain of victory? If you retreat, can you defend yourself? Certainly not!&lt;ref name=&quot;m96&quot;/&gt;}}

In his reply, Định demonstrated his awareness of the illegality of his insurgency and the southerners' obligation to obey their emperor. Định nevertheless refused to abandon his supporters, vowing to disobey royal orders:&lt;ref name=&quot;m96&quot;/&gt;

{{quote|The people of the three provinces, wanting to return to their former status, designated me as their leader. Therefore, we cannot take any course but our present one.... If Your Excellency still maintains that the agreements with the invaders must be preserved, then we will oppose the court's commands, and ... there can be no more peace or truce between us and Your Excellency.&lt;ref name=&quot;c122&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;m96&quot;/&gt;}}

Vietnamese records show that when Định disobeyed the court's orders, he was stripped of his position and titles:&lt;ref name=&quot;m97&quot;&gt;McLeod, p. 97.&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Trương Định has refused to return to the exercise of his office, and he is accordingly removed from that function with loss of honorific titles.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;m97&quot;/&gt; Nguyen Thong, a former mandarin who fought alongside Định and corresponded with many other guerrilla leaders, agreed with the court records. According to Thong, Định's continued resistance resulted from local initiatives contrary to Huế's explicit instructions. Định's supporters implored him to disobey the edicts of 1862 that directed the partisans to end hostilities:&lt;ref name=&quot;m97&quot;/&gt; &quot;Our people forced the Westerners to retreat many times, and now that the court has made peace with them, they will surely kill us.... Since the court has settled with them, who will support us? Let us unite to strike back at them, to take for ourselves a piece of land on which we can fight for our lives.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;m97&quot;/&gt;

According to Thong's account, Định agreed with these arguments and began to organise the resources required for his unapproved anti-French movement. Although he was fully aware of his imperial defiance, Định sent an appeal &quot;to all the righteous men, encouraging them in the name of loyalty to the court to rise and destroy the invaders&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;m97&quot;/&gt; Thong asserted that the imperial edicts used by Định—which were cited by French officers for subsequent aggression—were fake. Định had falsified them to make propaganda in order to rally popular support.&lt;ref name=&quot;m97&quot;/&gt; According to Mark McLeod, it is unclear whether hawkish mandarins in the imperial court were assisting Định's southern insurgents in contravention of Tự Đức's wishes.&lt;ref name=&quot;m98&quot;&gt;McLeod, p. 98.&lt;/ref&gt; Truong Buu Lam opined that &quot;if some partisans received assistance from the Vietnamese authorities, it was extended to them by local officials who acted independently&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;l9&quot;&gt;Lam, p. 9.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Disrespect of the mandate of heaven? ==
In light of Định's disobedience of Tự Đức, his justification for his defiance is discussed against the backdrop of the Confucian expectation for him to defer to the emperor's &quot;[[Mandate of Heaven]]&quot;. As Định left no explicit or definitive statement for his rationale for disobeying Tự Đức, scholars who have recognised or suspected Định's disobedience have been forced to speculate.&lt;ref name=&quot;m98&quot;/&gt;

Lam assumes Định's disobedience and explains it by asserting that the insurgents drew a distinction between the reigning monarch and the monarchy as an idealised institution.&lt;ref name=&quot;m98&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;l10&quot;&gt;Lam, p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|After the Huế court signed the Treaty of Saigon, a moral dilemma developed since the partisans could neither accept the loss of their country nor claim that their cause was righteous if they acted in violation of the court's orders. They therefore drew a careful distinction between the person of an individual king and the moral principle of loyalty to the monarchy.... The monarchy was therefore an idealised institution not tarnished by any accidental deviation from the ideal.&lt;ref name=&quot;l10&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;m99&quot;/&gt;}}

The historian [[David G. Marr|David Marr]] agrees, noting that &quot;the distinction quite rightly pointed out by Professor Truong Buu Lam was in all probability bred of immediate adverse conditions and not the product of a long tradition&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;m32&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;m99&quot;&gt;McLeod, p. 99.&lt;/ref&gt; Modern Vietnamese historians of the communist regime go to the extent of asserting that Định's justification for continued resistance was based on an implicit rejection of the monarchy at large. These historians base their hypothesis on the assertion that the Confucian virtue of monarchical loyalty was unconditional and absolute in 19th-century Vietnam. In the words of the editors of the [[Institute of Historical Study]]'s journal, ''[[Nghiên cứu lịch sử]]'' (''Historical Studies''), &quot;Loyalty to the king was the people's duty, and to satisfy the obligation of monarchical loyalty, the court's orders had to be followed&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;m100&quot;/&gt; In the view of Marxist authors, Định resolved the conflict between monarchical loyalty and resisting foreign occupation by discarding the constraints of Confucian ethics. They assert that Định justified his struggle by placing loyalty to Tự Đức below his loyalty to Vietnam and its people. The Institute of Historical Study's [[Nguyen Cong Binh]] stated, &quot;Relying on the people, Trương Định placed the country above the king, thus safeguarding his feelings of loyalty to the country&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;m100&quot;/&gt; These arguments are consistent with Marxist ideology and its criticism of the Nguyễn dynasty as a &quot;reactionary, feudal regime&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;l13&quot;/&gt; Communist party historiography has long criticised the Nguyễn dynasty and its roots in the [[Nguyễn lords]] for the division of the country in the centuries-long struggle with the [[Trịnh lords]] of the north and then the subsequent use of French aid of [[Pigneau de Behaine]] to unseat the [[Tây Sơn dynasty]]. It further accords with Hanoi's ideological line of portraying anti-colonial, anti-French fighters of the 19th century as the spiritual ancestors of the [[Vietnamese Communist Party]].&lt;ref name=&quot;m100&quot;&gt;McLeod, p. 100.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;l13&quot;&gt;Li, p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to historian Mark McLeod, these postulated explanations of Định's behaviour are plausible, given the chaos engulfing Vietnam at the time and the lack of conclusive documentation. However, Định and his supporters asserted their loyalty to the monarch and justified their struggle in his name, both before and after the signing of the treaty. These declarations show no hint of rejecting Tự Đức's authority nor any reference to a worthier, idealised monarch. Conversely, many of these proclamations display an intense feeling of personal loyalty. A placard that French forces found floating downstream near Định's base in Gò Công asserted:&lt;ref name=&quot;m101&quot;&gt;McLeod, p. 101.&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Gratitude ties us to our king. We will avenge the insults he has received [from the French], or we will die for him.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;m101&quot;/&gt; One of Định's proclamations to his followers read:&lt;ref name=&quot;m101&quot;/&gt; &quot;The Emperor does not recognise us, but it is indeed our duty to carry on our struggle.... The Emperor calls us rebels, but in the depth of his heart he cannot help but praise our loyalty. When the day of victory arrives, not only will the Emperor forgive us, he will furthermore grant us all kinds of awards.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;m101&quot;/&gt;
&lt;!--[[Image:Tu Duc.jpg|thumb|right|Emperor Tự Đức]]--&gt;

Such writings may be dismissed by skeptics as a political stunt aimed at attracting support for continued resistance by appealing to the widely held Confucian value of monarchical loyalty. This is the explanation suggested by the Marxist authors: &quot;On the one hand, Trương Định opposed Tự Đức's order to lay down his arms; on the other hand, he exploited Tự Đức's name in order to call upon the people to rise and fight the French&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;m101&quot;/&gt; McLeod argues that the best explanation for Định's continued insurgency was that the Confucian tradition allows for a loyal official to disobey his sovereign without calling the sovereign's authority into question. This is termed a ''tránh thần'', meaning a minister who is willing to dispute his sovereign's orders in order to prevent the ruler from committing a mistake, even if this incurred his ire. The minister who allowed the ruler to err rather than risk upsetting him was regarded as a sycophant, a careerist rather a loyal adviser. The loyal official was thus required in certain circumstances to remonstrate with and even to disobey his sovereign to show his concern for the monarch. Thus, according to McLeod, Định's disobedience did not ''ipso facto'' constitute a rejection of Tự Đức's authority.&lt;ref name=&quot;m101&quot;/&gt;

Định believed that Tự Đức would eventually realise his error and reward the insurgents. Historians feel that it is likely that Gian and Tự Đức saw Định's continued resistance as a misguided attempt to help the monarchy. In their written confrontation after the signing of the treaty, Gian did not accuse Định of being a rebel, but of excessive devotion to the emperor, which while admirable in principle, was hindering their current strategy. &quot;Monarchical loyalty is a noble quality&quot;, Gian had told the recalcitrant guerrilla leader,&lt;ref name=&quot;m103&quot;/&gt; but &quot;[i]t must have a limit. One cannot exceed this limit and still be faithful and pious. Too much is just as bad as not enough; when a snake begins to have legs, it is no longer a snake...&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;m103&quot;&gt;McLeod, p. 103.&lt;/ref&gt; Tự Đức also appeared to view Định's continued resistance as a misguided manifestation of loyalty. Although the southern insurgents' disobedience provided the French with a pretext for further aggression, thereby hindering Tự Đức's plans for regaining the lost territory, the emperor never accused them of rebelling against royal authority. Instead, he continued to refer to them as &quot;righteous recruits&quot; motivated by &quot;indignation&quot; at the actions of the Westerners.&lt;ref name=&quot;m103&quot;/&gt;

[[Nguyễn Đình Chiểu]], the leading poet of the southern struggle, did not portray Định as a rebel opposed to the Huế court. In an [[elegy]] to fallen insurgents, Chiểu asserted that the resistance continued its struggle after the treaty was signed &quot;because their hearts would not heed the Son of Heaven's edict&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;m104&quot;/&gt; Chiểu strongly supported the partisans' continuing efforts in attempting to expel the French from southern Vietnam, a cause he considered righteous. However, his reference to Tự Đức as the &quot;Son of Heaven&quot; indicates that the legitimacy of the emperor was not called into question.&lt;ref name=&quot;m104&quot;&gt;McLeod, p. 104.&lt;/ref&gt; After Định's death, Chiểu wrote in a poem:&lt;ref name=&quot;l11&quot;&gt;Lam, p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|You have spared no efforts to help your country,&lt;br&gt;
Although you disobeyed the royal orders, you shall not be considered a disloyal subject.&lt;ref name=&quot;l11&quot;/&gt;}}

Chiểu further hoped that the Vietnamese court would change its position and come to the aid of the insurgents, writing:&lt;ref name=&quot;l9&quot;/&gt; &quot;The sigh of the wind and the cry of the crane [announcing the official army's arrival] held you breathless for more than ten months. You were expecting news from the officials as one expects rain in the dry season.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;l9&quot;/&gt;

== Legacy ==
[[File:Đền và mộ Trương Định.JPG|thumb|right|200px|Tomb of Trương Định in [[Gò Công]], [[Tiền Giang]], Vietnam]]
The reputation of Định and his southern rebels persisted long after his death. [[Phan Bội Châu]], the leading Vietnamese revolutionary of the early 20th century, travelled into the south in 1904, seeking to start a new anti-French movement. He specifically attempted to recruit followers among the surviving elderly members of Định's movement.&lt;ref&gt;Marr, p. 103.&lt;/ref&gt; Định was highly regarded as a revolutionary hero by Vietnamese of both communist and anti-communist persuasions. In 1964, an article in the North Vietnamese ''Nghiên cứu lịch sửu'' described Định as &quot;the hero symbolising the spirit of resistance to the foreign colonialists of the people of Southern Viet-Nam&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;os&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |author=Mai-Hanh |date=August 1964 |title=Trương Định |journal=[[Nghiên cứu lịch sử]] |volume=66 |page=59 |language=Vietnamese}}&lt;/ref&gt; The same article extolled Định's physical appearance and his capabilities, stating &quot;He was handsome in appearance, understood the military manual and was a good shot&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;os&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;nv&quot;/&gt; During the [[Vietnam War]] era, North Vietnamese historians sought to portray the [[Viet Cong]]—which fought against the [[Army of the Republic of Vietnam]] and the United States—as Định's modern successor.&lt;ref name=&quot;os&quot;/&gt; Định was also highly regarded among anti-communist South Vietnamese scholars.&lt;ref name=&quot;os&quot;&gt;{{cite journal |first=Milton E. |last=Osborne |date=November 1970 |title=Truong Vinh Ky and Phan Thanh Gian: The Problem of a Nationalist Interpretation of 19th Century Vietnamese History |journal=[[Journal of Asian Studies]] |volume=30 |issue=1 |page=85 |doi=10.2307/2942724 |jstor=2942724}}&lt;/ref&gt; A prominent thoroughfare in the centre of [[Ho Chi Minh City]] in southern Vietnam is named after him.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| title=Vietnam Country Map |publisher=Periplus Travel Maps |year=2002–03 |isbn=0-7946-0070-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although Định received little attention in French academia, the North Vietnamese heavily relied on French sources for their accounts of the guerrilla leader. In the most detailed French account by Paulin Vial, Định is depicted as a &quot;criminal&quot; or &quot;rebel&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;os&quot;/&gt; Osborne said that Định's final manifesto before his death showed him &quot;to have been a man with a high concept of duty, an awareness of his own weakness and with a sense of despair, common to many of his countrymen, at the ambivalence of the Huế court&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;os&quot;/&gt;

==Notes==
{{reflist|colwidth=25em}}

== References ==
*{{cite book|title= The last emperors of Vietnam: from Tu Duc to Bao Dai |first=Oscar |last=Chapuis |publisher=Greenwood Press | year=2000 |isbn=0-313-31170-6 |location=Westport, Connecticut}}
*{{cite book| title=Vietnam: A history| first=Stanley |last=Karnow |authorlink=Stanley Karnow| year=1997 |publisher=Penguin Books | isbn=0-670-84218-4|location=New York}}
*{{cite book |title=Nguyen Cochinchina| author=Li Tana |year=1998 |publisher=Cornell Southeast Asia Program |isbn=0-87727-722-2 |location=Ithaca, New York}}
*{{cite book|title=Vietnamese anticolonialism, 1885&amp;ndash;1925| first= David G. |last=Marr |year=1970 |publisher=University of California |location=Berkeley, California| isbn=0-520-01813-3}}
*{{cite journal |first=Mark |last=McLeod |date=March 1993 |title=Truong Dinh and Vietnamese anti-colonialism, 1859&amp;ndash;64: A Reappraisal |journal=[[Journal of Southeast Asian Studies]] |volume=24 |issue=1 |pages=88–106 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=Singapore |doi=10.1017/S002246340000151X}}&lt;!--|accessdate=November 16, 2007 --&gt;
*{{cite book |first= Thanh Thi |last=Nguyen |title=The French conquest of Cochinchina, 1858&amp;ndash;1862 | publisher=University Microfilms International |year=1992 |location=Ann Arbor, Michigan}}
*{{Cite book |author=Truong Buu Lam | title=Patterns of Vietnamese response to foreign intervention: 1858&amp;ndash;1900 |year=1967 |publisher=Southeast Asia Studies Yale University |series=Monograph Series No. 11 |location=New Haven, Connecticut}}

{{Cochinchina campaign}}
{{Vietnamese independence movement}}

{{Authority control}}

== External links ==
* [http://truongdinh.tiengiang.edu.vn/ Trương hoc Trương Định]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Dinh, Truong}}
[[Category:1820 births]]
[[Category:1864 deaths]]
[[Category:Nguyen dynasty officials]]
[[Category:People from Quang Ngai Province]]
[[Category:People of the Cochinchina Campaign]]
[[Category:Vietnamese nationalists]]
[[Category:Vietnamese Confucianists]]</text>
      <sha1>luwcs47sua4n8cckrr5gxlene4nqwid</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
