<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Vitalian (general)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>25820000</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749424487</id>
      <parentid>717658944</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-14T07:05:48Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>CitationCleanerBot</username>
        <id>15270283</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Secondary */clean up, url redundant with jstor, and/or remove accessdate if no url using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20562">{{Infobox military person
|name=Vitalian
|image=
|caption=
|birth_date=
|death_date=July 520
|birth_place=[[Zaldapa]]
|death_place=[[Constantinople]]
|allegiance=[[Byzantine Empire]]
|rank=''[[magister militum]]''
|battles=
|relations=[[Bouzes]], [[Coutzes]] and [[Venilus]] (sons)&lt;br&gt;[[John (nephew of Vitalian)|John]] (nephew)
}}
'''Vitalian''' ({{lang-la|Flavius Vitalianus}}, {{lang-el|Βιταλιανός}}; died 520) was a general of the [[Byzantine Empire|East Roman (Byzantine) Empire]]. A native of [[Moesia]] in the northern [[Balkans]], and probably of mixed Roman and [[barbarian]] descent, he followed his father into the imperial army, and by 513 had become a senior commander in [[Thrace]].

In that year he rebelled against Emperor [[Anastasius I (emperor)|Anastasius I]] (r. 491–518), whose fiscal stringency and promotion of [[Miaphysitism]] were widely unpopular, and allowed Vitalian to quickly win over large parts of the army and the people of [[Thrace]] to his cause. After scoring a series of victories over loyalist armies, Vitalian came to threaten [[Constantinople]] itself, and forced Anastasius to officially recant his adoption of Miaphysitism in summer 515. Soon after, however, as Anastasius failed to honour some of the terms of the agreement, Vitalian marched on Constantinople, only to be decisively defeated by Anastasius' admiral, [[Marinus (praetorian prefect)|Marinus]].

Vitalian fled to his native Thrace and remained in hiding until Anastasius's death in 518. As a staunch promoter of [[Chalcedonian]] orthodoxy, he was pardoned by the new emperor [[Justin I]] (r. 518–527) and was engaged in the negotiations with the [[Papacy|Pope]] to end the [[Acacian Schism]]. He was named [[Roman consul|consul]] for the year 520, but was murdered shortly after, probably on the orders of Justin's nephew and heir-apparent, [[Justinian]] (r. 527–565), who saw in him a potential rival for the throne. His sons also became generals in the East Roman army.

==Biography==

===Origins and family===
Vitalian was born in [[Zaldapa]] in [[Lower Moesia]] (usually identified with modern Abrit in north-eastern [[Bulgaria]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Whitby|Whitby|1986|pp=182, 248}}.&lt;/ref&gt; He is called a &quot;[[Goths|Goth]]&quot; or a &quot;[[Scythian]]&quot; in the Byzantine sources. Since Vitalian's mother was a sister of [[Macedonius II]], [[Patriarch of Constantinople]] in 496–511, this points to a mixed marriage and a probable [[barbarians|barbarian]] origin for his father, Patriciolus.&lt;ref name=&quot;ODB&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Kazhdan|1991|p=2182}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Amory435&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Amory|2003|p=435}}.&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, the assertion that he was a &quot;Goth&quot; is based on a single [[Syriac language|Syriac]] source, and is today considered dubious.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Amory|2003|p=128}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Likewise, the &quot;Scythian&quot; label commonly applied to him by some contemporary authors is non-conclusive, since the term &quot;Scythian&quot; could mean an inhabitant of [[Scythia Minor]], or simply, in the [[Byzantine literature#Characteristics|classicizing]] language usual in Byzantine texts, someone from the north-eastern fringes of the Graeco-Roman world, centred on the [[Mediterranean]]; the term had a wide-encompassing meaning, devoid of clear ethnic attributes.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Amory|2003|pp=127–130}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, since none of the &quot;[[Scythian Monks]]&quot;, to whom Vitalian and members of his family seem to have been related, expressed any kinship, by blood or spiritually, with the [[Arianism|Arian]] Goths [[Ostrogothic Kingdom|who at that time ruled]] [[Italy]], a Gothic origin for Vitalian is questionable.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Amory|2003|p=130}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Whatever Patriciolus's origin, his name was [[Latin language|Latin]], while of Vitalian's own sons, the generals [[Bouzes]] and [[Coutzes]] had [[Thracian language|Thracian]] names and [[Venilus]] a Gothic name. His nephew, [[John (nephew of Vitalian)|John]], later also became a distinguished general in the wars against the [[Ostrogoths]] of Italy.&lt;ref name=&quot;PLRE1171&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Martindale|Jones|Morris|1980|p=1171}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Amory|2003|p=129}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the chroniclers' descriptions, Vitalian was short of stature and stammered, but his personal bravery and military skills were widely acknowledged.&lt;ref name=&quot;PLRE1176&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Martindale|Jones|Morris|1980|p=1176}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bury448&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Bury|1958a|loc=p. 448}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Revolt against Anastasius===
[[File:Semissis-Anastasius I-sb0007.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Gold ''[[semissis]]'' of Emperor Anastasius I (r. 491–518).]]

Vitalian is first mentioned in 503, when he accompanied his father in the [[Anastasian War]] against the [[Sassanid Empire|Persians]].&lt;ref name=&quot;PLRE1171&quot;/&gt; By 513, he had risen to the rank of ''[[comes]]'' in [[Thrace]], possibly ''comes foederatorum'', &quot;count of the ''[[foederati]]''&quot;, barbarian soldiers serving in the [[East Roman army]].&lt;ref name=&quot;PLRE1171&quot;/&gt;

From this post, he rebelled against Emperor [[Anastasius I (emperor)|Anastasius I]] (r. 491–518), taking advantage of widespread resentment over the emperor's military, religious, and social policies.&lt;ref name=&quot;ODB&quot;/&gt; In 511, Anastasius had changed the form of the ''[[Trisagion]]'' prayer and officially adopted the [[Miaphysite]] dogma, angering the Empire's [[Chalcedonian]] population, adding to the disaffection caused by his strict financial policies.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Bury|1958a|loc=pp. 447–448}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, Anastasius had refused to supply the ''annonae'' (&quot;rations, provisions&quot;) due to the ''foederati'', allowing Vitalian to quickly gain the allegiance of the regular troops stationed in the provinces of Thrace, [[Moesia II]], and Scythia Minor from the unpopular ''[[magister militum]] per [[Diocese of Thrace|Thracias]]'', Anastasius' nephew [[Hypatius (consul 500)|Hypatius]]. Hypatius's subordinate commanders were either killed or joined the rebellion.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Martindale|Jones|Morris|1980|pp=578–579, 1172}}.&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, posing as a champion of Chalcedonian orthodoxy, Vitalian was able to gain the support of the local people, who flocked to join his force. According to contemporary Byzantine historians, he quickly assembled an army of 50,000–60,000 men, &quot;both soldiers and peasants&quot;, and marched on [[Constantinople]], possibly hoping that the mostly Chalcedonian inhabitants would join him.&lt;ref name=&quot;ODB&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bury448&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;PLRE1172&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Martindale|Jones|Morris|1980|p=1172}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Indeed, it appears that Vitalian's revolt was primarily motivated by religious reasons, something suggested by his repeatedly demonstrated willingness to reach an accommodation with Anastasius.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Cameron|Ward-Perkins|Whitby|2000|pp=56–57}}.&lt;/ref&gt; To counter Vitalian's [[propaganda]], Anastasius ordered [[bronze]] [[cross]]es to be set up on the [[Walls of Constantinople|city walls]] inscribed with his own version of events. The emperor also reduced [[taxation|taxes]] in the provinces of [[Bithynia]] and [[Asia (Roman province)|Asia]] to prevent them from joining the rebellion.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bury448&quot;/&gt;

When Vitalian's forces reached the capital, they encamped at the suburb of [[Hebdomon]] and blockaded the landward side of the city. Anastasius opted for negotiations, and sent out Vitalian's former patron, the former [[Roman consul|consul]] and ''magister militum praesentalis'' [[Patricius (consul 500)|Patricius]], as ambassador.&lt;ref name=&quot;PLRE1172&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Martindale|Jones|Morris|1980|p=840}}.&lt;/ref&gt; To him, Vitalian declared his aims: the restoration of Chalcedonian orthodoxy and the settling of the Thracian army's grievances. Patricius then invited him and his officers in the city itself for negotiations. Vitalian refused for himself, but allowed his senior officers to go on the next day.&lt;ref name=&quot;PLRE1172&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Bury|1958a|loc=pp. 448–449}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The officers were well treated by Anastasius, who gave them gifts and promised that their soldiers' grievances would be settled. He also pledged to submit the religious dispute for resolution to the [[Patriarch of Rome]]. Upon their return to the rebel camp, these officers unanimously pressured Vitalian to accept this settlement. Faced with no alternative, only eight days after his arrival before the capital, Vitalian retreated and returned with his men to Lower Moesia.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bury449&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Bury|1958a|loc=p. 449}}.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;PLRE1173&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Martindale|Jones|Morris|1980|p=1173}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Dioecesis Thraciae 400 AD.png|thumb|left|250px|Map of the [[Diocese of Thrace]], the theatre of operations during Vitalian's rebellion.]]

Anastasius then appointed as ''magister militum per Thracias'' an officer called Cyril, who proceeded to attack Vitalian's forces. After a few inconclusive skirmishes, Vitalian managed to bribe his army's entry into [[Odessus]], Cyril's base, at night. Cyril was captured at his residence and killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;PLRE1173&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Croke|1995|pp=37–38}}.&lt;/ref&gt; At this point, Anastasius had Vitalian declared as a &quot;public enemy&quot; and sent out a new huge army – reportedly 80,000 men – under Hypatius, with a [[Huns|Hun]] called Alathar as the new ''magister militum'' of Thrace. After winning a minor initial victory, the imperial army was eventually pushed back towards Odessus (autumn 513). At [[Cape Kaliakra|Acris]], on the [[Black Sea]] coast, Vitalian's men attacked their fortified [[laager]] in darkness and dealt them a crushing defeat: the larger part of the imperial army was killed, and both imperial commanders were taken prisoner and held for ransom.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bury449&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Martindale|Jones|Morris|1980|pp=579, 1173}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The victory consolidated Vitalian's position. With the spoils, he was able to lavishly reward his followers, and at the news of the imperial army's annihilation, the remaining cities and forts in Lower Moesia and Scythia surrendered to him. Soon after, he had another stroke of luck: at [[Sozopol]]is, his men captured an embassy sent by Anastasius to ransom Hypatius, including the ransom money of 1,100 pounds of gold. Hypatius, whom Vitalian hated because he had once insulted his wife, was not released until a year later.&lt;ref name=&quot;PLRE1173&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bury450&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Bury|1958a|loc=p. 450}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In 514, Vitalian marched again towards Constantinople, this time gathering, in addition to his army, a fleet of 200 vessels from the Black Sea ports, which sailed down the [[Bosporus]] menacing the city from the sea as well. Anastasius was further disquieted by riots in the city, which left many casualties, and resolved to once again negotiate with Vitalian.&lt;ref name=&quot;PLRE1173&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Bury450&quot;/&gt; Vitalian accepted, on the conditions of his nomination to the post of ''magister militum per Thracias'' and the receipt of ransom money and gifts worth in total 5,000 pounds of gold for the release of Hypatius. Anastasius also conceded the removal of the changes from the ''Trisagion'', the restoration of the deposed Chalcedonian bishops, and the convocation of a general church council at Constantinople on 1 July 515.&lt;ref name=&quot;PLRE1173&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Bury|1958a|loc=pp. 450–451}}; {{harvnb|Cameron|Ward-Perkins|Whitby|2000|p=820}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The council never materialized, since [[Pope Hormisdas]] and Anastasius continued to be at loggerheads over the [[Acacian Schism]]. Neither were the deposed bishops returned to their [[episcopal see|sees]]. Seeing Anastasius failing to honour his promises, in late 515 Vitalian mobilized his army and marched again towards Constantinople.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bury451&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Bury|1958a|loc=p. 451}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Vitalian's army captured the suburb of Sycae (modern [[Galata]]) across the [[Golden Horn]] from the city and encamped there. The two ''magistri militum praesentalis'', Patricius and John, were unwilling to engage their old friend Vitalian, thus Anastasius gave command of his forces to the former [[praetorian prefect of the East]], [[Marinus (praetorian prefect)|Marinus]], a trusted and influential aide.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bury451&quot;/&gt; Despite his lack of military experience, Marinus defeated the rebel fleet in a battle at the entrance of the Golden Horn; according to the report of [[John Malalas]], this was achieved through the use of a [[sulphur]]-based chemical substance invented by the philosopher Proclus of Athens, similar to the later [[Greek fire]]. Marinus then landed with his men on the shore of Sycae and defeated the rebels he found there. Disheartened by the losses suffered, Vitalian and his army fled north under cover of night.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Bury|1958a|loc=pp. 451–452}}; {{harvnb|Cameron|Ward-Perkins|Whitby|2000|pp=57, 294}}.&lt;/ref&gt; As a sign of his victory, Anastasius led a procession to the village of [[Sosthenion]], where Vitalian had established his headquarters, and attended a service of thanks at the [[Michaelion|famed local church]] dedicated to the [[Archangel Michael]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Bury452&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Bury|1958a|loc=p. 452}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Later life===
Once back in northern Thrace, Vitalian went into hiding, while many of his erstwhile aides were captured and executed. Nothing is known of him for the next three years, although a short remark by a chronicler seems to indicate that he resurfaced and led another armed rebellion during the last months of Anastasius's life.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bury452&quot;/&gt; When Anastasius died in July 518, he was succeeded by [[Justin I]], the ''[[comes excubitorum]]'' (commander of the imperial bodyguard). The new emperor quickly moved to strengthen his rule, dismissing a number of potential rivals or enemies. At the same time, he called upon Vitalian to come to Constantinople.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Bury|1958b|loc=pp. 17, 20}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Upon his arrival, Vitalian was made ''magister militum in praesenti'', named honorary consul, and soon after raised to the rank of ''[[patrikios|patricius]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Martindale|Jones|Morris|1980|pp=1174–1175}}.&lt;/ref&gt; As a well-known champion of Chalcedonian orthodoxy, Vitalian was to play a role in the new regime's reaffirmation of the Chalcedonian doctrines and reconciliation with Rome. He played an active role in the negotiations with the Pope, and in 519, he was one of the prominent men who escorted a papal delegation into the capital.&lt;ref name=&quot;ODB&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Bury|1958b|loc=p. 20}}; {{harvnb|Martindale|Jones|Morris|1980|p=1175}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Vitalian also took vengeance on the staunchly Monophysite [[Patriarch of Antioch]], [[Severus of Antioch|Severus]], who had celebrated Vitalian's defeat in his [[panegyric]] ''On Vitalian the tyrant and on the victory of the Christ-loving Anastasius the king'': Justin ordered Severus's tongue to be cut, and Severus fled to Egypt along with Julian, Bishop of [[Halicarnassus]].&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Mango|Scott|1997|pp=245 note 1, 249–251}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Finally in 520, Vitalian was appointed ordinary consul for the year, sharing the office with [[Rusticius (consul 520)|Rusticius]]. Nevertheless, the former rebel continued to pose a potential challenge to Justin, and more importantly to his nephew and heir-apparent, [[Justinian I|Justinian]] (r. 527–565). Thus, in July of the same year he was murdered inside the [[Great Palace of Constantinople|Great Palace]] along with his secretary Paulus and his ''domesticus'' (aide) Celerianus.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Cameron|1982|pp=93–94}}. The month of Vitalian's death is taken from the chronicle of [[Marcellinus Comes]], ''sub anno'' 520. Alan Cameron discussed the supporting evidence, concluding that Marcellinus is correct.&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[John of Nikiou]], he was killed because he was plotting against Justin; most chroniclers, however, put the responsibility for the crime on Justinian's desire to rid himself of a potential rival for his uncle's succession.&lt;ref name=&quot;ODB&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;PLRE1176&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Bury|1958b|loc=pp. 20–21}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==

===Citations===
{{reflist|2}}

===Sources===

====Primary====
{{refbegin|2}}
*{{cite book|last=Charles|first=R.H.|title=The Chronicle of John, Bishop of Nikiu|location=London|publisher=Williams &amp; Norgate|year=1916|pages=131–134|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Croke|first=Brian|title=The Chronicle of Marcellinus: A Translation and Commentary|location=Sydney|publisher=Australian Association for Byzantine Studies|year=1995|isbn=0-9593626-6-5|pages=36–38, 41–42|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last1=Jeffreys|first1=Elizabeth|last2=Jeffreys|first2=Michael|last3=Scott|first3=Roger|title=The Chronicle of John Malalas: A Translation|location=Melbourne|publisher=Australian Association for Byzantine Studies|year=1986|isbn=0959362622|pages=225–227, 231–233|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last1=Mango|first1=Cyril|author1-link=Cyril Mango|last2=Scott|first2=Roger|title=The Chronicle of Theophanes Confessor. Byzantine and Near Eastern History, AD 284–813|location=Oxford, United Kingdom|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=1997|isbn=0-19-822568-7|pages=238–245, 249, 253|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Whitby|first=Michael|title=Ecclesiastical History of Evagrius Scholasticus|location=Liverpool|publisher=Liverpool University Press|year=2000|isbn=0-85323-605-4|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=YP9cuh3KX3wC|pages=193–194, 200–203|ref=harv}}
{{refend|2}}

====Secondary====
{{refbegin|2}}
*{{cite book|last=Amory|first=Patrick|title=People and Identity in Ostrogothic Italy, 489–554|location=Cambridge|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=2003|origyear=1997|isbn=0-521-52635-3|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=7ndeDi_fwq0C|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Bury|first=John Bagnell|authorlink=J. B. Bury|title=History of the Later Roman Empire: From the Death of Theodosius I to the Death of Justinian, Volume 1|location=Mineola, New York|publisher=Dover Publications|year=1958a|origyear=1923|isbn=0-486-20398-0|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Jn3pi1wWBNsC|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Bury|first=John Bagnell|authorlink=J. B. Bury|title=History of the Later Roman Empire: From the Death of Theodosius I to the Death of Justinian, Volume 2|location=Mineola, New York|publisher=Dover Publications|year=1958b|origyear=1923|isbn=0-486-20399-9|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=JxWifqqPtUcC|ref=harv}}
*{{cite journal|last=Cameron|first=Alan|title=The Death of Vitalian (520 A.D.)|journal=Zeitschrift für Papyrologie und Epigraphik|volume=48|year=1982|pages=93–94|location=Bonn|publisher=Dr. Rudolf Habelt GmbH|jstor=20183637|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|editor1-last=Cameron|editor1-first=Averil|editor1-link=Averil Cameron|editor2-last=Ward-Perkins|editor2-first=Bryan|editor3-last=Whitby|editor3-first=Michael|title=The Cambridge Ancient History, Volume XIV, Late Antiquity: Empire and Successors, A.D. 425–600|location=Cambridge|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=2000|isbn=978-0-521-32591-2|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Qf8mrHjfZRoC|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|editor-last=Kazhdan|editor-first=Alexander|editor-link=Alexander Kazhdan|title=[[The Oxford Dictionary of Byzantium]]|location=New York and Oxford|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=1991|isbn=978-0-19-504652-6|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|editor1-last=Martindale|editor1-first=John Robert|editor2-last=Jones|editor2-first=Arnold Hugh Martin|editor3-last=Morris|editor3-first=J.|title=The Prosopography of the Later Roman Empire, Volume II: A.D. 395–527|location=Cambridge|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=1980|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=m3keKQEACAAJ|isbn=978-0-521-20159-9|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last1=Whitby|first1=Michael|last2=Whitby|first2=Mary|title=The History of Theophylact Simocatta|location=Oxford|publisher=Claredon Press|year=1986|isbn=978-0-19-822799-1|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=AtRfAAAAMAAJ|ref=harv}}
{{refend|2}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-bef | before=[[Justin I|Imp. Caesar Iustinus Augustus]] I,&lt;br /&gt; [[Eutharic|Fl. Eutharicus Cillica]] }}
{{s-ttl | title=[[List of Roman consuls|Consul]] of the [[Roman Empire]] | years=520 |regent1=[[Rusticius (consul 520)|Fl. Rusticius]] }}
{{s-aft | after=[[Justinian I|Fl. Petrus Sabbatius Iustinianus]],&lt;br /&gt; [[Valerius (consul 521)|Fl. Valerius]] }}
{{s-end}}

{{good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Vitalian}}
[[Category:520 deaths]]
[[Category:5th-century births]]
[[Category:6th-century Byzantine people]]
[[Category:Magistri militum]]
[[Category:Imperial Roman consuls]]
[[Category:Assassinated military personnel]]
[[Category:Byzantine rebels]]
[[Category:Roman-era Thracians]]
[[Category:Roman consuls dying in year of consulship]]
[[Category:Assassinated Byzantine people]]</text>
      <sha1>9ru935wd55p6m3cgxzump8r91ns2ydi</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
