<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Łódź insurrection (1905)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>13650626</id>
    <revision>
      <id>743381071</id>
      <parentid>702323767</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-09T11:38:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>http&amp;rarr;https for [[Google Books]] and [[Google News]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18449">{{good article}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Łódź insurrection
|partof=
|image=[[File:Pomnik Czynu Rewolucyjnego Lodz 1.jpg|200px|alt=monument]]
|caption=[[Łódź]] monument to the 1905 insurrection
|date=21–25 June 1905{{Ref label|a|a|none}}
|place=[[Łódź]], [[Piotrków Governorate]], [[Congress Poland]]
|result=Russian victory
|combatant1={{flagicon image|Socialist red flag.svg}} Polish worker militias
|combatant2={{flagicon|Russia}} [[Russian Empire]]
|commander1=Unknown
|commander2=Unknown
|strength1=over 3,000
|strength2=six infantry regiments and several cavalry regiments
|casualties1=151 (official) – over 200 (unofficial) dead&lt;br&gt;150 (official) – 2,000 (unofficial) wounded
|casualties2=Unknown
}}

The '''Łódź insurrection''', also known as the '''June Days''', was an uprising by Polish workers in [[Łódź]] against the [[Russian Empire]] between 21–25 June 1905.{{Ref label|a|a|none}} This event was one of the largest disturbances in the Russian-controlled [[Congress Poland]] during the [[Russian Revolution (1905)|Russian Revolution of 1905]]. Poland was [[revolution in the Kingdom of Poland (1905-1907)|a major center of revolutionary fighting in the Russian Empire in 1905–1907]], and the Łódź insurrection was a key incident in those events.

For months, workers in Łódź had been in a state of unrest, with several major [[strike action|strikes]] having taken place, which were forcibly suppressed by the Russian police and military. The insurrection began spontaneously, without backing from any organized group. Polish revolutionary groups were taken by surprise and did not play a major role in the subsequent events. Around 21–22 June, following clashes with the authorities in the previous days, angry workers began building barricades and assaulting police and military patrols. Additional troops were called by the authorities, who also declared [[martial law]]. On 23 June, no businesses operated in the city, as the police and military stormed dozens of workers' barricades. Eventually, by 25 June, the uprising was crushed, with estimates of several hundred dead and wounded. The uprising was reported in the international press and widely discussed by socialist and communist activists worldwide. Unrest in Łódź would continue for many months, although without protests on such a large-scale as before.

==Background==
{{main|Revolution in the Kingdom of Poland (1905–1907)}}
[[File:Polska 1907 adm-light-frame.png|thumb|right|300px|Tsardom of Poland, administrative divisions in 1907. Łódź was in the northern part of the [[Piotrków Governorate]] (in yellow)|alt=Administrative map of Poland]]

At the beginning of the 20th century, worsening economic conditions contributed to mounting tensions in Russia and Poland: the [[Russo-Japanese War]] had damaged the economy of the [[Congress Poland|Kingdom of Poland]], and by late 1904, over 100,000 Polish workers had lost their jobs.&lt;ref name=&quot;AA&quot;/&gt; In the late 19th and early 20th centuries, Łódź had been a major Polish industrial center, heavily [[urbanized]] and [[industrialized]], and its large [[working class]] made it an important stronghold of the Polish [[socialist]] movement.&lt;ref name=&quot;LeslieLeslie1983-49&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;wybrm&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;lewicowo&quot;/&gt; News of the [[Russian revolution of 1905|1905 Russian revolution]], together with its revolutionary spirit, spread quickly into Russian-controlled Poland from [[Saint Petersburg]], where [[Bloody Sunday (1905)|demonstrators had been massacred]] on 22 January. Poland was [[revolution in the Kingdom of Poland (1905-1907)|a major center of revolutionary fighting in the Russian Empire in 1905–1907]], and the Łódź insurrection was a key incident in those events.&lt;ref name=&quot;WIEMRew1905007&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb&quot;/&gt; Workers in Łódź had already begun [[strike action|striking]] sometime before 22 January, and by 31 January the tsarist police were reporting demonstrators carrying placards with slogans such as &quot;Down with the autocracy! Down with the war!&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;AA&quot;/&gt; This was capitalized on by factions in Russia and Poland that wanted more or less radical changes. Soon over 400,000 workers became involved in strikes in Poland.&lt;ref name=&quot;WIEMRew1905007&quot;/&gt;

[[Polish Socialist Party - Revolution Faction|The wing]] of the [[Polish Socialist Party]] (''Polska Partia Socjalistyczna, PPS'') that was loyal to [[Józef Piłsudski]] believed that Poles should show their determination to regain independence through active, violent protests against the Russians.&lt;ref name=&quot;Zamoyski-330&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Urb 118&quot;/&gt; This view was not shared by [[Roman Dmowski]]'s [[Narodowa Demokracja|National Democratic Party]] (ND, {{lang-pl|endecja}})&lt;ref name=&quot;Urb 118&quot;/&gt; nor by the PPS's own [[Polish Socialist Party - Left|&quot;Left&quot; (or &quot;Young&quot;) wing]].&lt;ref name=&quot;PWN&quot;/&gt; The National Democrats favored cooperation with the Russian authorities,&lt;ref name=&quot;Urb 118&quot;/&gt; while the PPS Left wanted to work together with Russian revolutionaries to topple the [[tsardom]] and saw the creation of a socialist [[utopia]] as more important than Polish independence.&lt;ref name=&quot;PWN&quot;/&gt;

The Russo-Japanese War had caused rising dissent throughout the Russian Empire, including its Polish provinces.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb2&quot;/&gt; On 26 January 1905 about 6,000 workers in Łódź took part in a large strike.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb2&quot;/&gt; Next day, a general strike was declared, and the day after that, 70,000 workers were on strike.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb2&quot;/&gt; They demanded an [[Eight-hour day|8-hour work day]] and support for the sick.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb2&quot;/&gt; Some worker demonstrations were joined by the students, who demanded an end to the policy of [[Russification]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb2&quot;/&gt; Another large strike occurred during the [[Labor Day]] on 1 May.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb2&quot;/&gt; It affected close to half of the city's industry. On 3 May, [[Constitution_of_May_3,_1791#Holiday|the anniversary of the Polish May Constitution]], another demonstration with patriotic undertones took place.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb2&quot;/&gt; On 30 May, Łódź's industrialists asked the [[Governor-general of Poland|Russian governor-general]] for help.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb2&quot;/&gt;

The murder of the worker Jerzy Grabczyński by Russian [[Cossack]] cavalry at the Grohmana is mentioned as one of the sparks of the insurrection.&lt;ref name=&quot;NowakWimmer1973&quot;/&gt; On 18 June 1905, Russian police opened fire on one of the many workers' demonstrations in Łódź, killing approximately ten workers, whose funerals, attended by over 50,000–70,000 people, escalated into major demonstrations on 20 and 21 June.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NowakWimmer1973&quot;/&gt; The funeral on 21 June was met by Cossack cavalry again; the crowd threw stones, and the Russian cavalry returned fire, killing 25 people and wounding hundreds.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb2&quot;/&gt; [[Social Democracy of the Kingdom of Poland and Lithuania]] (SDKPiL) called for a general strike on 23 June.&lt;ref name=&quot;NowakWimmer1973&quot;/&gt; 
[[File:Internacjonal lodz.jpg|thumb|left|Members of an [[Anarchist communism|Anarchist communist]] group in Łódź in 1906.|alt=see caption]]
Piłsudski's PPS, while not planning for a major uprising then and there, had a policy of supporting the protest and harassing Russian forces.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb&quot;/&gt; The PPS, as well as other socialist organizations, such as [[General Jewish Labour Bund in Lithuania, Poland and Russia|Jewish Bund]] and SDKPiL, were as surprised by the scale of the spontaneous revolt as the Russian authorities; PPS forces in Łódź consisted of 10 regular and armed PPS members and a few dozen semi-enlisted workers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NowakWimmer1973&quot;/&gt; A larger group sent from [[Warsaw]] under [[Walery Sławek]] never made it in time to take control or affect the uprising; it was, in the end, an anarchic and unorganized violent protest against the Russian government.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb&quot;/&gt;

==Uprising==
Tensions mounted further, and in the evening of 21&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb2&quot;/&gt; or 22 June&lt;ref name=&quot;NowakWimmer1973&quot;/&gt; (sources vary), angry workers began building barricades and assaulting police and military patrols, killing those who did not surrender.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NowakWimmer1973&quot;/&gt; About a hundred barricades were constructed over the course of the next few days.&lt;ref name=&quot;NowakWimmer1973&quot;/&gt;

Around Wschodnia street, workers opened fire on a [[Company (military unit)|company]] of soldiers and cavalry, and on Południowa street, a unit of gendarmes was surrounded.&lt;ref name=&quot;NowakWimmer1973&quot;/&gt; Several fires begun in the town, as workers set liquor stores on fire, and the government forces assaulted the first barricades, initially without much success.&lt;ref name=&quot;NowakWimmer1973&quot;/&gt; The tsarist representatives called from reinforcements, which came from [[Częstochowa]], Warsaw, and summer training camps.&lt;ref name=&quot;NowakWimmer1973&quot;/&gt; Several [[infantry]] [[regiment]]s entered the city.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb&quot;/&gt; Eventually, Russian forces sent to suppress the workers numbered six infantry regiments and several cavalry regiments.&lt;ref name=&quot;NowakWimmer1973&quot;/&gt; Despite that, the situation was spiralling into a full blown uprising. On 23 June, all industries, workshops, shops and offices were closed, as the workers and government forces clashed.&lt;ref name=&quot;NowakWimmer1973&quot;/&gt;

Some of the heaviest fighting took place near the intersection of Wschodnia and Południowa (now Rewolucji 1905 r.) streets (where four barricades were located), near the Scheibler factory in the Źródliska park and on the Rokociny road (al. Piłsudskiego).&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NowakWimmer1973&quot;/&gt; The Rokociny area was manned by a 3,000-strong worker militia, which eventually was forced to retreat to the Źródliska park.&lt;ref name=&quot;NowakWimmer1973&quot;/&gt; The insurgents had no organized agenda, and commonly fought under [[red flag (politics)|red standards]]; common demands were the improvement of workers' living conditions and greater rights for the [[Poles|Polish population]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb&quot;/&gt; On 23 June (or as late as 26 June&lt;ref name=&quot;NowakWimmer1973&quot;/&gt; – sources vary) the [[Tsar#Russia|Tsar]] signed a decree of [[martial law]] in the city.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb&quot;/&gt;  

The PPS-supported worker factions found themselves facing not only Russian police and regular troops, but ''[[endecja]]'' militia.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb&quot;/&gt; Armed clashes broke out between gunmen loyal to Piłsudski's PPS and those loyal to Dmowski. Over the course of the &quot;June Days&quot;, as the Łódź uprising became known in Poland, a miniature [[civil war]] raged between Piłsudski's PPS and Dmowski's ''endeks.''&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Zamoyski-330&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Urb 118&quot;/&gt; 

The insurgents were poorly armed, and eventually were overwhelmed by the tsarist regular military.&lt;ref name=&quot;NowakWimmer1973&quot;/&gt; Most of the barricades fell by 24 June; the last of the [[barricade]]s (in the Źródliska park and Wschodnia street) were captured by Russian troops by the end of 24 June&lt;ref name=&quot;NowakWimmer1973&quot;/&gt; or by midday on 25 June&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb&quot;/&gt; (sources vary), but unrest—including occasional shots at police or military patrols—would continue for days afterwards.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb&quot;/&gt;

==Aftermath==
[[File:PL lodz Doly Cemetery Mogila Bojownikow PPS.jpg|thumb|upright|Monument to the PPS fighters who died in the fighting in the years 1905–1907 at the [[Doły Cemetery]] in Łódź|alt=see caption]]
The uprising was ultimately crushed by the Russian authorities. Official reports indicated 151 civilian deaths (55 Poles, 79 Jews and 17 Germans) and 150 wounded;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NowakWimmer1973&quot;/&gt; unofficial reports spoke of over 200 fatalities and between 800&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MWrW&quot;/&gt; and as many as 2,000 wounded.&lt;ref name=&quot;WIEMRew1905007&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NowakWimmer1973&quot;/&gt;

The Łódź uprising was neither the first nor the last disturbance in what has been described in Polish historiography as the [[revolution in the Kingdom of Poland (1905–1907)]]&lt;ref name=&quot;WIEMRew1905007&quot;/&gt;—various protests and strikes occurred in major Polish cities under Russian control throughout the year&lt;ref name=&quot;AA&quot;/&gt;—but it would be the most dramatic one.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb&quot;/&gt; In September 1905, two PPS activists would assassinate [[Juliusz Karol Kunitzer]], owner of the Heinzel &amp; Kunitzer factory, known for his poor treatment of workers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Deutsche Geschichte im Osten Europas: Land der grossen Ströme&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Samuś1993&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Paweł Samuś|title=&quot;Bunt łódzki&quot; 1892 roku: studia z dziejów wielkiego konfliktu społecznego|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Wi_tAAAAMAAJ|accessdate=28 May 2011|year=1993|publisher=Wydawn. Uniw. Lódzkiego|isbn=978-83-7016-733-2|pages=64–65}}&lt;/ref&gt; Strikes in Łódź continued until mid-1906, when the large Russian military presence and mass layoffs of striking workers from the factories finally pacified the city.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;MWrW&quot;/&gt; Even afterward, Łódź was not a peaceful city; in the years 1910–1914 it was the site of a radical, [[anarchist]] and socialist group [[Rewolucyjni Mściciele]] labeled as &quot;the most extreme, terrorist group in the history of Poland&quot;.&lt;ref name=wybrm/&gt;

The uprising was reported in the international press and recognized by socialist and communist activists worldwide.&lt;ref name=&quot;NowakWimmer1973&quot;/&gt;

==Notes==
'''a''' {{Note label|a|a|none}} Sources are not in universal agreement as to when the insurrection started and ended. Many sources give dates of 22–24 June; however, according to some sources, the police and military were attacked as early as 21 June,&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb2&quot;/&gt; and the final barricade fell on 25 June.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb&quot;/&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|2|refs=

&lt;ref name=&quot;AA&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Abraham Ascher|title=The Revolution of 1905|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=9J9Dt6EQHs8C&amp;pg=PA157|accessdate=26 May 2011|year=1988|publisher=Stanford University Press|isbn=978-0-8047-2327-5|pages=157–158}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Deutsche Geschichte im Osten Europas: Land der grossen Ströme&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=|title=Deutsche Geschichte im Osten Europas: Land der grossen Ströme|first1= Joachim |last1=Rogall |publisher=Siedler|year=1996|isbn=3-88680-204-3|page=313|language=German}}&lt;br&gt;[http://www.lodz.ap.gov.pl/fab6.html biography] {{pl icon}}&lt;br&gt;[http://query.nytimes.com/mem/archive-free/pdf?res=9A07E4DE153AE733A25752C0A9669D946497D6CF New York Times, 1 October 1905]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;LeslieLeslie1983-49&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=Roy Francis Leslie|author2=R. F. Leslie|title=The History of Poland since 1863|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=0tYVKUsnw9IC&amp;pg=PA49|accessdate=26 June 2011|year=1983|publisher=Cambridge University Press|isbn=978-0-521-27501-9|page=49}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;MWrW&quot;&gt;{{pl icon}} [http://www.mowiawieki.pl/artykul.html?id_artykul=1312 Rewolucyjna Warszawa], ''[[Mówią Wieki]]''. Retrieved on 9 October 2007&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;NowakWimmer1973&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author1=Tadeusz Nowak|author2=Jan Wimmer|author3=Eligiusz Kozłowski|author4=Mieczysław Wrzosek|title=Dzieje oręża polskiego, 963–1945: Kozłowski, E., Wrzosek, M. 1794–1938|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZilHAAAAIAAJ|accessdate=27 May 2011|year=1973|publisher=Wydawn. Ministerstwa Obrony Narodowej|pages=305–306}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;PWN&quot;&gt;{{pl icon}} Chojnowski, Andrzej. [http://encyklopedia.pwn.pl/haslo.php?id=3957301 &quot;Piłsudski, Józef Klemens&quot;]. ''Wydawnictwie Naukowym PWN''.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Urb 118&quot;&gt;[[Bohdan Urbankowski|Urbankowski, Bohdan]]. ''Józef Piłsudski: marzyciel i strateg'' [&quot;Józef Piłsudski: Dreamer and Strategist&quot;], Vol. 1. Warsaw: Wydawnictwo ALFA, 1997. ISBN 83-7001-914-5, p. 118&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;WIEMRew1905007&quot;&gt;{{pl icon}} [http://portalwiedzy.onet.pl/20246,,,,rewolucja_1905_1907_w_krolestwie_polskim,haslo.html &quot;Rewolucja 1905–1907 w Królestwie Polskim&quot;], portalwiedzy.onet.pl. [[Encyklopedia WIEM]] Retrieved on 9 October 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb&quot;&gt;{{pl icon}} Kalicki, Włodzimierz. [http://www.gazetawyborcza.pl/1,75478,3058864.html &quot;Rok 1905: Przebudzeni bombą&quot;], [[Gazeta Wyborcza]], 9 December 2005. Retrieved on 9 October 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Wyb2&quot;&gt;{{pl icon}} Joanna Podolska, Michał Jagiełło, ''[http://lodz.gazeta.pl/lodz/1,37846,4526453.html Barykady, które dały przykład ]'', Gazeta Wyborcza, 27 September 2007, Retrieved on 20 May 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Zamoyski-330&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Adam Zamoyski|title=The Polish way: a thousand-year history of the Poles and their culture|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=znCWQgAACAAJ|accessdate=26 May 2011|year=1987|publisher=John Murray|isbn=978-0-7195-4674-7|page=330}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;lewicowo&quot;&gt;{{pl icon}} Eugeniusz Ajnenkiel, ''[http://www.historialodzi.obraz.com.pl/?p=24873 Łódź – pochodnia polskiego socjalizmu]'', Księga Jubileuszowa Polskiej Partii Socjalistycznej 1892–1932”, Spółka Nakładowo-Wydawnicza „Robotnik”, Warszawa 1933&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;wybrm&quot;&gt;{{pl icon}} Maciej Stańczyk, ''[http://lodz.gazeta.pl/lodz/1,35136,8974439,Rewolucyjni_Msciciele__Zapomniana_lodzka_historia.html  Rewolucyjni Mściciele. Zapomniana łódzka historia ]'', Gazeta Wyborcza, 2011-01-20&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

==Further reading==
* Blobaum, Robert. ''Rewolucja: Russian Poland, 1904–1907''. Cornell: Cornell University Press, 1997. ISBN 0-8014-3287-1.
* Korzec, P. ''Walki rewolucyjne w Łodzi i okręgu łódzkim w latach 1905–1907''. Warsaw: Państwowe Wydawnictwo Naukowe, 1956.
* {{cite journal|title=Łódź w ogniu rewolucji 1905 r.|journal=Ilustrowana encyklopedia historii Łodzi. Miesięcznik Łódzki &quot;Piotrkowska 104&quot; (Supplement Historyczny)|volume=VII/12|issue=7|pages=196–197|url=http://uml.lodz.pl/get.php?id=835|accessdate=30 December 2011|editor1-first=Arkadiusz|editor1-last=Grzegorczyk|publisher=URZĄD MIASTA ŁODZI|issn=1731-092X}}

{{Polish uprisings}}
{{Polish wars and conflicts}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2010}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Lodz Insurrection (1905)}}
[[Category:1905 in Poland]]
[[Category:1905 in Russia]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1905]]
[[Category:History of Łódź]]
[[Category:History of Poland (1795–1918)]]
[[Category:Rebellions in Poland]]
[[Category:Piotrków Governorate]]
[[Category:1905 Russian Revolution]]
[[Category:Civil wars involving the states and peoples of Europe]]
[[Category:20th-century rebellions]]
[[Category:Labor disputes in Poland]]
[[Category:Civil wars of the Industrial era]]</text>
      <sha1>5p9nwhhzdjr3n6cjpv2ndgt43wtgz3a</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
