<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Treaty on the Final Settlement with Respect to Germany</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>983202</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738344162</id>
      <parentid>734969007</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-08T11:20:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Nick Mitchell 98</username>
        <id>19666637</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Nick Mitchell 98 moved page [[Talk:Treaty on the Final Settlement with Respect to Germany (Two-Plus-Four Treaty)]] to [[Talk:Treaty on the Final Settlement with Respect to Germany]] over redirect: No consensus or legitimate reason for page move, revert...</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12416">{{Talk header}}
{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WPMILHIST|class=Start
|&lt;!-- B-Class-1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points have appropriate inline citations. --&gt;
|B-Class-1=no
&lt;!-- B-Class-2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain obvious omissions or inaccuracies. --&gt;
|B-Class-2=no
&lt;!-- B-Class-3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content. --&gt;
|B-Class-3=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-4. It is free from major grammatical errors. --&gt;
|B-Class-4=yes
&lt;!-- B-Class-5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams. --&gt;
|B-Class-5=no
|German-task-force=yes|British-task-force=yes|Russian-task-force=yes
|US-task-force=yes|WWII-task-force=yes}}
{{WikiProject Germany|class=Start|importance=High|B-Class-1=no|B-Class-2=no|B-Class-3=y|B-Class-4=y|B-Class-5=no}}
{{WikiProject Russia|class=Start|importance=Low|hist=yes|mil=yes
&lt;!--1. It is suitably referenced, and all major points are appropriately cited.--&gt;
|B-Class-1=no
&lt;!--2. It reasonably covers the topic, and does not contain major omissions or inaccuracies.--&gt;
|B-Class-2=no
&lt;!--3. It has a defined structure, including a lead section and one or more sections of content.--&gt;
|B-Class-3=yes
&lt;!--4. It is free from major grammatical errors.--&gt;
|B-Class-4=yes
&lt;!--5. It contains appropriate supporting materials, such as an infobox, images, or diagrams.--&gt;
|B-Class-5=no
}}
{{WikiProject Soviet Union|class=Start|importance=Low|mil=yes}}
{{WikiProject Politics of the United Kingdom|class=Start|importance=Low}}
{{WikiProject Former countries|class=Start|importance=Mid|Prussia=yes}}
{{WikiProject Cold War}}
{{WikiProject International relations}}
{{WikiProject European history}}
}}
{{On this day|date1=2004-09-12|oldid1=6403933}}

==Redirect==
Could somebody who knows how create a couple redirects to this page, for example from &quot;2+4,&quot; &quot;2 + 4,&quot; &quot;2+4 negotiations,&quot; etc.?  That would be awesome, thanks.  [[User:Nicolasdz|Nicolasdz]] 21:45, 3 March 2006 (UTC)

: Done. [[2+4]] [[2 + 4]] [[2+4 Negotiations]] [[2 + 4 Negotiations]] [[2 4 Negotiations]] (The last one was a mistake, but oh well.) Any others? [[User:MarcusGraly|MarcusGraly]] 15:14, 10 March 2006 (UTC)

==Changing the navigation box==
I would like to change the template from [[Template:Politics of Germany]] to [[Template:German borders]].  Any objections?
--[[User:Richardshusr|Richard]] 19:20, 6 March 2007 (UTC)

Why this articel blong to POLISH history????

: Ha, I think someone really wanted to make this into something about Poland. The map of Poland on a page on Germany sure is trippy. Perhaps distracting. 

: I found a single reference to Poland in the body of the treaty text. While the border with Poland is defined (less specifically than in this article), it is ''confirmed''. You'd expect the borders of the state to be defined throughout the first article of an international merger, right? Poland's mentioned for reasons you can find in the link, and I know this is really important for Poland, but not close to &quot;perhaps the most important&quot;. The most important feature of this treaty was German unification. The provisions were against another war-capable, claim staking Germany. So that's the POV edit. [[User:JFHJr|JFHJr]] ([[User talk:JFHJr|㊟]]) 03:35, 27 June 2007 (UTC)

==Does the treaty still hold?==
Out of interest, does the treaty still hold (is it still valid)? I only wonder as the Soviet Union, one of the signatories and the one to whom the agreements on arms were made to, no longer exists, is Germany still bound by the agreement? [[User:Fetu&amp;#39;s dad|Fetu&amp;#39;s dad]] ([[User talk:Fetu&amp;#39;s dad|talk]]) 00:35, 12 March 2008 (UTC)
:As a german I hope so. I assume that Russia has taken over the place of the Soviet Union.--[[User:Oneiros|Oneiros]] ([[User talk:Oneiros|talk]]) 14:31, 12 March 2008 (UTC)
::Yeah! Today no foreign armed forces, nuclear weapons or their carriers are stationed in former East Germany or deployed there.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/85.178.89.141|85.178.89.141]] ([[User talk:85.178.89.141|talk]]) 03:33, 17 March 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

==Saar Region missing==
The Saarland used to be a UN protectorate after WWII, and after a failed vote to make it an independent country, it was reunited with Germany in 1957. Maybe somebody could link it: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saar_%281947%E2%80%931957%29 I don't want to mess up the box. ––[[User:Mwimmer|Mwimmer]] ([[User talk:Mwimmer|talk]]) 17:41, 8 August 2008 (UTC)

==Why?==
Why did the Allies even sign this treaty??? It seems they are only giving up the rights they were holding over Germany and Berlin, and got nothing in return. This must be one of the most one-sided international treaties ever made.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/77.181.194.12|77.181.194.12]] ([[User talk:77.181.194.12|talk]]) 23:03, 11 August 2011 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:What they got was a democratic, stable German state that they no longer had the responsibility to police. Sounds like a bargain. [[Special:Contributions/109.155.172.75|109.155.172.75]] ([[User talk:109.155.172.75|talk]]) 20:39, 25 September 2011 (UTC)
::sowjets got money; french got the euro; us got a reunifed germany in nato; only uk got nothing cause thatcher accepted no deal  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/85.195.69.112|85.195.69.112]] ([[User talk:85.195.69.112|talk]]) 18:59, 1 February 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:::And besides, it's rather the normal state of affairs that wars are followed with a peace treaty which 100% restores souvereignty and 100% ends occupation. Sometimes the loser has to &quot;pay with a province&quot; (Francis Joseph's expression concerning the Lombardy) - but then, Germany ''had'' paid Silesia, Eastern Prussia and so forth.--[[Special:Contributions/131.159.0.47|131.159.0.47]] ([[User talk:131.159.0.47|talk]]) 13:41, 4 May 2015 (UTC)

== &quot;Another of the treaty's important terms was Germany's confirmation of the internationally recognized border with Poland and Russia&quot; ==

Whoever wrote that is ignorant of International law.  The former German province of East Prussia was in a &quot;temporary administered pending the Final Peace Treaty with Germany&quot; status for 45 years (1945-1990).  It was only after the Germans in the 1990 Peace Treaty stipulated that &quot;Germany&quot; is only those lands within the 1990 Peace Treaty approved boundaries that the Russians and the Poles could petition for International Law to recognize the 45 year old line in East Prussia which separated the Russian &quot;Administrators&quot; from the Polish &quot;Administrators&quot; as being, post German Peace Treaty, an international boundary between Poland and Russia.

Here is from Article 1 of the 1990 German Peace Treaty:

ARTICLE 1
(1) The united Germany shall comprise the territory of the Federal Republic of Germany,
the German Democratic Republic and the whole of Berlin. Its external borders shall be
the borders of the Federal Republic of Germany and the German Democratic Republic
and shall be definitive from the date on which the present Treaty comes into force. The
confirmation of the definitive nature of the borders of the united Germany is an essential
element of the peaceful order in Europe.
(2) The united Germany and the Republic of Poland shall confirm the existing border
between them in a treaty that is binding under international law.
(3) The united Germany has no territorial claims whatsoever against other states and shall
not assert any in the future.
(4) The Governments of the Federal Republic of Germany and the German Democratic
Republic shall ensure that the constitution of the united Germany does not contain any
provision incompatible with these principles. This applies accordingly to the provisions
laid down in the preamble, the second sentence of Article 23, and Article 146 of the Basic
Law for the Federal Republic of Germany.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/76.14.243.123|76.14.243.123]] ([[User talk:76.14.243.123|talk]]) 06:37, 22 June 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

::Well, it was the German point of view that Eastern provinces were under Polish administration (though even in the German view, they said ''administration'', which is much much more than mere ''occupation''), but not necessarily the view of the rest of the world. Also, Germany itself had (somewhat) recognized the Polish border in a treaty in 1972 (or so), leaving a tiny loophole for the event of a future Reunification, but by no means more than that (which was highly controversial in the 1970s, to be sure).--[[Special:Contributions/131.159.0.47|131.159.0.47]] ([[User talk:131.159.0.47|talk]]) 13:49, 4 May 2015 (UTC)

==Fully sovereign==
Was the Federal Republic of Germany not a sovereign state before? I think I was the one who originally wrote that Germany became a fully sovereign state with the treaty, but I think I was wrong looking back. Can anyone point to me any powers the Allies had over West Germany before this treaty was signed (aside from Berlin, which was not part of the Federal Republic)?'''Bold text'''
&lt;br&gt; - 07:15, 28 December 2015‎ Reenem
::United Berlin became a part of the Federal Republic of Germany on 3 October 1990 at the moment of German Reunification, but Berlin was still under a (soft) Occupation regime until this Treaty entered into force on 15 March 1990 and the last Allied Forces left in 1994 under its terms. Also, East Germany was absorbed by the Federal Republic upon reunification, but the [[Group of Soviet Forces in Germany]] remained present in the new territory acquired by the Federal Republic until the completion of the Allied withdrawal on 31 August 1994 under the Treaty. So, yes, parts of the Federal Republic had a presence of Occupation forces that needed to withdraw. Granted that, regarding West Germany proper (not including West Berlin that technically was not a part of West Germany), the Occupation regime had ended with the Paris Treaty of 23 October 1954 that entered into force on 5 May 1955. But the Western Allies retained an Occupation presence in West Berlin, and only left as a consequence of the Two-Plus-Four Treaty. Also, the Allied Control Council had to meet to authorize the inclusion of the city of Berlin, due to its special international status as still-Occupied territory, in the German Reunification. Furthermore, the Potsdam Agreement had created ''provisional'' borders for Germany, and had ceded areas to Polish ''administration'' pending the final settlement of Germany's borders in a definitive Peace Treaty. Therefore, the solution was still provisional, and the areas acquired by Poland were not fully Polish ''de jure'' in international law until a final decision was made in the Peace Treaty with Germany. That decision was formalized in the Treaty of Final Settlement with respect to Germany: under the Treaty, Germany as required to renounce all claim to land situated to the East of the Oder-Niesse line, and assumed before the Allies the obligation to sign a Treaty with the Republic of Poland so as to confirm as permanent and final the then existing border between them. Germany complied with that demand, and signed the German-Polish Border Treaty.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Antonio Basto|Antonio Basto]] ([[User talk:Antonio Basto|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Antonio Basto|contribs]]) 16:16, 29 May 2016 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== What can we say about the negotiations ==

[[2+4 Negotiations]] [[2 + 4 Negotiations]] link here but there is nothing about the negotiations (sadly). I had heard that M Thatcher was reluctant to agree to this treaty but nothing here about the negotiations and trade-offs. - [[User:Rod57|Rod57]] ([[User talk:Rod57|talk]]) 11:37, 25 June 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>lsh5i4nxwrjvb5501ujaimsa6yggiy1</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
