<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Ljudevit</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>4220329</id>
    <revision>
      <id>699645077</id>
      <parentid>699644610</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-01-13T16:11:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Joy</username>
        <id>20318</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Joy moved page [[Talk:Liudewit]] to [[Talk:Ljudevit]]: per Talk, partially revert to the most common name (less Frankish, more Slavic)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12223">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Biography|living=no|class=Start|royalty-work-group=yes|listas=Posavski, Ljudevit}}
{{WikiProject Croatia|class=Start|importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Slovenia|class=start|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Serbia|class=Start|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject MILHIST|class=Start|b1=n|b2=n|b3=y|b4=y|b5=n|Biography=y|Balkan=yes|Medieval=yes}}
{{WikiProject Middle Ages|class=Start|importance=}}
}}

==Cleanup==

What's wrong?
*bad italicisation
*links in headings
*seems to be too many unnecessary links
*missing capitalisation
[[User:Srnec|Srnec]] 22:40, 27 February 2006 (UTC)

----
==About the Serbs==

It seems that the Serbs mentioned here are people of the Srb county in Lika.
I won't edit anything concerning this for now, meaning a month or two. In the meantime, I would be grateful for any replies on this issue.[[User:Mor Vilkacis|Mor Vilkacis]] 23:16, 22 April 2006 (UTC)

:If you find any '''''sources''''', place that here. --[[User:HolyRomanEmperor|HolyRomanEmperor]] 13:40, 24 April 2006 (UTC)

== The Source ==

It should be mentioned that the only surviving source for Ljudevit are Einhardt's annals, and since Einhard always glorified the Franks successes and usually didnt mention their defeats, the view on the entire event is pro-Frankish. An example is the fact that Einhard never mentions Franksih defeat, instead saying things like &quot;they returned leaving their work mostly undone&quot;. Another is the amount of casualties Ljudevit suffers - 3000 men would be crippling casualties for a small early medieval state.
One more thing, Ljudevit didn't flee to Borna, but to Borna's uncle Ljudemisl, who at first accepted him, but then had him killed from ambush.

: '''Be bold''', and corect it yourself. --[[User:HolyRomanEmperor|HolyRomanEmperor]] 10:01, 3 May 2006 (UTC)

== Clarified Croat Connection ==
* Changed link to Medieval state of Croatia instead of previous Pannonia b/c more relevant;
* Changed Slav link to Croats;
* Changed Pannonian reference to Pannonian Croats b/c better reflects actual population of the time and it's role as a forerunner to the [[Kingdom of Croatia]];
* Removed refernce to expanding &quot;Croatian lands eastward&quot; as it represents an opinion based on a certain interpretation of the annals;
* Removed reference to controlling much of Dalmatia as it caries little meaning because the roman province of Dalmatia wcovered an extensive area.  
[[User:Marinko|iruka]] 08:00, 1 December 2006 (UTC)

But you also removed mentions of Serbs. --[[User:PaxEquilibrium|PaxEquilibrium]] 22:03, 1 December 2006 (UTC)
: Correction - Removed mention of Serbs in ''''introduction'''' b/c carries little relevance to his rule &amp; b/c it's already covered in whole section in the main article devoted to Serbs. [[User:Marinko|iruka]] 03:31, 2 December 2006 (UTC)
::Partial rv
::* returned link to Medieval state of Croatia b/c directly relevant - Ljudevit was a duke of the medieval Croat state in Pannonia.  However made link to Pannonia article at the start of the main article;
::* kept reference to Serbs in introduction, but rewrote to give more context.
::* Changed Slav link to Croats - again b/c relevance. Ljudevit was the Duke of Pannonian Croats, Borna, Duke of Dalmatian Croats;
::* Changed Dlamatia link to History of Dalmatia link - b/c more relevant.  Created Dalmatia link elsewhere in article.
::* Changed Pannonian reference to Pannonian Croats b/c better reflects actual population of the time and it's role as a forerunner to the [[Kingdom of Croatia]].
::[[User:Marinko|iruka]] 03:31, 2 December 2006 (UTC)
::Removed refernce to expanding &quot;Croatian lands eastward&quot; as it represents an opinion based on an ''interpretation'' of the Frankish annals.  [[User:Marinko|iruka]] 03:47, 2 December 2006 (UTC)

:::That's better. :) However, I don't see your reformulation in the intro - while he ruled the Serbs, he ''did not'' rule the Croats - so why change that part. Also, his expansions of the Croatian state eastwards are completely logical - never did a Croatian state include Syrmia, for instance. --[[User:PaxEquilibrium|PaxEquilibrium]] 12:57, 2 December 2006 (UTC)
::::Can you explain by what you mean he didn't rule the Croats.  The precursor of the kingdom of Croatia was comprise of Croat Dukedoms in Pannonia and Dalmatia corresponding to Pannonian Croat and Dalmatian Croat populations. [[User:Marinko|iruka]] 13:43, 2 December 2006 (UTC)

:::::He ''fled''; abandoned his real - and ''never'' restored - rule over the Croats. This reflects that he ruled Pannonia, and ''then extended his territories to include Serbia'' - but he did no such thing. He ''stopped'' being the Croat ruler - and became the Serb ruler (of a totally different political faction). In the end he lost that throne as well, leaving him to live in further exile in the heart of his enemy - which eventually brought death upon him. --[[User:PaxEquilibrium|PaxEquilibrium]] 21:47, 2 December 2006 (UTC)
::::::Ok, I see what you mean now. I've rewritten to correct that ambiguity - can you pls review; also added the significance Ljudevit's in laying groundwork for unification of Pannonian &amp; Dalmatian Croatian Duchies. [[User:Marinko|iruka]] 00:45, 3 December 2006 (UTC)
::::::The problem I see with extending lands eastward remark is that the borders between the various medieval entities were very fluid, and the question of permanancy or when it happened is highly debateable.  Croatia's borders moved east and west and finally adopted a crescent shape as a result of Turkish expansion and Hasburg counter-response.  Serbia's moved east &amp; west, south until it moved north.  These developments ebb and flow and one cannot point to a decisive moment for such historical phenomena. [[User:Marinko|iruka]] 00:45, 3 December 2006 (UTC)

:::::::Actually, historians ''always'' (up to the 1990s - I guess the brake-up-of-Yugo-disease cough up with them) noted (read: '''always with no exception''') that this was the first panYugoslavic attempt, unifying Slovenes, a large number of Croats and even many Serbs (speaking about futuristic nations, normally - or better &quot;Pannonians&quot;, &quot;Timokians&quot;, &quot;Karantanians&quot;, etc.). His attempts were often called upon by Alexander Karadjordjevic, the Illyrists and other similar people. And I personally believe that his attempts made no relevance to the actual unification of all Croat lands - but pan-Slavic gathering. --[[User:PaxEquilibrium|PaxEquilibrium]] 10:55, 3 December 2006 (UTC)

==A question regarding comment==

A question posed to author of [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Ljudevit_Posavski&amp;curid=2892020&amp;diff=109615427&amp;oldid=109556226 this] posting:&lt;br&gt;
What does this comment mean [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Ljudevit_Posavski&amp;curid=2892020&amp;diff=109615427&amp;oldid=109556226]? &lt;br&gt;
&quot;''...Southern Dalmatia Serb''&quot;?[[User:Kubura|Kubura]] 13:38, 21 February 2007 (UTC)

a [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=User_talk:Kubura&amp;oldid=110411975 reply] on Kubura's talk page:&lt;br&gt;
:Re: Serbs settled the southern, larger, half of the Province of Dalmatia; Croats settled the northern, slightly smaller, half of the Province (I'm not going to get into Illyricum &amp; Praevalis complications). --[[User:PaxEquilibrium|PaxEquilibrium]] 20:33, 23 February 2007 (UTC)

::True. Many people use(d) ''double standards'' like [[User:Medule]]; at numerous occasions denying that these people are Croats '''and''' that Serbs lived from central Arboria to the river of Cetina ''at the same time''... a very naughty thing to do. --[[User:PaxEquilibrium|PaxEquilibrium]] 12:53, 12 March 2007 (UTC)

==Western Bosnia==

PE can you please explain what means &quot;Western Bosnia&quot;? I am removing the &quot;western&quot; because I think that is misleading. Do you talk about today [[Bosnia(region)|Bosnia]]? Becuase if you do, that would be wrong since what is today &quot;Western Bosnia&quot; was part of Croatia in medieval times. So basically stating Ljudevit fled to western Bosnia would collide with the rest stated in the section. Western Bosnia in the terms of Ljudevit's time would be somewhere around river Bosna or Sana. That is why I also think theory about Ljudevit fleeing to Srb at Una is also 
completely wrong. Is it possible we can somehow incorporate this into the article without confusing those who don't know much about the history of the region? --[[User:Verancin|Verancin]] 23:16, 12 September 2007 (UTC)

== Name ==

Is the present title of the article based on reliable sources published in English? He is mentioned as '''Liudewit''' in at least four modern scholarly work published in English: (1) Curta, Florin (2006). ''Southeastern Europe in the Middle Ages, 500&amp;ndash;1250''. Cambridge University Press. ISBN 978-0-521-89452-4. (2) Goldberg, Eric J. (2006). ''Struggle for Empire: Kingship and Conflict under Louis the German, 817&amp;ndash;876''. Cornell University Press. ISBN 978-0-8014-7529-0. (3) Bowlus, Charles R. (1994). ''Franks, Moravians and Magyars: The Struggle for the Middle Danube, 788&amp;ndash;907''. University of Pennsylvania Press. ISBN 0-8122-3276-3. (4) McCornick, Michael (2001). ''Origins of the European Economy: Communications and Commerce, AD 300–900''. Cambridge University Press. ISBN 0-521-66102-1. In other works, also published in English, he is mentioned as '''Ljudevit''' (Tanner, Marcus (1997). Croatia: A Nation Forged in War. Yale University Press. ISBN 978-0-300-16394-0 and Fine, John V. A. (2006). ''When Ethnicity Did Not Matter in the Balkans: A Study of Identity in Pre-Nationalist Croatia, Dalmatia, and Slavonia in the Medieval and Early-Modern Period''. The Universisty of Michigan Press. ISBN 978-0-472-11414-6) or '''Ljudevit of Pannonia''' (Magaš, Branka (2007). ''Croatia Through History''. SAQI. ISBN 978-0-86356-775-9). [[User:Borsoka|Borsoka]] ([[User talk:Borsoka|talk]]) 13:29, 30 December 2015 (UTC)
:I would definitely support changing &quot;Posavski&quot; to &quot;of Posavina&quot;. &quot;Liudewit&quot; also sounds reasonable. [[User:Surtsicna|Surtsicna]] ([[User talk:Surtsicna|talk]]) 15:09, 30 December 2015 (UTC)
:::The above cited sources suggest that &quot;Liudewit&quot; is his most common English name, without any adjective. [[User:Borsoka|Borsoka]] ([[User talk:Borsoka|talk]]) 15:30, 30 December 2015 (UTC)
::::If most scholarly works indeed use ''Liudewit'', move to &quot;Liudewit&quot;, without byname.--[[User_talk:Zoupan|Z&lt;small&gt;oupan&lt;/small&gt;]] 15:40, 30 December 2015 (UTC)
::::Agree. --[[User:Norden1990|Norden1990]] ([[User talk:Norden1990|talk]]) 20:49, 30 December 2015 (UTC)

:::::* https://www.google.com/search?q=Ljudevit+Pannonia+819&amp;tbm=bks&amp;pws=0 last page says 106 results
:::::* https://www.google.com/search?q=Liudewit+Pannonia+819&amp;tbm=bks&amp;pws=0 last page says 21 results
:::::* https://www.google.com/search?q=Ljudevit+Franks+819&amp;tbm=bks&amp;pws=0 can't seem to get to last page, says about 286 results
:::::* https://www.google.com/search?q=Liudewit+Franks+819&amp;tbm=bks&amp;pws=0 last page says 25 results
::::: On the first set, in the first 20, six are Croatian-looking authors, but still in English. Looks to me that the former spelling is far more common, so I'm inclined to move it back to &quot;Ljudevit&quot;. --[[User:Joy|Joy &amp;#91;shallot&amp;#93;]] ([[User talk:Joy|talk]]) 22:18, 12 January 2016 (UTC)
::::::I get 121, 17, 75, 23. So, yes, a move to ''Ljudevit'', as per CN.--[[User_talk:Zoupan|Z&lt;small&gt;oupan&lt;/small&gt;]] 03:47, 13 January 2016 (UTC)
::::::My only concern is that the present title can be properly pronounced even by readers who do not know Croatian alphabet (I assume that &quot;j&quot; is pronounced in Croatian as &quot;y&quot; in &quot;yes&quot;, not as &quot;j&quot; in &quot;jelousy&quot; or &quot;journal&quot;). [[User:Borsoka|Borsoka]] ([[User talk:Borsoka|talk]]) 06:14, 13 January 2016 (UTC)
{{unindent}} We could add IPA.--[[User_talk:Zoupan|Z&lt;small&gt;oupan&lt;/small&gt;]] 06:16, 13 January 2016 (UTC)
:: Yes. Liudewit isn't a panacea because it could still easily be pronounced 'liew-dew-it', so it gets a different vowel in the middle. Both spellings are clearly foreign and opaque to English speakers, so there's no big gain either way as far as that aspect is concerned. Heck, the word is pretty archaic even to Croatian speakers. --[[User:Joy|Joy &amp;#91;shallot&amp;#93;]] ([[User talk:Joy|talk]]) 16:06, 13 January 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>b314kpvisj92ptqv24jmqb9ueteaclf</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
