<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Mamluk Sultanate (Cairo)</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>20738602</id>
    <revision>
      <id>724406259</id>
      <parentid>723596718</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-06-09T01:58:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Iryna Harpy</username>
        <id>15706878</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Countries listed by alphabetical order */ r</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15144">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Africa |class=B |importance=Top}}
{{WikiProject Arab world |class=B |importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Egypt |class=B |importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Former countries |class=B |importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Israel |class=B |importance=}}
{{WikiProject Middle Ages |class=B |importance=High}}
{{WikiProject Military history |class=B |African-task-force=yes|Middle-Eastern-task-force=yes|Medieval=yes|Early-Modern=y}}
{{WikiProject Palestine |class=B |importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Syria |class=B |importance=High}}
}}

==Untitled==
I have begun this page in order to disambiguate the political government of the Mamluk Sultanate (1250-1517) from the wider social phenomenon of mamlukery (9th-19th centuries).  See discussion at [[Talk:Mamluk]].  This page is still very new.  I have entered section headings to organize future writing.  Most are empty now and a few have substubs.  These will be filled in soon, inshallah. [[User:Worlingham|Worlingham]] ([[User talk:Worlingham|talk]]) 03:32, 17 December 2008 (UTC)

== Extend to March 1, 1811 coup by Muhammad Ali ==
Perhaps being overbold (&amp; knowing nothing of the subject), based on the March 1, 2011 &quot;On this day...&quot; item on the front page, I have extended the article from the 14th Century to the 1811 coup by [[Muhammad Ali]], as seems needed based on the article title.  I have just copied text from three subsections of [[Mamluk Sultanate (Cairo)]] to here.  I hope other editors will correct any necessary disconnects that result.  I just want readers from the front page to find what the link there suggests they (as I) will want to learn. I have also made some of the spelling and capitalization consistent. [[User:Wwheaton|Wwheaton]] ([[User talk:Wwheaton|talk]]) 15:32, 1 March 2011 (UTC)

== Transfer to ''Mamluk Sultanate'' ==
Why the title includes the specifier ''(Cairo)''? There isn't other Mamluk Sultanate, if there is then the [[Mamluk Sultanate]] must become a disambiguation page. --[[User:Περίεργος|Περίεργος]] ([[User talk:Περίεργος|talk]]) 14:13, 20 August 2011 (UTC)

== Barakah ==

&quot;In 1377 a revolt broke out in Syria which spread to Egypt, and the government was taken over by the Circassians '''Barakah''' and Barquq&quot; (section &quot;Change in regime&quot;). Could anybody clarify who's that Barakah? Certainly, he is not sultan (not [[Al-Said Barakah]], of course). I can't find emir of this name in secondary sources such as Cambridge History of Egypt. --[[User:Bahatur|Bahatur]] ([[User talk:Bahatur|talk]]) 17:53, 18 December 2012 (UTC)

== Stop adding georgians to Mamluk Dynasty ==
Stop adding georgians to Mamluk Dynasty. there were two dynasty Bahri and Burji. Bahris were Turks and Burjis were Circassians. if you can show a ref for georgian Mamluk Sultan in Cairo you can add georgians, until then stop changing this page.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Oeneki|Oeneki]] ([[User talk:Oeneki|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Oeneki|contribs]]) 21:29, 10 March 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:FYI, You have been given a warning for edit warring. 
:*Also, this source[http://www.napoleon-series.org/military/organization/c_mameluks1.html], &quot;The Georgian Mameluks in Egypt&quot;, by Alexander Mikaberidze, checks out. &quot;''1382-1517 (in fact till 1811, including period of supremacy of Ottoman Empire) - Dynasty of Burji (&quot;Burgites&quot;) Mameluks, mostly of Georgian and Circassian origin. Their name has its origins in the Arabic word &quot;burj&quot; which means tower, castle or fortress where the Mameluk garrisons was deployed''&quot;. 
:*However, this source &quot;A History of African Societies to 1870&quot;, Elizabeth Isichei, p192, states, &quot;''Kurds or Slavs''&quot;, and mentions, &quot;''a majority in the later Mamluk period in Egypt came from the Caucasus''&quot;. but does not directly mention Georgians.[http://books.google.com/books?id=3C2tzBSAp3MC&amp;pg=PA192&amp;dq=A+History+of+African+Societies+to+1870+mamluk+Kurds+or+Slavs&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=6gI9UefoF-a32wXMuIGIDA&amp;ved=0CDAQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=A%20History%20of%20African%20Societies%20to%201870%20mamluk%20Kurds%20or%20Slavs&amp;f=false] 
:Therefore, the first source does mention Georgian Mamluks. --[[User:Kansas Bear|Kansas Bear]] ([[User talk:Kansas Bear|talk]]) 22:10, 10 March 2013 (UTC)

:Sources for Georgian mamluks;
:*[http://books.google.com/books?id=WoPF9T4ZiWsC&amp;pg=PA115&amp;dq=Georgian+mamluk&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=qwU9UaarJaik2gXFlYDYCA&amp;ved=0CDAQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=Georgian%20mamluk&amp;f=false], ''The Mamluks in Egyptian Politics and Society'', Thomas Philipp, Ulrich Haarmann.
:*[http://books.google.com/books?id=QtlY011yusEC&amp;pg=PA170&amp;dq=Georgian+mamluk&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=AAY9UYnECuW-2gWovYH4CQ&amp;ved=0CDcQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Georgian%20mamluk&amp;f=false], ''The Politics of Households in Ottoman Egypt: The Rise of the Qazdaglis'', Jane Hathaway.
:*[http://books.google.com/books?id=jLltMvZVBxsC&amp;pg=PA287&amp;dq=Georgian+mamluk&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=dgY9Ucf5OMqI2gXynIGACg&amp;ved=0CD0Q6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q=Georgian%20mamluk&amp;f=false], ''The Knights of Islam: The Wars of the Mamluks'', James Waterson.
:*[http://books.google.com/books?id=t6v2HHoWgbsC&amp;pg=PA51&amp;dq=Georgian+mamluk&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=wAY9UfmpJefm2AXty4G4Aw&amp;ved=0CEgQ6AEwBA#v=onepage&amp;q=Georgian%20mamluk&amp;f=false], ''Merchants, Mamluks, and Murder'',  Thabit Abdullah.
:*[http://books.google.com/books?id=hxaKj3AjyfwC&amp;pg=PA57&amp;dq=Georgian+mamluk&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=EQc9UfeVGua42QXsz4G4BA&amp;ved=0CE4Q6AEwBQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Georgian%20mamluk&amp;f=false], ''The Gulf States: A Modern History'', David Commins.
:*[http://books.google.com/books?id=c00jmTrjzAoC&amp;pg=PA675&amp;dq=Georgian+mamluk&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=TQc9UbykFeX02QWes4GgCg&amp;ved=0CFMQ6AEwBg#v=onepage&amp;q=Georgian%20mamluk&amp;f=false], ''An Economic and Social History of the Ottoman Empire:1600 - 1914'', Halil İnalcık, Suraiya Faroqhi, Donald Quataert. --[[User:Kansas Bear|Kansas Bear]] ([[User talk:Kansas Bear|talk]]) 22:22, 10 March 2013 (UTC)

Show a ref for georgian Mamluk Sultan. there were dozen of nations in Mamluks but Sultans were Turks and Circassians.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Oeneki|Oeneki]] ([[User talk:Oeneki|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Oeneki|contribs]]) 11:51, 11 March 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:No. I have presented sources and it is quite clear you have not read any of them. 
:The [[Wikipedia:Reliable Source|sources]], I have presented, show that Georgians were one of the ethnicities making up the Mamluk Sultanate of Egypt. You have shown &lt;u&gt;nothing&lt;/u&gt; that states Georgians were not mamluks in the Sultanate of Egypt. Therefore, I will be adding Georgian to the article along with the [[Wikipedia:Reliable Sources|reliable sources]] listed above. Continued removal of referenced information, can result in being blocked. --[[User:Kansas Bear|Kansas Bear]] ([[User talk:Kansas Bear|talk]]) 17:14, 11 March 2013 (UTC)

Name a georgian Mamluk sultan then, and we can all accept that.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Oeneki|Oeneki]] ([[User talk:Oeneki|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Oeneki|contribs]]) 20:08, 11 March 2013 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:Prove you have read the references listed above. --[[User:Kansas Bear|Kansas Bear]] ([[User talk:Kansas Bear|talk]]) 00:27, 15 March 2013 (UTC)

== Art and Architecture Missing Graphic ==
As of today, the Art and Architecture section contains this text:

&quot;This leaf contains portions of Surat (Chapter) Al’Ala(The most high) and was for use in a local mosque in Cairo. The leaf dates back to 1300 AD during the mamluk sultanate and its age clearly shows based on the tears that appear at the top of the leaf. Surat Al'Ala discusses the wonders that Allah has created and the rewards for those who believe the message of Islam, as well as the punishment for those who reject Islam. It is likely that the illuminator of the leaf was Abu Bakr aka Sandal, who was centered in the artistic hub of Islam at the time; Cairo, Egypt. The Qur'an verses are written in black ink and in the Naskh writing style, which was the easiest for the common man to read, opposed to other scripts that required individuals to be familiar with calligraphic styles.&quot;

It's obviously talking about a specific photo or graphic, but there is nothing accompanying the text. Either the editor who inserted it should remove it, or they should supply the graphic. I would do it myself, but I don't know enough about the topic.[[User:Darkstar8799|Darkstar8799]] ([[User talk:Darkstar8799|talk]]) 18:30, 26 April 2013 (UTC)

== is there any sources for Circassian language? ==
Hey, I removed Circassian language from spoken language. because there isn't any sources + I've read many poems of Circassian Mamluk Sultans, they wrote their poems in Turkish (not Kypchak but Turkish) also, their language more understandable than Ottoman poems to modern Turkish people. (They used a language which very close to modern Turkish) I couldn't find their poems on internet. if I find, I'll add some ref.
:Yes, [[Ibn Taghribirdi]] in his ''Nujum al-zahira fi muluk Misr wa'l-Qahira.'' mentions them as speaking Circassian. [[User:Irānshahr|Irānshahr]] ([[User talk:Irānshahr|talk]]) 20:56, 7 July 2013 (UTC)
ok then, could you send a link to his book?
:[http://www.al-eman.com/الكتب/النجوم%20الزاهرة%20في%20ملوك%20مصر%20والقاهرة%20**/النجوم%20الزاهرة/i51&amp;d1165&amp;p1 Nujum al-zahira fi muluk Misr wa'l-Qahira, xi, 224]. The current citation is another reference. [[User:Irānshahr|Irānshahr]] ([[User talk:Irānshahr|talk]]) 20:08, 9 July 2013 (UTC)
:Sorry, I can't read Arabic. :( anyway, I won't change it anymore. btw, adding Oghuz to list is good move. because in late era (mostly in Circassian era) they spoke Oghuz Turkish. I still couldn't find poems of Circassian Sultans. but, if I find I'll add some of them.

== Removal of &quot;ed-Devletü't-Türkiyye&quot; from the Infobox,  ==


Sorry I was just patrolling and looking into some Wikipedia articles, but this is outrageous, because Circassians are not a huge group to speak for themselves in Wikipedia, but you guys do realize that there were Circassian Sultans and during those periods it was known as '''dawlat al-jarākisa''' also the word Dawla doesn't mean Dynasty it means &quot;period of rule&quot;. I propose to get rid of that, because it is clear that we are using modern historical name which is Mamluk Sultanate, although that is wrong, but it is what we use. Another reason to drop it in case you think of adding '''dawlat al-jarākisa''' and making a full measure rather than half-measure is there are other names, I just chose one of those, for example '''al-dawla al-turkiyya al-jarkasiyya''' this for Circassians who speak Turkish.

I forgot to say that Jarakisa comes from Shirkas meaning '''Circas'''sian. [[User:Alexis Ivanov|Alexis Ivanov]] ([[User talk:Alexis Ivanov|talk]]) 07:31, 14 June 2015 (UTC)

== Mamluk vs ''mamluk'' ==

Just a note: I think its best to avert confusion by using the proper word &quot;Mamluk&quot; when describing anything related to the Mamluk state as in &quot;the Mamluk sultan&quot;, &quot;the Mamluks invaded ...&quot;, &quot;the Mamluks concluded agreements with ...&quot;, &quot;Mamluk architecture&quot;, while reserving the lowercased and italicized word ''mamluk'' to refer to the actual slave soldiers as in &quot;an emir was assigned his own group of ''mamluks''&quot;, &quot;the ''mamluks'' of the Bahri regiment&quot; or &quot;as a result of a ''mamluk'' revolt&quot;, etc. --[[User:Al Ameer son|Al Ameer]] ([[User talk:Al Ameer son|talk]]) 01:50, 9 January 2016 (UTC)

== Enough of Linda Northup ==

She is furthering misconceptions of the Mamluk Society. I would take with a grain of salt. [[User:Alexis Ivanov|Alexis Ivanov]] ([[User talk:Alexis Ivanov|talk]]) 05:43, 21 February 2016 (UTC)

== Dablink and redirects ==

I removed the dablink on the grounds that the title &quot;Mamluk Sultanate (Cairo)&quot; is not ambiguous, that is, it makes clear that the article is about
# a sultanate, not mamluks in general
# the sultanate based in Cairo, not any other, in particular not the one in Delhi
This removal was reverted (&quot;ambiguous enough for dab&quot;). I've looked at the redirects here and found a couple were actually ambiguous ([[Mameluke Sultanate]] and [[Mamluk State]]), so I've changed them to point at the dab page [[Mamluk dynasty]]. The only potentially ambiguous redirects left are
* [[Mamluk Empire]] and [[The Mamluk Empire]]: These should probably go to [[Mamluk dynasty]] as well, but it's arguable whether the Delhi Sultanate is likely to be described as an empire; if not, there should still be a dablink here using {{tl|redirect}}.
* [[Turkish State]] and [[Türkiye Devleti]]: I gather the latter means &quot;State of Turkey&quot;. My first assumption would be that these names (especially the first) should redirect to [[Turkey]], but they go here because it's apparently a historical name for the Cairo Sultanate, at least during the Turkish-dominated period. I suggest turning that redirect into a disambiguation page.
* [[State of Turkey]]: IMO this should definitely go to [[Turkey]], perhaps with a dablink there.
* [[Dawla al-Turkiyya]]: I gather this also means &quot;State of Turkey&quot;, in Arabic. This ''possibly'' should go to [[Turkey]], but I'm not sure whether an Arabic name for a secular Turkish state is appropriate.
IMO at least the dablink to [[Mamluk]] should be removed, since there's no way one could confuse this article about the Sultanate with the general topic of mamluks. The other one is debatable, but it possibly could be removed if the incoming redirects are sorted out. [[User:Hairy Dude|Hairy Dude]] ([[User talk:Hairy Dude|talk]]) 14:37, 21 April 2016 (UTC)
:One can not assume knowledge on the part of the reader.  Be grateful that you are both intelligent and knowledgeable on the subject.  The dab link was placed there precisely because someone got confused, and I concur that the average reader could reasonably get confused.  Experts on the topic won't, but they already know the difference. Wikipedia is for everyone, not just the intelligentsia. '''[[User:ScrapIronIV|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#306b1e&quot;&gt;Scr&lt;span style=&quot;background:#0404B4;border-radius:7px;color:#FFFFFF&quot;&gt;★&lt;/span&gt;pIron&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;sup&gt;[[User talk:ScrapIronIV|&lt;span style=&quot;color:#6E6E6E&quot;&gt;IV&lt;/span&gt;]]&lt;/sup&gt;''' 15:01, 21 April 2016 (UTC)

== Countries listed by alphabetical order ==

Is there a way I can organise the countries under the section &quot;Today part of&quot; in alphabetical order?? .  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Dont belittle245|Dont belittle245]] ([[User talk:Dont belittle245|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Dont belittle245|contribs]]) 00:08, 4 June 2016 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:{{done}} Fixed. --[[User:Iryna Harpy|Iryna Harpy]] ([[User talk:Iryna Harpy|talk]]) 01:58, 9 June 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>jonuc2hxo30c421beyn37cj9jeoeyj5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
