<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Syrian Armed Forces</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>2027067</id>
    <revision>
      <id>712649500</id>
      <parentid>702272876</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-03-30T10:02:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>80.91.194.173</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Syrian Armed Forces size during Civil War Contradictions. */ are idiots?~~~~</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17013">{{WikiProject Military history |class=C |Middle-Eastern-task-force=yes |National=yes}}
{{WikiProject Syria |class=C |importance=Top}}
{{Syrian Civil War sanctions}}

==Russia Presence==
It should be updated with russia new military and intellegence support for Syria and a New naval base there.   &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Mescovic|Mescovic]] ([[User talk:Mescovic|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Mescovic|contribs]]) 06:47, 17 December 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
==Defensive weapons==
I'm not sure what this sentence means: &quot;In addition, Syria is trying to develop defensive weapons to limit the Israeli abilities to attack it.&quot; It's not clear what a &quot;defensive weapon&quot; is. A source would be helpful. [[User:SlimVirgin|SlimVirgin]] &lt;sup&gt;&lt;font color=&quot;Purple&quot;&gt;[[User_talk:SlimVirgin|(talk)]]&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 22:39, Jun 11, 2005 (UTC)

Yep, I agree with SlimVirgin. Expression &quot;defensive weapon&quot; seems to be at least suspicious.
--[[User:83.240.4.195|83.240.4.195]] 12:13, 24 January 2006 (UTC) Jara

Syrian forces acquire nuclear missiles and a new fleet of 400 f-16s via pakistan.
War on syria would constitute self made genocide for the zionist israelis

&quot;Defensive Weapons&quot; as fast deploying minefields, buried T55 tanks as fire-posts, fortification, AA missile arrays and other such weapons intended to deter Israel form further aggression against Syria, as the Doctrine of the Syrian Arab Army suggests strongly that undertaking offensive action against Israel to return the Quneytra Province (Golan Heights to Israel) would not be effective, or even feasible use of it's army (And quite reasonable of them, taking the current technical gap between the aging equipment of the SyAA and the IDF). The source for this is, woefully, confidential.

Also of the Chemical Weapons, in 1973 stockpiles of Chem Shells for 100mm tank cannons and 130mm Artillery cannons was captured during the Yom Kipur War by Israel on the outskirts of Damascus, since then it's mostly assumed that they still have some of it. Well, it has legs as much as it had in the Iraq case, but we aren't talking about the sanest and most humane regimes on Earth. Better safe then sorry. 
----
==Merge of Syrian Air Force proposed==
Syrian Army has now been merged into this page as suggested 2005-12-15 and unopposed.&lt;br&gt;
It is now suggested that Syrian Air Force should likewise be merged.&lt;br&gt;
[[User:Boson|Boson]] 21:34, 24 August 2006 (UTC)

Done.[[User:Boson|Boson]] 17:43, 2 September 2006 (UTC)
----
Middle East

==Good Article==
This is a good article, well-written.

==Syria and Weapons of Mass Destruction==
Why doesn't this article mention Syria's development of chemical and biological weapons?  Who removed it?  I'm putting it back.

==No.==
Find a credible source that says Syria xzchemical and biological weapons and no one will have an issue with it.

==STOP==
Yeah um, wanna stop editing that 'militant and terrorists' part, it has already been discussed as a POV issue.
: Where?[[User:Ingsoc|Ingsoc]] 09:34, 10 May 2007 (UTC)
::It is POV to call them terrorist organizations, as that is simply an opinion. [[User:Asabbagh|Asabbagh]] 09:54, 10 May 2007 (UTC)
::: It is not POV when official governments and the UN have labelled them as such.--[[User:Degen Earthfast|Degen Earthfast]] ([[User talk:Degen Earthfast|talk]]) 12:46, 8 May 2011 (UTC)

==POV Issue==
Would someone like to correct this howler: &quot;Syria is buying additional weapons to either counter Israel's abilities to attack it or more likely as preparation to take back the Golan Heights at some point in the future.&quot; First, there is absolutely no need to interject uninformed predictions about Syrian foreign policy in an article about Syria's military. Second, what evidence there is points the other way -- to Syria's build-up as a defensive, deterring force. This is just anti-Arab POV without a shred of justification for it.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/24.20.140.12|24.20.140.12]] ([[User talk:24.20.140.12|talk]]) 01:47, 4 April 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Chiefs of Staff ==

Can someone please add a list of the Chiefs of Staff of the Syrian armed forces? I cannot find such a list anywhere else on the internet. Thanks, [[User:Ynhockey|Ynhockey]] &lt;sup&gt;([[User talk:Ynhockey|Talk]])&lt;/sup&gt; 00:44, 29 August 2008 (UTC)

==Image copyright problem with Image:Syriaaflogo.gif==
The image [[:Image:Syriaaflogo.gif]] is used in this article under a claim of [[WP:NFC|fair use]], but it does not have an adequate explanation for why it meets the [[WP:NFCC|requirements for such images]] when used here.  In particular, for each page the image is used on, it must have an [[Wikipedia:Non-free use rationale guideline|explanation]] linking to that page which explains why it needs to be used on that page.  Please check

:* That there is a [[Wikipedia:Non-free use rationale guideline|non-free use rationale]] on the image's description page for the use in this article.
:* That this article is linked to from the image description page.
&lt;!-- Additional 10c list header goes here --&gt;

This is an automated notice by [[User:FairuseBot|FairuseBot]]. For assistance on the image use policy, see [[Wikipedia:Media copyright questions]]. --03:09, 1 November 2008 (UTC)

== Active units ==

I miss some information on the amount of active soldiers. [[Special:Contributions/83.108.193.157|83.108.193.157]] ([[User talk:83.108.193.157|talk]]) 12:45, 24 August 2009 (UTC)
:Never mind, I inserted the numbers. [[Special:Contributions/83.108.193.157|83.108.193.157]] ([[User talk:83.108.193.157|talk]]) 08:39, 25 August 2009 (UTC)

== Women in the Syrian military! ==

I've read somewhere that; and seen videos of women serving in the Syrian military at the time of Hafez el Assad! I saw some syrian military women on parade eating snakes and such, was that a product of the socialist nationalist ideals of Hafez's time?? is it over?

I mean for an Arab country it is somewhat of a rare find and worth mentioning to dispel our image of women oppressors![[User:Zakster22`|Zakster22`]] ([[User talk:Zakster22`|talk]])  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|undated]] comment added 16:09, 18 November 2010 (UTC).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!--Template:Undated--&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:To force women to eate snakes is oppression. --[[Special:Contributions/46.115.23.77|46.115.23.77]] ([[User talk:46.115.23.77|talk]]) 13:40, 29 August 2011 (UTC)

==Update==

This page needs updating.--[[User:Degen Earthfast|Degen Earthfast]] ([[User talk:Degen Earthfast|talk]]) 12:46, 8 May 2011 (UTC)
==File:Syrian Army in Daraa 9 April 2011.jpg Nominated for Deletion==
{|
|-
| [[File:Image-x-generic.svg|100px]] 
| An image used in this article, [[commons:File:Syrian Army in Daraa 9 April 2011.jpg|File:Syrian Army in Daraa 9 April 2011.jpg]], has been nominated for deletion at [[Wikimedia Commons]] in the following category: ''Deletion requests December 2011'' 
;What should I do?
''Don't panic''; a discussion will now take place over on Commons about whether to remove the file. This gives you an opportunity to contest the deletion, although please review Commons guidelines before doing so.
* If the image is [[WP:NFCC|non-free]] then you may need to upload it to Wikipedia (Commons does not allow fair use)
* If the image isn't freely licensed and there is no [[WP:FUR|fair use rationale]] then it cannot be uploaded or used.

''This notification is provided by a Bot'' --[[User:CommonsNotificationBot|CommonsNotificationBot]] ([[User talk:CommonsNotificationBot|talk]]) 08:21, 10 December 2011 (UTC)
|}

== POV pushing in lead ==

The Reuters article says:
&quot;&quot;The commission has concluded, based on its findings, that members of the Syrian army and security forces have committed crimes again humanity in their repression of a largely civilian population in the context of a peaceful protest movement,&quot; Paulo Pinheiro, chairman of the three-member panel, told a news conference.&quot;

This article is about Syrian Army. There are number of armies in the world, where members have committed crimes, such as US army or Russian army. This does not mean that we should put such members deeds into the lead of articles about aforementioned armies. What would US army article lead look if we put all the human rights abuses in different wars into the beginning of articles? There are relevant articles about human rights in different countries. --[[User:Magabund|Magabund]] ([[User talk:Magabund|talk]]) 06:54, 29 May 2012 (UTC)
:I was the 'anon' that readded this statement to the lead, based on previous editors. Please see [[Talk:Syrian Army]], where the issue was initially raised (it also occurs there). Cheers [[User:Buckshot06|Buckshot06]] [[User_talk:Buckshot06|(talk)]] 07:35, 29 May 2012 (UTC)

== History - Insurgency ==

This section is so badly written:

&quot;Since the uprising began, the Armed Forces are sent to crash the protestors. As the uprising progressed growing number of soldiers began to defect from the Syrian Armed Forces and formed the rebels army called Free Syrian Army.[9] On March 2012 the Syrian government issued new travel restrictions for military-aged males. Under the new restrictions, reported by local Syrian news outlets, all males between 18 and 42 were banned from traveling outside the country.[10]

In late June, in an interview given by the rebels chief to Ashark Al-Awsat, Riad al-Asaad said that in recent time about 20-30 Syrian officers defect to Turkey each day.[11]&quot;

Can someone fix the English and link it to other articles that concern the Syrian insurrection?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;— Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/82.12.161.116|82.12.161.116]] ([[User talk:82.12.161.116|talk]]) 14:45, 1 July 2012 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Leadership section corrected to show Sunni majority in rank and file military ==

74% of the Syrian population are Sunni. Military service is mandatory for all males over the age of 18. Mathematics indicates that the military must be majority Sunni, but the article stated that they are majority Alawite. The cited references, 17 and 18, do not support this conclusion. In fact, State.gov said the opposite: &quot;Military leadership is heavily dominated by Alawi officers, but the vast majority of troops in uniform are Sunni.&quot;

One sentence was changed to indicate the Sunni majority in the military.

[[User:Becalmed|Becalmed]] ([[User talk:Becalmed|talk]]) 03:29, 26 July 2012 (UTC)

== Confusing Edits ==

Why is [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Syrian_Armed_Forces&amp;diff=554690308&amp;oldid=554689266 this] edit being reverted?[[User:Gobbleygook|Gobbleygook]] ([[User talk:Gobbleygook|talk]]) 06:19, 12 May 2013 (UTC)
:Because you are duplicating sections, links, and already existing content. Please work with the article sections already in place. Of course, this would involve actually ''reading'' the article and not copying and pasting content from another article here in a haphazard fashion.  This would involve doing actual research and writing actual content.  Please don't continue to copy and paste what you find from other articles over here. [[User:Viriditas|Viriditas]] ([[User talk:Viriditas|talk]]) 13:20, 13 May 2013 (UTC)
::If you read the title of the section, you'd know why it's being put there. [[User:Gobbleygook|Gobbleygook]] ([[User talk:Gobbleygook|talk]]) 13:49, 13 May 2013 (UTC)
:::You are duplicating sections that already exists and you are copying material from other articles ''that you did not write'' for no reason.  If you want to work on a section, then you need to work on the current section already in the article.  Is this making sense? We now have two sections about the civil war.  Further, you dishonestly claimed in your edit summary that there was an &quot;unexplained removal of sourced material&quot; when quite clearly, the explanation had been sitting here all along. [[User:Viriditas|Viriditas]] ([[User talk:Viriditas|talk]]) 13:52, 13 May 2013 (UTC)
::::Viriditas, there is no rule banning material from being copied from one article to another in Wikipedia. If the material helpfully explains and elaborates on the subject of the article, and is attributed through the proper talkpage attribution templates, there's no problem - instead it should be encouraged. [[User:Buckshot06|Buckshot06]] [[User_talk:Buckshot06|(talk)]] 00:25, 14 May 2013 (UTC)

== National Defense Force to Armed forces branches ==

According to reports [[http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/world/syria/ndf.htm |1]], [[http://www.reuters.com/article/2013/04/21/us-syria-crisis-paramilitary-insight-idUSBRE93K02R20130421 |2]], the NDF has been established and branded ''as a volunteer reserve army'' to augment the regular army (similar to the [[National Guard of the United States |US national Guard]]), while under army control. I propose adding it to the Armed Forces branches. Anyone share my views? [[User:Lugnuthemvar|Lugnuthemvar]] ([[User talk:Lugnuthemvar|talk]]) 01:13, 17 February 2014 (UTC)
:It has been reported [http://english.al-akhbar.com/node/15616] by several media that the NDF is a militia wich is not part of the Army, having a different chain of command ('''so its not under army control'''). The comparison with the US National Guard is your POV, not backed by any source. So please, stop insisting in something wich is not true.--[[User:HCPUNXKID|&lt;font color=&quot;Purple&quot;&gt;HC&lt;/font&gt;]][[User_talk:HCPUNXKID|&lt;font color=&quot;Gold&quot;&gt;PUNX&lt;/font&gt;]]&lt;font color=&quot;Purple&quot;&gt;KID&lt;/font&gt; 16:42, 24 February 2014 (UTC)

== Syrian Armed Forces size during Civil War Contradictions. ==

Try to explain how 220,000(Army) plus 100,000(Air force) results on 295,000. The wikipedian behind this edits thinks readers are idiots? This is an insult, please a little of math woudnt be bad, if thats a propaganda lie (100 % posible) do a better job next time.[[Special:Contributions/200.48.214.19|200.48.214.19]] ([[User talk:200.48.214.19|talk]]) 17:57, 31 October 2014 (UTC)
lol it&quot;s US freedom/real/good we trast  &lt;small class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/195.218.183.192|195.218.183.192]] ([[User talk:195.218.183.192|talk]]) 15:17, 29 January 2016 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned IP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
§ =)[[Special:Contributions/80.91.194.173|80.91.194.173]] ([[User talk:80.91.194.173|talk]]) 10:02, 30 March 2016 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:2|one external link|2 external links}} on [[Syrian Armed Forces]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=678127779 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20111120171332/http://news.sky.com/skynews/Home/World-News/Sky-News-Analysis-Tim-Marshall-Looks-At-Why-The-Bashir-Al-Assad-Regime-Has-Not-Collapsed/Article/201105115987446?lpos=World_News_First_Home_Page_Feature_Teaser_Region_0&amp;lid=ARTICLE_15987446_Sky_News_Analysis%3A_Tim_Marshall_Looks_At_Why_The_Bashir_Al_Assad_Regime_Has_Not_Collapsed_ to http://news.sky.com/skynews/Home/World-News/Sky-News-Analysis-Tim-Marshall-Looks-At-Why-The-Bashir-Al-Assad-Regime-Has-Not-Collapsed/Article/201105115987446?lpos=World_News_First_Home_Page_Feature_Teaser_Region_0&amp;lid=ARTICLE_15987446_Sky_News_Analysis%3A_Tim_Marshall_Looks_At_Why_The_Bashir_Al_Assad_Regime_Has_Not_Collapsed_
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20141009195423/http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/Page/document/v4/sub/MarketingPage?user_URL=http://www.theglobeandmail.com%2Fservlet%2FArticleNews%2FTPStory%2FLAC%2F20040928%2FCOSYRIA28%2FTPComment%2FTopStories&amp;ord=2674524&amp;brand=theglobeandmail&amp;redirect_reason=2&amp;denial_reasons=none&amp;force_login=false to http://www.theglobeandmail.com/servlet/Page/document/v4/sub/MarketingPage?user_URL=http://www.theglobeandmail.com%2Fservlet%2FArticleNews%2FTPStory%2FLAC%2F20040928%2FCOSYRIA28%2FTPComment%2FTopStories&amp;ord=2674524&amp;brand=theglobeandmail&amp;redirect_reason=2&amp;denial_reasons=none&amp;force_login=false

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers. —[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 15:05, 27 August 2015 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>ng0w9tn358l46ivlzvjt52kzfc0cydv</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
