<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Henry Percy (Hotspur)</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>429146</id>
    <revision>
      <id>640649408</id>
      <parentid>638912022</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-01-02T13:07:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Deb</username>
        <id>1219</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Did Prince Henry kill Hotspur? */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10347">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Biography|living=no
|class=Start
|peerage-work-group=yes
|military-work-group=yes
|listas=Percy, Henry
}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=Start
|Medieval-task-force=yes
|British-task-force=yes
|Biography=yes
}}
{{WikiProject England|class=start}}
}}

==Untitled==
We need a new place for Hotspur, but I'm not sure where it should be. [[User:John Kenney|john]] 04:41, 13 Jan 2004 (UTC)

The link is wrong for Elizabeth Mortimer.  ~~Aelfwyn

Do you think there should be some reference to Henry Percy relating to his link to Tottenham Hotspur football club. the club is said to be named after him ~~joe  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Joe a lewis|Joe a lewis]] ([[User talk:Joe a lewis|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Joe a lewis|contribs]]) 12:53, 28 May 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

Aelf old stick, I do believe that Hotspur was indeed married to Elizabeth de Mortimer.[[Special:Contributions/216.78.56.213|216.78.56.213]] ([[User talk:216.78.56.213|talk]]) 08:52, 12 January 2009 (UTC) WSP

== Name ==

This article name is erroneous, It should either be at [[Henry Percy (1366-1403)]] as per WP non inclusion of Knighthood honorifics, or at [[Harry Hotspur]]. He was never referred to as Henry Hotspur Percy, or even Henry Hotspur. He was however referred to as Sir Henry Percy, Harry Hostspur, or just plain Hostspur. Such was the problem encountered with the great grandfather of Hotspur's Scots foe, [[Archibald Douglas, 4th Earl of Douglas]]. Sir William Douglas (d.c 1298), known as ''Le Hardi'' or the Hardy, was never known as &quot;William Douglas the Hardy&quot; or &quot;William the Hardy Douglas&quot;, as per a prior incarnation of that article, and is now at [[William the Hardy, Lord of Douglas]]. These assignation of random Wiki titles is insidious, as it allows any random editor to change nomenclature that has been around for centuries. [[User:Brendandh|Brendandh]] ([[User talk:Brendandh|talk]]) 14:37, 31 August 2011 (UTC)

== Matilda Percy? ==

You will find the correct names of Henry and Elizabeth's children here: [http://books.google.com/books?id=p_yzpuWi4sgC&amp;pg=PA577&amp;dq=Elizabeth+Mortimer+Henry+Hotspur&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=BLGGTqTxIcfs0gGtmojiDw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CC0Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=Elizabeth%20Mortimer%20Henry%20Hotspur&amp;f=false ''Plantagenet Ancestry''] -- [[User:Lady Meg|Lady Meg]] ([[User talk:Lady Meg|talk]]) 06:28, 1 October 2011 (UTC)

== Requested move ==
&lt;div class=&quot;boilerplate&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #efe; margin: 2em 0 0 0; padding: 0 10px 0 10px; border: 1px dotted #aaa;&quot;&gt;&lt;!-- Template:polltop --&gt;
:''The following discussion is an archived discussion of the proposal. &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/span&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on the talk page. No further edits should be made to this section. ''

'''Page moved''' to [[Henry Percy (Hotspur)]].  Consensus was to move, but the target was left open.  The name chosen was one of those with support.  Stronger support appeared to be for titles that were dab pages.  A move there was not going to happen without establishing a primary topic and a multipage move listing to include the dab page.  So having said that, feel free to renominate this if it really is in fact the primary topic for one of the other proposed names as part of a multipage move.  A discussion here first to see which other name would be the best choice to nominate would seem to be the best direction forward so as not to muddy the new discussion about what the best alternative is. [[User:Vegaswikian|Vegaswikian]] ([[User talk:Vegaswikian|talk]]) 20:40, 16 October 2011 (UTC)

[[Henry Hotspur Percy]] → {{no redirect|1=Harry Hotspur}} – &lt;small&gt;'''Relisted'''. [[User:Vegaswikian|Vegaswikian]] ([[User talk:Vegaswikian|talk]]) 02:00, 9 October 2011 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt; Henry Hotspur Percy is neologistic rubbish. Sir Henry Percy or Harry Hotspur. They are the only names for him in contemporary record or in Shakespeare [[User:Brendandh|Brendandh]] ([[User talk:Brendandh|talk]]) 00:19, 2 October 2011 (UTC)
*'''Prefer''' [[Henry Percy, &quot;Hotspur&quot;]].  Sir Henry Percy was a historical person, most famous from Shakespeare's portayal of him.  An alternative might by [[Henry Percy, nicknamed Hotspur]].  The present form is certainly not appropriate.  However, Hotspur was a nickname not a surname.  The present version is a credible search term and should be retained as a redirect.  [[User:Peterkingiron|Peterkingiron]] ([[User talk:Peterkingiron|talk]]) 21:42, 2 October 2011 (UTC)
**Prob is there are more than a few Henry Percys, insofar as there are more than a few Archibald or James Douglases. As per &quot;Robert the Bruce&quot; or &quot;William the Lion&quot; I suggest moving this article to a name by which the man was known, rather than just his Christian common name...[[User:Brendandh|Brendandh]] ([[User talk:Brendandh|talk]]) 00:05, 3 October 2011 (UTC)
*Several possibilities: 
**[[Henry Percy]], since he's the only one on which we have an article and who ''doesn't'' have a peerage or courtesy title.
**[[Henry Percy (Hotspur)]] as the obvious disambiguator.
**[[Hotspur]] as the obvious unique name. [[User:Pmanderson|Septentrionalis]] &lt;small&gt;[[User talk:Pmanderson|PMAnderson]]&lt;/small&gt; 21:02, 3 October 2011 (UTC)

Would maybe concur with that first one, with the Earls &amp; Dukes on a top of the page dab. [[User:Brendandh|Brendandh]] ([[User talk:Brendandh|talk]]) 21:43, 3 October 2011 (UTC)

*I agree that a move should be made. [[Henry Percy]] and [[Harry Hotspur]] are both acceptable to me, even [[Hotspur]], which ought to redirect, and [[Henry Hotspur]] are okay. Any of the other suggestions above would be an improvement, but not my choice. [[User:Srnec|Srnec]] ([[User talk:Srnec|talk]]) 00:21, 4 October 2011 (UTC)
 
*I suggest '''Sir Henry Percy''', which is what ''[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/451189/Sir-Henry-Percy Britannica]'' calls him. &quot;Sir&quot; makes it clear that we are not referring to one of the various earls named &quot;Henry Percy&quot;. I am OK with '''Henry Percy''' as well. [[User:Kauffner|Kauffner]] ([[User talk:Kauffner|talk]]) 10:42, 15 October 2011 (UTC)
:''The above discussion is preserved as an archive of the proposal.  &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;'''Please do not modify it.'''&lt;/span&gt; Subsequent comments should be made in a new section on this talk page. No further edits should be made to this section.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;!-- Template:pollbottom --&gt;

== Wrong picture ==

This picture is clearly not Harry Hotspur. He lived in the 14th Century and the clothes are totally wrong for the period. I've no idea who that is in the picture on the page.

[[User:Kotch5|Kotch5]] ([[User talk:Kotch5|talk]]) 23:36, 11 February 2012 (UTC)

:This is a 19th century artist's impression, which somewhat polishes the details of the armour, but is there evidence it is not ''intended'' to portray Hotspur?[[User:Cloptonson|Cloptonson]] ([[User talk:Cloptonson|talk]]) 12:34, 20 December 2014 (UTC)

::The picture appears to have been removed since I posted but I declare I did not remove it.[[User:Cloptonson|Cloptonson]] ([[User talk:Cloptonson|talk]]) 12:55, 20 December 2014 (UTC)

== Consolidation of cite references ==

Thanks to Trappist the Monk for consolidating the citation references. I didn't know how to do that. [[User:NinaGreen|NinaGreen]] ([[User talk:NinaGreen|talk]]) 16:51, 30 September 2012 (UTC)

== Ancestry Inconsistency ==

In looking at the Ancestry tree here, it shows 15 as Isolt Mortimer, 30 as Edmund Mortimer, 1st Lord of Mortimer, and 31 as Margaret Fiennes.  However, in looking around the rest of Wikipedia, I find [[Margaret Mortimer, Baroness Mortimer]] nee Fiennes is apparently married to [[Edmund Mortimer, 2nd Baron Mortimer]], and that his father was 1st Baron Mortimer.  However, neither of their pages show a daughter named Isolt, nor a daughter who married an Audley.  Those pages appear to have good sources for their data, while there is no source listed on this tree.  Does anyone have a source which could help clarify here?  [[User:1bandsaw|1bandsaw]] ([[User talk:1bandsaw|talk]]) 22:00, 1 March 2014 (UTC)

==Did Prince Henry kill Hotspur?==

I have not found any attempt in articles about Hotspur, the Battle of Shrewsbury and Henry V, as the Prince of Wales became, to distinctly point out whether or not Prince Henry actually killed Hotspur.  Shakespeare, and those who have followed his ''Henry IV Part I'' narrative - such as Orson Welles in his movie ''Chimes at Midnight'' (1966) - dramatically portray the prince killing Hotspur in single combat.  Could someone clarify?  In the article by Simon Walker on Percy/Hotspur in the ODNB (2003), the latter's death is summed up: ''...Hotspur himself, driving towards the royal standard, was struck down and killed'' but is silent on the actual killer.[[User:Cloptonson|Cloptonson]] ([[User talk:Cloptonson|talk]]) 12:49, 20 December 2014 (UTC)
:Always good to look at surrounding articles in a case like this. Allmand, in the article on Henry V, says Henry &quot;''was probably not personally responsible for Hotspur's death (as Shakespeare was to have it), but that event led quickly to the collapse of the rebel army''&quot; (C. T. Allmand, ‘Henry V (1386–1422)’, Oxford Dictionary of National Biography, Oxford University Press, 2004; online edn, Sept 2010 [http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/12952, accessed 16 Mar 2014]), and Jacob that Hotspur was &quot;''surrounded and killed''&quot; (Jacob, E.F., ''The Fifteenth Century'', Oxford (repr.) 1993, p.52)
::Thank you. I have just read John Barratt's book on the Battle of Shrewsbury (published 2010) in the ''Campaign Chronicles'' series, which mentions chronicler Thomas Wolsingham stated Hotspur ''was unexpectedly cut down, by whose hand is not known''.  Prince Henry being on the victor side, there was opportunity for the claim to be made by him or on his behalf in his lifetime.[[User:Cloptonson|Cloptonson]] ([[User talk:Cloptonson|talk]]) 14:38, 20 December 2014 (UTC)
:::Also, Henry was seriously wounded in the battle by an arrow which put him out of action.  This could be interpreted as meaning that he never got into close combat with anyone. [[User:Deb|Deb]] ([[User talk:Deb|talk]]) 13:06, 2 January 2015 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>kvhghs6942396c93mw2y266hvrhvoa3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
