<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Studebaker US6</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>12955210</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750733782</id>
      <parentid>750725780</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-21T14:48:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Sammy D III</username>
        <id>17643515</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Name 21 Nov 2016 */ new section</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8168">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Automobiles|class=start|importance=low}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=Start|importance=
|B1=n
|B2=n
|B3=y
|B4=y
|B5=n
|Weaponry=y
|Technology=y
|Land-vehicles=yes
|US=yes
|WWII=y
}}
{{WikiProject Brands|class=start|importance=}}
}}

== Sources? ==

It's unclear which sources have been used to create this article, which needs still some improvement. Can anyone please help clarify this? Thanks &amp; regards, [[User:DPdH|DPdH]] ([[User talk:DPdH|talk]]) 14:21, 20 February 2014 (UTC)

== Was the ZiS 151 a US6? ==

It is sometimes said in the US that the Soviets built the Studebaker US6 as the ZiS/ZiL 151, a direct copy, without having a license.

The US6 was not all Studebaker parts. The cab, which the Soviets copied very closely, is the one we see (the first ZIS trucks had wood cabs). A ladder frame with 3 beam axles on leaf springs is pretty basic.

The US6 had a Hercules engine of 320 c.i.d., the ZiS’s 6.55 liter comes out at about 400 c.i.d., not very close. It also has metric dimensions. They were both valve in block, hardly very advanced. The Soviets also had Chevrolet/GMC overhead valve engines, a more advanced design, which they did not use.

Much of the US6 is vendor parts, Spicer, Bendix, Timken, etc., some also used by Chevrolet and GMC. I do not know how closely they were copied. The US6 had 20” wheels, probably with vacuum/hydraulic brakes (GMCs did), the ZiS had 18” with air brakes. Some ZiS dimensions are larger than the US6. 

I do not see that the ZiS 151 was a direct copy of the US6, so it would not have been a stolen Studebaker design built without a license. It appears to be a very close, but not exact, copy, possibly of US trucks in general.

(this is a cut and paste from [[Talk:Automotive industry in the Soviet Union]]) [[User:Sammy D III|Sammy D III]] ([[User talk:Sammy D III|talk]]) 19:49, 29 September 2014 (UTC)

== Different trucks ==

I have been playing with some similar trucks, the [[Chevrolet G506 trucks|Chevy G506]], [[GMC CCKW]] &amp; [[DUKW]], [[Studebaker US6|Stude US6]], [[ZiS-151|ZiS-151 (USSR)]], and [[Jiefang_CA-30|Jiefang CA-30 (China)]]. [[User:Sammy D III|Sammy D III]] ([[User talk:Sammy D III|talk]]) 04:48, 9 November 2014 (UTC)

== Inches to feet ==

I have been told that feet are easier than inches for many people. [[User:Sammy D III|Sammy D III]] ([[User talk:Sammy D III|talk]]) 19:07, 21 September 2015 (UTC)

== Facts from Russian Wikipedia ==

Studebaker US6 (ˈstʲyːdəbɛjkɐ, в СССР и затем в России устоялось произношение «Студебекер» или «Студебеккер», иногда просто «Студер») &lt;br&gt;
Translation: Studebaker US6 (ˈstʲyːdəbɛjkɐ, in USSR and later in Russia become settled the pronunciation &quot;Studebeker&quot; or &quot;Studebekker&quot;, sometimes simply &quot;Studer&quot;)
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;

&quot;Первые автомобили Studebaker прибыли в СССР осенью 1941 года. Технический комитет Главного автомобильного управления (ГАУ) Красной армии организовал испытание одиннадцати «Студебеккеров» (как их стали называть в СССР), длившееся с 18 июля 1942 года по 15 мая 1943 года, по результатам которых были выпущены брошюры по эксплуатации и наставление по увеличению грузоподъёмности. Согласно этим документам, несмотря на то, что официально «Студебеккер» имел грузоподъёмность в 2,5 тонн, была рекомендована грузоподъёмность 4 тонны[2]. В 1945 году норму загрузки снизили до 3,5 т, хотя по хорошим грунтовым дорогам автомобиль успешно мог перевозить грузы до 5 т. Автомобиль также имел высокое расположение частей, чувствительных к воздействию воды. Вследствие этого грузовик стал основным средством перевозки реактивных установок «Катюша» БМ-8-48, БМ-13Н, БМ-13НС и БМ-31-12 — самых мощных установок того времени. После окончания ВОВ часть машин была отправлена обратно в США в соответствии с договором о ленд-лизе. Оставшиеся машины эксплуатировались ещё какое-то время в Советской Армии, а также участвовали в восстановлении народного хозяйства СССР.

Недостатком автомобиля (по сравнению с техникой СССР того времени) являлся тот факт, что Студебеккер US6 требовал более качественные смазку и горючее. Из-за постоянной перегрузки ломались диски сцепления, чулки задних мостов. Но это не помешало использовать отдельные Студебеккеры US6 в СССР вплоть до середины шестидесятых годов и даже до конца 1980-х,[3] тем более, что остальные ленд-лизовские грузовики в подавляющем большинстве имели ещё большую степень сжатия и потребляли ещё более высокооктановый бензин.&quot;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;

Translation:
First automobiles Studebaker arrived in USSR in the autumn of 1941. The Technical Commitee of Main Agency for Automobiles (MAA) of the Red Armee did organize
a test of eleven &quot;Studebekkers&quot; (as they become/were called in the USSR), which took place from July 18th 1942 til Mai 15th 1943, on the results of which, a brochure for explatation and precept for enlargening the carrying/payload was released. According to these documents, although the official &quot;Studebekker&quot; had a payload of 2,5 tons, it was recommanded a payload of 4 tons[2]. In 1945, the norm of carrying was lowered down to 3.5 tons, although on well phreatic/grounded ways, this automobile could successfully carry loadings up to 5 tons. This automobile also had an upper emplacement/disposition /location of the parts, sensitive to the effects of water.
In consequence of it, this lorry/truck became the main mean of transportation [transport] for rocket-launcher &quot;Katusha&quot; BM-8-48, BM-13N, BM-13NS and BM-31-12 - the most powerful launcher of these time. After the end of the WW2, a part of the cars was send back to the USA according to the contract of Lend-Lease. 
The remained automobiles were exploited a while in the Soviet Army, and also took part in the restoring of the national economy of the USSR.

The disadvantages of this automobile (comparing to the technique of the USSR during this time) was those fact, that Studebekker US6 demanded more qualitative lubricant and fuel. Due to the permanent overloading, the coupling discs and the stocking of the back crossovers did crash. But it didn't hinder to use particular Studebekkers US6 in the USSR til the middle of the sixtees and even till the end of the 1980s,[3]  all the more, the rest of [the other] lend-lease trucks in the overwhelming majority had an even higher compression ratio and used an even more high-octane gas/benzin.
:This is good stuff. It should be used. There are also articles about [[ZiS-151]] and [[ZIL-157]]. [[User:Sammy D III|Sammy D III]] ([[User talk:Sammy D III|talk]]) 17:57, 22 February 2016 (UTC)

== Name 21 Nov 2016 ==

I am thinking of changing the name to &quot;Studebaker US6 {{frac|2|1|2}}-ton 6x6 truck. [[User:Sammy D III|Sammy D III]] ([[User talk:Sammy D III|talk]]) 14:48, 21 November 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>inlw350xelw1clk6d02kazsj5ioskdj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
