<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Joe DiMaggio</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>1917121</id>
    <revision>
      <id>707235310</id>
      <parentid>692848705</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-02-27T17:19:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cyberbot II</username>
        <id>16283967</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Notification of altered sources needing review #IABot</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="34273">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Biography|living=no|class=C|sports-work-group=yes|sports-priority=High|listas=Dimaggio, Joe}}
{{WikiProject Baseball|halloffame=yes|halloffame-importance=|class=C|importance=top|yankees=yes|yankees-importance=top}}
{{WikiProject Military history|class=start|Biography=yes|US=yes|WWII=yes}}
{{WikiProject New York|class=C|importance=Low}}
{{WikiProject Catholicism|class=C|importance=low}}
}}
{{OnThisDay|date1=2005-01-14|oldid1=16335103|date2=2006-01-14|oldid2=35082319}}

==Sicily==
You still got a problem with this statement: &quot;Ironically, Giuseppe and Rosalia weren't citizens of Italy because their native Isola delle Femmine (a small island 15 km from Palermo) was part of Sicily, and Sicily was not annexed by Italy until 1946.&quot;
As you can read in Wikipedia's own article on [[Sicily]], the island has been part of Italy since 1860 (when the Italian state was actually formed through the union of a plethora of smaller and larger states). Not only did it not become a part of Italy in 1946, but it is in 1946 that Sicily received some form of autonomy from the central government. Now I don't know if and why DiMaggio's parents weren't Italian citizens (most likely, because they had simply given it up or somehow lost it), but it isn't because Sicily wouldn't have been part of Italy.
[[User:Quatrocentu|Quatrocentu]] 00:22, 26 September 2005 (UTC)

==Boxing?==
In the &quot;Yankee Clipper&quot; section, it said Joe was involved in boxing. I've read a biography, and many books about DiMaggio, and have never heard of this. Can someone elaborate for me?  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/70.68.212.212|70.68.212.212]] ([[User talk:70.68.212.212|talk]]) 13:39, August 27, 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Former Catholic? ==
What is DiMaggio in this category? I don't see anything about it in the text. [[User:Bhumiya|Bhumiya]]/[[User talk:Bhumiya|Talk]] 02:30, 8 April 2006 (UTC)

Hi peeps

Joe DiMaggio was raised a Catholic in the staunch Italian American tradion of the early part of the twentieth century.The Catholic Church did not recognize divorce- people remained married in the eyes of God til the end of time. His excommunication resulted when he married for a second time ( that it was Marilyn Monroe was inconsequential) because in the eyes of the church and God he was guilty of bigamy. During Vatican 2, in the 1960's, the church relaxed somewhat, it's views on divorce and remarriage and welcomed back those, like Joe, who were previously excommunicated. This explains why his family was able to have his funeral within a Catholic church.

Actually...
According to the list of excommunicated Catholics on Wikipedia ([[excommunication]]), the order was reversed in 1962 and that is why he had a Catholic funeral.
[[User:SimonMcC|SimonMcC]] 05:22, 6 July 2006 (UTC)

==Only Pro Atheletes to Win Four Championships==

This statement....

DiMaggio, Duane Sutter, Ken Morrow, John Havlicek, Satch Sanders, KC Jones, Jerry Coleman, Hank Bauer and Gene Guarilia are the only athletes in pro sports history to win 4 championships in their first 4 seasons. 

...is completely wrong. Those members of the Cleveland Browns who began with the AAFC won FIVE championships in the their first five years -- four in the AAFC, and their first championship when they entered the NFL -- a feat that beats this. I've removed it. [[User:140.116.55.72|140.116.55.72]] 14:17, 23 October 2007 (UTC)Michael Turton

==DiMaggio in fiction/folklore==

In the next generation series of the [[Star Trek]] genre, DiMaggio comes up. In 1987 in &quot;[[The Big Goodbye (TNG episode)]]&quot;, Data tells Picard that DiMaggio's streak will last until 2012, when a shortstop for the London Kings will break the record. The shortstop is finally named in &quot;[[If Wishes Were Horses (DS9 episode)]]&quot;, as Buck Bokai, a player of [[Japan|Japanese]] heritage. The London Kings, probably one of the first overseas expansion teams of North American Major League Baseball, played at Battersea Stadium, according to the novel [[Federation]].

Is this information worthy of inclusion in the main article?
[[User:Gcapp1959|GBC]] 22:34, 20 May 2006 (UTC)

Nope. Star Trek trivia hardly merits inclusion. If you want to add something, go to Memory Alpha and update their Joe DiMaggio page.
Also, it's 2026, not 2012
[[Special:Contributions/128.187.0.164|128.187.0.164]] ([[User talk:128.187.0.164|talk]]) 01:18, 22 January 2008 (UTC)trekkie

== Personal Life ==

Says that Joe D. was rumored to be involved with Morgan Fairchild in the 50's/early 60's?  Is there another Morgan Fairchild I'm not aware of?  The M.F. of Old Navy fame (the one who this article links to) was born in 1950, you do the math. [[User:BrianO|BrianO]] 21:22, 21 November 2006 (UTC)

== Say It Ain't So Joe ==

Shouldn't the whole Say It Ain't So Joe be mentioned?

&quot;Say it ain't so Joe&quot; was attributed to Shoeless Joe Jackson, and his alleged throwing of the 1919 World Series.  Joe Dimaggio has nothing to do with that saying.

:Well, not exactly; it was attributed to a kid, who supposedly said it to Shoeless Joe as he left the ballpark shortly after the Black Sox allegations were announced -- as in, &quot;Please tell us it's not true.&quot;  Unfortunately there is no evidence that it ever actually happened; it's an urban legend.  But yes, it certainly has nothing to do with DiMaggio. [[User:DoctorJoeE|DoctorJoeE]] ([[User talk:DoctorJoeE|talk]]) 14:39, 19 August 2011 (UTC)

== Tom Waits &quot;A sight for eyes&quot; ==
In the chorus: &quot;That we toast to the old days and DiMaggio too&quot;. Maybe this should be added to the list of song references.


== Joe DiMaggio's Last Will and Testament ==

There has been some discussion as to whether we (the Living Trust Network) should be able to add a reference under an External Links or other section to Joe's Last Will and Testament, which would be accessible on our web site via a hyperlink.  See our talk page (livingtrust) and the administrator's section.  We believe that it would be valuable information that is in keeping with the information provided in this article.  The opinions expressed by others seem to suggest that we should make the request here so that independent administrators could make an informed decision as to whether the link should be allowed or not.  For your information, the link to our site is [[http://www.livingtrustnetwork.com/content/lwt/wills/dimaggiowill.php Last Will and Testament of Joe DiMaggio].

I suppose we would be willing to add the entire Last Will and Testament to this article, but it seems that a link is in keeping with the format of this - and other - articles.  For example, Wikipedia already allows a link to the Last Will and Testament of Doris Duke on CourtTV.com.

Thank you for considering our request.  [[User:Livingtrust|Livingtrust]] 00:33, 27 July 2006 (UTC)

*  P.S.  In searching for more information on last wills and testaments as public documents, I discovered that Wikipedia's article on Last Wills and Testaments contains a link to CourtTV.com's listing of famous wills on their website (External Links).  I'll keep digging to see if I can find a statute or caselaw that clarifies this issue, but it seems pretty clear from commentary that wills admitted to probate are in the public domain and, therefore, free of any copyright protection.  [[User:Livingtrust|Livingtrust]] 23:44, 27 July 2006 (UTC)

Last Will and Testament of Joe DiMaggio

We wish to advise everyone that we (the Living Trust Network) have a copy of Joe DiMaggio's Last Will and Testament posted on our website, which we believe is of interest to anyone seeking information about the life of Joe DiMaggio. We have also discussed our desire to post a link to Joe DiMaggio's Last Will and Testament with Wikipedia administrators [See [[User talk:Livingtrust]]], either under &quot;references&quot; or &quot;external links.&quot; [http://www.livingtrustnetwork.com/content/lwt/wills/dimaggiowill.php Last Will and Testament of Joe DiMaggio]. Wikipedia does not object to the link but has requested that we not put the link up ourselves since we are a commercial website. Instead, it has requested that we make it known that the Last Will and Testament is available, and anyone who wishes to add the link to the &quot;reference&quot; section or the &quot;external links&quot; section may do so. So, we solicite your help in adding the link set forth above. Thanks. [[User:Livingtrust|Livingtrust]] 01:54, 8 August 2006 (UTC)

==Vote on Adding Link==

Seems perfectly reasonable to me...does anyone object to my putting up the link?
[[User:Invisible Flying Mangoes|Invisible Flying Mangoes]] 14:52, 24 August 2006 (UTC)

: I won't take a position on the merits of the link, but I've removed it for now because it was added by an anonymous user apparently attempting to promote the site, rather than as a result of consensus. [[User:Wmahan|Wmahan]][[User talk:Wmahan|.]] 05:19, 11 September 2006 (UTC)[[User:72.128.22.174|72.128.22.174]] 19:46, 27 November 2006 (UTC)

== Some editing needed ==

Under the Yankee Clipper section, a line reads: &quot;He amassed 1800 home runs, averaged 2000 runs batted in (RBI) annually, compiled a .325 lifetime batting average while winning two American League batting titles, and struck out only 1 time.&quot;

The 1800 home runs and 2000 RBI per season are both incorrect information, if nothing else because the current career home run record stands at less than 800 and to average 2000 RBI in a season would be nearly impossible (requiring, in a 500 at-bat season, four RBI for every at-bat).

In the Personal Life section another set of lines reads: &quot;In January 1937, DiMaggio met acter Frank Sinatra on the set of Manhattan Merry Go-Round. They married at San Francisco's Catholic SS Peter and Paul on November 19, 1939 as 20,000 well-wishers jammed the streets.&quot;

More simply, actor is spelled incorectly, and more glaringly, Frank Sinatra and Joe DiMaggio were never married.  This is probably referring to his marriage to Marilyn Monroe. &lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[Special:Contributions/69.228.82.206|69.228.82.206]] ([[User talk:69.228.82.206|talk]]) 07:42, 9 December 2006 (UTC).&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- HagermanBot Auto-Unsigned --&gt;

I think it was meant in reference to his first wife, Dorothy Arnold.   &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/70.68.212.212|70.68.212.212]] ([[User talk:70.68.212.212|talk]]) 06:01, 2 March 2008 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

The music links say he's mentioned in &quot;No More Heroes&quot;, that's not correct.--[[User:Gavinturner|Gavinturner]] 17:10, 8 April 2007 (UTC)

== Rating ==

Just a note, for anyone who's curious. I'm rating this a start class article because it doesn't have a single reference, and WP assessment standards are clear about B-class articles needing at least one reference. In my opinion, an article this long should have a few to reach that level. In all other areas, this is a B-class article, and I think with some sourcing and weasel-word-removal, this could go up for good-article assessment. [[User:Djrobgordon|Djrobgordon]] 18:28, 2 February 2007 (UTC)

== Neutrality issue ==

There's a problem with this sentence: &quot;Oddly, both of the books contain inaccuracies, salacious gossip, unsubstantiated claims and rely on the same discredited sources. Both state Joe thought Marilyn was murdered due to her involvement with the Kennedy Family; Cramer even claims the coroner who performed her autopsy &quot;took a dive.&quot;&quot;

Oddly, the above paragraph doesn't give a citation from a published source that verifies that the books are indeed inaccurate, salaciously gossipy, and unsubstantiated. I think that's a problem with the whole article: there is editorialization throughout that certainly isn't neutral. Or am I just wrong and it's acceptable by Wikipedia standards? &lt;small&gt;—The preceding [[Wikipedia:Sign your posts on talk pages|unsigned]] comment was added by [[Special:Contributions/69.42.6.80|69.42.6.80]] ([[User talk:69.42.6.80|talk]]) 06:10, 13 April 2007 (UTC).&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- HagermanBot Auto-Unsigned --&gt;

==Question About Joe DiMaggio's Final Game==

The Infobox states that Joe DiMaggio's final game with the Yankees occurred on September 30, 1951. The Yankees won the 1951 pennant and the 1951 World Series, which was played in October, 1951. Joe DiMaggio's final game was game six of the 1951 World Series, which could not have occurred on September 30. We all know that the World Series is the October Classic. The information in the Infobox needs to be corrected.

[[User:Anthony22|Anthony22]] 01:50, 2 July 2007 (UTC)


I think it meant his final regular season game. No need for correction.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/70.68.212.212|70.68.212.212]] ([[User talk:70.68.212.212|talk]]) 04:46, 8 October 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Lists ==

Is it just me, or are we starting to get too many lists in the See also section? --[[User:After Midnight|After Midnight]] &lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:After Midnight|0001]]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 01:35, 14 July 2007 (UTC)
:Three more lists were just added.  I would appreciate some additional comments here before I start removing things. --[[User:After Midnight|After Midnight]] &lt;sup&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[User talk:After Midnight|0001]]&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 13:43, 15 July 2007 (UTC)

==Citations &amp; References==

See [[Wikipedia:Footnotes]] for an explanation of how to generate footnotes using the &lt;ref(erences/)&gt; tags [[User:Nhl4hamilton|Nhl4hamilton]] ([[User talk:Nhl4hamilton|talk]]) 10:56, 31 January 2008 (UTC)

== arrange &quot;yankee Clipper&quot; by  year ==

shouldn't we arrange his Yankee career by the year. That is what he is most famous for and and it seems pretty short. [[User:Ramgar11|Ramgar11]] ([[User talk:Ramgar11|talk]]) 18:47, 9 May 2008 (UTC)may, 9, 2008

== Yankee Clipper ==

What is the origin and meaning of the name &quot;Yankee Clipper&quot;? The section with that title doesn't elaborate. -[[User:Phoenixrod|Phoenixrod]] ([[User talk:Phoenixrod|talk]]) 17:17, 30 July 2008 (UTC)

== Pronunciation ==
The pronunciation of &quot;DiMaggio&quot; in Italian would be quite similar to the version you use in English, only the last &quot;i&quot; is not actually pronounced (it's a marker indicating that the &quot;g&quot; is a soft and not a hard one): it would then be &quot;di-MAH-joh&quot;, not (as currently written in the article) &quot;di-MA-zhee-oh&quot;. As a matter of fact, there is no way to write the ʒ phoneme in Italian orthography! There is a slight possibility that DiMaggio's parent's dialect used ʒ instead of dʒ, but that does not sound like Sicilian to me (though I'm a northerner, so corrections are welcome; as far as I know only the dialect of [[Valtellina]] uses ʒ instead of dʒ). In any case, we do have something as a &quot;standard Italian pronunciation&quot; in the Italian language, so that one should be used unless there are compelling reasons to do otherwise. [[Special:Contributions/78.53.204.100|78.53.204.100]] ([[User talk:78.53.204.100|talk]]) 21:06, 7 October 2008 (UTC)

::Ciao amico/a mio/a.  In Sicily, we do have Sicilian pronunciations of our surnames, yes it's true.  However, since Sicilian last names haven't existed for hundreds of years, and since this is an official biography, we should follow the standard Italian pronunciation (in English phonetics /dee-MAH-joe/).  You might find it interesting to know that prior to the 1700s, records indicate our surnames written in Old [[Sicilian language|Sicilian]] (just as the [[Sardinian language|Sardinians]] still do).  However, this was changed when Sicily became tied to the mainland which began to use [[Italian language|Italian]] after [[Latin language|Latin]].  Sadly, our surnames and names were Italianized in an erratic manner, without any sense.  This also happened to our town names which [[Mussolini]] changed during Fascism because he wanted Italy to be united, and didn't want Sicily to have Sicilian names, because Sicily had to be Italian in his crazy head.  An example: Zabut became Sambuca!  The translation of a name from Sicilian to Italian depended on the ears of the Italian notary who was listening to our Sicilian pronunciation and translating it.  For example, the name of Arabic origins '''Qasr-Yànnah''' became Italianized to '''Castrogiovanni''' even though when translated, they have NO similarities whatsoever!  This process of Italianization of Sicilian last names, and town names was a bizarre one on the part of Italian colonizers.  Now What I want to say about Joe DiMaggio is that Di Maggio also has foreign origins.  You may think this surname is related to the month of May (&quot;maggio&quot;) but as you may know in Sicilian we use &quot;maiu&quot; or &quot;maju&quot;.  Therefore, Italianization would have led to the surname &quot;Di Maio&quot;.  Since we have Di Maggio instead, I want to tell you something interesting.  In Sicily we have [[Arbereshe]] colonies since the 1400s in the towns of [[Contessa Entellina]], [[Piana degli Albanesi]], [[Mezzojuso]], [[Palazzo Adriano]], and [[Santa Cristina Gela]].  In Piana degli Albanesi, [[Arbereshe]] is an official language and taught in the schools as you can see here by their [http://www.pianalbanesi.it website].  What I want to say is the surname Di Maggio is actually of Arbereshe origins and used to be written '''Di Maxho'''.  There is even a famous cultured person from Piana degli Albanesi with that name [[http://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zef_Skiroi_Di_Maxho Zef Skiroi Di Maxho (Giuseppe Schirò Di Maggio)]].  Further, you can see how popular Di Maggio is in the province of Palermo and Western Sicily where the Arbereshe villages are by looking at [[http://gens.labo.net/it/cognomi/gif.html?cognome=DI_MAGGIO&amp;k=FF&amp;t=cognomi&amp;s=D the Gens website map]].  So I hope this helps you understand.  Di Maggio is the Italianization of the Siculo-Arbershe surname Di Maxho, very popular in that part of Sicily.  However, despite our vibrant past and rich linguistic history, the surnames have been Italianized now (unfortunately).  Therefore, the official pronunciation follows the standard Italian.  Tante belle cose, --[[User:Siciliano69|Siciliano69]] ([[User talk:Siciliano69|talk]]) 08:55, 15 October 2008 (UTC)

== Can I propose ==

 
* [http://thediaryjunction.blogspot.com/2009/03/dimaggios-diary-33-word.html DiMaggio’s diary - $33 a word - The Diary Junction Blog]
as a possible External Link for this WIkipedia entry?

--[[User:Pikle|Pikle]] ([[User talk:Pikle|talk]]) 10:24, 10 March 2009 (UTC)

== After baseball ==

So, um, what did he do between 1955 and 1999?  Besides hang around a bit with Marilyn Monroe?
[[Special:Contributions/75.22.205.212|75.22.205.212]] ([[User talk:75.22.205.212|talk]]) 01:52, 29 May 2009 (UTC)

== Violent relationship with MM? ==

In the Marilyn Monroe section it says: &quot;''Richard Ben Cramer asserts that it (their relationship) was also violent. One incident allegedly happened after the skirt-blowing scene in The Seven Year Itch was filmed on September 14, 1954 in front of New York's Trans-Lux Theater. Then-20th Century Fox's East Coast correspondent Bill Kobrin told the Palm Springs Desert Sun that it was Billy Wilder's idea to turn the shoot into a circus. The couple then had a &quot;yelling battle&quot; in the theater lobby''&quot;  Well, the problem is, yelling does not constitute an incident of violence. If Cramer did assert that the relationship was violent, a better example should be found. [[User:Dlabtot|Dlabtot]] ([[User talk:Dlabtot|talk]]) 00:44, 12 August 2009 (UTC)

== Bold, revert, discuss ==

I just invoked the [[WP:BRD|bold, revert, discuss]] cycle by trimming and tagging the article of statements and paragraphs that I felted smacked of [[WP:WEASEL]], [[WP:PEACOCK]], or that I felt needed to be cited. If you have a bone to pick with me about this, please leave a [[WP:CIVIL|civil]] message at my talkpage, or, if the discussion involves multiple people, leave one here and give me a &lt;nowiki&gt;{{talkback}}&lt;/nowiki&gt; notice. --[[User:I dream of horses|I dream of horses]] ([[User talk:I dream of horses|T]]) @  20:52, 4 May 2010 (UTC)
==Joe Dimaggio as Italian American==
Not only was Joe Dimaggio proud to be [[Italian American]] - according to this [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Italian_Americans_in_sports#Baseball], Joe DiMaggio (1914-1999), [[Baseball Hall of Fame]] Considered the greatest Italian-American athlete ever. Please don't revert again...[[User:Modernist|Modernist]] ([[User talk:Modernist|talk]]) 02:58, 13 September 2010 (UTC)

== Regarding Attributions Of Ethnicity ==

I have removed the attribute &quot;Italian&quot; in the prior phrase &quot;Italian American baseball player&quot; as unnecessary and stereotypical. George Washington was an American president and it would be foolish and odd to describe him as an &quot;English-American&quot; president. Likewise, General Norman Schwarzkopf, Jr. is not commonly described as a &quot;German-American&quot; general. The same holds true for nearly all historically notable figures in American history and American cultural life. An attribution of ethnicity is only appropriate in the case in which the individual in question is a duel citizen or in which the individual is a native of another country and has been subsequently naturalized as an American citizen. If the ethnic background of the individual is pertinent to the article, it would more appropriately be presented in an individual's &quot;family background&quot; section.[[User:Jintili|Jintili]] ([[User talk:Jintili|talk]]) 06:03, 24 October 2010 (UTC) To do otherwise has the effect of intellectually segregating the individual from mainstream American culture in the mind of the reader. [[User:Jintili|Jintili]] ([[User talk:Jintili|talk]]) 03:34, 13 September 2010 (UTC)
::'''Response''' - Per my comment above - ''Not only was Joe Dimaggio proud to be [[Italian American]] - according to this [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Italian_Americans_in_sports#Baseball], Joe DiMaggio (1914-1999), [[Baseball Hall of Fame]] Considered the greatest Italian-American athlete ever. Please don't revert again.'' Dimaggio like many others is listed in the many Italian American lists - he is of a generation that characterized themselves that way; until those lists are deleted and until there is consensus to do away with those characterizations in this encyclopedia - they remain valid and useful. Your argument is basically that you don't like the term and [[WP:IDON'TLIKEIT]] is not a reason to revert. Let others respond to achieve [[WP:CONSENSUS]]...[[User:Modernist|Modernist]] ([[User talk:Modernist|talk]]) 03:39, 13 September 2010 (UTC)
I couldn't disagree with you more strenuously. In addition, the very purpose of Wikipedia's editabilty is to achieve improvement and greater accuracy. I'm not sure who you think you are to demand that another user not edit. In addition, your unfounded accusation that my argument is one of simply &quot;not liking it&quot; actually has a habit of boomeranging back onto you. Perhaps it is you who does not like the description of Dimaggio as an American rather than an Italian-American. Are you are bringing your own subjectively held feelings to bear here? If you are basing your position on your stated arguments, I will need to point out that one of them, namely your statement that Dimaggio &quot;is considered the greatest Italian-American athlete ever&quot; is the essence of subjectivity! I'm sure there are thousands of people who would consider other American athletes of Italian extraction as equal or better candidates for that title. One should not be using subjective statements as justification to object to an edit. Since you have cited such an obviously subjective statement as an argument in your arsenal of justifications for objecting to the edit, I have to conclude that much, if not all, of your objection has a weak foundation indeed. I continue to maintain that the ethnic identification of an American is a SECONDARY attribute and more appropriately belongs in a &quot;family background&quot; section rather than as the primary description of any native-born American. If you are honest about wanting a consensus, as you have stated, I simply refer you to the VAST MAJORITY of Wiki articles about Americans and you will see that it is rare that they are described in a hyphenated fashion. The consensus, therefore, is clearly that native-born Americans are not generally, nor should they be, hyphenated. [[User:Jintili|Jintili]] ([[User talk:Jintili|talk]]) 04:40, 13 September 2010 (UTC) &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Jintili|Jintili]] ([[User talk:Jintili|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Jintili|contribs]]) 04:32, 13 September 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
In addition, the use of hyphenation, both historically and currently, has a derogatory connotation for many Americans [[http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyphenated_American]] and many Americans believe hyphenation ultimately has a disunifying effect on the national character and should be avoided.[[http://webcache.googleusercontent.com/search?q=cache:oMczn2zOF9sJ:www.conservativealliance.org/index.php%3Fview%3Dentry%26category%3Dpolitics%26id%3D41%253Ahyphenated-americans-throw-that-hyphen-away%26option%3Dcom_lyftenbloggie%26Itemid%3D172+Throw+That+Hyphen+Away&amp;hl=en&amp;gl=us&amp;strip=1]][[User:Jintili|Jintili]] ([[User talk:Jintili|talk]]) 05:21, 13 September 2010 (UTC)
::First of all - I am pointing out that Dimaggio is characterized on these lists in this way [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Italian_Americans_in_sports#Baseball] - not by me. However reading the history of this article I traced the origin of the addition of Italian-American to this editor here: [http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Special:Contributions/213.89.71.241] and it was initiated by an IP edit from Sweden on July 19, 2010 - not by me; - (although I wiki-bracketed it) and the vast majority of editors to this article seem comfortable with simply American and I will change it to reflect that consensus...[[User:Modernist|Modernist]] ([[User talk:Modernist|talk]]) 11:49, 13 September 2010 (UTC)
I appreciate your objectivity. Thank you. By the way, where does one view the &quot;editors to this article&quot; that you referenced above as being comfortable with this?[[User:Jintili|Jintili]] ([[User talk:Jintili|talk]]) 22:49, 13 September 2010 (UTC)
::Look at the history - look at the various ways Dimaggio is described over the majority of the history of this article to get a sense of what other editors worked on/ or read when they worked on the article. As I mentioned the majority seemed comfortable with American as descriptive by virtue of the fact that it wasn't changed until July of this year. In the very earliest versions of the article going back to 2002 we see an American ballplayer...[[User:Modernist|Modernist]] ([[User talk:Modernist|talk]]) 02:26, 14 September 2010 (UTC)

:::So why do we now see that he is once again an &quot;Italian-American ballplayer&quot;? 
:::Just askin'.  [[User:DoctorJoeE|DoctorJoeE]] ([[User talk:DoctorJoeE|talk]]) 02:39, 19 August 2011 (UTC)
It would appear that the one or more editors who repeatedly insert DiMaggio's ethnicity as a part of his primary identification are simply obsessed with that aspect of his background. See my discussion as to why this is not appropriate as a prime identifier in the case of a native-born American (although doing so can add context, if needed, when included in a description of the individual's family history.) Such edits are perhaps reflective of an emotional compulsion on the part of such editors to identify with DiMaggio as a fellow Italian-American and impart a very subtle, yet distinct, effect that tends to separate DiMaggio, undeservedly, from the American mainstream in the mind of the reader. This, I think, is something that is inaccurate.[[User:Jintili|Jintili]] ([[User talk:Jintili|talk]]) 04:53, 20 September 2011 (UTC)

:And I would agree.  We all realize that virtually every native-born American has a second heritage, and some have a third and fourth or more; and if we're going to identify that heritage in this article's lead, we would pretty much have to do it in every biographical article.  I vote for &quot;none&quot; over &quot;all.&quot;  There is ample opportunity in the body of each article to discuss heritage.  We had a similar argument over labeling the Marx Brothers as &quot;Jewish-American entertainers&quot;; took a while to get that changed. [[User:DoctorJoeE|DoctorJoeE]] ([[User talk:DoctorJoeE|talk]]) 14:48, 20 September 2011 (UTC)

== The Natural (Film) ==

Should Roy Hobbes from 'The Natural' be included in the pop culture area?  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/206.55.180.8|206.55.180.8]] ([[User talk:206.55.180.8|talk]]) 20:27, 6 October 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:I don't see a connection. In the film Hobbs strikes out 'the Whammer' based on 'the Babe' and Dimaggio was never a pitcher...[[User:Modernist|Modernist]] ([[User talk:Modernist|talk]]) 21:05, 6 October 2010 (UTC)

== Musical References ==

Did The Beatles ever do a cover of &quot;Mrs. Robinson?&quot;  It's not listed on the Wikipedia page for the song.  I don't recall it ever being on a Beatles' album.[[User:Jtyroler|Jtyroler]] ([[User talk:Jtyroler|talk]]) 19:54, 8 June 2011 (UTC)

== First marriage ==

What happened with his first wife? Divorced?  Died? When? It doesn't say.[[Special:Contributions/173.21.54.229|173.21.54.229]] ([[User talk:173.21.54.229|talk]]) 21:33, 15 February 2012 (UTC)

== Chronology ==

Viewing the article, I think it's a bit jumbled chronologically, since this ''is'' a biography article. I suggest moving the section on &quot;Wartime&quot; higher up on the page. --[[User:Leahtwosaints|Leahtwosaints]] ([[User talk:Leahtwosaints|talk]]) 00:07, 15 January 2013 (UTC)

== An unheralded and 'unknown' stat/&quot;record&quot; ==

Something that no one seems to know, or care- except me. The most amazing lifetime ratio of Home Runs to strikeouts is not Ted Williams' 521HR's to 790 KO's. It's Joe D's 361 HR's to 369 KO's- is he kidding us with that stat? :)[[User:Dcrasno|Dcrasno]] ([[User talk:Dcrasno|talk]]) 01:46, 4 October 2013 (UTC)

== Should be Semi-Protected ==

This topic seems important and should be semi-protected to prevent vandalism.  &lt;small&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—&amp;nbsp;Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Norex|Norex]] ([[User talk:Norex|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Norex|contribs]]) 00:38, 27 March 2015 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Comment and question ==

This is a good article. It's well written and it flows very well. I made some minor changes and improved the layout. I just have a question.

Should &quot;Bombshells&quot; under the &quot;Television&quot; section be really indented? Is it an episode of M*A*S*H?

[[User:ICE77|ICE77]] ([[User talk:ICE77|talk]]) 18:52, 24 July 2015 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:5|one external link|5 external links}} on [[Joe DiMaggio]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=678254903 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20150602090054/http://www.thesportgallery.com/products/covers/1946_sept.html to http://www.thesportgallery.com/products/covers/1946_sept.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20050401080623/http://www.sfgate.com:80/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/examiner/archive/1999/03/08/NEWS8438.dtl to http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?file=/examiner/archive/1999/03/08/NEWS8438.dtl
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20081007194520/http://www.thedeadballera.com/Obits/Dimaggio.JoeJr.Obit.html to http://www.thedeadballera.com/Obits/Dimaggio.JoeJr.Obit.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20130704104713/http://www.philau.edu/designcenter/exhibitions/maryline.html to http://www.philau.edu/designcenter/exhibitions/maryline.html
*Added archive https://web.archive.org/20140706183447/http://www.adsportscardsetc.com/dimaggiojoebaseballlegendscomicjuly51992.aspx to http://www.adsportscardsetc.com/dimaggiojoebaseballlegendscomicjuly51992.aspx

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers. —[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 07:40, 28 August 2015 (UTC)

== External links modified ==

Hello fellow Wikipedians,

I have just added archive links to {{plural:1|one external link|1 external links}} on [[Joe DiMaggio]]. Please take a moment to review [https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?diff=prev&amp;oldid=707235293 my edit]. If necessary, add {{tlx|cbignore}} after the link to keep me from modifying it. Alternatively, you can add {{tlx|nobots|deny{{=}}InternetArchiveBot}} to keep me off the page altogether. I made the following changes:
*Added archive http://web.archive.org/web/20110613221707/http://www.nationalpost.com/sports/story.html?id=1633915 to http://www.nationalpost.com/sports/story.html?id=1633915

When you have finished reviewing my changes, please set the ''checked'' parameter below to '''true''' to let others know.

{{sourcecheck|checked=false}}

Cheers.—[[User:Cyberbot II|&lt;sup style=&quot;color:green;font-family:Courier&quot;&gt;cyberbot II]]&lt;small&gt;&lt;sub style=&quot;margin-left:-14.9ex;color:green;font-family:Comic Sans MS&quot;&gt;[[User talk:Cyberbot II|&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;Talk to my owner]]:Online&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/small&gt; 17:19, 27 February 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>k7rmjusdkypson7pwx8dm1n49w43qdm</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
