<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Talk:Wilhelm, German Crown Prince</title>
    <ns>1</ns>
    <id>5075237</id>
    <revision>
      <id>723537244</id>
      <parentid>723271104</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-06-03T16:42:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jsc1973</username>
        <id>951</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Requested move */ Another request from someone with no knowledge of German history.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15929">{{WikiProjectBannerShell|1=
{{WikiProject Military history|class=start|B1=n|B2=n|B3=y|B4=y|B5=y
|German-task-force=yes
|Biography=yes
|WWI-task-force=yes
}}
{{WikiProject Germany|class=start|importance=low|Prussia=yes|PrussiaImp=Mid}}
{{WikiProject Biography
|living=no
|class=Start
|royalty-work-group=yes
|military-work-group=yes
|military-priority=mid
|listas=William, , German Crown Prince
}}
}}
{{Translated page|it|Guglielmo di Prussia (1882-1951)}}




==Untitled==
Refused to endorse the Nazis?  What about this photo - he is wearing SA Uniform: http://forum.axishistory.com/files/kronprinz_sa_147.jpg

:^^ Image is not visible because the forum doesn't permit hotlinking. [[User:Drutt|Drutt]] 04:18, 18 July 2007 (UTC)
:The article does say that the Prince &quot;allowed himself to be used by the Nazi government in various symbolic actions&quot;.  &lt;span style=&quot;font-size: smaller;&quot; class=&quot;autosigned&quot;&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/162.27.9.20|162.27.9.20]] ([[User talk:162.27.9.20|talk]]) 19:54, 29 October 2010 (UTC)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

== Name ==

He was never officially titled Germany's crownprince. He was Crown Prince of Prussia. [[User:Finlandais|Finlandais]] 14:18, 3 July 2006 (UTC)
:Why was he an Imperial Highness then? [[User:Cfvh|Charles]] 14:42, 3 July 2006 (UTC)

::At a guess, because as the son of the Emperor he was still a Prince of the German Empire, just like his brothers.  But he wasn't ''Crown'' Prince of the Empire because the Empire technically didn't have a succession order; the constitution just said that the Emperor was whoever happened to be King of Prussia.  [[User:Binabik80|Binabik80]] 15:53, 13 October 2006 (UTC)

:::No, no other Prussian princes were entitled to the style of Imperial Highness. The Crown Prince was an Imperial Highness because he was titled German Crown Prince in addition to being Crown Prince of Prussia. [[User:Cfvh|Charles]] 16:46, 14 October 2006 (UTC)

== A conversation copied from Talk about NC of monarchs, royals and other titled people ==

Now, I forgot one thing: What of &quot;[[Crown Prince Wilhelm of Germany]]&quot;? Shouldn't his titled be affixed to the end of his forename, as with all other past crown princes (who never acceded?) and current crown princes? Depending on whether William or Wilhelm is more appropriate (I prefer William, of course, but common usage may say otherwise), he would be at ''[[William, German Crown Prince]]'' or ''[[Wilhelm, German Crown Prince]]''. [[User:Cfvh|Charles]] 17:17, 16 June 2006 (UTC)

We should not join the crown prince into this equation. I see nothing serious against him being at &quot;W, Crown Prince of Germany&quot;. How about first seeing the result of the emperor naming, and then, if any question remains regarding crown prince, return to that. [[User:Shilkanni|Shilkanni]] 17:37, 16 June 2006 (UTC)

:I've taken the liberty to make this a subheading, so that it will remain and will stay placed under the &quot;emperor discussion&quot; for reference. [[User:Cfvh|Charles]] 17:50, 16 June 2006 (UTC)

:how was he styled? &quot;Crown Prince Wilhelm&quot; or &quot;The Crown Prince&quot;. that should determine with title to use.--[[User:Jiang|Jiang]] 21:24, 20 June 2006 (UTC)

::No, it wouldn't. The Crown Prince could have been called ''Crown Prince William'', ''The Crown Prince'' or, outside Germany or in other German states, ''The German Crown Prince'' or ''German Crown Prince William''. Whether or not his forename was included does not determine his title. [[User:Cfvh|Charles]] 23:04, 20 June 2006 (UTC)

:::why not? It is the difference between [[Charles, Prince of Wales]] and [[Prince William of Wales]]. The former is &quot;The Prince of Wales&quot; and never &quot;Prince Charles of Wales&quot; --[[User:Jiang|Jiang]] 00:36, 21 June 2006 (UTC)

::::Crown Prince is not a title that is shared amongst members of a family. There is only one Crown Prince for any given royal/imperial family. For instance, the children of a Crown Prince are not all crown princes and crown princesses in the same way that the children of a King and Queen are not all kings and queens. [[User:Cfvh|Charles]] 01:59, 21 June 2006 (UTC)

:::::But frequently &quot;Crown Prince&quot; isn't an official title, unlike &quot;Prince of Wales&quot; or &quot;King of Prussia&quot;. [[User:John Kenney|john k]] 19:43, 23 June 2006 (UTC)

:::::: I agree.  Prince of Wales is an actual title and as such belongs in proper usage, expecially for those princes of Wales who never lived to become king. [[User:Imladjov|Imladjov]] 16:42, 29 June 2006 (UTC)

:::::::Was there ever a proclaimation as to the title of Crown Prince of Prussia with regard to the German Empire? I am certain that there was never such a person as a &quot;Crown Prince of Germany&quot;. [[User:Cfvh|Charles]] 01:50, 3 July 2006 (UTC)

::::::::If he was not crown prince of Germany, that's clear enough reason to move him to crown prince of Prussia. Rhis page would be right place to continue the discussion about naming of precisely one article - here, all evidence about what he was called in English sources, and what he was proclaimed and what not, should be given. This individual's naming is obviously not a question of principle, but about individual facts. I took the liberty of copying the above writings from policy discussion arena to here. [[User:Shilkanni|Shilkanni]] 19:19, 3 July 2006 (UTC)

== German Crown Prince or Crown Prince of Germany? ==

I've always seen him called the &quot;Crown Prince of Germany&quot;.  The [[Almanach de Gotha]] calls him &quot;rince impérial de Allemagne,&quot; not &quot;Prince impérial allemand&quot; (although it also says &quot;Empereur d'Allemagne,&quot; rather than &quot;Empereur allemand.&quot;  At any rate, since &quot;Crown Prince&quot; is often an informal or only semi-formal title, I'd like to see some actual evidence that he was &quot;Deutscher Kronprinz&quot; rather than &quot;Kronprinz von Deutschland&quot;. [[User:John Kenney|john k]] 18:47, 7 December 2006 (UTC)
:Although I would have thought it would be otherwise, ''Genealogisches Handbuch des Adels Fürstliche Häuser Band VIII'' (1968) page 128 refers to Wilhelm II's eldest son as &quot;Friedrich ''Wilhelm'' Viktor August Ernst Kronprinz des Deutschen Reiches und v. Preussen&quot; and ''L'Allemagne Dynastique Tome V Hohenzollern-Waldeck'' page 251 refers to him as &quot;Guillaume, prince héritier (Kronprinz) de l'Empire Allemand et du Royaume de Prusse&quot;, Burke's Guide to the Royal Family, page 300 says &quot;HI and RH Crown Prince Friedrich ''Wilhelm'' Viktor Ernst of the German Empire and of Prussia&quot;. [[User:Lethiere|Lethiere]] 20:51, 7 December 2006 (UTC)
::So, technically it's &quot;Crown Prince of the German Empire.&quot;  Do we think a move to [[Wilhelm, Crown Prince of Germany]], is appropriate? [[User:John Kenney|john k]] 23:11, 7 December 2006 (UTC)
:::I don't think the move would be appropriate. Were Holy Roman Emperors not &quot;of the Holy Roman Empire&quot;, for instance? Wilhelm may be called &quot;Crown Prince of the German Empire&quot; just as his father could very well be called &quot;Emperor of the German Empire&quot;, but he certainly wasn't &quot;Crown Prince of Germany&quot;. No one in the Prussian Royal Family was &quot;of Germany&quot;. Wilhelm is best described as German Crown Prince for the same reasons that his father is German Emperor, not Emperor of Germany. [[User:Cfvh|Charles]] 03:23, 8 December 2006 (UTC)
::::Except that he was called &quot;Crown Prince of Germany&quot;.  &quot;German Emperor&quot; is a direct translation of the German.  &quot;German Crown Prince&quot; is not. [[User:John Kenney|john k]] 04:27, 8 December 2006 (UTC)
:::::Elizabeth II is sometimes called the Queen of England, but it isn't so. [[User:Cfvh|Charles]] 05:40, 8 December 2006 (UTC)
::::::But &quot;German Crown Prince&quot; isn't right either. [[User:John Kenney|john k]] 06:18, 8 December 2006 (UTC)
::::I don't understand this reasoning. All of the sources cited that agree Wilhelm was Crown Prince of the German Empire (''not'' Crown Prince &quot;of Germany&quot;) also describe his father as &quot;German Emperor&quot; and &quot;King of Prussia&quot;, and his siblings as &quot;Prince/ss of Prussia&quot;. I see no reason to presume that they got the father's title right, and the junior siblings' title right, but somehow got the eldest son's title wrong. Moreover, whereas Burke's may be only usually reliable when it comes to German titles, GHdA and L'Allemagne Dynastique, while not infallible, are both ''extremely'' careful with respect to German titles -- I do not know of any better sources, short of seeing the original titular decree for the German Empire's heir apparent. Does anyone have access to that document? Otherwise, what sources should be relied upon? [[User:Lethiere|Lethiere]] 07:49, 8 December 2006 (UTC)

Most of the previous reasonings are irrelevant and all are imprecise. William II. was formally never ´the Emperor of Germany´, but only ´German Emperor´ (deutscher Kaiser). By analogy William junior, was only ´German Crown Prince´ and not ´Crown Prince of Germany´. These titles are much lower in esteem than those ending with ´of Germany´. 
I am working on a full scale biography of the Crown Prince and I can give more explanations if you wish. hjajonker@chello.nl
:By analogy?  That's not a very strong argument.  Was he ''called'' &quot;German Crown Prince&quot;?  As Lethiere notes, his title according to GHdA and L'Allemagne Dynastique, his title was &quot;Crown Prince of the German Empire and of Prussia&quot;.  We can't just say that his  title was &quot;German  Crown Prince&quot; because that's analogous to &quot;German Emperor&quot; - that's not how it works. [[User:John Kenney|john k]] 05:54, 26 June 2007 (UTC)
:: He was called &quot;German Crown Prince&quot; familiarly.  He was known as Wilhelm Deutscher Kronprinz, as seen on postcards, but his full name was &quot;Friedrich '''Wilhelm''' Victor August Ernst '''Kronprinz des Deutschen Reiches und Kronprinz von Preußen K.u.K.H.'''&quot;, or &quot;His Imperial and Royal Highness, Wilhelm Crown Prince of the German Empire and Crown Prince of Prussia.&quot;  This was the format used in the ''Handbuch über den Königlich Preußischen Hof und Staat'', the annual official court and state handbook, and in the ''Rangliste der Königlich Preußischen Armee'', the army rank list. I can scan and upload copies of the entries, if that will help develop a consensus, but both the formal title and the familiar form were commonly used. Regards, [[User:Airbornelawyer|Airbornelawyer]] 06:38, 16 July 2007 (UTC)

== Ancestry Section ==

Since titles are more often ten not used such King or Duke or Duchess or Princess or Landgravine are used, for consistancy's sake, use titles for all entries in the chart.  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[User:Cladeal832|Cladeal832]] ([[User talk:Cladeal832|talk]] • [[Special:Contributions/Cladeal832|contribs]]) 19:01, 13 November 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:Unsigned --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;

:I have reverted the ancestry because there is no constructive use to make it &quot;consistent&quot; when the consistent naming convention is [[WP:NC(NT)]], which distinguishes sovereigns and consorts from other royals. The current titles are closer or equal to the article names or what they should be. [[User talk:Charles|Charles]] 03:13, 15 November 2007 (UTC)

::Also, as for the claim of initiating ancestry, see when the ancestry was first added to this article [http://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=William%2C_German_Crown_Prince&amp;diff=142592991&amp;oldid=142584468 here]. It was added to reflect naming conventions. [[User talk:Charles|Charles]] 03:15, 15 November 2007 (UTC)

== What's wrong with a redirect? ==

What's wrong with redirects?  &lt;small&gt;—Preceding [[Wikipedia:Signatures|unsigned]] comment added by [[Special:Contributions/24.57.196.130|24.57.196.130]] ([[User talk:24.57.196.130|talk]]) 04:25, 15 November 2007 (UTC)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;!-- Template:UnsignedIP --&gt; &lt;!--Autosigned by SineBot--&gt;
:[[Talk:William I of Württemberg#What's wrong with redirects?]]. [[User talk:Charles|Charles]] 04:56, 15 November 2007 (UTC)

==Rename==

I propose that this article be renamed Wilhelm, German Crown Prince.  His father and great-grandfather are at Wilhelm and I'm assuming that he's frequently called Wilhelm in English due to his father's usage.  [[User:Emperor001|Emperor001]] ([[User talk:Emperor001|talk]]) 00:42, 22 January 2009 (UTC)
:Agreed. Be consistent. If his father is Wilhelm, so is he. [[User:Jsc1973|Jsc1973]] ([[User talk:Jsc1973|talk]]) 18:41, 22 May 2011 (UTC)
::Per this the article should be moved to [[Wilhelm, German Crown Prince]]?--[[User:The Emperor&amp;#39;s New Spy|The Emperor&amp;#39;s New Spy]] ([[User talk:The Emperor&amp;#39;s New Spy|talk]]) 21:41, 13 July 2013 (UTC)

==Title==
Do you think the title should be called [[Wilhelm, Crown Prince of the German Emipre and Prussia]] instead of current title?[[User:Mr Hall of England|Mr Hall of England]] ([[User talk:Mr Hall of England|talk]]) 14:54, 16 July 2013 (UTC)
:Follow these steps [[Wikipedia:Requested moves]] and I will put myself as the first to oppose per above and consistency with the three German Emperors--[[User:The Emperor&amp;#39;s New Spy|The Emperor&amp;#39;s New Spy]] ([[User talk:The Emperor&amp;#39;s New Spy|talk]]) 17:59, 16 July 2013 (UTC)
==Requested move==
[[Wilhelm, German Crown Prince]] should be Wilhelm, Crown Prince of Germany becuase look at the following last Crown Princes of former and current monarchies:

*[[Ahmad Shah, Crown Prince of Afghanistan]]
*[[Leka, Crown Prince of Albania]]
*[[Jean-Bédel Bokassa, Crown Prince of the Central African Empire]]
*[[Frederik, Crown Prince of Denmark]]
*[[Pavlos, Crown Prince of Greece]]
*[[Crown Prince Naruhito]]
*[[Hussein bin Abdullah, Crown Prince of Jordan]]
*[[Danilo, Crown Prince of Montenegro]]
*[[Moulay Hassan, Crown Prince of Morocco]]
*[[Paras, Crown Prince of Nepal]]
*[[Haakon, Crown Prince of Norway]]
*[[Victoria, Crown Princess of Sweden]]
*[[Husain Bey, Crown Prince of Tunisia]]
*[[Alexander, Crown Prince of Yugoslavia]]

Also the German Emperors should be styled:
*[[William I, German Emperor]] to William I of Germany
*[[Frederick III, German Emperor]] to Frederick III of Germany
*[[William II, German Emperor]] to William II of Germany

This is long overdue.

[[User:Mr Hall of England|Mr Hall of England]] ([[User talk:Mr Hall of England|talk]]) 11:34, 20 July 2013 (UTC)

*'''Oppose''' per [[Talk:Wilhelm II, German Emperor/Archive 2#Requested move]] and [[#Rename]]. It is consistent with the current titles for the German Emperors. His title was German Crown Prince, Crown Prince of Prussia not Crown Prince of Germany; we leave Prussia out because German Crown Prince is higher, the same reason we leave King of Prussia out for the titles of the German Emperor. --[[User:The Emperor&amp;#39;s New Spy|The Emperor&amp;#39;s New Spy]] ([[User talk:The Emperor&amp;#39;s New Spy|talk]]) 21:04, 20 July 2013 (UTC)
*'''Oppose''' per [[User:The Emperor&amp;#39;s New Spy|The Emperor&amp;#39;s New Spy]], who took the words right out of my mouth. [[User:FactStraight|FactStraight]] ([[User talk:FactStraight|talk]]) 21:30, 20 July 2013 (UTC)
*'''Strong Oppose''' The correct title is &quot;German Emperor.&quot; When Wilhelm I received the title in 1871, he was styled in that manner because while he was, in fact, becoming a German Emperor, he was not Emperor of all of Germany. In those days, Austria was considered a part of Germany, and it was ruled by a Habsburg Emperor. Since Wilhelm wasn't claiming to be paramount sovereign over Austria, he wasn't the Emperor of Germany, he was a German Emperor. In fact, had he made such a claim, it's very likely that Austria would have declared war on his new German Empire while they were still at war with France, which would have been disastrous. But he never wanted to be Emperor of all of Germany, anyway. He and Bismarck were perfectly happy with the Kleindeutschland solution that excluded Catholic Austria, but left it as a potential ally. [[User:Jsc1973|Jsc1973]] ([[User talk:Jsc1973|talk]]) 16:42, 3 June 2016 (UTC)</text>
      <sha1>je95pmiezk7kysqwgi7ocugonieexyc</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
