<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>107th Regiment Royal Armoured Corps</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>37042768</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738512271</id>
      <parentid>738327341</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-09T11:47:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>86.183.122.124</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18777">{{infobox military unit
|unit_name=107th Regiment Royal Armoured Corps (King's Own)
|image=
|caption=
|dates=1941–1945
|country=
|allegiance={{flag|United Kingdom|23px}}
|branch={{army|United Kingdom|23px}}
|type=[[Armoured warfare|Armoured]]
|role=Infantry Support
|size=[[Regiment]]
|command_structure=[[Royal Armoured Corps]]
|garrison=
|garrison_label=
|nickname=
|patron=
|motto=
|colors=
|colors_label=
|march=
|mascot=
|equipment=[[Valentine tank]]&lt;br&gt;[[Churchill tank]]
|equipment_label=
|battles=
|anniversaries=
|decorations=
|battle_honours=
|battle_honours_label=
|disbanded=1945
|notable_commanders=
}}
The '''107th Regiment Royal Armoured Corps (King's Own)''' (107 RAC) was a [[Armoured warfare|tank]] [[regiment]] of the [[Royal Armoured Corps]], raised by the [[British Army]] during the [[World War II|Second World War]]. The regiment served with distinction in [[Western Front (World War II)|North-west Europe]] from July 1944 to May 1945.

==Origin==
107th Regiment RAC was formed on 1 November 1941 by the conversion to the armoured role of the 5th Battalion, [[King's Own Royal Regiment (Lancaster)]], a 1st Line [[Army Reserve (United Kingdom)|Territorial Army]] infantry battalion. In common with other infantry units transferred to the Royal Armoured Corps, all personnel would have continued to wear their King's Own cap badge on the black beret of the RAC.&lt;ref&gt;Forty pp. 50–1.&lt;/ref&gt; In this instance, however, the brass [[cap badge]]s of the King's Own Royal Regiment (Lancaster) were plated white metal, chrome or silver by the [[Royal Electrical and Mechanical Engineers]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kingsownmuseum.plus.com/ww2-5ko.htm King's Own Royal Regiment Museum&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

The 5th Battalion, King's Own Royal Regiment had been serving in [[126th (East Lancashire) Brigade|126th Infantry Brigade]] of [[42nd (East Lancashire) Infantry Division]] which had [[Battle of France|fought in France]] and been [[Dunkirk evacuation|evacuated at Dunkirk]] in May 1940. Later, they were redesignated [[11th Armoured Brigade (United Kingdom)|11th Armoured Brigade]] (later 11th Tank Brigade) and [[42nd Armoured Division (United Kingdom)|42nd Armoured Division]] respectively.&lt;ref&gt;Joslen, pp. 29, 68, 165, 199.&lt;/ref&gt; Serving alongside the regiment in the brigade was [[110th Regiment Royal Armoured Corps|110 RAC]] (previously 5th [[Border Regiment|Borders]]) and [[111th Regiment Royal Armoured Corps|111 RAC]] (5th [[Manchester Regiment|Manchesters]]). Based in [[Yorkshire]] (mainly at [[Keighley]] and later [[Leyburn]]) the regiment trained on [[Valentine tank]]s throughout 1942 and early 1943.&lt;ref&gt;107 RAC War Diaries February–December 1942, [[The National Archives (United Kingdom)|The National Archives, Kew]] file WO 166/6929.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Training==
In January 1943 11th Tank Brigade was attached to [[77th Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|77th Infantry (Reserve) Division]] and given the role of holding and training replacements.&lt;ref&gt;Joslen, pp. 100, 199.&lt;/ref&gt; Consequently, 107 RAC became an advanced training regiment, taking in men who had completed individual training at the training regiments, forming them into crews with responsibility for their own tanks, and instructing them in troop and finally squadron tactics.&lt;ref&gt;107 RAC War Diary February 1943, The National Archives, file WO 166/11100.&lt;/ref&gt; The regiment moved to [[Otley]], re-equipped with [[Churchill tank]]s and trained its crews (about 24 at a time) on the nearby moors.&lt;ref&gt;107 RAC War Diaries April–September 1943, The National Archives, file WO 166/11100.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Disbandment and Re-creation==
In Autumn 1943 the decision was made to disband 11th Tank Brigade, without it ever having seen active service,&lt;ref&gt;Joslen, pp. 199.&lt;/ref&gt; and on 8 September 107 RAC was ordered to disperse. Most of the regiment's personnel were transferred to other RAC regiments, and disbandment was completed on 31 December. A 'token party' of three officers and 47 other ranks from 107 RAC was sent to [[151st Regiment Royal Armoured Corps]] – which had been converted from the 10th Battalion, King's Own Royal Regiment, a hostilities-only unit created in 1940.&lt;ref&gt;107 RAC War Diaries September–December 1943, The National Archives, file WO 166/11100.&lt;/ref&gt;

The 151st Regiment RAC formed part of [[34th Armoured Brigade (United Kingdom)|34th Tank Brigade]] which also included [[147th Regiment Royal Armoured Corps|147 RAC]] (formerly 9th [[Royal Hampshire Regiment|Hampshire Regiment]]) and [[153rd Regiment Royal Armoured Corps|153 RAC]] (formerly 8th [[Essex Regiment]]). The brigade was based at [[Folkestone]] in [[Kent]], and also equipped with Churchills. On 30 December 1943 151 RAC formally disbanded in order to adopt the number of 107 RAC – thus perpetuating the link with the 5th Battalion, King's Own Royal Regiment, a permanent '1st Line' [[Army Reserve (United Kingdom)|Territorial Army]] battalion as opposed to the 'hostilities-only' 10th Battalion that had been converted to 151 RAC.&lt;ref&gt;Joslen, p. 207.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;151 RAC (10th King's Own) War Diary November 1943 Appendix F, The National Archives file WO 166/11115.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Normandy==
At the beginning of July 1944, 107 RAC embarked at [[Gosport]] for Normandy with the rest of 34th Tank Brigade&lt;ref name=July44&gt;107 RAC War Diary July 1944, The National Archives, file WO171/876.&lt;/ref&gt; Fighting in the [[Operation Overlord|Normandy Campaign]] as an independent brigade under [[21st Army Group]] command, it could be assigned to support any infantry division that required the assistance of tanks, its regiments usually split up to form [[brigade group]]s with the infantry.

107 RAC went into action on 15 July during Operation Greenline, part of the [[Second Battle of the Odon]], designed to pin German forces so that they could not interfere with the planned breakout from the Normandy beachhead (codenamed [[Operation Cobra]]).&lt;ref&gt;Ellis, Vol I, p. 334.&lt;/ref&gt; The regiment supported [[15th (Scottish) Infantry Division|15th (Scottish) Division]] in a night attack towards [[Evreux]]. 107 RAC's War Diary records that 'the attack from the inf. point of view was a complete success', but complains that the regiment's tanks were blinded by the 'excellent' smoke laid down by the artillery and infantry, and were late withdrawing the following day. The regiment had lost six tanks, with six men killed, seven wounded, and one missing.&lt;ref name=July44/&gt; On 22 July 107 RAC supported troops of [[53rd (Welsh) Infantry Division|53rd (Welsh) Division]] in a raid, and then went to support [[59th (Staffordshire) Infantry Division|59th (Staffordshire) Division]] in case of counter-attack.&lt;ref name=July44/&gt;

[[File:The British Army in Normandy 1944 B7635.jpg|thumb|right|Lt Fathergill, OC 'B' Squadron, 107 RAC, 34th Tank Brigade, with his crew on their [[Churchill tank]], 17 July 1944.]]

On 7 August 107 RAC moved up in support of [[176th (2/1st Staffordshire) Brigade|176th Brigade]] of 59th Division who had established a bridgehead across the [[Orne (river)|River Orne]]. A Squadron managed to ford the river, followed by C Sqn. The Germans put in a vigorous counter-attack and some of the British infantry withdrew, leaving 107 RAC's two forward squadrons exposed to attacks by Tiger and [[Panther tank]]s. Despite heavy casualties, the bridgehead was held, but 107's shattered squadrons had to be reformed as a single composite squadron until the regiment could be withdrawn from the line on 19 August.&lt;ref&gt;Ellis, Vol I, p. 408.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Aug44&gt;107 RAC War Diary August 1944, The National Archives, file WO171/876.&lt;/ref&gt;

Out of the line to reorganise, the regiment received the whole of C Squadron of [[153rd Regiment Royal Armoured Corps|153 RAC]], which was being broken up to provide replacements, due to a shortage of manpower. This became a new C Squadron for 107 RAC.&lt;ref name=Aug44/&gt;

By early September, the regiment was sufficiently reorganised to take part in [[Operation Astonia]], the attack on [[Le Havre]]. On 11 September. 107 RAC attacked in support of [[147th Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|147th Brigade]] of [[49th (West Riding) Infantry Division|49th (West Riding) Division]], attacking the high ground on the North East side of the port. The tanks picked their way through lanes cut through the minefields by [[Mine flail|flail tanks]] and went on to assist the infantry in mopping up machine gun positions and (with some [[Churchill Crocodile]] flamethrowers under command) to clear buildings. The following day, 107 RAC's tanks took up hull-down positions on the high ground and gave fire support to the infantry advance on the town, which fell later that day.&lt;ref&gt;Ellis, Vol II, p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;107 RAC War Diary September 1944, The National Archives, file WO 171/876.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Clarkeforce==
107 RAC was back in the line in early October, supporting small-scale infantry operations and standing ready to counter-attack if called upon. On 18 October it became part of 'Clarkeforce', a mobile column commanded by [[Brigadier (United Kingdom)|Brigadier]] [[William Stanhope Clarke|W.S. Clarke]] of 34th Tank Brigade. As part of operations on the Belgian–Dutch border to clear the approaches to the port of [[Antwerp]], 49 Division was to attack towards Loenhout, and then unleash Clarkeforce to exploit the breakthrough and move up the main road to [[Wuustwezel]] (Operation Rebound).

Clarkeforce was launched at 16.00 on 20 October. The Churchills of 107 RAC's C Sqn carried D Company of the 1st Battalion, [[Royal Leicestershire Regiment|Leicestershire Regiment]], and the regiment had a troop of [[17pdr SP Achilles|Achilles]] self-propelled 17-pounders from 248 Battery, [[62nd Anti-Tank Regiment, Royal Artillery]],&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ra39-45.pwp.blueyonder.co.uk/atk/page19.html RA 1939–45 62 A/Tk Rgt&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; and a troop of [[Churchill Crocodile]] flamethrowing tanks of the [[Fife and Forfar Yeomanry|1st Fife and Forfar Yeomanry]] in support. Progress was not fast: the column was restricted to one tank's width, and the [[M3 Stuart]] ('Honey') light tanks of 107's Recce Troop were held up by the bad tank going, but the leading squadrons moved on in the approaching darkness to allow C Sqn and the infantry to clear Wuustwezel, taking some prisoners. 'The night was pitch dark, it was raining, and there was no moon', and the Recce Trp scouting ahead were held up by a roadblock of trees, which were cleared by the leading Churchills. After a short rest, the regiment moved on at 0800 the following morning towards Nieuwmoer. By now the Recce Troop had run out of fuel, and the advance was led by A Sqn of [[49 (West Riding) Reconnaissance Regiment RAC]]. When they came across a bridge that had been blown, the tanks had to fan out to the flanks in search of alternative crossings, and with no cover they were engaged over the flat country by German Self-Propelled guns. The advance had to be covered by smoke. Once clearance of the village was well in hand, the Recce Trp came up and pushed on carelessly into a wood occupied by German troops and SP guns. Four Honeys were knocked out, bringing the regiment's casualties to eight tanks in the day.

On 22 October the advance continued towards Esschen, 107 RAC engaging enemy infantry and SP guns. The regiment's A Echelon vehicles, following behind, were ambushed and further casualties received. For the next day's advance the Leicesters were relieved by two companies from 7th Battalion, [[Duke of Wellington's Regiment]], who attacked Schanker successfully with C Sqn's Churchills on 24 October.&lt;ref&gt;107 RAC War Diary October 1944, The National Archives, file WO 171/876.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;34 Tank Bde War Diary October 1944, The National Archives, file WO 171/643.&lt;/ref&gt;

After a day's pause for planning, Clarkeforce was launched for a second time on 26 October for [[Operation Thruster]] towards [[Roosendaal]]. Clarkeforce pushed on towards [[Brembosch]], losing four tanks and an SP gun from 245 Bty, 62nd A/Tk Regt. The following day, 107 RAC supported the 1st Leicesters in an attack along the Brembosch–[[Wouwse Hil]] road, and reached Oostlaar by nightfall. At first light, while replenishing their tanks, C Sqn came under fire, lost some vehicles and had to withdraw under smoke and covering fire, but  at 0815 the regiment was ready to support an attack by 11th [[Royal Scots Fusiliers]] and cut the [[Wouw]]–[[Bergen-op-Zoom]] road, despite enemy SP guns. The advances were masked by smoke and covered by the remaining Achilles. The last day of Operation Thruster saw 107 RAC positioned to support an attack by [[146th Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|146th Infantry Brigade]] and the [[9th Royal Tank Regiment]]. 107 RAC was withdrawn to Wouwe on 31 October to reorganise.

==Netherlands==
After a period of maintenance, 107 RAC was temporarily attached to [[31st Tank Brigade]] (part of [[79th Armoured Division (United Kingdom)|79th Armoured Division]], equipped with specialist armour) and on 3 December went into action at [[Blerick]] in support of [[15th (Scottish) Infantry Division|15th (Scottish) Division]] in [[XII Corps (United Kingdom)|XII Corps]]. This well-planned and executed Corps attack on this heavily defended suburb of the Dutch town of  [[Venlo]] (Operation Guildlford), was accompanied by strong artillery and [[Hawker Typhoon|Typhoon]] support, preceded by flail tanks to breach minefields, bridge-laying [[Armoured Vehicle Royal Engineers|AVRE]]s to cross an anti-tank ditch, and with a well-executed cover plan that misled the enemy as to the direction from which the attack would come. The objectives were achieved with remarkably few casualties.&lt;ref name=Dec44&gt;107 RAC War Diary December 1944, The National Archives, file WO 171/876.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ellis, Vol II, pp. 160–1.&lt;/ref&gt;

Although due to return to 34 Tank Bde at the end of December,&lt;ref name=Dec44/&gt; 107 RAC was suddenly moved to the [[Ardennes]] sector where it came under the command of [[6th Airborne Division (United Kingdom)|6th Airborne Division]]&lt;ref&gt;107 RAC War Diary January 1945, The National Archives, file WO 171/4717.&lt;/ref&gt; to take part in [[Second Army (United Kingdom)|British Second Army]]'s counter-attack against the Northern edge of the 'Bulge' created by the German [[Battle of the Bulge|Ardennes Offensive]]. 6th Airborne Division and its supporting tanks, attacking on 3 January in atrocious weather, had a very hard fight with the Germans in [[Bure, Belgium|Bure]] (see [[Battle of Bure]]), which changed hands several times in the next few days.&lt;ref&gt;Ellis, Vol II, p. 191.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Germany==
107 RAC reverted to the command of 34th Armoured Brigade (as 34 Tank Brigade had been redesignated),&lt;ref&gt;Joslen, pp. 184, 207.&lt;/ref&gt; for [[Operation Veritable]], the British attack on the [[Siegfried Line]] in the [[Klever Reichswald|Reichswald]]. Each of the regiment's squadrons was assigned to a different brigade of [[51st (Highland) Division]]: A Sqn to [[154th Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|154 Brigade]], B Sqn to [[153rd Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|153 Brigade]] and C Sqn to [[152nd Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|152 Brigade]], supported by AVREs and flails to cross the anti-tank obstacles.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;107 RAC War Diary February 1945, The National Archives, file WO 171/4717.&lt;/ref&gt; Progress was slow in the close terrain, mud, and obstacles. Although 153 Brigade cleared the German anchor position in the Kiekberg Woods and got across the Gennep road on 9 February,&lt;ref&gt;Ellis, Vol II, pp. 258, 261.&lt;/ref&gt; the acting commanding officer of 1st Battalion, [[Gordon Highlanders]] ([[Major (United Kingdom)|Major]] [[Sir Martin Lindsay, 1st Baronet|Martin Lindsay]]) was scathing about the  support he received from B Sqn, which he described as 'The windiest and wettest imaginable'.&lt;ref&gt;Lindsay, p 193.&lt;/ref&gt; Daily attacks continued until 21 February when 51st Highland took Goch. 107 RAC continued to support the Highlanders in their advance to the Rhine.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

34th Armoured Brigade was attached to XII Corps for the assault on the Rhine in March 1945,&lt;ref&gt;Elis, Vol II, p. 285.&lt;/ref&gt; but 107 RAC saw little activity. In April it crossed the Rhine and took up occupation duties, with B Sqn attached to Second British Army as part of the GHQ guard. The regiment ended the war in Europe clearing battlefields and administering camps for displaced persons and released prisoners of war.&lt;ref&gt;107 RAC War Diary March–May 1945, The National Archives, file WO 171/4717.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Disbandment==
The regiment was disbanded at the end of the [[World War II|Second World War]] in 1945.&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20051226113822/http://regiments.org/regiments/uk/cav/RAC.htm Royal Armoured Corps [UK&amp;#93;&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; The 5th Battalion, [[King's Own Royal Regiment (Lancaster)]] was reconstituted in the [[Army Reserve (United Kingdom)|Territorial Army]] in 1947 and bore the honorary distinction (on its colours and appointments) of the badge of the [[Royal Armoured Corps]] with the dates '1944–45' and a scroll carrying the words 'North-West Europe', to commemorate its career as 107th Regiment Royal Armoured Corps.&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20051122180128/http://regiments.org/regiments/uk/volmil-england/vinf-no/cu-KO45.htm 4th/5th Battalion, The King's Own Royal Regiment [UK&amp;#93;&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
* [[Lionel Ellis|Major L. F. Ellis]], ''History of the Second World War: United Kingdom Military Series: Victory in the West'', Volume I: ''The Battle of Normandy'', London: HMSO, 1962/Uckfield: Naval &amp; Military, 2004, ISBN 1-84574-058-0.
* Major L.F. Ellis, ''History of the Second World War: United Kingdom Military Series: Victory in the West'', Volume II: ''The Defeat of Germany'', London: HMSO, 1968/Uckfield: Naval &amp; Military, 2004, ISBN 1-84574-059-9. 
* George Forty, ''British Army Handbook 1939–1945'', Stroud: Sutton Publishing, 1998, ISBN 0-7509-1403-3.
* Lt-Col H.F. Joslen, '''Orders of Battle, United Kingdom and Colonial Formations and Units in the Second World War, 1939–1945'', London: HM Stationery Office, 1960/Uckfield: Naval &amp; Military, 2003, ISBN 1-84342-474-6.
* Lt-Col Martin Lindsay, ''So Few Got Through'', London: Collins, 1946/Arrow Books (pbk; nd)/Leo Cooper, 2000, ISBN 0-85052-754-6. Page references are to Arrow edition.

[[Category:Military units and formations established in 1941]]
[[Category:Royal Armoured Corps]]
[[Category:Regiments of the Royal Armoured Corps]]
[[Category:Regiments of the British Army]]
[[Category:Regiments of the British Army in World War II|Royal Armoured Corps 107]]
[[Category:Military units and formations disestablished in 1945]]</text>
      <sha1>kvv5jial0tl6vyiv10lyporxn267vgu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
