<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>10th Arkansas Cavalry Regiment (Newton's)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>33189198</id>
    <revision>
      <id>741348886</id>
      <parentid>738331555</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-26T23:05:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* References */http&amp;rarr;https for [[Google Books]] and [[Google News]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18048">{{Hide in print|1=
{{Infobox military unit
|unit_name=Newton's 10th Arkansas Cavalry (Confederate)
|image=[[File:Robert C Newton.PNG|300px]]
|caption=Robert C Newton, first commander of the [[Pulaski Light Artillery]]. Later commanded the [[5th Arkansas Cavalry]]. Promoted to Major General during the [[Brooks-Baxter War]]
|dates=August 1864–May 31, 1865
|country=[[Confederate States of America]]
|allegiance=[[Image:Confederate National Flag since Mar 4 1865.svg|border|23px|Dixie]] [[Confederate States of America|CSA]]
|branch=[[Infantry]]
|type=
|role=
|size=[[Regiment]]
|command_structure=
|garrison=
|garrison_label=
|nickname=
|patron=
|motto=
|colors=
|colors_label=
|march=
|mascot=
|equipment=
|equipment_label=
|battles=[[American Civil War]]
*[[Red River Campaign]]
*[[Battle of Marks' Mills]]
*[[Battle of Dardanelle]]
|anniversaries=
|decorations=
|battle_honours=
|battle_honours_label=
|disbanded=May 31, 1865
|flying_hours=
|website=
&lt;!-- Commanders --&gt;
|commander1=
|commander1_label=
|commander2=
|commander2_label=
|commander3=
|commander3_label=
|commander4=
|commander4_label=
|notable_commanders=
&lt;!-- Insignia --&gt;
|identification_symbol=
|identification_symbol_label=
|identification_symbol_2=
|identification_symbol_2_label=
|identification_symbol_3=
|identification_symbol_3_label=
|identification_symbol_4=
|identification_symbol_4_label=
}}}}
The '''Netwon's 10th Arkansas Cavalry Regiment''' (1864–1865) was a [[Confederate Army]] [[Cavalry]] [[regiment]] during the [[American Civil War]]. The unit was originally organized from volunteer companies raised from the Arkansas State Militia in the Southern Arkansas Counties in the winter of 1863–1864 after the fall of Little Rock. It was originally organized as '''Pettus Battalion, Arkansas State Troops''' but was later enrolled in Confederal Service and Robert Crittenden Newton was elected Colonel.

== Organization ==
Netwon's 10th Arkansas Cavalry Regiment was originally organized as a group of Volunteer Companies raised from the militia regiments of southern Arkansas, immediately following the fall of Little Rock, Arkansas, to Union forces in September 1863. Governor [[Harris Flanagin]] began organizing a new force of state troops issuing a proclamation on August 10, 1863, just a month before the capitol fell, announcing that he had been authorized to raise new regiments of state troops and that by special agreement these new units could not be transferred out of the state by Confederate authorities.&lt;ref name=&quot;google190&quot;/&gt;

After the fall of Little Rock, recruiting was far more difficult than it had been in the first years of the war. The constant transfer of Arkansas troops into the eastern theater of the war, across the Mississippi River from their homes, was a major objection by the remaining population of men eligible for military service. With Federal forces now occupying the state capitol, the Confederate state government had no way of enforcing conscription laws in the counties behind the Union lines, except during raids by Generals Price and Shelby in 1864. The remaining Confederate regiments were plagued by desertions.&lt;ref name=&quot;THE WAR OF THE REBELLION 1898, Page 901&quot;/&gt;

On September 16, 1863, in the immediate aftermath of the fall of the state capitol, Governor Flanagin issued General Order No. 6 from Arkadelphia, which called into service the militia regiments of the counties of Clark, Hempstead, Sevier, Pike, Polk, Montgomery, La Fayette, Ouachita, Union, and Columbia in order to resist the Federal army. The Governor's order directed the regiments to march to Arkadelphia at the earliest possible day. Companies were to be mounted and commanders were to compel persons evading the call to come to the rendezvous. The intent was to form companies of twelve-month mounted volunteers. Only six physicians, one druggist, millers to supply the wants of the country, clerks, sheriffs, postmasters, and persons in the employ of the Confederate States were exempted from the order.&lt;ref name=&quot;google191&quot;/&gt; In describing this call in a letter to General Holmes dated October 18, 1863, from Washington, Arkansas, the new Confederate state capitol, Flanagin stated that he issued the order calling out the militia, as an experiment, expecting to get volunteers. The order succeeded so well as to get companies organized in the counties where the call for the militia was enforced which resulted in seven companies being collected under the call.&lt;ref name=&quot;THE WAR OF THE REBELLION 1898, Page 901&quot;/&gt; Flanagin also stated that &quot;the troops raised by the State are more than double all the troops raised by volunteering, or by the conscript law, within the past few months&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;THE WAR OF THE REBELLION 1898, Page 901&quot;/&gt;

On October 26, 1863 Governor Flanagin directed his Adjutant General Gordon N. Peay to:
{{quotation|&quot;visit Lewisville, in La Fayette County, and see Captain Ford, who has been raising a company of mounted riflemen under the State. I have been informed that this company has been sworn into the service of the Confederate States. If so, the only thing to be done is to communicate this fact to General Fagan. If the State troops which can be raised in La Fayette County are already raised you are authorized to disband the militia. If convenient, I would like for you to go to Union County. Captain Holloway has been raising a company of mounted riflemen in that county. If his company is organized, you can disband the militia of that county. If the colonel is inefficient, and Captain Holloway has not got his company formed, let him swear his men in and get the militia together, and compel those who are liable to the conscript law to go into the State or C. S. service&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;google192&quot;/&gt;}} These new units of Arkansas State Troops were placed under the overall command of Col. William H. Trader who was detailed to Governor Flanagin by General [[E. Kirby Smith]]. Col. Trader remained in command of the state troops until he resigned in June 1864.&lt;ref name=&quot;google193&quot;/&gt;

=== Pettus Battalion, Arkansas State Troops ===
On January 14, 1864, Governor Flanagin, through General Peay, issued General Orders, No. 8. which directed the following named companies of Arkansas mounted volunteers, which had been called into the service of the State under the proclamation of the August 10, A.D. 1863, compose and be designated as the 1st Battalion, Arkansas State Troops:{{citation needed|date=December 2012}}
* Company A – of Hempstead County, Captain E. K. Williamson, commanding.&lt;ref name=&quot;Arkansas Military Department Records 1862, Page 303&quot;/&gt;
* Company B – of Clark County, Captain Reuben C. Reed, commanding.&lt;ref name=&quot;Arkansas Military Department Records 1862, Page 303&quot;/&gt;
* Company C – of Sevier County, Captain Allen T. Pettus, commanding.&lt;ref name=&quot;Arkansas Military Department Records 1862, Page 303&quot;/&gt;
* Company D – of Polk County, Captain G. A. Hale, commanding.&lt;ref name=&quot;Arkansas Military Department Records 1862, Page 303&quot;/&gt;
* Company E – of Hot Spring County, Captain John W. Dyer, commanding.&lt;ref name=&quot;Arkansas Military Department Records 1862, Page 303&quot;/&gt;

Allen T. Pettus was elected Lieutenant Colonel of this battalion. The unit participated in the battle of Marks Mill on April 25, 1864, as a part of Brigadier General [[William L. Cabell]]’s Division. Lt. Col. Pettus was killed during the battle and Capt. P.K. Williamson of Company A commanded the battalion until the unit was increased to a regiment and transferred to Confederate service.

=== Newton's 10th Arkansas Cavalry Regiment ===
In August 1864 when the term of enlistment for these state troops was about to expire, Adjutant General Peay issued an order which directed that companies be allowed to vote on the subject of being transferred into Confederate service. However, the chance to vote on being transferred was merely a matter of form because Peay's order also had directions for those who refused transfer to Confederate service:{{citation needed|date=December 2012}}

{{quotation|&quot;Men whose terms of service have expired, and who are not willing to be transferred, will be reported to and turned over to the proper enrolling officer of the Confederate States for conscription. Men whose terms of service have not expired and who are opposed to the transfer will be required to serve until the expiration of their term of enlistment, and such as do not then re enlist will be turned over to the proper enrolling officers of the Confederate States for conscription.&lt;ref name=&quot;google194&quot;/&gt;}}

On September 5, 1864, the State Troop companies, including Pettus Battalion, were formed into one regiment of cavalry to be designated as the 3rd Regiment of Arkansas Cavalry, with Col. Robert C. Newton assigned to the command of the regiment until an election could be held for field officers. The companies of this regiment included:&lt;ref name=&quot;google195&quot;/&gt;

* Company A — Capt. Reuben C. Reed, composed of men from Clark County.&lt;ref name=&quot;Arkansas Military Department Records 1862, Page 303&quot;/&gt; This company was originally organized as a volunteer company, in the 67th Regiment, Arkansas State Militia, Clark County on October 8, 1863.&lt;ref&gt;Arkansas Military Department Records, Spanish American War, List of Commissioned Officers of the Militia 1827–1862, Arkansas History Commission, Microfilm Roll 38-8, Page 544&lt;/ref&gt; 
* Company B — Capt. Robert S. Burke, composed of men from Montgomery County.&lt;ref name=&quot;Arkansas Military Department Records 1862, Page 303&quot;/&gt;
* Company C — Capt. Cyrus K. Holman (replaced Allen T. Pettus), composed of men from Sever County.&lt;ref name=&quot;Arkansas Military Department Records 1862, Page 303&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;couchgenweb196&quot;/&gt;
* Company D — Capt. James B. Williamson, composed of men from Polk County.&lt;ref name=&quot;Arkansas Military Department Records 1862, Page 303&quot;/&gt;
* Company E — Capt. Samuel Ogden (replaced P.K. Williamson), composed of men from Hempstead County.&lt;ref name=&quot;Arkansas Military Department Records 1862, Page 303&quot;/&gt;
* Company F — Capt. Theophilus G. Henley, composed of men from Hempstead County.&lt;ref name=&quot;Arkansas Military Department Records 1862, Page 303&quot;/&gt;
* Company G — Capt. George A. Hale, composed of men from Polk County.&lt;ref name=&quot;Arkansas Military Department Records 1862, Page 303&quot;/&gt;
* Company H — Capt. William C. Corcoran, composed of men from Scott County.&lt;ref name=&quot;Arkansas Military Department Records 1862, Page 303&quot;/&gt;
* Company I — Capt. Allen A. McDonald (replaced John W. Dyer), composed of men from Hot Spring County.&lt;ref name=&quot;Arkansas Military Department Records 1862, Page 303&quot;/&gt;
* Company K — Capt. John Connally, composed of men from Yell County.  This company was originally organized as a volunteer company, in the 26th Regiment, Arkansas State Militia, Yell, County on October 8, 1863.&lt;ref&gt;Arkansas Military Department Records, Spanish American War, List of Commissioned Officers of the Militia 1827–1862, Arkansas History Commission, Microfilm Roll 38-8, Page 352&lt;/ref&gt;

This unit was mustered into the Confederate Service on the October 31, 1864, as the 10th Arkansas Cavalry Regiment. Col. Newton was elected Regimental Commander.&lt;ref name=&quot;google197&quot;/&gt;

== Battles ==
The unit operated in the Arkansas River Valley, interdicting the supply route between Little Rock and Fort Smith during the winter of 1864 to 1865.

*[[Red River Campaign]], Arkansas March–May, 1864.
*[[Battle of Marks' Mills]], Arkansas, April 25, 1864.
*[[Battle of Dardanelle]], Arkansas, January 14 and 17, 1865.

== Surrender ==
It appears that rather than surrender, the regiment simply disbanded.  It served until May 31, 1865, when the encampment, which was near Dooleys Ferry, in Hempstead County, Arkansas, was abandoned, the most of the men having been given furloughs to go home and cut wheat.&lt;ref&gt;Wallis, W.M., &quot;Colonel R.C. Newton’s 10th Arkansas Cavalry and The Muster Roll for Captain C.K. Holman’s Company C, Newton’s 10th Arkansas Cavalry, Sept. 1, 1864 - Oct. 31, 1864, Inclusive.&quot; Rootsweb, Accessed 23 September 2011, http://www.rootsweb.ancestry.com/~arcivwar/10arcav.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em|refs=

&lt;ref name=&quot;couchgenweb196&quot;&gt;Byrd, Kenneth E., &quot;COLONEL ROBERT C. NEWTON'S, FIRST BATTALION, 10TH ARKANSAS CAVALRY REGIMENT, COMPANY C&quot;, Edward G. Gerdes Civil War Page, Accessed May 11, 2011, {{cite web|url=http://www.couchgenweb.com/civilwar/10thregt.htm |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2011-05-12 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090901034432/http://www.couchgenweb.com/civilwar/10thregt.htm |archivedate=2009-09-01 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;google190&quot;&gt;Reynolds, John H., &quot;Official Orders of Governor Harris Flanagin&quot;, by Publications of the Arkansas Historical Association, Volume 2, Arkansas Historical Association, Fayetteville, Arkansas, 1908, Page 370, Accessed May 11, 2011, https://books.google.com/books?id=RTw7AAAAIAAJ&amp;lpg=PA406&amp;ots=dFjyDBfTF9&amp;dq=Gordon%20N.%20Peay%20Arkansas&amp;pg=PA370#v=onepage&amp;q=newton&amp;f=false&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;THE WAR OF THE REBELLION 1898, Page 901&quot;&gt;THE WAR OF THE REBELLION, THE OFFICIAL RECORD OF THE UNION AND CONFEDERATE ARMIES, SERIES I—VOLUME LIU, GOVERNMENT PRINTING OFFICE, 1898, Page 901, Accessed May 11, 2011, https://books.google.com/books?id=XpM3AQAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA901&amp;lpg=PA1019&amp;ots=bt2XZDsv0s&amp;dq=Governor+Flanagin+appointed+Gordon+N.+Peay&amp;output=text#c_top&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;ref name=&quot;google193&quot;&gt;Reynolds, John H., &quot;Official Orders of Governor Harris Flanagin&quot;, by Publications of the Arkansas Historical Association, Volume 2, Arkansas Historical Association, Fayetteville, Arkansas, 1908, Page 362, Accessed May 11, 2011, https://books.google.com/books?id=RTw7AAAAIAAJ&amp;lpg=PA406&amp;ots=dFjyDBfTF9&amp;dq=Gordon%20N.%20Peay%20Arkansas&amp;pg=PA403#v=onepage&amp;q=Gordon%20N.%20Peay%20Arkansas&amp;f=false&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;google194&quot;&gt;THE WAR OF THE REBELLION, THE OFFICIAL RECORD OF THE UNION AND CONFEDERATE ARMIES, SERIES I—VOLUME LIU, GOVERNMENT PRINTING OFFICE, 1898, Page 1018, Accessed 11&amp;nbsp;May2011, https://books.google.com/books?dq=Governor%20Flanagin%20appointed%20Gordon%20N.%20Peay&amp;q=peay&amp;id=XpM3AQAAIAAJ&amp;output=text&amp;pg=PA1019&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;Arkansas Military Department Records 1862, Page 303&quot;&gt;Arkansas Military Department Records, List of Commissioned Officers of the Militia 1827–1862, Arkansas History Commission, Microfilm Roll 00000038-8, Page 303&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;google191&quot;&gt;THE WAR OF THE REBELLION, THE OFFICIAL RECORD OF THE UNION AND CONFEDERATE ARMIES, SERIES I—VOLUME LIU, GOVERNMENT PRINTING OFFICE, 1898, Page 889, Accessed May 11, 2011, https://books.google.com/books?pg=PA896&amp;lpg=PA1019&amp;dq=Governor%20Flanagin%20appointed%20Gordon%20N.%20Peay&amp;sig=Ye8GGU9Ry-kuZ9mDZS1sy03FUvE&amp;ei=xEXLTf-WOJSUtwfmz5XjBw&amp;ct=result&amp;id=XpM3AQAAIAAJ&amp;ots=bt2XZDsv0s&amp;output=text&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;google192&quot;&gt;THE WAR OF THE REBELLION, THE OFFICIAL RECORD OF THE UNION AND CONFEDERATE ARMIES, SERIES I—VOLUME LIU, GOVERNMENT PRINTING OFFICE, 1898, Page 903, Accessed 11&amp;nbsp;May2011, https://books.google.com/books?pg=PA903&amp;lpg=PA1019&amp;dq=Governor%20Flanagin%20appointed%20Gordon%20N.%20Peay&amp;id=XpM3AQAAIAAJ&amp;ots=bt2XZDsv0s&amp;output=text&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;google193&quot;&gt;Reynolds, John H., &quot;Official Orders of Governor Harris Flanagin&quot;, by Publications of the Arkansas Historical Association, Volume 2, Arkansas Historical Association, Fayetteville, Arkansas, 1908, Page 362, Accessed May 11, 2011, https://books.google.com/books?id=RTw7AAAAIAAJ&amp;lpg=PA406&amp;ots=dFjyDBfTF9&amp;dq=Gordon%20N.%20Peay%20Arkansas&amp;pg=PA403#v=onepage&amp;q=Gordon%20N.%20Peay%20Arkansas&amp;f=false&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;google194&quot;&gt;THE WAR OF THE REBELLION, THE OFFICIAL RECORD OF THE UNION AND CONFEDERATE ARMIES, SERIES I—VOLUME LIU, GOVERNMENT PRINTING OFFICE, 1898, Page 1018, Accessed 11&amp;nbsp;May2011, https://books.google.com/books?dq=Governor%20Flanagin%20appointed%20Gordon%20N.%20Peay&amp;q=peay&amp;id=XpM3AQAAIAAJ&amp;output=text&amp;pg=PA1019&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;google195&quot;&gt;THE WAR OF THE REBELLION, THE OFFICIAL RECORD OF THE UNION AND CONFEDERATE ARMIES, SERIES I—VOLUME LIU, GOVERNMENT PRINTING OFFICE, 1898, Page 1019, Accessed May 11, 2011, https://books.google.com/books?id=XpM3AQAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA1019&amp;dq=Robert+C.+Newton+Gordon+Peay+Arkansas+Official+records&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=n17LTbHsEYy2twe1rpH9Bw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CDwQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name=&quot;google197&quot;&gt;Reynolds, John H., &quot;Official Orders of Governor Harris Flanagin&quot;, by Publications of the Arkansas Historical Association, Volume 2, Arkansas Historical Association, Fayetteville, Arkansas, 1908, Page 421, Accessed May 11, 2011, https://books.google.com/books?id=RTw7AAAAIAAJ&amp;lpg=PA406&amp;ots=dFjyDBfTF9&amp;dq=Gordon%20N.%20Peay%20Arkansas&amp;pg=PA421#v=onepage&amp;q=newton&amp;f=false&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
{{Hide in print|1=

== External links ==
*[http://www.couchgenweb.com/civilwar Edward G. Gerdes Civil War Home Page]
*[http://encyclopediaofarkansas.net/encyclopedia/item-detail.aspx?type=Time+Period&amp;item=Civil+War+through+Reconstruction+(1861+-+1874) The Encyclopedia of Arkansas History and Culture]
*[http://digital.library.cornell.edu/m/moawar/waro.html The War of the Rebellion: a Compilation of the Official Records of the Union and Confederate Armies]
*[http://arkansascivilwar.com The Arkansas History Commission, State Archives, Civil War in Arkansas]

== See also ==
{{portal|American Civil War}}
*[[List of Arkansas Civil War Confederate units]]
*[[Lists of American Civil War Regiments by State]]
*[[Lists of American Civil War Regiments by State#Confederate Forces|Confederate Units by State]]
*[[Arkansas in the American Civil War]]
*[[Arkansas Militia in the Civil War]]
*{{USGovernment|sourceURL=[http://www.civilwar.nps.gov/cwss/regiments.cfm Civil War Soldiers and Sailors System], National Park Service}}

{{Arkansas in the Civil War}}
{{American Civil War|expanded=CTCBS}}

}}

[[Category:Arkansas Confederate Civil War regiments]]
[[Category:Military units and formations in Arkansas]]
[[Category:Military in Arkansas]]
[[Category:1864 establishments in Arkansas]]</text>
      <sha1>rjo4lvs69upuwhit8ldys5dlrmf48uk</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
