<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>1113–15 Balearic Islands expedition</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>21471592</id>
    <revision>
      <id>740905285</id>
      <parentid>738508407</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-24T02:26:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>MZMcBride</username>
        <id>212624</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>wrap [[ISBN]] in template</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10342">{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict   = 1113–1115 Balearic Islands expedition
| partof     = the [[Crusades]]
| image      = [[File:Location map Taifa of Mallorca.svg|250px]]
| caption    = The ''taifa'' of the Balearics (green), with its capital (Mallorca), the Crusaders' chief target, indicated.
| date       = 1113–1115
| place      = [[Balearic Islands]]
| result     = Decisive Christian victory
| combatant1 = [[Republic of Pisa]]&lt;br&gt;[[Catalan counties]]&lt;br&gt;[[County of Provence]]&lt;br&gt;[[Giudicato of Torres]]&lt;br&gt;[[Papal States]]
| combatant2 = [[Taifa of Majorca]]&lt;br&gt;[[Almoravids]]
| combatant3  = 
| commander1  =[[Pietro Moriconi]]&lt;br&gt;[[Ramon Berenguer III of Barcelona]]&lt;br&gt;[[Hug II of Empúries]]&lt;br&gt;[[Saltaro of Torres]]
| commander2  = [[Abu-I-Rabi Sulayman]]{{POW}}
| strength1   = 300 Pisan ships&lt;br&gt;150 Catalan and Provençal ships
| strength2   = Unknown
| casualties1 = Unknown
| casualties2 = High
| campaignbox = {{Crusade}}
}}
In 1114, an '''expedition to the [[Balearic Islands]]''', then a [[Muslim]] ''[[taifa]]'', was launched in the form of a [[Crusade]]. Founded on a treaty of 1113 between the [[Republic of Pisa]] and [[Ramon Berenguer III, Count of Barcelona]], the expedition had the support of [[Pope Paschal II]] and the participation of many lords of [[Principality of Catalonia|Catalonia]] and [[Occitania]], as well as contingents from northern and central [[Italy]], [[Sardinia]], and [[Corsica]]. The Crusaders were perhaps inspired by the [[Norwegian king]] [[Sigurd I of Norway|Sigurd I's]] attack on [[Formentera]] in 1108 or 1109 during the [[Norwegian Crusade]].&lt;ref&gt;Gary B. Doxey (1996), &quot;Norwegian Crusaders and the Balearic Islands&quot;, ''Scandinavian Studies'', 10–11. In the ''Liber maiolichinus'' the Norwegian king is referred to only as ''rex Norgregius'', and is recorded as sailing with 100 ships, though the later [[saga]]s record sixty.&lt;/ref&gt; The expedition ended in 1115 in the conquest of the Balearics, but only until the next year. The main source for the event is the Pisan ''[[Liber maiolichinus]]'', completed by 1125.

==Treaty and preparations==
In 1085 [[Pope Gregory VII]] had granted suzerainty over the Balearics to Pisa.&lt;ref name=bishko&gt;Charles Julian Bishko (1975), [http://libro.uca.edu/bishko/spr1.htm &quot;The Spanish and Portuguese Reconquest, 1095–1492&quot;], ''A History of the Crusades, Vol. 3: The Fourteenth and Fifteenth Centuries'', ed. Harry W. Hazard (Madison: University of Wisconsin Press), 405.&lt;/ref&gt; In September 1113 a Pisan fleet making an expedition to [[Majorca]] was put off course by a storm and ended up near [[Blanes]] on the coast of Catalonia, which they initially mistook for the Balearics.&lt;ref&gt;Silvia Orvietani Busch (2001), ''Medieval Mediterranean Ports: The Catalan and Tuscan Coasts, 1100 to 1235'' (BRILL, {{ISBN|90-04-12069-6}}), 207. The fleet had left Pisa in August.&lt;/ref&gt; The Pisans met with the Count of Barcelona in the port of [[Sant Feliu de Guíxols]], where on 7 September they signed a treaty ''causa corroborandae societatis et amicitiae'' (&quot;for the cause of social cooperation and friendship&quot;). Specifically the Pisans were exempted from the ''[[usagium]]'' and the ''[[jus naufragii]]'' in all the territories, present and future, of the Count of Barcelona, though [[Arles]] and [[Saint-Gilles, Gard|Saint-Gilles]], in the recently acquired [[March of Provence]], were singled out for special mention (three times).&lt;ref name=busch208&gt;Busch, 208.&lt;/ref&gt;

The only surviving copy of the treaty between Pisa and Barcelona is found interpolated in a charter of [[James I of Aragon|James I]] granted to Pisa in 1233. It affirms that the meeting was unplanned and apparently arranged by God.&lt;ref&gt;It records the Providential meeting of Pisans and Catalans as ''divino ducatu in portu Sancti Felicis prope Gerundam apud Barcinonam ''[''Pisanorum exercitus'']'' applicuisset'' (Busch, 207).&lt;/ref&gt; Some scholars have expressed doubt about the lack of preparation, citing the Catalans' rapid response to the presence of the Pisans as evidence of some previous contact.&lt;ref&gt;Busch, 208 n4. Enrica Salvatori, [http://www.stm.unipi.it/clioh/tabs/libri/6/02-salvatori_13-32.pdf &quot;Pisa in the Middle Ages: the Dream and the Reality of an Empire&quot;], ''Empires Ancient and Modern'', 19, likewise believes the familiarity of the author of the ''Liber maiolichinus'' with Catalonian and Occitanian geography points to longer and earlier Pisan contacts.&lt;/ref&gt; The attribution of the meeting to [[Divine Providence|Providence]] alone may have been concocted to add an &quot;aura of sacredness&quot; to the alliance and the crusade.&lt;ref name=busch208/&gt;

The treaty, or what survives of it, does not refer to military cooperation or a venture against Majorca; perhaps that agreement was oral, or perhaps its record has been lost, but a Crusade was planned for 1114. The chief goal was the freeing of Christian captives and the suppression of Muslim piracy.&lt;ref&gt;Doxey, 13. The memory of Sigurd's abundant spoils may have played a secondary rôle.&lt;/ref&gt; Most of the Pisan fleet returned to Pisa, but some ships damaged by the storm remained to be repaired and some men remained behind to construct [[siege engines]].&lt;ref name=busch210&gt;Busch, 210. During their winter in Catalonia, many Pisan knights reportedly wandered abroad into southern France (''Provintia'', [[Provence]], to the author of the ''Liber'') as far as [[Nîmes]] and Arles.&lt;/ref&gt; In the spring of 1114 a new fleet of eighty ships arrived from Pisa, following the French coast, briefly staying at [[Marseille]].&lt;ref&gt;Many of the Pisans killed were buried at the [[Abbey of Saint Victor, Marseille|Abbey of Saint Victor]] in Marseille on the return trip, cf. Salvatori, 19.&lt;/ref&gt;

The fleet brought with it [[Boso of Sant'Anastasia|Cardinal Bosone]], an envoy from Paschal II, who vigorously supported the expedition, authorising it in a [[Papal bull|bull]] as early as 1113.&lt;ref name=bishko/&gt; Paschal had also granted the Pisans the ''Romana signa, sedis apostolicae vexillum'' (&quot;Roman standard, the flag of the apostolic see&quot;),&lt;ref&gt;This is almost certainly the ''vexillum sancti Petri'' (&quot;banner of Saint Peter&quot;) used by papal armies on other occasions. The pope also gave a processional cross to the Pisan archbishop, who gave it to a certain layman, Atho, to carry. Cf. [[Carl Erdmann]] (1977), ''The Origin of the Idea of Crusade'' (Princeton: Princeton University Press), 186, who points out that the banner of Saint Peter is not the basis for the later [[:File:Pisa-Stemma.png|white cross on a red field]] associated with Pisa.&lt;/ref&gt; and his appeals for the expedition had borne fruit. Besides the 300 ships of the Pisan contingent, there were 120 Catalan and Occitan vessels (plus a large army), contingents from the Italian cities of [[Florence]], [[Lucca]], [[Pistoia]], [[Rome]], [[Siena]], and [[Volterra]], and from Sardinia and Corsica under [[Saltaro of Torres|Saltaro]], the son of [[Constantine I of Logudoro]]. Among the Catalan princes there were Ramon Berenguer, [[Hug II of Empúries]], and [[Ramon Folc II of Cardona]].&lt;ref name=busch210n12&gt;Busch, 210 n12.&lt;/ref&gt; The most important lords of Occitania participated, with the exception of the [[Count of Toulouse]], [[Alfonso Jordan]]: [[William V of Montpellier]], with twenty ships; [[Aimeric II of Narbonne]], with twenty ships; and [[Raymond I of Baux]], with seven ships.&lt;ref name=busch210n12/&gt; [[Bernard Ato IV]], the chief of the [[Trencavel]] family, also participated.&lt;ref name=salvatori19&gt;Salvatori, 19.&lt;/ref&gt; Ramon Berenguer and his wife, [[Douce I of Provence|Douce]], borrowed 100 ''[[morabatins]]'' from the [[Ramon Guillem (Bishop of Barcelona)|Ramon Guillem]], the [[Bishop of Barcelona]], to finance the expedition.{{cn|date=November 2014}}

==Conquest and loss==
The combined Crusader fleet raided [[Ibiza]] in June, and destroyed its defences, since Ibiza lay between Majorca and the mainland and would have posed a continued threat during a siege. The ''Liber maiolichinus'' also records the taking of captives, who were trying to hide in ''careae'' (probably caves), on Formentera.&lt;ref name=doxey11&gt;Doxey, 11.&lt;/ref&gt; Ibiza was under Crusader control by August.&lt;ref name=salvatori19/&gt; The Crusaders invested [[Palma de Majorca]] in August 1114.&lt;ref name=busch211&gt;Busch, 211.&lt;/ref&gt; As the siege dragged on the counts of Barcelona and Empúries entered into peace negotiations with the Muslim ruler of Majorca, but the cardinal and [[Pietro Moriconi]], the [[Archbishop of Pisa]], interfered to put an end to the discussions. Probably the Catalan rulers, whose lands lay nearest the Balearics, expected an annual payment of ''[[parias]]'' (tribute) from the Muslims and the cessation of pirate raids in return for lifting the siege.&lt;ref name=busch211/&gt;

Muslim reinforcements, [[Almoravids]] from the Iberian port of [[Denia]], surprised a Pisan flotilla of six in the waters off Ibiza, with only two of the Pisan vessels making it to safety, which consisted of the remains of a fortress burned by the king of Norway a decade earlier.&lt;ref name=doxey11/&gt; In April 1115 the city capitulated and its entire population was enslaved. This victory was followed by the capture of most of the Balearics' major settlements and the freeing of most captive Christians on the islands. The independent Muslim ''taifa'' ruler was taken back to Pisa a captive.&lt;ref&gt;Giuseppe Scalia (1980), &quot;Contributi pisani alla lotta anti-islamica nel Mediterraneo centro-occidentale durante il secolo XI e nei prime deceni del XII&quot;, ''Anuario de estudios medievales'', '''10''', 138.&lt;/ref&gt; The greatest victory, however, was the annihilation of Majorcan piracy.{{cn|date=November 2014}}

The conquest of the Balearics lasted no more than a few months. In 1116 they were reconquered by the Almoravids of peninsular Iberia.&lt;ref name=busch211/&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite journal |title=Pisa, Catalonia, and Muslim Pirates: Intercultural Exchanges in the Balearic Crusade of 1113–1115 |first=Matthew E. |last=Parker |pages=77–100 |journal=Viator |volume=45 |issue=2 |year=2014}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:1113-15 Balearic Islands expedition}}

[[Category:1113–15 Balearic Islands expedition| ]]
[[Category:1110s conflicts]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1113]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1114]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1115]]</text>
      <sha1>5dgx7g1038po1gj2xzrnei4ttvdb9e5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
