<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>11th Division (Spain)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>46185876</id>
    <revision>
      <id>715050885</id>
      <parentid>670745240</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-04-13T12:13:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>LilHelpa</username>
        <id>8024439</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Women in the 11th Division */General fixes and [[WP:AWB/T|Typo fixing]], replaced: to became →  to become using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23688">{{About|the Spanish Republican military unit|other formations|11th Division (disambiguation)}}
{{Infobox military unit
|unit_name=11th Division&lt;br&gt;''11ª División''
|image=Flag of the 11 Division Spanish Popular Army.svg
|caption=Flag of the 11th Division of the People's Republican Army
|dates=1937–1939
|country=[[Image:Flag of Spain 1931 1939.svg|25px]] [[Spain]]
|allegiance=
|branch= [[Spanish Republican Army]]
|type=[[Infantry]] [[Division (military)|division]]
|role=Home Defence
|size= Three [[mixed brigade]]s: &lt;br&gt;[[1st Mixed Brigade|1st]], [[9th Mixed Brigade|9th]] and [[100st Mixed Brigade|100st]]
|command_structure=[[V Army Corps (Spain)|V Army Corps]] (July 1937 - February 1939)
|garrison=
|ceremonial_chief=
|colonel_of_the_regiment=
|nickname=''División Líster''
|patron=
|motto=
|colors=
|decorations=[[File:Laureada de Madrid-fondo blanco.png|30px]][[Laureate Plate of Madrid]] 
|battle_honours=
|march=
|mascot=
|battles=[[Spanish Civil War]]
|notable_commanders=[[Enrique Lister]]
}}
[[File:Кольцов Энрике Листер.JPG|thumb|300px|Enrique Líster with Soviet journalist [[Mikhail Koltsov]].]]
[[File:Spain Ebro river in Tortosa.JPG|thumb|300px|Metal bridge at [[Tortosa]] where the 11th Division stopped the Fascist Italian troops of the ''[[Corpo Truppe Volontarie]]''.]]
The '''11th Division''' ({{lang-es|11ª División}})&lt;ref name=&quot;CE&quot;&gt;Carlos Engel, ''Historia de las Brigadas Mixtas del E. P. de la República'', 1999&lt;/ref&gt; was a [[Division (military)|division]] of the [[Spanish Republican Army]] in the [[Spanish Civil War]]. It was formed in January 1937 in [[Madrid]] beginning with the [[1st Mixed Brigade]] which in turn had originated in the [[Fifth Regiment]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.sbhac.net/Republica/Fuerzas/EPR/EprL/BM001.htm SBHAC - 1a Brigada Mixta]&lt;/ref&gt;

Nicknamed ''División Líster'', it would become one of the elite divisions, as well as one of the most battle-hardened formations, of the [[Spanish Republican Armed Forces]].

==History==

===Origins: The 'C Division'===
Although the 11th Division was officially established on 24 January 1937, its origin lies in the [[C Division]] of the Republican Army that was created owing to circumstances by joining a number of newly constituted [[mixed brigades]] in order to send them to the [[Jarama River]] area in order to respond to the rebel attacks towards the [[Valencia]] road. However, after much effort, [[Enrique Líster]]'s men were successful in repelling the rebel offensive at the [[Battle of Jarama]],&lt;ref&gt;[[Hugh Thomas (writer)|Hugh Thomas]] (1976). ''Historia de la Guerra Civil Española.'' París: Ruedo Ibérico. p. 638&lt;/ref&gt; where the combats in the ''El Pingarrón'' area caused a high number of casualties in loyalist ranks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Engel&quot;&gt;Carlos Engel (1999); p. 10&lt;/ref&gt; Finally, towards the end of February the rebel advance in the Jarama banks was halted and fixed until the end of the Civil War. After the victory and, as a result of the reorganization of the Spanish Republican Armed forces, the 'C Division' firmly became the 11th Division.

===Battles of Guadalajara and Brunete===
Following the bloodbath at the Jarama the 11th Division was barely being reorganized when it was sent to [[Guadalajara, Castile-La Mancha|Guadalajara]] where on 8 March the [[Fascist Italian]] [[Corpo Truppe Volontarie]] had launched an offensive. The purpose of the Italians was to encircle the loyalists in a pocket around [[Madrid]] and the ensuing battle would be known as [[Battle of Guadalajara]]. In this conflict the 11th Division was formed by the [[9th Mixed Brigade|1st Bis Mixed Brigade]], the 1st Mobile Shock Brigade ''(1.ª Brigada Móvil de Choque)'' led by [[Valentín González]] ''&quot;El Campesino&quot;'' —which would later be known as the [[10th Mixed Brigade]]— as well as the [[XI International Brigade]] (&quot;Thälmann Brigade&quot;) and the [[XII International Brigade]] (&quot;Garibaldi Brigade&quot;).&lt;ref&gt;[[Ramón Salas Larrazábal|Salas Larrazábal]] (2001); pág. 876&lt;/ref&gt; The 11th Division, together with the [[12th Division (Spain)|12th]] and the [[14th Division (Spain)|14th]] divisions —the latter under [[Cipriano Mera]]—, was put under the newly established [[IV Army Corps (Spain)|IV Army Corps]] under the command of [[Enrique Jurado Barrio]].&lt;ref&gt;Hugh Thomas (1976); p. 648&lt;/ref&gt; 
After Guadalajara the 11th Division took part in the [[Battle of Brunete]] in the summer 1937. There Líster and his division resisted at the [[Brunete]] graveyard until 25 July, but ended up losing the disputed town in the face of the heavy Francoist assaults.&lt;ref name=&quot;Thomas771&quot;&gt;Hugh Thomas (1976); p. 771&lt;/ref&gt;

===Interventions in Aragon===
The independence with which the [[Regional Defence Council of Aragon]] acted had always been an irritant for the republican authorities. Thus, after having re-established its control over [[Catalonia]], the republican government, backed by its [[Izquierda Republicana|republican]], socialist and communist sectors, was determined to disband this Aragonese entity.&lt;ref Name=&quot;Thomas780&quot;&gt;Hugh Thomas, (1976). ''Historia de la Guerra Civil Española.'' Barcelona: Círculo de Lectores. ISBN 84-226-0873-1.; p. 780-781&lt;/ref&gt; Finally on 4 August 1937 [[Indalecio Prieto]], the National Defense Minister, ordered the [[Spanish Republican Army]] to intervene and the 11th Division was sent to [[Aragon]], officially disbanding the Aragon Council (''Consejo de Aragón'') on 10 August.&lt;ref Name=&quot;Gacetarepublica&quot;&gt;[http://www.boe.es/datos/pdfs/BOE/1937/223/B00573-00573.pdf Gaceta de la República: Diario Oficial núm. 223, (11 August 1937)]&lt;/ref&gt; [[Joaquín Ascaso]] and various anarchist members of the Regional Defence Council were arrested under various charges, such as jewel smuggling. A total of about 700 anarchists ended up being arrested in those days in Aragon.&lt;ref Name=&quot;Thomas780&quot;/&gt; The fact that the 11th Division was chosen for this operation demonstrated the high regard in which it was held by the Republican government.&lt;ref&gt;Enrique Líster Forján,  (1966). ''Nuestra guerra. Memorias de un luchador.'' p. 152&lt;/ref&gt;

Once in Aragon the division participated in the [[Zaragoza Offensive]] on 24 August which eventually gave way to the difficult [[Battle of Belchite (1937)|Battle of Belchite]]. The 11th Division fought these battles together with the [[35th Division (Spain)|35th International]] led by [[Karol Świerczewski|General &quot;Walter&quot;]] and again with the [[46th Division (Spain)|46th Division]] led by &quot;[[El Campesino]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Hugh Thomas (1976); p. 779 (Although there are authors claiming that the 46th Division did not intervene)&lt;/ref&gt; The 11th Division was then under the [[V Army Corps (Spain)|V Army Corps]] led by ''[[Juan Guilloto León|Modesto]]''. In October the division was again sent to an operation against the rebels in [[Zaragoza]] through [[Fuentes de Ebro]], but despite the forty new [[BT tank|BT-5 tanks]] deployed by Lister's unit, the battle ended in disaster owing to the intense rains and the muddy terrain, so that only 28 tanks came back safely to Republican lines. After this turn of events the campaign stabilized and the 11th Division remained in Aragon through the Autumn of 1937, being later sent to fight the [[Battle of Teruel]].&lt;ref&gt;Hugh Thomas (1976); p.784&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Teruel]] the 11th Division fought together with the [[25th Division (Spain)|25th Division]] led by [[Miguel García Vivancos|García Vivancos]] in the ''Columna Norte'', of the [[XXII Army Corps (Spain)|XXII Army Corps]] led by Lieutenant Colonel [[Juan Ibarrola Orueta|Ibarrola]].&lt;ref&gt;de Miguel; Sánchez (2006); pp. 308-327&lt;/ref&gt; Here the 11th was given the mission to break the front and be at the vanguard of the attack, which the division did on 15 December under heavy snow.&lt;ref name=&quot;p.849&quot;&gt;Hugh Thomas (1976); p. 849&lt;/ref&gt; Before the evening the city was surrounded by Republican and Lister went to  the strategic ''La Muela'' hill.&lt;ref name=&quot;p.849&quot; /&gt; The 11th Division suffered many casualties, as all units involved in the ensuing defence of the city against the fierce rebel counterattacks.&lt;ref&gt;[[Enrique Líster Forján]] (1966); p. 301&lt;/ref&gt; When the defence became impossible, Líster was ordered to withdraw his troops, following which he was criticized by ''[[Valentín González|El Campesino]]'', who was trapped with the [[46th Division (Spain)|46th Division]] in the city. But later both Líster and ''[[Juan Guilloto León|Modesto]]'', leader of the [[V Army Corps (Spain)|V Army Corps]], would in turn accuse ''El Campesino'' of having fled Teruel leaving his men behind.&lt;ref&gt;Hugh Thomas (1976); p. 853&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the bloodbath at Teruel the 11th Division was sent to the [[rearguard]] in order to recover from the heavy losses it had suffered. But there would be no respite for the much-battered Republicans, for right after reconquering Teruel the [[rebel faction]] launched the massive [[Aragon Offensive]] that caught all republican units that were in [[Aragon]] by surprise and routed the [[Eastern Army (Spain)|Eastern Army]] ''(Ejército del Este)''. In the middle of the hasty and chaotic withdrawal the 11th Division troops were able, however, to contain the Fascist Italian ''[[Corpo Truppe Volontarie]]'' troops when these arrived to the lower course of the [[Ebro]] at the beginning of April 1938. The resistance put up by the 11th Division would be decisive to briefly stop their advance in the Ebro,&lt;ref&gt;Hugh Thomas (1976); p. 862&lt;/ref&gt; but the division would remain henceforward locked in Catalonia and isolated from the remaining Republican territory when the rebel troops led by General [[Antonio Aranda Mata|Aranda]] reached the [[Mediterranean Sea]] on 3 April, dividing the Spanish Republic in two.&lt;ref&gt;Hugh Thomas (1976); p. 861&lt;/ref&gt;

===Last battles and end of the division===
{{see also|Group of Eastern Region Armies|Battle of the Ebro}}
[[File:Serradepandols20.JPG|thumb|270px|View of the [[Pandols Range]], defended by the 11th Division during the [[Battle of the Ebro]].]]
[[File:Monument-cota705.JPG|thumb|270px|Monument to those who died defending the Spanish Republic on the much disputed Hill 705 of the Pandols Range where many men of the 11th Division lost their lives.]]

====Battle of the Ebro====
On 25 July 1938 in the early morning, at the onset of the [[Battle of the Ebro]], the 11th Division crossed the [[Ebro River]] between [[Ginestar]] and [[Benifallet]]. It was one of the favourite units of ''[[Juan Guilloto León|Modesto]]'', Chief Commander of the [[Ebro Army]], and had been awarded the honor and responsibility of being the spearhead of the whole V Republican Army Corps during the attack. However, the 11th Division would be also the first unit that was seen by the troops of the rebel army and thus had to endure the fiercest and most scathing attacks.&lt;ref&gt;[[Jorge Martínez Reverte]], ''La batalla del Ebro''&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the difficulties the division fulfilled all its military targets and launched an attack against [[Móra d'Ebre]], the most important town in the [[Ribera d'Ebre]] ''[[comarca]]''.

But Móra d'Ebre housed a large number of enemy troops and the 11th Division, not being able to dislodge them, chose to encircle the town leaving its defenders isolated. After conquering the [[bridgehead]], the 11th Division advanced towards the mountains in order to link with the troops of the [[46th Division (Spain)|46th Division]] in order to control the strategic heights of the [[Serra de Pandols|Pandols]] and [[Serra de Cavalls|Cavalls]] ranges above the town of [[Gandesa]]. In the early morning hours of 26 July the Republican troops reached their objectives, but after the long march and the ascension of the rocky ranges the men of the 11th Division were physically exhausted. Thus the division did not launch the planned surprise attack against Gandesa and was not able to continue the advance southwards in order to reach [[Bot, Tarragona|Bot]] and [[Batea, Tarragona|Batea]].

On 2 August the Republican advance had run out of steam and the 11th Division occupied the [[Pandols Range]],&lt;ref&gt;Carlos Engel (1999); p. 24&lt;/ref&gt; holding its position against the [[84th Division (Francoist Army)|84th Division]] of the rebel faction&lt;ref name=&quot;Besolí&quot;&gt;Andreu Besolí ''et al'' (2005); p. 164-165&lt;/ref&gt; and entrenching itself in the rocky hills awaiting the enemy counterattack. The Francoist counterattack was fierce and intense. For a whole week the Republican division was subjected to a continuous hail of artillery and airborne projectiles, while its men repelled numerous attacks of the enemy infantry,&lt;ref name=&quot;Laureada&quot; /&gt; especially from the [[IV Navarra Division]] which was made up of three [[Spanish Legion]] units.&lt;ref name=&quot;Besolí&quot;/&gt; 
Despite the bloodbath in the veteran Republican ranks ''[[Juan Guilloto León|Modesto's]]'' insisted in keeping the Pandols position and ordered the integration of all the artillery of the V Corps in the 11th Division.&lt;ref name=&quot;Besolí&quot;/&gt; However, after numerous waves of continuous attacks the Francoist troops succeeded in wrestling the hills from the Republican division on 15 August —including the highly disputed Hill 705, which changed hands no less than eight times on 14 August.&lt;ref&gt;Andreu Besolí ''et al'' (2005); p. 166-167&lt;/ref&gt; Owing to the high number of casualties caused by enemy artillery and [[close combat]] in the highest points of the range, the battered 11th Division units were relieved and partially replaced by the [[35th Division (Spain)|35th Division]].&lt;ref&gt;Andreu Besolí ''et al'' (2005); pág. 167&lt;/ref&gt; Following its valiant and resilient behaviour and the losses it had to bear, the 11th Division was awarded the [[Laureate Plate of Madrid]], but the Spanish Republic had lost a great number of irreplaceable battle-hardened veterans.&lt;ref name=Laureada&gt;Carlos Engel, p.136&lt;/ref&gt;

At the beginning of September the division returned to its former positions in the Pandols Range, where the Francoist armies would give no respite, so that again it fought fierce battles against the rebel troops for a period of two months,&lt;ref name=&quot;p.136&quot;&gt;Carlos Engel (1999); p. 136&lt;/ref&gt; losing some key positions and continuing to suffer a high number of casualties. Finally a massive Francoist [[counteroffensive]] began at the end of October and the much crushed 11th Division could no longer bear the avalanche of rebel attacks. The rebel counteroffensive marked the end of the [[Battle of the Ebro]] and on 5 November what remained of the 11th Division withdrew, crossing again the Ebro River at [[Benifallet]].&lt;ref name=&quot;p.136&quot; /&gt;

==== Catalonia Campaign ====
[[File:GCE frente en feb 1939.svg|thumb|270px|Last area under Republican control after the [[Fall of Catalonia]] in February 1939. The French authorities would not allow the 11th Division to be transferred to this area after having entered France.]]
Following the Battle of the Ebro debacle the 11th Division retreated to the rearguard in order to recover and reorganize, being temporarily made part of the [[Military reserve|Republican Military Reserve]]. But not long thereafter, on 23 December, the rebel faction launched its final [[Catalonia Offensive]] and the 11th Division —which had been in need of a longer period of rest— was urgently deployed in the [[Battle of the Segre|Segre Front]], together with the remainder of the [[V Army Corps (Spain)|V Army Corps]] commanded by [[Enrique Lister]], in order to close the gaps in the front where inexperienced groups of the [[Eastern Army (Spain)|Eastern Army]] had fled in panic before the fierce rebel assault, abandoning the lines they were defending at the [[Segre River]].&lt;ref&gt;Hugh Thomas (1976); p. 933&lt;/ref&gt; Enrique Lister set up his general headquarters at [[Castelldans]]&lt;ref name=&quot;p.934&quot;&gt;Hugh Thomas (1976); p. 934&lt;/ref&gt; and with his competent, battle-hardenend troops he was able to contain the Francoist onslaught for almost two weeks in the area near [[Borges Blanques]]. Finally on 3 January 1939 the rebels launched a powerful attack against Lister's divisions with armoured vehicles in the vanguard, so that even the men 11th Division became overwhelmed and had to abandon their lines of defence and the much devastated town of Borges Blanques fell to the Fascist Italian troops of the [[Corpo Truppe Volontarie]] (CTV).&lt;ref name=&quot;p.934&quot; /&gt;
Later some of the Republican forces counterattacked and made some prisoners among the Italian Fascists, which were executed after having been interrogated.&lt;ref&gt;Hugh Thomas (1976); p. 935&lt;/ref&gt; But in the face of the vehement Francoist offensive all Republican units had to retreat and left the area of the Segre Front, gradually withdrawing in a northeastern direction.

Thus the [[Ebro Army]] covered the massive Republican retreat along the Mediterranean coastline until reaching [[Barcelona]], where there had been plans to organize a strong resistance against the Fascist onslaught on the lines of the [[Defence of Madrid]] in 1936.&lt;ref&gt;Hugh Thomas (1976); p. 936&lt;/ref&gt; But the option proved unrealistic, for the city's population was hungry and demoralized and the troops lacked arms and ammunition, hence the only option open for the exhausted Republican divisions of the elite V Corps was to abandon Barcelona to its fate and retreat towards the French border.&lt;ref&gt;[[Ramón Salas Larrazabal|Salas Larrazabal]] (2001); pp. 2213-2226&lt;/ref&gt; By the beginning of February what remained of the units of the 11th Division arrived to the northern zone of [[Catalonia]] where, together with other retreating Republican units, they tried to establish a [[Main Line of Resistance|defensive line]] along the lower course of the [[Tordera River]] to halt the powerful advance of the rebel armies, but this effort quickly proved unsuccessful in the face of scathing enemy attacks.&lt;ref name=&quot;p.946&quot;&gt;Hugh Thomas (1976); pág. 946&lt;/ref&gt;

This last-ditch attempt had been part of a grand strategy of the Spanish Republic to resist the Francoist offensives until the deemed onset of a [[World War II|larger European War]] between the [[Axis powers|Fascist powers]] and the [[Allies of World War II|western democracies]], in order to link the Spanish conflict with the wider European one. Thus [[Juan Modesto|''Modesto'']] and [[Enrique Líster|Líster]] saw the retreat to [[France]] of the remainder of the Ebro Army as part of a tactical evacuation, with the aim to regroup these units with the remaining units of the last area under Republican control in order to continue the resistance.&lt;ref&gt;[[Ramón Salas Larrazabal|Salas Larrazábal]] (2001); p. 2237&lt;/ref&gt; 
The French government, however, would not allow the Republican units that crossed the border to be transferred to the remaining Spanish Republican territory, for all the veteran survivors of the 11th Division, together with all Republican military, were disarmed and swiftly interned in [[Concentration camps in France|French concentration camps]] right after crossing its border. Thus the 11th Division, along with all units of the V Army Corps, disappeared.&lt;ref name=&quot;p.943&quot;&gt;Hugh Thomas (1976); p. 943&lt;/ref&gt;

Before its demise the 11th Division had briefly resisted, however, in the line of the [[Ter River]] on 5 February, and after crossing the [[Muga River]] on 8 February. Finally, in the early morning of 9 February the last units of the once mighty [[Ebro Army]] under ''Modesto'' crossed the border into France and the very next day all Spanish border posts fell into Francoist hands.&lt;ref name=&quot;p.943&quot;/&gt;

=== Women in the 11th Division ===
Some women from militia background managed to be promoted to commanding positions in the 11th Division. Foremost among them was Encarnación Hernández Luna, born in [[Beneixama]] near [[Valencia]]. At the time of the first combats of the Civil War she joined the militias of the [[Fifth Regiment]], in a machine gun unit which subsequently was integrated into the [[1st Mixed Brigade]]. She became a lieutenant on 1 January 1937 and a captain on 15 June of the same year. She went on to become a commander in the [[Battle of the Ebro]] in 1938. 
She had married Alberto Sánchez Méndez, a [[Cuba]]n member of the [[International Brigades]], who died in the [[Battle of Brunete]] of wounds sustained in combat, while Encarnación held fast to the position with her machine gun. [[Pablo Neruda]] composed a poem to the couple. After the end of the Civil War Encarnación went with her father to exile in France and then the USSR. She died in [[Quebec]] in 2004.&lt;ref&gt;[http://cubanosenlaguerracivil.blogspot.com/2007/04/alberto-sanchez-mendez-este-voluntario.html Cubanos en la guerra civil;  Alberto Sánchez Méndez]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Order of Battle==
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Date !! Army Corps!! Mixed Brigades!! Battlefront
|-
| February 1937 || [[III Army Corps (Spain)|III Army Corps]] || [[1st Mixed Brigade|1st]], [[9th Mixed Brigade|1st Bis]], [[23rd Mixed Brigade|23rd]], [[66th Mixed Brigade|66th]] and [[70th Mixed Brigade|70th]]&lt;ref name=11Div&gt;Carlos Engel. (1999). ''Historia de las Brigadas Mixtas del Ejército Popular de la República.'' Madrid: Almena. ISBN 8492264470 p. 288&lt;/ref&gt; || [[Battle of Jarama|Jarama]]
|-
| March 1937 || [[IV Army Corps (Spain)|IV Army Corps]] || [[9th Mixed Brigade|1st Bis]], [[10th Mixed Brigade|10th]], [[XI International Brigade|XI]] and [[XII International Brigade|XII]] || [[Battle of Guadalajara|Guadalajara]]
|-
| 2 April 1937 || [[V Army Corps (Spain)|V Army Corps]] || [[1st Mixed Brigade|1st]], [[48th Mixed Brigade|48th]] and [[71st Mixed Brigade|71st]] || [[Madrid Front|Madrid]]
|-
| 27 April 1937 || [[V Army Corps (Spain)|V Army Corps]] || [[1st Mixed Brigade|1st]], [[9th Mixed Brigade|9th]] and [[XII International Brigade|XII]]&lt;ref name=&quot;11Div&quot;/&gt; || [[Madrid Front|Madrid]]
|-
| 4 July 1937 || [[V Army Corps (Spain)|V Army Corps]] || [[1st Mixed Brigade|1st]], [[9th Mixed Brigade|9th]] and [[100th Mixed Brigade|100th]] || [[Battle of Brunete|Brunete]]
|-
| 15 December 1937 || [[XXII Army Corps (Spain)|XXII Army Corps]]&lt;ref name=&quot;11Div&quot;/&gt; || [[1st Mixed Brigade|1st]], [[9th Mixed Brigade|9th]] and [[100th Mixed Brigade|100th]] || [[Battle of Teruel|Teruel]]
|-
| 13 March 1938&lt;ref name=&quot;11Div&quot;/&gt; || [[V Army Corps (Spain)|V Army Corps]] || [[1st Mixed Brigade|1st]], [[9th Mixed Brigade|9th]] and [[100th Mixed Brigade|100th]]&lt;ref name=&quot;11Div&quot;/&gt; || [[Military reserve force|Reserve]]
|-
| December 1938 || [[V Army Corps (Spain)|V Army Corps]] || [[1st Mixed Brigade|1st]], [[9th Mixed Brigade|9th]] and [[100th Mixed Brigade|100th]] || [[Battle of the Segre|Segre]]
|}

== Commanders ==
*'''Commanders in Chief'''
** [[Enrique Lister]]
** [[Joaquín Rodríguez López]]
*'''Commissars'''
** [[Santiago Álvarez Gómez]]
** [[José Fusimaña Fábregas]]
*'''Chief of Staff Leaders'''
** [[Julio Suárez-Llanos Adiansens]]
** [[Manuel López Iglesias]]
** [[Fernando Pozo Oliver]] July 1938
** [[Jesús Sáiz Barberá]]

==See also==
*[[Fifth Regiment]]
*[[Mixed Brigades]]

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==External links==
*[http://www.sbhac.net/Republica/Fuerzas/EPR/EPR.htm SBHAC - El Ejército Popular]
*[http://www.1936laserenalosmonegros.es/organizacionr.asp Organización militar republicana - 1936 - La Guerra Civil]
*[http://www.parquelineal.es/guerracivil/ejercito_popular_republicano.php El Ejército Popular Republicano (EPR)]
{{Divisions of the Spanish Republic}}

[[Category:Military units and formations established in 1937]]
[[Category:Military units and formations disestablished in 1939]]
[[Category:Divisions of Spain]]
[[Category:Spanish Civil War]]
[[Category:Military history of Spain]]
[[Category:Armed Forces of the Second Spanish Republic]]</text>
      <sha1>t6x71mkpd8jhhguzglfbem01yfeve69</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
