<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>133d Operations Group</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>23943623</id>
    <revision>
      <id>737257007</id>
      <parentid>728539796</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-01T16:57:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Chris the speller</username>
        <id>525927</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>cap, punct using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="36283">{{Use American English|date=July 2016}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2011}}
{{Infobox military unit
|unit_name= 133d Operations Group
|image= [[File:110228-F-3188G-115-C-130H3.jpg|290px]]
|caption=133d Operations Group C-130H
|dates= 1943–1945; 1947–1952; 1952–present
|country={{flag|United States|23px}}
|allegiance=
|branch= [[File:US-AirNationalGuard-2007Emblem.svg|25px]]&amp;nbsp; [[Air National Guard]]
|type=
|role=[[Airlift]]
|size=
|command_structure=
|current_commander=
|garrison=
|ceremonial_chief=
|colonel_of_the_regiment=
|nickname=
|patron=Splendentes in Defensione [[Latin]] Splendid in Defense
|motto=
|colors=
|march=
|mascot=
|battles=[[European Theater of Operations]]
|notable_commanders= 
|anniversaries=
|decorations=[[Distinguished Unit Citation]]&lt;br/&gt; [[Belgian Fourragere]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Air Force Outstanding Unit Award]]
|battle_honours=
&lt;!-- Commanders --&gt;
| commander1 =Col Robert Hagel&lt;ref name=MNwebsite&gt;As of 10 October 2014.  {{cite web |url= http://www.minnesotanationalguard.org/units/unit_template.php?unit=133OG |last1=|first1=|title=133rd Operations Group|date=10 October 2014|publisher=Minnesota National Guard|deadurl=no |accessdate=10 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| commander1_label =&lt;!-- default current commander --&gt;
| commander2 =Brig Gen Edwin S. Chickering&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.arlingtoncemetery.net/eschickering.htm |last1=Patterson|first1=Michael Robert|title=Edwin S. Chickering, Brigadier General, United States Air Force|date=20 June 2004|publisher=Arlington National Cemetery|deadurl=no |accessdate=10 June 2015}} (commander from November 1944 until inactivation)&lt;/ref&gt;
| commander2_label =Notable commander
&lt;!-- Insignia --&gt;
|identification_symbol=[[File:133d Airlift Wing.png|150px]]
|identification_symbol_label=133d Operations Group emblem &lt;small&gt;(Approved 9 July 1954)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name=Maurer367FG&gt;Maurer, ''Combat Units'', pp. 252–254&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref group=note&gt;The group uses the wing emblem with the group designation on the scroll. Air Force Instruction 84–105, Organizational Lineage, Honors and Heraldry, 19 March 2013, para 3.3.3.&lt;/ref&gt;
|identification_symbol_2=
|identification_symbol_2_label=
}}

The '''133rd Operations Group''' is the flying component of the [[Minnesota Air National Guard]]'s [[133d Airlift Wing]], stationed at [[Minneapolis–Saint Paul Joint Air Reserve Station]], Minnesota. If activated to federal service, the group is gained by [[Air Mobility Command]] of the [[United States Air Force]].

The [[group (military aviation unit)|group]] was first activated as the '''367th Fighter Group''', an [[Army Air Forces]] unit.  The group trained in the western United States with [[Bell P-39 Airacobra]]s.  The 367th moved to England in the spring of 1944, where it became part of [[IX Fighter Command]] (later XIX Tactical Air Command) and converted to [[Lockheed P-38 Lightning]]s.  The group engaged in combat with Lightnings, and later with [[Republic P-47 Thunderbolt]]s, in the [[European Theater of Operations]] until [[VE Day]], earning two [[Distinguished Unit Citation]]s and the [[Belgian Fourragere]] for its actions.  It returned to the United States in the fall of 1945 and was inactivated on 7 November 1945.

In May 1946, the group was allotted to the [[National Guard (United States)|National Guard]] and renumbered as the '''133d Fighter Group'''.&lt;ref group=note&gt;United States National Guard units are traditionally numbered between 101 and 300.&lt;/ref&gt;  It trained with [[North American P-51 Mustang]]s.  In 1951 it was mobilized for the [[Korean War]] and served in an [[air defense]] role until inactivating in February 1952 in a reorganization of [[Air Defense Command]].

The group was returned to the [[Minnesota Air National Guard]] in December 1952.  It was an [[interceptor aircraft|air defense fighter]] unit until 1960, when it converted to the [[Boeing C-97 Stratofreighter]] and the [[airlift]] mission.  It was called to active duty during the [[Berlin Crisis of 1961]].  The 133d replaced its C-97s with [[Lockheed C-130 Hercules]] aircraft in 1971.  It was inactivated in early 1975, when its component units were assigned directly to its parent [[133d Tactical Airlift Wing]].  It was reactivated in 1994 and resumed its role as the operational component of the 133d Wing.

==Mission==
The [[group (military aviation unit)|group]] commands units that support federal and state requirements for the airlift of troops, cargo, and medical patients anywhere in the world. It performs missions tasked by other headquarters within its capabilities. It monitors standardization of all flying and support unit operating procedures and insures units maintain an environment conducive to safe training activities.&lt;ref name=MNwebsite/&gt;

==History==

===World War II===

====Training in the United States====
[[File:Airacobra Bell P-39D (16114458896).jpg|thumb|P-39D as used by the group for training]]
The 367th Fighter Group was first activated at [[Hamilton Field, California|Hamilton Field]], California on 15 July 1943 with the [[392d Fighter Squadron|392d]], [[393d Fighter Squadron|393d]] and [[394th Fighter Squadron]]s as its initial components.&lt;ref name=Maurer367FG/&gt;&lt;ref name=Maurer392FS&gt;Maurer, ''Combat Squadrons'', pp. 481–482 (392d Fighter Squadron)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Maurer393FS&gt;Maurer, ''Combat Squadrons'', p. 483 (393d Fighter Squadron)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Maurer394FS&gt;Maurer, ''Combat Squadrons'', pp. 484–485 (394th Fighter Squadron)&lt;/ref&gt;  Several members of its initial [[en cadre|cadre]] were former [[Flying Tigers]] with prior combat experience.  It was not until late August, however, that the group received its first [[Bell P-39 Airacobra]].&lt;ref&gt;Groh, p. 12&lt;/ref&gt;  After building up its strength, the group moved in October to [[Santa Rosa Army Air Field]], California.&lt;ref name=Maurer367FG/&gt; In December the group moved to [[Oakland Municipal Airport]], while its squadrons moved to separate fields in northern California.&lt;ref group=note&gt;The 392d was at [[Sacramento Municipal Airport]], the 394th at [[Hayward Army Air Field]], while the 393d was with the group in Oakland.  Maurer, ''Combat Squadrons'', pp. 481–485.&lt;/ref&gt; The squadrons moved temporarily in sequence to [[Tonopah Army Air Field]], Nevada, where they performed [[dive bombing]] and [[strafing|gunnery]] training.   Training accidents with the Airacobra cost eight pilots their lives.  In January 1944, as it prepared for overseas movement, the 367th was beefed up with personnel from the [[328th Fighter Group|328th]] and [[368th Fighter Group]]s.&lt;ref name=Chickering78&gt;Chickering, p. 78&lt;/ref&gt;  The group staged through [[Camp Shanks]], and sailed for England aboard the {{SS|Duchess of Bedford}}.&lt;ref&gt;Groh, pp. 23–24&lt;/ref&gt;  The &quot;Drunken Duchess&quot;&lt;ref group=note&gt;Nicknamed for its unusual rolling motion in heavy weather.  Groh, p. 23.&lt;/ref&gt; docked at [[Greenock]], Scotland on 3 April and the group was transported by train to its airfield at [[RAF Stoney Cross]], England.&lt;ref name=Chickering78/&gt;

====P-38 transition and combat operations from England====
[[File:392d Fighter Squadron Lockheed P-38G-10-LO Lightning 42-12982.jpg|thumb|392d Fighter Squadron P-38&lt;ref group=note&gt;Aircraft is Lockheed P-38G-10-LO Lightning, serial 42-12982&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Having trained on single engine aircraft, the group's pilots were surprised to find [[Lockheed P-38 Lightning]]s sitting on Stoney Cross's dispersal pads.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chickering, p. 79&quot;&gt;Chickering, p. 79&lt;/ref&gt; Only four group pilots, members of the advance party, had any experience flying the Lightning.  These pilots had flown combat sorties with the [[55th Fighter Group]].&lt;ref&gt;Groh, p. 26&lt;/ref&gt; The change from single engine to twin engine aircraft required considerable retraining for both pilots and ground crew.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chickering, p. 79&quot;/&gt; Although some pilots entered combat with as little as eight hours of flying time on the P-38, in late April the group was reinforced by fourteen pilots who had trained on the Lightning in the States and were more experienced on the type.&lt;ref&gt;Groh, p. 31&lt;/ref&gt;  However, the lack of instrument training in the P-38 took its toll on the group as weather, not enemy action, caused the loss of pilots and airplanes.&lt;ref&gt;Groh, pp. 50–51&lt;/ref&gt;

On 9 May, the group flew its first combat mission, a fighter sweep over [[Alençon]].&lt;ref&gt;Groh. p. 32&lt;/ref&gt; For the remainer of the month, the group flew fighter sweeps, bomber escort and [[dive bombing]], missions and suffered its first combat losses.&lt;ref&gt;Groh. pp. 32–37&lt;/ref&gt;

On [[D-Day]] and the next three days the group flew nine missions maintaining air cover over shipping carrying invasion troops.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chickering, p. 79&quot;/&gt;  These missions continued for the next three days.  The 367th and other P-38 groups stationed in England were selected for these missions with the expectation that the distinctive silhouette of the Lightning would prevent potential friendly fire incidents by anti-aircraft gunners mistaking them for enemy fighters.&lt;ref&gt;Groh, p. 42&lt;/ref&gt;  Shortly after the Normandy invasion, on 12 June, the group was selected to test the ability of the P-38 to carry a 2,000 lb bomb under each wing.  The selected target was a [[railroad yard]], and results were mixed.  However, on this mission, the group scored its first air-to-air victory when Lts James Pinkerton and James Mason teamed up to shoot down a [[Messerschmitt Me 410]] flying near the assigned target.&lt;ref&gt;Groh, p. 43&lt;/ref&gt;

By mid June [[German Army (Wehrmacht)|German ground forces]] had withdrawn to defend a perimeter around [[Cherbourg]], a major port whose capture had become more important to the allies with the destruction of [[Mulberry harbour|Mulberry]] A, one of the artificial harbors constructed near the Normandy beachhead. An attack by [[VII Corps (United States)|VII Corps]] on 22 June was to be preceded by low level bombing and strafing attack by [[IX Fighter Command]]. Briefed by intelligence to expect a &quot;milk run&quot; The 367th flew at low altitude through what turned out to be a heavily defended area.  Within two to three minutes after beginning the attack the 394th Squadron lost five pilots. Seven group pilots were killed in action. Nearly all surviving group aircraft received battle damage and the 367th was out of action for several days.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chickering, p. 79&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Groh, p. 46&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Ninth Air Force]] moved its medium bomber forces to bases closer to the Continent in July, so they would be able to strike targets near the expanding front in France.  The [[387th Bombardment Group]] was moved to Stoney Cross, forcing the 367th to vacate their station and move the short distance to [[RAF Ibsley]].&lt;ref&gt;Groh, p. 52&lt;/ref&gt;   From Ibsley the group struck railroads, marshaling yards, and trains to prevent enemy reinforcements from reaching the front during [[Operation Cobra|the Allied breakthrough at Saint Lo in July 1944]].&lt;ref name=Maurer367FG/&gt;

====Operations on the European Continent====
Starting on 19 July the group's forward echelon crossed the [[English Channel]] to take up stations in [[Normandy]].&lt;ref&gt;Groh, p. 59&lt;/ref&gt;  Group [[headquarters]] and the 394th shared [[Beuzeville Airfield]] with the [[371st Fighter Group]], while the 392d Squadron was at [[Carentan Airfield]],&lt;ref name=Maurer392FS/&gt; and the 393d at [[Cricqueville Airfield]],&lt;ref name=Maurer393FS/&gt; advanced landing grounds made from [[pierced steel planking]].&lt;ref group=note&gt;Maurer gives the location of the 394th as [[Sainte-Mère-Église]], but this is the same airfield (A-6) called Beuzeville elsewhere. Maurer, ''Combat Squadrons'', pp. 484–485, Groh, p. 59.&lt;/ref&gt;   After the breakout of ground forces in the [[Saint-Lô]] area, the group concentrated on close air support of [[George S. Patton|General Patton's]] [[Third United States Army|Third Army]]. In late August, the group attacked [[7th Army (Wehrmacht)|German Seventh Army]] convoys which, to prevent being surrounded, were withdrawing eastward from the [[Falaise pocket]]. Five convoys and 100 [[Tiger I|Tiger Tanks]] were destroyed on one day.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chickering, p. 79&quot;/&gt;  By mid August the group and its squadrons were able to operate from a single base, [[Cricqueville Airfield]].&lt;ref&gt;Groh. p. 64&lt;/ref&gt;

On 22 August the group attacked three [[Luftwaffe]] airfields near [[Laon]]. The 392d Squadron dive bombed and destroyed two hangars on one airfield but were jumped by twelve [[Focke-Wulf Fw 190]]s as they completed their attack. Eighteen [[Messerschmitt Me 109]]s and FW 190s engaged the 393d Squadron as it reformed from its dive bomb run. After bombing its target, the 394th Squadron turned to reinforce the 392d. The group claimed fourteen enemy aircraft against a loss of one Lightning.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chickering, p. 79&quot;/&gt;

The 367th received a [[Distinguished Unit Citation]] when it returned to the Laon area three days later.  That day, the group attacked [[Luftwaffe]] airfields at [[Clastres]], [[Péronne, Somme|Péronne]] and [[Rosières-en-Haye]] through an intense [[anti-aircraft warfare|flak]] barrage.  The group then engaged more than thirty Focke-Wulf 190 fighters that had just taken off. Group claims were 25 enemy aircraft destroyed, one probably destroyed and 17 damaged against the loss of 6 group aircraft.&lt;ref group=note&gt;These claims were from an estimated 50 enemy aircraft engaged in the air and on the ground.  Chickering, p. 79&lt;/ref&gt;  Then, despite a low fuel supply, the group [[strafe]]d a train and convoy after leaving the scene of battle.  Captain Larry Blumer of the 393d Squadron destroyed five enemy aircraft becoming an [[flying ace|ace]] on one mission.  In the afternoon the 367th destroyed sixteen [[Junkers Ju 52]]s while on a long range fighter sweep of more than 800 miles to airfields in the [[Dijon]]-[[Bordeaux]] area.&lt;ref name=Maurer367FG/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Chickering, p. 79&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Groh, p. 72&lt;/ref&gt;

As Allied forces moved forward across France the group began leap-frogging to new bases.  In early September they relocated at [[Peray Airfield]] (A-44),&lt;ref name=Maurer392FS/&gt;&lt;ref name=Maurer393FS/&gt;&lt;ref name=Maurer394FS/&gt; but moved again a week later to [[Clastres Airfield]] (A-71).  From Clastres The 367th supported [[Operation Market-Garden]] by escorting troop carrier aircraft and attacking flak positions. For its attacks that fall, the group was cited in the Order of the Day by the Belgium Army.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chickering, p. 79&quot;/&gt;

In late October, as Ninth Air Force brought its medium bombers to bases in France, the 367th was bumped from its station for the second time by the 387th Bombardment Group, when it moved to [[Juvincourt Airfield]] (A-68), north of [[Reims]].&lt;ref name=Maurer367FG/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Maurer, ''Combat Units'', p. 274&lt;/ref&gt;  Juvincourt was a former Luftwaffe base with permanent facilities, in contrast to the advanced landing grounds where the group had been based since moving to France.&lt;ref&gt;Groh, pp. 98–99&lt;/ref&gt;  The group attacked German strong points to aid the Allied push against the [[Siegfried Line]] throughout the fall of 1944.&lt;ref name=Maurer367FG/&gt;

The German [[Ardennes Offensive]] occurred as the holidays approached. A planned move to a field in Belgium was canceled. On 18 December, the 393rd Squadron was sent a [[Forward Air Control]] team to [[Bastogne]] to assist the [[101st Airborne Division]], arriving just an hour before the Wehrmacht cut the last road access to Bastogne. When the weather finally broke, the team was able to direct flights of [[fighter-bomber]] aircraft attacking the Germans.  During the Battle of the Bulge, the 367th, after escorting C-47s on a resupply drop to encircled troops at Bastogne, conducted an armed reconnaissance of the [[Trier]] area. The 394th Squadron was engaged by FW 190s and a 40-minute air battle ensued in which the group claimed eight destroyed, two probably destroyed and nine damaged.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chickering, p. 79&quot;/&gt;

====Transition to the P-47 Thunderbolt====
[[File:P-47D CO 367th FG 1944-45.jpg|thumb|The P-47D of the Group commander, Col. Chickering, in 1945]]
Early in 1945 a desire to standardize the fighter-bombers in Ninth Air Force, the group transitioned into [[Republic P-47 Thunderbolt]]s. Pilots flew Lightings on combat missions while training at the same time with the Thunderbolt. The 393d Squadron was the first to fly a combat missions with the P-47s. Using the Thunderbolt the group was again cited in a Belgium Army Order of the Day, earning the [[Fourragère#Belgian fourragère|Belgian Fourragere]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Chickering, p. 79&quot;/&gt;

The 367th received a second Distinguished Unit Citation for action on 19 March 1945.  The group's target was the headquarters of [[Albert Kesselring|Field Marshal Kesselring]], the German Commander-ln-Chief, West,&lt;ref group=note&gt;Kesselring assumed command the day of the attack.  American intelligence believed [[Gerd von Rundstedt|Field Marshall von Rundstedt]] was still in command.  Groh, p. 136.&lt;/ref&gt; at Ziegenburg near [[Bad Nauheim]], Germany.  Aircraft of the leading 394th Squadron would attack at low level to achieve surprise, carrying a 1,000-pound bomb under each wing. The P-47s of the 392d Squadron would be similarly armed, but would [[dive bomber|dive bomb]] from a higher altitude.  The bombs were equipped with time-delay fuses intended to crack the concrete roofs of the bunker. The 393rd Squadron carried [[napalm]] intended to seep into the bunkers and burn what remained. The attack was scheduled for a time that intelligence reports indicated would find senior staff and commanders at lunch, the only time they would not be in the reinforced tunnels underneath the castle that housed the headquarters. The target was located in mountainous terrain well defended by antiaircraft artillery.  Moreover, to avoid alerting the Germans to the pending attack, photographic reconnaissance aircraft had avoided the area, so detailed target photography was not available.  The day of the attack the castle was concealed by ground haze which caused the 394th to stray off course at the last minute, preventing them from executing the attack as planned and reducing the element of surprise.&lt;ref&gt;Groh, p. 136&lt;/ref&gt; Although senior German officers reached the underground bunkers and survived the attack, the group reduced the military complex to ruins, disrupting communications and the flow of intelligence at a critical time.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chickering, p. 79&quot;/&gt;

The group struck tanks, trucks, flak positions, and other objectives in support of the assault across the [[Rhine]] late in March and the final allied operations in Germany.&lt;ref name=Maurer367FG/&gt;  It was commended by the commanding generals of [[XII Corps (United States)|XII Corps]] and the [[11th Armored Division (United States)|11th Armored Division]] for the close air support the group provided for their commands. On 10 April the group moved to [[Eschborn Airfield]] on the northwest side of [[Frankfurt]], Germany. The 367th flew its last combat mission, a defensive patrol, one year after entering combat on 8 May.&lt;ref&gt;Groh, p. 158&lt;/ref&gt;

All hostilities ceased [[Victory in Europe Day|the following day]], exactly one year after the group became operational. On 4 June the 367th led a flyby for [[Otto P. Weyland|General Weyland]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Chickering, p. 79&quot;/&gt;  On 1 July it was announced the 367th was to redeploy to the [[Asiatic-Pacific Theater|Pacific Theater of Operations]] after it was re-equipped with and trained with long range P-47Ns in preparation for [[Operation Downfall]], the invasion of Japan.&lt;ref name=Maurer367FG/&gt; The group moved to Camp Detroit in France then to a staging area near [[Marseille]]. Here it boarded two ships, the {{USS|General C. G. Morton }}, and the {{USNS|John Ericsson (T-AO-194)}}. When Japan surrendered, the ''Morton'' was diverted to [[Newport News]], Virginia while the ''Ericcson'' sailed for [[Staten Island]], New York.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chickering, p. 79&quot;/&gt;  Following leave for everyone, the few personnel that remained in the group after transfers and discharges reassembled at [[Seymour Johnson Field]], North Carolina on 2 November, and the 367th was inactivated there on 7 November 1945.&lt;ref name=Maurer367FG/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Chickering, p. 79&quot;/&gt;

====Statistical summary====
The 367th participated in seven campaigns. It had flown 14,175 combat sorties destroying 432 enemy aircraft, probably destroying another 28 and damaging 344.&lt;ref group=note&gt;Ninth Air Force included credit for aircraft destroyed in the air or on the ground and that practice is reflected in these totals.  The victories in the table include air-to-air victories only and reflect adjustments made to totals between 1945 and 1962.&lt;/ref&gt; They had also destroyed or damaged 384 locomotives, 4,672 motor vehicles and 8,288 railroad cars.&lt;ref name=&quot;Chickering, p. 79&quot;/&gt;

{{Col-begin}}
{{Col-break|width=50%}}
'''367th Fighter Group''' 
{| border=&quot;10&quot;
|-
! Aerial Victories !! Call Sign !! Fuselage Code !! Number !! Note
|-
| Group Hq || Dynamite || || 0 ||&lt;ref name=Groh5&gt;Groh, p. 5.  Call signs changed periodically.  These are the ones used in the last months of the war.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Newton &amp; Senning, p. 634&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 392d Fighter Squadron || Knobhole ||&lt;center&gt;H5&lt;/center&gt;|| 39.5 || &lt;ref name=&quot;Groh5&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Newton &amp; Senning, p. 645&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Watkins&gt;Watkins, p. 38 (Fuselage codes)&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 393d Fighter Squadron || Decco ||&lt;center&gt;8L&lt;/center&gt;|| 22.5 ||&lt;ref name=Groh5/&gt;&lt;ref name=Watkins/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Newton &amp; Senning, pp. 645–646&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 394th Fighter Squadron || Casket ||&lt;center&gt;4N&lt;/center&gt;|| 23 || &lt;ref name=Groh5/&gt;&lt;ref name=Watkins/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Newton &amp; Senning, pp. 646&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| Group Total || || || 85 || 
|}

===Air National Guard===

====Organization and federal recognition====
[[File:109th Fighter Squadron F-51 Mustangs late 1940s.jpg|thumb|109th Fighter Squadron F-51 Mustangs parked in the snow]]
The 367th Fighter Group was redesignated the '''133rd Fighter Group''' and was allotted to the [[National Guard (United States)|National Guard]] on 24 May 1946.&lt;ref name=Maurer367FG/&gt; The group was organized at [[Holman Field]], Saint Paul, Minnesota and was extended federal recognition on 28 August 1947.  It was assigned the [[109th Fighter Squadron]] and 179th Fighter Squadron at Holman Field and the 178th Fighter Squadron of the [[South Dakota National Guard]].&lt;ref group=note&gt;The 178th and 179th Fighter Squadrons were two of the group's World War II squadrons, the 392d and 393d, which had also been allotted to the National Guard and renumbered. Maurer, ''Combat Squadrons'', pp. 481–483.&lt;/ref&gt; All three squadrons had been federally recognized earlier and had begun training with the [[North American F-51D Mustang]].  The 179th soon moved to [[Duluth Municipal Airport]].

In the fall of 1950, the [[Air National Guard]] reorganized under the [[Hobson Plan|wing base organization]] system, and the [[133d Fighter Wing]] was activated on 1 November 1950 to command the 133d Fighter Group and its newly formed support organizations.

====Mobilization during Korean War====
The group and its squadrons were called to active duty in March 1951 due to the growth of the Air Force during the [[Korean War]].  It was assigned to [[Air Defense Command]] (ADC), along with its two squadrons in Minnesota, but the 178th Squadron was transferred to the [[146th Fighter-Bomber Group]] upon mobilization.&lt;ref&gt;Maurer, ''Combat Units'', p. 260&lt;/ref&gt;  The group and its two remaining squadrons were renamed [[interceptor aircraft|fighter-interceptor]] units with a mission of [[air defense]].  The group continued to fly the Mustang while on active duty.  ADC was having difficulty under the existing wing base organizational structure in deploying fighter squadrons to best advantage.  It reorganized by inactivating its fighter wings and groups and reassigning their squadrons to geographically organized headquarters.&lt;ref&gt;Grant,  p. 33&lt;/ref&gt;  The group was inactivated in February 1952 and its squadrons assigned to the [[31st Air Division]].&lt;ref name=Maurer367FG/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cornett &amp; Johnson, pp. 122, 124&lt;/ref&gt;

====Return to state control====
{{main|133rd Airlift Wing}}
[[File:109th Fighter-Interceptor Squadron Lockheed F-94C-1-LO Starfire 50-980.jpg|thumb|left|109th Fighter-Interceptor Squadron F-94C&lt;ref group=note&gt;Aircraft is Lockheed F-94C-1-LO Starfire serial 50–980.  This aircraft now on display at the [[National Museum of the United States Air Force]], marked as 50-1054&lt;/ref&gt;]]
In December 1953 the group was returned to the  [[Minnesota Air National Guard]], retaining its air defense mission.  In 1956, the 133d Fighter-Interceptor Wing reorganized along the regional model of its gaining command, ADC, becoming the 133d Air Defense Wing.  The 133d Group became the '''133d Fighter Group''' (Air Defense) and its squadrons in Duluth, [[Hector Airport]], North Dakota and [[Sioux Falls Municipal Airport]], South Dakota were reassigned to newly formed Fighter Groups.  The wing support organizations were split among the 133d Group and the newly formed organizations.

[[File:109th Air Transport Squadron Boeing C-97A Stratofreighter 49-2607.jpg|thumb|109th Air Transport Squadron C-97A&lt;ref group=note&gt;Aircraft is Boeing C-97A Stratofreighter serial 49-2607.&lt;/ref&gt;]]
It continued as an air defense fighter organization until 1960 when it transitioned into an [[airlift]] mission with [[Boeing C-97 Stratofreighter]]s.  during the [[Berlin Crisis of 1961]], the group was mobilized and its units served directly wing contol.  In 1971, the group transitioned into [[Lockheed C-130 Hercules]] aircraft.  The group was inactivated in 1975, but reactivated in 1994, again flying the Hercules.
{{Clear}}

==Lineage==
* Constituted as '''367th Fighter Group''' on 26 May 1943
: Activated on 15 July 1943
: Inactivated on 7 November 1945
* Redesignated '''133d Fighter Group''' and allotted to the [[National Guard (United States)|National Guard]] on 24 May 1946
: Activated on 22 August 1947
: Federally recognized on 28 August 1947
* Ordered into active service on 1 March 1951
* Redesignated '''133d Fighter-Interceptor Group''' on 23 March 1951&lt;ref name=cj76&gt;Cornett &amp; Johnson, p. 76&lt;/ref&gt;
: Inactivated on 6 February 1952
: Relieved from active duty, returned to the [[Air National Guard]] and activated on 1 December 1952
: Redesignated '''133d Fighter Group''' (Air Defense) on 15 April 1956
: Redesignated '''133d Air Transport Group''', Heavy c. 11 April 1960
: Federalized and placed on active duty on 1 October 1961
: Released from active duty and returned to Minnesota state control on 31 August 1962
: Redesignated '''133d Military Airlift Group''' on 1 January 1966
: Redesignated '''133d Tactical Airlift Group''' on 20 March 1971
: Inactivated on 9 February 1975
* Redesignated '''133d Operations Group'''
: Activated c. 1 March 1994&lt;ref&gt;World War II lineage and lineage while federalized in 1952 in Maurer, ''Combat Units'', pp. 252–254&lt;/ref&gt;

===Assignments===
* [[IV Fighter Command]], 15 July 1943 (attached to [[San Francisco Fighter Wing]], 10 December 1943 – 8 March 1944)
* [[70th Fighter Wing]], 6 July 1944 (attached to [[IX Tactical Air Command]] after 3 October 1944)
* [[XIX Tactical Air Command]], 16 January – July 1945
* [[III Fighter Command]], September – 7 November 1945
* [[71st Fighter Wing]], 28 August 1947
* [[86th Fighter Wing (World War II)|86th Fighter Wing]], c. 1 August 1949
* 133d Fighter Wing (later 133d Fighter-Interceptor Wing), 1 November 1950 – 6 February 1952
* 133d Fighter-Interceptor Wing (later 133d Air Defense Wing, 133d Air Transport Wing, 133d Military Airlift Wing, 133d Tactical Airlift Wing), 1 December 1952 – 9 February 1975
* 133d Airlift Wing, 1 March 1994 – present

===Stations===
{{div col|2}}
* Hamilton Field, California, 15 July 1943
* Santa Rosa Army Air Field, California, 11 October 1943
* Oakland Municipal Airport, California, 10 December 1943 – 8 March 1944
* RAF Stoney Cross (AAF-452),&lt;ref name=Anderson&gt;Anderson (Station numbers).&lt;/ref&gt; England, 5 April 1944
* RAF Ibsley (AAF-347),&lt;ref name=Anderson/&gt; England, 6 July 1944
* Beuzeville Airfield (A-6),&lt;ref name=Johnson&gt;Johnson (Station numbers).&lt;/ref&gt; France, 22 July 1944
* [[Cricqueville Airfield]] (A-2),&lt;ref name=Johnson/&gt; France, 14 August 1944
* Peray Airfield (A-44),&lt;ref name=Johnson/&gt; France, 4 September 1944
* Clastres Airfield (A-71),&lt;ref name=Johnson/&gt; France, 8 September 1944
* Juvincourt Airfield (A-68),&lt;ref name=Johnson/&gt; France, 28 October 1944
* [[St-Dizier Airfield]] (A-64),&lt;ref name=Johnson/&gt; France, 1 February 1945
* [[Conflans Airfield]] (A-94),&lt;ref name=Johnson/&gt; France, 14 March 1945
* Eschborn Airfield (Y-74),&lt;ref name=Johnson/&gt; Germany, 20 April – July 1945
* [[Seymour Johnson Field]], North Carolina, September – 7 November 1945
* Holman Field, Minnesota, 28 August 1947
* [[Fort Snelling]] (later Snelling Air Force Station, 21 January 1951 – 6 February 1952
* Holman Field, 1 December 1952
* [[Minneapolis–Saint Paul Joint Air Reserve Station|Wold-Chamberlain Field]] (later Minneapolis-St Paul International Airport), Minnesota, c. 1 January 1956 – 9 February 1975
* Minneapolis-St Paul International Joint Air Reserve Station, Minnesota, 1 March 1994 – present&lt;ref&gt;World War II stations and stations while federalized in 1952 in Maurer, ''Combat Units'', pp. 252–254&lt;/ref&gt;
{{div col end}}

===Components===
; Operational Squadrons
* 392d Fighter Squadron: 15 June 1943 – 7 November 1945
:: Later 178th Fighter Squadron, 178th Fighter-Interceptor Squadron, 17 September 1947 − 1 March 1951; 1 January 1953 − 15 April 1956
* 393d Fighter Squadron: 15 June 1943 – 7 November 1945
:: Later 179th Fighter Squadron, 179th Fighter-Interceptor Squadron, 28 August 1947 − 6 February 1952, 1 December 1952 –  15 April 1956
* 394th Fighter Squadron: 15 June 1943 – 7 November 1945
* 109th Fighter Squadron (later 109th Fighter-Interceptor Squadron, 109th Air Transport Squadron, 109th Military Airlift Squadron, 109th Tactical Airlift Squadron, 109th Airlift Squadron, 28 August 1947 − 6 February 1952, 1 December 1952 – 9 February 1975, 1 March 1994 – present
* [[167th Air Transport Squadron]] (later 167th Military Airlift Squadron, 167th Tactical Airlift Squadron), 1 April 1961 − 30 June 1972 (West Virginia ANG)
* [[175th Fighter Squadron]] (later 175th Fighter-Interceptor Squadron), 2 March 1951 − 6 February 1952, 1 December 1952 16 April 1956
: Sioux Falls Municipal Airport, South Dakota

; Support Organizations
* 133d Aeromedical Evacuation Squadron, 19 August 1951 – c. 1967
* 133d Air Base Squadron, 15 April 1956 – 1 July 1961
* 133d Consolidated Aircraft Maintenance Squadron, 1 January 1959 – 9 February 1975
* 133d Materiel Squadron, 15 April 1956 –  1 February 1965
* 133d Operations Support Squadron, 1 March 1994 – present
* 133d Support Squadron (later 133d Combat Support Squadron), 1 October 1963 – 9 February 1975
* 109th Aeromedical Evacuation Flight, 1 March 1994 – present
* 133d Aerial Port Flight, 20 March 1971 – 9 February 1975
* 133d Airlift Control Flight, 1 March 1994 – present
* 133d USAF Dispensary, 15 April 1956 – 1 April 1960

===Aircraft===
{{div col|2}}
* Bell P-39 Airacobra, 1943–1944
* Lockheed P-38 Lightning, 1944–1945
* Republic P-47 Thunderbolt, 1945-1945
* F-51D Mustang, 1947–1954
* [[Lockheed F-94A Starfire]], 1954–1957
* Lockheed F-94B Starfire, 1954–1957
* Lockheed F-94C Starfire, 1957–1960
* [[Northrop F-89H Scorpion]], 1958–1960
* [[Boeing C-97 Stratofreighter]], 1960–1971
* Lockheed C-130A Hercules, 1971–1975
* Lockheed C-130E Hercules, 1994–1995
* Lockheed C-130H Hercules, 1995–present
{{div col end}}

==See also==
{{Portal|United States Air Force|Military of the United States|World War II}}
* [[List of United States Air National Guard Groups &amp; Wings]]
* [[List of C-130 Hercules operators]]
* [[F-89 Scorpion units of the United States Air Force]]
* [[F-94 Starfire units of the United States Air Force]]
* [[List of P-38 Lightning operators]]
* [[Aviators who became ace in a day]]

==References==

===Notes===
{{reflist|group=note}}

===Citations===
{{Reflist|30em}}

===Bibliography===
{{Air Force Historical Research Agency}}
* {{cite book|last=Anderson|first=Capt. Barry|title= Army Air Forces Stations: A Guide to the Stations Where U.S. Army Air Forces Personnel Served in the United Kingdom During World War II|url=http://www.afhra.af.mil/shared/media/document/AFD-081010-027.pdf|accessdate=7 July 2012|year=1985|publisher=Research Division, USAF Historical Research Center|location=Maxwell AFB, AL |page= }}
* {{cite book|last=Chickering|first=Edwin S.|others=Air Force Association (compiler)|title=Air Force Fifty|url= https://books.google.com/books?id=1kN1wEYvql8C&amp;pg=PA79&amp;hl=en#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|accessdate=28 May 2015|year=1998|publisher=Turner Publishing|location= Nashville, TN|isbn=978-1563114090|chapter=367th Fighter Group}}
* {{cite book|last=Cornett|first=Lloyd H|author2=Johnson, Mildred W|title=A Handbook of Aerospace Defense Organization, 1946 – 1980|url= http://www.usafpatches.com/pubs/handbookofadcorg.pdf |accessdate=23 March 2012|year=1980|publisher=Office of History, Aerospace Defense Center|location = Peterson AFB, CO|page= }}
* {{cite web |url= http://www.afhra.af.mil/shared/media/document/AFD-090529-030.pdf |last1=Grant|first1=C. L.|title= The Development of Continental Air Defense to 1 September 1954, USAF Historical Study No. 126|date=|publisher=Research Studies Institute, USAF Historical Division, Air University|deadurl=no |accessdate=17 August 2014}}
* {{cite book|last=Groh|first=Richard|title=The Dynamite Gang: The 367th Fighter Group in World War II|series=World War II|year=1983|publisher= Aero Publishers|location= Fallbrook, CA|isbn=978-0816897704|lccn=83007241}}
* {{cite book|last=Johnson|first=1st Lt. David C.|title=U.S. Army Air Forces Continental Airfields (ETO) D-Day to V-E Day|url= http://www.afhra.af.mil/shared/media/document/AFD-081010-026.pdf |accessdate= |year=1988|publisher=Research Division, USAF Historical Research Center|location=Maxwell AFB, AL|page= }}
* {{cite book|editor=Maurer, Maurer|title=Air Force Combat Units of World War II|origyear= 1961|url= http://newpreview.afnews.af.mil/shared/media/document/AFD-100921-044.pdf |edition=reprint|year=1983|publisher=Office of Air Force History|location=Washington, DC|isbn=0-912799-02-1|lccn=61060979|pages=}}
* {{cite book|editor=Maurer, Maurer|title=Combat Squadrons of the Air Force, World War II|origyear=1969|url= http://www.afhso.af.mil/shared/media/document/AFD-101202-002.pdf|edition= reprint|year=1982|publisher=Office of Air Force History|location=Washington, DC|isbn=0-405-12194-6|oclc=72556|lccn=70605402|pages= }}
* {{cite web |url= http://www.afhra.af.mil/shared/media/document/AFD-090601-121.pdf |last1=Newton|first1=Wesely P., Jr.|last2=Senning|first2=Calvin F.|title= USAF Credits for the Destruction of  Enemy Aircraft, World War II, USAF Historical Study No. 85|date=1963|publisher=Research Studies Institute, USAF Historical Division, Air University|deadurl=no |accessdate=27 April 2014}}
* {{cite book|last=Watkins|first=Robert|title=Battle Colors|volume=Vol  III Insignia and Markings of the Ninth Air Force In World War II|year=2008|publisher=Shiffer Publishing|location=Atglen, PA|isbn=978-0-7643-2938-8|page= }}

; Further Reading
{{Commons category|367th Fighter Group (United States Army Air Forces)|United States Army Air Forces 367th Fighter Group}}
* {{cite book|last=Hallade|first=Jean|title=Quand le ciel de l'Aisne était en feu|trans_title=When the Sky over the Aisne was on Fire|year=1978|publisher=Presses de l'Aisne Nouvelle|location=Laon, France|language=French|asin=B0014M4STC}} (Chapter 12 deals with the combat of 25 August 1944).
* {{cite book|last=|first=|title=Projecting Peace Proudly: A commemorative history of the 133rd Airlift Wing, 1921–1996|year=1996|publisher=Minnespta Air National Guard|location=St Paul, MN|asin=}}

{{USAAF 9th Air Force UK}}
{{USAAF 4th Air Force World War II}}

[[Category:Military units and formations in Minnesota]]
[[Category:Military units and formations of the United States in the Cold War]]
[[Category:Operations groups of the United States Air Force]]
[[Category:Military units and formations established in 1943]]</text>
      <sha1>lvm2uaegry7mgwpe9ar7ty49i8ld0op</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
