<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>140th Rifle Division (Soviet Union)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>41823755</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750345662</id>
      <parentid>743445563</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-19T04:31:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Hmains</username>
        <id>508734</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* top */copyedit, links and AWB general fixes, replaced: WWII. → World War II. using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10828">{{Infobox military unit
|unit_name= 140th Rifle Division
|image= 
|caption= 
|dates= 16 August 1939 – 1946
|country= {{flag|Soviet Union|1923}}
|allegiance=
|branch= [[Image:Red Army flag.svg|23px]] [[Red Army]]
|type= Division
|role= Infantry
|size=
|command_structure=  
|current_commander= 
|garrison=
|march= 
|motto= 
|mascot= 
|battles= [[Operation Barbarossa]]&lt;br&gt;[[Operation Typhoon]]&lt;br&gt;[[Operation Blue]]&lt;br&gt;[[Battle of Kursk]]&lt;br&gt;[[Operation Kutuzov]]&lt;br&gt;[[Battle of the Dnieper]]&lt;br&gt;[[Battle of Kiev (1943)]]&lt;br&gt;[[Lvov-Sandomierz Offensive]]&lt;br&gt;[[Vistula-Oder Offensive]]&lt;br&gt;[[Prague Offensive]]
|notable_commanders= Mjr. Gen. M.A. Enshin&lt;br&gt;[[File:Hero of the Soviet Union medal.png|10px]]Mjr. Gen. A.Ya. Kiselyov&lt;br&gt;Col. M.M. Vlasov
|anniversaries=
}}
The '''140th Rifle Division''' was a [[Red Army]] rifle division of the Great Patriotic War. Originally formed before the War, the 140th might be regarded as the unluckiest division in the Army, as it had to be completely, or almost completely, re-formed three times between 1941 and 1943. In spite of this, the fourth formation of the 140th went on to have a distinguished record in combat, a testament to the resiliency of the Red Army in World War II.

== 1st Formation ==
The division was first organized on Aug. 16, 1939 at [[Uman]] in the [[Kiev Military District|Ukrainian (later: Kiev Special) Military District]]. On June 22, 1941, it was still in that District, and comprised:
* 445th Rifle Regiment
* 637th Rifle Regiment
* 798th Rifle Regiment
* 309th Light Artillery Regiment
* 371st Howitzer Regiment
* 181st Reconnaissance Battalion&lt;ref&gt;Charles S. Sharp, ''&quot;Red Legions&quot;, Soviet Rifle Divisions Formed Before June 1942, Soviet Order of Battle World War II, Vol. VIII'', Nafziger, 1996, p 70&lt;/ref&gt;
When the German invasion began, the 140th was assigned to the [[36th Rifle Corps (Soviet Union)|36th Rifle Corps]] in Kiev District reserves, and by June 27 it was in [[6th Army (Soviet Union)|6th Army]], fighting off German armor. By late July it was in [[49th Rifle Corps (Soviet Union)|49th Rifle Corps]] in that same army then it was relocated to [[Southern Front (Soviet Union)|South Front]]. In early August the division was trapped in the [[Battle of Uman|encirclement at Uman]], and was destroyed by the middle of the month. The division number was finally deleted from the Soviet order of battle on Sept. 19.&lt;ref&gt;Sharp, ''&quot;Red Legions&quot;, p 70&lt;/ref&gt;

== 2nd Formation ==
The division was reformed on 26 September from the [[13th Moscow Militia Division]] with:
* 1305th Rifle Regiment – from 37th Militia Regiment
* 1307th Rifle Regiment – from 38th Militia Regiment
* 1309th Rifle Regiment – from 39th Militia Regiment
* 977th Artillery Regiment – from Militia Artillery Battalion (76mm)

The 13th Militia ''(Opolchenie)'' Division reported 8,010 men on hand in mid-July, including 1,700 members of the Communist Party or [[Komsomol]]s. The division spent most of August and September with the [[32nd Army (Soviet Union)|32nd Army]] in [[Reserve Front]], training and probably being reinforced. It made little difference in October, when the division was encircled near Lozino, northwest of [[Vitebsk]] during [[Operation Typhoon]] and largely destroyed by mid-month, although it was not officially disbanded until 27 December.&lt;ref&gt;Charles C. Sharp, ''&quot;Red Tide&quot;, Soviet Order of Battle World War II, Vol. IX'', Nafziger, 1996, p 21&lt;/ref&gt; Enough personnel escaped the encirclement to make a cadre for the next formation of the division.

== 3rd Formation ==
The third formation of the 140th Rifle Division began in late December, based on escaped elements of the previous division. The order of battle reverted to that of the first formation, except the howitzer regiment was no longer present, and the 309th was now a standard artillery regiment. A new divisional commander was not appointed until late January, 1942, and the unit remained in the [[Moscow Military District]] until May. In late May the 140th was transferred to the [[24th Army (Soviet Union)|24th Army]] in ''STAVKA'' reserves and sent south. 24th Army arrived in [[Southern Front (Soviet Union)|Southern Front]] just at the opening of the German summer offensive, [[Operation Blue]], in June. In early July the division was transferred to the reserves of [[9th Army (Soviet Union)|9th Army]]. Retreating across the open steppes with the [[First Panzer Army]] in pursuit, the 140th was caught up in the encirclement south of [[Millerovo, Millerovsky District, Rostov Oblast|Millerovo]] and effectively destroyed by the third week of July. It is listed as &quot;reorganizing&quot; in the [[Caucasus]] Region on 1 August,&lt;ref&gt;David M. Glantz, ''To the Gates of Stalingrad'', University Press of Kansas, Lawrence, KS, 2009, pp 112, 177, 414&lt;/ref&gt; but this was abandoned and the division was officially disbanded on 19 August.&lt;ref&gt;Charles C. Sharp, ''&quot;Red Swarm&quot;, Soviet Order of Battle World War II, Vol. X'', Nafziger, 1996, pp 53 – 54&lt;/ref&gt;

== 4th Formation ==
The fourth formation of the division began on 1 November 1942, using personnel from the [[NKVD]], at [[Novosibirsk]] in the [[Siberian Military District]]. It consisted of:
* 96th &quot;[[Chitinsky District|Chitinsk]]&quot; Rifle Regiment
* 258th &quot;[[Khabarovsk]]&quot; Rifle Regiment
* 283rd &quot;Krasnofouminsk&quot; Rifle Regiment
* 371st &quot;[[Siberia|Sibirsk]]&quot; Artillery Regiment
* 92nd Antitank Battalion
* 87th Sapper Battalion, and other supporting units.&lt;ref&gt;Sharp; ''&quot;Red Swarm&quot;''; p 54&lt;/ref&gt;
The NKVD began forming the division, and three others, to serve as NKVD rifle divisions prior to being authorized by the Commissar of Defense on 7 December. The division was passed to Red Army control as the 140th in Feb., 1943. At that time it had 8,685 officers and men assigned, 69 percent of whom were under 30 years of age, quite a youthful cadre for a late-war division. Officially these men were drawn from internal troops and border guards of the NKVD. As the Siberian Military District had no external borders, it's likely that some were taken from guards of the [[GULAG]] and other sources that were off-limits to the Red Army.&lt;ref&gt;Sharp; ''&quot;Red Swarm&quot;''; p 54&lt;/ref&gt;

As with the other NKVD divisions, the 140th was assigned to the [[70th Army (Soviet Union)|70th Army]] in the [[Central Front (Soviet Union)|Central Front]]. During the [[Battle of Kursk]] the 70th Army fought on the left flank of the [[2nd Tank Army]] and played a role in stopping the German [[9th Army (Wehrmacht)|9th Army]] that was trying to break through to Kursk from the north.&lt;ref&gt;Robin Cross; ''The Battle of Kursk''; Penguin Books, London, 1993; p 166&lt;/ref&gt; During the subsequent Red Army counterattack, the 70th Army took part in [[Operation Kutuzov]] and attacked Trosna to the south of the town of [[Kromy]]. On 5 Aug., its units reached the region southwest of Kromy, and on 17 Aug., they reached the German &quot;Hagen&quot; defense line near Domakha.

== Advance ==
In August the division was moved to the [[19th Rifle Corps]] of the [[65th Army (Soviet Union)|65th Army]], and participated in the advance towards the [[Dnepr River]] in the following months. On 16 September it was successful in liberating the town of [[Novgorod-Severski]] and was later given the name of that town as its divisional honorific, in addition to the title ''Siberian'', which it had carried since its fourth formation. By November it was depleted to the point that it went into [[1st Belorussian Front|Belorussian]] (the renamed Central) Front reserves. On 13 December the 140th was moved to the [[13th Army (Soviet Union)|13th Army]] in [[1st Ukrainian Front]]. By the turn of the year the division was back in the front line, and on 3 January 1944 liberated the town of [[Novograd-Volynsky|Novograd-Volynskiy]], for which it received its first [[Order of the Red Banner]]. In Feb. the division was transferred to the [[28th Rifle Corps]] of the [[60th Army (Soviet Union)|60th Army]] of the same Front. In July the division was reassigned to the [[38th Army (Soviet Union)|38th Army]], and remained in this Army for the duration.

The 38th Army moved to the [[4th Ukrainian Front]] in Nov., 1944, and the 140th remained in this Front for the duration, although it was bounced from one rifle corps to another during this time. Along with its Army, the division fought through the [[Carpathian Mountains]] and eastern Czechoslovakia during the winter and spring of 1945. During this operation division commander Mjr. Gen. A.Ya. Kiselyov was killed in a German airstrike while successfully directing the penetration of the strong German lines south of the Polish city of Iaslo. He was awarded the Gold Star of the [[Hero of the Soviet Union]], posthumously.&lt;ref&gt;Aleksander A. Maslov, ''Fallen Soviet Generals'', trans. &amp; ed. by David M. Glantz, Frank Cass Publishers, London, 1998, pp 169–70&lt;/ref&gt; At the end of the war, the 140th was near Prague, in the [[101st Rifle Corps]].&lt;ref&gt;Sharp; ''&quot;Red Swarm&quot;''; p 54&lt;/ref&gt;

Apart from Mjr. Gen. Kiselyov, who commanded the division from May 11, 1943 until his death, only two men of the 140th were awarded the Gold Star of the Hero of the Soviet Union, Lt. [[Georgy Gridasov]] and Maj. [[Georgy Fedoseyevich Andreyev|Georgy Andreyev]], on May 15, 1945. The division honorifics were – Russian: Сибирская Новгород-Северская ордена Ленина, дважды Краснознамённая, орденов Суворова и Кутузова. (English: ''Siberian, Novgorod-Severski, [[Order of Lenin]], Order of the Red Banner, [[Order of Suvorov]], [[Order of Kutuzov]].'')

The 38th Army was moved back into the short-lived Lvov Military District by 1946, and the 101st Rifle Corps headquarters was established at [[Kolomyia]]. 140th Rifle Division is listed by Feskov et al 2013, soon after the war, with the Military Unit No. (V/Ch) 28278 with headquarters seemingly located at [[Kalush, Ivano-Frankivsk Oblast|Kalush]]. The division and its parent corps were both disbanded in 1946.&lt;ref&gt;Feskov et al 2013, 474.&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}
* {{Cite book|title=Вооруженные силы СССР после Второй Мировой войны: от Красной Армии к Советской|last=Feskov|first=V.I.|last2=Golikov|first2=V.I.|last3=Kalashnikov|first3=K.A.|last4=Slugin|first4=S.A.|publisher=Scientific and Technical Literature Publishing|year=2013|isbn=9785895035306|location=Tomsk|language=Russian|trans-title=The Armed Forces of the USSR after World War II: From the Red Army to the Soviet: Part 1 Land Forces}}
{{Soviet Union divisions}}

[[Category:Infantry divisions of the Soviet Union in World War II]]
[[Category:Military units and formations established in 1939]]
[[Category:Military units and formations awarded the Order of the Red Banner]]</text>
      <sha1>a86x5r470vzrzqc63nbbth7n8h5tx76</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
