<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>2nd SS Panzer Division Das Reich</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1672788</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749102628</id>
      <parentid>748969077</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-12T12:11:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>88.77.118.217</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="29890">{{refimprove|date=November 2015}}
{{DISPLAYTITLE:2nd SS Panzer Division ''Das Reich''}}
{{Infobox military unit
| unit_name               = 2nd SS Panzer Division ''Das Reich''
| image                   = [[File:SS-Panzer-Division symbol.svg|175px]]
| caption                 = The ''Wolfsangel''
| dates                   = 1939–45
| country                 = {{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
| allegiance              =
| branch                  = [[File:Flag Schutzstaffel.svg|23px]] [[Waffen-SS]]
| type                    = [[Panzer]]
| role                    = [[Armoured warfare]]
| size                    = [[Division (military)|Division]]
| command_structure       =
| Past_commanders         =
| ceremonial_chief        =
| notable_commanders      = [[Paul Hausser]]
| identification_symbol   =
| identification_symbol_2 =
| nickname                =
| patron                  =
| motto                   = 
| colors                  =
| march                   =
| mascot                  =
| battles                 = {{plainlist |
* [[Battle of France|Battle of France 1940]]
* [[Operation Barbarossa]]
* [[Operation Typhoon]]
* [[Battle of Kursk]]
* [[operation Overlord]]
* [[Battle of the Bulge]]
}}
| anniversaries           =
| decorations             =
| battle_honours          =
| associated units        = {{plainlist |
* SS Regiment,''Deutschland''
* SS Regiment, ''Der Führer''
* SS Regiment,''Germania''
}}
}}

The '''2nd SS Panzer Division ''Das Reich''''' was an elite division of the Nazi [[Waffen-SS]] during [[World War II]]. It was one of the thirty-eight [[division (military)|division]]s fielded by the Waffen-SS. ''Das Reich'' served during the invasion of France and took part in several major battles on the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]], including in the [[Battle of Prokhorovka]] against the [[5th Guards Tank Army (Soviet Union)|5th Guards Tank Army]] at the [[Battle of Kursk]]. It was then transferred to the West and took part in the fighting in Normandy and the [[Battle of the Bulge]], ending the war in Hungary and Austria. ''Das Reich'' committed the [[Oradour-sur-Glane]] and [[Tulle massacre]]s.

==Operational history==
In August 1939 [[Adolf Hitler]] placed the ''[[Leibstandarte SS Adolf Hitler]]'' (LSSAH) and the ''[[SS-Verfügungstruppe]]'' (SS-VT) under the operational command of the [[OKH]], (Supreme High Command of the German Army). Events during the [[Invasion of Poland (1939)|Invasion of Poland]] raised doubts over the combat effectiveness of the SS-VT. Himmler insisted that the SS-VT should be allowed to fight in its own formations under its own commanders, while the OKW tried to have the SS-VT disbanded altogether. Hitler was unwilling to upset either the army or Himmler, and chose a third path. He ordered that the SS-VT form its own divisions but that the divisions would be under army command.{{sfn|Flaherty|2004|p=149}}

In October 1939 the ''[[SS-Verfügungstruppe]]'' (SS-VT) regiments, ''Deutschland'', ''Germania'' and ''Der Führer'', were organized into the ''SS-Verfügungs-Division'' with Paul Hausser as commander.{{sfn|Flaherty|2004|p=149}}{{sfn|Stein|1984|p=32}} Thereafter, the SS-VT and the LSSAH took part in combat training while under army commands in preparation for [[Fall Gelb|Operation ''Fall Gelb'']] against the Low Countries and France in 1940.{{sfn|Flaherty|2004|pp=149–151}}
 
In May 1940, the ''Der Führer'' Regiment was detached from the SS-VT Division and relocated near the Dutch border, with the remainder of the division behind the line in [[Münster]], awaiting the order to [[Battle of the Netherlands|invade the Netherlands]].{{sfn|Flaherty|2004|p=152}} ''Der Führer'' Regiment and LSSAH participated in the ground invasion of the Netherlands which began on 10 May. On the following day the rest of the SS-VT Division crossed into the Netherlands, participating in the drive for the Dutch central front and [[Rotterdam]], which they reached on 12 May.{{sfn|Flaherty|2004|p=152}}{{sfn|Stein|1984|pp=62–64}} After that city had been captured, the SS-VT Division, along with other German formations, were sent to &quot;mop up&quot; the remaining French-Dutch force holding out in the area of [[Zeeland]] and the islands of Walcheren and South Beveland.{{sfn|Stein|1984|pp=65–66}}

After the fighting in the Netherlands ended, the SS-VT Division was ordered to make for France.{{sfn|Stein|1984|p=66}} On 24 May the LSSAH, along with the SS-VT Division were positioned to hold the perimeter around [[Dunkirk]] and reduce the size of the pocket containing the encircled [[British Expeditionary Force (World War II)|British Expeditionary Force]] and French forces.{{sfn|Stein|1984|pp=65–69}} A patrol from the SS-VT Division crossed the canal at [[Saint-Venant]], but was destroyed by British armor. A larger force from the SS-VT Division then crossed the canal and formed a bridgehead at Saint-Venant; 30 miles from Dunkirk.{{sfn|Flaherty|2004|p=154}} On the following day, British forces attacked Saint-Venant, forcing the SS-VT Division to retreat and relinquish ground.{{sfn|Flaherty|2004|p=154}} On 26 May the German advance resumed. On 27 May the ''Deutschland'' regiment of the SS-VT Division reached the allied defensive line on the [[Leie River]] at [[Merville, Nord|Merville]]. They forced a bridgehead across the river and waited for the SS  Division ''Totenkopf'' to arrive to cover their flank. What arrived first was a unit of British tanks, which penetrated their position. The SS-VT managed to hold on against the British tank force, which got to within 15 feet of commander Felix Steiner's position. Only the arrival of the ''Totenkopf'' [[Panzerjäger]] platoon saved the ''Deutschland'' from being destroyed and their bridgehead lost.{{sfn|Flaherty|2004|p=155}} By 30 May, most of the remaining Allied forces had been pushed back into Dunkirk where they were evacuated by sea to England. The SS-VT Division next took part in the drive towards Paris.{{sfn|Flaherty|2004|p=156}} 

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101III-Zschaeckel-130-05, Russland, Fahrzeuge der SS-Division &quot;Das Reich&quot;.jpg|thumb|right|USSR, 21 June 1941]]
After the close of the Battle of France, the SS-VT was officially renamed the Waffen-SS in July 1940.{{sfn|Flaherty|2004|p=156}} In December 1940 the ''Germania'' Regiment was removed from the ''Verfügungs-Division'' and used to form the cadre of a new division, [[5 SS|SS Division Germania]].{{sfn|Stein|1984|p=103}} It was made up of mostly Danes, Norwegians, Dutch and Flemish volunteers from the occupied territories.{{sfn|Flaherty|2004|p=160}} By the start of 1941 the division was renamed &quot;Reich&quot; (in 1942 &quot;Das Reich&quot;), and &quot;Germania&quot; was renamed &quot;Wiking&quot;.{{sfn|Stein|1984|p=104}}

In April 1941, Germany [[Invasion of Yugoslavia|invaded Yugoslavia]] and [[Battle of Greece|Greece]]. The LSSAH and ''Das Reich'' were attached to separate army Panzer Corps. [[Fritz Klingenberg]], a company commander in the ''Das Reich'', led his men across Yugoslavia to the capital, [[Belgrade]], where a small group in the vanguard accepted the surrender of the city on 13 April. A few days later Yugoslavia surrendered.{{sfn|Flaherty|2004|pp=162, 163}} SS police units immediately began taking hostages and carrying out reprisals, a practice that became common. In some cases, they were joined by the Wehrmacht.{{sfn|Bessel|2006|pp=110–111}}

For the invasion of the Soviet Union ([[Operation Barbarossa]]), ''Das Reich'' fought with [[Army Group Center]], taking part in the [[Yelnya offensive|Battle of Yelnya]] near [[Smolensk]]; it was then in the spearhead of [[Operation Typhoon]] aimed at the capture of the Soviet capital. By the time ''Das Reich'' took part in the [[Battle of Moscow]], it had lost 60 percent of its combat strength. It was further reduced in the Soviet Winter Counter-Offensive: for example, the ''Der Führer'' Regiment was down to 35 men out of the 2,000 that had started the campaign in June. The division was &quot;mauled&quot;.{{sfn|Flaherty|2004|p=168}} By February 1942, it had lost 10,690 men.{{sfn|Stein|1984|p=167}} By mid-1942, the division now known as ''Das Reich'' was pulled out of the fighting line and sent to the west to refit as a ''Panzer-Grenadier Division''.{{sfn|Flaherty|2004|p=173}}

In 1943, ''Das Reich'' was transferred back from France to the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]]. There it participated in the fighting around [[Kharkov]].{{sfn|Stein|1984|pp=204, 207}} Thereafter, it was one of three SS divisions which made up the [[II SS Panzer Corps]], which took part in the [[Battle of Kursk]] that summer.{{sfn|Clark|2012|p=247}} ''Das Reich'' operated in the southern sector of the Kursk bulge. It was pulled out of the battle along with the other SS divisions when the offensive was discontinued, giving the strategic initiative to the Red Army.{{sfn|Glantz|1986|p=66}} The Battle of Kursk was the first time that a German strategic offensive was halted before it could break through enemy defences and penetrate to its [[strategic depth]]s.{{sfn|Glantz|2013|p=184}} In October, ''Das Reich'' was redesignated, this time as ''SS Panzer Division &quot;Das Reich&quot;'' to reflect its complement of tanks.{{sfn|Stein|1984|p=210}}

Beginning on 6 June 1944, the Allied [[Normandy landings]] took place on the coast of France. At that time, ''SS-Das Reich'' was located in [[Southern France]].{{sfn|McNab|2013|p=295}} The division was ordered north shortly after the Normandy landings occurred.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Hastings |first=Max |title=Das Reich: The March of the 2nd SS Panzer Division Through France, June 1944 |accessdate=June 15, 2016 |year=2013 |orig-year=1981 |publisher=Zenith Press |series=Zenith Military Classics |isbn= 978-0760344910}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 4 August Hitler ordered a counter-offensive ([[Operation Lüttich]]) from Vire towards [[Avranches]]; the operation included ''Das Reich''. However, the Allied forces were prepared for this offensive, and an air assault on the combined German units proved devastating.{{sfn|Stein|1984|pp=222–223}} [[Liberation of Paris|Paris was liberated]] on 25 August, and the last of the German forces withdrew over the [[Seine]] by the end of August, ending the Normandy campaign.{{sfn|Shirer|1960|pp=1085–1086}} The U.S. [[2nd Armored Division (United States)|2nd Armored Division]] had encircled ''Das Reich'' and the [[17th SS Panzergrenadier Division Götz von Berlichingen]] around [[Roncey]].&lt;ref&gt;Zaloga p. 3&lt;/ref&gt; In the process ''Das Reich'' and 17th SS Panzergrenadier Division had lost most of their armored equipment.&lt;ref&gt;Zaloga p. 3&lt;/ref&gt; ''Das Reich'' had about 2,650 men along with 14 75-mm. antitank guns, about 37 artillery pieces, 1 [[assault gun]], and 1 [[Panther tank]] with two other tanks in the repair shop by September 1944.{{sfn|MacDonald|1963|p=51}}
&lt;!--- Comment out: Uncited from Nov 2015 || 
===1942===
Part of the formation under Werner Ostendorff was left in the east, and they were titled ''Kampfgruppe SS-Reich''. Ostendorff was to rejoin the division in June 1942.

In November 1942, portions of the division took part in an attempt to prevent the [[Scuttling of the French fleet in Toulon|scuttling]] of the French Fleet at [[Toulon]]. Soon after, the division was retitled again, this time to ''SS-Panzer Grenadier-Division ''&quot;Das Reich&quot;''.
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101III-Hoffmann-023-11, Russland, bei Charkow, Himmler bei SS-Division &quot;Das Reich&quot;.jpg|thumb|left|''Das Reich'' captured enough [[T-34]] tanks to form the III/Battalion ''SS Panzer Regiment'' 2 (April 1943)]]

===1943===
It was soon sent back to try to halt the Soviet counterattack (Operation [[Operation Polkovodets Rumyantsev|''Polkovodets Rumyantsev'']]). Along with the 3rd ''SS Totenkopf, Das Reich'' launched a counterattack against two Soviet tank armies which soon faltered due to Soviet reinforcements.
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101III-Zschaeckel-206-34, Schlacht um Kursk, Panzer VI (Tiger I).jpg|thumb|right|''Das Reich'' [[Tiger I|Tiger]] tanks, Kursk July 1943]]

Afterwards, ''Das Reich'' was refitted, this time as ''SS Panzer Division &quot;Das Reich&quot;''. It left a portion of the division in the East titled ''Kampfgruppe &quot;Das Reich&quot;'', also known as ''Kampfgruppe Lammerding''. The rest of the division was transferred to the West to refit, and while doing so, took part in anti-[[French resistance|partisan]] operations in France, and perpetrated the massacre at [[Oradour-sur-Glane]].

In winter 1943–1944, ''Kampfgruppe &quot;Das Reich&quot;'' continued to fight on the eastern front. In February 1944 the ''Kampfgruppe'' was transferred to France to join the rest of the division already stationed there. The remaining small portion of the division left in the East was renamed ''[[Kampfgruppe Weidinger]]'' and was involved in the retreats through [[Khmelnytskyi, Ukraine|Proskurov]] and [[Ternopil|Tarnopol]]. Most of ''Das Reich'' was stationed in the southern French town of [[Montauban]] north of [[Toulouse]], where it received new equipment and fresh troops.

===1944===
Ordered to [[Normandy]], ''Das Reich'' arrived in its designated billeting area just behind the front near St. Lo in mid-June 1944. The division was held back as &quot;Army Group Reserve&quot; for possible German counter-attack by the 7. Armee that never took place.{{sfn|Weidinger|Das Reich V|p=68}}{{citation not found | date = January 2016}}

After the [[Normandy landings|D-Day]] invasion of 6 June, ''Das Reich'' was committed piecemeal (at first only the I. &quot;Der Führer&quot; and I. &quot;Deutschland&quot; attached to the [[Panzer Lehr Division]]) to stop the Allied advance, and took part in the attempts to stop the Americans near [[Saint-Lô]] alongside the ''[[Panzer-Lehr-Division]]''. The division recaptured Mortain, but was forced to retreat when it became apparent the Allies were going to encircle the Division along with a large number of other German elements in the [[Falaise pocket]]. Due to the efforts of ''Das Reich'' along with the ''[[9th SS Panzer Division Hohenstaufen|9th SS Panzer Division &quot;Hohenstaufen,&quot;]]'' a large number of German forces were able to escape the pocket and retreat to the east.

[[File:MortainDasReich.jpg|thumb|right|An armored [[SdKfz 251]] half-track of the ''2.SS-Panzer division &quot;Das Reich&quot;'' and the corpse of a German soldier near Mortain, 12 August 1944]]

Withdrawn across the [[Seine River]] and then behind the '[[Siegfried Line|Westwall]]' fortifications in Germany, the 2nd SS Panzer Division ''Das Reich'' took part in the [[Battle of the Bulge]] to punch through the [[Ardennes Forest]] in an attempt to reclaim the port of [[Antwerp]] on 16 December 1944. Coming within {{convert|37|km|abbr=on}} of the [[River Meuse]], the division was halted at Manhay on 25 December and then slowly smashed by Allied counter-attacks.

===1945===
Pulled out of the offensive, ''Das Reich'' was transferred into Germany to refit again, then to Hungary to take part in the [[Lake Balaton Offensive]] in early and mid-March. The attack failed, and ''Das Reich'' spent the remaining few weeks of the war in retreat through [[Vienna]] to the area north of [[Linz]], where--&gt;The division surrendered to the U.S. Army in May 1945.

[[File:Laclotte7juin44.png|thumb|left|One of the [[:fr:Crime de guerre de Laclotte|War crimes took place at Laclotte Castle]] on 7 June 1944. At right, the location where civilians were shot.]]

==War crimes==

===Oradour-sur-Glane===
{{details|Oradour-sur-Glane}}

[[File:Car in Oradour-sur-Glane4.jpg|thumb|Burned out cars and buildings still litter the untouched remains of the original village of [[Oradour-sur-Glane]]]]
The division massacred 642 French civilians in the village of [[Oradour-sur-Glane]] on 10 June 1944 in the [[Limousin (région)|Limousin]] region. SS-''Sturmbannführer'' Adolf Diekmann, commander of the I Battalion, 4th SS Panzergrenadier Regiment (''Der Führer'') that committed the massacre, claimed that it was a just retaliation due to partisan activity in nearby [[Tulle]] and the kidnapping of ''Sturmbannführer'' [[Helmut Kämpfe]], commander of the III Battalion, although the German authorities had already executed ninety-nine people in the [[Tulle massacre]], following the killing of some forty German soldiers in Tulle by the [[Maquis (World War II)|Maquis]] resistance movement.

On 10 June, Diekmann's battalion sealed off Oradour-sur-Glane, and ordered all the townspeople to assemble in the village square, ostensibly to have their identity papers examined. All the women and children were locked in the church. &lt;!-- Comment out apologia from the member of the division, if this is it be included should be cited to WP:RS secondary source || while the village was searched. Diekmann later claimed to have found multiple stores of weapons and ammunition secretly hidden in the village and to have thus ordered it to be burned as a hub of partisan activity.&lt;ref&gt;Weidinger, Das Reich V, pg. 61&lt;/ref&gt; According to the account put forward by Weidinger, the commanding officer of Das Reich, the ammunition that was hidden exploded in the fires, causing the nearby church (where the women and children were being held) to catch fire accidentally.&lt;ref&gt;Weidinger, Das Reich V, pg. 63&lt;/ref&gt; He also claimed some attempts were made to assist the townspeople by the German soldiers&lt;ref&gt;Weidinger, Das Reich V, pg. 65&lt;/ref&gt; yet many died in the fire. --&gt;One of the six survivors of the massacre, Robert Hebras, described the killings as a deliberate act of [[mass murder]]. In 2013, he told the U.K. newspaper ''[[Daily Mirror|The Mirror]]'' that the SS intentionally burned men, women, and children after locking them in the church and spraying it with machine gun fire:
&lt;blockquote&gt;It was simply an [[summary execution|execution]]. There were a handful of Nazis in front of us, in their uniforms. They just raised their machine guns and started firing across us, at our legs to stop us getting out. They were strafing, not aiming. Men in front of me just started falling. I got caught by several bullets, but I survived because those in front of me got the full impact. I was so lucky. Four of us in the barn managed to get away because we remained completely still under piles of bodies. One man tried to get away before they had gone – he was shot dead. The SS were walking around and shooting anything that moved. They poured petrol on bodies and then set them alight.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.mirror.co.uk/news/world-news/robert-hebras-last-witness-of-nazi-1569947#ixzz31Qazz900&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Marcel Darthout's experience was similar. His testimony appears in historian Sara Farmer's 2000 book ''Martyred Village: Commemorating the 1944 Massacre at Oradour-sur-Glane'':&lt;ref&gt;Farmer, Sarah. Martyred Village: Commemorating the 1944 Massacre at Oradour-sur-Glane. University of California Press, 2000.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;We felt the bullets, which brought me down. I dove... everyone was on top of me. And they were still firing. And there was shouting. And crying. I had a friend who was lying on top of me and who was moaning. And then it was over. No more shots. And they came at us, stepping on us. And with a rifle they finished us off. They finished off my friend who was on top of me. I felt it when he died.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Darthout and Hebras' eyewitness testimony was corroborated by other survivors of the massacre. One other survivor, Roger Godfrin, escaped from the school for refugees despite being shot at by SS soldiers. Only one woman, Marguerite Rouffanche, survived from the church. She later testified that at about five in the afternoon, two German soldiers placed a crate of explosives on the altar and attached a fuse to it. She and another women and her baby hid behind the sacristy; after the explosion they climbed on a stool and jumped out of a window three meters from the ground. A burst of machine gun fire hit all of them, but Rouffanche was able to crawl into the presbytery garden. The woman and infant were killed.&lt;ref&gt;Farmer, Sarah. Martyred Village: Commemorating the 1944 Massacre at Oradour-sur-Glane. University of California Press, 2000.&lt;/ref&gt;

Diekmann was later killed in the battle of Normandy in 1944. On 12 January 1953, a military tribunal in [[Bordeaux]], heard the case against the surviving sixty-five of the approximately two hundred SS soldiers who had been involved. Only twenty-one of them were present. Seven of them were Germans, but fourteen were [[Alsace|Alsatians]], (French nationals of Germanic culture). On 11 February, twenty defendants were found guilty, but were released after only a few months for lack of evidence. In December 2011 German police raided the homes of six former members of the division, all aged 85 or 86, to determine exactly what role the men had played that day.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/europe/exss-soldiers-face-massacre-charges-6272847.html Ex-SS soldiers face massacre charges]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Tulle massacre===
{{Main|Tulle massacre}}
After the Allied second front opened on 6 June 1944, all resistance groups joined &quot;into the uprising&quot;. Part of ''Das Reich'' was ordered to attack strongholds of the rural [[guerrilla warfare|guerrilla]] bands of [[French Resistance]] fighters as it moved to Normandy.&lt;ref&gt;Farmer, Sarah. Martyred Village: Commemorating the 1944 Massacre at Oradour-sur-Glane. University of California Press, 2000, pp. 46, 47.&lt;/ref&gt; After a successful [[Francs-tireurs|FTP]] offensive on 7 and 8 June 1944, ''Das Reich'' was ordered to the Tulle-Limoges area.&lt;ref&gt;Farmer, p. 49.&lt;/ref&gt; The arrival of ''Das Reich'' troops &quot;rescued the beleaguered&quot; army troops and ended the fighting in the city of [[Tulle]].&lt;ref&gt;Farmer, p. 49.&lt;/ref&gt; In reprisal for the German losses, on the following day, the SS hanged 99 men from the town and another 149 were deported back to Germany.&lt;ref&gt;Farmer, p. 49.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Post-war apologia==
Following the war, one of the regimental commander of the division, [[Otto Weidinger]], wrote an [[apologia]] of the division under the auspices of [[HIAG]], the [[Historical revisionism (negationism)|revisionist]] organization and a [[advocacy group|lobby group]] of former Waffen-SS members. The unit narrative was extensive and strived for a so-called official representation of their history, backed by maps and operational orders. &quot;No less than 5 volumes and well over 2,000 pages were devoted to the doings of the 2nd Panzer Division ''Das Reich''&quot;, points out the military historian [[Simon MacKenzie|S.P. MacKenzie]].{{sfn|MacKenzie|1997|p=138}}

The ''Das Reich'' history was published by HIAG's publishing house Munin Verlag. Its express aim was to publish the &quot;war narratives&quot; of former Waffen-SS member, and the titles did not go through the rigorous fact-checking processes common in the traditional historical works; they were revisionist accounts unedited by professional historians and presented the former Waffen-SS members' version of events.{{sfn|Wilke|2011|p=379}} The ''Das Reich'' divisional history, like other HIAG publications, focused on the positive, &quot;heroic&quot; side of National Socialism. The French author Jean-Paul Picaper, who studied the Oradour massacre, notes the tendentious nature of Weidinger's narrative: it provided a sanitized version of history without any references to war crimes.{{sfn|Picaper|2014}}

==Commanders==
* SS-''Sturmbannführer'' [[Wilhelm Kment]], Prior to 1935
* SS-''Obergruppenführer'' [[Paul Hausser]], 19 October 1939 – 14 October 1941
* SS-''Brigadeführer'' [[Wilhelm Bittrich]], 14 October 1941 – 31 December 1941
* SS-''Brigadeführer'' [[Matthias Kleinheisterkamp]], 31 December 1941 – 19 April 1942
* SS-''Gruppenführer'' [[Georg Keppler]], 19 April 1942 – 10 February 1943
* SS-''Brigadeführer'' [[Herbert-Ernst Vahl]], 10 February 1943 – 18 March 1943
* SS-''Standartenführer'' [[Kurt Brasack]], 18 March 1943 – 29 March 1943
* SS-''Gruppenführer'' [[Walter Krüger (SS general)|Walter Krüger]], 29 March 1943 – 23 October 1943
* SS-''Brigadeführer'' [[Heinz Lammerding]], 23 October 1943 – 24 July 1944
* SS-''Obersturmbannführer'' [[Christian Tychsen (Waffen-SS)|Christian Tychsen]], 24 July 1944 – 28 July 1944
* SS-''Oberführer'' [[Otto Baum]], 28 July 1944 – 23 October 1944
* SS-''Brigadeführer'' [[Heinz Lammerding]], 23 October 1944 – 20 January 1945
* SS-''Standartenführer'' [[Karl Kreutz]], 20 January 1945 – 4 February 1945
* SS-''Gruppenführer'' [[Werner Ostendorff]], 4 February 1945 – 9 March 1945
* SS-''Standartenführer'' [[Rudolf Lehmann (SS officer)|Rudolf Lehmann]], 9 March 1945 – 13 April 1945
* SS-''Standartenführer'' [[Karl Kreutz]], 13 April 1945 – 8 May 1945{{citation needed|date=December 2015}}

&lt;!-- Comment out: Uncited from Nov 2015 || ==Order of battle==

===1941 – 1942===

*SS Infantry Regiment ''Deutschland''
*SS Infantry Regiment ''Der Führer''
*11th SS Infantry Regiment
*2nd SS Artillery Regiment
*2nd ''SS [[Sturmgeschütz]]'' Battery
*2nd SS Motorcycle Battalion
*2nd SS Reconnaissance Battalion
*2nd ''SS [[Panzerjäger]]'' (anti-tank) Battalion
*2nd ''SS Pionier'' Battalion
*2nd SS Signal Battalion
*2nd SS Rocket Battalion
*2nd SS Supply Battalion
*2nd SS Medical Battalion
*2nd SS Reserve Battalion

===1944 – 1945===
*2nd SS Panzer Regiment
*3rd SS Panzer Grenadier Regiment ''Deutschland''
*4th SS Panzer Grenadier Regiment ''Der Führer''
*2nd SS Panzer Artillery Regiment
*2nd SS Motorcycle Battalion
*2nd ''SS [[Sturmgeschütz]]'' Battalion
*2nd SS Reconnaissance Battalion
*2nd ''SS [[Panzerjäger]]'' Battalion
*2nd ''SS [[Flak]]'' Battalion
*2nd ''SS Pionier'' Battalion
*2nd SS Signal Battalion
*2nd SS Rocket Launcher Battalion
*2nd SS Supply Battalion
*2nd SS Maintenance Battalion
*2nd SS Medical Battalion --&gt;

==See also==
* [[List of Knight's Cross Recipients 2nd SS Panzer Division Das Reich]]

==References==
===Citations===
{{reflist|30em}}

===Bibliography===
{{refbegin}}
* US Tank Battles in France 1944-45 by Steven Zaloga
* {{cite book | last = Bessel | first = Richard | authorlink = Richard Bessel | title = Nazism and War | publisher = Modern Library | location = New York | year = 2006 | isbn = 978-0-81297-557-4 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book
 | last = Clark
 | first = Lloyd
 | title = Kursk: The Greatest Battle: Eastern Front 1943
 | publisher = Headline Publishing Group
 | location = London
 | year = 2012
 | isbn = 978-0-7553-3639-5
 | ref = harv
 }}
* {{cite book | last = Flaherty | first = T.H. | title = The Third Reich: The SS | publisher = Time-Life Books | year = 2004 | origyear = 1988 | isbn = 1-84447-073-3 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite journal
 | last = Glantz
 | first = David M.
 | authorlink = David Glantz
 | title = Soviet Defensive Tactics at Kursk, July 1943
 | journal = U.S. Army Command and General Staff College
 | location= Ft. Belvoir
 |date=September 1986
 | volume = Soviet Army Studies Office Combined Arms Center Combat Studies Institute
 | issue = CSI Report No. 11
 | url = http://www.cgsc.edu/carl/download/csipubs/glantz2.pdf
 | oclc = 320412485
 | ref = harv
 }}
* {{cite book
 | last = Glantz
 | first = David M.
 | title = Soviet Military Intelligence in War
 | publisher = Taylor &amp; Francis
 | year = 2013
 | location = London
 | isbn = 978-1-136-28934-7
 | ref = harv
}}
* {{Cite book | last=MacKenzie | first=S.P. | authorlink=Simon MacKenzie | year=1997 | title=Revolutionary Armies in the Modern Era: A Revisionist Approach | url=https://www.routledge.com/products/9780415867771 | location=New York | publisher=Routledge | isbn=978-0-415-09690-4 | ref = harv }}
* [[Charles B. MacDonald|MacDonald, Charles B.]] ''[http://www.history.army.mil/books/wwii/Siegfried/Siegfried%20Line/siegfried-fm.htm The Siegfried Line Campaign (Publication 7-7)]''. Retrieved July 24, 2016.
* {{cite book | last = McNab | first = Chris | title = Hitler's Elite: The SS 1939–45 | publisher = Osprey | year = 2013 | isbn = 978-1-78200-088-4 | ref = harv }} 
* {{Cite book | last=Picaper | first=Jean-Paul | year=2014 | title=Les Ombres d'Oradour: 10 Juin 1944 | trans_title=The Shadows of Oradour: 10 June 1944 | language = French | location= Paris | publisher=Éditions l'Archipel | isbn=978-2-8098-1467-5 |ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last = Penaud | first = Guy | title = La Das Reich : 2e SS Panzer-Division | year = 2005 | publisher = Lauze | location = Périgueux | language = French | isbn = 978-2-912032-76-8 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Shirer | first = William L. | authorlink = William L. Shirer | title = [[The Rise and Fall of the Third Reich]] | publisher = Simon &amp; Schuster | location = New York | year = 1960 | isbn = 978-0-671-62420-0 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last = Stein | first = George H. | title = The Waffen SS: Hitler's Elite Guard at War, 1939–1945 | publisher = Cornell University Press | location = Ithaca, NY | year = 1984 | isbn = 0-8014-9275-0 | ref = harv }}
* {{cite book | last = Wilke | first = Karsten  | authorlink = | year = 2011 | title = Die &quot;Hilfsgemeinschaft auf Gegenseitigkeit&quot; (HIAG) 1950–1990: Veteranen der Waffen-SS in der Bundesrepublik |trans_title = HIAG 1950–1990: Waffen-SS veterans in the Federal Republic | location = Paderborn | language = German| publisher = Schoeningh Ferdinand GmbH | isbn = 978-3-506-77235-0 |ref=harv}}
{{refend}}
{{SS Divisions}}
{{German Armoured Divisions of World War II}}
{{Knight's Cross recipients of the 2nd SS PD}}
{{Authority control}}
{{Subject bar
| portal1=Military of Germany
| portal2=Tank
| portal3=World War II
| commons=y
| commons-search=Category:2nd SS Panzer Division Das Reich
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:2nd SS Panzer Division Das Reich}}
[[Category:Panzer divisions of the Waffen-SS]]
[[Category:Military units and formations established in 1939]]
[[Category:Military units and formations disestablished in 1945]]
[[Category:German units in Normandy]]
[[Category:1939 establishments in Germany]]</text>
      <sha1>1igyd300dtms2klcwwpe1vyjxzvi0wk</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
