<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>416th Air Expeditionary Wing</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9406442</id>
    <revision>
      <id>741846345</id>
      <parentid>738523927</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-30T01:12:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 0 sources and tagging 1 as dead. #IABot (v1.2.4)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="29605">{{Use American English|date=December 2015}}
{{Infobox military unit
|unit_name= 416th Air Expeditionary Wing
|image=[[File:416thaeg-c17-landing.jpg|300px]]
|caption=A 416th Air Expeditionary Group airman positions a fire bottle while preparing a C-17 Globemaster III for parking
|dates= 1943–1945; 1962–1995; 2002–2005
|country={{flag|United States|23px}}
|allegiance=
|branch={{air force|USA}}
|type= Air Expeditionary
|role= Combat Support
|size=
|command_structure=
|current_commander=
|garrison=
|motto=
|colors=
&lt;!-- Insignia --&gt;
|identification_symbol=[[File:416th Bombardment Wing.PNG|175px]]
|identification_symbol_label=416th Air Expeditionary Wing emblem &lt;small&gt;(approved 2 March 1964)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name=Ravenstein&gt;Ravenstein, pp. 223–224&lt;/ref&gt;
|identification_symbol_2=5H (668th Bomb Sq) 2A (669th Bomb Sq) F6 (670th Bomb Sq) 5C (671st Bomb Sq)&lt;ref name=Watkins&gt;Watkins, pp. 118–119&lt;/ref&gt;
|identification_symbol_2_label=World War II Fuselage Identification Codes
|identification_symbol_3=GR
|identification_symbol_3_label=ACC tail marking at Griffiss AFB)&lt;ref&gt;Rogers{{page needed|date=March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|march=
|mascot=
|decorations=[[Distinguished Unit Citation]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Air Force Outstanding Unit Award]]
|battles=[[European Theatre of World War II|European Theater of World War II]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Southwest Asia Service Medal|Southwest Asia]]
|anniversaries=
}}
The '''416th Air Expeditionary Wing''' (AEW) is a provisional unit assigned to the [[Air Combat Command]] of the [[United States Air Force]] to activate or inactivate as needed.

The wing began life in [[World War II]] as the '''416th Bombardment Group''' (BG).  The group was a [[Douglas A-20 Havoc]] light bomb [[group (military aviation unit)|group]] assigned to [[Ninth Air Force]] in [[Western Europe]]. It was awarded a [[Distinguished Unit Citation]] for its actions in France when, in spite of intense resistance, the group bombed bridges, railways, rolling stock, and a radar station to disrupt the German retreat through the Falaise-Argentan gap.  It converted to [[Douglas A-26 Invader]]s while engaged in combat and continued to support ground forces through the end of the war.

The group's heritage was continued by the '''416th Bombardment Wing''' (BW), a [[Strategic Air Command]] [[B-52 Stratofortress]] [[wing (military aviation unit)|wing]] that conducted strategic bombardment training and air refueling operations on a global scale based at [[Griffiss Air Force Base]] in New York. 416th BW crews and aircraft deployed to the Pacific during the [[Vietnam War]] era to support SAC operations during the conflict.  In 1984, the wing and group were consolidated and became a single unit. In 1991, wing crews and aircraft participated in the war in Southwest Asia.  The 416th was inactivated as part of the Post-[[Cold War]] drawdown of United States strategic forces in 1995 (BRAC 1993) and the closure of [[Griffiss AFB]].

In 2002 the wing was converted to provisional status as the '''416th Air Expeditionary Group''' It served as the host unit at [[Karshi-Khanabad Air Base]] (K2), in [[Qarshi]], Uzbekistan, from 2002 to 2005, where it supported operations against the [[Taliban]] and [[al-Qaeda]] in Afghanistan.  It was redesignated as the '''416th Air Expeditionary Wing''' in 2010, but the current status of this unit is not publicly known.

==History==

===World War II===
{{Commonscat-inline|416th Bombardment Group (United States Army Air Forces)|416th Bombardment Group}}
[[File:416thbg-a20-d-day.jpg|thumb|A-20 from the 416th Bomb Group making a bomb run on D-Day, 6 June 1944]]
[[File:416thbg-a20flight.jpg|thumb|Flight of A-20 from the 416th Bomb Group making a bomb run]]
[[File:416th Bombardment Group Douglas A-26 Invader 1945.jpg|thumb|416th Bombardment Group Douglas A-26 Invader, Laon/Athies Airfield (A-69), France, 1945]]

====Training in the United States====
The [[wing (military aviation unit)|wing]] was first activated on 5 February 1943&lt;ref name=Maurer299&gt;Maurer, ''Combat Units'', pp. 299–300&lt;/ref&gt; without personnel, at [[Will Rogers Field]], Oklahoma as the '''416th Bombardment Group''' (Light) (BG).&lt;ref group=note&gt;The authority for the organization of this group was contained in General Orders #3, Headquarter Army Air Base, Will Rogers Field, Oklahoma, 4 February 1943.&lt;/ref&gt; The original [[squadron (aviation)|squadrons]] of the [[group (military aviation unit)|group]] were the [[668th Bombardment Squadron|668th]],&lt;ref name=Maurer668&gt;Maurer, ''Combat Squadrons'', p. 698&lt;/ref&gt; [[669th Bombardment Squadron|669th]],&lt;ref name=Maurer669&gt;Maurer, ''Combat Squadrons'', pp. 698-699&lt;/ref&gt; [[670th Bombardment Squadron|670th]],&lt;ref name=Maurer670&gt;Maurer, ''Combat Squadrons'', pp. 699-700&lt;/ref&gt; and [[671st Bombardment Squadron]]s&lt;ref name=Maurer671&gt;Maurer, ''Combat Squadrons'', pp. 700&lt;/ref&gt;

Fifty-one officers and two hundred and forty-one (241) enlisted men were transferred to the group on 15 February 1943. The source of the [[en cadre|cadre]] was the [[46th Bombardment Group]] and units from Will Rogers Field; [[Blythe AAF]], California; [[Barksdale Field]], Louisiana and a number of men with considerable overseas experience from the [[Third Air Force]] Replacement Center, Plant Park, Florida. On that date, the 46th BG moved to the North side of Will Rogers Field, leaving the South side to the 416th BG.{{Citation needed|reason=need support for cadre and transfer information|date=February 2013}}

The group originally operated as an Operational Training Unit under the [[III Air Support Command]], providing a portion of the initial cadre of the [[417th Bombardment Group]].&lt;ref&gt;Green &amp; Keane, p. 18&lt;/ref&gt; The group fell back on the 46th BG for assistance with its training. Pilots were attached to the 46th BG for transition flying during the first three months of its existence. On 11 May, the first eight (8) planes were assigned to the 416th Group. One [[North American B-25|North American B-25C Mitchell]] and one [[Douglas A-20|Douglas A-20B Havoc]] was given to each of the 668th and 669th Squadrons. Two A-20B's were assigned to each of the 670th and 671st Squadrons. Classes in all the military occupational specialties were conducted by the 46th until 1 June 1943. The Pilots attended Ground School, for five hours a day, in the following subjects: code, link trainer, aircraft recognition, operation and maintenance of the A-20 and B-25, air navigation, radio, instrument procedure, etc. The Intelligence personnel attended classes for one hour a day.{{Citation needed|reason=need support for paragraph|date=February 2013}}

====Combat in the European Theater====
The [[bombardment group]] moved to England in January to February 1944, and was assigned to [[Ninth Air Force]].  It entered combat in March 1944, and during the next several weeks directed most of its attacks against [[V-1 flying bomb|V-1]] and [[V-2]] sites in France.&lt;ref name=Maurer299/&gt; In addition to the assigned code markings assigned to each of its squadrons, the 416th's aircraft were marked with a &quot;white diagonal stripe emanating outwards from the [trailing] edge of the&amp;nbsp;... rudder.&quot;&lt;ref name=Watkins/&gt;  The 416th flew a number of missions against [[airfield]]s and [[Coastal defence and fortification|coastal defenses]] to help prepare for the [[invasion of Normandy]].  It supported the invasion in June 1944 by striking road junctions, [[marshalling yard]], bridges, and railway overpasses.  The group assisted ground forces at [[Caen]] and [[Saint-Lô]] in July and at [[Brest, France|Brest]] later in the summer, by hitting transportation facilities, supply dumps, [[radar]] installations, and other targets. In spite of intense resistance, the group bombed bridges, railways, rolling stock, and a radar station to disrupt the enemy's retreat through the Falaise gap, 6–9 August 1944, and received a [[Distinguished Unit Citation]] for the missions.&lt;ref name=Maurer299/&gt;

The group assisted the [[Operation Market Garden|airborne attack on the Netherlands]] in September. It also supported the assault on the [[Siegfried Line]] by pounding transportation, warehouses, supply dumps, and defended villages in Germany.&lt;ref name=Maurer299/&gt; in November, the group converted to [[Douglas A-26 Invader]] aircraft. With its new aircraft it attacked transportation facilities, strong points, communications centers, and troop concentrations during the [[Battle of the Bulge]] from December 1944 through January 1945. It aided the [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] thrust into Germany by continuing its strikes against transportation, communications, airfields, storage depots, and other objectives, February—May 1945. It also bombed flak positions in support of the airborne assault across the Rhine in March 1945.&lt;ref name=Maurer299/&gt;  The group returned to the US between July and October 1945 and was inactivated at the Port of Embarkation on 24 October 1945.

===Cold War===

====4039th Strategic Wing====
&lt;!-- linked from redirect [[4039th Strategic Wing]] --&gt;
[[File:Boeing B-52G in flight 061026-F-1234S-021.jpg|thumb|Boeing B-52G Stratofortress]]
[[File:Wing 4039th Strategic.gif|thumb|125px|left|4039th Strategic Wing Patch]]
The origins of the 416th Bombardment Wing begin on 1 August 1958 when [[Strategic Air Command]] established the '''4039th Strategic Wing''' at [[Griffiss AFB]], New York&lt;ref name=&quot;Mueller205&quot;&gt;Mueller, pp. 205–210&lt;/ref&gt; as part of SAC's plan to disperse its [[B-52 Stratofortress]] heavy bombers over a larger number of bases, thus making it more difficult for the [[Soviet Union]] to knock out the entire fleet with a surprise first strike.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.airforcehistoryindex.org/data/001/056/917.xml|last1=|first1=|title=Abstract (Unclassified), Vol 1, History of Strategic Air Command, Jan-Jun 1957 (Secret)|date=|publisher=Air Force History Index|deadurl=no |accessdate=4 March 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The wing remained a headquarters only until 5 January 1959 when the [[41st Air Refueling Squadron]], flying [[Boeing KC-135 Stratotanker]]s and three maintenance squadrons were activated and assigned to the wing and the wing was transferred from [[Eighth Air Force]] to the [[820th Air Division]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.afhra.af.mil/factsheets/factsheet.asp?id=10159 |title=Factsheet 820 Strategic Aerospace Division |publisher=Air Force Historical Research Agency |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20121030120240/http://www.afhra.af.mil/factsheets/factsheet.asp?id=10159 |date=11 October 2007|archivedate=30 October 2012|accessdate=5 March 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;  In July, the '''56th Aviation Depot Squadron''' was activated to oversee the wing's special weapons. It became fully organized on 15 October 1959 when the [[75th Bombardment Squadron]] (BS), consisting of 15 [[Boeing B-52 Stratofortress]]es moved to Griffiss from [[Loring AFB]], Maine where it had been one of the three squadrons of the [[42d Bombardment Wing]]. Starting in 1960, one third of the squadron's aircraft were maintained on fifteen-minute [[alert state|alert]], fully fueled and ready for combat to reduce vulnerability to a Soviet missile strike.  This was increased to half the squadron's aircraft in 1962.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.airforcehistoryindex.org/data/001/010/802.xml|last1=|first1=|title=Abstract (Unclassified), History of the Strategic Bomber since 1945 (Top Secret, downgraded to Secret)|date=1 April 1975|publisher=Air Force History Index|deadurl=no |accessdate=4 March 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 4039th (and later the 416th) continued to maintain an alert commitment until December 1991.&lt;ref name=416AEWfacts&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.afhra.af.mil/factsheets/factsheet.asp?id=16598 |last1=Kane|first1=Robert B.|title=Factsheet 416 Air Expeditionary Wing (ACC)|date=6 April 2010|publisher=Air Force Historical Research Agency|deadurl=no |accessdate=4 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;  On 1 April 1961 the wing was reassigned from the 820th to the [[6th Air Division]], which was activated at Dow.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.afhra.af.mil/factsheets/factsheet.asp?id=10056 |title=Factsheet 6 Air Division |publisher=Air Force Historical Research Agency |archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20121030120133/http://www.afhra.af.mil/factsheets/factsheet.asp?id=10056 |date=4 October 2007|archivedate=30 October 2012|accessdate=5 March 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;   In 1962, the wing [[bomber]]s began to be equipped with the [[GAM-77 Hound Dog]] and the [[GAM-72 Quail]] air-launched [[cruise missiles]], The '''4039th Airborne Missile Maintenance Squadron''' was activated in November to maintain these missiles.  However, SAC Strategic Wings could not carry a permanent history or lineage and SAC looked for a way to make its Strategic Wings permanent.

====416th Bombardment Wing====
[[File:Boeing B-52H Stratofortress, USA - Air Force AN1572112.jpg|thumb|416th Wing B-52H]]
In 1962, in order to perpetuate the lineage of many currently inactive bombardment units with illustrious [[World War II]] records, Headquarters SAC received authority from Headquarters USAF to discontinue its Major Command controlled (MAJCON) strategic wings that were equipped with combat aircraft and to activate Air Force controlled (AFCON) units, most of which were inactive at the time which could carry a lineage and history.

The 4039th SW was replaced by the newly constituted '''416th Bombardment Wing''' (416th BW) on 1 February 1963&lt;ref name=Ravenstein/&gt; and was assigned to SAC's 6th Air Division.&lt;ref group=note&gt;Although the 416th Wing was a new organization, it continued, through temporary bestowal, the history, and honors of the World War II 416th Bombardment Group.  It was also entitled to retain the honors (but not the history or lineage) of the 4039th.  This temporary bestowal ended in January 1984, when the wing and group were consolidated into a single unit.&lt;/ref&gt;  The 75th BS was also replaced by the [[668th Bombardment Squadron]], one of the unit's [[World War II]] historical bombardment squadrons.  The '''41st Air Refueling Squadron''' and '''56th Munitions Maintenance Squadron''' transferred to the 416th.  The 4039th's maintenance and security [[squadron (aviation)|squadrons]] were replaced by ones with the 416th numerical designation of the newly established wing.  Each of the new units assumed the personnel, equipment, and mission of its predecessor.  Under the Dual Deputate organization, all components were directly assigned to the wing, no operational or maintenance group element was activated. The history, lineage and honors of the '''416th Bombardment Group''' were temporarily bestowed upon the newly established wing upon activation.

The 416th Bomb Wing continued to conduct strategic bombardment training and air refueling operations to meet operational commitments of [[Strategic Air Command]], including deployments to [[Southeast Asia]] during the [[Vietnam War]] with tankers and crews from December 1964 through December 1975 and with [[bomber]] crews from June 1968 through 1975.&lt;ref name=Ravenstein/&gt; The 416th BW assumed host wing responsibility at Griffiss AFB, New York on 1 July 1970,&lt;ref name=Ravenstein/&gt; when the [[military airbase|base]] was transferred from [[Air Force Systems Command]] to SAC.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mueller205&quot;/&gt;

In 1988, the wing began to prepare for a primarily conventional warfare role.&lt;ref name=&quot;416AEWfacts&quot;/&gt;  In June 1990, the wing added a second air refueling squadron when the [[509th Air Refueling Squadron]] moved to Griffiss from [[Pease AFB]], New Hampshire and became part of the wing.  Shortly afterward, in August, it began to deploy KC-135s to [[Seeb International Airport]] and B-52s to Spain, Diego Garcia, and England. From January to April 1991 the wing flew combat missions in Southwest Asia.&lt;ref name=416AEWfacts/&gt;

In September 1991, the wing ended its support of worldwide [[aerial refueling|air refueling]] operations.&lt;ref name=416AEWfacts/&gt;  The wing was assigned to [[Air Combat Command]] (ACC) after inactivation of SAC on 1 June 1992 and its refueling squadrons were assigned to the [[380th Operations Group]] of [[Air Mobility Command]].&lt;ref name=509WSfacts&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.afhra.af.mil/factsheets/factsheet.asp?id=10803 |last1=Bailey|first1=Carl E.|title=Factsheet 509 Weapons Squadron (AMC)|date=19 December 2007|publisher=Air Force Historical Research Agency|deadurl=no |accessdate=5 February 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Wing aircraft carried ACC Tail Code &quot;GR&quot;.  The wing was inactivated in 1995 due to closure of Griffiss AFB.  The 416th transferred the last two of its B-52Hs to the [[5th Bomb Wing]] at [[Minot AFB]], North Dakota on 15 November 1994 in preparation for inactivation in 1995 with the closure of Griffiss AFB.&lt;ref name=416AEWfacts/&gt;

===Post Cold War era===
[[File:USAF - 416th Air Expeditionary Group.png|thumb|125px|left|Unofficial Emblem used by 416th Air Expeditionary Group]][[File:Russian-built Antonov AN-12.JPEG|thumb|A 416th Air Expeditionary Group airman gives directions to the crew of a Russian-built AN-12 cargo plane at Karshi-Khanabad AB]]
The wing became a provisional air [[expeditionary warfare|expeditionary]] group as part of the [[Global War on Terrorism]] in 2002. It was assigned to [[Uzbekistan]] as an [[Air Combat Command]] unit in early 2002. There it operated the base, which was used for transshipments of cargo and supplies from United States, for onward tactical [[airlift]] to combat forces in Afghanistan fighting [[Taliban]] and [[Al-Qaeda]] forces. The group was inactivated in November 2005 after the Uzbek government requested the United States withdraw its forces from their territory.  In 2010, the group was upgraded to wing but is not known to have been active under that designation.

==Lineage==
'''416th Bombardment Group'''
* Constituted as '''416th Bombardment Group''' (Light) on 25 January 1943
: Activated on 5 February 1943
: Redesignated '''416th Bombardment Group''', Light on 20 August 1943
: Inactivated on 24 October 1945&lt;ref name=Maurer299/&gt;
* Consolidated with the '''416th Bombardment Wing''', Heavy on 31 January 1984 as the '''416th Bombardment Wing''', Heavy&lt;ref name=416AEWfacts/&gt;

'''416th Bombardment Wing'''
* Constituted as '''416th Bombardment Wing''', Heavy, on 15 November 1962
: Activated on 15 November 1962
: Organized on 1 February 1963
: Consolidated with the '''416th Bombardment Group''', Light on 31 January 1984&lt;ref name=Ravenstein/&gt;
: Redesignated '''416th Wing''' on 1 September 1991
: Redesignated '''416th Bomb Wing''' on 1 June 1992
: Inactivated on 30 September 1995
* Redesignated '''416th Air Expeditionary Group''', and converted to provisional status, on 3 May 2002
: Redesignated '''416th Air Expeditionary Wing''' on 23 February 2010&lt;ref name=416AEWfacts/&gt;

===Assignments===
{{Col-begin}}
{{Col-break|width=50%}}
* III Air Support Command, 5 February 1943
* [[III Bomber Command]] (attached to [[II Tactical Air Division]] 1 Nov 1943 – 22 Nov 1943), 6 August 1943
* [[IX Bomber Command]] ''ca''. 1 February 1944
* [[97th Combat Bombardment Wing]] (later 97th Bombardment Wing) (under operational control of [[99th Combat Bombardment Wing]] until 20 March 1944, IX Bomber Command, 11–18 September 1944, 99th Combat Bombardment Wing – 28 September 1944), 4 February 1944
*  Assembly Area Command, c. 27 July 1945 – 24 October 1945
* Strategic Air Command, 15 November 1962
{{Col-break|width=50%}}
* 6th Air Division, 1 February 1963
* [[57th Air Division]], 2 July 1966
* [[817th Air Division]], 2 September 1966
* [[45th Air Division]], 2 July 1969
* [[40th Air Division]], 30 June 1971
* 45th Air Division, 1 July 1973
* 40th Air Division, 1 December 1982
* [[Eighth Air Force]], 8 June 1988 – 30 September 1995
* [[Air Combat Command]] to activate or inactivate any time after September 2001&lt;ref name=416AEWfacts/&gt;
: Attached to: [[United States Central Command Air Forces]], 2002–2005
{{Col-end}}

===Components===
'''Groups'''
* 416th Combat Support Group (later 416th Support Group),&lt;ref name=&quot;Mueller205&quot;/&gt; 1 July 1970 – 30 September 1995
* 416th Logistics Group, 1 September 1991 – 30 September 1995
* 416th Operations Group, 1 September 1991 – 30 September 1995

'''Operational Squadrons'''
* 41st Air Refueling Squadron: 1 February 1963 – 1 September 1991&lt;ref name=416AEWfacts/&gt;
* 509th Air Refueling Squadron: 30 June 1990 – 1 September 1991&lt;ref name=509WSfacts/&gt;
* 668th Bombardment Squadron: 5 February 1943 – 24 October 1945; 1 February 1963 – 1 September 1991&lt;ref name=&quot;Maurer668&quot;/&gt;
* 669th Bombardment Squadron: 5 February 1943 – 24 October 1945&lt;ref name=&quot;Maurer669&quot;/&gt;
* 670th Bombardment Squadron: 5 February 1943 – 24 October 1945&lt;ref name=&quot;Maurer670&quot;/&gt;
* 671st Bombardment Squadron: 5 February 1943 – 24 October 1945&lt;ref name=&quot;Maurer671&quot;/&gt;

'''Support Squadrons'''
* 56th Munitions Maintenance Squadron, 1 February 1963 – 1 October 1972&lt;ref name=Mueller205/&gt;
* 416th Airborne Missile Maintenance Squadron, 1 February 1963 – 30 September 1974&lt;ref name=Mueller205/&gt;
* 416th Armament &amp; Electronics Maintenance Squadron (later 416th Avionics Maintenance Squadron, 416th Intermediate Level Maintenance Squadron), 1 February 1963 – 1 September 1991&lt;ref name=Mueller205/&gt;
* 416th Combat Defense Squadron (later 416th Security Police Squadron), 1 February 1963 – 1 July 1970&lt;ref name=Mueller205/&gt;
* 416th Field Maintenance Squadron,&lt;ref name=Mueller205/&gt; 1 February 1963 – 1 September 1991
* 416th Munitions Maintenance Squadron,&lt;ref name=Mueller205/&gt; 1 October 1972 – 1 September 1991
* 416th Organizational Maintenance Squadron,&lt;ref name=Mueller205/&gt; 1 February 1963 – 1 September 1991

'''Detachments'''
* Detachment 1
: [[Otis AFB]] Massachusetts 2 Alert KC-135A's (Shared with Detachment), [[99th Bombardment Wing]] from [[Westover AFB]], Massachusetts also with 2 Alert KC-135A's,{{Citation needed|reason=need support for aircraft|date=February 2013}} 2 April 1969 – 31 December 1971
* Detachment{{Citation needed|reason=need support for detachment|date=February 2013}}
: Minot AFB, North Dakota 2 Alert B-52G's &amp; 2 KC-135A's (Shared with a Detachment [[380th Bombardment Wing]] from [[Plattsburgh AFB]], New York with 2 Alert KC-135A's Relocated after April 1972 but prior to October 1973 Attached to the [[5th Bombardment Wing]]

===Stations===
{{Col-begin}}
{{Col-break|width=50%}}
* Will Rogers Field, Oklahoma, 5 February 1943
* [[Lake Charles Army Air Field]], Louisiana, 4 June 1943
* [[Laurel Army Airfield]], Mississippi, November 1943 - 1 January 1944
* [[RAF Wethersfield]] (AAF-170),&lt;ref&gt;Station number from Anderson&lt;/ref&gt; England, 1 February 1944
* [[Melun/Villaroche Airfield]] (A-55),&lt;ref name=Johnson&gt;Station number from Johnson&lt;/ref&gt; France, 23 September 1944
* [[Laon/Athies Airfield]] (A-69),&lt;ref name=Johnson/&gt; France, ''ca''. 12 February 1945
{{Col-break|width=50%}}
* [[Cormeilles en Vexin Airfield]] (A-59), France,&lt;ref name=Johnson/&gt; 24 May 1945
* [[Cambrai]], France, ''ca''. 15 July 1945
* Camp Chicago, France, 27 July 1945 – September&lt;ref group=note&gt;Located near Laon&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Camp Myles Standish]], Massachusetts, 23 October 1945 – 24 October 1945
* [[Griffiss AFB]], New York, 15 November 1962 – 30 September 1995&lt;ref name=416AEWfacts/&gt;
* [[Karshi-Khanabad Air Base]] (K2), Uzbekistan, 2002–November 2005.
{{Col-end}}

===Aircraft===
{{Col-begin}}
{{Col-break|width=50%}}
* [[Douglas A-20 Havoc]], 1943, 1944–1945&lt;ref name=416AEWfacts/&gt;
* [[Douglas A-26 Invader]], 1944–1945&lt;ref name=416AEWfacts/&gt;
{{Col-break|width=50%}}
* [[Boeing B-52 Stratofortress]]&lt;ref name=416AEWfacts/&gt; (B-52G, 1963–1991; B-52H, 1991–1995)
* [[Boeing KC-135 Stratotanker]]&lt;ref name=416AEWfacts/&gt; (KC-135A, 1963–1990; KC-135R, 1990–1993)
* [[Cessna T-37 Tweet]], 1993–1995{{Citation needed|reason=need support for aircraft|date=February 2013}}
{{Col-end}}

==Awards and Campaigns==
{{unit awards table
|award_image1=AF PUC
|award_name1=[[Distinguished Unit Citation]]
|award_date1=6 August 1944 – 9 August 1944
|award_notes1=France, 416th Bombardment Group&lt;ref name=Maurer299/&gt;
|award_image2=AF OUA w/ v
|award_name2=[[Air Force Outstanding Unit Award]] w/[[Combat &quot;V&quot; Device]]
|award_date2=1 July 2004 – 31 May 2005
|award_notes2=416th Air Expeditionary Group&lt;ref name=AFAP&gt;[http://access.afpc.af.mil/AwardsDMZ/SearchAwards.aspx Air Force Recognition Programs]{{dead link|date=September 2016 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }} searchable page (retrieved 5 February 2013)&lt;/ref&gt;
|award_image3=AF OUA w/ v
|award_name3=[[Air Force Outstanding Unit Award]] w/[[Combat &quot;V&quot; Device]]
|award_date3=1 June 2005 – 31 May 2006
|award_notes3=416th Air Expeditionary Group&lt;ref name=AFAP/&gt;
|award_image4=AF OUA
|award_name4=[[Air Force Outstanding Unit Award]]
|award_date4=15 September 1981 – 31 October 1982
|award_notes4=416th Bombardment Wing&lt;ref name=416AEWfacts/&gt;
|award_image5=AF OUA
|award_name5=[[Air Force Outstanding Unit Award]]
|award_date5=1 July 1984 – 30 June 1986
|award_notes5=416th Bombardment Wing&lt;ref name=416AEWfacts/&gt;
|award_image6=AF OUA
|award_name6=[[Air Force Outstanding Unit Award]]
|award_date6=1 July 1989 – 30 June 1991
|award_notes6=416th Bombardment Wing&lt;ref name=416AEWfacts/&gt;
}}

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|- bgcolor=&quot;#efefef&quot;
! Campaign Streamer
! Campaign
! Dates
! Notes
|-
|[[File:European-African-Middle Eastern Campaign Medal streamer.png|200px]]||Air Offensive, Europe||1 February 1944 – 5 June 1944||416th Bombardment Group&lt;ref name=Maurer299/&gt;
|-
|[[File:European-African-Middle Eastern Campaign Medal streamer.png|200px]]||Normandy||6 June 1944 – 24 July 1944||416th Bombardment Group&lt;ref name=Maurer299/&gt;
|-
|[[File:European-African-Middle Eastern Campaign Medal streamer.png|200px]]||Northern France||25 July 1944 – 14 September 1944||416th Bombardment Group&lt;ref name=Maurer299/&gt;
|-
|[[File:European-African-Middle Eastern Campaign Medal streamer.png|200px]]||Rhineland||5 September 1944 – 21 March 1945||416th Bombardment Group&lt;ref name=Maurer299/&gt;
|-
|[[File:European-African-Middle Eastern Campaign Medal streamer.png|200px]]||Ardennes-Alsace||6 December 1944 – 25 January 1945||416th Bombardment Group&lt;ref name=Maurer299/&gt;
|-
|[[File:European-African-Middle Eastern Campaign Medal streamer.png|200px]]||Central Europe||22 March 1944 – 21 May 1945||416th Bombardment Group&lt;ref name=Maurer299/&gt;
|-
|[[File:Streamer SAS.PNG|200px]]||Defense of Saudi Arabia||||416th Air Expeditionary Group&lt;ref name=416AEWfacts/&gt;
|-
|[[File:Streamer SAS.PNG|200px]]||Liberation of Kuwait||||416th Air Expeditionary Group&lt;ref name=416AEWfacts/&gt;
|}

==See also==
{{Portal|United States Air Force|Military of the United States|World War II}}
* [[List of B-52 Units of the United States Air Force]]

==References==

===Notes===
{{reflist|group=note}}

===Citations===
{{Reflist|2}}

===Bibliography===
{{Air Force Historical Research Agency}}
* {{cite book|last=Anderson|first=Capt. Barry|title= Army Air Forces Stations: A Guide to the Stations Where U.S. Army Air Forces Personnel Served in the United Kingdom During World War II|url=http://www.afhra.af.mil./shared/media/document/AFD-081010-027.pdf |accessdate= 7 July 2012|year=1985|publisher=Research Division, USAF Historical Research Center|location=Maxwell AFB, AL |page= }}
* {{cite book|last=Green|first=Eugene L.|author2=Keane, Paul A. |author3=Callanan, Lewis E.|title=The Sky Lancer: The 417th Bomb Group |url= http://digicom.bpl.lib.me.us/ww_reg_his/75 |accessdate=28 September 2013|series=Bangor Public Library World War Regimental Histories No. 75|year=1946 |publisher=John Sands Pty., Ltd.|location=Sydney, NSW, Australia|isbn= |page=}}
* {{cite book|last=Johnson|first=1st Lt. David C.|title=U.S. Army Air Forces Continental Airfields (ETO) D-Day to V-E Day|url=   http://www.afhra.af.mil/shared/media/document/AFD-081010-026.pdf  |accessdate= |year=1988|publisher=Research Division, USAF Historical Research Center|location=Maxwell AFB, AL|page= }}
* {{cite book|editor=Maurer, Maurer|title=Air Force Combat Units of World War II|origyear= 1961|url= http://newpreview.afnews.af.mil/shared/media/document/AFD-100921-044.pdf |edition=reprint|year=1983|publisher=Office of Air Force History|location=Washington, DC|isbn=0-912799-02-1|lccn=61060979|pages=}}
* {{cite book|editor=Maurer, Maurer|title=Combat Squadrons of the Air Force, World War II|origyear=1969|url= http://www.afhso.af.mil/shared/media/document/AFD-101202-002.pdf|edition= reprint|year=1982|publisher=Office of Air Force History|location=Washington, DC|isbn=0-405-12194-6|oclc=72556|lccn=70605402|pages= }}
* {{cite book|last=Mueller|first=Robert|title=Air Force Bases, Vol. I, Active Air Force Bases Within the United States of America on 17 September 1982|url= http://www.afhso.af.mil/shared/media/document/AFD-100921-026.pdf |year=1989|publisher=Office of Air Force History|location=Washington, DC|isbn=0-912799-53-6|page=  }}
* {{cite book|last=Ravenstein|first=Charles A.|title=Air Force Combat Wings, Lineage &amp; Honors Histories 1947-1977|url= http://www.afhso.af.mil/shared/media/document/AFD-100921-047.pdf|year=1984|publisher=Office of Air Force History|location=Washington, DC|isbn=0-912799-12-9|pages=}}
* {{cite book|last=Watkins|first=Robert|title=Battle Colors|volume=Volume III Insignia and Markings of the Ninth Air Force In World War II|year=2008|publisher=Shiffer Publishing Ltd.|location=Atglen, PA|isbn=978-0-7643-2938-8|page= }}

{{USAF Air Combat Command}}
{{Strategic Air Command}}
{{USAAF 9th Air Force UK}}
{{USAAF 3d Air Force World War II}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2011}}

[[Category:Air expeditionary wings of the United States Air Force|0416]]</text>
      <sha1>ref45z4py74vjla5uhou2lfr9y9rx8d</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
