<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>A. Lorne Campbell</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>44097574</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750223940</id>
      <parentid>750223772</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-18T13:04:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mr Serjeant Buzfuz</username>
        <id>10643005</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>copyedits</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="13763">{{Infobox Officeholder
| honorific-prefix = 
| name             = A. Lorne Campbell
| honorific-suffix = [[Order of Canada|O.C.]], [[Canadian Forces Decoration|C.D.]], [[Queen's Counsel|Q.C.]]
| image            = 
| imagesize        = 
| office           = 42nd President of the [[Canadian Bar Association]]
| predecessor      = Arthur Sydney Pattillo, [[Queen's Counsel|QC]]
| successor        = [[John Lauchlan Farris|John Lauchlan Farris, QC]]
| term_start       = 1970
| term_end         = 1971
| appointed        = 
| birth_date       = {{Birth date|1920|09|18|mf=yes}}
| birth_place      = Winnipeg
| death_date       = {{Death date and age|2014|01|15|1920|09|18|mf=yes}}
| death_place      = Winnipeg
| nationality      = 
| spouse           = Kathleen F. Campbell (née Perkin)
| party            = 
| relations        = 
| children         = Andrew, Jennifer, Deborah and Duncan
| residence        = 
| alma_mater       = [[University of Winnipeg|United College, Winnipeg]];  [[Robson Hall (Faculty of Law – University of Manitoba)|Manitoba Law School]]
| occupation       = 
| profession       = Lawyer
| religion         = [[Anglican]]
&lt;!--Military service--&gt;
| nickname           = 
| allegiance         = 
| branch             = [[Canadian Army]]
| serviceyears       = 
| rank               = Lieutenant-Colonel
| unit               = [[Royal Canadian Artillery]], 14th Field Regiment
| commands           = 
| battles            = [[Juno Beach]]
| mawards            = [[Canadian Forces Decoration]]
}}

'''Andrew Lorne Campbell''' (known as A. Lorne Campbell), [[Order of Canada|O.C.]], [[Canadian Forces Decoration|C.D.]], [[Bachelor of Laws#Canada|LL.B.]], [[Doctor of law#Canada|LL.D.]], [[Doctor of Canon Law|D.C.L.]], [[Queen's Counsel|Q.C.]] (September 18, 1920 – January 15, 2014) was a Canadian lawyer in [[Winnipeg]], [[Manitoba]]. He was very active in his community and in the legal profession, serving as President of The [[Law Society of Manitoba]] and as the national President of the [[Canadian Bar Association]].&lt;ref name=&quot;cba&quot;&gt;[https://www.cba.org/Who-We-Are/Governance/President-Executive/Past-CBA-Presidents Canadian Bar Association: Past CBA Presidents]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life and family==
Campbell was born in Winnipeg, the son of Arnold Munroe and Petrina Flora Isobel (née Wilson) Campbell. He had a brother, Allan Barrie, and a sister, Barbara (Carpenter). The family lived in [[East Kildonan, Winnipeg|East Kildonan]], one of the oldest areas of Winnipeg, dating back to the [[Red River Colony|Selkirk Settlers]]. The Campbells were descended from some of the original settlers, who arrived at the Red River colony in 1816 from Scotland.&lt;ref name=&quot;obit&quot;&gt;[http://passages.winnipegfreepress.com/passage-details/id-210018/name-A_Lorne_Campbell/order-publish_date%7CDESC,last_name%7CASC,first_name%7CASC/ ''Winnipeg Free Press'' Obituary]&lt;/ref&gt;

His father, Arnold M. Campbell, K.C., was a lawyer in Winnipeg. He served as a bencher of The [[Law Society of Manitoba]] from 1944 to 1947, and was appointed a judge of the [[Court of Queen's Bench of Manitoba|Manitoba Court of King's Bench]] in 1947, serving until his death on February 13, 1963.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.mhs.mb.ca/docs/people/campbell_am4.shtml Memorable Manitobans: Arnold Munroe Campbell (1892-1963).]&lt;/ref&gt;

His brother Barrie earned a Ph.D. in plant science at The University of Minnesota and worked his entire career with the Winnipeg Research Centre of Agriculture Canada. Both brothers were to receive the [[Order of Canada]] for their professional and community work.&lt;ref&gt;[http://umanitoba.ca/admin/governance/senate/hdr/1045.html University of Manitoba: Allan Barrie Campbell, D.Sc., May 27, 1992]&lt;/ref&gt;

Campbell's wife, Kathleen, was a [[war bride]]. He met her while in England during World War II. They married in 1945 and had four children: Andrew, Jennifer, Deborah and Duncan. He was pre-deceased by his younger son Duncan in 1996.

==Education==
Campbell studied first at United College, Winnipeg (now The [[University of Winnipeg]]), and then enrolled in the Manitoba Law School (now [[Robson Hall (Faculty of Law – University of Manitoba)|Robson Hall (Faculty of Law – The University of Manitoba)]]. He earned his Bachelor of Laws degree in 1947.&lt;ref name=&quot;obit&quot;/&gt;

==Military career==
Campbell interrupted his legal studies to join the [[Canadian Army]] in 1942, enlisting with the [[Royal Canadian Artillery]], the same unit his father had served in during World War I. He shipped overseas as a Lieutenant. On [[D-Day]] he landed on [[Juno Beach]], [[Invasion of Normandy|Normandy]], with the 14th Field Regiment of the Royal Canadian Artillery.&lt;ref name=&quot;obit&quot;/&gt;

While in England, he met his future wife, Kathleen (née Perkin). They married in January, 1945, when Campbell was able to obtain leave from his Regiment, by then fighting in the Netherlands.

After the war, Campbell maintained his connection with the Army, serving in the reserves from 1948 to 1958. He retired from the reserves with the rank of Lieutenant Colonel and the [[Canadian Forces Decoration]]. He then served for some years as a governor of the Manitoba Division of the [[Commissionaire#Canadian Corps of Commissionaires|Canadian Corps of Commissionaires]].

==Legal career==
Campbell returned to Winnipeg in 1946 and was [[called to the Bar]] in 1947. He began practising in a firm with his father's former partner, John J. Kelly, his father having just been appointed to the Bench. He worked in a number of firms, being named [[Queen's Counsel]] in 1960, and eventually joining the large firm of Aikins, MacAulay and Thorvaldson in 1964, specialising in the area of tax and companies law. In 1963, he was on a volunteer committee of the Canadian Bar Association which assisted the Manitoba government in preparing a new ''Companies Act''. Two other volunteers on the committee were [[Brian Dickson]], who went on to be Chief Justice of Canada, and [[Irwin Dorfman]] who, like Campbell, would serve as national president of the Canadian Bar Association.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.gov.mb.ca/news/archives/1963/10/1963-10-25-midnight_oil_is_burned_for_manitoba.pdf &quot; 'Midnight Oil' is Burned for Manitoba - - - Corporation Lawyers Tackle Companies Act,&quot; October 25, 1963.]&lt;/ref&gt;

Like his father before him, Campbell was elected by his peers in the legal profession to serve as a [[Bencher]] of the [[Law Society of Manitoba]], including a term as President of the Society. He was also active in the [[Canadian Bar Association]], serving as President of the Manitoba Bar Association, and also as national President of the Canadian Bar Association in 1970-71.&lt;ref name=&quot;cba&quot;/&gt; He was the fourth lawyer from Aikins MacAulay &amp; Thovaldson to serve as national president, the previous three being [[James Albert Manning Aikins|Sir James Aikins]] (1914-1927), Gordon Harold Aikins (1942-1943) and [[John MacAulay]] (1953-1954).  He was also a member of the [[Canadian Tax Foundation]],&lt;ref name=&quot;obit&quot;/&gt; an independent, non-partisan, non-profit tax research organization under the joint sponsorship of the [[Canadian Institute of Chartered Accountants]] and the Canadian Bar Association.

==The Wilson Committee: Role of the Auditor General==
After his term as President of the Canadian Bar Association, Campbell was asked by the [[Auditor General of Canada]] to sit on the Independent Committee for the Review of the Office of the Auditor General of Canada. The other two members were the Chair, J.R.M Wilson, F.C.A., past-president of the Canadian Institute of Chartered Accountants and the senior and managing partner of the large and well-known accounting firm, Clarkson, Gordon &amp; Co., and [[Marcel Bélanger]], also a Chartered Accountant, as well as professor of economics at [[Laval University]], advisor to the Quebec government on public finance, and former member of several Royal Commissions.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Learning Lessons, Transplanting Policy: The Wilson Committee and the Genesis of Efficiency Auditing&quot;, p. 10. {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141018235855/http://criticalperspectivesonaccounting.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/paper-cpa-037.pdf |date=October 18, 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The committee, known as the Wilson Committee, produced an extremely influential report, recommending that efficiency accounting (also known as performance audits) be used in government audits.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, J. R. M., Bélanger, M., &amp; Campbell, A. L. (1975). ''Report of the Independent Review Committee on the Office of the Auditor General of Canada''. Ottawa: Information Canada.&lt;/ref&gt; The Wilson Committee's recommendations became the foundation for a new ''Auditor General Act'', enacted by the federal government in 1977.&lt;ref&gt;''Auditor General Act'', S.C. 1976-77, c. 34, s. 1.&lt;/ref&gt; When testifying in favour of the new bill in the Commons, the Auditor-General referred to the Committee's report as the &quot;Magna Carta of the [Auditor-General] office.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Canada. ''House of Commons Hansard'', 1977, p. 7197.&lt;/ref&gt; All ten provinces subsequently passed similar legislation, authorising performance audits by the provincial auditors.&lt;ref&gt; &quot;Learning Lessons, Transplanting Policy: The Wilson Committee and the Genesis of Efficiency Auditing&quot;, p. 40. {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141018235855/http://criticalperspectivesonaccounting.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/paper-cpa-037.pdf |date=October 18, 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The principles set out by the Committee also proved very influential in other Commonwealth countries using the Westminster model of responsible government.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Learning Lessons, Transplanting Policy: The Wilson Committee and the Genesis of Efficiency Auditing&quot;, p. 2. {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141018235855/http://criticalperspectivesonaccounting.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/paper-cpa-037.pdf |date=October 18, 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Community involvement==
For many years, Campbell was a trustee of the Manitoba Law School, and was involved in the law school becoming the Faculty of Law of The University of Manitoba in 1966. He was also the chairman of The University of Manitoba's Centennial Campaign, which included the construction of the [[Max Bell Centre (Winnipeg)|Max Bell Centre]].

Campbell was also involved with the Anglican Church in Winnipeg, serving as the Registrar of the [[Diocese of Rupert's Land]]. He also served as charter member of the Advisory Council for the [[St. John's College, University of Manitoba|Saint John's College]] Capital Campaign, and as chair of the special gifts committee.

Campbell worked for the Society for Crippled Children and Adults of Manitoba (now the [http://www.smd-services.com/ Society for Manitobans with Disabilities]), and the Canadian Rehabilitation Council for the Disabled. He eventually served as president of both groups.

Campbell served on the boards of the Manitoba Cancer Treatment and Research Foundation (now CancerCare Manitoba) from 1991 to 2003, the Deer Lodge Foundation for Geriatrics, and the Winnipeg Habitat for Humanity Foundation Advisory Board. In 2004, he was also appointed a Serving Member of the Order of Saint John.

Campbell was a member of The [[Manitoba Club]], and a member and honorary solicitor of [http://www.lordselkirk.ca/ The Lord Selkirk Association of Rupert's Land]. He was also active in The [http://www.standrews-wpg.ca/ Saint Andrew's Society of Winnipeg], being an honorary life member, member of the Advisory Committee, and past president.

==Later life and death==
Campbell finally retired from the practice of law in 2005, after a legal career of 58 years.

He died on January 15, 2014, and was buried in the [http://www.mhs.mb.ca/docs/sites/kildonanpresbyteriancemetery.shtml Old Kildonan Presbyterian church cemetery], the Selkirk Settlers' church, after a funeral service at Saint George's Anglican Church, Wilton at Grosvenor, Winnipeg.

In his obituary,&lt;ref name=&quot;obit&quot;/&gt; his family stated:

{{quote|text=He never thought of living anywhere other than Winnipeg; his roots were historically established. He enjoyed the practice of law and the fellowship of both the legal profession and the many friends he made through his belief in community involvement.}}

==Honours and awards==

In 1985, Campbell was named an officer of the Order of Canada.  His citation mentioned his work on the Wilson Committee, &quot;the report of which is considered a landmark study in Canada and abroad,&quot; as well as his service as President of the Canadian Bar Association and his work for the Society for Crippled Children and Adults of Manitoba and the Canadian Rehabilitation Council for the Disabled.&lt;ref&gt;[http://archive.gg.ca/honours/search-recherche/honours-desc.asp?lang=e&amp;TypeID=orc&amp;id=247 Order of Canada Citation:  A. Lorne Campbell]&lt;/ref&gt;

Campbell's other honours included:

* 1960: [[Queen's Counsel]]
* 1977: Doctor of Laws (honorary), The University of Manitoba
* 1992: Distinguished Service Award, Manitoba Bar Association
* 1993: Doctor of Canon Law (honorary), St. John's College
* 1999: Citizen of the Year Award, The St. Andrew's Society of Winnipeg
* 2006: 87th Honorary Life Member, The Manitoba Club
* Life Bencher of The Law Society of Manitoba

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Campbell, A. Lorne}}
[[Category:1920 births]]
[[Category:2014 deaths]]
[[Category:University of Manitoba alumni]]
[[Category:Canadian people of Scottish descent]]
[[Category:Officers of the Order of Canada]]
[[Category:Canadian Army officers]]
[[Category:Royal Regiment of Canadian Artillery personnel]]
[[Category:Canadian Anglicans]]
[[Category:People from Winnipeg]]
[[Category:Lawyers in Manitoba]]
[[Category:Canadian Queen's Counsel]]
[[Category:Canadian Bar Association Presidents]]
[[Category:University of Winnipeg alumni]]</text>
      <sha1>i4svm48m7krv8sv6cojpdckpw7onyfk</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
