<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Albert Jacka</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>943281</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749824901</id>
      <parentid>749824375</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-16T10:11:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ian Rose</username>
        <id>502570</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Revert to revision 738271067 dated 2016-09-07 23:26:26 by 14GTR using [[:en:Wikipedia:Tools/Navigation_popups|popups]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24629">{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2014}}
{{Use Australian English|date=February 2014}}
{{Infobox military person
|name= Albert Jacka
|image= Albert Jacka portrait A02868.jpg
|image_size= 250px
|alt= 
|caption= Captain Albert Jacka c. 1920
|nickname= Bert
|birth_date= {{birth date|1893|01|10|df=y}}
|birth_place= [[Winchelsea, Victoria]]
|death_date= {{Death date and age|1932|01|17|1893|01|10|df=y}}
|death_place= [[St. Kilda, Victoria]]
|placeofburial= 
|allegiance= Australia
|branch= [[First Australian Imperial Force|Australian Imperial Force]]
|serviceyears= 1914–20
|rank= [[Captain (armed forces)|Captain]]
|servicenumber= 
|unit= [[14th Battalion (Australia)|14th Battalion]]
|commands= 
|battles= First World War
* [[Gallipoli Campaign]]
* [[Battle of Chunuk Bair]]
* [[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]]
* [[Battle of the Somme]]
* [[Battle of Pozières]]
* [[Battle of Messines (1917)|Battle of Messines]]
* [[Battle of Polygon Wood]]
|awards= [[Victoria Cross]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Military Cross]] &amp; [[Medal bar|Bar]]
|relations     =
|laterwork     =Mayor of the [[City of St Kilda]] (1930–31)
}}
'''Albert Jacka''', {{postnominals|country=AUS|size=100%|sep=,|VCi|MC1}} (10 January 1893 – 17 January 1932) was an [[List of Australian Victoria Cross recipients|Australian recipient]] of the [[Victoria Cross]], the highest decoration for gallantry &quot;in the face of the enemy&quot; that can be awarded to members of the British and [[Commonwealth of Nations|Commonwealth]] armed forces. Jacka was the first Australian to be decorated with the VC during the First World War, receiving the medal for his actions during the [[Gallipoli Campaign]]. He later served on the [[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]] and was twice further decorated for his bravery.

Upon the conclusion of the war, Jacka returned to Australia and entered business; establishing the electrical goods importing and exporting business ''Roxburgh, Jacka &amp; Co. Pty Ltd''. He was later elected to the local council, where he became the [[mayor]] of the [[City of St Kilda]]. Jacka never fully recovered from the multiple wounds he sustained during his war service, and died at the age of 39.

==Early life==
Albert Jacka was born on a dairy farm near [[Winchelsea, Victoria]] on 10 January 1893, the fourth of seven children to Nathaniel Jacka and his English-born wife Elizabeth (ńee Kettle).&lt;ref&gt;Snelling. ''VCs of the First World War: Gallipoli'', p. 116&lt;/ref&gt; His family moved to [[Wedderburn, Victoria]] when he was five years old, where he attended the local school before working with his father as a haulage contractor. He was working for the Victorian State Forests Department when the First World War broke out.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.hardjacka.com/jacka.html |title= Hard Jacka – The Story of a Gallipoli Legend |accessdate=10 July 2008| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080725063313/http://www.hardjacka.com/jacka.html| archivedate= 25 July 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==First World War==
===Enlistment and training===
Jacka enlisted in the [[First Australian Imperial Force|Australian Imperial Force]] on 18 September 1914, with the rank of [[Private (rank)|private]]. He was assigned to the [[14th Battalion (Australia)|14th Battalion]],&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.awm.gov.au/people/226.asp |title=Australian War Memorial Biography |accessdate=10 July 2008| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080705083647/http://www.awm.gov.au/people/226.asp| archivedate= 5 July 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; 4th Brigade, [[1st Division (Australia)|1st Division]] and finished his training at Broadmeadows Camp.&lt;ref name=&quot;14th&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.awm.gov.au/units/unit_11201.asp |title=Australian War Memorial – 14th Battalion |accessdate=11 July 2008| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080726133255/http://www.awm.gov.au/units/unit_11201.asp| archivedate= 26 July 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After Turkey became a German ally, the 1st Division was sent to Egypt to defend the [[Suez Canal]]. Jacka and his battalion arrived at [[Alexandria]] on 31 January 1915. During ten weeks of training south of [[Cairo]] the 4th Brigade was merged with two New Zealand brigades and merged with the 1st Light Horse Brigade to form the [[New Zealand and Australian Division]] (NZ&amp;A) under [[Major General]] [[Alexander Godley]].&lt;ref name=&quot;14th&quot;/&gt;

===Gallipoli===
[[File:Albert Jacka at Mudros.jpg|thumb|right|Corporal Albert Jacka on Mudros, 1915]]
Jacka fought in the [[Gallipoli Campaign]] that started on 25 April 1915, when his new division landed at [[Anzac Cove]] on the 26th in the [[Dardanelles]], fighting against Turkish defenders on a narrow beach. The NZ&amp;A-held position, a series of trenches which became known as Courtney's Post, was where Jacka won the [[Victoria Cross]].&lt;ref name=&quot;14th&quot;/&gt;

On 19 May 1915, the Turks launched an [[Second attack on ANZAC Cove|assault against the Anzac Line]], capturing a section of the trench at Courtney's Post; one end of which was guarded by Jacka.&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB&quot;&gt;{{cite web |author=Kevin J. Fewster  |url=http://www.adb.online.anu.edu.au/biogs/A090442b.htm |title=Jacka, Albert (1893–1932) |work=Australian Dictionary of Biography |volume=9 |pages=442–453 |year=1983 |publisher=Melbourne University Press |accessdate=11 July 2008| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080720061031/http://www.adb.online.anu.edu.au/biogs/A090442b.htm| archivedate= 20 July 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; For several minutes he fired warning shots into the trench wall until reinforcements arrived, after which he attempted to enter the trench with three others; all but Jacka were either wounded or pinned.&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB&quot;/&gt; It was then decided that while a feint attack was made from the same end, Jacka would attack from the rear. The party then proceeded to engage the Turks with rifle fire, throwing in two bombs as Jacka skirted around to attack from the flank. He climbed out onto &quot;[[no man's land]]&quot;, entering the trench via the [[parapet]]. In the resulting conflict, Jacka shot five Turkish soldiers and [[bayoneted]] two others, forcing the remainder to flee the trench;&lt;ref name=&quot;ADDO&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.anzacday.org.au/miscellaneous/jacka.html |title=Albert Jacka |work=AnzacDay.org |accessdate=11 July 2008| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080725113034/http://www.anzacday.org.au/miscellaneous/jacka.html| archivedate= 25 July 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; he then held the trench alone for the remainder of the night. Jacka's platoon commander, Lieutenant Crabbe, informed him the following morning that he would be recommended for his bravery.&lt;ref&gt;Snelling. ''VCs of the First World War: Gallipoli'', p. 115&lt;/ref&gt;

The full citation for the Victoria Cross appeared in a supplement to the ''[[London Gazette]]'' on 23 July 1915:&lt;ref&gt;{{LondonGazette |issue=29240 |date=23 July 1915 |startpage=7279 |supp=yes |accessdate=10 July 2008}} ''(VC)''&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote|''War Office, 24th&amp;nbsp;July, 1915''

His Majesty the King has been graciously pleased to award the Victoria Cross to the undermentioned Officers and Non-commissioned Officers:-

No. 465 Lance-Corporal Albert Jacka, 14th Battalion, Australian Imperial Forces.

For most conspicuous bravery on the night of the 19th–20th&amp;nbsp;May, 1915 at &quot;Courtney's Post&quot;, Gallipoli Peninsula.

Lance-Corporal Jacka, while holding a portion of our trench with four other men, was heavily attacked. When all except himself were killed or wounded, the trench was rushed and occupied by seven Turks. Lance-Corporal Jacka at once most gallantly attacked them single-handed, and killed the whole party, five by rifle fire and two with the bayonet.}}

Following his VC action, Jacka instantly became a national hero; he received the £500 and gold watch that the prominent [[Melbourne]] business and sporting identity, [[John Wren]], had promised to the first Australian of the war to receive the VC, his image was used on recruiting posters and magazine covers,&lt;ref name=&quot;DH&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.diggerhistory.info/pages-vc/jacka_vc.htm |title=Albert JACKA VC, MC and Bar |work=Digger History |accessdate=11 July 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; and he received rapid promotions; first to [[corporal]] on 28 August, to [[sergeant]] two weeks later on 12 September, and then to [[company sergeant major]] on 14 November.&lt;ref&gt;Snelling. ''VCs of the First World War: Gallipoli'', pp. 116-117&lt;/ref&gt; He became company sergeant major of C Company, and saw much fighting at Gallipoli where, during August at [[Battle of Chunuk Bair|Chunuk Bair]], Hill 971, and Hill 60, his battalion took part in an Allied offensive aimed at trying to break the deadlock around the beachhead.&lt;ref name=&quot;14th&quot;/&gt; After nine months of fighting and 26,111 Australian casualties, the Allied forces began to evacuate the peninsula in December 1915, after which Jacka's battalion was withdrawn to Egypt.&lt;ref name=&quot;14th&quot;/&gt;

In Egypt, he passed through [[officer training]] school with high marks, and on 29 April 1916 was [[Commissioned officer|commissioned]] as a [[second lieutenant]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB&quot;/&gt; During this time, the AIF expanded and was reorganised; the 14th Battalion was split and provided experienced soldiers for the [[46th Battalion (Australia)|46th Battalion]], and the 4th Brigade was combined with the 12th and 13th Brigades to form the 4th Australian Division.&lt;ref&gt;Polanski. ''We Were the 46th: The History of the 46th Battalion in The Great War of 1914–18'', p. 2.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Western Front===
[[File:Albert Jacka and Martin OMeara 1916.jpg|thumb|left|Jacka with fellow VC recipient [[Martin O'Meara]], 1916. Both were recuperating from wounds in England.]]
The division was sent to France, and the [[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]], in June 1916,&lt;ref name=&quot;14th&quot;/&gt; where Jacka and his unit were assigned to the Allied trenches near [[Armentières]], participating in several raids against the German trenches.&lt;ref&gt;Lawriwsky. ''Hard Jacka'', p. 108&lt;/ref&gt; Following the heavy casualties on the [[Battle of the Somme (1916)|Somme]], the 14th Battalion was transferred to the [[Pozières]] sector of the Somme offensive. Jacka's division, on 23 July 1916, was involved in the attack of Pozières planned by Major General [[Harold Bridgwood Walker]]. The Australian division suffered 5,285 casualties after three days of fighting. The Australian force captured Pozières,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.awm.gov.au/units/event_72.asp |title=Battle of Pozières |publisher=Australian War Memorial |accessdate=11 July 2008| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080602214554/http://www.awm.gov.au/units/event_72.asp| archivedate= 2 June 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; but the fight was so bloody that the Australians could only identify their trenches by the bodies of their comrades showing their red-and-white shoulder patches.{{Citation needed|date=March 2015}}

On the morning of 7 August 1916, after a night of heavy shelling, the Germans began to overrun a portion of the line which included Jacka's dug-out. Jacka had just completed a reconnaissance, and had gone to his dug-out when two Germans appeared at its entrance and rolled a bomb down the doorway, killing two of his men.&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB&quot;/&gt; Emerging from the dug-out, Jacka came upon a large number of Germans rounding up some forty Australians as prisoners. Only seven men from his platoon had recovered from the blast; rallying these few, he charged at the enemy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.anzacsite.gov.au/5environment/vc/biography.html|title=Biographies of VC Winners |work=Anzacsite.gov.au |accessdate=11 July 2008| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20080723000638/http://anzacsite.gov.au/5environment/vc/biography.html| archivedate= 23 July 2008 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;| deadurl= no}}&lt;/ref&gt; Heavy hand-to-hand fighting ensued, as the Australian prisoners turned on their captors. Every member of the platoon was wounded, including Jacka who was wounded seven times; including an injury from a bullet that passed through his body under his right shoulder, and two head wounds.&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs&quot;&gt;Snelling. ''VCs of the First World War: Gallipoli'', p. 118&lt;/ref&gt; Fifty Germans were captured and the line was retaken;&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB&quot;/&gt; Jacka was personally credited with killing between twelve and twenty Germans during the engagement.&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs&quot;/&gt;
[[File:Captain A Jacka, VC, MC and Bar (1919) (Art. IWM ART 1915).jpg|thumb|''Captain A Jacka, VC, MC and Bar'' (1919) by [[Colin Gill]] (Art. IWM ART 1915)]]

Jacka was awarded the [[Military Cross]] for his actions at Pozières,&lt;ref&gt;{{LondonGazette |issue=29824 |date=14 November 1916 |startpage=11074 |supp=yes |accessdate=10 July 2008}} ''(MC)''&lt;/ref&gt; although he was originally recommended for the [[Distinguished Service Order]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.awm.gov.au/cms_images/awm28/1/180P1/0020.pdf |title=Recommendation for Albert Jacka to be awarded a Distinguished Service Order |publisher=Australian War Memorial  |accessdate=10 July 2008 |format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many present at the time, as well as many historians since, have voiced the opinion that Jacka deserved a second Victoria Cross for the Pozières action.&lt;ref&gt;Snelling. ''VCs of the First World War: Gallipoli'', p. 117&lt;/ref&gt; One of only two bars (second award) to the Victoria Cross awarded during the war was earned the following day by Captain [[Noel Godfrey Chavasse]] of the [[Royal Army Medical Corps]]. Chavasse subsequently died of wounds sustained during this second VC action. The other bar to the VC was earnt by [[Arthur Martin-Leake]] during the period 29 October to 8 November 1914 near [[Zonnebeke]], Belgium, when, according to his award citation, Martin-Leake showed most conspicuous bravery and devotion to duty in rescuing, while exposed to constant fire, a large number of the wounded who were lying close to the enemy's trenches. Martin-Leake was the first of only three men to be awarded a bar to his VC.{{citation needed|date=November 2014}}

Although traditionally the reason Jacka was not awarded a bar to his VC has been ascribed to British [[snobbery]] towards a &quot;rough [[Colony|colonial]]&quot;, this view has been challenged. [[Gordon Corrigan]], in ''Blood Mud and Poppycock'', points out that  it was Jacka's Australian superiors who chose not to recommend him for the award, and he argues that this may have been due to the fact that the Germans easily infiltrated Jacka's platoon position in broad daylight without being challenged. The sentries were most likely asleep or absent and Jacka should have ensured that they were not; as such it may have been perceived that while Jacka should be commended for his robust action in responding to the situation, he also bore a responsibility for allowing it to happen in the first place.{{citation needed|date=November 2014}}

After the incident, Jacka was evacuated to England, where he was promoted to [[lieutenant]] on 18 August 1916, but was falsely reported dead on 8 September. He attended an investiture ceremony at [[Windsor Castle]] on 29 September; receiving his Victoria Cross from [[George V of the United Kingdom|King George V]],&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs&quot;/&gt; before rejoining his unit in November.&lt;ref name=&quot;DH&quot;/&gt; Promoted to [[Captain (land)|captain]] on 15 March 1917, he was appointed the 14th Battalion's intelligence officer.&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB&quot;/&gt;
[[File:Jacka-medals-Adelaide2010.jpg|thumb|left|250px|Albert Jacka's medals on display whilst on loan to the [[State Library of South Australia]], 8 August 2010.&lt;ref&gt;Left to right, Jacka's medals include: Victoria Cross; Military Cross &amp; Bar; [[1914–15 Star]]; [[British War Medal]]; and [[Victory Medal (United Kingdom)|Victory Medal]]. See: [http://cas.awm.gov.au/item/REL/18215.001 REL/18215.001 – Victoria Cross: Lance Corporal A Jacka, 14 Battalion, AIF], Australian War Memorial; [http://cas.awm.gov.au/item/REL/18215.002 REL/18215.002 – Military Cross and bar: Captain A Jacka, 14 Battalion, AIF], Australian War Memorial; [http://cas.awm.gov.au/item/REL/18215.003 REL/18215.003 – 1914–15 Star: Sergeant A Jacka, 14 Battalion, AIF], Australian War Memorial; [http://cas.awm.gov.au/item/REL/18215.004 REL/18215.004 – British War Medal 1914–20: Captain A Jacka, 14 Battalion, AIF], Australian War Memorial; [http://cas.awm.gov.au/item/REL/18215.005 REL/18215.005 – Victory Medal: Captain A Jacka, 14 Battalion, AIF], Australian War Memorial.&lt;/ref&gt;]]

By early 1917, the Germans had retired to the [[Hindenburg Line]], and on 8 April Jacka led a night reconnaissance party into ''&quot;no man's land&quot;'', near [[Bullecourt 1917, Jean and Denise Letaille museum|Bullecourt]] to inspect enemy defences before an Allied attack against the new German line. He penetrated the wire at two places, reported back, then went out again to supervise the laying of tapes to guide the assault parties; in the process he single-handedly captured a two-man German patrol.&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB&quot;/&gt; He was awarded a [[Medal bar|Bar]] to his Military Cross for this action.&lt;ref&gt;{{LondonGazette |issue=30135 |date=15 June 1917 |startpage=5983 |supp=yes |accessdate=10 July 2008}} ''(MC bar)''&lt;/ref&gt;

Later, Jacka was given command of D Company, 14th Battalion, and in June led his men through the [[Battle of Messines (1917)|Battle for Messines Ridge]]. During their advance, the company overran several [[machine-gun]] posts and captured a German [[field gun]]; Jacka's actions went unrecognised.&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs&quot;/&gt; On 8 July, he was wounded by a [[sniper]] near [[Ploegsteert Wood]], resulting in nearly two months hospitalisation.&lt;ref name=&quot;DH&quot;/&gt; Returning to the front, he led the 14th Battalion on 26 September in an attack against German [[Bunker#Pillbox|pill-box]]es during the [[Battle of Polygon Wood]].&lt;ref name=&quot;DH&quot;/&gt; Jacka was recommended for the Distinguished Service Order a second time for this feat, but again it was not granted.&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs&quot;/&gt; In May 1918, Jacka was finally removed from the conflict when, outside the village of [[Villers-Bretonneux]], he was badly gassed and a missile passed through his [[Vertebrate trachea|trachea]]. He was evacuated to No. 20 Casualty Clearing Station at [[Vignacourt]], where it was thought that he would not recover. When he did, he was sent to Britain for two operations and a long recuperative period.&lt;ref name=&quot;ADDO&quot;/&gt;

He returned to Australia on 6 September 1919 and his AIF appointment ended on 10 January 1920, when he returned to [[Melbourne]] to a hero's welcome.&lt;ref name=&quot;ADDO&quot;/&gt;

==Later life==
[[File:Albert Jacka VC grave.jpg|thumb|right|The grave of Albert Jacka in St Kilda cemetery.]]
After the war, Jacka, R. O. Roxburgh and E. J. L. Edmonds, both former members of the 14th Battalion, established the electrical goods importing and exporting business ''Roxburgh, Jacka &amp; Co. Pty Ltd''.&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB&quot;/&gt; The business was heavily financed by [[John Wren]], but collapsed with the [[Great Depression]] in 1931.&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs2&quot;&gt;Snelling. ''VCs of the First World War: Gallipoli'', p. 119&lt;/ref&gt;

On 17 January 1921, at St Mary's [[Catholic Church]], St Kilda, Jacka married Frances Veronica Carey, a typist from his office. The pair settled in St. Kilda, and later adopted a daughter, Betty.&lt;ref name=&quot;ADB&quot;/&gt; In September, 1929, he was elected to the Council of the [[City of St Kilda]], becoming mayor the following year. Much of his civic work was characterised by his strong interest in assisting the unemployed,&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM&quot;/&gt; defending evictees and proposing public works for the ‘sussos’: 'sustenance workers', employed on public works by the Government as a relief measure.{{citation needed|date=November 2014}}

On 14 December 1931, Jacka collapsed after a council meeting and was admitted to [[Caulfield, Victoria|Caulfield]] [[Military Hospital]]. On 17 January 1932, one week after his 39th birthday, he died from chronic [[nephritis]];&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs2&quot;/&gt; he was buried at [[St Kilda Cemetery]], with eight other Victoria Cross recipients acting as [[pallbearer]]s and an estimated 6,000 witnesses to the burial as his body passed en route to the cemetery.&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM&quot;/&gt;

Albert Jacka's Victoria Cross is displayed at the [[Australian War Memorial]] in [[Canberra]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.awm.gov.au/encyclopedia/vic_cross.asp |title=Victoria Crosses held at the Memorial |publisher=Australian War Memorial |accessdate=8 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; and a commemorative service is held every 17 January in St. Kilda to honour Jacka; originally organised by former members of the 14th Battalion, it is now held by the local council.&lt;ref name=&quot;VCs2&quot;/&gt;

==Memorials==
[[File:WedderburnAlbertJackaGates.JPG|thumb|Wedderburn Albert Jacka Gates]]
*Albert Jacka Grave ([https://tools.wmflabs.org/geohack/geohack.php?pagename=Albert_Jacka_Grave=37.861094_S_145.002349_E_ Coordinates -37.861094 145.002349]).&lt;ref name=MonAus7&gt;{{cite web|title=Albert jacka Tombstone|url=http://monumentaustralia.org.au/search/display/33518-albert-jacka|website=Monument Australia|accessdate=29 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Every year in January, a memorial service at the grave is organised by the St Kilda Council.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=ALBERT JACKA MEMORIAL SERVICE 2014|url=http://www.stkildahistory.org.au/|website=St Kilda Historical Society|accessdate=29 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Jacka Park, Wedderburn, St Kilda ([https://tools.wmflabs.org/geohack/geohack.php?pagename=Jacka_Park=33.775598_S_151.285118_E_ Coordinates -33.775598 151.285118])  is named in his honour and the gates inscribed with &quot;1914-18 Dedicated to the memory of Cpt. Albert Jacka V.C. M.C. &amp; Bar&quot;&lt;ref name=MonAus1&gt;{{cite web|title=Albert Jacka Gates|url=http://monumentaustralia.org.au/display/33938-albert-jacka|website=Monument Australia|accessdate=29 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Plaque in [[Returned and Services League of Australia|RSL]] Club, Acland Street, St Kilda ([https://tools.wmflabs.org/geohack/geohack.php?pagename=Jacka_Park=37.867466_S_144.978858_E_ Coordinates -37.867466 144.978858]) inscribed &quot;In memory of Captain Albert Jacka V.C., M.C. and bar 1893–1932. served in the 4th Brigade, 14th Battalion – 'Jacka's Mob' Australian Imperial Forces 1914–1920&quot;.&lt;ref name=MonAus2&gt;{{cite web|title=Albert Jacka Plaque|url=http://monumentaustralia.org.au/display/99721-albert-jacka|website=Monument Australia|accessdate=29 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*Inscription of name on Victoria Cross Memorial in [[Alfred Square, St Kilda]], along with other Victoria Cross recipients from St Kilda. &quot;&lt;ref name=MonAus3&gt;{{cite web|title=Albert Jacka – Victoria Cross Inscription|url=http://monumentaustralia.org.au/display/33536-victoria-cross-monument
|website=Monument Australia|accessdate=29 July 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The suburb of [[Jacka, Australian Capital Territory|Jacka]] located in [[Canberra]], Australia's national capital, is named in his honour.
*Jacka Boulevard, St Kilda ([https://tools.wmflabs.org/geohack/geohack.php?pagename=Jacka_Boulevard=37.865673_S_144.97344_E_ Coordinates -37.865673 144.97344]) was named in his honour.

==Notes==
{{reflist|30em}}

==References==
* Lawriwsky, Michael. ''Hard Jacka: The Story of a Gallipoli Legend'' (Mira Books, 2007)
* Macklin, Robert. ''Jacka VC: Australian Hero'' (NSW: [[Allen &amp; Unwin]], 2006)
* Polanksi, Ian. ''We Were the 46th: The History of the 46th Battalion in The Great War of 1914–18'' (Jenkin Buxton Printers, 1999)
* Snelling, Stephen. ''VCs of the First World War: Gallipoli'' (Alan Sutton Publishing, 1995)

==Further reading==
* Grant, Ian. ''Jacka, VC: Australia's Finest Fighting Soldier'' (MacMillan Australia, 1989 – in association with The Australian War Memorial, Canberra)

==External links==
{{Commons category|Albert Jacka}}
* [http://www.theaustralian.news.com.au/story/0,25197,22482412-31477,00.html The Australian: An uncommon hero]
* [http://www.theaustralian.news.com.au/story/0,25197,22483446-31477,00.html The Australian: First Digger to win VC in World War I 'punished for outspokenness']
* [http://naa12.naa.gov.au/scripts/searchold.asp?Number=8334256&amp;O=I Digital copy of Jacka's personal war service record]

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Jacka, Albert}}
[[Category:1893 births]]
[[Category:1932 deaths]]
[[Category:Australian Army officers]]
[[Category:Australian Gallipoli Campaign recipients of the Victoria Cross]]
[[Category:Australian World War I recipients of the Victoria Cross]]
[[Category:Deaths from nephritis]]
[[Category:Mayors of places in Victoria (Australia)]]
[[Category:Military personnel from Melbourne]]
[[Category:Australian people of Cornish descent]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Military Cross]]</text>
      <sha1>fcjo0bhldux20d9xfwa0s64yaez4tml</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
