<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of Schwechat</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>25371927</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750735417</id>
      <parentid>723704958</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-21T14:59:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>89.96.190.232</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9500">{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Battle of Schwechat
|partof=the [[Hungarian Revolution of 1848]]
|image=[[File:Schwechati csata.jpg|285px]]
|caption=&quot;The Battle of Schwechat&quot; by [[Anton Ziegler]], 1850
|date=30 October 1848
|place=[[Schwechat]], near [[Vienna]], [[Austria]]
|result=Austrian victory
|combatant1={{Hungarian Revolution of 1848 participant|Hungary}}
 |combatant2={{Hungarian Revolution of 1848 participant|Austria}}&lt;br/&gt;{{Hungarian Revolution of 1848 participant|Croatia}}
|commander1 = {{Hungarian Revolution of 1848 participant|Móga}}&lt;br /&gt;{{Hungarian Revolution of 1848 participant|Guyon}}&lt;br /&gt;{{Hungarian Revolution of 1848 participant|Görgey}}
|commander2 = {{Hungarian Revolution of 1848 participant|Grätz}}&lt;br /&gt;{{Hungarian Revolution of 1848 participant|Liechtenstein}}&lt;br /&gt;{{Hungarian Revolution of 1848 participant|Jelačić}}
|strength1 = c.&amp;nbsp;30,000 men&lt;br/&gt;70 cannon
|strength2 = 80,000 men&lt;br/&gt;210 cannon
|casualties1=
|casualties2=
}}
{{Campaignbox Hungarian Revolution of 1848}}

The '''Battle of [[Schwechat]]''' was a battle in the [[Hungarian Revolution of 1848]], fought on 30 October 1848 between the revolutionary [[Hungary|Hungarian]] Army against the army of the [[Austrian Empire]], in [[Schwechat]], near [[Vienna]]. This was the last battle of 1848 in the Transdanubian campaign. The Hungarian Army was under the command of [[János Móga]] and the Austrian Army was under the command of [[Alfred I, Prince of Windisch-Grätz]].

==Pretext==

=== Jelačić’s retreat===
Some days after the [[Battle of Pákozd]] János Móga and his Hungarian army pursued [[Ban (viceroy) of Croatia|Croatian Ban]] [[Josip Jelačić]]. Jelačić and his [[Croats|Croat]] army retreated towards [[Vienna]] for two reasons: first, he knew he would get some support from Vienna; second, he could not retreat, because [[militiamen]] and territorials were occupying South Transdanubia. Neither could they retreat in the direction of the fortress of [[Komárno|Komárom]], because it switched allegiance to the [[Constitution of Hungary]], an allegiance that lasted until the end of the revolution. On 4 October Jelačić arrived at [[Moson]]. He planned to wait for reinforcements and then attack the Hungarian Army.

During Jelačić’s retreat there was major political upheaval. The Emperor had not heard of the Hungarian victory at the [[Battle of Pákozd]], but he received the news that [[Ferenc Lamberg]] had been killed. The Emperor thought it was time to attack the Constitution of Hungary in public. The Emperor refused to recognise the [[Batthyány Government]] and ordered the Hungarian Parliament be dissolved. Furthermore, he appointed Jelačić as the civic and military [[regent]] of Hungary.

Jelačić's main supporter, the Austrian Secretary of War [[Theodor Franz, Count Baillet von Latour]], sent troops to help him; however, von Latour was unaware that Vienna had very few soldiers.&lt;!--citation?--&gt; This was a mistake, and he paid for the error with his life. Those in Vienna sympathetic to the Hungarian cause started [[Vienna Rebellion|a rebellion]] on 6 October. The Emperor and his subjects escaped to [[Olmütz]] but Latour was lynched by rebels. After Jelačić heard of the rebellion, he left Hungary towards Vienna. On 10 October the Hungarian Army reached the Austrian border and stopped pursuing Jelačić.

===The delayed Hungarian attack===
The delayed attack by the Hungarian army is controversial among those studying Hungarian military history. When the rebellion started in Vienna, everyone took for granted that the Hungarians would come to the rebels' aid. Had they done so, it could have changed the course of the revolution. More so, had they done so and won, the [[Habsburg Empire]] might have collapsed.&lt;!--citation?--&gt;
[[File:Jellasics harcosai kozott.jpg|left|thumb|250px|bélyegkép|Jelačić  with his soldiers before the Battle of Schwechat (Hand-coloured lithograph by [[Joseph Kriehuber]] and [[Johann Höfelich]])]]
The Hungarian army had good reason not cross the Austrian border. After the Battle of Pákozd, Jelačić’s army was stronger than ever. &lt;!--why? didn't the Hungarians win that battle?--&gt; Jelačić sent the inexperienced Croatians back to [[Croatia]] under the command of [[Kuzman Todorović]] because he knew that troops were en route from Vienna. As a result, the Hungarian army had to fight the more experienced, stronger Austrian army. This decision led to some infighting among the leaders of the Hungarian army. János Móga decided to follow the orders of the Hungarian National Defence Commission not to attack. But the members of the Commission varied in their views about crossing the Austrian border. The Left wanted to help the rebels in Vienna, but the Right objected to this idea. From the start [[Lajos Kossuth]] said that the Hungarians were not rebels, but were only protecting their own country. Later, he changed his mind, and on 18 October he visited the Hungarian army &lt;!-- where? --&gt; to tell them his views.

==Battle==
[[File:Schwechati csata.png|thumb|200px|Battle plan]]
[[File:Görgei Artúr by Miklós Barabás.jpg|thumb|200px|Artúr Görgey was promoted to [[general officer|General]] after his actions in the battle. He also became the leader of the army of the Upper Danube. (Painting by [[Miklós Barabás]])]]
[[File:Jellasics tamadasa EN.jpg|thumb|left|250px|Jelačić’s attack in the last quarter of 1848]]
The start of the battle was promising for the Hungarian army. The right flank, under the command of [[Richard Debaufre Guyon]], took control of [[Manswörth]] after twenty minutes' fighting. But the battle was less easily won in the centre, the left flank (under the command of Colonel [[Mihály Répásy]]) arrived too late, so Guyon's success changed the formation of the Hungarian line: it became one arm of a pincer movement. This was unfortunate because the Austrian army could get into the centre very easily, so Móga gave an order to [[Artúr Görgey]] to recall his central troops.

Jelačić realised that the centre was defenceless and ordered lieutenant-general [[Prince Franz de Paula of Liechtenstein|Lichtenstein]]'s cavalry to move towards the central Hungarian army. At the same time major-general [[Karl Zeisberg]] attacked Görgey. Most of Görgey's legion lacked experience, were afraid of gunfire and deserted. The Hungarian artillery &amp;ndash; after a short retreat &amp;ndash; started to attack the Austrians, who were advancing towards the central Hungarian army.

Fortunately for the Hungarians, although Répásy delayed he still arrived before the Austrian army started to attack the central Hungarian army. His presence persuaded Lichtenstein not to start fighting, so the Austrian army could not encircle the central Hungarian army. Windisch-Grätz also made a strategic error by not retreating to Vienna, so he was in no position to pursue the Hungarian army.

==Aftermath==
The main aim of the Austrian army's leaders was to prevent the rebels in Vienna and the Hungarian army banding together. In that respect, Windisch-Grätz won the battle as he successfully attacked the Hungarians and the rebels capitulated. But the defeat was not decisive as the Hungarian army kept its strength until they reached the Austrian border.

The battle showed that inexperienced men were not good enough to fight against the Emperor's army. It became clear that the Hungarian army needed brave leaders too. After this battle, only the loyal and brave leaders got higher positions in the Hungarian army.

==See also==
{{Portal|Austria-Hungary}}

==References==
{{No footnotes|date=December 2009}}

==Sources==
* {{citation|first=Róbert|last=Hermann|title=Az 1848–1849-es szabadságharc nagy csatái ''(&quot;Great Battles of the Hungarian Revolution of 1848 &amp;ndash; 1849&quot;)''|publisher=Zrínyi|year=2004|isbn=963-327-367-6|language=Hungarian}}
* {{citation|first=Róbert|last=Hermann|chapter=Az eldöntő döntetlen. A schwechati csata 1848. október 30-án ''(&quot;The Semi-final is Drawn. The Battle of Schwechat, 30 October 1848&quot;)|title=A Drávától a Lajtáig. Tanulmányok az 1848. nyári és őszi dunántúli hadi események történetéhez ''(&quot;From the River Dráva to the River Lajta. Studies on the summer and autumn military events of 1848&quot;)''|publisher=Balassi|year=2008|isbn=978-963-506-758-9|language=Hungarian}}
* {{citation|title=Magyarország hadtörténete két kötetben ''(&quot;Hungarian Military History in Two Volumes&quot;)''|editor=Ervin Liptai|publisher=Zrínyi Katonai (Zrínyi Military)|year=1985|isbn=963-326-337-9|language=Hungarian}}
* {{citation|first=László|last=Pusztaszeri|title=Görgey Artúr a szabadságharcban ''(&quot;Artúr Görgey in the Hungarian Revolution of 1848&quot;)''|publisher=Magvető|year=1984|isbn=963-14-0194-4|language=Hungarian}}
* {{citation|first1=Gyula|last1=Kedves|first2=József|last2=Zachar|first3=Péter Krisztián|last3=Zachar|title=1848/49-ről százötven év távlatából ''(&quot;1848-49 Seen 150 years Thence&quot;)''|publisher=Siklósi Vár és Múzeumbaráti Kör (Friends of Siklós Castle and Museum)|year=1999|isbn=963-03-9298-4|language=Hungarian}}
{{Commons category|Battle of Schwechat}}
{{Hungarian Revolution of 1848}}
{{coord missing|Austria}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Battle Of Pakozd}}
[[Category:Battles involving Austria|Schwechat 1848]]
[[Category:Battles involving Hungary|Schwechat 1848]]
[[Category:Battles involving the Habsburg Croatia|Schwechat 1848]]
[[Category:Hungarian Revolution of 1848]]</text>
      <sha1>1ro183zw1oam01uud4ih2evwvrnkj7l</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
