<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of Mirbat</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>684588</id>
    <revision>
      <id>742081674</id>
      <parentid>739037824</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-01T16:03:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Douts</username>
        <id>1211560</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Battle */  typo</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24495">{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2014}}
{{More footnotes|date=September 2010}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Battle of Mirbat
|image=[[File:Mirbat14.jpg|300px|Mirbat Castle, site of the Battle of Mirbat]]
|caption=The Wali's Fort.  The Battle centred on the DG Fort (not shown)
|partof=[[Dhofar Rebellion]]
|date=19 July 1972
|place=[[Mirbat]], South [[Oman]]
|coordinates = {{coord|16.9924934|54.6919477|format=dms|type:event|display=title,inline}}
|result=British/Oman sultanate victory
|combatant1={{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Special Air Service|British SAS]]
{{flagicon|Oman}} [[Royal Air Force of Oman]]  
|combatant2={{flagicon image|Flag of the Popular Front for the Liberation of the Occupied Arabian Gulf.svg}} [[Popular Front for the Liberation of the Occupied Arabian Gulf|Adoo guerillas]]
|commander1=[[Mike Kealy]]
|commander2=
|strength1=9 SAS soldiers&lt;br /&gt;
25 men from Omani Gendarmerie&lt;ref name=&quot;Peterson&quot;/&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
30 [[Baloch people|Balochi]] [[Askari]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Peterson&quot;/&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
1 local firqat&lt;ref name=&quot;Peterson&quot;&gt;[Peterson, J. E. (2007) &quot;Oman's Insurgencies: The Sultanate's Struggle for Supremacy&quot;. Saqi]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br/ &gt;
3 [[BAC Strikemaster]] light attack jets
|strength2=200-300 Adoo guerrillas
|casualties1=3 killed, 1 wounded
|casualties2=80+ killed
}}
{{Campaignbox Dhofar Rebellion}}
The '''Battle of Mirbat''' took place on 19 July 1972&lt;ref&gt;Winner, Pete, &amp; Kennedy, Michael. (2010). ''Soldier 'I' The Story of an SAS Hero'' ISBN 978-1-84603-995-9. Osprey Publishing. p. 101.&lt;/ref&gt; during the [[Dhofar Rebellion]] in [[Oman]], which was supported by [[Communist]] [[Guerrilla warfare|guerrillas]] from [[South Yemen]]. [[United Kingdom|Britain]] assisted the [[Government of Oman|Omani government]] by sending elements of its [[Special Air Service]] both to train [[soldier]]s and compete against the [[Popular Front for the Liberation of the Occupied Arabian Gulf]] (PFLOAG) guerrillas for the &quot;hearts and minds&quot; of the Omani people.&lt;ref name=&quot;smallwars&quot;/&gt;

==Battle==
At 6 am on 19 July 1972 the PFLOAG attacked the British Army Training Team (BATT) house, which housed the nine SAS soldiers, based just outside the Port of Mirbat. The PFLOAG (locally known as the Adoo) attacked the SAS BATT house knowing that to be able to reach the Port of Mirbat they would first have to defeat the SAS guarding the approach to the town in Jebel Ali, a series of small desert slopes leading to the Port.&lt;ref name=&quot;smallwars&quot;/&gt;

The Officer in Command, Captain [[Mike Kealy]] observed the waves advancing on the fort, but at first did not order his men to open fire because he thought it was the &quot;Night Picket&quot; coming back from night shift. The Night Picket were a loyal group of the [[Royal Army of Oman|Omani Army]] positioned on the slopes to warn the BATT house of Adoo troop movements. Realising that the Night Picket must have been killed, due to them not warning the SAS of the assault, Mike Kealy ordered his men to open fire. Mike Kealy along with other members of the team took up positions behind the sand-bag parapet on the roof of the BATT house, firing at the Adoo with [[L1A1 Self-Loading Rifle|L1A1 SLR]] [[battle rifle]]s, with one man firing the [[M2 Browning|Browning M2HB]] [[heavy machine gun]], with a further two men on ground level operating and firing an [[Mortar (weapon)|infantry mortar]] surrounded by sand-bags.  The Adoo were armed with [[AK-47]] [[assault rifle]]s, and were mortar bombing the area around the BATT house. Kealy ordered the signaller to establish communications with SAS Headquarters at Um al Quarif, to request reinforcements.&lt;ref name=&quot;smallwars&quot;/&gt;

There were also a small number of Omani Intelligence Service personnel in the BATT House, a small contingent of Pakistani soldiers and a member of British Military Intelligence seconded to the OIS. They joined the team on the roof and fired on the Adoo with SLRs and other small arms.{{Citation needed|date=September 2010}}  Initially some of the Pakistani soldiers were reluctant to join the defence of the fort because their roles with the BATT were largely administrative, but they obeyed orders from Mike Kealy and the British Military Intelligence Corporal.{{Citation needed|date=September 2010}}
[[File:Dhofar-BATT house (2).jpg|thumb|right|Overflying the BATT House, Mirbat.]]Knowing that the SLRs would not be of full use until the Adoo were closer than the weapon's range of 800&amp;nbsp;metres, and lacking heavier firepower, Sergeant [[Talaiasi Labalaba]] made a run for the [[Ordnance QF 25 pounder|25 Pounder Artillery Piece]], which was positioned next to a smaller fort manned by nine{{Citation needed|date=February 2015}} Omani Army Special Forces soldiers, who had not played a part in the battle. The Omani policeman who was guarding the weapon had been seriously wounded. Talaiasi Labalaba managed to operate the weapon, which is a six-man job, by himself and fire a round a minute at the approaching Adoo, directing their attention away from the BATT house. Kealy received a radio message from Talaiasi reporting that a bullet had skimmed his face, he was badly injured, and was struggling to operate the gun on his own. At the BATT house Kealy asked for a volunteer to run to Talaiasi's aid. Trooper Sekonaia Takavesi volunteered to go.&lt;ref name=&quot;smallwars&quot;/&gt;

Sekonaia Takavesi ran from the BATT house, with the remaining men providing covering fire, in an attempt to distract the Adoo. Sekonaia ran the 800&amp;nbsp;metres through heavy gunfire, and reached the gun emplacement. Sekonaia tried to give aid to his injured friend, while firing at the approaching Adoo with his personal weapon. Realising that they needed help, Sekonaia tried to raise the small number of Omani soldiers inside the smaller fort and Walid Khamis emerged. The remaining Omani soldiers in the fort engaged the enemy with small arms fire from firing positions on the roof and through the windows of the fort.{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}} As the two men made it back to the emplacement, the Omani soldier fell wounded after being shot in the stomach with a 7.62&amp;nbsp;mm bullet. Adoo continued to advance upon both the BATT house and the artillery emplacement. At one point, the Adoo were so close that Sekonaia and Talaiasi fired the weapon at point blank range, aiming down the barrel. Talaiasi crawled across a small space to reach a 60&amp;nbsp;mm Infantry Mortar, but fell dead after being shot in the neck. Sekonaia, also shot through the shoulder and grazed by a bullet to the back of his head, continued to fire at the approaching Adoo with his personal weapon. The squad signaller sent messages through to the main Forward Operating Base, to request air support and medical evacuation for the men in the gun emplacement.&lt;ref name=&quot;smallwars&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Dhofar-BATT house.jpg|thumb|left|Inside the BATT House at Mirbat]]
Captain Kealy and Trooper Tobin made a run to the artillery piece. Upon reaching it, they dived in to avoid increasingly intense gunfire from the Adoo. Sekonaia continued to fire on the attackers, propped up against sand bags after being shot through the stomach (the bullet narrowly missing his spine). The Adoo threw several [[Grenade|hand grenades]], but only one detonated, exploding behind the emplacement with no one injured. During the battle, Trooper Tobin attempted to reach over the body of Talaiasi. In so doing, Tobin was mortally wounded when a bullet struck his face.  By this time, [[BAC Strikemaster]] light-attack jets of the [[Sultan of Oman's Air Force]] had arrived and began strafing the Adoo in the Jebel Ali. With a low cloud base making for low-altitude attack runs, only machine-guns and light rockets were used.&lt;ref&gt;White, Rowland ''Storm Front'' London Transworld 2011 pp278-9 ISBN 978-0-593-06434-4&lt;/ref&gt; Reinforcements arrived from G&amp;nbsp;Squadron and, defeated, the PFLOAG withdrew at about 12:30. All wounded SAS soldiers were evacuated, and given medical treatment. Trooper Tobin eventually died in hospital, not due to the multiple gunshot wounds but to an infection in his lung caused by a splintered tooth, which he had inhaled when his bottom jaw was blown off by an AK-47 round.&lt;ref name=&quot;smallwars&quot;/&gt;

==Aftermath==
[[File:Mirbat gun.jpg|250px|thumb|&quot;Mirbat gun&quot; at the Firepower museum of the Royal Artillery]]
The 25-pounder gun (now known as the &quot;Mirbat gun&quot;) used by Fijian Sergeant Talaiasi Labalaba during the siege is now housed in the [[Firepower - The Royal Artillery Museum|Firepower museum]] of the [[Royal Artillery]] at the former [[Royal Arsenal]], [[Woolwich]]. Though killed in action, Sgt Labalaba displayed remarkable bravery by singlehandedly operating the 25-pounder gun, a weapon normally requiring four to six soldiers to operate. Labalaba's heroism was a key factor in halting the Adoo's assault on the emplacement, allowing time for reinforcements to arrive. Labalaba was awarded a posthumous [[Mention in Dispatches]] for his actions in the Battle of Mirbat, though some of his comrades have since campaigned for him to be awarded the more prestigious [[Victoria Cross]].&lt;ref name=&quot;smallwars&quot;&gt;[http://wayback.archive.org/web/20131231194422/http://britains-smallwars.com/Desert_song/Mirbat.htm Description of the battle]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;At the time, the Victoria Cross and Mention in Despatches were the only combat decorations which could be awarded posthumously.&lt;/ref&gt;

The following SAS soldiers were present at Mirbat on 19 July 1972:&lt;ref name=&quot;smallwars&quot;/&gt;

*[[Mike Kealy|Captain Mike Kealy]]
*Staff Sergeant [[Talaiasi Labalaba|Talaiasi &quot;Laba&quot; Labalaba]] (Killed in action)
*Sergeant Bob Bennett
*Corporal Roger Cole
*Corporal L. M. Taylor (Believed to be an alias - possibly Corporal Alan McNeice)
*Lance Corporal P. Warne (Also known as Pete Wignall, Pete Winner &amp; Soldier I, nickname Snapper)
*Trooper Sekonaia &quot;Tak&quot; Takavesi&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kxmtbMFGSXo SAS Heroes: Last Stand In Oman on You Tube.]&lt;/ref&gt;
*Trooper Thomas Tobin (Died of wounds)
*Austin &quot;Fuzz&quot; Hussey

Kealy received the [[Distinguished Service Order]], Takavesi the [[Distinguished Conduct Medal]], Bennett and McNeice the [[Military Medal]]. These were announced three years after the event.&lt;ref name=&quot;smallwars&quot;/&gt; An Omani from the fort, Walid Khamis, was injured during the battle and received the Sultan's Gallantry Medal&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.royalark.net/Oman/medals.htm Oman: medals]&lt;/ref&gt; - Oman's highest award.

The battle was underreported, and many considered the SAS team deserving of further individual awards for gallantry. However, many in Oman at that time perceived a desire by HM Government and the MoD to downplay incidents of direct involvement of British service personnel in military action.  The British Military Intelligence Corporal received a medal for gallantry from the Sultan (for this action and others), but was threatened with disciplinary action by the British Army for being directly involved in the action at Mirbat.{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}}

==In popular culture==
*Sir [[Ranulph Fiennes]] alleged in his book ''[[The Feather Men]]'' that Mike Kealy was murdered years later in the [[Brecon Beacons]] by an Arab militant cell. However, the circumstances of Kealy's death suggest that this is somewhat fanciful, as he was seen by other service personnel undergoing the same SAS endurance exercise only a few hours beforehand in deteriorating weather conditions, and was in fact found alive (but in poor condition) by a two-man search party, one of whom stayed with him and attempted to keep him warm. It was later acknowledged by the Coroner that one of the major contributory factors to his death was the delay of some 19 hours in recovering him from the hillside. Subsequently, the author admitted the book was fiction and that no such assassinations ever took place.&lt;ref name=dailybeast&gt;{{cite news|last=Stern|first=Marlow|title=The Real-Life ‘Killer Elite’|url=http://www.thedailybeast.com/articles/2011/09/30/sir-ranulph-fiennes-talks-the-feather-men-and-killer-elite-with-robert-de-niro.html|accessdate=15 March 2013|newspaper=The Daily Beast|date=30 September 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The battle is briefly depicted in the 2011 film ''[[Killer Elite (film)|Killer Elite]]'', where it is central to the plot. The film is based on Fiennes' fictional book.
*The battle is also mentioned by [[Frederick Forsyth]] in his book ''[[The Veteran (short story collection)|The Veteran]]'', where a member of the SAS team is murdered by two criminals 30 years after the engagement.
*The battle is referred to in [[Chris Ryan]]'s &quot;Land of Fire&quot;, but is called &quot;The Battle of Merbak&quot;, the Adoo are numbered in the thousands and Laba is replaced by a character called Tom who is wounded but lives.
*The battle is described in [[Rowland White]]'s &quot;Storm Front&quot;.

==See also==
*[[Dhofar Rebellion]]
*[[Oman]]
*[[PFLOAG]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}
{{Refbegin}}
*{{cite news |last=Warman |first=Matt |title=Special Forces Heroes |url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/tvandradio/3563394/Special-Forces-Heroes.html |work=Telegraph |date=19 November 2008 |accessdate=2009-10-21}}
*{{cite news |last=Lord Ashcroft |first=|title=Special forces heroes: A unique type of valour, a rare kind of courage |url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-1088456/Special-forces-heroes-MICHAEL-ASHCROFT-examines-makes-soldier-hero-coward.html |work=Daily Mail |date=25 November 2008 |accessdate=2009-10-21}}
{{Refend}}

==External links==
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/england/hereford/worcs/3219357.stm BBC News Article]
* [http://www.soldierisas.com/mirbat Battle of Mirbat 1972, Soldier 'I']

&lt;!--    
{{Copypaste|date=May 2012}}
Intelligence Background to the Battle of Mirbat – 19 July 72

The information in this article was almost entirely obtained during interviews with around 120 ex-hard core and militia members of PFLOAG (otherwise known as ‘The Front’ or ‘adoo’) who had been organised into ‘firqats’ (teams’ or ‘units’) to fight against the Government of Oman on the mountains (jebal) of Dhofar. For various reasons they had surrendered to the Government when they ‘nazalt min al jebal’ (‘came down from the mountain’) during the 12 months following the failure of the Front attack on Mirbat on 19 July 1972. These personnel were referred to as Surrendered Enemy Personnel (SEPs) and they usually ended up changing sides and joining Omani Government backed ‘firqats’ and then fighting on the jebal against their ex-comrades in the Front.

Reasons for their surrender varied, but after the failure of the attack on Mirbat many of them were now convinced that the Front could not win the war and an effective political, religious and economic ‘Hearts and Minds’ campaign among the Dhofari civilian jebalis also had a disheartening effect on them.

These SEPs were debriefed by personnel from the Intelligence Cell at HQ Dhofar Brigade after their surrender, during the period July 1972 to July 1973

Planning

The attack on Mirbat was probably conceived and planned by the OC of the Central Area Unit or firqat (CAU). He was killed in action at Mirbat and after his death the unit was then re named after him (Firqat Shaheed Salim Musalim ?).  As far as is known the force that attacked Mirbat involved all the hard-core fighters (muqaatil) of the Eastern Area Unit (EAU) (the firqat mintaqat sharqiya), most of the CAU and elements from the Western Area Unit (WAU) and the Ho Chi Min Unit (HCM) plus some members of the PFLOAG militia (Idaarat).  The total number of adoo is not known for certain but was probably between 200 – 300.

All the adoo brought their personal small arms with them (AK47s, RPD, RPG, hand grenades) plus a few heavier weapons like 60mm and 82mm mortars. One Dshk 12.7mm HMG was also mounted on Jebal Ali during the attack and probably some Goryunov MMGs were deployed. As far as is known no 75mm RCLs were used.  The adoo also had an 84mm Carl Gustav (‘Charlie G’) recoilless rifle that had been passed on to them from the PDRY government in Aden, who had in turn inherited it from the British army when the UK left Aden in 1967 – the reasons why it was only used a few times during the attack and disappeared shortly afterwards will be described later on.

Background to the attack.

It had long been assumed by the Intelligence Cell (‘The Spooks’) at HQ Dhofar Brigade and the BATT HQ that the Front wanted to carry out a ‘spectacular’ attack around the time of the anniversary of the accession of Sultan Qaboos in July 1971. Adoo propaganda leaflets had shown pictures of possible Vietcong visitors to the Dhofar jebal the previous year and it was felt that they might try to emulate the North Vietnamese Tet offensive of 1967 by demonstrating that they now had the power not only to defeat the Sultan’s Armed Forces in a major battle, but also seize and hold a high-profile Government-held town or village. This would show the local population that they now had the military and political power to defeat the Government forces on a wider scale and form an alternative government.

Intelligence gathering on the Adoo

There were very real limitations to gathering intelligence on adoo activities on the jebal.  A low key but effective Government propaganda campaign, emphasising the benefits to be gained from supporting the new Government had produced a trickle of SEPs over the previous few months and a few, e.g. Muhammad Suhail from the Eastern Area, had a high profile within the adoo before they surrendered, so while there was good intelligence on the Order of Battle (ORBAT) of the adoo there was very little on their future intentions.  The weather (the ‘khareef’ or monsoon) at the time of the Mirbat attack in July precluded any aerial reconnaissance so nearly all information came from intelligence reports (Intreps) produced by the various BATT and Sultan’s Armed Forces (SAF) locations on the jebal, who in turn usually received it in the form of verbal debriefings of Government firqat patrols who lived and patrolled in the local areas.  These reports had to be treated with caution as most of the members of the Government firqats were ex-adoo who often had a vested interest in producing information that suited their own motives.

Intelligence leading up to the Attack

On the evening of 18 July the BATT HQ in Umm al Gwarif camp in Salalah received an Intrep from the BATT unit in Taqa, a Government-held small town on the coast to the east of Salalah, the capital of Dhofar. It reported that one of their firqat patrols had received information from civilians on the jebal that 40(+) adoo had recently been seen crossing the Wadi Darbat, moving from east to west.  A sighting of an adoo unit of this size was unusual (they normally operated in groups of 4 to 6) but even allowing for the inherent unreliability of such reports it was certainly an indicator that something might be about to happen, especially so close to the anniversary of the Sultan’s succession.  The direction in which the adoo force was reported to be moving indicated that an attack on Taqa might be in the offing, and Taqa was warned to that effect.

Operationally there was not much that Dhofar Bde HQ could do to reinforce the Taqa location.  There was a company-sized Quick Reaction Force (QRF) of the Northern Frontier Regiment on standby at Umm al Gwariff who were ready to move at very short notice, but the BATT were in the middle of changing units (the main body of G Sqn 22 SAS had arrived that very day and were in the process of taking over from B Sqn) and with the lack of any more credible intelligence the HQ would just have to wait and react to events.  The BATT team at Mirbat were informed of the situation, but as Mirbat had been relatively quiet for a long time and there were few indications of adoo activity in that area (to the east of Taqa) it was felt that Mirbat was a less likely target than Taqa. However, the government firqat from Mirbat did go out on patrol to the jebal to try to obtain information the night before the attack.

Post-Exercise (PX) Report

A subsequent investigation into the apparent failure of intelligence showed that the original signal, warning of the movement of the 40+ adoo across the Wadi Darbat from east to west, had been garbled in transmission and should have reported that they were moving from west to east, away from Taqa, and were therefore probably heading towards Mirbat, as that was the only other Government-held town in the area.  As it happens there was very little else that could have been done to reinforce Mirbat.  Movement at night by foot or vehicle across the jebal and at such short notice was virtually impossible due to the terrain difficulties; reinforcement by helicopter was not feasible because of the very poor visibility, due to heavy mist and fog caused by the khareef.

The adoo tried to achieve surprise by a dawn attack on the following morning (19 July) coming from the north towards Mirbat, but the alarm was raised before they were in position to sweep through the town.  The subsequent battle has been well described by various sources and plays no part in this article, but the end result was a devastating defeat and blow to the image and morale of the Front, and from that time a steady stream of SEPs started leaving the jebal and surrendering to the Omani Government.

Subsequent Events

A couple of interesting stories might help to flesh out events during and after the battle.  The first one concerns the aforementioned Carl Gustav (CG) RCL that the adoo possessed and used against the defences in Mirbat. After the battle this weapon disappeared and it was not until a later SEP described what happened that the full story came out.

Apparently the National Liberation Front (NLF) government in Aden handed over this particular Carl Gustav and some ammunition to the Front around 1971 for them to use as they saw fit.  When it was used at Mirbat against one of the Government Forts there only a few rounds were fired and for a long time it was a mystery as to why it was not used more effectively.

During his debrief the SEP said that was because the man who was firing it during the battle started to suffer head injuries from the recoil and after a few rounds refused to fire it again. Nobody else could be found to volunteer to take his place and the weapon disappeared and was never used again.  One of the empty missile cases used at Mirbat was subsequently recovered after the battle and when the serial number of the round was checked against British army records it was found to be part of a batch of ammunition that had been issued to the Irish Guards when they were stationed in Aden in 1965/6.  They had test-fired some rounds but after several of their personnel received head injuries from the excessive recoil it was realised that the ammunition was defective and withdrawn from service. When Aden was handed over to the incoming National Liberation Front government this ammunition was left behind, and was subsequently handed over to the adoo.

Another story concerns the fate of one of the adoo who was injured during the battle.  Although his injuries were not life threatening it was decided that he would be evacuated to Hauf, just across the border from Dhofar in the PDRY, where the Front had a hospital that was manned by a Palestinian doctor and some local medical staff.

The injured man was carried on a stretcher by four of his comrades across the jebal from the battlefield at Mirbat to the Front hospital in Hauf, avoiding SAF and BATT patrols and harassing fire from SAF artillery. They all arrived safely in Hauf after a very arduous journey lasting about a month. In the hospital he was examined by the Palestinian doctor who gave him an injection.  For unknown reasons the patient reacted badly to the injection and promptly died, while his comrades looked on in disbelief.  Naturally they were very upset and it was only the presence of other Front personnel that dissuaded them from killing the doctor on the spot.  It was as a result of this that all four of the men subsequently became SEPs.
--&gt;

{{DEFAULTSORT:Mirbat, Battle of 1972}}
[[Category:Mirbat|Battle]]
[[Category:Communism in Oman]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1972]]
[[Category:Rebellions in Asia]]
[[Category:History of Oman]]
[[Category:Dhofar Rebellion]]
[[Category:Special Air Service]]
[[Category:1972 in Asia]]
[[Category:1972 in Oman]]
[[Category:Battles involving the United Kingdom]]</text>
      <sha1>18vol2zcrfybentyby78e3k6qie6iac</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
