<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of Orsha</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>964136</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749097013</id>
      <parentid>746821067</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-12T11:05:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bartoha</username>
        <id>1881950</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* External links */ A link to an article in English about Polish Winged Hussars, by Polish historian R. Sikora and Polish diplomat B. Musialowicz</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17209">{{refimprove|date=September 2011}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Battle of Orsha
|image=[[File:Autor nieznany (malarz z kręgu Lukasa Cranacha Starszego), Bitwa pod Orszą.jpg|300px]]
|caption=Painting attributed to [[Hans Krell]]
|partof=the [[Muscovite–Lithuanian_Wars#Fourth_war_.281512.E2.80.931522.29|fourth Muscovite–Lithuanian War]] (1512–1522)
|date=8 September 1514
|place=[[Orsha]], [[Grand Duchy of Lithuania]], present day [[Belarus]]
|coordinates={{coord|54|30|N|30|23|E|region:BY_type:event|display=inline,title}}
|result=Polish–Lithuanian victory
|combatant1=[[Grand Duchy of Lithuania]], [[Kingdom of Poland (1385–1569)|Kingdom of Poland]]
|combatant2=[[Grand Duchy of Moscow]]
|commander1=[[Konstanty Ostrogski]]
|commander2=[[Ivan Chelyadnin]]{{POW}}
|strength1=12,000&lt;ref&gt;Лобин А. Н. К вопросу о численности и составе польско-литовской армии в битве под Оршей в 1514 г. // Праблемы інтэграцыі і iнкарпарацыі ў развіцці Цэнтральнай і Усходняй Еўропы ў перыяд ранняга Новага часу. Мінск, 2010. С. 18-42&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;
25,000&lt;ref name=&quot;Podhorodecki&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title=Sławne bitwy Polaków | publisher=MADA | author=Podhorodecki, Leszek | year=1997 | pages=105–106 | isbn=8386170247}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;
35,000 men&lt;ref name=&quot;Spieralski&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title=Wojskowość polska w okresie odrodzenia [w:] Zarys dziejów wojskowości polskiej do roku 1864, t. I, pod red. Janusza Sikorskiego | publisher= | author=Spieralski, Zdzisław | year=1965 | pages=331 | isbn=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wojciechowski&quot;&gt;{{cite book | title=Zygmunt Stary (1506-1548) | publisher= | author=Wojciechowski, Zygmunt | year=1946 | pages=50 | isbn=}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 300 cannons
|strength2=12,000&lt;ref name=&quot;Lobin&quot;&gt;Лобин А. Н. К вопросу о численности вооружённых сил Российского государства в XVI в.//Studia Slavica et Balcanica Petropolitana 2009 Nr 1-2. p. 66&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;
35,000-40,000&lt;ref name=&quot;Podhorodecki&quot;/&gt;&lt;br&gt;
80,000 men&lt;ref name=&quot;Spieralski&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wojciechowski&quot;/&gt;&lt;br /&gt; 140 to 300 cannons 
|casualties1=Unknown
|casualties2= 13,000-40.000 dead and wounded, at least 5,000 captured
}}
{{Campaignbox Muscovite–Lithuanian War (1512–1522)}}
The '''Battle of Orsha''' was fought on 8 September 1514, between the allied forces of the [[Grand Duchy of Lithuania]] and the [[Jagiellon Poland|Kingdom of Poland]], under the command of [[Hetman]] [[Konstanty Ostrogski]]; and the army of the [[Grand Duchy of Moscow]] under [[Konyushy]] [[Ivan Chelyadnin]] and [[Kniaz]] [[Galitzine|Mikhail Golitsin]]. The Battle of Orsha was part of a long series of [[Muscovite–Lithuanian Wars]] conducted by Muscovite rulers striving to gather all the former [[Kievan Rus']] lands under their rule.

According to ''[[Rerum Moscoviticarum Commentarii]]'' by [[Sigismund von Herberstein]], the primary source for information on the battle, the much smaller army of Poland–Lithuania (under 30,000 men) defeated a force of 80,000 Muscovite soldiers, capturing their camp and commander. These numbers and proportions have been disputed by modern historians.

==Eve of battle==
At the end of 1512, the [[Grand Duchy of Moscow]] began a new war for the [[Grand Duchy of Lithuania]]'s [[Ruthenia]]n lands in present-day [[Lithuania]], [[Belarus]] and [[Ukraine]]. [[Albert I, Duke of Prussia|Albrecht I]], Grand Master of the [[Teutonic Knights]], rebelled and refused to give a vassal pledge to [[Sigismund I the Old]] of Poland-Lithuania, as required by the [[Second Peace of Thorn (1466)]]. Albrecht I was supported by [[Maximilian I, Holy Roman Emperor]].&lt;ref name=&quot;baranauskas&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.delfi.lt/news/ringas/lit/article.php?id=10641866 |first=Tomas |last=Baranauskas |authorlink=Tomas Baranauskas | title= Oršos mūšis – didžiausia Lietuvos karinė pergalė prieš Rusiją |date=2006-09-08|language=lt}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The fortress of [[Smolensk]] was then the easternmost outpost of the Grand Duchy of Lithuania and one of the most important strongholds guarding it from the east. It repelled several Muscovite attacks, but in July 1514 a Muscovite army besieged and finally captured it. Spurred on by this initial success, the [[Grand Prince of Moscow]] [[Vasili III of Russia|Vasili III]] ordered his forces farther into present-day Belarus, occupying the towns of [[Krichev]], [[Mstislavl]] and [[Dubrovna]].

Meanwhile, [[Sigismund the Old]] gathered some 35,000 troops for war with his eastern neighbor. This army was inferior in numbers, but consisted mostly of well-trained [[cavalry]]. The forces of the Grand Duchy of Lithuania and the Kingdom of Poland placed under the command of Hetman [[Konstanty Ostrogski]] included 16,000 Lithuania cavalry, 14,000 [[Polish cavalry]] (light and heavy), 3,000 Polish [[mercenary]] [[infantry]], and 2,500 volunteers, mostly from [[Bohemia]]. Sigismund left 4,000–5,000 men in the town of [[Barysau]], while the main force, around 30,000 strong, moved on to face the Muscovites.&lt;ref name=&quot;baranauskas&quot;/&gt; At the end of August, several skirmishes took place at the crossings of the [[Berezina]], [[Bobr Rivier|Bobr]] and [[Drut River]]s, but the Muscovite army avoided a major confrontation.

Suffering negligible losses, the Muscovites advanced to the area between [[Orsha]] and [[Dubrovno]] on the [[Krapivna River]], where they set up camp. [[Ivan Chelyadnin]], confident that the Lithuanian-Polish forces would have to cross one of the two bridges on the [[Dnieper River]], split his own forces to guard those crossings. However, Ostrogski's army crossed the river farther north via two [[pontoon bridge]]s. On the night of 7 September, the Lithuanian-Polish army began preparations for a final battle with the Muscovites. Hetman Konstantyn Ostrogski placed most of his 16,000 horses from the Grand Duchy in the center, while most of the Polish [[infantry]] and the auxiliary troops manned the flanks. The [[Bohemia]]n and [[Silesia]]n infantry were deployed in the center of the line, in front of the reserves comprising Lithuanian and Polish [[cavalry]].

===The size of the Muscovite army===
[[File:Russo-Polish war XVI century.JPG|thumb|right|Russo-Polish war, image from Jacob Piso ''Die Schlacht von dem Kunig von Poln und mit dem Moscowiter'', 1514]]
The size of the Muscovite army remains an unsolved question. Narrative Lithuanian-Polish sources generally give large numbers. King Sigismund wrote to [[Pope Leo X]] about a &quot;horde of Muscovites&quot; which consisted of 80,000 men.&lt;ref&gt;Лобин А. Н. К вопросу о численности вооружённых сил Российского государства в XVI в.//Studia Slavica et Balcanica Petropolitana 2009 Nr. 1-2. page 61&lt;/ref&gt; Sigismund also claimed that his army had killed 30,000 Muscovites and taken prisoner 46 commanders and 1,500 nobles. Extant Polish and Lithuanian documents, however, list all captured nobles by name; only 611 men in all. The Polish historian Bohun considers it improvident to rely on what he terms &quot;propaganda data&quot; given by Sigismund.&lt;ref&gt;Bohun T. Bitwa pod Orsza 08.09.1514 // Rzeczpospolita. 2006. ¹ 4/20. S. 13.&lt;/ref&gt; Gembarowicz (another Polish researcher) is of the opinion that the Muscovite army was about 40,000 strong. It also remains unclear why - if the figure of 70,000–80,000 men is to be trusted - King Sigismund (who knew about this superiority of the Muscovite army from [[Michael Glinski|Mikhail Glinsky]]'s letters) kept a personal guard of about 5,000 men (about 15% of his army) in reserve, without sending them into the battle. The Muscovite chronicles ([[Novgorodian codex|Novgorodian]] and [[Sophian codex]]es) claim a Lithuanian-Polish numerical superiority.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lobin&quot;/&gt;

The Russian historian A. Lobin tried to calculate the size of the Muscovite army at Orsha based on the mobilisation capacities of the towns which had to send townspeople for military service.&lt;ref&gt;Лобин А. Н. К вопросу о численности вооружённых сил Российского государства в XVI в.//Studia Slavica et Balcanica Petropolitana 2009 Nr 1-2. pp.45-78&lt;/ref&gt; It is known that except for Boyar sons of the sovereign's regiment, the army consisted of people from at least 14 towns: [[Novgorod]], [[Pskov]], [[Velikie Luki]], [[Kostroma]], [[Murom]], [[Borovsk]], [[Tver]], [[Volokolamsk|Volok]], [[Roslavl]], [[Vyazma]], [[Pereslavl-Zalessky|Pereyaslavl]], [[Kolomna]], [[Yaroslavl]] and [[Starodub]].&lt;ref&gt;Лобин А. Н. К вопросу о численности вооружённых сил Российского государства в XVI в.//Studia Slavica et Balcanica Petropolitana 2009 Nr. 1-2. pp. 63-64&lt;/ref&gt; Based on figures from the well-documented [[Polotsk]] campaign of 1563, the author gives the following estimates: 400–500 Tatars, 200 boyar sons of the sovereign's regiment, 3,000 Novgorodian and Pskovians, and about 3,600 representatives of other towns, altogether about 7,200 noblemen. Once servants are included, the overall size of the Muscovite army could be 13,000-15,000 men. Considering the losses during the campaign, the level of desertion which is documented in the sources and the number of soldiers left as a garrison in Smolensk; the number of Muscovite troops present at Orsha could have been as low as about 12,000 men.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lobin&quot;/&gt;

This calculation method has been backed by such historians as Brian Davies (University of Texas at San Antonio, USA),&lt;ref name=&quot;davies&quot;&gt;Форум//Studia Slavica et Balcanica Petropolitana 2009 Nr 1-2. pp.120-121&lt;/ref&gt; N. Smirnov, A. Pankov, O. Kurbatov,&lt;ref name=&quot;kurbatov&quot;&gt;Курбатов О. А. Отклик на статью А. Н. Лобина//Studia Slavica et Balcanica Petropolitana 2009 Nr 1-2. pp.104-119&lt;/ref&gt; М. Krom,&lt;ref name=&quot;krom&quot;&gt;Кром М. М. Еще раз о численности русского войска в XVI в. (По поводу статьи А. Н. Лобина)//Studia Slavica et Balcanica Petropolitana 2009 Nr 1-2. pp.79-90&lt;/ref&gt; and V. Penskoy.&lt;ref name=&quot;penskoy&quot;&gt;Пенской В. В. Некоторые соображения по поводу статьи А. Н. Лобина «К вопросу о численности вооружённых сил Российского государства XVI в.»//Studia Slavica et Balcanica Petropolitana 2009 Nr. 1-2. pp.79-90&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battle==
[[File:Сергей В. Иванов - Военная кампания в России в 16 веке.jpg|thumb|upright=1.3|left|''Russian campaign against the Lithuanians'' (oil on canvas by [[Sergey Ivanov (painter)|Sergey Ivanov]], 1903).]]
On 8 September 1514, shortly after dawn, [[Ivan Chelyadnin]] gave the order to attack. The Muscovite forces attempted to outflank the Lithuanians and Poles by attacking their flanks, which were manned by Polish, Lithuanian light hussar and Tartar troops. One of the pincers of the attack was commanded by Chelyadnin personally, while the other was led by Prince [[Galitzine|Bulgakov-Golitsa]]. The initial attack failed, and the Muscovites withdrew toward their starting positions. Chelyadnin was still confident that the odds, almost 3:1 in his favor, would give him the victory. However, preoccupied with his own wing of the Muscovite forces, he lost track of the other sectors and failed to coordinate a defense against the counterattack by the Lithuanian light and Polish heavy cavalry, which until then had been kept in reserve.

The Lithuanian  and Polish [[light cavalry|light horse]] and Tartars attacked the overstretched center of the Muscovite lines in an attempt to split them. At the crucial moment the Lithuanian-Polish cavalry seemed to waver, then went into retreat. The Muscovites pursued with all their [[cavalry]] reserves. The Lithuanian Tartars and Polish cavalry, after retreating for several minutes under chase from the Russians, suddenly turned to the sides. The Muscovite cavalry now found themselves confronted by [[artillery]] concealed in the forest. From both sides, Polish and Lithuanian forces appeared and proceeded to surround the Muscovites. Ivan Chelyadnin sounded [[withdrawal (military)|retreat]], which soon became somewhat panicky. The Muscovite forces were pursued by the army of the [[Grand Duchy of Lithuania]] for five kilometres.

The Muscovite defeat is often attributed to repeated failures by Ivan Chelyadnin and [[Galitzine|Golitsa]] to coordinate their operations.

[[Sigismund von Herberstein]] reported that 40,000 Muscovites were killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;baranauskas&quot;/&gt; According to accounts in Polish [[chronicle]]s, 30,000 Russians were killed and an additional 3,000 were taken captive, including Ivan Chelyadnin and eight other commanders. The forces of the Grand Duchy of Lithuania and Kingdom of Poland seized the Muscovite [[military camp|camp]] and all 300 [[cannon]]s. Upset at word of the massive defeat, Grand Prince [[Vasili III of Muscovy|Vasili III]] allegedly remarked that &quot;the prisoners [were] as useful as the dead&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;baranauskas&quot;/&gt;

==Aftermath==
[[File:Husaria.JPG|thumb|225px|Polish Hussars during the Battle of Orsha (1514)]]
Ostrogski's forces continued their pursuit of the routed Russian army and retook most of the previously captured strongholds, including [[Mstislavl]] and Krychev, and the advancement of the Russians was stopped for four years.&lt;ref name=&quot;baranauskas&quot;/&gt; However, the Lithuanian and Polish forces were too exhausted to besiege [[Smolensk]] before the winter. This meant that Ostrogski did not reach the gates of Smolensk until late September, giving Vasili III enough time to prepare defense.

In December 1514, [[Hetman]] [[Konstanty Ostrogski]] triumphantly entered [[Vilnius]]. To commemorate the victory, two Orthodox churches were erected: the Church of the Holy Trinity and the [[St. Nicholas Orthodox Church, Vilnius|Church of Saint Nicholas]], which remain among the most impressive examples of [[Orthodox Church]] architecture in Lithuania. Immediately after the victory, the Polish–Lithuanian state started to exploit the battle for its [[propaganda]] aimed at other nations in Europe, with the intent of improving the image of Poland-Lithuania abroad. Several panegyrical accounts of the battle were sent to [[Rome]]. &quot;The Polish message was similar to Bomhover's: the Muscovites are not Christians; they are cruel and barbaric; they are Asians and not Europeans; they are in league with Turks and the Tatars to destroy Christendom&quot;.&lt;ref name=poe&gt;{{cite book |first=Marshall T. |last=Poe |title=A People Born to Slavery: Russia in Early Modern European Ethnography, 1478-1748 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=bvLHqFOTLL4C&amp;pg=PA21 |publisher=Cornell University Press |year=2001 |isbn= 0-8014-3798-9 |page=21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Impressed by the scope of the Lithuanian and Polish victory, Maximilian I, Holy Roman Emperor, started peace negotiations with the [[Jagiellon dynasty|Jagiellons]] in Vienna. On 22 July 1515, final agreements for peace were made and the broad coalition against Lithuania and Poland ceased.&lt;ref name=&quot;baranauskas&quot;/&gt;

The war between the [[Grand Duchy of Lithuania]] and [[Grand Duchy of Moscow]] lasted until 1520. In 1522 a peace was signed, under the terms of which Lithuania was forced to cede to Moscow about a quarter of its possessions within the lands of the former [[Kievan Rus']], including [[Smolensk]]. The latter city was not retaken until almost a century later, in 1611. After the peace agreement of 1522, the Grand Duchy of Lithuania tried to attack Russia one more time, but major military conflicts were settled for around 40 years.&lt;ref name=&quot;baranauskas&quot;/&gt;

==Modern times==
The battle is regarded by [[Belarusians]] as a symbol of national revival, but its significance is being suppressed by state authorities. In September 2005, by order of President [[Alexander Lukashenko]], four members of the [[Belarusian National Front]] opposition were each fined almost 4 million [[Belarusian ruble|rubles]] (roughly [[Euro|€]]1,500) for celebrating the 491st anniversary of the battle.

The Battle of Orsha is commemorated on the [[Tomb of the Unknown Soldier, Warsaw]], with the inscription &quot;ORSZA 8 IX 1514&quot;.

==Popular Culture==
On the [[BBC]] television program ''[[Being Human (UK TV series)|Being Human]]'', Hal Yorke was made a vampire after the Battle of Orsha.

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* Cherkas, B. ''[http://www.istpravda.com.ua/articles/2013/07/24/131707/ Battle of Orsha. Prince of Ostroh against Prince of Moscow]''. [[Ukrayinska Pravda]] (originally from [[Tyzhden]]). July 24, 2013.
*[https://www.msz.gov.pl/resource/21badcbf-0c18-4fb8-8b19-3d382469d25f:JCR ''Winged Hussars''], Radoslaw Sikora, Bartosz Musialowicz, ''BUM Magazine'', October 2016.

[[Category:1514 in Lithuania]]
[[Category:Battles involving Poland|Orsza 1514]]
[[Category:Battles involving Russia|Orsha 1514]]
[[Category:Battles involving the Grand Duchy of Lithuania|Orsha 1514]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1514|Orsha]]</text>
      <sha1>kl3p3n7s8ztdplqb8efu95ems6cq9x0</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
