<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of Bannockburn</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>50993</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749520311</id>
      <parentid>749517423</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-14T19:38:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Hchc2009</username>
        <id>9559123</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 749517423 by [[Special:Contributions/81.109.243.236|81.109.243.236]] ([[User talk:81.109.243.236|talk]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25871">{{shortlead|date=October 2016}}
{{Use British English|date=August 2011}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2011}}
{{Coord|56.092|-3.915|display=title|region:GB_scale:50000}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict    = Battle of Bannockburn
|partof      = the [[First War of Scottish Independence]]
|image       = [[File:Battle of Bannockburn.jpg|240px]]
|caption     = This depiction from the [[Scotichronicon]] (c.1440) is the earliest known image of the battle.  King Robert wielding an axe and Edward II fleeing toward Stirling feature prominently, conflating incidents from the two days of battle.
|date        = 23–24 June 1314
|place       = [[Bannockburn]], south of [[Stirling]], Scotland
|result      = Decisive Scottish victory
|combatant1  = [[File:Royal Arms of the Kingdom of Scotland.svg|25px]] [[Kingdom of Scotland]]
|combatant2  = [[File:Royal Arms of England (1198-1340).svg|24px]] [[Kingdom of England]]
|commander1  = [[File:Royal Arms of the Kingdom of Scotland.svg|25px]] [[Robert the Bruce]]&lt;br/&gt;[[File:Armoiries de Pouilly 1.svg|20px]] [[Edward Bruce]] &lt;br&gt;[[Sir Robert Keith, Marischal of Scotland]]&lt;br&gt;[[File:Douglas Arms 1.svg|20px]] [[James Douglas, Lord of Douglas|James Douglas]] &lt;br&gt;[[File:Moray Coat of Arms.svg|20px]] [[Thomas Randolph, 1st Earl of Moray|Thomas Randolph, Earl of Moray]]
|commander2  = [[File:Royal Arms of England (1198-1340).svg|24px]] [[Edward II of England|Edward II]]&lt;br/&gt;[[File:Blason Humphrey de Bohun, Comte de Northampton (selon Gelre).svg|20px]] [[Humphrey de Bohun, 4th Earl of Hereford|Humphrey de Bohun]] &lt;br&gt; [[File:Blason Guillaume de Valence (William of Pembroke).svg|20px]] [[Aymer de Valence, 2nd Earl of Pembroke|Earl of Pembroke]]&lt;br&gt; [[File:CoA Gilbert de Clare.svg|20px]] [[Gilbert de Clare, 6th Earl of Hertford|Gilbert de Clare]]† &lt;br&gt; [[File:CliffordArms.png|20px]] [[Robert de Clifford, 1st Baron de Clifford|Robert de Clifford]]†
|strength1   = 5,000&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Battle of Bannockburn 1314 |last=Nusbacher |first=Aryeh |year=2000 |publisher=Tempus|location=Stroud |isbn=0-7524-1783-5 |page=85}}&lt;/ref&gt;–10,000&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=A History of the Art of War in the Middle Ages Vol. II|last=Oman |first=Charles |authorlink=Charles Oman|year=1991|origyear=1924 |publisher=Greenhill Books |location=London |isbn=1-85367-105-3|page=88}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|strength2   = 13,700&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Bannockburn |last=Armstrong |first=Pete|year=2002 |publisher=[[Osprey Publishing]] |location=Botley, Oxford|isbn=1-85532-609-4|page=43}}&lt;/ref&gt;–25,000&lt;ref&gt;Grant, R.G. (2008), ''Battle: A visual journey through 5,000 years of combat'', DK Publishing,p.118.&lt;/ref&gt;
|casualties1 = 400&lt;ref&gt;Sadler, John, ''Scottish Battles'', (Biddles Ltd., 1998), 52–54.&lt;/ref&gt;–4,000&lt;ref name=&quot;Grant, 118&quot;&gt;Grant, 118.&lt;/ref&gt;
|casualties2 = 700 cavalry&lt;ref name=&quot;referencing1&quot;/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;4,000&lt;ref&gt;Sadler, 52.&lt;/ref&gt;–11,000 infantry&lt;ref name=&quot;Reese1&quot;&gt;Reese, p.174&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
{{Campaignbox First War of Scottish Independence}}
{{Campaignbox Wars of Scottish Independence}}

The '''Battle of Bannockburn''' (''Blàr Allt nam Bànag'', often mistakenly called ''Blàr Allt a' Bhonnaich'' in [[Scottish Gaelic]]) (24 June 1314) was a significant [[Scotland|Scottish]] victory in the [[First War of Scottish Independence]], and a landmark in Scottish history.

[[Stirling Castle]], a Scots royal fortress, occupied by the English, was under siege by the Scottish army. The English king, [[Edward II of England|Edward II]], assembled a formidable force to relieve it.  This attempt failed, and his army was defeated in a [[pitched battle]] by a smaller army commanded by the King of Scots, [[Robert the Bruce]].

==Background==
The [[Wars of Scottish Independence]] between [[England]] and [[Scotland]] began in 1296 and initially the English were successful under the command of [[Edward I]], having won victories at the [[Battle of Dunbar (1296)]] and at the [[Capture of Berwick (1296)]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot;&gt;Black, Jeremy. (2005). ''The Seventy Great Battles of All Time''. pp. 71–73. Thames &amp; Hudson Ltd. ISBN 0-500-25125-8.&lt;/ref&gt; The removal of [[John Balliol]] from the Scottish throne also contributed to the English success.&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot;/&gt; The Scots had been victorious in defeating the English at the [[Battle of Stirling Bridge]] in 1297, however this was countered by Edward I's victory at the [[Battle of Falkirk (1298)]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot;/&gt; By 1304 Scotland had been conquered, but in 1306 [[Robert the Bruce]] seized the Scottish throne and the war was reopened.&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot;/&gt;

[[Edward II of England]] came to the throne in 1307 but was incapable of providing the determined leadership that had been shown by his father, Edward I, and the English position soon became more difficult.&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot;/&gt; [[Stirling Castle]] was one of the most important castles that was held by the English as it commanded the route north into the [[Scottish Highlands]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot;/&gt; It was besieged in 1314 by Robert the Bruce's brother, [[Edward Bruce]], and an agreement was made that if the castle was not relieved by mid-summer then it would be surrendered to the Scots.&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot;/&gt; The English could not ignore this challenge and military preparations were made for a substantial campaign in which the English army probably numbered 2,000 cavalry and 15,000 infantry, many of whom would have been [[longbow]]men.&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot;/&gt; The Scottish army probably numbered between 7,000 and 10,000 men, of whom no more than 500 would have been mounted.&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot;/&gt; Unlike the heavily armoured English cavalry, the Scottish cavalry would have been light horsemen who were good for skirmishing and reconnaissance but were not suitable for charging the enemy lines.&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot;/&gt; The Scottish infantry would have had axes, swords and pikes, with few bowmen among them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot;/&gt;

The precise size of the English force relative to the Scottish forces is unclear but estimates range from as much as at least two or three times the size of the army Bruce had been able to gather, to as little as only 50% larger.&lt;ref name=&quot;watson&quot;&gt;Watson, F., [http://www.bbc.co.uk/iplayer/episode/b00y2srx/In_Our_Time_The_Battle_of_Bannockburn/ &quot;In Our Time: The Battle of Bannockburn&quot;], BBC Radio, 3 February 2011&lt;/ref&gt;

==Prelude==
[[File:Battle from Holkham Bible.jpg|thumb|300px|An early 14th century English depiction of a Biblical battle giving an impression of how soldiers were equipped at Bannockburn. The image of a king wielding a battle axe in the top half has led some historians to link this image to Bannockburn.]]
Edward II and his advisors were aware of the places that the Scots were likely to challenge them and sent out orders for their troops to prepare for an enemy established in boggy ground near to the [[River Forth]], near [[Stirling]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot;/&gt; The English appear to have advanced in four divisions whereas the Scots were in three divisions, known as '[[Sheltron|schiltrons]]' which were strong defensive circles of men bristling with pikes.&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot;/&gt; [[Thomas Randolph, 1st Earl of Moray]], commanded the Scottish [[Vanguard (military tactics)|vanguard]], which was stationed about a mile to the south of Stirling, near the church of St. Ninian, while the king commanded the rearguard at the entrance to the New Park. His brother Edward led the third division. According to Barbour, there was a fourth division nominally under the youthful [[Walter Stewart, 6th High Steward of Scotland|Walter the Steward]], but actually under the command of [[James Douglas, Lord of Douglas|Sir James Douglas]].&lt;ref&gt;Nicholson, Later Middle Ages pp.87–89&lt;/ref&gt; The Scottish archers used yew-stave longbows and though these were not weaker or inferior to English longbows, there were fewer Scottish archers than English archers,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= The Great Warbow|last=Strickland |first= Matthew|author2=Hardy,Robert |year=2005 |publisher=Sutton|location=Stroud |isbn= 0-7509-3167-1|page=162}}&lt;/ref&gt; possibly numbering only 500. These archers played little part in the battle.&lt;ref&gt;The Chronicle of Lanercost says that on the second day of the battle, &quot;''the English archers were thrown forward before the line, and the Scottish archers engaged them, a few being killed and wounded on either side; but the King of England's archers quickly put the others to flight.''&quot; The Chronicle of Lanercost, 1272–1346: Translated, with notes by Sir Herbert Maxwell. p. 206&lt;/ref&gt; There is firsthand evidence in a poem by the captured Carmelite friar Robert Baston, written just after the battle, that one or both sides employed slingers and crossbowmen.&lt;ref&gt;Walter Bower, ''Scotichronicon,''Book XII, p. 371&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battle==

===Location of the battlefield===
There is some confusion over the exact site of the Battle of Bannockburn, although most modern historians agree that the traditional site, where a visitor centre and statue have been erected, is not the correct one.&lt;ref name=&quot;mackenzie&quot;&gt;Mackenzie, W. M. (1913). ''The Battle of Bannockburn: a Study in Mediaeval Warfare'', Publisher: James MacLehose; Glasgow.&lt;/ref&gt; Although a large number of possible alternatives have been proposed, most can be dismissed leaving two serious contenders:&lt;ref name=&quot;barrow&quot;&gt;Barrow, Geoffrey W.S. (1998). ''Robert Bruce &amp; The Community of The Realm of Scotland''. ISBN 0-85224-604-8&lt;/ref&gt;
* the area of peaty ground known as the Dryfield outside the village of [[Balquhiderock]], about three-quarters of a mile to the east of the traditional site,&lt;ref name=&quot;barron&quot;&gt;Barron, E.M., ''The Scottish War of Independence: a Critical Study'', 1934&lt;/ref&gt; and
* the Carse of Balquhiderock, about a mile and a half north-east of the traditional site, accepted by the [[National Trust for Scotland|National Trust]] as the most likely candidate.&lt;ref name=&quot;christison&quot;&gt;[[Philip Christison|Christison, Philip]], ''Bannockburn: The Story of the Battle'', 1960, Edinburgh: The National Trust for Scotland.&lt;/ref&gt;

===First day of battle===
[[File:Mapbannockburn1.svg|thumb|right|300px|An interpretation of the battle of Bannockburn-first day]]
Most medieval battles were short-lived, lasting only a few hours, therefore the Battle of Bannockburn is unusual in that it lasted for two days.&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot;/&gt; On 23 June 1314 two of the English cavalry formations advanced, the first commanded by the [[Gilbert de Clare, 8th Earl of Gloucester|Earl of Gloucester]] and the [[Earl of Hereford]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot;/&gt; They encountered a body of Scots, among them Robert the Bruce himself.&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot;/&gt; A celebrated single combat then took place between Bruce and [[Henry de Bohun]] who was the nephew of the Earl of Hereford.&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot;/&gt; Bohun charged at Bruce and when the two passed side by side, Bruce split Bohun's head with his axe.&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hyland, Ann. ''The Warhorse 1250–1600'', UK: Sutton Publishing, 1998, p 38&lt;/ref&gt; The Scots then rushed upon the English under Gloucester and Hereford who struggled back over the Bannockburn.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.britishbattles.com/scottish/battle-bannockburn.htm The Battle of Bannockburn] britishbattles.com. Retrieved 14 June 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

The second English cavalry force was commanded by [[Robert de Clifford, 1st Baron de Clifford|Robert Clifford]] and [[Henry de Beaumont]] and included Sir [[Thomas Grey (of Heaton)|Thomas de Grey of Heaton]], father of the chronicler [[Thomas Grey (chronicler)|Thomas Grey]] whose account of events follows;
&lt;section begin=Beaumont-vs-Grey /&gt;
&quot;''Robert Lord de Clifford and Henry de Beaumont, with three hundred men-at-arms, made a circuit upon the other side of the wood towards the castle, keeping the open ground. [[Thomas Randolph, 1st Earl of Moray]], Robert de Brus's nephew, who was leader of the Scottish advanced guard, hearing that his uncle had repulsed the advanced guard of the English on the other side of the wood, thought that he must have his share, and issuing from the wood with his division marched across the open ground towards the two afore-named lords.''

Sir Henry de Beaumont called to his men: &quot;Let us wait a little; let them come on; give them room&quot;&lt;br /&gt;
&quot;Sir,&quot; said Sir Thomas Gray, &quot;I doubt that whatever you give them now, they will have all too soon&quot;&lt;br /&gt;
&quot;Very well&quot; exclaimed the said Henry, if you are afraid, be off&quot;&lt;br/&gt;
&quot;Sir,&quot; answered the said Thomas, &quot;it is not from fear that I shall fly this day.&quot;

''So saying he spurred in between Beaumont and Sir William Deyncourt, and charged into the thick of the enemy. William was killed, Thomas was taken prisoner, his horse being killed on the pikes, and he himself carried off with the Scots on foot when they marched off, having utterly routed the squadron of the said two lords. Some of the English fled to the castle, others to the king's army, which having already left the road through the wood had debouched upon a plain near the water of Forth beyond Bannockburn, an evil, deep, wet marsh, where the said English army unharnessed and remained all night, having sadly lost confidence and being too much disaffected by the events of the day.''&quot;
&lt;section end=Beaumont-vs-Grey /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Maxwell&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Maxwell|1907}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Second day of battle===
[[File:Mapbannockburn1.2.svg|thumb|right|300px|An interpretation of the battle of Bannockburn-second day]]
Under nightfall the English forces crossed the stream that is known as the Bannock Burn, establishing their position on the plain beyond it.&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot;/&gt; A Scottish knight, [[Alexander Seton (Governor of Berwick)|Alexander Seton]], who was fighting in the service of Edward II of England, deserted the English camp and told Bruce of the low English morale, encouraging Bruce to attack them.&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot;/&gt; In the morning the Scots then advanced from New Park.&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot;/&gt; 

Not long after daybreak, the Scots spearmen began to move towards the English. Edward was surprised to see Robert's army emerge from the cover of the woods. As Bruce's army drew nearer, they paused and knelt in prayer. Edward is supposed to have said in surprise &quot;They pray for mercy!&quot; &quot;For mercy, yes,&quot; one of his attendants replied, &quot;But from God, not you. These men will conquer or die.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Scott158&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Scott|1982|p=158}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The English responded to the Scots advance with a charge of their own, led by the Earl of Gloucester. Gloucester had argued with the Earl of Hereford over who should lead the vanguard into battle, and argued with the king that the battle should be postponed. This led the king to accuse him of cowardice, which perhaps goaded Gloucester into the charge.&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot;/&gt; Few accompanied Gloucester in his charge and when he reached the Scottish lines he was quickly surrounded and killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot;/&gt; Gradually the English were pushed back and ground down by the Scots' [[schiltron]]s.&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot;/&gt; The English longbowmen attempted to support the advance of the knights but were ordered to stop shooting, as they were causing casualties among their own. An attempt to employ the English and Welsh longbowmen to shoot at the advancing Scots from their flank failed when they were dispersed by 500 Scottish cavalry under the Marischal [[Robert II Keith, Marischal of Scotland|Sir Robert Keith]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Scott&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Scott|1982}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although sometimes described as light cavalry, this appears to be a misinterpretation of Barbour's statement that these were men-at arms on lighter horses than their English counterparts.&lt;ref&gt;(Brown, C. (2008) pp 129-130)&lt;/ref&gt;
The English cavalry was hemmed in making it difficult for them to manoeuvre.&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot;/&gt; As a result, the English were unable to hold their formations and broke ranks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot;/&gt; It soon became clear to [[Aymer de Valence, 2nd Earl of Pembroke]] and [[Giles d'Argentan]] (reputedly the third best knight in Europe) that the English had lost and Edward II needed to be led to safety at all costs, so, seizing his horse's reins, dragged him away, and were closely followed by five hundred knights of the royal bodyguard.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scott159&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Scott|1982|p=159}}&lt;/ref&gt; Once they were clear of the battle d'Argentan turned to the king, said &quot;''Sire, your protection was committed to me, but since you are safely on your way, I will bid you farewell for never yet have I fled from a battle, nor will I now.''&quot; and turned his horse to charge back into the ranks of Scottish where he was overborn and slain.&lt;ref name=&quot;Scott160&quot;&gt;{{harvnb|Scott|1982|p=160}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===English retreat===
Edward fled with his personal bodyguard, ending the remaining order in the army; panic spread and defeat turned into a [[rout]]. He arrived eventually at [[Dunbar Castle]], from which he took ship to Berwick. From the carnage of Bannockburn, the rest of the army tried to escape to the safety of the English border, ninety miles to the south. Many were killed by the pursuing Scottish army or by the inhabitants of the countryside that they passed through. Historian Peter Reese says that, &quot;only one sizeable group of men—all foot soldiers—made good their escape to England.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Reese1&quot;/&gt; These were a force of Welsh spearmen who were kept together by their commander, [[Maurice de Berkeley, 2nd Baron Berkeley|Sir Maurice de Berkeley]], and the majority of them reached [[Carlisle, Cumbria|Carlisle]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Reese1&quot;/&gt; Weighing up the available evidence, Reese concludes that &quot;it seems doubtful if even a third of the footsoldiers returned to England.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Reese1&quot;/&gt; Out of 16,000 infantrymen, this would give a total of about 11,000 killed. The English chronicler [[Thomas Walsingham]] gave the number of English men-at-arms who were killed as 700,&lt;ref name=&quot;referencing1&quot;&gt;Mackenzie, p.88 referencing Walsingham, p.141&lt;/ref&gt; while 500 more men-at-arms were spared for ransom.&lt;ref&gt;Mackenzie, p.90&lt;/ref&gt; The Scottish losses appear to have been comparatively light, with only two knights among those killed.&lt;ref&gt;Reese, p.176&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==

The defeat of the English opened up the north of England to Scottish raids&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot;/&gt; and allowed the [[Bruce campaign in Ireland|Scottish invasion of Ireland]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Scott&quot;/&gt; These finally led, after the failure of the [[Declaration of Arbroath]] to reach this end by diplomatic means, to the [[Treaty of Edinburgh–Northampton]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Scott&quot;/&gt;  Under the treaty the English Crown recognised the full [[independence]] of the Kingdom of Scotland, and acknowledge Robert the Bruce, and his heirs and successors, as the rightful rulers.

It was not until 1332 that the [[Second War of Scottish Independence]] began with the [[Battle of Dupplin Moor]], followed by the [[Battle of Halidon Hill]] (1333) which were won by the English.&lt;ref name=&quot;Black&quot;/&gt;

==Notable casualties==

===Deaths===
* [[Gilbert de Clare, 8th Earl of Gloucester]]
* Sir [[Giles d'Argentan]]
* [[John Lovel, 2nd Baron Lovel]]
* [[John Comyn (c. 1294-1314)|John Comyn, Lord of Badenoch]]
* [[Robert de Clifford, 1st Baron de Clifford]]
* Sir [[Henry de Bohun]]
* [[William le Marshal]], Marshal of Ireland
* [[Edmund de Mauley]], [[Lord Steward|King's Steward]]
* [[Sir Robert de Felton]] of [[Litcham]], 1st Lord

===Captives===
* [[Humphrey de Bohun, 4th Earl of Hereford]]
* [[John Segrave, 2nd Baron Segrave]]
* [[Maurice de Berkeley, 2nd Baron Berkeley]]
* [[Thomas de Berkeley, 1st Baron Berkeley|Thomas de Berkeley]]
* Sir [[Marmaduke Tweng]]
* [[Ralph de Monthermer, 1st Baron Monthermer]]
* [[Robert de Umfraville, Earl of Angus]]
* Sir [[Anthony de Luci]]
* Sir [[Ingram de Umfraville]]
* Sir [[John Maltravers, 1st Baron Maltravers]]
* Sir [[Thomas Grey (of Heaton)|Thomas de Grey of Heaton]]

==Legacy==

===Bannockburn Visitor Centre===
[[File:MK18538 Bannockburn.jpg|thumb|The hemicircle of the modern Bannockburn monument]]

In 1932 the Bannockburn Preservation Committee, under [[Edward Bruce, 10th Earl of Elgin]] and Kincardine, presented lands to the [[National Trust for Scotland]]. Further lands were purchased in 1960 and 1965 to facilitate visitor access. A modern monument stands in a field above the battle site, where the warring parties are believed to have camped on the night before the battle. The monument consists of two hemicircular walls depicting the opposing parties. Nearby stands the 1960s statue of Bruce by [[Pilkington Jackson]]. The monument, and the associated visitor centre, is one of the most popular tourist attractions in the area. The battlefield has been included in the [[Inventory of Historic Battlefields in Scotland]] and protected by [[Historic Scotland]] under the Historic Environment (Amendment) Act 2011.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.historic-scotland.gov.uk/index/heritage/battlefields/battlefieldsunderconsideration.htm |title=Inventory battlefields|publisher=Historic Scotland |accessdate=2012-04-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;gallery mode=&quot;packed&quot; heights=&quot;190px&quot;&gt;
MK18535 Bannockburn.jpg|Alley to the monument
MK18541 Bannockburn Robert the Bruce.jpg|Statue of Robert the Bruce by [[Pilkington Jackson]]
MK18543 Bannockburn.jpg|View of the circular walls and the flag pole
MK18545 Bannockburn Robert the Bruce.jpg|Close Up of the statue
&lt;/gallery&gt;
The [[National Trust for Scotland]] operates the Bannockburn Visitor Centre (previously known as the Bannockburn Heritage Centre), which is open daily from March through October. On 31 October 2012 the building was closed&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-scotland-tayside-central-20141188 |publisher=BBC News |title=Bannockburn Heritage Centre closes before demolition |date=31 October 2012 |accessdate=31 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; for demolition and replacement by a new design, inspired by traditional Scottish buildings, by Reiach and Hall Architects. The project is a partnership between the National Trust for Scotland and [[Historic Scotland]], funded by the Scottish Government and the [[Heritage Lottery Fund]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.battleofbannockburn.com/About-the-project/|title=Battle of Bannockburn: Bannockburn : About the project|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The battlefield's new visitor centre - now rebranded as the Bannockburn Visitor Centre - opened in March 2014. One of the attractions created by a £9m redevelopment of the centre and the nearby battlefield memorial is a computerised multiplayer game.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://battleofbannockburn.com/updates/timeline/the-battle-of-bannockburn-visitor-centre-opens/|title=Battle of Bannockburn: : The Battle of Bannockburn Visitor Centre Opens|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Arts===
&quot;[[Scots Wha Hae]]&quot; is the title of a patriotic poem by [[Robert Burns]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gutenberg.org/files/18500/18500-h/18500-h.htm#CCVII The Complete Works of Robert Burns] at Project Gutenberg.&lt;/ref&gt; The chorus of Scotland's unofficial national anthem ''[[Flower of Scotland]]'' refers to Scotland's victory over Edward and the English at Bannockburn.

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Sources==

===Primary===
* Barbour, John, ''[[The Brus]]'', trans. A. A. M. Duncan, 1964.
* Bower, Walter, ''[[Scotichronicon]]'', ed. D. E. R. Watt, 1987–1993.
*{{Cite book |title = Scalacronica; The reigns of Edward I, Edward II and Edward III as Recorded by Sir Thomas Gray  |last = Maxwell
  |first = Herbert, trans.  |location = Glasgow  |publisher = James Maclehose &amp; Sons  |year = 1907  |url = https://archive.org/details/scalacronicareig01grayuoft  |accessdate = 17 October 2012  |ref = harv}}
* ''[[Lanercost Chronicle]]'', edited and translated by H. Maxwell, 1913.
* ''[[Vita Edwardi Secundi]]'' (Life of Edward the Second), ed. N. D. Young, 1957.
* Walsingham, Thomas, ''Historia Anglicana''.

===Secondary===
* Armstrong, Pete (illustrated by Graham Turner), ''Bannockburn 1314: Robert Bruce's Great Victory'', Osprey Publishing, 2002 ISBN 1-85532-609-4
* Barrow, G. W. S., ''Robert Bruce and the Community of the Realm of Scotland'', 1988,ISBN 0-85224-604-8
* Brown, C.A., &quot;Bannockburn 1314&quot;,History Press,Stroud, 2008, ISBN 978-0-7524-4600-4.
* Brown, C.A., ''Robert the Bruce. A life Chronicled''.
* {{cite book| title=Bannockburn. The Scottish War and the British Isles 1307-1323| author1-first=Michael
| author1-last=Brown| year=2008| publisher=Edinburgh University Press| location=Edinburgh| page=| ref=harv}}
* Brown, M., ''Wars of Scotland''
* {{Cite EB1911|wstitle=Bannockburn}}
* Mackenzie, W. M., ''Bannockburn: A Study in Medieval Warfare'', The Strong Oak Press, Stevenage 1989 (first published 1913), ISBN 1-871048-03-6
* MacNamee, C., ''The Wars of the Bruces''
* Nicholson, R., ''Scotland-the Later Middle Ages'', 1974.
* Prestwich, M., ''The Three Edwards: War and State in England, 1272–1377'', 1980
* Ramsay, J. H., ''The Genesis of Lancaster'', 1307–99, 1913.
* Reese, P., ''Bannockburn'', Canongate, Edinburgh, 2003, ISBN 1-84195-465-9
* {{cite book| title=Robert the Bruce King of Scots| author1-first=Ronald McNair| author1-last=Scott| year=1982| publisher=Hutchinson &amp; Co
| location=London| page=| ref=harv}}

==External links==
*[http://www.battleofbannockburn.com The Battle of Bannockburn 700th Anniversary Project]
*[http://www.medievalarchives.com/battleofbannockburn Battle of Bannockburn] on [http://www.medievalarchives.com/PodcastList Medieval Archives Podcast]
*[http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b00y2srx BBC &quot;In our time&quot; discussion on the battle and it's consequences]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Battle Of Bannockburn}}
[[Category:1314 in Scotland]]
[[Category:Battles between England and Scotland]]
[[Category:Battles of the Wars of Scottish Independence|Bannockburn, Battle of]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1314]]
[[Category:History museums in Scotland]]
[[Category:Inventory of Historic Battlefields in Scotland|Bannockburn]]
[[Category:Military and war museums in Scotland]]
[[Category:Museums in Stirling (council area)]]
[[Category:National Trust for Scotland properties]]</text>
      <sha1>kurjydydhbpofve0wsyte0ewfnqr8am</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
