<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of the Neva</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>953371</id>
    <revision>
      <id>737637233</id>
      <parentid>726657747</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-04T03:53:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GreenC bot</username>
        <id>27823944</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[User:Green Cardamom/WaybackMedic 2|WaybackMedic 2]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12368">{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Battle of the Neva
|partof=[[Swedish-Novgorodian Wars]]
|image=[[Image:Chorikov.jpg|center|275px]]
|caption=''Alexander Nevsky Fighting the Swedes'', by [[Boris Chorikov]]
|date=July 15, 1240
|place=[[Neva River]], [[Russia]]
|result=Novgorodian victory
|combatant1=[[Novgorod Republic]]&lt;br/&gt;'''Supported by:'''&lt;br/&gt; [[Karelians|People of Ladoga]] 
|combatant2=[[Kingdom of Sweden]] &lt;br/&gt;'''Supported by:'''&lt;br/&gt; [[Finns]] &lt;br/&gt; [[Tavastia (historical province)|Tavastia]]ns  &lt;br/&gt; [[Norwegians]]
|commander1=[[Alexander Nevsky]]
|commander2=[[Bishop Thomas]]
}}
The '''Battle of the Neva''' ({{lang-ru|Невская битва}}, ''Nevskaya bitva'', {{lang-sv|slaget vid Neva}}, [[Finnish language|Finnish]]: ''Nevan taistelu'') was fought between the [[Novgorod Republic]] and [[Karelia|Karelians]] against [[Sweden|Swedish]], [[Norwegians|Norwegian]], [[Southwest Finland|Finnish]] and [[Tavastians|Tavastian]] armies on the [[Neva River]], near the settlement of [[Ust-Izhora]], on July 15, 1240. The battle is only mentioned in Russian sources, which raises doubts about its significance or even existence.

The purpose of the [[invasion]] was probably to gain control over the mouth of the Neva and the city of [[Staraya Ladoga|Ladoga]] and, hence, seize the most important part of the [[trade route from the Varangians to the Greeks]], which had been under [[Novgorod]]'s control for more than a hundred years. The battle was part of the medieval [[Swedish-Novgorodian Wars]] and continuum to [[Finnish–Novgorodian wars|Finnish-Novgorodian wars]].

== Russian sources ==

The existence of the battle is only known from Russian sources. The first source to mention the battle is the [[Novgorod First Chronicle]] from the 14th century.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://193.184.161.234/DF/detail.php?id=83|title=Description of the battle in the First Novgorod Chronicle|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070927051426/http://193.184.161.234/DF/detail.php?id=83|archivedate=2007-09-27}}; in Swedish. Hosted by the [http://www.narc.fi narc.fi]. See [http://www.narc.fi/Arkistolaitos/sahkoiset/ Arkistolaitos/sahkoiset] and ''Diplomatarium Fennicum'' from the menu. See also [http://www.portalus.ru/modules/rushistory/print.php?subaction=showfull&amp;id=1161587409&amp;archive=&amp;start_from=&amp;ucat=14&amp; original text]; in Russian.&lt;/ref&gt; According to the chronicle, on receiving the news of the advancing Swedish, Norwegian, Finnish and Tavastian fleets, the 20-year-old [[Prince]] [[Alexander Yaroslavich]] of Novgorod quickly moved his small army and local men to face the enemy before they had reached [[Lake Ladoga]]. The chronicle described the battle as follows:

[[File:AlexanderNevski.jpg|left|thumb|Battle of the Neva contributed to Alexander's later sainthood.]]
&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;Swedes came with a great army, and [[Norwegians]] and [[Southwest Finland|Finns]] and [[Tavastia (historical province)|Tavastians]] with ships in great numbers, Swedes with their prince and bishops, and they stayed on the [[Neva River|Neva]], at the mouth of the [[Izhora River|Izhora]], willing to take [[Staraya Ladoga|Ladoga]], and to put it short, Novgorod and all of its lands. But still protected the merciful, man-loving God us and sheltered us from the foreign people, and the word came to Novgorod that Swedes were sailing to Ladoga; but prince Alexander did not hesitate at all, but went against them with Novgorodians and people of Ladoga and overcame them with the help of Saint Sophia and through prayers of our lady, the [[Mother of God]] and [[Virgin Mary]], July 15, in the memory of [[Quiricus and Julietta|Kirik and Ulita]], on Sunday, (the same day that) the 630 holy fathers&lt;ref&gt;Actually the meeting was held between October 8 and November 1, not on July 15.&lt;/ref&gt; held a meeting in [[Chalcedon]]; and there was a great gathering of the Swedes; and their leader called [[Spiridon of Neva|Spiridon]]&lt;ref&gt;In the later version of the battle, &quot;Spiridon&quot; also appears as the name of the [[Archbishop of Novgorod]], who blessed Alexander before the battle.&lt;/ref&gt; was killed there; but some claimed that even the bishop was slain;&lt;ref&gt;No Scandinavian bishop is known to have died in 1240.&lt;/ref&gt; and a great number of them fell; and when they had loaded two ships with the bodies of high-born men, they let them sail to the sea; but the others, that were unnumbered, they cast to a pit, that they buried, and many others were wounded; and that same night they fled, without waiting for the Monday light, with shame. Of Novgorodians there fell: Konstantin Lugotinitch, Yuryata Pinyashchinich, Namest Drochilo, Nesdylov son of Kozhevnik,&lt;!--Костянтин Луготиничь, Юрята Пинящиничь, Намест Дрочило, Нездилов сын Кожевничь--&gt; but including the people of Ladoga 20 men or less, God knows. But prince Alexander came back home with Novgorodians and people of Ladoga, all well, protected by God and [[Holy Wisdom|Saint Sophia]] and all the prayers of the holy men.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

A 16th-century version of the battle gave plenty of additional details, expanding the conflict to biblical proportions, but otherwise following the earlier described developments.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.goldschp.net/SIG/nevskii/nev2.html &quot;Battle on the Neva&quot;] 16th century version of the battle, provided by the Slavic Interest Group of the [[Society for Creative Anachronism]]. In English.&lt;/ref&gt;

Prince Alexander Yaroslavich was [[nickname]]d &quot;Nevsky&quot; (of Neva) for his first significant victory. Two years later, Alexander stalled an invasion of the [[Livonian Knights]] during the [[Battle on Lake Peipus|Battle on the Ice]]. Despite the victories, there were no Novgorodian advances further west to [[Finland]] or [[Estonia]].

== Swedish sources ==

There is no reference to a battle of the Neva in Swedish sources.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://arzamas.academy/materials/785|title=Мифы о главных русских победах|last=Lourie|first=Lev|publisher=Arzamas Academy|language=Russian|accessdate=21 April 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Situation in Sweden ===
{{original research|section|date=May 2016}}
Since the death of King [[John I of Sweden|John]] in 1222, Sweden was in a ''de facto'' state of civil war until 1248 when [[Birger Jarl]] managed to seize power in the kingdom. Unrest was due to the struggle between those who wanted to keep the old tribal structure,&lt;ref name=&quot;Larsson1&quot;&gt;Larsson 2002, p. 178.&lt;/ref&gt; the [[folkung]] party, and the king, who was assisted by the church. Folkungs, who were mainly from [[Uppland]], heavily resisted the centralization of power,&lt;ref name=&quot;harv&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Kari|2004|p=117}}.&lt;/ref&gt; taxation of the [[Suiones|Swedes of Uppland]],&lt;ref name=&quot;Larsson1&quot;/&gt; and church privileges.&lt;ref name=&quot;harv&quot;/&gt; They had temporarily succeeded in deposing the king in 1229, but were forced to give in five years later, but were far from defeated yet. Uppland remained largely independent of the king, and its northern areas continued to be in folkung hands. An uneasy truce continued until 1247, when the folkung rebellion was put to an end at the [[Battle of Sparrsätra]] and its leader beheaded a year later.

Furthermore, the official Sweden was on the brink of war with [[Norway]] ever since the Norwegians' infamous [[Värmland]] expedition in 1225.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.smb.nu/index.php/svenskakrig/krig-1222-1388/vaermlandstaget-1225/88-krig-1222-1388/171-vaermlandstaget-1225 Värmland expedition by the Svenskt Militärhistoriskt Bibliotek].&lt;/ref&gt; Relations improved only after the [[Treaty of Lödöse]] in 1249, which was forged by the newly empowered Birger Jarl.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.smb.nu/svenskakrig/freder/1249.asp Treaty of Lödöse].&lt;/ref&gt; Before the treaty, Norway remained an ally of the folkungs, giving them refuge and providing men and arms.

In this situation, it seems unlikely that Sweden could have been able to organize a major expedition against Novgorod.  Swedes are not known to have carried out any other military campaigns between 1222 and 1249, making the claims about their forceful appearance at the Neva with Norwegians as their allies seem questionable.

=== Theories ===
Taking these facts into consideration, it has been suggested in a recent book aimed at a wide readership,&lt;ref&gt;Kari, Risto. ''Suomalaisten keskiaika''. WS Bookwell Oy. Porvoo 2004. ISBN 951-0-28321-5. See page 107.&lt;/ref&gt; that the Swedish expedition may have been an indirect result of the papal letter in 1237 that was sent to the Swedish [[Archbishop of Uppsala]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://193.184.161.234/DF/detail.php?id=82|title=Letter by Pope Gregory IX about an uprising against the church in Tavastia|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070927051432/http://193.184.161.234/DF/detail.php?id=82|archivedate=2007-09-27}}. In Latin. Hosted by the [http://www.narc.fi National Archive of Finland]. See [http://www.narc.fi/Arkistolaitos/sahkoiset/] and ''Diplomatarium Fennicum'' from the menu.&lt;/ref&gt; The letter eloquently called for a crusade, not against Novgorod, but against [[Tavastians]] in [[Finland]], who had allegedly started hostilities against the church. In his defunct position, the king may not have been willing or able to act, but the letter may have provided the frustrated folkungs an opportunity to regain part of their [[Viking Age]] glory. Mostly free to act without interference from the king, folkungs would have been able to [[leidang|raise an army of their own]], get volunteers from Norway and even assistance from [[Bishop Thomas|Thomas]], the independent [[Bishop of Finland]], who needed to constantly worry about [[Finnish-Novgorodian wars|attacks from the east]]. Instead of Tavastia, this mixed set of interests and nationalities would have headed for the more lucrative Neva and there met its fate at the hands of Alexander.{{Citation needed|date=October 2009}} In the possible aftermath of the said battle, the King of Norway approached his Swedish counterpart for peace talks in 1241, but was turned down at the time.

However, some recent research has fundamentally questioned the importance of the battle, seeing it as an ordinary border skirmish that was exaggerated for political purposes, thus also explaining its absence from Swedish and other western sources.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.uta.fi/laitokset/historia/sivut/ylhitutsem2001/Maki-PetaysMari.pdf Alexander Nevskij and the Holy War]. Based on presentations in the Leeds International Medieval Conference. Hosted by the Tampere University.&lt;/ref&gt;

Additional theories are numerous. Some historians have suggested that the Swedish army was already under the command of the very young Birger Jarl, eight years before his appointment to the position of [[Jarl in Sweden|jarl]].&lt;ref&gt;Even if Spiridon was said to have died in the battle, some historians still associate him with Birger. See e.g. Riasanovsky, Nicholas V.: A History of Russia. Oxford 1993.&lt;/ref&gt; It has also been suggested that the suspicious information on Norwegians', Finns' and Tavastians' participation was made up in the 14th century, the time of writing of the First Novgorod Chronicle, when Sweden was in control of Norway, Finland and Tavastia.{{Cn|date=May 2016}}

=== Consequences ===

All in all, the first known Swedish military expedition against Novgorod after the events at the Neva took place in 1256, following folkungs' demise, peace with Norway and conquest of Finland. If the battle of the Neva had any long-term consequences, it was in Sweden's determination to take over Finland first before attempting to proceed further east.{{citation needed|date = July 2013}}

==See also==
* [[Battle of Lihula]]
* [[Bishop Thomas]]
* [[Second Swedish Crusade]]

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Bibliography==
*{{Citation|surname=Kari|given=Risto|authorlink=|year=2004|title=Suomalaisten keskiaika|place=|publisher=WSOY|url=|isbn=951-0-28321-5}}
*Larsson, Mats G (2002). ''Götarnas Riken : Upptäcktsfärder Till Sveriges Enande''. Bokförlaget Atlantis AB ISBN 978-91-7486-641-4
*{{Efron}}

{{Coord|59|48|27|N|30|36|15|E|display=title|type:event_source:dewiki}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Neva, Battle of the}}
[[Category:1240 in Europe]]
[[Category:Battles involving the Novgorod Republic|Neva 1240]]
[[Category:Battles involving Sweden|Neva 1240]]
[[Category:Battles of the Middle Ages]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1240]]</text>
      <sha1>bfp1wagnuuzwd2jj9xxn37ddkjnxlcs</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
