<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Battle of Réunion</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>20401731</id>
    <revision>
      <id>716734004</id>
      <parentid>711905204</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-04-23T14:22:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Fayenatic london</username>
        <id>1639942</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>[[Help:Cat-a-lot|Cat-a-lot]]: Moving from [[Category:Mediterranean, Middle East and African theatres of World War II]] to [[Category:African theatres of World War II]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12483">{{Refimprove|date=October 2014}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Battle of Réunion
|partof=the [[Indian Ocean in World War II|Indian Ocean theatre]] of [[World War II]]
|image=[[Image:Re-map.png|250px|Map of Réunion]]
|caption=Map of La Réunion. The invasion forces landed at [[Saint-Denis, Réunion|Saint-Denis]]; action also took place at [[Le Port, Réunion|Le Port]] and [[Pointe des Galets]].
|date=28 November 1942
|place=[[Saint-Denis, Réunion|Saint Denis]], [[Réunion]]
|result= Free French victory
|combatant1={{flag|Free France}}
|combatant2={{flag|Vichy France}} 
|commander1={{flagicon|Free French Forces}} Jules Evenou&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Free French Forces}} André Capagorry
|commander2={{flagicon|Vichy France}} Pierre Aubert&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Vichy France}} [[Émile Hugot]] {{WIA}}
|strength1= Destroyer [[French destroyer Léopard|''Léopard'']]&lt;br&gt;
One company of ''[[Fusiliers Marins]]'' &lt;br&gt;[[French Resistance|Local resistance]]
|strength2= 260 men
|casualties1= 1+ killed
|casualties2= 2+ killed&lt;br&gt;1+ wounded
|campaignbox=
{{Campaignbox Indian Ocean Theatre}}
{{Campaignbox Vichy France Military in World War II}}
}}
The '''Battle of Réunion''' or '''Liberation of Réunion''' ({{lang-fr|Bataille de La Réunion ''or'' Libération de La Réunion}}) was an amphibious landing and uprising which brought the island of [[Réunion]] onto the [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] side during the [[World War II|Second World War]]. The invasion was performed by the [[Free French Naval Forces]] (FNFL) destroyer [[French destroyer Léopard|''Léopard'']] on 28 November 1942, which toppled the administration loyal to the [[Vichy France|Vichy French regime]] and replaced it with a [[Free France|Free French]] administration.

== Background ==

=== Vichy and Réunion ===
Since the [[Battle of France]] in May–June 1940, the island of La Réunion had had little strategic importance, and little defences as a consequence. The [[Armistice with France (Second Compiègne)|Compiègne Armistice]] had reduced the military on the island to three officers, one doctor, eleven non-commissioned officers and about 270 men, of which only 23 were professionals. The coastal artillery were out of order.

On 23 June 1940, Raoul Nativel, president of the ''[[General councils (France)|conseil général]]'', denounced the Armistice on Radio Saint-Denis. The next day,  British consul Maurice Gaud met with the governor of the island, Pierre Aubert, proposing to pay the French administration on British treasure if La Réunion would fight on. The proposal became public when Radio [[British Mauritius|Mauritius]] broadcast it. Aubert consulted with local notabilities, but faced with the choice of illegally surrendering the island to a foreign government, he decided to stay loyal to Marshal [[Philippe Pétain]]'s [[Vichy France|Vichy France government]]. Supporters of the French exile government of [[Charles De Gaulle]], General secretary Angelini and captain Plat were transferred, and the president of the colonial commission Adrien Lagourgue was discharged, as well as Nativel.

Governor Aubert, although loyal to the Vichy Regime, was relatively moderate in his support of Pétain's policies. He had however the supreme authority on the island. On the other hand, his cabinet director, Jean-Jacques Pillet, was enthusiastic in his support of the Vichy ''[[Révolution nationale]]'', organising censorship, propaganda, a special criminal court, and a pro-Vichy militia.

A local resistance movement soon emerged. On 11 November 1941, for [[Remembrance Day]], about 20 women put flowers on the 1918 memorial at Saint-Denis; they were consequently fined. Communist cells operated under Léon de Lepervanche, though kept a low profile. La Réunion also harboured [[Duy Tân]], exiled [[Nguyễn Dynasty|Emperor of Vietnam]], who was a keen [[radio amateur]] and managed to communicate with Mauritius; he was shortly detained and had his equipment confiscated.

=== Strategic situation ===
After the [[Battle of Singapore]], in February 1942, the British [[Eastern Fleet]] retreated to [[Addu Atoll]] in [[Maldives]]. Then, following [[Chuichi Nagumo]]'s [[Indian Ocean raid]] in early 1942, the Fleet moved its operational base to [[Kilindini]] near [[Mombasa]] in [[Kenya]], increasing the British presence on the Eastern African coasts. Soon afterwards, the British struck the French possessions of Madagascar, under Vichy Regime control, with [[Battle of Madagascar|Operation ''Ironclad'']], on 5 May 1942. La Réunion lost her shipping communications with mainland Africa, and the attack further encouraged anti-British sentiments among the Vichy loyalists. On the other hand, De Gaulle, who had not been involved in ''Ironclad'', felt hard-pressed to re-claim La Réunion from Vichy before the British or Americans would.

On 8 May, Vichy elements in Madagascar signaled that a British cruiser had left South Africa with 600 men aboard to seize the island. Aubert then decided to obstruct the harbour of [[Le Port, Réunion|Le Port]] by scuttling a ship in the entrance. He also ordered evacuation of the capital of Saint-Denis, so as to avoid a bloody bombing like that at [[Antsiranana|Diego Soares]]; in the evening, about 9,000 people had moved to La Montagne, Le Brûlé, Saint-François, and Sainte Marie. No bombing materialised, however, and the population gradually returned to its homes.

The incident had highlighted the fact that the island was helpless against any invasion; on 18 September, it was decided that resistance to a landing would be limited to a mere token fight. Some elements of the military were however determined to fiercely resist a British invasion. On 27 September, Saint-Denis was declared [[open city]], while authorities moved to [[Hell-Bourg]], mocked by De Gaulle's supporters.

On 8 November, [[Operation Torch|Operation ''Torch'']] triggered [[Case Anton]], the German invasion of the so-called &quot;Free Zone&quot;, resulting in the [[scuttling of the French fleet in Toulon]]. [[François Darlan]] emerged as a rival to De Gaulle, negotiating with [[Mark W. Clark|General Mark Clark]].

== Invasion ==
[[Image:Chacal-1.jpg|thumb|A ''Chacal'' class destroyer similar to [[French destroyer Léopard|''Léopard'']]]]
On the night of 26 to 27 November 1942, the [[FNFL]] large destroyer ''Léopard'' sailed with 74 troops from [[Mauritius]], arriving off [[Saint-Denis, Réunion|Saint-Denis]] on 27 at 23:00. She was captained by commander [[Jules Evenou]], who went by the [[nom de guerre]] of &quot;Jacques Richard&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;ordredelaliberation&quot;&gt;[http://www.ordredelaliberation.fr/fr_compagnon/326.html Jules Evenou]&lt;/ref&gt;

Two launches were sent with a 5-man party to search for a favourable landing spot. At 2:30, ''Léopard'' was sighted by lookouts, as the invasion troops were boarding boats. About 60 men landed and, led by Lieutenant Moreau, took control of the government palace, and the rest of Saint-Denis was under Free France control by the evening. Barraquin, chief of the invasion troops, made contact with friendly elements in the population, notably Communist leader [[Léon de Lépervanche]], and General secretary Rivière, who started arranging the hand-over of the island. Hard-core Vichyist Pillet then fled to Hell-Bourg to organise a resistance. The new governor designated by De Gaulle, [[André Capagorry]], arrived around 6 o'clock, cheered by the population, and gave a speech calling for calm on Radio Saint-Denis.

[[File:General De Gaulle inspecting sailors on the Free French ship LEOPARD at Greenock, 24 June 1942. A10354.jpg|left|thumb|[[Charles de Gaulle]] inspecting sailors on the ''Léopard'' in June 1942]]
The next day, on 28 November, Communist cells under Lépervanche activated, seizing the city hall, arresting the mayor and electing Lépervanche as leader of a &quot;Committee of Public Safety&quot;; they next failed in an attempt to capture the 95-mm coastal battery of Le Port, commanded by lieutenant [[Émile Hugot]], considered a hard-core Pétainist. In retaliation, the battery opened fire on ''Léopard'', which retreated to the open sea and started firing back, killing two. Engineer Raymond Decugis attempted to have the battery cease fire, but was killed by small arms fire.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ordredelaliberation.fr/fr_compagnon/257.html Raymond Decugis]&lt;/ref&gt; A sortie by the Vichyists was thwarted by small arms fire from the Resistants, severely wounding Hugot. Fearing an assault of their positions by regular troops, the gunners retreated, silencing the battery, and ''Léopard'' approached Le Port.

Upon learning that the invasion force was French rather than British, and without any response from his government in spite of repeated requests for instructions, Aubert renounced the idea of even a symbolic fight. However, Captain Evenou, growing increasingly nervous at the thought of enemy submarines and fearing for his ship, clumsily attempted to force the issue by threatening to destroy factories on the island. After lengthy negotiations involving Capagorry, Aubert eventually agreed to surrender on the condition that the ultimatum on the factories be made again as a way for him to save face. The surrender was formalised on 30 at 8:45.

Capagorry broadcast the statements:
{{cquote|Governor André Capagorry, governor of La Réunion, is pleased to inform the population that Governor Pierre Aubert has renounced pursuing a hopeless and fratricidal fight. Consequently, hostilities have ceased on the territory of the colony, and blood shall not be spilled any longer. Governor Pierre Aubert has done his duty with courage and correction, and shall be given military honours. Now that the interest of France has prevailed, the whole population is encouraged to forget local quarrels and unite around the government of Fighting France to work at the liberation of the fatherland.}}

== Aftermath ==
[[File:2 francs croix de Lorraine de la Réunion, 1943.jpg|thumb|Banknote issued by Free French Réunion in 1943]]
On 2 December, Pillet and captain Artignan were discreetly brought aboard ''Léopard'' as to avoid any popular retaliation. Aubert boarded the next day after lunch with Capagorry, Evenou and Barraquin, and the destroyer departed for Mauritius.

''Léopard'' made several trips between Mauritius and La Réunion to provide rice, which had been lacking, contributing greatly to Capagorry's popularity. He gained the nickname ''papa de riz'' or the &quot;rice daddy&quot;.

From 20 April 1943, a special court cancelled all sanctions and discharges imposed under the Vichy Regime. Officials of the Vichy administration suffered at most light penalties, except for Jean-Jacques Pillet, who was discharged. In recognition of his role in the battle, Raymond Decugis was later declared a ''Chevalier'' of the [[Legion of Honour]] and a [[Order of Liberation|Companion of the Liberation]].

== See also ==
{{portal|World War II|France}}
* [[Battle of Madagascar]]
* [[French Somaliland in World War II]]
* [[History of Réunion]]

== Sources and references ==
{{reflist}}

== Further reading ==
*{{cite journal|last=Fageol|first=Pierre-Éric|title=La Révolution Nationale et L'Exaltation Impériale à La Réunion Durant la Période de Vichy (1940-1942)|journal=Guerres mondiales et conflits contemporains|date=April 2012|volume=246|series=Les territoires de l'Océan Indien dans la Deuxième Guerre mondiale|pages=41–62|jstor=23324971}}
*{{cite journal|last=Combeau|first=Yvan|title=La Réunion: Une Colonie Gaulliste en Reconstruction (1942-1945)|journal=Guerres mondiales et conflits contemporains|date=April 2012|volume=246|series=Les territoires de l'Océan Indien dans la Deuxième Guerre mondiale|pages=63–78|jstor=23324972}}

== External links ==
{{commons category|Réunion in World War II}}
* [http://www.clicanoo.com/article.php3?id_article=97623 Le jour du ''Léopard'']
* [http://www.clicanoo.com/index.php?page=article&amp;id_article=97621 La Réunion et le régime de Vichy (2e partie)]
* [http://www.reunion.pref.gouv.fr/etat/presse/capagorry.php CAPAGORRY ET LE RALLIEMENT DE LA RÉUNION À LA FRANCE LIBRE]

{{coord missing|France}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Reunion, Liberation of}}
[[Category:Naval battles involving France]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1942]]
[[Category:Military battles of Vichy France]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving France]]
[[Category:African theatres of World War II]]
[[Category:History of Réunion|Battle]]
[[Category:1942 in Réunion]]</text>
      <sha1>hg4bed8mk7mdhgfrkognuvvfm1tebm0</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
