<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Big Horn Expedition</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>43587591</id>
    <revision>
      <id>746502150</id>
      <parentid>733279219</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-27T20:09:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mitchumch</username>
        <id>722802</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Modified infobox</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="26865">{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict    =Big Horn Expedition
|partof      =the [[Great Sioux War of 1876]]
|image       =
|caption     =
|date        =March 1–26, 1876
|place       =[[Wyoming Territory]], [[Montana Territory]]
|coordinates =
|map_type    =
|map_relief  =
|latitude    =
|longitude   =
|map_size    =
|map_marksize =
|map_caption =
|map_label   =
|territory   =
|result      =Inconclusive
|status      =
|combatants_header =
|combatant1  =[[Cheyenne]]&lt;br&gt;[[Oglala Lakota|Oglala Lakota Sioux]]
|combatant2  ={{flag|United States|1867}}
|commander1  =Old Bear&lt;br&gt;[[He Dog]]
|commander2  =[[George Crook|George R. Crook]]&lt;br&gt;[[Joseph J. Reynolds]]
|strength1   =~250
|strength2   =883
|casualties1 =4–6 killed, including women and children&lt;br&gt;1–3 wounded
|casualties2 =4 killed&lt;br&gt;8 wounded&lt;br&gt;67 injured&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=tJsdAQAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA29&amp;dq=Killed+March+17,+1876+Powder+River,+Montana&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=9M2cTMuRONOlngeJy_W8DQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=4&amp;ved=0CDgQ6AEwAzge#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false 1876 Annual Report of the Secretary of War .p.29]&lt;/ref&gt;
|notes       =
|campaignbox ={{Campaignbox Big Horn Expedition}}&lt;br&gt;{{Campaignbox 1876 North Plains Campaign}}
}}
:''This event should not be confused with the [[Powder River Expedition (1865)]].''
The '''Big Horn Expedition''', or '''Bighorn Expedition''', was a military operation of the [[United States Army]] against the [[Sioux]], and [[Cheyenne]] [[American Indians in the United States|Indians]] in [[Wyoming Territory]] and [[Montana Territory]]. Although soldiers destroyed one Cheyenne and Oglala Sioux village, the expedition solidified [[Lakota people|Lakota]] Sioux and northern Cheyenne resistance against the United States attempt to force them to sell the [[Black Hills]] and live on a reservation, beginning the [[Great Sioux War of 1876]].&lt;ref&gt;Greene, Jerome A. ''Lakota and Cheyenne: Indian Views of the Great Sioux War, 1876-1877'' Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1994, p. xvi&lt;/ref&gt;

== Background ==
The [[Treaty of Fort Laramie (1868)]] granted the [[Lakota Sioux]] and their northern Cheyenne allies a reservation, including the [[Black Hills]], in [[Dakota Territory]] and a large area of &quot;unceded territory&quot; in what became [[Montana]] and [[Wyoming]]. Both areas were for the exclusive use of the Indians, and whites except for government officials, were forbidden to trespass.  In August, 1874, soldiers of the Black Hills Expedition under [[Lieutenant Colonel]] [[George A. Custer]] confirmed the discovery of gold in the Black Hills. This caused the United States to attempt to buy the Hills from the Sioux.  The U.S. ordered all bands of Lakota and Cheyenne to come to the Indian agencies on the reservation by January 31, 1876 to negotiate the sale. Some of the bands did not comply and when the deadline of January 31 passed, the [[Commissioner of Indian Affairs]], [[John Q. Smith]], wrote that &quot;without the receipt of any news of [[Sitting Bull]]'s submission, I see no reason why...military operations against him should not commence at once.&quot; On February 8, 1876, General [[Phillip Sheridan]] telegraphed Generals [[George Crook|George R. Crook]] and [[Alfred Howe Terry|Alfred H. Terry]], ordering them to undertake winter campaigns against the &quot;hostiles&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Commissioner of Indian Affairs to Secretary of the Interior, January 31st, 1876; Secretary of the Interior to the Secretary of War, February 1st, 1876; Colonel Drum to Gen. Terry and Gen. Crook, February 8th, 1876, National Archives.&lt;/ref&gt;

== March 1-3 ==
In bitterly cold weather, [[Brigadier General]] [[George Crook]], commander of the [[Department of the Platte]], marched north from [[Fort Fetterman]] near [[Douglas, Wyoming]] on March 1, 1876. General Crook's objective was to strike against the Indians while they were at their most vulnerable in their winter camps. [[Sitting Bull]], [[Crazy Horse]], and their followers were thought to be on the [[Powder River (Montana)|Powder]], [[Tongue River (Montana)|Tongue]], or Rosebud rivers. Crook's force consisted of 883 men, including ten companies of United States [[cavalry]], and two companies of [[infantry]], along with civilian packers, scouts, guides, and a newspaper reporter, [[Robert Edmund Strahorn]] of [[Denver, Colorado|Denver]]'s [[Rocky Mountain News]].&lt;ref&gt;Collins, Jr., Charles D. ''Atlas of the Sioux Wars'', Second edition, Fort Leavenworth, Kansas: Combat Studies Institute Press, 2006, Map 14, 15&lt;/ref&gt;  Crook's highly valued chief scout was [[Frank Grouard]], who had lived among the Lakota and spoke their language.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Vestal|first=Stanley|title=New Sources of Indian History 1850-1891|publisher=Read Books |year=2008|page=339|isbn=1-4437-2631-1|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=flT9DcDFY-sC&amp;pg=PA339&amp;lpg=PA339&amp;dq=Frank+Grouard&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=ja7dY4l-rl&amp;sig=WtgJNovKGqWIAcsQ0xMnwHR29J4&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=dMTwSfoTy7aMB9q1qLgM&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=10|accessdate=2009-04-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Cattle herd skirmish ==
In the early morning hours of March 3, 1876 north of Fort Fetterman, Indian warriors attacked the Big Horn Expedition's [[Cattle]] herd, numbering over 200 animals. The two herders fired at the warriors, and the Indians fired back. One of the government civilian employees, cattle herder John Wright was severely wounded by a bullet. The warriors then drove off and captured most of the cattle. The Cattle herd skirmish is significant for being the first engagement of the [[Great Sioux War of 1876]], making John Wright the conflict's first casualty. Wright died of wounds received in the fight on April 9, 1876.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Vaughn|first1=J. W.|title=The Reynolds Campaign On Powder River|date=1961|publisher=University of Oklahoma Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== March 4-5 ==
The soldiers had to heat their forks in the coals of fires to prevent the tines from freezing to their tongues. A [[blizzard]] on March 5 deposited over a foot of snow and significantly delayed Crook's progress. Temperatures fell so low that the [[thermometers]] could not record the cold. Crook's column slowly followed the [[Bozeman Trail]] north to [[Fort Reno (Wyoming)|Old Fort Reno]], reaching it on March 5. The fort had been abandoned by the army eight years earlier. The expedition establish its supply base near the abandoned post and Crook ordered that the wagons be left at the depot. The Infantry accompanying the column, Companies C and I of the [[4th Infantry Regiment (United States)|4th U.S. Infantry]], under the command of Captain Edwin M. Coates would serve as the station's guard. That evening, the expedition camped on the east bank of the Powder River opposite the site of the fort.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Vaughn|first1=J. W.|title=The Reynolds Campaign On Powder River|date=1961|publisher=University of Oklahoma Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Fort Reno skirmish ==
By 8:00&amp;nbsp;p.m. on March 5, 1876, the soldiers' pickets were on duty and the camp was asleep, when Native American warriors hiding near the east end of the camp suddenly fired on the infantry picket lines. The soldiers on guard answered their fire, but being a dark night, all either side could see were the flashes of gunfire. The sleeping camp quickly awoke and many of the soldiers went toward the picket lines. In the firefight that ensued, Private James M. Slavey of Company I, [[4th Infantry Regiment (United States)|4th Infantry]] was wounded in the cheek by a bullet. The skirmish lasted for less than an hour. One aspect that made the engagement rare was that it was a night battle, which was not a common event during the [[American Indian Wars]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Vaughn|first1=J. W.|title=The Reynolds Campaign On Powder River|date=1961|publisher=University of Oklahoma Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== March 6–16 ==
On March 6, the Bighorn expedition continued north, and on March 7 the five cavalry battalions set out toward the confluence of Prairie Dog Creek and the [[Tongue River (North Dakota)|Tongue River]]. After reaching that point on March 12, the ten cavalry companies rode first down the Tongue, then to the headwaters of Otter Creek, reaching it on March 16. On the 16th, scout Frank Grouard spotted two [[Oglala Lakota]] warriors observing the soldiers. Because of this, Grouard believed that the [[Oglala Lakota]] camp of the war chief [[Crazy Horse]] might be nearby. This was reported to Crook, and at 5 p.m. on March 16, he divided his command and sent [[Colonel]] [[Joseph J. Reynolds]] (a [[West Point]] classmate of President [[Ulysses S. Grant]], and a combat veteran of both the [[Mexican-American War]], and [[American Civil War|Civil War]]) on a night march with about 379 men, supplying them with rations for one day, and following the trail of the two Oglala's southeast toward the Powder River. General Crook kept with him about 300 of the expedition's men and the pack train, with which he planned to rendezvous with Reynolds at the mouth of Lodge Pole Creek on the 17th. During the night Frank Grouard and the other scouts led Reynolds's advance and followed the two warriors's trail in the snow. It led to what they were looking for, a Cheyenne and Lakota Sioux Indian village, which they described as containing more than 100 lodges on the west bank of Powder River. The scouts immediately reported this information back to Colonel Reynolds.&lt;ref&gt;Porter, Joseph C. ''Paper Medicine Man: John Gregory Bourke and his American West'' Norman: University of Oklahoma Press, 1986, pp. 30-32&lt;/ref&gt;

== Battle of Powder River ==
{{Main|Battle of Powder River}}
The village, however, was somewhat further north than anticipated, with the result that initially only Captain James Egan's 2nd Cavalry Company K, of 47 men, including Second Lieutenant [[John Gregory Bourke|John G. Bourke]], charged into the village from the south, while the other companies were delayed by the distance and rough terrain. The soldiers were under fire for approximately five hours when, at about 2:30&amp;nbsp;p.m., with the destruction of the village complete, Reynolds ordered his soldiers to withdraw. Over 700 Indian ponies had been captured. In his premature haste to withdraw, the command left behind the bodies of its three dead soldiers, with one in the village, and two at a field hospital as well as Private Lorenzo E. Ayers, who was badly wounded and subsequently killed by vengeful Indians. The men made their way across to the east side of the frozen Powder River, withdrawing south.&lt;ref&gt;Porter, pp, 32-35&lt;/ref&gt;

Reynolds's command withdrew about {{convert|21|mi|km}} south that afternoon and evening, crossing and recrossing the frozen Powder River when necessary, up the river to the confluence of the Powder and Lodge Pole Creek, arriving there after 9:00&amp;nbsp;p.m. in an exhausted condition. However, General Crook was not there as he had camped over {{convert|10|mi|km}} to the northeast and had failed to inform Reynolds of his new location.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Reynold's Attack on Crazy Horse's Village on Powder River, March 17, 1876&quot; [http://www.rootsweb.ancestry.com/~nalakota/wotw/military/reynoldsattackcrazyhorsevillage_wotw043034.html], accessed 8 Jan 2013&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the Indians suffered only two to three killed and one to three wounded during the battle, they lost most of their property and, in the words of the Cheyenne warrior Wooden Leg, were &quot;rendered very poor.&quot;  The people walked several days to reach the Oglala Sioux village of [[Crazy Horse]] farther north near the [[Little Powder River]], where they were given shelter and food. On the way, several Cheyenne froze to death. The army stated that the village consisted of about 104 lodges, including tipis and wikiups, while Cheyenne accounts said the village had about 40-65 tipis, and about 50 other structures. Therefore, around a hundred total structures made up the Indian village that day. The number of warriors involved in the battle numbered between 100 and 250, while there were about 379 U. S. soldiers and civilians present.&lt;ref&gt;Porter, p. 36; Green, pp. 3, 7, 12&lt;/ref&gt;

== March 18–26 ==
Early in the morning of March 18, the Cheyenne recaptured over 500 of their ponies, but Colonel Reynolds ordered his men not to pursue. At approximately 1:30&amp;nbsp;p.m. that day, Crook's command rejoined Reynolds with the pack train, and the six companies were finally able to collect their rations and blankets. The reunited column returned to the supply base at [[Fort Reno (Wyoming)|Old Fort Reno]], where the wounded soldiers were placed in wagons, and Captain Coates's companies of the 4th Infantry rejoined the Big Horn Expedition after two weeks of separation. On March 26, 1876, the entire command, except for the four soldiers killed on March 17, returned to [[Fort Fetterman]], [[Wyoming Territory]], ending the 26-day campaign.&lt;ref&gt;Bourke, John Gregory ''On the Border with Crook'' Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1971, pp. 279-280&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
The Big Horn Expedition's path covered over {{convert|410|mi|km}} across five present-day counties in two states. The command suffered more than 79 casualties from various causes, including 4 killed, 8 wounded, 1 injured in an accident, and over 66 frostbitten. Colonel Reynolds was accused of dereliction of duty for failing to properly support the first charge at Powder River with his entire command; for burning the captured supplies, food, blankets, buffalo robes, and ammunition instead of keeping them for army use; and most of all, for losing hundreds of the captured horses. In January, 1877, his [[court-martial]] at [[Cheyenne, Wyoming|Cheyenne, Wyoming Territory]] found Reynolds guilty of all three charges. He was sentenced to suspension from rank and command for one year. Reynolds's friend and West Point classmate, President Ulysses S. Grant, remitted the sentence, but he never served again. Joseph J. Reynolds retired on disability leave on June 25, 1877, exactly one year after the culminating battle of the Great Sioux War at the [[Battle of Little Bighorn|Little Bighorn]]. Crook's and Reynolds's failed expedition and their inability to seriously damage the Lakota and Cheyenne probably encouraged Indian resistance to the demands of the United States.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Vaughn|first1=J. W.|title=The Reynolds Campaign On Powder River|date=1961|publisher=University of Oklahoma Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Casualties ==
'''Native Americans'''

Killed in action-
* Eagle Chief, [[Northern Cheyenne]], March 17.
* Whirlwind, [[Northern Cheyenne]], March 17.

Wounded in action-
* Braided Locks, [[Northern Cheyenne]], March 17, &quot;one cheek furrowed by a bullet&quot;.
* unknown warrior, [[Northern Cheyenne]], March 17 &quot;forearm badly shattered&quot;.

'''United States Army'''

Killed in action-
* Private Peter Dowdy, Company E, [[3d Cavalry Regiment (United States)|3rd Cavalry]], March 17.
* Private George Schneider, Company K, [[2nd Cavalry Regiment (United States)|2nd Cavalry]], March 17.
* Private Michael I. McCannon, Company F, [[3d Cavalry Regiment (United States)|3rd Cavalry]], March 17.
* Private Lorenzo E. Ayers, Company M, [[3d Cavalry Regiment (United States)|3rd Cavalry]], March 17.

Mortally wounded-

* Cattle Herder John Wright, first casualty of the [[Great Sioux War of 1876]], mortally wounded March 3, died of wounds April 9, 1876.

Wounded in action-
* Private James M. Slavey, Company I, [[4th Infantry Regiment (United States)|4th Infantry]], March 5.
* First Lieutenant William C. Rawolle, Company E, [[2nd Cavalry Regiment (United States)|2nd Cavalry]], March 17.
* Sergeant Charles Kaminski, Company M, [[3d Cavalry Regiment (United States)|3rd Cavalry]], March 17.
* Corporal John Lang, Company E, [[2nd Cavalry Regiment (United States)|2nd Cavalry]], March 17.
* Farrier Patrick Goings, Company K, [[2nd Cavalry Regiment (United States)|2nd Cavalry]], March 17.
* Private John Droege. Company K, [[2nd Cavalry Regiment (United States)|2nd Cavalry]], March 17.
* Private Edward Eagan, Company K, [[2nd Cavalry Regiment (United States)|2nd Cavalry]], March 17.

Injured-

* Corporal John H. Moore, Company D, [[3d Cavalry Regiment (United States)|3rd Cavalry]], March 9, crushed by horse and severely injured

Frostbitten-

* Second Lieutenant [[John Gregory Bourke|John G. Bourke]], Company L, [[3d Cavalry Regiment (United States)|3rd Cavalry]]
* 65 additional soldiers

==Orders of battle==
'''Native Americans''', Chief's [[Two Moons|Two Moon]], [[He Dog]], [[Little Wolf|Little Coyote (Little Wolf)]], and Old Bear.  Between 100 and 250 warriors.
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! width=25% | Native Americans
! width=25% | Tribe
! Leaders
|-
| rowspan=2 |
[[Native Americans in the United States|Native Americans]]&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
| [[Northern Cheyenne]]
&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
|
* [[Two Moons|Two Moon]]
* [[Little Wolf|Little Coyote (Little Wolf)]]
* [[Wooden Leg]]
* Old Bear
* Maple Tree
* White Bull (Ice Bear), (Ice)
* Kate Bighead, sister of Ice
* Bear-Walks-on-a-Ridge 
* Powder Face
* Yellow Eagle
* Bull Coming Behind
* Tall Sioux
* Eagle Chief [[Killed in action|†]]
* Whirlwind [[Killed in action|†]]
|-
| [[Lakota people|Lakota Sioux]]
&lt;br/&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
|
* [[He Dog]]
* [[Grant Short Bull|Short Bull]] brother of He Dog
* Rock (''Inyan'') wife of He Dog
* Crawler
|-
|}

'''United States Army'''

Big Horn Expedition, March 1–26, 1876, Brigadier General [[George Crook|George R. Crook]] and Colonel [[Joseph J. Reynolds]], commanding.
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
! width=25% | Big Horn Expedition
! width=25% | Battalion
! Companies and Others
|-
| rowspan=9 |
&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
Brigadier General [[George Crook]], commanding
| 1st Battalion
&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
Captain [[Anson Mills]]
|
* Company E, [[3d Armored Cavalry Regiment|3rd Cavalry]]: First Lieutenant John B. Johnson
* Company M, [[3d Armored Cavalry Regiment|3rd Cavalry]]: Captain [[Anson Mills]], First Lieutenant Augustus C. Paul
|-
| 2nd Battalion
&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
Captain William Hawley
|
* Company A, [[3d Armored Cavalry Regiment|3rd Cavalry]]: Captain William Hawley, First Lieutenant Joseph Lawson, Second Lieutenant Charles Morton, Detached as adjutant
* Company D, [[3d Armored Cavalry Regiment|3rd Cavalry]]: First Lieutenant William W. Robinson, Jr., Detached from Company H
|-
| 3rd Battalion
&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
Captain Henry E. Noyes
|
*  Company I, [[2nd Cavalry Regiment (United States)|2nd Cavalry]]: Captain Henry E. Noyes, First Lieutenant Christopher T. Hall
*  Company K, [[2nd Cavalry Regiment (United States)|2nd Cavalry]]: Captain James Egan
|-
| 4th Battalion
&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
Captain Thomas B. Dewees
|
*  Company A, [[2nd Cavalry Regiment (United States)|2nd Cavalry]]: Captain Thomas B. Dewees, First Lieutenant Martin E. O'Brien, Second Lieutenant Daniel C. Pearson
*  Company B, [[2nd Cavalry Regiment (United States)|2nd Cavalry]]: Captain James T. Peale, Second Lieutenant Frank U. Robinson
|-
| 5th Battalion
&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
Captain Alexander Moore
|
* Company E, [[2nd Cavalry Regiment (United States)|2nd Cavalry]]: First Lieutenant William C. Rawolle, Detached from Company B, ([[Wounded in action|Wounded]]), Second Lieutenant [[Frederick W. Sibley]]
* Company F, [[3d Armored Cavalry Regiment|3rd Cavalry]]: Captain Alexander Moore, Second Lieutenant Bainbridge Reynolds 
|-
| 6th Battalion
&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
Captain Edwin M. Coates
|
* Company C, [[4th Infantry Regiment (United States)|4th Infantry]]: Captain Edwin M. Coates
* Company I, [[4th Infantry Regiment (United States)|4th Infantry]]: Captain Samuel P. Ferris, Second Lieutenant Charles W. Mason
|-
| Pack Train
&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
Thomas Moore, Chief Packer
|
* Thomas McAuliff, 1st Battalion Pack Train
* Richard &quot;Uncle Dick&quot; Closter (Kloster), 2nd Battalion Pack Train
* Mr. Foster, 3rd Battalion Pack Train
* Mr. Young, 4th Battalion Pack Train
* Edward DeLaney, 5th Battalion Pack Train
|-
| Medical Detachment
&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
Assistant Surgeon Curtis E. Munn 
|
* Assistant Surgeon Curtis E. Munn 
* Acting Assistant Surgeon Charles R. Stephens
* Acting Assistant Surgeon John Ridgely 
* Hospital Steward [[William C. Bryan]]
|-
| Scouts and Guides
&lt;br&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;
Major Thaddeus H. Stanton
|
* Second Lieutenant [[John Gregory Bourke|John G. Bourke]], Aide-de-camp to General George Crook, Company L, [[3d Cavalry Regiment (United States)|3rd Cavalry]]
* Second Lieutenant Charles Morton, Acting Regimental Adjutant and Quartermaster of Cavalry, Company A, [[3d Cavalry Regiment (United States)|3rd Cavalry]]
* [[Robert Edmund Strahorn|Robert E. Strahorn]], newspaper correspondent for the [[Rocky Mountain News]]
* [[Frank Grouard]]
* Benjamin Clark
* Louis Richard
* Buckskin Jack
* Baptiste Pourier (Big Bat)
* Baptiste Garnier (Little Bat)
* Charlie Jennesse
* Louis Shangreau
* John Shangreau
* John Wright [[Killed in action|†]], Cattle Herder 
|-
|
|}

'''United States Army''', Colonel [[Joseph J. Reynolds]], [[3d Cavalry Regiment (United States)|3rd United States Cavalry Regiment]], in command. Brigadier General [[George Crook]] following as an observer.

* [[2nd Cavalry Regiment (United States)|2nd United States Cavalry Regiment]].
** Company A, First Lieutenant Daniel C. Pearson.
** Company B, Captain James T. Peale.
** Company E, 53 men, First Lieutenant William C. Rawolle.
** Company I, 56 men, Captain Henry E. Noyes.
** Company K, 47 men, Captain James Egan.
* [[3d Cavalry Regiment (United States)|3rd United States Cavalry Regiment]].
** Company A, First Lieutenant Joseph Lawson
** Company D, First Lieutenant William W. Robinson.
** Company E, 69 men, First Lieutenant John B. Johnson.
** Company F, 68 men, Captain Alexander Moore.
** Company H, 1 man, Second Lieutenant William W. Robinson, Jr.
** Company L, 1 man, Second Lieutenant John G. Bourke.
** Company M, 68 men, Captain [[Anson Mills]].
* [[4th Infantry Regiment (United States)|4th United States Infantry Regiment]].
** Company C, Captain Edwin M. Coates
** Company I, Captain Samuel P. Ferris
* Scouts, Guides, Herders, Packers, Wagoners, Ambulance Employees, Unattached Soldiers, and Civilians, 191 men.
* Commissioned Officers......................................30
* Enlisted Soldiers..............................................662
* Scouts, Guides, Herders...................................35
* 5 Pack Trains, Chief Packer and employees....62
* Wagon Train employees...................................89
* Ambulance employees........................................5
* Aggregate......................................................883 men

==Officers of the expedition==
* [[Brigadier General (United States)|Brigadier General]] [[George Crook|George R. Crook]], Commander, Department of the Platte
* [[Colonel (United States)|Colonel]] [[Joseph J. Reynolds|Joseph Jones Reynolds]], Field and Staff, 3rd Cavalry
* [[Major (United States)|Major]] Thaddeus Harlan Stanton, Paymaster, Chief of Scouts
* [[Surgeon's assistant|Assistant Surgeon]] Curtis E. Munn, Medical Service, Department of the Platte
* [[Surgeon's assistant|Acting Assistant Surgeon]] Charles R. Stephens, Medical Service, Department of the Platte
* [[Surgeon's assistant|Acting Assistant Surgeon]] John Ridgely, Medical Service, Department of the Platte 
* [[Captain (United States)|Captain]] [[Anson Mills]], Company M, 3rd Cavalry, Commander, 1st Battalion
* [[Captain (United States)|Captain]] William Hawley, Company A, 3rd Cavalry, Commander, 2nd Battalion
* [[Captain (United States)|Captain]] Henry Erastus Noyes, Company I, 2nd Cavalry, Commander, 3rd Battalion
* [[Captain (United States)|Captain]] Thomas Bull Dewees, Company A, 2nd Cavalry, Commander, 4th Battalion
* [[Captain (United States)|Captain]] Alexander Moore, Company F, 3rd Cavalry, Commander, 5th Battalion
* [[Captain (United States)|Captain]] Edwin Mortimer Coates, Company C, 4th Infantry, Commander, 6th Battalion
* [[Captain (United States)|Captain]] Samuel P. Ferris, Company I, 4th Infantry
* [[Captain (United States)|Captain]] James T. Peale, Company B, 2nd Cavalry
* [[Captain (United States)|Captain]] James &quot;Teddy&quot; Egan, Company K, 2nd Cavalry
* [[First Lieutenant (United States)|First Lieutenant]] William Charles Rawolle ([[Wounded in action|wounded]]), Company E, 2nd Cavalry
* [[First Lieutenant (United States)|First Lieutenant]] Martin E. O'Brien, Company A, 2nd Cavalry
* [[First Lieutenant (United States)|First Lieutenant]] Christopher T. Hall, Company I, 2nd Cavalry
* [[First Lieutenant (United States)|First Lieutenant]] Joseph Lawson, Company A, 3rd Cavalry
* [[First Lieutenant (United States)|First Lieutenant]] William Wallace Robinson, Company D, 3rd Cavalry
* [[First Lieutenant (United States)|First Lieutenant]] John Burgess Johnson, Company E, 3rd Cavalry
* [[First Lieutenant (United States)|First Lieutenant]] Augustus Choutea Paul, Company M, 3rd Cavalry
* [[Second Lieutenant (United States)|Second Lieutenant]] [[John Gregory Bourke]], [[Aide-de-camp#United States|Aide-de-camp]] to General George Crook, Company L, 3rd Cavalry
* [[Second Lieutenant (United States)|Second Lieutenant]] Charles Morton, Acting Regimental Adjutant and Quartermaster of Cavalry, Company A, 3rd Cavalry
* [[Second Lieutenant (United States)|Second Lieutenant]] Charles W. Mason, Company I, 4th Infantry
* [[Second Lieutenant (United States)|Second Lieutenant]] Daniel Crosby Pearson, Company A, 2nd Cavalry
* [[Second Lieutenant (United States)|Second Lieutenant]] Frank U. Robinson
* [[Second Lieutenant (United States)|Second Lieutenant]] [[Frederick W. Sibley|Frederick William Sibley]], Company E, 2nd Cavalry
* [[Second Lieutenant (United States)|Second Lieutenant]] Joseph Lawson, Company A, 3rd Cavalry
* [[Second Lieutenant (United States)|Second Lieutenant]] Bainbridge Reynolds, Company F, 3rd Cavalry

== In popular culture ==
In 1951, [[Cinema of the United States|Hollywood]] produced a fictional movie loosely based upon the [[Battle of Powder River]] of the Big Horn Expedition, starring [[Van Heflin]], [[Yvonne De Carlo]], [[Jack Oakie]], and [[Rock Hudson]]. The movie was released in the United States under the name ''Tomahawk,'' and entitled ''Battle of Powder River'' in the [[United Kingdom]], and elsewhere.

== Further reading ==
* Vaughn, J. W., ''The Reynolds Campaign On Powder River'', University of Oklahoma Press, 1961.
* Dillon, Richard H., ''North American Indian Wars'' 1983. 
* Greene, Jerome A. (editor), ''Battles and Skirmishes of the Great Sioux War, 1876-1877: The Military View'', University of Oklahoma Press, 1993. ISBN 0-8061-2535-7. 
* Marquis, Thomas, ''[[Wooden Leg: A Warrior Who Fought Custer]]''. 1920
* [http://www.rootsweb.com/~nalakota/wotw/military/reynoldsattackcrazyhorsevillage_wotw043034.html Voices from the Western Frontier]

== References ==
{{reflist}}

{{Montana Indian Battles}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Big Horn Expedition}}
[[Category:1876 in the United States]]
[[Category:Montana Territory]]</text>
      <sha1>fq1outxezok7ix8r5qwbs7b5treah71</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
