<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Black Hawk (Sauk leader)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1720677</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750980498</id>
      <parentid>750913775</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-22T17:11:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>BillHart93</username>
        <id>13240721</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 750913775 by [[Special:Contributions/104.251.65.240|104.251.65.240]] ([[User talk:104.251.65.240|talk]]) unexplained deletion</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="41253">{{Infobox person
|name=Black Hawk
|image=Chief Black Hawk3.jpg
|caption= An illustration of Black Hawk, from ''[[History of the Indian Tribes of North America]]''
|alt=
|birth_name=Ma-ka-tai-me-she-kia-kiak
|birth_date=1767
|death_date= October 3, {{Death year and age|1838|1767}}
|birth_place=[[Black Hawk State Historic Site|Saukenuk]], [[Illinois]]
|death_place=[[Davis County, Iowa]]
|resting_place=
|nationality=[[Sauk people|Sauk]]
|other_names=Black Sparrow Hawk
|known_for=[[Black Hawk War]]
|occupation=War captain; band leader
|monuments=[[Black Hawk Statue]], [[Black Hawk State Historic Site]]
}}

'''Black Hawk''', born '''''Ma-ka-tai-me-she-kia-kiak''''', (1767&amp;nbsp;– October 3, 1838) was a band leader and warrior of the [[Sauk people|Sauk]] [[Native Americans in the United States|American Indian]] tribe in what is now the Midwest of the [[United States]]. Although he had inherited an important historic [[medicine bundle]] from his father, he was not a hereditary civil chief. Black Hawk earned his status as a war chief or captain by his actions: leading raiding and war parties as a young man, and a band of Sauk warriors during the [[Black Hawk War]] of 1832.

During the [[War of 1812]], Black Hawk had fought on the side of the [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland|British]] against the U.S., hoping to push white American settlers away from Sauk territory. Later he led a band of Sauk and Fox warriors, known as the [[British Band]], against European-American settlers in [[Illinois]] and present-day [[Wisconsin]] in the 1832 Black Hawk War. After the war, he was captured by U.S. forces and taken to the eastern U.S. He and other war leaders were taken on tour of several cities.

Shortly before being released from custody, Black Hawk told his story to an interpreter; aided also by a newspaper reporter, he published ''[[Autobiography of Ma-Ka-Tai-Me-She-Kia-Kiak, or Black Hawk, Embracing the Traditions of his Nation...]]'' in 1833 in [[Cincinnati, Ohio]]. The first Native American autobiography to be published in the U.S., his book became an immediate bestseller and has gone through several editions. Black Hawk died in 1838 (at age 70 or 71) in what is now southeastern [[Iowa]]. He has been honored by an enduring legacy: his book, many eponyms, and other tributes.

==Early life==
Black Hawk, or Black Sparrow Hawk ([[Fox language|Sauk]] Ma-kat-tai-me-she-kia-kiak [''Mahkate:wi-meši-ke:hke:hkwa''], &quot;be a large black hawk&quot;)&lt;ref name=bright&gt;Bright, William (2004). ''Native American Place Names of the United States'', [[Norman, Oklahoma]]: University of Oklahoma Press, pg. 66.&lt;/ref&gt; was born in 1767 in the village of ''[[Saukenuk]]'' on the [[Rock River (Illinois)|Rock River]] (present-day [[Rock Island, Illinois|Rock Island]], [[Illinois]]).&lt;ref name=auto/&gt; Black Hawk's father ''Pyesa'' was the tribal [[medicine man]] of the [[Sauk people]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Stevens |first=Frank Everett |url=http://myeducationresearch.org/databases/cgi-bin/kwq.asp?qu=@recnumber%20EBK30012662&amp;FreeText=&amp;sc=%2Fpierianp%2Febk%2F|title=Black Hawk War, Part 02 -- Black Hawk and His Times |date=18 May 1743|work= myeducationresearch.org |publisher=The Pierian Press |year=2000 |accessdate=2011-05-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Sauk used the village in the summer for raising corn and as a burial site. During the winter, they moved across the Mississippi to present-day Iowa for winter hunts and fur trapping.

Little is known about Black Hawk's youth. He was said to be a descendant of ''Nanamakee'' (Thunder), a Sauk chief who, according to tradition, met an early French explorer, possibly [[Samuel de Champlain]].&lt;ref&gt;Roger L. Nichols, ''Black Hawk and the Warrior's Path'' (Arlington Heights, Illinois: Harlan Davidson, 1992; ISBN 0-88295-884-4), 4, 12.&lt;/ref&gt; At age 15, Black Hawk accompanied his father Pyesa on a raid against the [[Osage Nation|Osage]]. He won approval by killing and [[scalping]] his first enemy.&lt;ref&gt;Nichols, 14.&lt;/ref&gt; The young Black Hawk tried to establish himself as a war captain by leading other raids. He had limited success until, at age 19, he led 200 men in a battle against the Osage, in which he personally killed five men and one woman.&lt;ref&gt;Nichols, 16.&lt;/ref&gt; Soon after, he joined his father in a raid against [[Cherokee]] along the [[Meramec River]] in Missouri. After Pyesa died from wounds received in the battle, Black Hawk inherited the Sauk [[medicine bundle]] which his father had carried, giving him an important role in the tribe.&lt;ref&gt;Nichols, 16–17.&lt;/ref&gt;

==War leader==
After an extended period of mourning for his father, Black Hawk resumed leading raiding parties over the next years, usually targeting the traditional enemy, the Osage. Black Hawk did not belong to a clan that provided the Sauk with hereditary civil leaders, or [[tribal chief|&quot;chiefs&quot;]]. He achieved status through his exploits as a warrior and by leading successful raiding parties. Men like Black Hawk are sometimes called &quot;war chiefs&quot;, but historian Patrick Jung writes, &quot;It is more accurate to call them 'war leaders' since the nature of their office and the power that it wielded was much different from that of a civil chief.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Jung, 55.&lt;/ref&gt; Twenty-first century historians such as John W. Hall have suggested the term &quot;war captain&quot; for this role.&lt;ref&gt;See for example John W. Hall, ''Uncommon Defense: Indian Allies in the Black Hawk War'' (Harvard University Press, 2009), p. 2.&lt;/ref&gt;

==War of 1812==
[[File:Fort Madison 1810.jpg|thumb|right|upright=1.25|Plans of the original [[Fort Madison]], 1810. Black Hawk participated in the 1809 and 1812 sieges; the fort fell to British-supported Indians in 1813.]]

During the War of 1812, Black Hawk, now 45, served as a war leader of a Sauk band at their village of [[Saukenuk]], which fielded about 200 warriors. He supported the invalidity of [[Quashquame]]'s [[Treaty of St. Louis (1804)]] between the Sauk and [[Fox (tribe)|Fox]] nations and then-Governor [[William Henry Harrison]] of the [[Indiana Territory]] that ceded territory, including Saukenuk, to the [[United States]].&lt;ref name=smith/&gt; The Sauk and Fox are [[consensus]]-based decision makers and those representatives sent to the meeting with the US government did not have the power to cede tribal territory although Quashquame did. The lack of the consensus aspect by each the Sauk and Fox councils the treaty could never be considered valid by Black Hawk and other traditionalists.&lt;ref name=lewis2/&gt; Black Hawk took part in skirmishes against US forces at the newly constructed [[Fort Madison]] in the disputed land; this was the first time he fought directly against the U.S. Army.&lt;ref name=&quot;mckusick2009&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|last=McKusick|first=Marshall B.|title=Frontier Forts of Iowa: Indians, Traders, and Soldiers, 1682–1862|editor=William E. Whittaker|publisher=University of Iowa Press|location=Iowa City|year=2009|pages=55–74|chapter=Fort Madison, 1808-1813|isbn=978-1-58729-831-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the [[War of 1812]], forces of [[Great Britain]] and its colonies in present-day Canada were engaged against those of the U.S., with major battles on the Great Lakes and surrounding remote lands. The British depended upon alliances with the Native American population to wage war in this area since the British were occupied with [[Napoleon]] in Europe. Colonel Robert Dickson, an English [[fur trader]], amassed a sizable force of Native Americans at [[Green Bay (Lake Michigan)|Green Bay]] to assist the British in operations around the Great Lakes. Most were from the [[Potawatomi]], [[Ho-Chunk]], [[Kickapoo people|Kickapoo]], and [[Ottawa (tribe)|Ottawa]] tribes. Black Hawk and his band of about 200 Sauk warriors were included in this group of allies.

Dickson commissioned Black Hawk at the rank of [[Brevet (military)|brevet]] [[Brigadier General]],&lt;ref name=smith&gt;Smith, William Rudolph. ''The History of Wisconsin: In Three Parts, Historical, Documentary, and Descriptive'', ([https://books.google.com/books?id=YGPggXpQnGEC&amp;pg=PA221&amp;lpg=PA221&amp;dq=black+hawk's+band&amp;source=web&amp;ots=AFV9mPs3ub&amp;sig=83ojd-ZdXsl4sANrD78h_sk9QR4 Google Books]), B. Brown: 1854, pp. 221–406. Retrieved 20 September 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; with command over all native allies at Green Bay and presented him with a silk flag, a medal, and a written certificate of good behavior and alliance with the British. The war leader preserved the certificate for 20 years; it was found by US forces after the [[Battle of Bad Axe]], along with a flag similar in description to that Dickson gave to Black Hawk.&lt;ref name=smith/&gt;

During the war, Black Hawk and Native warriors fought in several engagements with Major-General [[Henry Procter (British Army officer)|Henry Procter]] on the borders of [[Lake Erie]].&lt;ref name=lewis2/&gt; Black Hawk was at the [[Battle of Frenchtown]], [[Fort Meigs]], and the attack on [[Fort Stephenson]].&lt;ref name=trask&gt;[[Trask, Kerry A.]] ''Black Hawk: The Battle for the Heart of America'', ([https://books.google.com/books?id=8ZIXkMBBLw0C&amp;pg=PA220&amp;ots=jRiESpfwqk&amp;dq=Battle+of+Yellow+Creek+Black+Hawk&amp;sig=mSbBrxx8pVQi-EUv-5GCHirzrnA#PPA221,M1 Google Books]), Henry Holt: 2006, p. 109, 308, (ISBN 0805077588), pp. 220-221. Retrieved 26 October 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=lewisb1&gt;Lewis, James. &quot;[http://lincoln.lib.niu.edu/blackhawk/pageb1.html The Black Hawk War of 1832: FAQ] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070913122800/http://lincoln.lib.niu.edu/blackhawk/pageb1.html |date=September 13, 2007 }},&quot; ''Abraham Lincoln Digitization Project'', Northern Illinois University. Retrieved 26 October 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; The U.S. repulsed the British and the Indian Confederacy led by [[Tecumseh]], with high casualties suffered by the British and their allies.

Black Hawk despaired over the many lives lost due to European attack methods; soon after, he quit the war to return home. Back in Saukenuk, he found that his rival ''[[Keokuk (Sauk leader)|Keokuk]]'' had become the tribe's war chief.&lt;ref name=smith/&gt; Black Hawk rejoined the British effort toward the end of the war, fighting alongside British forces in campaigns along the Mississippi River near the [[Illinois Territory]].&lt;ref name=trask/&gt; At the Battle of [[Credit Island]] and by harassing U.S. troops at [[Fort Johnson]], Black Hawk helped to push the Americans out of the upper Mississippi River valley.&lt;ref name=&quot;nolan2009&quot;&gt;{{Cite book|last=Nolan|first=David J.|title=Frontier Forts of Iowa: Indians, Traders, and Soldiers, 1682–1862|editor=William E. Whittaker|publisher=University of Iowa Press|location=Iowa City|year=2009|pages=85–94|chapter=Fort Johnson, Cantonment Davis, and Fort Edwards|isbn=978-1-58729-831-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Black Hawk fought in the [[Battle of the Sink Hole]] (May 1815), leading an ambush on a group of Missouri Rangers. Conflicting accounts of the action were given by the Missouri leader John Shaw&lt;ref name=&quot;Stevens&quot;&gt;{{Cite book |last=Stevens |first=Walter B. |title=Centennial History of Missouri (The Center State) One Hundred Years in the Union |publisher=S. J. Clarke |location=St. Louis |year=1921}}&lt;/ref&gt; and by Black Hawk.&lt;ref name=Life_of_Black_Hawk&gt;{{Cite book |author=Black Hawk |editor=Milo M. Quaife |title=Life of Black Hawk, Ma-ka-tai-me-she-kia-kiak |publisher=Lakeside Press |location=Chicago |date=1916 |origyear=1834 |pages=66–68 |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=JpBOAAAAMAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After the end of the War of 1812, Black Hawk signed a peace treaty in May 1816 that re-affirmed the treaty of 1804. Later he said he was not aware of this stipulation.&lt;ref name=lewis2&gt;Lewis, James. &quot;[http://lincoln.lib.niu.edu/blackhawk/background.html &quot;Background: The Black Hawk War of 1832&quot;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080516083221/http://lincoln.lib.niu.edu/blackhawk/background.html |date=May 16, 2008 }}, ''Abraham Lincoln Digitization Project'', Northern Illinois University. Retrieved 20 September 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Black Hawk War==
{{Main|Black Hawk War}}
[[File:Black hawk life cast.jpg|thumb|left|Plaster life cast of Black Hawk, original ca. 1830, at [[Black Hawk State Historic Site]] ]]

As a consequence of the 1804 treaty, the Sauk and Fox tribes had ceded their lands in [[Illinois]] and in 1828 removed west of the [[Mississippi]]. Black Hawk and other tribal members disputed the treaty, as noted above, and said leaders had signed it without full tribal authorization.&lt;ref name=lewis/&gt; Angered by the loss of his birthplace, between 1830 and 1831 Black Hawk led a number of incursions across the [[Mississippi River]] to Illinois. He was persuaded to return west each time without bloodshed.

In April 1832, encouraged by promises of alliance with other tribes and with [[United Kingdom|Britain]], he moved his so-called &quot;[[British Band]]&quot; of more than 1500 people, both warriors and non-combatants, into Illinois.&lt;ref name=lewis&gt;Lewis, James. &quot;[http://lincoln.lib.niu.edu/blackhawk/page2c.html The Black Hawk War of 1832] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090815021319/http://lincoln.lib.niu.edu/blackhawk/page2c.html |date=August 15, 2009 }},&quot; Abraham Lincoln Digitization Project, ''Northern Illinois University''. Retrieved August 1, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; Finding no allies, he tried to return to [[Iowa]], but the undisciplined Illinois [[militia]] provoked open attack and the [[Battle of Stillman's Run]].&lt;ref name=wiscsr&gt;&quot;[http://www.wisconsinhistory.org/diary/002795.asp May 14: Black Hawk's Victory at the Battle of Stillman's Run],&quot; ''Historic Diaries: The Black Hawk War'', Wisconsin State Historical Society. Retrieved 6 August 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;  A number of other violent engagements followed. The governors of [[Michigan Territory]] and Illinois mobilized their militias to hunt down Black Hawk's Band. These actions led to the last Native American War fought on the east side of the Mississippi River.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.blackhawkpark.org/History/Black_Hawk.html &quot;’I Am a Sauk... I Am a Warrior’].&quot; Black Hawk State Historic Site. Black Hawk Park &amp; Foundation. Web. 26 Sept. 2014.&lt;/ref&gt; The conflict became known as the [[Black Hawk War]].

When Black Hawk entered Illinois in April, his British Band was composed of about 500 warriors and 1,000 old men, women, and children.&lt;ref name=nrhp2&gt;Harmet, &quot;Apple River Fort,&quot; p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=lewis3&gt;Lewis, James. &quot;[http://lincoln.lib.niu.edu/blackhawk/scholarshipindex.html Introduction] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090420194551/http://lincoln.lib.niu.edu/blackhawk/scholarshipindex.html |date=April 20, 2009 }},&quot; ''The Black Hawk War of 1832'', Abraham Lincoln Digitization Project, Northern Illinois University. Retrieved 20 September 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; The group included members of the [[Sauk people|Sauk]], [[Fox (tribe)|Fox]] and [[Kickapoo people|Kickapoo]] tribes. They crossed the river near the mouth of the [[Iowa River]] and followed the [[Rock River (Illinois)|Rock River]] northeast. Along the way, they passed the ruins of Saukenuk and headed for the village of [[Ho-Chunk]] prophet [[White Cloud (prophet)|White Cloud]].&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;Lewis, &quot;Introduction.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

As the war progressed, factions of other tribes joined, or tried to join Black Hawk. Other Native Americans and settlers carried out acts of violence for personal reasons amidst the chaos of the war.&lt;ref name=wisc2&gt;&quot;[http://www.wisconsinhistory.org/diary/002816.asp &quot;May 21, Indian Creek, Ill.: Abduction of the Hall Sisters&quot;], ''Historic Diaries: The Black Hawk War'', Wisconsin State Historical Society. Retrieved 20 September 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=matile2&gt;Matile, Roger. &quot;[http://www.ledgersentinel.com/article.asp?a=6216 The Black Hawk War: Massacre at Indian Creek],&quot; ''Ledger-Sentinel'' ([[Oswego, Illinois]]), 31 May 2007, Retrieved 20 September 2007&lt;/ref&gt; In one example, a band of hostile Ho-Chunk intent on joining Black Hawk's Band attacked and killed the party of [[Felix St. Vrain]] in what Americans knew as the [[St. Vrain massacre]].&lt;ref name=wisc/&gt; This act was an exception as most Ho-Chunk sided with the U.S. during the Black Hawk War.&lt;ref name=wisc/&gt; The warriors who attacked St. Vrain's party had acted independently of the Ho-Chunk nation.&lt;ref name=wisc&gt;&quot;[http://www.wisconsinhistory.org/diary/002832.asp &quot;The Killing of Felix St. Vrain&quot;], ''Historic Diaries: Black Hawk War'', Wisconsin Historical Society, Retrieved 20 September 2007&lt;/ref&gt; From April to August, Potawatomi warriors also joined with Black Hawk's Band.&lt;ref name=lewis2d/&gt;

The war stretched from April to August 1832, with a number of battles, skirmishes and massacres on both sides. Black Hawk led his men in another conflict, the [[Battle of Wisconsin Heights]].  Afterward, the Illinois and Michigan Territory militias caught up with Black Hawk's &quot;British Band&quot; for the final confrontation at [[Battle of Bad Axe|Bad Axe]]. At the mouth of the [[Bad Axe River]], pursuing soldiers, their Indian allies, and a U.S. [[gunboat]] killed hundreds of Sauk and Potawatomi men, women and children.&lt;ref name=mil&gt;[http://www.jsonline.com/story/index.aspx?id=597233 McCann, Dennis. &quot;Black Hawk's name, country's shame lives on&quot;], ''Milwaukee Journal-Sentinel'', April 28, 2007. Retrieved July 30, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;  On August 27, 1832, Black Hawk and ''Wabokieshiek'' surrendered at [[Prairie du Chien]] to Indian agent Joseph Street.&lt;ref&gt;Jung, p. 182.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Trask, pp. 294–95.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://lincoln.lib.niu.edu/blackhawk &quot;Lincoln/Net: The Black Hawk War&quot;]. Lincoln / Net. Northern Illinois University, n.d. Web. 03 May 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Tour of the East==
[[File:Black hawk calumet.jpg|thumb|[[Calumet (pipe)|Calumet]] (or &quot;peace pipe&quot;) used by Black Hawk, on display at [[Black Hawk State Historic Site]].]]

Following the war, with most of the British Band killed and the rest captured or disbanded, the defeated Black Hawk was held in captivity at [[Jefferson Barracks]] near [[St. Louis|Saint Louis]], [[Missouri]] together with Neapope, White Cloud, and eight other leaders.&lt;ref name=lewis2d/&gt; After eight months, in April 1833 they were taken east, as ordered by [[U.S. President]] [[Andrew Jackson]]. The men were taken by steamboat, carriage, and railroad, and met with large crowds wherever they went. Jackson wanted them to be impressed with the power of the United States. Once in [[Washington, D.C.]], they met with Jackson and [[United States Secretary of War|Secretary of War]] [[Lewis Cass]]. Afterward, they were delivered to their final destination, prison at [[Fortress Monroe]] in Norfolk, [[Virginia]].&lt;ref name=lewis2d/&gt; They were held only a few weeks at the prison, during which they posed for portraits by different artists.

On June 5, 1833, the men were sent west by steamboat on a circuitous route that took them through many large cities. Again, the men were a spectacle everywhere they went, and were greeted by huge crowds of people in cities such as [[Baltimore]], [[Philadelphia]] and [[New York City|New York]], .&lt;ref name=lewis2d/&gt; In the west, closer to the battle sites and history of conflict, the reception was much different. For instance, in [[Detroit]], a crowd burned and hanged [[effigies]] of the prisoners.&lt;ref name=lewis2d&gt;[http://lincoln.lib.niu.edu/blackhawk/page2d.html Lewis, James. &quot;The Black Hawk War of 1832&quot;], ''Abraham Lincoln Digitization Project'', Northern Illinois University, p. 2D. Retrieved 20 September 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early autobiography by Native American==
Near the end of his captivity in 1833, Black Hawk told his [[autobiography|life story]] to [[Antoine LeClaire]], a government interpreter. Edited by the local reporter J.B. Patterson, Black Hawk's account was one of the first Native American autobiography published in the U.S.&lt;ref name=gmu&gt;[http://historymatters.gmu.edu/d/5817/ &quot;Black Hawk Remembers Village Life Along the Mississippi],&quot; ''History Matters: The U.S. Survey Course on the Web'', George Mason University. Retrieved 20 September 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Autobiography of Ma-Ka-Tai-Me-She-Kia-Kiak, or Black Hawk, Embracing the Traditions of his Nation, Various Wars In Which He Has Been Engaged, and His Account of the Cause and General History of the Black Hawk War of 1832, His Surrender, and Travels Through the United States. Also Life, Death and Burial of the Old Chief, Together with a History of the Black Hawk War'' was published in 1833 in [[Cincinnati, Ohio]].&lt;ref name=auto&gt;[http://lincoln.lib.niu.edu/cgi-bin/philologic/navigate.pl?lincoln.3431 Black Hawk; LeClair, Antoine, interpreter; Patterson, J.B., editor, ''Autobiography of Ma-Ka-Tai-Me-She-Kia-Kiak, or Black Hawk, Embracing the Traditions of his Nation, Various Wars In Which He Has Been Engaged, and His Account of the Cause and General History of the Black Hawk War of 1832, His Surrender, and Travels Through the United States. Also Life, Death and Burial of the Old Chief, Together with a History of the Black Hawk War'', J.B. Patterson, Oquawka, IL: reprint 1882, Retrieved 20 September 2007] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070830032623/http://lincoln.lib.niu.edu/cgi-bin/philologic/navigate.pl?lincoln.3431 |date=August 30, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=trask/&gt; The book immediately became a best seller and has gone through numerous editions.&lt;ref name=trask/&gt;  (William Apes published the first autobiography written by an Native American in 1829.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://faculty.weber.edu/kmackay/native_american_literature.htm|title=Native American Literature|publisher=|accessdate=27 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;)

==Assessment as Sauk leader==
[[File:Black hawk statue.jpg|thumb|Statue of Black Hawk at [[Black Hawk State Historic Site]]]]

Although not a hereditary chief, Black Hawk filled a leadership void within the Sauk community. When [[Quashquame]] ceded much of the Sauk homeland in 1804 to the United States, including the main village [[Saukenuk]], he was viewed as ineffective. Black Hawk wrote in his autobiography:
{{quote|It subsequently appeared that they had been drunk the greater part of the time while at St. Louis. This was all myself and nation knew of the treaty of 1804. It has since been explained to me. I found by that treaty, that all of the country east of the Mississippi, and south of Jeffreon was ceded to the United States for one thousand dollars a year. I will leave it to the people of the United States to say whether our nation was properly represented in this treaty? Or whether we received a fair compensation for the extent of country ceded by these four individuals? I could say much more respecting this treaty, but I will not at this time. It has been the origin of all our serious difficulties with the whites.&lt;ref name=auto/&gt;}}

[[File:Black Hawk illustration from old book.jpg|thumb|left|Portrait of Black Hawk, from the [[Library of Congress|U.S. Library of Congress]]]]
Because of his role in the disputed 1804 treaty, the tribe reduced its support of ''Quashquame'' and made him a minor chief. &quot;Quasquawma, was chief of this tribe once, but being cheated out of the mineral country, as the Indians allege, he was denigrated from his rank and his son-in-law [[Taimah]] elected in his stead.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Atwater, Caleb. ''Remarks Made of A Tour to Prairie du Chien: Thence to Washington City, in 1829.'' Columbus, OH: Isaac N. Whiting, 1831&lt;/ref&gt; Although Quashquame and Black Hawk were at odds, the younger man did not directly challenge the civil chief. They apparently remained on good terms as Black Hawk rose in importance and Quashquame faded. Quashquame avoided confrontation with the U.S., while Black Hawk did not. After Black Hawk led an aborted takeover of [[Fort Madison]] in the Spring of 1809, Quashquame worked to restore relations with the US Army the next day.&lt;ref&gt;Van der Zee, Jacob (1913) &quot;Old Fort Madison: Some Source Materials&quot;, ''Iowa Journal of History and Politics'' Vol. 11.&lt;/ref&gt;

Quashquame told Gen. [[William Clark (explorer)|William Clark]] during a meeting in 1810 or 1811:
{{quote|My father, I left my home to see my great-grandfather, the president of the United States, but as I cannot proceed to see him, I give you my hand as to himself. I have no father to whom I have paid any attention but yourself. If you hear anything, I hope that you will let me know, and I will do the same. I have been advised several times to raise the tomahawk. Since the last war we have looked upon the Americans as friends, and I shall hold you fast by the hand. The [[Great Spirit]] has not put us on the earth to war with the whites. We have never struck a white man. If we go to war it is with the red flesh. Other nations send belts among us, and urge us to war. They say that if we do not, the Americans will encroach upon us, and drive us off our lands.&lt;ref&gt;Johnson, W.F. (1919) ''History of Cooper County, Missouri.'' Topeka: Historical Publishing Co., p. 62.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

During the run up to the [[War of 1812]], the US viewed Quashquame as loyal, or at least neutral. They knew Black Hawk led those Sauk warriors allied with the British. Quashquame led all Sauk non-combatants during the war, and they retreated to Saint Louis. Black Hawk thought this was an ideal arrangement:
{{quote|... all the children and old men and women belonging to the warriors who had joined the British were left with them to provide for. A council had been called which agreed that Quashquame, the Lance, and other chiefs, with the old men, women and children, and such others as chose to accompany them, should descend the Mississippi to St. Louis, and place themselves under the American chief stationed there. They accordingly went down to St. Louis, were received as the friendly band of our nation, were sent up the Missouri and provided for, while their friends were assisting the British!&lt;ref name=auto/&gt;}}

A rift developed among the Sauk after the war. In 1815 Quashquame was part of a large delegation who signed a treaty confirming a split between the Sauk along the Missouri River and the Sauk who lived along the Rock River at Saukenuk.&lt;ref&gt;''Indian Treaties 1795 to 1862 Vol. XX - Sauk &amp; Fox'' L.S. Watson (ed.) 1993&lt;/ref&gt; The Rock River group of Sauk was commonly known as the British Band; their warriors were the core of those Sauk who participated in the [[Black Hawk War]]. About 1824, Quashquame sold a large Sauk village in Illinois to a trader Captain James White. White gave Quashquame &quot;a little 'sku-ti-apo' [liquor] and two thousand bushels of corn&quot; for the land, which later was developed as [[Nauvoo, Illinois]].&lt;ref&gt;Campbell, James W. (1884) &quot;Address of Capt. Jas. W. Campbell.&quot;, in ''Report of the Organization and First Reunion of the Tri-State Old Settlers' Association of Illinois, Missouri and Iowa'', edited by J. H. Cole and J. M. Schaffer, pp. 33–38, Keokuk: IA, Tri-State Printing&lt;/ref&gt; This land sale likely aggravated Black Hawk and other Sauk who wanted to maintain their claim on Illinois.

As Quashquame was eclipsed by his son-in-law ''[[Taimah]]'' as the Sauk chief favored by the U.S., his compromise position lost standing compared to Black Hawk's resistance. When [[Caleb Atwater]] wrote about his visit to Quashquame in 1829, he depicted the leader as feeble, more interested in art and leisure than politics, but still advocating diplomacy over conflict.&lt;ref&gt;Caleb Atwater (1829) ''Remarks Made of A Tour to Prairie du Chien: Thence to Washington City'' (published 1831, pp. 60-62)&lt;/ref&gt; In the summer of 1830, Black Hawk began his incursions into the disputed territory of Illinois, which eventually leading to the Black Hawk War.

Black Hawk's frequent rival was ''[[Keokuk (Sauk leader)|Keokuk]],'' a Sauk war chief held in high esteem by the U.S. government. Officials believed that he was calm and reasonable, willing to negotiate, unlike Black Hawk. Black Hawk despised Keokuk, and viewed him as cowardly and self-serving, at one point threatening to kill him for not defending Saukenuk.&lt;ref&gt;Trask, Kerry (2006) ''Black Hawk: The Battle for the Heart of America.'' Henry Holt. pp. 75-80.&lt;/ref&gt; After the Black Hawk War, US officials designated Keokuk as the main Sauk leader and would only deal with him.

==Last days==
[[File:BlackHawkGraveIowaville.JPG|thumb|right|Putative Black Hawk grave at Iowaville Cemetery. There are conflicting accounts about what happened to his remains.]]
[[File:BlackHawkGravePlaque.jpg|thumb|right|Black Hawk Memorial Plaque at Iowaville Cemetery]]

After his tour of the east, Black Hawk lived with the Sauk along the [[Iowa River]] and later the [[Des Moines River]] near [[Iowaville, Iowa|Iowaville]]&lt;ref&gt;''Andreas Atlas of Iowa&quot;, 1903, &quot;Van Buren Co. Early History&quot; and &quot;Davis Co. Early History&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; in what is now southeast Iowa. At the end of his life, he tried to reconcile both with American settlers and with his Sauk rivals, including Keokuk.

In an 1838 address at Fort Madison in the year of his death, he said the following:
{{quote|It has pleased the [[Great Spirit]] that I am here today— I have eaten with my white friends. The earth is our mother— we are now on it, with the Great spirit above us; it is good. I hope we are all friends here. A few winters ago I was fighting against you. I did wrong, perhaps, but that is past—it is buried—let it be forgotten.

Rock River was a beautiful country. I liked my towns, my cornfields and the home of my people. I fought for it. It is now yours. Keep it as we did— it will produce you good crops.

I thank the Great Spirit that I am now friendly with my white brethren. We are here together, we have eaten together; we are friends; it is his wish and mine. I thank you for your friendship.

I was once a great warrior; I am now poor. Keokuk has been the cause of my present situation; but I do not attach blame to him. I am now old. I have looked upon the Mississippi since I have been a child. I love the great river. I have dwelt upon its banks from the time I was an infant. I look upon it now. I shake hands with you, and as it is my wish, I hope you are my friends.|--Address by Black Hawk, July 4, 1838, at Fort Madison.&lt;ref&gt;Antrobus, Augustine M. (1915) ''History of Des Moines County, Iowa: And Its People, Vol. 1'', p. 141 S.J. Clarke, Chicago.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Black Hawk died on October 3, 1838 after two weeks of illness. He was buried on the farm of his friend James Jordan on the north bank of the [[Des Moines River]] in [[Davis County, Iowa|Davis County]].

In July 1839, his remains were stolen by James Turner, who prepared his skeleton for exhibition. Black Hawk's sons Nashashuk and Gamesett went to Governor [[Robert Lucas (governor)|Robert Lucas]] of [[Iowa Territory]], who used his influence to bring the bones to security in his offices in [[Burlington, Iowa|Burlington]]. With the permission of Black Hawk's sons, the remains were held by the Burlington Geological and Historical Society. When the Society's building burned down in 1855, Black Hawk's remains were destroyed.&lt;ref name=davlibrary&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.qcmemory.org/Default.aspx?PageId=260&amp;nt=207&amp;nt2=229|title=Makataimeshekiakiak: Black Hawk and his War|publisher=[[Davenport, Iowa|Davenport]] Public Library|accessdate=2007-03-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

An alternative account is that Governor Lucas passed Black Hawk's bones to Enos Lowe, a Burlington physician, who was said to have left them to his partner, Dr. McLaurens. After McLaurens moved to California, workers were reported to have found the bones at his house. They buried the remains in a potter's grave in Aspen Grove Cemetery in Burlington.&lt;ref name=&quot;nyt&quot;&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=9C07E5D7153AE533A25756C2A96F9C94609ED7CF|title=BLACK HAWK'S VARNISHED BONES.; THEY ARE BELIEVED TO BE LYING UNMARKED IN A POTTER'S FIELD.|date=September 25, 1891|work=New York Times|accessdate=4 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

There is a marker for him&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.findagrave.com/cgi-bin/fg.cgi?page=gr&amp;GRid=40633143&amp;|title=Chief Blackhawk (1760 - 1838) - Find A Grave Memorial|publisher=|accessdate=27 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; in the [[Iowaville]] Cemetery on the hill over the river, although it is unknown if any of his remains are there.

==Personal life==
Though the Sauk practiced plural marriage, Black Hawk had one wife, known as As-she-we-qua&lt;ref name=&quot;Black Hawk wife.&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=Black Hawk State Historic Site - History|url=http://www.blackhawkpark.org/History/Black_Hawk.html|publisher=blackhawkpark.org|accessdate=2 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; (died 28 August 1846),&lt;ref name=&quot;Native peoples A to Z&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Native peoples A to Z : a reference guide to native peoples of the western hemisphere, Vol. 8|date=2009|publisher=Native American Books|location=Hamburg, Mich.|isbn=1878592734|pages=1784–785|edition=2nd|url=https://books.google.com.mx/books?id=Hx98AgAAQBAJ&amp;lpg|accessdate=2 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; or Singing Bird (her English name was Sarah Sally Baker) with whom he had five children. His oldest son and youngest daughter died in the same year, before 1820, and he mourned their passing following Sauk tradition for two years.&lt;ref name=&quot;Black Hawk wife.&quot; /&gt; His other children were a daughter Namequa (Running Fawn, Ailey Baker was her English name) and his sons Nasheakusk (aka Nashashuk) and Gamesett (aka Nasomsee).&lt;ref name=&quot;Native peoples A to Z&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=Wesson&gt;{{cite web|last1=Wesson|first1=Sarah|title=Black Hawk Makataimeshekiakiak: Black Hawk and his War|url=http://www.davenportlibrary.com/genealogy-and-history/local-history-info/the-people/black-hawk/|publisher=Davenport (Iowa) Public Library|accessdate=2 January 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
[[File:BlackHawkStatue 003.jpg|thumb|The ''[[Black Hawk Statue|Eternal Indian]]'', a sculpture by [[Lorado Taft]] inspired by Black Hawk.]]

Through interpreter [[Antoine LeClair]], Black Hawk dictated an autobiography titled ''Life of Ma-ka-tai-me-she-kia-kiak'' (or, ''Life of Black Hawk''), originally published in 1833.&lt;ref name=Life_of_Black_Hawk/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.wisconsinhistory.org/turningpoints/search.asp?id=248 &quot;The Life of Ma-ka-tai-me-she-kia-kiak, or Black Hawk, 1833 summary&quot;]. Wisconsin Historical Society&lt;/ref&gt;

A sculpture by [[Lorado Taft]] overlooks the Rock River in [[Oregon, Illinois]]. Entitled ''The Eternal Indian'', this statue is commonly known as the [[Black Hawk Statue]].&lt;ref name=or&gt;[http://www.oregonil.com/scupture-trail.html Oregon Sculpture Trail], The Eternal Indian, City of Oregon. Retrieved 28 September 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; In modern times Black Hawk is considered a tragic hero and numerous commemorations exist.&lt;ref name=trask/&gt; These are mostly in the form of [[eponym]]s; many roads, sports teams and schools are named after Black Hawk. Among the numerous wars in United States history, however; the Black Hawk War is one of few named for a person.&lt;ref name=shannon&gt;Shannon, B. Clay. ''Still Casting Shadows: A Shared Mosaic of U.S. History'', ([https://books.google.com/books?id=hBY_tIqFBysC&amp;pg=RA1-PA215&amp;dq=named+after+Black+Hawk&amp;ie=ISO-8859-1&amp;sig=SX2wn7WL_eeTVseLxwqEAuxSmq8 Google Books]), iUniverse, New York: 2006, p. 215, (ISBN 0595397239). Retrieved 26 October 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

According to a widespread myth, the [[Olympic gold medal]]-winning athlete [[Jim Thorpe]] was said to be descended from Black Hawk.&lt;ref&gt;''County Chronicles: A Vivid Collection of Fayette County, Pennsylvania Histories'', ([https://books.google.com/books?id=JI1vLkN_IoEC&amp;pg=PA129&amp;dq=Chief+Black+Hawk+born&amp;ie=ISO-8859-1&amp;sig=Miqn1AeG-iKaICKeYExFB_uEEic#PPA130,M1 Google Books]), Mechling Bookbindery: 2004, pp. 129–30, (ISBN 0976056348). Retrieved 4 October 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Wisconsin]] born [[African American]] [[spiritualist]] and [[trance medium]] [[Leafy Anderson]] claimed that Black Hawk was one of her major [[spirit guides]]. This spirit's guidance and protection are sought by the members of many churches within the loosely allied [[Spiritual Church Movement]] which she founded.&lt;ref name=berry&gt;{{cite book |title=The Spirit of Blackhawk: a Mystery of Africans and Indians |author =Jason Berry |publisher= University Press of Mississippi |year= 1995}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=nola&gt;{{cite book |last1= Jacobs |first1= Claude F. |last2= Kaslow |first2= Andrew J. |year= 1991 |title= The Spiritual Churches of New Orleans Origins, Beliefs, and Rituals of an African-American Religion |publisher= The University of Tennessee Press |ISBN= 1-57233-148-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=spiritworld&gt;{{cite book |last=Smith |first=Michael |year= 1992 |title= Spirit World: Pattern in the Expressive Folk Culture of New Orleans |publisher= Pelican Publishing |ISBN= 978-0-88289-895-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; Special &quot;Black Hawk services&quot; are held to invoke his assistance, and busts or statues representing him are kept on home and church altars by his devotees.&lt;ref name=berry/&gt;

==Notable examples of eponyms==
*Several place names, including [[Black Hawk County, Iowa]], the [[Black Hawk Bridge]] between Iowa and Wisconsin, and the historical [[Black Hawk Purchase]] in Iowa.{{cn|date=February 2016}}
*Four United States Navy vessels were named [[USS Black Hawk]].{{cn|date=February 2016}}
*The [[Chicago Blackhawks]] of the [[National Hockey League]] indirectly derive their name from Black Hawk. Their first owner, [[Frederic McLaughlin]], was a commander with the 333rd Machine Gun Battalion of the [[86th Infantry Division (United States)|86th Infantry Division]] during [[World War I]], nicknamed the &quot;Black Hawk Division&quot; after the war leader. McLaughlin named the hockey team in honor of his military unit.&lt;ref&gt;[http://blackhawks.nhl.com/club/page.htm?id=46778 &quot;History&quot;], Chicago Blackhawks&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Blackhawk Middle School]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bsd2.org/index.aspx?nid=57|title=Bensenville School District 2, IL - Website - Blackhawk Middle School|publisher=|accessdate=27 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; in Bensenville, Illinois
*Blackhawk Country Club, a private golf club in Shorewood Hills, Wisconsin is named for Black Hawk.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.blackhawkcc.com/about-us/history |title= About Us - History |publisher=blackhawkcc.com |accessdate=27 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*The athletic teams of [[Prairie du Chien Area School District|Prairie du Chien High School]] in [[Prairie du Chien, Wisconsin]] are nicknamed the ''Blackhawks'' in his honor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.southwestwisconsinconference.org/g5-bin/client.cgi |title=Southwest Wisconsin Conference |publisher= |accessdate=27 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The athletic teams of [[Fort Atkinson, Wisconsin|Fort Atkinson]] High School, Wisconsin are named &quot;Blackhawks&quot; for Black Hawk.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dailyunion.com/news/article_7b52f32e-97de-11e3-93c3-001a4bcf6878.html|title=Fort High won’t drop ‘Blackhawks’ name|work=Daily Jefferson County Union|accessdate=27 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* The [[Atlanta Hawks]] were named the Tri-Cities Blackhawks in the inaugural season of the [[NBA]] in the Tri-Cities (now [[Quad Cities]]) area in  [[Illinois]] and [[Iowa]]. The team was named for the [[Black Hawk War]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sportsmemorabilia.com/resources/team-jerseys/tri-cities-blackhawks.html&lt;/ref&gt;
*The [[Sikorsky UH-60 Blackhawk]], a four-blade, twin-engine, medium-lift utility helicopter manufactured by Sikorsky Aircraft, used by the US military and many armed forces around the world.

==See also==
*[[Wisconsin Heights Battlefield]]

==References==
{{Reflist|33em}}

==Further reading==
* Brown, Nicholas A. and Sarah E. Kanouse. ''Re-Collecting Black Hawk: Landscape, Memory, and Power in the American Midwest''. Pittsburgh, PA: University of Pittsburgh Press, 2015.

==External links==
{{Commons category|Black Hawk}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20070629163715/http://www.gilcrease.org/images/Samples/0126.1007.jpg Black Hawk with his son Whirling Thunder] (1833), by [[John Wesley Jarvis]], Gilcrease Museum
* {{Gutenberg author |id=Black+Hawk,+Sauk+chief | name=Sauk chief Black Hawk}}
* {{Internet Archive author |sname=Black Hawk |birth=1767 |death=1838}}
* [http://www.illinoishistory.gov/hs/black_hawk.htm &quot;Black Hawk State Historic Site&quot;], Illinois History
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20070715135822/https://usinfo.state.gov/usa/infousa/facts/democrac/12.htm &quot;Black Hawk Surrender Speech&quot;], State Department
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20070717100036/http://history.alliancelibrarysystem.com:80/IllinoisAlive/files/wi/htm1/wi000002.cfm &quot;Black Hawk (Ma-ka-tai-me-she-kia-kiak)&quot;], in John E. Hallwas, ed. ''Illinois Literature: The Nineteenth Century'', Macomb, IL: Illinois Heritage Press, 1986
* {{Cite Appletons'|wstitle=Black Hawk|year=1900 |short=x |notaref=x}}
* {{Cite EB1911|wstitle=Black Hawk|short=x}}
* {{findagrave|2625}}

{{Black Hawk War (1832)}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Black Hawk}}
[[Category:1767 births]]
[[Category:1838 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Rock Island, Illinois]]
[[Category:Native American leaders]]
[[Category:Native Americans in the War of 1812]]
[[Category:Native American history of Illinois]]
[[Category:Native American history of Iowa]]
[[Category:Native American history of Wisconsin]]
[[Category:People from Iowa]]
[[Category:Native Americans of the Black Hawk War]]
[[Category:People of pre-statehood Illinois]]
[[Category:People of pre-statehood Iowa]]
[[Category:People of pre-statehood Wisconsin]]
[[Category:Quad Cities]]
[[Category:Sac and Fox people]]</text>
      <sha1>ls20scusnw35gxby85kbbrfp8qm7nzt</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
