<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Book of Joshua</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4331</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745989558</id>
      <parentid>745959787</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-24T16:34:13Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>PatGallacher</username>
        <id>164032</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>rv - open to question what traditional scholarship means here</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="39221">{{about|the [[Biblical canon|canonical]] book of the [[Hebrew Bible]]|information on the [[Samaritan]] version|Book of Joshua (Samaritan)}}
{{Tanakh OT|Nevi'im|historical}}

The '''Book of Joshua''' ({{lang-he|ספר יהושע}} ''{{transl|he|Sefer Yĕhôshúa}}'') is the sixth book in the [[Hebrew Bible]] (the Christian [[Old Testament]]) and the first book of the [[Deuteronomistic history]], the story of Israel from the conquest of Canaan to the [[Babylonian exile]].{{sfn|McNutt|1999|p=42}} It tells of the campaigns of the Israelites in central, southern and northern [[Canaan]], the destruction of their enemies, and the division of the land among the twelve tribes, framed by two set-piece speeches, the first by God commanding the conquest of the land, and, at the end, the last by [[Joshua]] warning of the need for faithful observance of the Law (''[[torah]]'') revealed to [[Moses]].&lt;ref name=achb&gt;Achtemeier and Boraas&lt;/ref&gt;

Almost all scholars agree that the book of Joshua holds little historical value for early Israel and most likely reflects a much later period.&lt;ref&gt;Killebrew, pp.152&lt;/ref&gt; Although [[Rabbinic]] tradition holds that the book was written by Joshua, it is probable that it was written by multiple editors and authors far removed from the times it depicts.&lt;ref&gt;Creach, pp.9–10&lt;/ref&gt; The earliest parts of the book are possibly chapters 2–11, the story of the conquest; these chapters were later incorporated into an early form of Joshua written late in the reign of king [[Josiah]] (reigned 640–609&amp;nbsp;BCE), but the book was not completed until after the fall of [[Jerusalem]] to the [[Neo-Babylonian Empire]] in 586 BCE, and possibly not until after the return from the [[Babylonian exile]] in 539 BCE.&lt;ref&gt;Creach, pp.10–11&lt;/ref&gt;

==Contents==
[[File:Dore joshua crossing.jpg|thumb|''Joshua and the Israelites crossing the Jordan'' ([[Gustave Doré]])]]

===Structure===
I. Transfer of leadership to Joshua (1:1–18)
:A. God's commission to Joshua (1:1–9)
:B. Joshua's instructions to the people (1:10–18)
II. Entrance into and conquest of Canaan (2:1–5:15)
:A. Entry into Canaan
::1.Reconnaissance of [[Jericho]] (2:1–24)
::2. Crossing the River Jordan (3:1–17)
::3. Establishing a foothold at [[Gilgal]] (4:1–5:1)
::4. [[Circumcision]] and [[Passover]] (5:2–15)
:B. Victory over Canaan (6:1–12:24)
::1. Destruction of Jericho (6)
::2. Failure and success at [[Ai (Canaan)|Ai]] (7:1–8:29)
::3. Renewal of the covenant at [[Mount Ebal]] (8:30–35)
::4. Other campaigns in central Canaan (9:1–27)
::5. Campaigns in southern Canaan (10:1–43)
::6. Campaigns in northern Canaan (11:1–15)
::7. Summary of lands conquered (11:16-23)
::8. Summary list of defeated kings (12:1–24)
III. Division of the land among the tribes (13:1–22:34)
:A. God's instructions to Joshua (13:1–7)
:B. Tribal allotments (13:8–19:51)
::1. Eastern tribes (13:8–33)
::2. Western tribes (14:1–19:51)
:C. Cities of refuge and levitical cities (20:1–21:42)
:D. Summary of conquest (21:43–45)
:E. De-commissioning of the eastern tribes (22:1–34)
IV. Conclusion (23:1–24:33)
:A. Joshua's farewell address (23:1–16)
:B. Covenant at [[Shechem]] (24:1–28)
:C. Deaths of Joshua and [[Eleazar]]; burial of Joseph's bones (24:29–33)&lt;ref name=achb/&gt;

===Biblical narrative===

====God's commission to Joshua (chapter 1)====
&lt;!--Linked from [[Template:Tanakh OT]]--&gt;
Chapter 1 commences &quot;after the death of Moses&quot; (Joshua 1:1) and presents the first of three important moments in Joshua marked with major speeches and reflections by the main characters; here first God, and then Joshua, make speeches about the goal of conquest of the [[Promised Land]]; in chapter 12, the narrator looks back on the conquest; and in chapter 23 Joshua gives a speech about what must be done if Israel is to live in peace in the land).&lt;ref&gt;De Pury, p.49&lt;/ref&gt;

Methodist writer [[Joseph Benson]] suggests that God's revelation to Joshua comes &quot;either immediately after [Moses' death], or when the [[Shiva (Judaism)|days of mourning]] for Moses were expired&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://biblehub.com/commentaries/benson/joshua/1.htm Benson Commentary] on Joshua 1, accessed 3 August 2016&lt;/ref&gt;

God commissions Joshua to take possession of the land and warns him to keep faith with the Covenant. God's speech foreshadows the major themes of the book: the crossing of the [[Jordan River]] and conquest of the land, its distribution, and the imperative need for obedience to the Law; Joshua's own immediate obedience is seen in his speeches to the Israelite commanders and to the Transjordanian tribes, and the Transjordanians' affirmation of Joshua's leadership echoes Yahweh's assurances of victory.&lt;ref name=y175&gt;Younger, p.175&lt;/ref&gt;

====Entry into the land and conquest (chapters 2–12)====
[[File:Joshua Leading the Israelites Across the Jordan on 10th of Nisan.jpg|thumb|250px|Joshua Leading the Israelites Across the Jordan on 10th of Nisan]]
The Israelites cross the [[Jordan River]] through the miraculous intervention of [[God]] and the [[Ark of the Covenant]] and are [[Circumcision in the Bible|circumcised]] at [[Gibeath-Haaraloth]] (translated as ''hill of foreskins''), renamed [[Gilgal]] in memory (''Gilgal'' sounds like ''Gallothi'', ''I have removed'', but is more likely to translate as ''circle of standing stones''). The conquest begins in Canaan with [[battle of Jericho|Jericho]], followed by [[Ai (Canaan)|Ai]] (central Canaan), after which Joshua builds an altar to Yahweh at [[Mount Ebal]] (northern Canaan) and renews the Covenant. The covenant ceremony has elements of a divine land-grant ceremony, similar to ceremonies known from [[Mesopotamia]].&lt;ref&gt;Younger, p.180&lt;/ref&gt;

The narrative then switches to the south. The [[Gibeon (ancient city)|Gibeon]]ites trick the Israelites into entering into an alliance with them by saying they are not Canaanites; this prevents the Israelites from exterminating them, but they are enslaved instead. An alliance of [[Amorite]] kingdoms headed by the Canaanite king of [[Jerusalem]] is defeated with [[Yahweh]]'s miraculous help, and the enemy kings are hanged on trees. (The Deuteronomist author may have used the then-recent 701&amp;nbsp;BCE campaign of the [[List of Assyrian kings|Assyrian king]] [[Sennacherib]] in Judah as his model; the hanging of the captured kings is in accordance with Assyrian practice of the 8th century BCE).&lt;ref&gt;Na'aman, p.378&lt;/ref&gt;

With the south conquered the narrative moves to the northern campaign. A powerful multi-national (or more accurately, multi-ethnic) coalition headed by the king of [[Tel Hazor|Hazor]], the most important northern city, is defeated with Yahweh's help and Hazor captured and destroyed. Chapter 11:16–23 summarises the extent of the conquest: Joshua has taken the entire land, almost entirely through military victories, with only the Gibeonites agreeing to peaceful terms with Israel. Joshua 11:18 asserts that the conquest took &quot;a long time&quot; - the [[Amplified Bible]] and the [[Cambridge Bible for Schools and Colleges]] suggest this was &quot;at least five years&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://biblehub.com/commentaries/cambridge/joshua/11.htm Cambridge Bible for Schools and Colleges] on Joshua 11, accessed 4 August 2016&lt;/ref&gt; Anglican churchman [[Charles Ellicott]] thinks &quot;the war seems to have lasted seven years&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://biblehub.com/commentaries/ellicott/joshua/11.htm Ellicott's Commentary for English Readers] on Joshua 11, accessed 4 August 2016&lt;/ref&gt;

The land then &quot;had rest from war&quot; (Joshua 11:23, repeated at 14:15). Chapter 12 lists the vanquished kings on both sides of the [[Jordan]]: the two kings who ruled east of the Jordan who were defeated under Moses' leadership (Joshua 12:1-6; cf. Numbers 21), and the 31 kings on the west of the Jordan who were defeated under Joshua's leadership (Joshua 12:7-24). The list of the 31 kings is quasi-tabular:
:''the king of Jerusalem, one; the king of Hebron, one'';
:''the king of Jarmuth, one; the king of Lachish, one''; (etc.) (Joshua 12:10-11).&lt;ref&gt;The [[Jerusalem Bible]] lays out verses Joshua 12:9-24 in tabular form&lt;/ref&gt;

====Division of the land (chapters 13–22)====
[[File:1759_map_Holy_Land_and_12_Tribes.jpg|thumb|right|1759 map of the tribal allotments of Israel]]
Having described how the Israelites and Joshua have carried out the first of their God's commands, the narrative now turns to the second: to &quot;put the people in possession of the land.&quot; Joshua is &quot;old, advanced (or stricken) in years&quot; by this time (Joshua 13:1) - &quot;about ninety years of age&quot; in the Cambridge Bible for Schools and Colleges' estimation;&lt;ref&gt;[http://biblehub.com/commentaries/cambridge/joshua/13.htm Cambridge Bible for Schools and Colleges] on Joshua 13, accessed 6 August 2016&lt;/ref&gt; Joseph Benson refers to an estimate that he was 83,&lt;ref&gt;[http://biblehub.com/commentaries/benson/joshua/13.htm Benson Commentary] on Joshua 13, accessed 6 August 2016&lt;/ref&gt; but the [[Jamieson-Fausset-Brown Bible Commentary]] says that he was &quot;probably above a hundred years old&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://biblehub.com/commentaries/jfb/joshua/13.htm Jamieson-Fausset-Brown Bible Commentary] on Joshua 13, accessed 6 August 2016&lt;/ref&gt;

This land distribution is a &quot;covenantal land grant&quot;: Yahweh, as king, is issuing each [[Tribes of Israel|tribe]] its territory.&lt;ref&gt;Younger, p.183&lt;/ref&gt; The &quot;[[cities of refuge]]&quot; and [[Levitical city|Levitical cities]] are attached to the end, since it is necessary for the tribes to receive their grants before they allocate parts of it to others. The Transjordanian tribes are dismissed, affirming their loyalty to Yahweh.

The book reaffirms Moses' allocation of land east of the Jordan to the tribes of [[Tribe of Reuben|Reuben]] and [[Tribe of Gad|Gad]] and the half-tribe of [[Tribe of Manasseh|Manasseh]] (Joshua 13:8-32; cf. {{bibleverse||Numbers|32:1-42|NKJV}}), and then describes how Joshua divided the newly conquered land of [[Canaan]] into parcels, and assigned them to the tribes by [[Land Lottery|lot]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/articles/8907-joshua-book-of|title=JOSHUA, BOOK OF - JewishEncyclopedia.com|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Joshua 14:1 also makes reference to the role of [[Eleazar|Eleazar the priest]] (ahead of Joshua) in the distribution process.&lt;ref&gt;Theologian [[Carl Friedrich Keil]] suggested that he is mentioned here before Joshua because “the division by lot was presided over by the high priest as the representative of the government of the Lord in Israel&quot;; quoted in [http://biblehub.com/commentaries/cambridge/joshua/14.htm Cambridge Bible for Schools and Colleges] on Joshua 14, accessed 9 August 2016&lt;/ref&gt; The description serves a theological function to show how the [[Promised Land|promise of the land]] was realized in the biblical narrative; its origins are unclear, but the descriptions may reflect geographical relations among the places named.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author=Dorsey, David A. | title=The Roads and Highways of Ancient Israel | publisher=Johns Hopkins University Press | year=1991 | isbn=0-8018-3898-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|5}}

The wording of {{bibleverse||Joshua|18:1-4|NKJV}} suggests that the tribes of Reuben, Gad, [[Tribe of Judah|Judah]], [[Tribe of Ephraim|Ephraim]] and Manasseh received their land allocation some time before the &quot;remaining seven tribes&quot;, and a 21-member expedition set out to survey the remainder of the land with a view to organising the allocation to the tribes of [[Tribe of Simeon|Simeon]], [[Tribe of Benjamin|Benjamin]], [[Tribe of Asher|Asher]], [[Tribe of Naphtali|Naphtali]], [[Tribe of Zebulun|Zebulun]], [[Tribe of Issachar|Issachar]] and [[Tribe of Dan|Dan]]. Subsequently, 48 [[Levitical city|cities]] with their surrounding lands were allocated to the [[Tribe of Levi]] ({{bibleverse||Joshua|21:1-41|NKJV}}, cf. {{bibleverse||Numbers|35:7|NKJV}}).

Omitted in the Hebrew text, but present in the [[Septuagint]], is a statement that:
:''Joshua completed the division of the land in its boundaries, and the children gave a portion to Joshua, by the commandment of the Lord. They gave to him the city for which he asked, [[Timnath-heres|Thamnath Sarach]] gave they him in Mount Ephraim, and Joshua built the city, and dwelt in it. And Joshua took the stone knives with which he had [[Circumcision|circumcised]] the children of Israel, which were in the way in the wilderness, and he placed them in Tamnath Sarach''.&lt;ref&gt;Septuagint, after Joshua 21:42, quoted in [http://biblehub.com/commentaries/pulpit/joshua/21.htm Pulpit Commentary] on Joshua 21, accessed 23 August 2016&lt;/ref&gt;

By the end of chapter 21, the narrative records that the fulfilment of God's promise of land, rest and supremacy over the enemies of the Israelites was complete.&lt;ref&gt;Joshua 21:43-45&lt;/ref&gt; The writer of the [[Epistle to the Hebrews|Letter to the Hebrews]] makes reference to Joshua and the promise of rest in {{bibleverse||Hebrews|4:8|NKJV}}. The tribes to whom Moses had granted land east of the Jordan are authorized to return home to [[Gilead]] (here used in the widest sense for the whole trans-Jordan district),&lt;ref&gt;[http://biblehub.com/commentaries/barnes/joshua/22.htm Barnes' Notes on the Bible] on Joshua 22, accessed 24 August 2016&lt;/ref&gt; having faithfully 'kept the charge' &lt;ref&gt;Joshua 22:3, [[English Revised Version]]&lt;/ref&gt; of supporting the tribes occupying Canaan. They are granted &quot;riches ... with very much livestock, with [[silver]], with [[gold]], with [[bronze]], with iron, and with very much clothing&quot; as a reward (Joshua 22:1-9).

====Joshua's farewell speeches (chapters 23–24)====
Joshua, in his old age and conscious that he is &quot;going the way of all the earth&quot;,&lt;ref&gt;Joshua 23:14&lt;/ref&gt; gathers the leaders of the Israelites together, &quot;perhaps at Timnath-serah, or possibly at Shiloh&quot; &lt;ref&gt;[http://biblehub.com/commentaries/cambridge/joshua/23.htm Cambridge Bible for Schools and Colleges] on Joshua 23, accessed 25 August 2016&lt;/ref&gt; and reminds them of Yahweh's great works for them, and of the need to love Yahweh (Joshua 23:11). The Israelites are told - just as Joshua himself had been told &lt;ref&gt;Joshua 1:7&lt;/ref&gt; - that they must comply with &quot;all that is written in the Book of the Law of Moses&quot; (Joshua 23:6), neither &quot;turn[ing] aside from it to the right hand or to the left&quot; (i.e. by adding to the law, or diminishing from it).&lt;ref&gt;[http://biblehub.com/commentaries/poole/joshua/23.htm Matthew Poole's Commentary] on Joshua 23, accessed 25 August 2016&lt;/ref&gt;

Joshua charges the people to remain faithful to Yahweh and the covenant, warning of judgment if (or when) Israel were to leave Yahweh and [[Apostasy in Judaism|follow other gods]]. The hypothetical &quot;if&quot; is used in the [[New International Version]], [[Revised Standard Version]], [[Jerusalem Bible]] and [[Common English Bible]]; the predictive &quot;when&quot; is used in the [[Geneva Bible]], [[King James Version]] and [[New King James Version]].&lt;ref&gt;All examples taken from [[BibleGateway.com]] except Jerusalem Bible&lt;/ref&gt;

Joshua meets again with all the people at Shechem in chapter 24 and addresses them a second time. He recounts the history of God's formation of the Israelite nation, beginning with &quot;[[Terah]], the father of [[Abraham]] and [[Nahor, son of Terah|Nahor]], [who] lived beyond the [[Euphrates|Euphrates River]] and worshiped other gods&quot; ({{Bibleref2|Joshua|24:2|NIV| Joshua 24:2}}). He invited the Israelites to choose between serving the LORD who had delivered them from [[Egypt]], or the gods which their ancestors had served on the other side of the Euphrates, or the gods of the Amorites in whose land they now lived. The people chose to serve the LORD, a decision which Joshua recorded in the Book of the Law of God, and he then erected a memorial stone &quot;under the oak that was by the sanctuary of the Lord&quot; in Shechem.&lt;ref&gt;Joshua 24:1-27&lt;/ref&gt; The oak is associated with the Oak of [[Moreh]] where Abram had set up camp during his travels in this area.&lt;ref&gt;Genesis 12:6&lt;/ref&gt; Thus &quot;Joshua made a covenant with the people, literally &quot;cut a covenant&quot;, a phrase common to the Hebrew, Greek, and Latin tongues, and derived from the custom of sacrifice, in which the victims were cut in pieces and offered to the deity invoked in ratification of the engagement&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://biblehub.com/commentaries/pulpit/joshua/24.htm Pulpit Commentary] on Joshua 24, accessed 29 August 2016&lt;/ref&gt;

The people then returned to their inheritance i.e. their allocated lands (Joshua 24:28).

====Closing items====
The Book of Joshua closes with three concluding items (referred to in the Jerusalem Bible as &quot;Two Additions&quot;):&lt;ref&gt;[[Jerusalem Bible]], heading before Joshua 24:29-33&lt;/ref&gt;
:The death of Joshua and his burial at Timnath-serah (Joshua 24:29-31)
:The burial of the bones of Joseph at Shechem (Joshua 24:32)
:The death of Eleazar and his burial in land belonging to Phinehas in the mountains of Ephraim (Joshua 24:33).
There were no Levitical cities given to the descendants of [[Aaron]] in Ephraim, so theologians [[Keil and Delitzsch]] suppose the land may have been at [[Geba (city)|Geba]] in the territory of Benjamin: &quot;the situation, 'upon the mountains of Ephraim', is not at variance with this view, as these mountains extended, according to Judges 4:5, etc., far into the territory of Benjamin&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://biblehub.com/commentaries/kad/joshua/24.htm Keil and Delitzsch OT Commentary] on Joshua 24, accessed 30 August 2016&lt;/ref&gt;

In some Manuscripts and editions of the Septuagint, there is an additional verse relating to the apostasy of the Israelites after Joshua's death.

==Composition==
[[File:Prise de Jéricho.jpg|thumb|''The Taking of Jericho'' ([[Jean Fouquet]], c.1452–1460)]]

The Book of Joshua is anonymous. The [[Babylonian Talmud]], written in the 3rd to 5th centuries CE, was the first attempt to attach authors to the holy books: each book, according to the authors of the Talmud, was written by a prophet, and each prophet was an eyewitness of the events described, and [[Joshua]] himself wrote &quot;the book that bears his name&quot;. This idea was rejected as untenable by [[John Calvin]] (1509–1564), and by the time of [[Thomas Hobbes]] (1588–1679) it was recognised that the book must have been written much later than the period it depicted.&lt;ref&gt;De Pury, pp.26–30&lt;/ref&gt; There is now general agreement that Joshua was composed as part of a larger work, the [[Deuteronomistic history]], stretching from [[Deuteronomy]] to [[Books of Kings|Kings]].&lt;ref name=y174&gt;Younger, p.174&lt;/ref&gt; In 1943 the German biblical scholar [[Martin Noth]] suggested that this history was composed by a single author/editor, living in the time of the Exile (6th century BCE).&lt;ref&gt;Klein, p.317&lt;/ref&gt; A major modification to Noth's theory was made in 1973 by the American scholar [[Frank M. Cross]], to the effect that two editions of the history could be distinguished, the first and more important from the court of king [[Josiah]] in the late 7th century BCE, and the second Noth's 6th century BCE Exilic history.&lt;ref&gt;De Pury, p.63&lt;/ref&gt; Later scholars have detected more authors or editors than either Noth or Cross allowed for.&lt;ref&gt;Knoppers, p.6&lt;/ref&gt;

==Themes and genre==
[[File:JoshuaSun Martin.jpg|thumb|''Joshua Commanding the Sun to Stand Still upon Gideon'' ([[John Martin (painter)|John Martin]])]]

===Historical and archaeological evidence===
{{see also|History of ancient Israel and Judah}}
The prevailing scholarly view is that Joshua is not a factual account of historical events.&lt;ref name=mcc4&gt;McConville (2010), p.4&lt;/ref&gt; The apparent setting of Joshua is the 13th century BCE;&lt;ref name=mcc4/&gt; this was a time of widespread city-destruction, but with a few exceptions ([[Tel Hazor|Hazor]], [[Tel Lachish|Lachish]]) the destroyed cities are not the ones the Bible associates with Joshua, and the ones it does associate with him show little or no sign of even being occupied at the time.&lt;ref&gt;Miller&amp;Hayes, pp. 71–2.&lt;/ref&gt;

Given its lack of historicity, Carolyn Pressler, in her 2002 commentary for the ''Westminster Bible Companion'' series, suggests that readers of Joshua should give priority to its theological message (&quot;what passages teach about God&quot;) and be aware of what these would have meant to audiences in the 7th and 6th centuries BCE.&lt;ref&gt;Pressler, pp.5–6&lt;/ref&gt; [[Richard D. Nelson|Richard Nelson]] explains: The needs of the centralised monarchy favoured a single story of origins combining old traditions of an [[the Exodus|exodus from Egypt]], belief in a national god as &quot;divine warrior,&quot; and explanations for ruined cities, social stratification and ethnic groups, and contemporary tribes.&lt;ref&gt;Nelson, p.5&lt;/ref&gt;

===Themes===
The overarching theological theme of the Deuteronomistic history is faithfulness and God's mercy (and their opposites, faithlessness and God's wrath). In Judges, [[Samuel]], and Kings, [[Israel]] becomes faithless and God ultimately shows his anger by sending his people into exile,&lt;ref&gt;Laffer, p.337&lt;/ref&gt; but in Joshua Israel is obedient, Joshua is faithful, and God fulfills his promise and gives them the land.&lt;ref&gt;Pressler, pp.3–4&lt;/ref&gt; Yahweh's war campaign in [[Canaan]] validates Israel's entitlement to the land&lt;ref&gt;McConville (2001), pp.158–159&lt;/ref&gt; and provides a paradigm of how [[Israel]] was to live there: twelve tribes, with a designated leader, united by [[covenant (historical)|covenant]] in warfare and in worship of Yahweh alone at single sanctuary, all in obedience to the commands of [[Moses]] as found in [[Deuteronomy]].&lt;ref&gt;Coogan 2009, p. 162.&lt;/ref&gt;

====God and Israel====

Joshua takes forward [[Deuteronomy]]'s theme of Israel as a single people worshiping Yahweh in the land God has given them.&lt;ref&gt;McConville (2001), p.159&lt;/ref&gt; Yahweh, as the main character in the book, takes the initiative in conquering the land, and it is Yahweh's power that wins battles (for example, the walls of [[Jericho]] fall because Yahweh is fighting for Israel, not because the Israelites show superior fighting ability).&lt;ref&gt;Creach, pp.7–8&lt;/ref&gt; The potential disunity of Israel is a constant theme, the greatest threat of disunity coming from the tribes east of the Jordan, and there is even a hint in chapter 22:19 that the land across the Jordan is unclean and the tribes who live there are of secondary status.&lt;ref&gt;Creach, p.9&lt;/ref&gt;

====Land====
Land is the central topic of Joshua.&lt;ref&gt;McConville (2010), p.11&lt;/ref&gt; The introduction to Deuteronomy recalled how Yahweh had given the land to the Israelites but then withdrew the gift when Israel showed fear and only Joshua and [[Caleb]] had trusted in God.&lt;ref&gt;Miller (Patrick), p.33&lt;/ref&gt; The land is Yahweh's to give or withhold, and the fact that he has promised it to Israel gives Israel an inalienable right to take it. For exilic and post-exilic readers, the land was both the sign of Yahweh's faithfulness and Israel's unfaithfulness, as well as the centre of their ethnic identity. In Deuteronomistic theology, &quot;rest&quot; meant Israel's unthreatened possession of the land, the achievement of which began with the conquests of Joshua.&lt;ref&gt;Nelson, pp.15–16&lt;/ref&gt;

====The enemy====
Joshua &quot;carries out a systematic campaign against the civilians of Canaan&amp;nbsp;— men, women and children&amp;nbsp;— that amounts to [[genocide]].&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Dever, p.38&lt;/ref&gt; In doing this he is carrying out ''[[herem (war or property)|herem]]'' as commanded by Yahweh in Deuteronomy 20:17: &quot;You shall not leave alive anything that breathes&quot;. The purpose is to drive out and dispossess the Canaanites, with the implication that there are to be no treaties with the enemy, no mercy, and no intermarriage.&lt;ref name=y175/&gt; &quot;The extermination of the nations glorifies Yahweh as a warrior and promotes Israel's claim to the land,&quot; while their continued survival &quot;explores the themes of disobedience and penalty and looks forward to the story told in Judges and Kings.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Nelson, pp.18–19&lt;/ref&gt; The divine call for massacre at [[Battle of Jericho|Jericho]] and elsewhere can be explained in terms of cultural norms (Israel wasn't the only [[Iron Age]] state to practice ''herem'') and theology (a measure to ensure Israel's purity as well as the fulfillment of God's promise),&lt;ref name=y175/&gt; but Patrick D. Miller in his commentary on Deuteronomy remarks, &quot;there is no real way to make such reports palatable to the hearts and minds of contemporary readers and believers.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Miller (Patrick), pp.40–41&lt;/ref&gt;

====Obedience====
Obedience vs. disobedience is a constant theme.&lt;ref&gt;Curtis, p.79&lt;/ref&gt; Obedience ties in the Jordan crossing, the defeat of Jericho and [[Ai (Bible)|Ai]], circumcision and Passover, and the public display and reading of the Law. Disobedience appears in the story of [[Achan (Bible)|Achan]] (stoned for violating the ''herem'' command), the [[Gibeonites]], and the altar built by the Transjordan tribes. Joshua's two final addresses challenge the Israel of the future (the readers of the story) to obey the most important command of all, to worship Yahweh and no other gods. Joshua thus illustrates the central Deuteronomistic message, that obedience leads to success and disobedience to ruin.&lt;ref&gt;Nelson, p.20&lt;/ref&gt;

===Moses, Joshua and Josiah===
The Deuteronomistic history draws parallels in proper leadership between [[Moses]], Joshua and [[Josiah]].&lt;ref&gt;Nelson, p.102&lt;/ref&gt; God's commission to Joshua in chapter 1 is framed as a royal installation, the people's pledge of loyalty to Joshua as successor Moses recalls royal practices, the covenant-renewal ceremony led by Joshua was the prerogative of the kings of Judah, and God's command to Joshua to meditate on the &quot;book of the law&quot; day and night parallels the description of Josiah in 2 Kings 23:25 as a king uniquely concerned with the study of the law&amp;nbsp;— not to mention their identical territorial goals (Josiah died in 609&amp;nbsp;BCE while attempting to annex the former Israel to his own kingdom of Judah).&lt;ref&gt;Finkelstein, p.95&lt;/ref&gt;

Some of the parallels with Moses can be seen in the following, and not exhaustive, list:&lt;ref name=y174/&gt;
*Joshua sent spies to scout out the land near Jericho (2:1), just as Moses sent spies from the wilderness to scout out the [[Promised Land]] (Num. 13; Deut. 1:19–25).
*Joshua led the Israelites out of the wilderness into the Promised Land, crossing the Jordan River as if on dry ground (3:16), just as Moses led the Israelites out of Egypt through the Red Sea, which they crossed as if on dry land (Ex. 14:22).
*After crossing the [[Jordan River]], the Israelites celebrated the Passover (5:10–12) just as they did immediately before [[the Exodus]] (Exodus 12).
*Joshua's vision of the &quot;commander of Yahweh's army&quot; (5:13–15) is reminiscent of the divine revelation to Moses in the burning bush (Ex. 3:1–6).
*Joshua successfully intercedes on behalf of the Israelites when Yahweh is angry for their failure to fully observe the &quot;ban&quot; ([[herem (war or property)|herem]]), just as Moses frequently persuaded God not to punish the people (Ex. 32:11–14, Num. 11:2, 14:13–19).
*Joshua and the Israelites were able to defeat the people at Ai because Joshua followed the divine instruction to extend his sword (Josh 8:18), just as the people were able to defeat the Amalekites as long as Moses extended his hand that held &quot;the staff of God&quot; (Ex. 17:8–13).
*Joshua is &quot;old, advanced in years (13:1) at the time when the Israelites can begin to settle on the promised land, just as Moses was old when he died having seen, but not entered, the promised land (Deuteronomy 34:7)
*Joshua served as the mediator of the renewed covenant between Yahweh and Israel at Shechem (8:30–35; 24), just as Moses was the mediator of Yahweh's covenant with the people at [[Mount Sinai]]/[[Mount Horeb]].
*Before his death, Joshua delivered a farewell address to the Israelites (23–24), just as Moses had delivered his farewell address (Deuteronomy 32–33).
*Moses lived to be 120 (Deuteronomy 34:7) and Joshua lived to be 110 (Joshua 24:29).

== See also ==
* ''[[The Bible Unearthed]]''
* &quot;[[The Bible's Buried Secrets]]&quot;
* [[Ed (biblical reference)]]
* [[Transjordan (Bible)]]

==References==

===Citations===
{{reflist|3}}

===Bibliography===

*{{Cite book|last=Creach|first=Jerome F.D|title=Joshua|publisher=Westminster John Knox Press|year=2003|url=https://books.google.com/?id=1V6ca8r3DssC&amp;pg=PR11&amp;dq=Joshua#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|isbn=9780664237387}}
*{{Cite book|last=Curtis|first=Adrian H.W|title=Joshua|publisher=Sheffield Academic Press|year=1998|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=6pCu7R5ubdwC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Joshua#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|isbn=9781850757061}}
* Harstad, Adolph L. (2002). ''Joshua'' (in series, ''Concordia Commentary''). Arch Books. ISBN 978-0-570-06319-3.
*{{Cite book|last1=McConville|first1=Gordon|last2=Williams|first2=Stephen|title=Joshua|publisher=Eerdmans|year=2010|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=U_8LhXUU6NQC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Joshua#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|isbn=9780802827029}}
*{{Cite book|last=McConville|first=Gordon|chapter=Joshua|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3surkLVdw3UC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=The+Oxford+Bible+commentary#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|editor=John Barton |editor2=John Muddiman|title=Oxford Bible Commentary|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=2001|isbn=9780198755005}}
*{{Cite book|last=Miller|first=Patrick D|title=Deuteronomy|publisher=Cambridge University Press|year=1990|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=-yoFvN_QOjYC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Deuteronomy+Patrick+D.+Miller#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|isbn=9780664237370}}
*{{Cite book|last=Nelson|first=Richard D|title=Joshua|publisher=Westminster John Knox Press|year=1997|url=https://books.google.com/?id=Iwfg_zQHRR4C&amp;pg=PR5#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|isbn=9780664226664}}
*{{Cite book|last=Pressler|first=Carolyn|title=Joshua, Judges and Ruth|publisher=Westminster John Knox Press|year=2002|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=7W4-RjlzWy4C&amp;pg=PA1&amp;lpg=PA1&amp;dq=Joshua,+Judges,+and+Ruth+Carolyn+Pressler#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|isbn=9780664255268}}
*{{Cite book|last=Younger|first=K. Lawson Jr|chapter=Joshua|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=2Vo-11umIZQC&amp;pg=PA174&amp;lpg=PA174&amp;dq=Joshua+K+Lawson+Younger#v=onepage&amp;q=Joshua%20K%20Lawson%20Younger&amp;f=false
|editor=James D. G. Dunn |editor2=John William Rogerson|title=Eerdmans Commentary on the Bible|publisher=Eerdmans|year=2003|isbn=9780802837110}}

*{{Cite book|last1=Achtemeier|first1=Paul J|last2=Boraas|first2=Roger S|title=The HarperCollins Bible Dictionary|publisher=HarperSanFrancisco|year=1996}}
*{{Cite book|last=Bright|first=John|title=A History of Israel|publisher=Westminster John Knox Press|year=2000|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=0VG67yLs-LAC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Bright+History+of+Israel#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|isbn=9780664220686}}
*{{Cite book|last=Campbell|first=Anthony F|chapter=Martin Noth and the Deuteronomistic History|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3gnxJjuqld0C&amp;pg=PA178&amp;dq=The+history+of+Israel%27s+traditions:+the+heritage+of+Martin+Noth+Thomas+Romer+The+Book+of+Deuteronomy#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|editor=Steven L. McKenzie |editor2=Matt Patrick Graham|title=The history of Israel's traditions: the heritage of Martin Noth|publisher=Sheffield Academic Press|year=1994|isbn=9780567230355}}
*{{Cite book|last1=Campbell|first1=Anthony F|last2=O'Brien|first2=Mark|title=Unfolding the Deuteronomistic history: origins, upgrades, present text|publisher=Fortress Press|year=2000|url=https://books.google.com/?id=AvZWPFqd2sEC&amp;pg=PP3#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|isbn=9781451413687}}
*{{Cite book|last=Coogan|first=Michael D.|title=A Brief Introduction to the Old Testament|publisher=Oxford University Press|year=2009|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=nlb1PQAACAAJ&amp;dq=A+brief+introduction+to+the+old+testament+coogan}}
*{{Cite book|last=Day|first=John|title=Yahweh and the Gods and Goddesses of Canaan|publisher=Sheffield Academic Press|year=2002|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=y-gfwlltlRwC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Yahweh+and+the+gods+and+goddesses+of+Canaan#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|isbn=9780826468307}}
*{{Cite book|last1=De Pury|first1=Albert|last2=Romer|first2=Thomas|chapter=Deuteronomistic Historiography (DH): History of Research and Debated Issues|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=rex7ASbY_bkC&amp;pg=PA5&amp;dq=Isra%C3%ABl+constructs+its+history:+Deuteronomistic+historiography+in+recent+research#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|editor=Albert de Pury |editor2=Thomas Romer |editor3=Jean-Daniel Macchi|title=Israël constructs its history: Deuteronomistic historiography in recent research|publisher=Sheffield Academic Press|year=2000|isbn=9780567224156}}
*{{Cite book|last=Dever|first=William|title=Who Were the Early Israelites and Where Did They Come From?|publisher=Eerdmans|year=2003|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=8WkbUkKeqcoC&amp;dq=Who+were+the+early+Israelites,+and+where+did+they+come+from%3F&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false|isbn=9780802809759}}
*{{Cite book|last1=Finkelstein|first1=Israel|last2=Silberman|first2=Neil Asher|title=The Bible Unearthed|publisher=Free Press|year=2001|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=lu6ywyJr0CMC&amp;pg=PA95&amp;lpg=PA95&amp;dq=parallels+between+Joshua+and+Josiah#v=onepage&amp;q=parallels%20between%20Joshua%20and%20Josiah&amp;f=false|isbn=9780743223386}}
*{{Cite book|last=Killebrew|first=Ann E.|title=Biblical Peoples and Ethnicity: An Archaeological Study of Egyptians, Canaanites, and Early Israel, 1300–1100 B.C.E.|publisher=Society of Biblical Literature|year=2005|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=VtAmmwapfVAC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Biblical+peoples+and+ethnicity:+an+archaeological#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|isbn=9781589830974}}
*{{Cite book|last=Klein|first=R.W.|chapter=Samuel, books of|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=6OJvO2jMCr8C&amp;pg=PA314&amp;lpg=PA314&amp;dq=narrative+sources+books+of+samuel#v=onepage&amp;q=narrative%20sources%20books%20of%20samuel&amp;f=false|editor=Bromiley, Geoffrey W|title=The international standard Bible encyclopedia|publisher=Eerdmans|year=2003|isbn=9780802837844}}
*{{Cite book|last=Knoppers|first=Gary|chapter=Introduction|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=CoHhPAKgETkC&amp;dq=Reconsidering&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|editor=Gary N. Knoppers |editor2=J. Gordon McConville|title=Reconsidering Israel and Judah: recent studies on the Deuteronomistic history|publisher=Eisenbrauns|year=2000|isbn=9781575060378}}
*{{Cite book|last=Laffey|first=Alice L|chapter=Deuteronomistic history|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=k85JKr1OXcQC&amp;pg=PA337&amp;lpg=PA337&amp;dq=The+account+of+the+history+of+the+people+of+Israel+Laffey#v=onepage&amp;q=The%20account%20of%20the%20history%20of%20the%20people%20of%20Israel%20Laffey&amp;f=false|editor=Orlando O. Espín |editor2=James B. Nickoloff|title=An introductory dictionary of theology and religious studies|publisher=Liturgical Press|year=2007|isbn=9780814658567}}
*{{Cite book|last=McNutt|first=Paula|title=Reconstructing the Society of Ancient Israel|publisher=Westminster John Knox Press|year=1999|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=hd28MdGNyTYC&amp;pg=PA33&amp;lpg=PA33&amp;dq=Reconstructing+the+Society+of+Ancient+Israel++By+Paula+M.+McNutt#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false|isbn=9780664222659}}
*{{Cite book|last=Miller|first=James Maxwell|last2=Hayes|first2=John Haralson|title=A History of Ancient Israel and Judah|publisher=Westminster John Knox Press|year=1986|isbn=0-664-21262-X|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=uDijjc_D5P0C&amp;dq=A+history+of+ancient+Israel+and+Judah++By+James+Maxwell+Miller,+John+Haralson+Hayes&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q=&amp;f=false}}
*{{Cite book|last=Naʾaman|first=Nadav|title=Ancient Israel and Its Neighbors: Collected Essays: Volume 2|publisher=Eisenbrauns|year=2005|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=HmTOoQmf23AC&amp;pg=PA378&amp;lpg=PA378&amp;dq=#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|isbn=9781575061139}}
*{{Cite book|last=Van Seters|first=John|chapter=The Deuteronomist from Joshua to Samuel|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=CoHhPAKgETkC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Reconsidering+Israel+and+Judah:+recent+studies+on+the+Deuteronomistic+history#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|editor=Gary N. Knoppers |editor2=J. Gordon McConville|title=Reconsidering Israel and Judah: Recent Studies on the Deuteronomistic History|publisher=Eisenbrauns|year=2000|isbn=9781575060378}}

==Tribal allotments of Israel: Books and maps==
* {{cite book | author=Abu-Sitta, Salman H. | title=Atlas of Palestine, 1948 | url=http://www.plands.org/atlas/index.htm |publisher=Palestine Land Society | year=2004}}
* {{cite book | author=Aharoni, Yohanan | title=The Land of the Bible; A Historical Geography | publisher=The Westminster Press | year=1979 | isbn=0-664-24266-9}}
* {{cite book | author=Campbell, E., Jr. | title=Shechem II | publisher=ASOR | year=1991 | isbn=0-89757-062-6}}
* {{cite book | author=Dever, William G. | title=Who Were the Early Israelites and Where Did They Come From? | publisher=Wm. B. Eerdmans | year=2003 | isbn=0-8028-0975-8}}
* {{cite book | author=Finkelstein, I. and Z. Lederman (eds.)| title=Highlands of Many Cultures: The Southern Samaria Survey  | publisher=Tel Aviv University Institute of Archaeology | year=1997 | isbn=965-440-007-3}}
* {{cite book | author=Curtis, Adrian | title=Oxford Bible Atlas, Fourth Edition | publisher=Oxford University Press| year=2009 | isbn= 9780199560462}}
* {{cite book | author=Kallai, Zecharia | title=Historical Geography of the Bible; The Tribal Territories of Israel | publisher=The Magnes Press, The Hebrew University | year=1986 | isbn=965-223-631-4}}
* {{cite book | author=Miller, Robert D., II, | title=Chieftains Of The Highland Clans: A History Of Israel In The Twelfth And Eleventh Centuries B.C. | publisher=Wm. B. Eerdmans | year=2005 | isbn=0-8028-0988-X}}
* {{cite book | author=Na'aman, Nadav | title=Borders and Districts in Biblical Historiography | publisher=Simor, Ltd. | year=1986 | isbn=965-242-005-0}}

==External links==
{{wikisource|Joshua (Bible)}}
{{commons category}}

*Hebrew text:
**[http://www.mgketer.org/mikra/6/1/1 Joshua - Mikraot Gedolot Haketer - online edition], [[Menachem Cohen (scholar)|Menachem Cohen]], Bar Ilan University (Hebrew)
*Hebrew and English text:
**[http://www.mechon-mamre.org/p/pt/pt0601.htm יְהוֹשֻׁעַ ''Yehoshua''–Joshua] ([[Hebrew language|Hebrew]]–English at Mechon-Mamre.org, Jewish Publication Society translation)
*[[Judaism|Jewish]] translations:
**[http://www.chabad.org/article.asp?AID=15749 Joshua (Judaica Press)] translation with [[Rashi]]'s commentary at chabad.org
*[[Christian]] translations
**[http://www.gospelhall.org/bible/bible.php?passage=Joshua+1 ''Online Bible'' at GospelHall.org]
**[[s:EN:Bible, King James, Joshua|Joshua at Wikisource]] (Authorised King James Version)
** {{librivox book | dtitle=Joshua | stitle=Bible Joshua}} Various versions

{{s-start}}
{{s-hou | [[Nevi'im|Prophets]]|||}}
{{s-bef | before= [[Book of Deuteronomy|Deuteronomy]] | rows = 2 }}
{{s-ttl | title = [[Tanakh|Hebrew Bible]] }}
{{s-aft | after = [[Book of Judges|Judges]] | rows= 2 }}
{{s-ttl | title = [[Christianity|Christian]]&lt;br&gt;[[Old Testament]] }}
{{s-end}}
{{Books of the Bible}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Joshua, Book Of}}
[[Category:7th-century BC books]]
[[Category:6th-century BC books]]
[[Category:Book of Joshua| ]]
[[Category:Nevi'im]]
[[Category:Protocanonical books]]</text>
      <sha1>rmkwty60aamuq7k9uxibtv6l8jope36</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
