<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Bramble-class gunboat (1898)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>43226054</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748262310</id>
      <parentid>748013060</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-07T08:09:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 3 sources and tagging 0 as dead. #IABot (v1.2.6)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16928">{{about|the Royal Navy gunboat class of 1898|the identically named Royal Navy gunboat class of 1886|Bramble-class gunboat (1886)}}
{|{{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
|Ship image=[[File:HMS Thistle, 1st Class Gunboat at the China Station 1910 - 1912 Q114767.jpg|300px]]
|Ship caption=HMS ''Thistle'', c.1910.
}}
{{Infobox ship class overview
| Name                     = ''Bramble'' class
| Builders                 =*[[W.H. Potter &amp; Sons]]
*[[London and Glasgow Shipbuilding Company|London &amp; Glasgow]]
| Operators                = {{navy|UK}}
| Class before             = [[Redbreast-class gunboat|''Redbreast'' class (1889)]]
| Class after              = n/a - designation abolished
| Subclasses               = 
| Built range              = 1898 - 1899
| In commission range      = 1900 - 1925
| Total ships building     = 
| Total ships planned      = 
| Total ships completed    = 4
| Total ships cancelled    = 
| Total ships active       = 
| Total ships laid up      = 
| Total ships lost         = 
| Total ships retired      = 
| Total ships scrapped     = 
| Total ships preserved    = 
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
|Hide header=
|Header caption=
|Ship class=
|Ship type=First class gunboat
|Ship displacement=710&amp;nbsp;tons standard
|Ship tons burthen=
|Ship length={{convert|180|ft|m|abbr=on}}
|Ship beam={{convert|33|ft|m|abbr=on}}
|Ship height=
|Ship draught={{convert|8|ft|m|abbr=on}}
|Ship depth=
|Ship hold depth=
|Ship power={{convert|1300|ihp|lk=in|abbr=on}}
|Ship propulsion=*Triple-expansion steam engine
*Twin screw
|Ship speed={{convert|13.5|kn|km/h|abbr=on}}
|Ship range=*2050 nm at 10.85 kn (HMS ''Bramble'')
*2000 nm at 11.5 kn (HMS ''Thistle'')
|Ship endurance=
|Ship boats=*1 × 27' [[Whaleboat|whaler]]
*1 × 25' [[Cutter (boat)|cutter]]
*1 × 16' [[skiff]] or [[dinghy]]
*1 × 23' steam cutter
|Ship crew=85
|Ship armament=*2 × [[QF 4 inch naval gun Mk I – III|4-inch]] [[British ordnance terms#QF|QF]]
*4 × [[QF 12-pounder 12 cwt naval gun|12pdr]] [[British ordnance terms#QF|QF]]
*4 × 0.45 inch [[Maxim gun]]
|Ship armour=
|Ship notes=
}}
|}

The '''''Bramble''-class gunboat''' was a type of warship used by the [[Royal Navy]] between the 1890s and the 1920s. The four ships of this class were notable as the final development of the Victorian [[gunboat]] tradition, and for being one of the last classes of warship designed to travel under sail. One of them, [[HMS Thistle (1899)|HMS ''Thistle'']], retained a functional sailing rig into the mid-1920s.

==Design==
The four ''Bramble''-class gunboats were designed to protect the far-flung outposts of Great Britain's [[colonial empire]]. At 180 feet long and 33 feet in beam, with a draft of just 8 feet and a displacement of only 710 tons, they were the smallest seagoing vessels built for the Royal Navy in the 1890s. They were also among the cheapest, built at a cost of just over £50,000 each, less than 5% of the cost of a contemporary [[battleship]].

===Limited steaming range and the continuing need for sails===
The small dimensions and shallow draught of the ''Bramble'' class were designed to facilitate navigation on the complex coastlines and great rivers of Africa, South Asia and the Far East. The drawback this imposed was a limited fuel supply. The type entered service with a standard bunkerage of just 50 tons of coal. For ''Thistle'', considered one of the better-performing ships of the class, this would only provide two and a half days' movement at her sustained cruising speed of 11.5 knots, and full-speed runs used nearly twice the quantity of coal over any given length of time. In practice, storage was found for 145 tons of coal, but this was still sufficient for only one week of cruising.

The ''Bramble'' class were therefore designed with a sailing rig to supplement their engines. This was still widely accepted in the 1890s as a necessity for long-range warships, which would not always have reliable access to [[fuelling station|coaling stations]]. Modern ships which retained a full sailing rig in the 1890s included the Russian armoured cruiser ''[[Russian cruiser Rurik (1892)|Rurik]]'', the six German [[Bussard-class cruiser|''Bussard''-class light cruisers]], the United States Navy's [[USS Annapolis (PG-10)|''Annapolis''-class gunboats]], and the Royal Navy's own [[Condor-class sloop|''Condor''-class]] and [[Cadmus-class sloop|''Cadmus''-class]] sloops.

However, the use of sails was not universally accepted: the armoured [[battleship]]s of the [[great power]]s had become so large and heavy that they had abandoned the remnants of sailing rig in the mid-1880s, and modernizers argued that any sailing warship was automatically obsolete.

Whereas most cruisers of the 1890s adopted a three-masted [[barque]] or [[barquentine]] rig combining a strong emphasis on [[Fore-and-aft rig|fore-and-aft]] sails with a partial [[square rig]], the ''Bramble'' class differed by being designed as two-masted ships, and in 1911, the authoritative partnership of [[Philip Watts (naval architect)|Sir Philip Watts]] and [[John Harper Narbeth]] noted that they only used a &quot;reduced&quot; fore-and-aft sailplan. Thus rigged, they somewhat resembled the much larger contemporary Royal Navy [[protected cruiser]]s such as the [[Astraea-class cruiser|''Astrea'' class]] and [[Eclipse-class cruiser|''Eclipse'' class]], which had two &quot;military masts&quot;, principally used for [[Flag signals|signal halyards]], [[Crow's nest|lookout positions]] and [[Top (sailing ship)#Fighting top|fighting tops]], but designed to set auxiliary fore-and-aft sails in an emergency. On the other hand, HMS ''Thistle'' used some square sails, and there appears to be no [[Wikipedia:Identifying reliable sources|clear evidence]] what their designed sailplan was (an original [[brig]] or [[brigantine]] sailplan like the earlier [[HMS Temeraire (1876)|HMS ''Temeraire'']] cannot be ruled out).

===Other features===
In order to further reduce the logistical requirements (and construction costs) of the new gunboats, a number of other decisions were taken which seemed almost willfully anachronistic. They had [[copper sheathing]] to protect their hulls against fouling in tropical seas. With minimal machinery, old-fashioned human strength on the [[Capstan (nautical)|capstan]] was required to raise the [[anchor]]s, and a functional [[ship's wheel]] was provided to turn the [[rudder]]. All lighting came from [[candle]]s rather than [[light bulb]]s. Only one of the four [[ship's boat]]s was equipped with an engine, the rest being powered by sails and oars. Some of the guns were even mounted internally behind [[gunport]]s.

In some important respects, however the gunboats were thoroughly up-to-date. Their armament of two [[QF 4 inch naval gun Mk I – III|4-inch guns]], four [[QF 12-pounder 12 cwt naval gun|12-pounders]] and four or more heavy-calibre [[Maxim gun]]s was modern, and the firepower it provided was comparable to that of comparable ships from rival navies, such as the German gunboat [[SMS Panther|SMS ''Panther'']]. Each ship's triple-expansion steam engine was capable of 13.5 knots, only slightly slower than contemporary [[battleship]]s and [[cruiser]]s, and their hulls were built of steel, exploiting metallurgical advances of the 1880s, rather than using older wrought iron or [[Composite ship|composite]] construction techniques.

In layout, the gunboats were also modern, resembling a miniature version of contemporary [[protected cruiser]]s, with a straight [[Stem (ship)|stem]], high [[forecastle]], taller [[pilothouse|charthouse]], and a long low [[deckhouse]] extending aft to an even lower [[quarterdeck]]. This was a distinct contrast with the sloops of the ''Condor'' and ''Cadmus'' classes, which resembled contemporary sailing [[windjammer]]s with a [[bowsprit]] and [[figurehead]], a high [[Freeboard (nautical)|freeboard]], and a raised [[poop deck]] aft.

Internally, the class also adopted the defining characteristic of the protected cruiser, positioning the coal bunkers to act as a form of armour around the vital spaces. The parallel was also expressed in other ways, as U.S. Navy observers noted that the quality of the fittings, both mechanical and domestic, was comparable throughout to that of a large cruiser: the crew cabins were all generously [[Panelling|wood-panelled]] and comfortably [[air-conditioning|air-conditioned]], features that were rationalized with the claim that they would protect the crew from the heat of a metal hull under tropical skies. There was even an [[icemaker]].

===Later modifications===
Almost at the moment that the ships entered service, high-level opinion in the Royal Navy swung decisively against the use of sail-power (and indeed against gunboats in principle). The sails were packed away, and gradually the apparatus of rigging and spars was physically discarded. During World War I, the ships retained only their immobile lower masts, and in some cases the fore topmast to support a radio antenna.

The loss of sailing capabilities made long-range deployment problematic, as the gunboats now had to travel with extra coal supply heaped on their open decks, and their engines struggled to propel them on sustained ocean-crossing voyages. HMS ''Thistle'' eventually reverted to a practical sailing rig in 1919, but adopted a progressively simplified arrangement, going from a [[brig]] to a [[ketch]] and finally becoming a sort of [[Cutter (boat)|cutter]].

In the 1920s, the two surviving ships of the type were re-armed. They retained their two 4-inch guns, but exchanged their 12-pounders and Maxims for an anti-aircraft armament of two [[Ordnance QF 3-pounder Vickers|Vickers 3-pounders]] and two [[QF 2-pounder naval gun|2-pounder pom-poms]]. Four [[QF 3-pounder Hotchkiss|Hotchkiss 3-pounders]] were also carried as saluting guns.

===Japanese derivatives===
The [[Imperial Japanese Navy]] adapted the design of the ''Bramble'' class as the model for two gunboats of its own, though both ships differed in many detail from their British model, as well as from each other. The [[Japanese gunboat Uji (1903)|''Uji'']] was launched in 1903, and her plans were further modified for [[Japanese gunboat Saga|''Saga'']] in 1912.

==Service history==
Two of the gunboats were laid down at the [[W.H. Potter &amp; Sons]] shipyard in [[Liverpool]] on 1 December 1897, while the other two were begun the next day by [[London and Glasgow Shipbuilding Company|London &amp; Glasgow]] in [[Govan]].  The Liverpool ships were launched as HMS ''Bramble'' (26 November 1898) and HMS ''Britomart'' (29 March 1899), while their counterparts in Glasgow were named HMS ''Dwarf'' (15 November 1898) and HMS ''Thistle'' (22 June 1899). These names had all been borne by distinguished precursors among the small warships of the Royal Navy. Logs of all four vessels can be found online at http://www.naval-history.net/.

===HMS ''Dwarf'' in West Africa, 1899–1925===
HMS ''Dwarf'' was the first ship of the class to enter service, being commissioned on 31 August 1899. She spent her entire active career around the western and southern coasts of Africa, covering a vast and varied zone from [[Gibraltar]] to the [[Limpopo River]]. During her career she participated in the [[Boer War]] of 1899–1902, where she was one of the first British ships equipped with [[radio]], and in 1914, she played a prominent role in a [[Naval operations of the Kamerun Campaign|successful Allied naval campaign]] against [[German West Africa]], defeating the armed steamer ''Nachtigal'' in a ship-to-ship engagement.

In the later stages of her career, HMS ''Dwarf'' appears to have spent periods in reserve at [[Gibraltar]] and may have only been put into commission when a ship with her shallow-draught capabilities was specifically needed. She was eventually paid off around 1925, and sold for scrap the next year.

===''Bramble'' and ''Britomart'', 1900–1920===
HMS ''Bramble'' and HMS ''Britomart'' were commissioned simultaneously on 28 June 1900, and dispatched together for the [[China Station]]. They would remain there for the majority of their careers, although between 1906 and 1915, evidence suggests that they only spent limited periods at sea.

''Bramble'' and ''Britomart'' were put back in commission in late 1915, and moved to the [[Indian Ocean]]. They subsequently alternated between long deployments in the [[Persian Gulf]] in support of the [[Mesopotamian campaign]], and periods of refit in [[Mumbai|Bombay]].

HMS ''Bramble'' was paid off on 5 October 1919, and sold for scrap in January 1920. ''Britomart'' is sometimes said to have shared her fate, as she had shared her career, but in fact she remained in service for a few months longer, and she was eventually sold on to a civilian owner on 6 October 1920, and modified to serve as a merchant ship, retaining her old name. In 1925, her name was changed to ''Shakuntala''  ([[Shakuntala]] in the ''[[Mahabharata]]'', like [[The Faerie Queene#List of major characters|Britomart]] in ''[[The Faerie Queene]]'', is a heroine characterized by chaste loyalty to a true love who is unaware of her identity). Sources state that the former gunboat was eventually scrapped in 1926.

===HMS ''Thistle'', 1901–1925===
{{main|HMS Thistle (1899)}}
The ''Thistle'' had the most diverse career of all the ''Bramble''-class gunboats. In varied pre-war duties in [[West Africa]] and on the [[Yangtze]], she played a role in the introduction of [[association football|football]] in [[Nigeria]], and single-handedly attempted to contain the unrest in [[Hankou]] which precipitated the [[Xinhai Revolution|1912 Revolution]].

In 1915, ''Thistle'' was dispatched across the [[Indian Ocean]] to participate in the [[East African Campaign (World War I)|East Africa Campaign]]. She arrived too late to assist in the destruction of [[SMS Königsberg (1905)|SMS ''Königsberg'']], but she played a successful role in the amphibious landings in [[German East Africa]] and the defense of [[Portuguese Mozambique]].

In 1919, the ''Thistle'' was ordered back around [[Cape Horn]] to West Africa, but not before her new commanding officer had restored her sailing rig in order to compensate for her damaged engines. Even after her machinery was repaired, the ''Thistle'' subsequently retained her sails to supplement her propulsion. She finally arrived back in England for decommissioning in 1925, after an absence of over twenty years in distant waters. By this time, she was the last remaining sailing warship of the Royal Navy.

==Sources==
* &quot;Thistle&quot;, ''Journal of the American Society of Naval Engineers'', 11 (1899), p.&amp;nbsp;1106 [https://archive.org/stream/journalamerican05engigoog#page/n1228/mode/2up]
* U.S. Office of Naval Intelligence, ''Notes on Naval Progress, November 1899'' (ONI General Information Series, No. XVIII; Washington, 1899) [https://archive.org/stream/generalinformati3539unit#page/84/mode/2up]
* U.S. Office of Naval Intelligence, ''Notes on Naval Progress, July 1900'' (ONI General Information Series, No. XVIII; Washington, 1900) [https://archive.org/stream/generalinformati3540unit#page/40/mode/2up]
* T.A. Brassey, ed. ''[[Brassey's Naval Annual|The Naval Annual, 1902]]'' (Portsmouth, 1902) [https://archive.org/stream/brasseysnavala1902brasuoft#page/n5/mode/2up]
* [[Philip Watts (naval architect)|Sir Philip Watts]] with [[John Harper Narbeth|J.H. Narbeth]], &quot;Ship&quot;, [[Encyclopædia Britannica Eleventh Edition|''Encyclopædia Britannica'', 11th ed.]] (1911), vol. xxiv, p. 914 [https://archive.org/stream/encyclopaediabri24chisrich#page/914/mode/2up]
* Antony Preston and John Major, ''Send a Gunboat: The Victorian Navy And Supremacy At Sea, 1854–1904'' (London 1967, 2007) [https://books.google.com/books?id=80KN6I__JPYC&amp;pg=PA120]
* Log books of HMS ''Bramble'': [http://www.naval-history.net/OWShips-WW1-19-HMS_Bramble.htm March 1914 to December 1817], [https://web.archive.org/web/20140708074832/http://naval-history.net/OWShips-WW1-19-HMS_Bramble2.htm  January 1918 to October 1919]
* Log books of HMS ''Britomart'': [http://www.naval-history.net/OWShips-WW1-19-HMS_Britomart.htm January 1917 to March 1920]
* Log books of HMS ''Dwarf'': [http://www.naval-history.net/OWShips-WW1-19-HMS_Dwarf.htm July 1914 to February 1916], [https://web.archive.org/web/20140707172701/http://naval-history.net/OWShips-WW1-19-HMS_Dwarf2.htm September 1920 to September 1923]
* Log books of HMS ''Thistle'': [https://web.archive.org/web/20140326220322/http://naval-history.net/OWShips-WW1-19-HMS_Thistle1.htm March 1914 to December 1916], [http://www.naval-history.net/OWShips-WW1-19-HMS_Thistle2.htm January 1917 to December 1919], [http://www.naval-history.net/OWShips-WW1-19-HMS_Thistle3.htm January 1920 to July 1924]

[[Category:Gunboat classes]]
[[Category:Bramble-class gunboats (1898)]]
[[Category:Victorian-era gunboats of the United Kingdom| Bramble (1898)]]
[[Category:1898 ships]]</text>
      <sha1>hahxphy4odhw8tf44r28b2nl0abjz3b</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
