<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Brodie helmet</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>602022</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749294696</id>
      <parentid>745886831</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-13T15:58:43Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2601:46:C802:1E1F:EDF0:C168:67BE:14CA</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>fix initially the United States purchased 40,000 British Mark I helmets to 400,000</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="21865">{{for|the 1951 film by Samuel Fuller|The Steel Helmet}}
[[File:M1917helmet.jpg|thumb|300px|M1917 helmet worn by members of the [[5th Marine Regiment (United States)|U.S. 5th Marine Regiment]].]]
The '''Brodie helmet''' is a [[steel]] [[combat helmet]] designed and patented in London in 1915 by John Leopold Brodie. In modified form it became the '''Helmet, steel, Mark I''' in Britain and the '''M1917 Helmet''' in the U.S. Colloquially, it was called the '''shrapnel helmet''', '''Tommy helmet''', '''tin hat''', and in the United States the '''doughboy helmet'''. Worn by Australians during WW2 and sometimes known as '''Panic Hat'''.  It was also known as the dishpan hat, tin pan hat, washbasin, battle bowler (when worn by officers), and Kelly helmet. The US version, the M1917, was copied from the British Mk 1 steel helmet of 1916. The German Army called it the ''Salatschüssel'' (salad bowl).&lt;ref name=&quot;Helmet M-1917&quot;&gt;{{cite book |chapterurl=http://www.worldwar1.com/dbc/helmet17.htm |chapter=The M-1917 Helmet |title=U.S. Combat Helmets of the 20th Century |first=Mark A. |last=Reynosa  |location=Atglen, PA |publisher=Schiffer Publ. |year=1997 |isbn=9780764303579 |accessdate=30 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The term ''Brodie'' is often mis-used. It is correctly applied only to the original 1915 ''Brodie's Steel Helmet, War Office Pattern'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://thebrodiehelmet.weebly.com/war-office-pattern.html |title=Brodie's Steel Helmet, War Office Pattern |work=The Brodie Helmet and its derivatives |year=2015 |accessdate=30 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 
==Background==
[[File:Ilwarnews brodie.jpg|thumb|''[[The Illustrated War News]]''—17 November 1915&lt;br/&gt;The caption reads: &lt;br&gt;Head-wounds have been more than usually numerous during the war, owing to the trench-fighting, and more than usually severe, owing to the extensive use of shrapnel. But the danger, although it cannot be avoided, can be minimised. Our Army has now followed the French by adopting steel helmets, calculated to stop shell-splinters and shrapnel. Even in cases of extreme risk, not only has death been avoided, but injuries have been confined to bruises or superficial wounds. Cases have occurred in which the wearers have been hit, but saved by these helmets from what without them would have meant certain death. The fur coats, as they did last year, mean mitigation of the rigours of winter. The French helmets are known as &quot;Adrians,&quot; after their inventor. (Photo by Illustrations Harrow).]]

At the outbreak of [[World War I]], none of the combatants provided steel helmets to their troops. Soldiers of most nations went into battle wearing cloth, felt, or leather headgear that offered no protection from modern weapons.

The huge number of lethal head wounds that modern artillery weapons inflicted upon the [[French Army]] led them to introduce the first modern steel helmets in the summer of 1915.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.militarytrader.com/military-trader-news/the_first_modern_steel_combat_helmet_the_french_adrian |title=The first modern steel combat helmet: the French 'Adrian' |first=Peter |last=Suciu |work=Military Trader |date=2 February 2009 |accessdate=30 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://militaryheadgear.com/countries/91-Croatia/garments/115-Infantry-Helmets |title=Infantry Helmets |work=Military Headgears |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110714094102/http://www.militaryheadgear.com/countries/91-Croatia/garments/115-Infantry-Helmets |archivedate=July 14, 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The first French helmets were bowl-shaped steel &quot;skullcaps&quot; worn under the cloth caps. These rudimentary helmets were soon replaced by the Model 1915 [[Adrian helmet]], designed by August-Louis Adrian.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://salg71.free.fr/index.html |title=Heaumes Page |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20061130020747/http://salg71.free.fr/index.html |archivedate=November 30, 2006 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The idea was later adopted by most other combatant nations.

==Origins==
At about the same time, the British [[War Office]] had seen a similar need for steel helmets. The War Office Invention Department was ordered to evaluate the French design. They decided that it was not strong enough and too complex to be swiftly manufactured. British industry was not geared up to an all-out effort of war production in the early days of World War I, which also led to the [[Shell Crisis of 1915|shell shortage of 1915]].

John Leopold Brodie (1873-1945), born Leopold Janno Braude&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= |title=Oxford Biography Index entry - John Brodie |last1= |first1= |last2= |first2= |date= |website=http://www.oxforddnb.com/index/109/101109198/ |publisher=Oxford University Press |access-date=10 August 2016 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt; in [[Riga]], was an entrepreneur and inventor who had made a fortune in the gold and diamond mines of [[South Africa]], but was working in London at that time.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.buffalohistorygazette.net/2010/11/brodie-hat.html |title=Brodie's &quot;Tin Hat&quot; |last1= |first1= |last2= |first2= |date=1 November 2010 |website=www.buffalohistorygazette.net |publisher=The Buffalo History Gazette |access-date=10 August 2016 |quote=}}&lt;/ref&gt; A design patented by him in August 1915 offered advantages over the French helmet. It was constructed in one piece that could be pressed from a single thick sheet of steel, giving it added strength and making it simple to manufacture. Brodie's patent deals mainly with the innovative lining arrangements; an engineer called Alfred Bates of the firm of Willis &amp; Bates of [[Halifax, West Yorkshire|Halifax, Yorkshire]], a manufacturer of [[Vapalux|metal lamps]], claimed that he was asked by the War Office to find a method of manufacturing an anti-shrapnel helmet and that it was he who had devised the basic shape of the steel shell. Aside from some newspaper articles, there is nothing to substantiate Bates's claim.&lt;ref&gt;Liddle, Dr Peter (2016), [https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=xAWkDAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA182&amp;dq=%22John+Leopold+Brodie%22&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjbtdfh77nOAhXLDcAKHZm_AW44ChDoAQgbMAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22John%20Leopold%20Brodie%22&amp;f=false ''Britain and a Widening War, 1915-1916: From Gallipoli to the Somme''], Pen &amp; Sword Military, ISBN 978-1-47386-717-8 (p. 182)&lt;/ref&gt;

Brodie's design resembled the medieval infantry [[kettle hat|kettle hat or ''chapel-de-fer'']], unlike the German ''[[Stahlhelm]]'', which resembled the medieval [[sallet]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Edwards|first1=Nina|title=Dressed for war : uniform, civilian clothing and trappings, 1914 - 1918|date=2013|publisher=Tauris|location=London|isbn=9781780767079|page=26}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Brodie had a shallow circular crown with a wide brim around the edge, a leather liner and a leather chinstrap. The helmet's &quot;soup bowl&quot; shape was designed to protect the wearer's head and shoulders from [[shrapnel shell]] projectiles bursting from above the trenches. The design allowed the use of relatively thick steel that could be formed in a single pressing while maintaining the helmet's thickness. This made it more resistant to projectiles but it offered less protection to the lower head and neck than other helmets.

The original design (Type A) was made of [[Carbon steel|mild steel]] with a brim {{convert|1.5|–|2|in|mm}} wide. The Type A was in production for just a few weeks before the specification was changed and the Type B was introduced in October 1915. The specification was altered at the suggestion of Sir [[Robert Hadfield]] to a harder steel with 12% [[manganese]] content, which became known as &quot;[[Hadfield steel]]&quot;, which was virtually impervious to shrapnel hitting from above.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Dunstan |first1=Simon |first2=Ron |last2=Volstad |title=Flak Jackets: 20th Century Military Body Armour |publisher=Osprey Publishing |year=1984 |location=London |page=5 |isbn=0-85045-569-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ballistically this increased protection for the wearer by 10 per cent. It could withstand a .45 caliber pistol bullet traveling at {{convert|600|ft|m}} per second fired at a distance of {{convert|10|ft|m}}.&lt;ref name=&quot;Index CEF Helmets&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.kaisersbunker.com/cef/helmets/ |title=Canadian Expeditionary Force Steel Helmets |work=kaisersbunker.com |year=2006 |accessdate=30 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; It also had a narrower brim and a more domed crown.

[[File:NorthLancsRegShowingNewHelmets1916.jpg|thumb|The [[Loyal Regiment (North Lancashire)|Loyal North Lancashire Regiment]] showing off their new Brodie helmets (1916).]]
The original paint scheme, suggested by Brodie, was a mottled light green, blue, and orange camouflage but they were also painted in green or blue-grey.&lt;ref name=bull&gt;{{cite book |last1=Bull |first1=Stephen |first2=Adam |last2=Hook |title=World War I Trench Warfare (1): 1914–16 |publisher=Osprey Publishing |year=2002 |location=Oxford; New York |pages=10–11 |isbn=1-84176-197-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; That same month the first delivery of the helmets was made to [[British Army]] troops. Initially, there were far from enough helmets to equip every man, so they were designated as &quot;trench stores&quot;, to be kept in the front line and used by each unit that occupied the sector. It was not until the summer of 1916, when the first one million helmets had been produced, that they could be generally issued.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Sheffield |first1=Gary |title=War on the Western Front: In the Trenches of World War I |publisher=Osprey Publishing |year=2007 |location=Oxford; New York |page=227 |isbn=1-84603-210-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Brodie helmet reduced casualties but was criticized by General [[Herbert Plumer, 1st Viscount Plumer|Herbert Plumer]] on the grounds that it was too shallow and too light-reflective, its rim was too sharp, and its lining was too slippery. These criticisms were addressed in the Mark I model helmet of 1916, which had a separate folded rim, a two-part liner and matte [[khaki]] paint finished with sand, sawdust, or crushed cork to give a dull, non-reflective appearance.&lt;ref name=bull/&gt; In 1917, the liner was modified to include a [[rubber]] cushion to make it more comfortable, although this was not adopted for the M1917. Towards the end of the war, helmets were often painted with unit insignia. These are often called &quot;parade helmets&quot; by collectors.

The weight of a Mark I helmet was approximately {{convert|1.3|lb|kg}}.

==Service==
It was first used in battle in April 1916 at the [[Sint-Elooi|Battle of St Eloi]]. Troops from other countries also used the Brodie helmet, including the [[Military of the United States|United States Armed Forces]], when they began to deploy in France late in 1917. The [[government of the United States|United States government]] initially purchased some 400,000 helmets from Britain. From January 1918 the [[United States Army|U.S. Army]] began to use helmets manufactured in the U.S. and these helmets were designated M1917.&lt;ref name=&quot;Helmet M-1917&quot;/&gt; The steel helmet was known to the troops as a &quot;tin hat&quot;, or, for the officers, a &quot;battle bowler&quot; (from [[bowler hat]]).

By the end of the war some 7.5 million Brodie helmets had been produced, including 1.5 million M1917 helmets, for use by American forces.

===Current safety concerns===
In May 2014, the UK's [[Health and Safety Executive]], in consultation with the [[Imperial War Museum]], advised that World War I-era helmets were not safe to handle, owing to the likelihood of them containing [[asbestos#Health problems|asbestos]]. It advised that schools should not allow pupils to handle such artefacts, but should instead ensure that the objects were either safely disposed of, have the asbestos removed from the object or safely display the object.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/education-27391955 |date=14 May 2014 |title=Wartime helmets and gas masks 'dangerous', schools told |publisher=[[BBC News]] |first=Judith |last=Burns |accessdate=30 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Post World War I==
[[File:Infantryman in 1942 with M1 Garand, Fort Knox, KY.jpg|thumb|U.S. Army Infantryman in 1942 wearing Brodie helmet]]
From 1936, the Mark I Brodie helmet was fitted with an improved liner and an elasticated (actually, sprung) [[webbing]] chin strap. This final variant served until late 1940, when it was superseded by the slightly modified Mk II, which served the British and [[Commonwealth of Nations|Commonwealth]] forces throughout World War II. Several Commonwealth nations, such as [[Australia]], [[New Zealand]], [[Canada]] and [[South Africa]], produced local versions of the MK II, which can be distinguished from those made in Britain. During this period, the helmet was also used by the [[British Police|police]], the [[fire brigade]] and [[Air Raid Precautions|ARP]] wardens in [[United Kingdom|Britain]]. The helmets for the ARP wardens came in two principal variants, black with a white &quot;W&quot; for wardens and white with a black &quot;W&quot; for Chief Wardens; however numerous different patterns were used.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.military-history.org/wp-content/uploads/2011/01/London-Blitz-Civil-Defence-Helmets.jpg |title=London Blitz Civil Defence Helmets |work=military-history.org |year=2014 |accessdate=30 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; A civilian pattern was also available for private purchase, known as the [[Zuckerman helmet]], which was a little deeper but made from ordinary mild steel.

In 1944, the British replaced it with a significantly modified design, known as the [[Mk III helmet|Mk III &quot;Turtle&quot; helmet]].

The U.S. Army used the basic Brodie-patterned M1917 helmet until 1942 with some modifications, which included a totally new liner and canvas chin strap. It was finally superseded by the [[M1 Helmet]] in 1942 and passed down to civil defense.

The helmet was the inspiration for the name of the [[Memorable Order of Tin Hats]] (or the MOTH), a brotherhood of ex-front-line soldiers founded in 1927 by [[Charles Evenden]].

==Variants==
===United Kingdom===
*'''Brodie's Steel Helmet, War Office Pattern, Type A''': the original 1915 helmet with the shell made from magnetic mild steel.
*'''Brodie's Steel Helmet, Type B''': with the shell made from Hadfield (manganese) steel.
*'''Helmet, Steel, Mark I''': introduced in Spring, 1916, a modified version of the Brodie helmet with a wholly redesigned liner and a mild steel rim to the shell. In 1917, a rubber ring or &quot;doughnut&quot; was added between the liner and the top of the shell, and in 1935, the liner and chinstrap were modified to make them removable.
*'''Helmet, Steel, Mark I*''': introduced in 1938 and made up from old Mark I shells, but fitted with an all new liner and chinstrap. This was the standard British Army helmet at the start of the Second World War.
[[File:British_helmet.JPG|thumb|right|A British helmet dating from the Second World War, probably a Mark II. The grey finish suggests that it was issued to one of the civil defence services.]] 
*'''Helmet, Steel, Mark II''': also introduced in 1938, the Mark II featured a new shell with a non-magnetic rim (so that the wearer could use a [[magnetic compass]]) and the new liner and chinstrap used in the Mark I*. Early production went to the ARP services, the fire brigade and the police. It was re-designated in July 1940 as the '''Helmet, Steel, Mark II, No 1''' and in the following year, as the '''Helmet, Steel, No 1, Mark 1'''. 
*'''Helmet, Steel, Mark II, No 2''': by July 1940, it had been realised that demand for the Mark II helmet could not be met, and so helmets which had either been rejected as substandard, or had been newly manufactured from cheaper mild steel, began to be issued under the designation &quot;Mark II, No 2&quot; to the Home Guard and civilian services. These helmets were marked with between one and four small holes drilled into the rim, showing the level of protection that they would provide. This type of helmet was re-designated in 1941 as the '''Helmet, Steel, No 2, Mark 1'''.&lt;ref&gt;Brayley, Martin J (2008), ''Tin Hats to Composite Helmets: A Collector's Guide'', Crowood Press, ISBN 978-1-84797-024-4 (pp. 58-60)&lt;/ref&gt; 
*'''Helmet, Steel, Civilian''', '''Civilain Protective Helmet''' or '''[[Zuckerman helmet]]''': when it was found that a large number of civilians were needed to keep a lookout for fires started by [[incendiary bomb]]s, an even cheaper mass-produced helmet was required. Designed by a team led by government adviser [[Solly Zuckerman]], the thin mild steel helmet was broadly similar in shape to the military pattern but had a taller crown to the shell, providing space for the helmet to crumple. The simple liner was attached to the shell by a boot lace or string passed through holes in the shell. It was made available to civilian fire watchers at a cost of five [[Shilling (British coin)|shilling]]s and [[Sixpence (British coin)|sixpence]] (27½ [[new pence]]) each, starting in December 1940.
*'''Commercial helmets''': in 1939, a number of British companies began to manufacture helmets for sale to concerned civilians. These usually had the appearance of Brodie-style helmets, but were generally made of cheap materials such as alloys, leather, resin-impregnated fibre or even [[Bakelite]] (an early form of plastic), and offered little protection to the wearer.&lt;ref&gt;Brayley, pp. 66-67&lt;/ref&gt;

===Belgium===
*'''M1949''': a post-war Belgian-made copy of the Mark II helmet. The shell was identical to the British original, except that the liner fixing screw on the crown sat in a small indentation. The liner was of Belgian design and the chinstrap was copied from the British Mark III helmet.&lt;ref&gt;Brayley, pp. 19-20&lt;/ref&gt;

===Canada===
[[File:Canadian troops in England, 1942.jpg|thumb|right|Canadian troops wearing Mark II helmets; England, 1942.]]
*'''Helmet, Steel, Mark II''': having purchased British helmets in the First World War and at the outbreak of the Second, Canadian helmet production commenced in 1940. The helmets were identical to the British original, except that the rubber &quot;bumper&quot; pads in the lining were only fitted to horizontal helmet band and not to the vertical bands. The Mark II continued in front-line service with Canadian forces until March 1960.&lt;ref&gt;Brayley, pp. 25-26&lt;/ref&gt;

===Portugal===
*'''M1916''': on Portugal's entry into the First World War in 1916, the country lacked the facilities to produce its own helmets and looked to the United Kingdom. British helmet production at that time was giving priority to their own forces, however the Director of Munitions Supply was able to source a commercially produced version of the Brodie helmet, originally intended to be sold to British officers at the time when helmets were in short supply. Given the Portuguese designation &quot;M1916&quot;, it equipped the [[Portuguese Expeditionary Corps]]. Made of thin-gauge steel, the bowl was fluted in an attempt to add strength. Unfortunately, the fluting actually increased the chances of penetration if a missile hit one of the ridges, so some M1916s were produced with a plain bowl. A simple liner was laced to the shell through a series of holes.  
*'''M1917''': the Portuguese designation for the Mark I helmet, which was supplied as soon as the British production facilities became available. 
*'''M1917/30''': in 1930, the M1917 helmets were refurbished with a redesigned leather liner.&lt;ref&gt;Brayley, pp. 93-94&lt;/ref&gt;

===United States===
*'''M1917''': initially the United States purchased 400,000 British Mark I helmets to equip the [[American Expeditionary Force]] in 1917, and those units which were to integrate with French formations were provided with ''Adrian'' helmets. The first US made copies of the Mark I were supplied before the end of 1917 and some 2,700,000 had been made by the end of the war. The M1917 differed little from the British original; different rivets were used to secure the liner, the wire loop onto which the chinstrap was fixed was thicker and the rubber &quot;doughnut&quot; pad was not adopted. However, the US manufacturers were able to produce a shell with better ballistic protection than the original.
*'''M1917A1''': a redesigned liner and a new webbing chinstrap were approved for service in 1934. This model went into full production in 1941, when 904,020 were produced.
*'''M1917 Civil Defense Helmet''': this helmet was produced to equip the [[United_States_civil_defense#World_War_II|Civil Defense Corps]] at the start of the war, and differed from the standard helmet in having a simplified liner and thin webbing chinstrap.&lt;ref&gt;Brayley, pp. 112-113&lt;/ref&gt;

==Present day==
Brodie helmets are still being used, most notably until recently, by the [[Israel]]i [[Civil Guard (Israel)|civil defence]] forces.

Some [[LARP|live-action role players]] use Brodie helmets as substitute Medieval ''[[kettle hat|chapel de fer]]''. The Brodie helmet resembles its Medieval original enough to be an acceptable substitute.

==See also==
* [[Tommy Atkins]]
* [[Doughboy]]
* [[Kettle hat]]
* [[Zuckerman helmet]]

==References==
{{Research help|Mil}}
{{reflist|2}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|Brodie helmets}}
* {{cite web |url= http://helm.at.ua/ |title=стальной шлем |trans_title=Steel helmet |work=helm.at.ua |year=2015 |language=Russian}}
* {{cite web |url= http://world-war-helmets.com/country.php?q=angleterre |title=Angleterre |work=World War Helmets: Référence de casques de 1915 à nos jours... |year=2015 |language=French}}

{{helmets}}
{{US Army uniforms}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Brodie Helmet}}
[[Category:1910s fashion]]
[[Category:1920s fashion]]
[[Category:1930s fashion]]
[[Category:1940s fashion]]
[[Category:British Army equipment]]
[[Category:Canadian military uniforms]]
[[Category:Combat helmets of Canada]]
[[Category:Combat helmets of the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Combat helmets of the United States]]
[[Category:Military equipment of World War I]]
[[Category:Military equipment of World War II]]</text>
      <sha1>gfdhtx519zombse2t14efqe2wxyfxss</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
