<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Castra</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>678701</id>
    <revision>
      <id>747650637</id>
      <parentid>747351439</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-03T15:45:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Laurel Lodged</username>
        <id>11628060</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>removed [[Category:Ancient Roman forts]] using [[WP:HC|HotCat]] is not a place</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="47436">{{about|the Latin term|the star system|Epsilon Capricorni}}
{{italic title}}
[[File:Templeborough Roman Fort visualised 3D flythrough - Rotherham.webm|thumb|Templeborough Roman Fort visualised 3D flythrough, produced for  Rotherham Museums and Archives.]]
{{RomanMilitary}}
In the [[Roman Empire]], the [[Latin]] word '''castrum'''&lt;ref&gt;A nominative plural noun of neuter gender. According to Lewis &amp; Short, dictionary item linked in External links, General, either the singular or plural was used, castra with a possible meaning of &quot;tents.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt; (plural '''castra''') was a building, or plot of land, used as a fortified military camp.

''Castrum'' was the term used for different sizes of camps including a large [[Roman legion|legionary]] fortress, smaller ''[[Auxilia|auxiliary]]'' forts, temporary encampments and &quot;marching&quot; forts. The diminutive form ''[[castellum]]'' was used for fortlets, typically occupied by a detachment of a ''[[Cohort (military unit)|cohort]]'' or a ''[[centuria|century]]''.&lt;ref&gt;See Vegetius, ''Epitoma rei militaris'', 3.8.&lt;/ref&gt; 

In [[English language|English]], the terms &quot;Roman fortress&quot;, &quot;Roman fort&quot; and &quot;Roman camp&quot; are commonly used for ''castrum''. However, scholastic convention tends toward the use of the word &quot;camp&quot;, &quot;marching camp&quot; and &quot;fortress&quot; as a translation of ''castrum''.&lt;ref&gt;D. B. Campbell, ''Roman Auxiliary Forts 27 BC-AD 378'', Oxford 2009, page 4, with a discussion about the typologies of Roman fortifications.&lt;/ref&gt;

For a list of known castra see ''[[List of castra]]''.

==Etymology==
This term appears in three [[Italic languages]]: [[Oscan language|Oscan]], [[Umbrian language|Umbrian]] and Latin.&lt;ref&gt;According to [[Julius Pokorny]], ''Indogermanisches Etymologisches Wörterbuch'', p. 586 under ''kes''- (palatal &quot;k&quot;), Oscan ''castrous'' ([[genitive case]]) and Umbrian ''castruo'', ''kastruvuf'' ([[nominative case]]) have the same original meaning as ''castrum'', which was an estate, or tract of land. Not enough is known of Oscan and Umbrian culture to understand whether the [[word]] was a military reservation in their cultures, allowing the possibility that the Romans took their military practices partially or wholly from elsewhere or developed them, or some combination&lt;/ref&gt; In Latin ''castrum'' was probably originally the term for an estate or a tract of land enclosed by a fence or a wooden or stone wall of some kind, as seems to be used in a few passages in [[Cornelius Nepos]]' works.&lt;ref&gt;See Cornelius Nepos, ''Alcibiades'', 9.3.&lt;/ref&gt;

Considering that the earliest military shelters were [[tent]]s made of hide or cloth, and all but the most permanent bases housed the men in barracks of tents placed in quadrangles and separated by numbered streets, a ''castrum'' may originally have been a tent.&lt;ref&gt;Lewis &amp; Short under External links, General, as well as many uncited Latin dictionaries, make this suggestion.&lt;/ref&gt; 

The commonest Latin syntagmata for the term ''castra'' are:
* ''castra stativa'': permanent camp/fortresses
* ''castra aestiva'': summer camp/fortresses
* ''castra hiberna'': winter camp/fortresses
* ''castra navalia'' or ''castra nautica'': navy camp/fortresses

In Latin the term ''castrum'' is much more frequently used as a proper name for geographical locations: e.g. Castrum Album, Castrum [[Inuus|Inui]], Castrum Novum, Castrum Truentinum, Castrum Vergium. The plural was also used as a place name, as Castra Cornelia, and from this come the Welsh place name prefix &quot;Caer&quot; and English suffixes &quot;Caster&quot; and &quot;Chester&quot;; e.g. Winchester, Lancaster.

''Castrorum Filius'' was one of names used by the emperor [[Caligula]] and then also by other emperors.

&quot;[[Castro (surname)|Castro]]&quot;, also derived from &quot;Castrum&quot;, is a common [[Spanish naming customs|Spanish family name]] as well as toponym in [[Italy]], the [[Balkans]] and [[Spain]] and other [[Hispanophone]] countries, either by itself or in various compounds such as the [[World Heritage Site]] of [[Gjirokastër]] (earlier ''Argurokastro'').

The terms '''''[[Towns of ancient Greece#Military settlements|stratopedon]]''''' (&quot;army camp&quot;) and '''''[[Towns of ancient Greece#Military settlements|phrourion]]''''' (&quot;[[fortification]]&quot;) were used by [[Greek language]] authors to translate ''castrum'' and ''castellum'', respectively.

==Description==
[[File:Castra1.png|thumb|right|195px|Basic ideal plan of a Roman ''castrum''. (1) Principia; (2) Via Praetoria; (3) Via Principalis; (4) Porta Principalis Dextra; (5) Porta Praetoria (main gate); (6) Porta Principalis Sinistra; (7)Porta Decumana (back gate).]]
A ''castrum'' was designed to house and protect the soldiers, their equipment and supplies when they were not fighting or marching. 

This most detailed description that survives about Roman military camps is ''[[De Munitionibus Castrorum]]'', a manuscript of 11 pages that dates most probably from the late 1st to early 2nd century AD.&lt;ref&gt;https://www.academia.edu/865462/A_Camp_in_search_of_a_Campaign_The_reality_of_Hyginus_Roman_army&lt;/ref&gt;

Regulations required a major unit in the field to retire to a properly constructed camp every day. &quot;...as soon as they have marched into an enemy's land, they do not begin to fight until they have walled their camp about; nor is the fence they raise rashly made, or uneven; nor do they all abide ill it, nor do those that are in it take their places at random; but if it happens that the ground is uneven, it is first levelled: their camp is also four-square by measure, and carpenters are ready, in great numbers, with their tools, to erect their buildings for them.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Flavius Josephus: ''The Jewish War''. III.5.1, trans. William Whiston.&lt;/ref&gt; To this end a marching column ported the equipment needed to build and stock the camp in a baggage train of wagons and on the backs of the soldiers.

Camps were the responsibility of engineering units to which specialists of many types belonged, officered by ''architecti'', &quot;chief engineers&quot;, who requisitioned manual labor from the soldiers at large as required. They could throw up a camp under enemy attack in as little as a few hours. Judging from the names, they probably used a repertory of camp plans, selecting the one appropriate to the length of time a legion would spend in it: ''tertia castra'', ''quarta castra'', etc., &quot;a camp of three days&quot;, &quot;four days&quot;, etc.&lt;ref&gt;Ramsay's classic article, linked under External links, General, below, covers types of camps and camps in general. This Wikipedia article is heavily indebted but not exclusively to it.&lt;/ref&gt;

More permanent camps were ''castra stativa'', &quot;standing camps&quot;. The least permanent of these were ''castra aestiva'' or ''aestivalia'', &quot;summer camps&quot;, in which the soldiers were housed ''sub pellibus'' or ''sub tentoriis'', &quot;under tents&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;See Rebecca H. Jones 2012 ''Roman camps in Britain'', Amberley Press, Stroud.&lt;/ref&gt; Summer was the campaign season. For the winter the soldiers retired to ''castra hiberna'' containing barracks and other buildings of more solid materials, with timber construction gradually being replaced by stone.&lt;ref&gt;see W.S. Hanson 2009 Building the forts and frontiers, in W.S. Hanson (ed) ''The army and frontiers of Rome. Papers offered to David Breeze on the occasion of his sixty-fifth birthday and his retirement from Historic Scotland'', JRA Supplementary Series 74, Portsmouth, Rhode Island, 33-43.&lt;/ref&gt;

The camp allowed the Romans to keep a rested and supplied army in the field. Neither the Celtic nor Germanic armies had this capability: they found it necessary to disperse after only a few days.

The largest castra were ''[[List of Roman legions|legionary fortresses]]'' built as bases for one or more whole legions.&lt;ref&gt;Roman Legionary Fortresses 27BC-378AD, D.B.Campbell, Osprey.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;M. C. Bishop, Handbook to Roman Legionary Fortresses, Pen &amp; Sword, Hbk 208 pp ISBN 9781848841383&lt;/ref&gt;

From the time of [[Augustus]] more permanent castra with wooden or stone buildings and walls were introduced as the distant and hard-won boundaries of the expanding empire required permanent garrisons to control local and external threats from war-like tribes. Previously, legions were raised for specific military campaigns and subsequently disbanded, requiring only temporary castra. From then on many castra of various sizes were established many of which became permanent settlements.

==Plan of forts==
[[File:Kastell Theilenhofen Iciniacum (English).png|thumb|Plan of a typical Roman fort.]]
[[File:Arbeia Roman Fort reconstructed gateway.jpg|thumb|right|Reconstructed gateway of a ''Castrum Stativum''. Note the battlements, the Roman arches, the ''turres''.]]

[[File:Wp12 77 Rekonstruktion.jpg|thumb|left|Reconstruction of the ''specula'' or ''vigilarium'' (Germanic ''[[burgus]]''), &quot;watchtower&quot;, a type of ''castrum'', of [[Fectio]]. An ancient watchtower would have been surrounded by wall and ditch.&lt;ref&gt;See Hanson and Friel (1995) under External links, Forts and fortifications, below.&lt;/ref&gt;]]

===Sources and origins===
From the most ancient times Roman camps were constructed according to a certain ideal pattern, formally described in two main sources, the ''[[De Munitionibus Castrorum]]'' and the works of [[Polybius]].&lt;ref&gt;Book VI Section 19 ''The Roman Military System'' pages 313-368 in Thayer's Loeb's Polybius under Primary sources below..&lt;/ref&gt; P. Fl. Vegetius Renatus has a small section on entrenched camps as well. The terminology varies but the basic plan is the same.&lt;ref&gt;An extensive lexicon at the ''Romans in Britain'' site, linked under External links, General, below, matches military terms of all periods of ancient Rome to English equivalents.&lt;/ref&gt; The hypothesis of an [[Etruscan civilization|Etruscan origin]] is a viable alternative.&lt;ref&gt;Bell (2001) linked in External links, General, favors the view that the Greeks either influenced the Romans directly in the choice of the quadrangular plan or influenced the Etruscans, who influenced the Romans. The Greek theory certainly does not exclude an Indo-European origin.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Layout===
[[File:Porta Praetoria Kastell Pfünz.jpg|thumb|The reconstructed ''porta praetoria'' of the castle Pfünz, [[Germany]], near the Raetian Limes.]]

The ideal enforced a linear plan for a camp or fort: a square for camps to contain one legion or smaller unit, a rectangle for two legions, each legion being placed back-to-back with headquarters next to each other. Laying it out was a geometric exercise conducted by experienced officers called ''metatores'', who used graduated measuring rods called ''decempedae'' (&quot;10-footers&quot;) and ''gromatici'' who used a [[Groma surveying|groma]], a sighting device consisting of a vertical staff with horizontal cross pieces and vertical plumb-lines. Ideally the process started in the centre of the planned camp at the site of the headquarters tent or building (principia). Streets and other features were marked with coloured pennants or rods.

The street plans of various present-day cities still retain traces of a Roman camp, for example [[Marsala]] in Sicily, the ancient Lilybaeum, where the name of the main street, the Cassaro, perpetuates the name &quot;castrum&quot;.

===Wall and ditch===
[[File:Masada Roman Ruins by David Shankbone.jpg|thumb|right|Castrum at [[Masada]]. Note the classical &quot;playing-card&quot; layout.]]
The Castrum's special structure also defended from attacks.

The base (''munimentum'', &quot;fortification&quot;) was placed entirely within the ''[[vallum]]'' (&quot;wall&quot;), which could be constructed under the protection of the legion in battle formation if necessary. The ''vallum'' was quadrangular aligned on the cardinal points of the compass. The construction crews dug a trench (''fossa''), throwing the excavated material inward, to be formed into the rampart (''agger''). On top of this a palisade of stakes (''[[Sudis (stake)|sudes]]'' or ''valli'') was erected. The soldiers had to carry these stakes on the march.&lt;ref&gt;Smith (1875) under External links, Forts and fortifications. The ''sudes'' were not just simple stakes. Three or four branches were left on for interlocking.&lt;/ref&gt; Over the course of time, the palisade might be replaced by a fine brick or stone wall, and the ditch serve also as a moat. A legion-sized camp always placed towers at intervals along the wall with positions between for the division artillery.

===Interval===
Around the inside periphery of the ''vallum'' was a clear space, the ''intervallum'', which served to catch enemy missiles, as an access route to the ''vallum'' and as a storage space for cattle (''capita'') and plunder (''praeda''). Legionaries were quartered in a peripheral zone inside the ''intervallum'', which they could rapidly cross to take up position on the ''vallum''. Inside of the legionary quarters was a peripheral road, the ''Via Sagularis'', probably a type of &quot;service road&quot;, as the ''[[sagum]]'', a kind of cloak, was the garment of soldiers.

===Streets, gates and central plaza===
&lt;!-- &quot;Dibsi Faraj&quot; links here --&gt;
[[File:Ostkastell Welzheim.jpg|thumb|right|Reconstructed east gate of a ''Castrum Stativum'', a more permanent base.]]
[[File:Susa PortaSavoia.jpg|thumb|left|Porta called ''Savoia'', [[Susa, Piedmont]], 275-290 BC.]]

Every camp included &quot;main street&quot;, which ran unimpeded through the camp in a north-south direction and was very wide. The names of streets in many cities formerly occupied by the Romans suggest that the street was called ''[[cardo]]'' or ''cardus maximus''. This name applies more to cities than it does to ancient camps.&lt;ref&gt;''Cardo'' is the hinge line of a door and therefore is any main axis. In surveying it was the line drawn across (at 90° using a [[groma surveying|groma]]) the east-west ''decumanus'', which was the first line drawn based on the position of the sun at [[sunrise]]. The ''via principalis'' would certainly be a cardo.&lt;/ref&gt;

Typically &quot;main street&quot; was the ''via principalis''. The central portion was used as a parade ground and headquarters area. The &quot;headquarters&quot; building was called the ''[[praetorium]]'' because it housed the ''[[praetor]]'' or base commander (&quot;first officer&quot;), and his staff. In the camp of a full legion he held the rank of ''[[Roman consul|consul]]'' or ''[[proconsul]]'' but officers of lesser ranks might command.

On one side of the ''praetorium'' was the ''quaestorium'', the building of the ''[[quaestor]]'' (supply officer). On the other side was the ''[[Forum (Roman)|forum]]'', a small duplicate of an urban forum, where public business could be conducted. Along the ''Via Principalis'' were the homes or tents of the several [[tribune]]s in front of the barracks of the units they commanded.

The ''Via Principalis'' went through the ''vallum'' in the ''Porta Principalis Dextra'' (&quot;right principal gate&quot;) and ''Porta Principalis Sinistra'' (&quot;left, etc.&quot;), which were gates fortified with ''turres'' (&quot;towers&quot;). Which was on the north and which on the south depends on whether the praetorium faced east or west, which remains unknown.

The central region of the ''Via Principalis'' with the buildings for the command staff was called the ''Principia'' (plural of ''principium''). It was actually a square, as across this at right angles to the ''Via Principalis'' was the ''Via Praetoria'', so called because the ''praetorium'' interrupted it. The ''Via Principalis'' and the ''Via Praetoria'' offered another division of the camp into four quarters.

[[File:Weißenburg Porta decumana2.jpg|thumb|left|Porta Decumana at [[Weißenburg in Bayern|Weißenburg]], [[Bavaria]], [[Germany]]]]
Across the central plaza (''principia'') to the east or west was the main gate, the ''Porta Praetoria''. Marching through it and down &quot;headquarters street&quot; a unit ended up in formation in front of the headquarters. The standards of the legion were located on display there, very much like the flag of modern camps.

On the other side of the praetorium the ''Via Praetoria'' continued to the wall, where it went through the ''Porta Decumana''. In theory this was the back gate. Supplies were supposed to come in through it and so it was also called, descriptively, the ''Porta Quaestoria''. The term Decumena, &quot;of the 10th&quot;, came from the arranging of ''manipuli'' or ''turmae'' from the first to the 10th, such that the 10th was near the ''intervallum'' on that side. The ''Via Praetoria'' on that side might take the name ''Via Decumena'' or the entire ''Via Praetoria'' be replaced with ''[[Decumanus Maximus]]''.&lt;ref&gt;''Decumana'' (feminine of ''decumanus'') derives most likely from ''decima manus'', &quot;tenth part&quot; or &quot;tenfold&quot;. As tenfold, it meant &quot;immense.&quot; As tenth part, it also meant &quot;across&quot;, such as a cross-path or cross-boundary. In surveying it was the first line drawn, after noting the position of the sun at [[sunrise]] in order to know exactly where [[east]] was; the ''cardo'' was then drawn across it at right angles. This was necessary, because the ancient Romans did not have the [[compass]] to determine the position of the [[magnetic north]]. The connection between tenth and across remains obscure. The presence of numbered streets makes it less likely that the ''via decumana'' was &quot;cross street&quot; than that it was &quot;10th street.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

===Canteen===
In peaceful times the camp set up a marketplace with the natives in the area. They were allowed into the camp as far as the units numbered 5 (half-way to the praetorium). There another street crossed the camp at right angles to the ''Via Decumana'', called the ''Via Quintana'', &quot;5th street&quot;. If the camp needed more gates, one or two of the ''Porta Quintana'' were built, presumably named ''dextra'' and ''sinistra''. If the gates were not built, the ''Porta Decumana'' also became the ''Porta Quintana''. At &quot;5th street&quot; a public market was allowed.{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}}

===Major buildings===
[[File:Arbeia Roman Fort grannaries.jpg|thumb|left|Not much remains of these ''horrea'' (granaries) at Arbeia, but the longitudinal supports for the floor can be seen.]]
The ''Via Quintana'' and the ''Via Principalis'' divided the camp into three districts: the ''Latera Praetorii'', the ''Praetentura'' and the ''Retentura''. In the ''latera'' (&quot;sides&quot;) were the ''Arae'' (sacrificial altars), the ''[[Augur]]atorium'' (for [[auspice]]s), the ''Tribunal'', where courts martial and arbitrations were conducted (it had a raised platform), the guardhouse, the quarters of various kinds of staff and the storehouses for grain (''horrea'') or meat (''carnarea''). Sometimes the ''horrea'' were located near the barracks and the meat was stored on the hoof. Analysis of sewage from latrines indicates the legionary diet was mainly grain. Also located in the ''Latera'' was the ''Armamentarium'', a long shed containing any heavy weapons and artillery not on the wall.

[[File:Roman Onager.jpg|thumb|right|Roman artillery piece ([[Onager (siege weapon)|Onager]])]]

The ''Praetentura'' (&quot;stretching to the front&quot;) contained the ''Scamnum Legatorum'', the quarters of officers who were below general but higher than company commanders (''Legati'').&lt;ref&gt;The term ''legatus'' had other meanings in other contexts, such as governor or ambassador.&lt;/ref&gt; Near the ''Principia'' were the ''Valetudinarium'' (hospital), ''Veterinarium'' (for horses), ''Fabrica'' (&quot;workshop&quot;, metals and wood), and further to the front the quarters of special forces. These included ''[[Roman navy|Classici]]'' (&quot;marines&quot;, as most European camps were on rivers and contained a river naval command), ''Equites'' (&quot;cavalry&quot;), ''[[Speculatores|Exploratores]]'' (&quot;scouts&quot;), and ''Vexillarii'' (carriers of vexillae, the official pennants of the legion and its units). Troops who did not fit elsewhere also were there.

The part of the ''Retentura'' (&quot;stretching to the rear&quot;) closest to the ''Principia'' contained the ''Quaestorium''. By the late empire it had developed also into a safekeep for plunder and a prison for hostages and high-ranking enemy captives. Near the ''Quaestorium'' were the quarters of the headquarters guard (''Statores''), who amounted to two [[Centuria|centuries]] (companies). If the ''[[Imperator]]'' was present they served as his bodyguard.

===Barracks===
[[File:2006 0602TurdaPotaissa0122.jpg|thumb|right|A sanitary channel at [[Potaissa]], [[Roman Dacia|Dacia]] (modern [[Romania]]). It is placed cross-slope with a slight decline and then exits down-slope.]]
Further from the ''Qaestorium'' were the tents of the ''Nationes'' (&quot;natives&quot;), who were auxiliaries of foreign troops, and the legionaries themselves in double rows of tents or barracks (''Strigae''). One ''Striga'' was as long as required and 18&amp;nbsp;m wide. In it were two ''Hemistrigia'' of facing tents centered in its 9&amp;nbsp;m strip. Arms could be stacked before the tents and baggage carts kept there as well. Space on the other side of the tent was for passage.

In the northern places like Britain, where it got cold in the winter, they would make wood or stone barracks. The Romans would also put a fireplace in the barracks. They had about three bunk beds in it. They had a small room beside it where they put their armour; it was as big as the tents. They would also make these barracks if the fort they had was going to stay there for good.&lt;ref&gt;Sims, Lesley: &quot;Roman Soldier's Handbook&quot;, page 55-56. Usborne Publishing Ltd, 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

A tent was 3 by 3.5 metres (0.6&amp;nbsp;m for the aisle), ten men per tent. Ideally a company took 10 tents, arranged in a line of 10 companies, with the 10th near the ''Porta Decumana''. Of the c. 9.2 square metres of bunk space each man received 0.9, or about 0.6 by 1.5&amp;nbsp;m, which was only practical if they slept with heads to the aisle. The single tent with its men was called ''[[contubernium]]'', also used for &quot;squad&quot;. A squad during some periods was 8 men or fewer.

The ''Centurion'', or company commander, had a double-sized tent for his quarters, which served also as official company area. Other than there, the men had to find other places to be. To avoid mutiny, it became extremely important for the officers to keep them busy.

A covered portico might protect the walkway along the tents. If [[barracks]] had been constructed, one company was housed in one barracks building, with the arms at one end and the common area at the other. The company area was used for cooking and recreation, such as gaming. The army provisioned the men and had their bread (''panis militaris'') baked in outdoor ovens, but the men were responsible for cooking and serving themselves. They could buy meals or supplementary foods at the canteen. The officers were allowed servants.

===Sanitation===
For sanitary facilities, a camp had both public and private latrines. A public latrine consisted of a bank of seats situated over a channel of running water. One of the major considerations for selecting the site of a camp was the presence of running water, which the engineers diverted into the sanitary channels. Drinking water came from wells; however, the larger and more permanent bases featured the ''[[Roman aqueduct|aqueduct]]'', a structure running a stream captured from high ground (sometimes miles away) into the camp. The praetorium had its own latrine, and probably the quarters of the high-ranking officers. In or near the ''intervallum'', where they could easily be accessed, were the latrines of the soldiers. A public bathhouse for the soldiers, also containing a latrine, was located near or on the ''Via Principalis''.

===Territory===
[[File:Arbeia Roman Fort reconstructed barracks.jpg|thumb|right|Reconstructed barracks of a ''Castra Hiberna'', or &quot;winter camp&quot;. Each doorway provides entry to a large room, the sleeping quarters of one ''contubernium'', or &quot;squad&quot; of about 10 men.]]
The influence of a base extended far beyond its walls. The total land required for the maintenance of a permanent base was called its ''territoria''. In it were located all the resources of nature and the terrain required by the base: pastures, woodlots, water sources, stone quarries, mines, exercise fields and attached villages. The central castra might also support various fortified adjuncts to the main base, which were not in themselves self-sustaining (as was the base). In this category were ''speculae'', &quot;watchtowers&quot;, ''castella'', &quot;small camps&quot;, and naval bases.

All the major bases near rivers featured some sort of fortified naval installation, one side of which was formed by the river or lake. The other sides were formed by a polygonal wall and ditch constructed in the usual way, with gates and watchtowers. The main internal features were the boat sheds and the docks. When not in use, the boats were drawn up into the sheds for maintenance and protection. Since the camp was placed to best advantage on a hill or slope near the river, the naval base was usually outside its walls. The ''classici'' and the ''optiones'' of the naval installation relied on the camp for its permanent defense. Naval personnel generally enjoyed better quarters and facilities. Many were civilians working for the military.

===Modifications in practice===
This ideal was always modified to suit the terrain and the circumstances. Each camp discovered by archaeology has its own specific layout and architectural features, which makes sense from a military point of view.

If, for example, the camp was built on an outcrop, it followed the lines of the outcrop. The terrain for which it was best suited and for which it was probably designed in distant prehistoric times was the rolling plain. The camp was best placed on the summit and along the side of a low hill, with spring water running in rivulets through the camp (''aquatio'') and pastureland to provide grazing (''pabulatio'') for the animals. In case of attack, arrows, javelins and sling missiles could be fired down at an enemy tiring himself to come up. For defence troops could be formed in an ''acies'', or &quot;battle-line&quot;, outside the gates, where they could be easily resupplied and replenished, as well as being supported by archery from the palisade.

The streets, gates and buildings present depended on the requirements and resources of the camp. The gates might vary from two to six and not be centred on the sides. Not all the streets and buildings might be present.

===Quadrangular camps in later times===
Many settlements in [[Europe]] originated as Roman military camps and still show traces of their original pattern (e.g. [[Castres]] in [[France]], [[Barcelona]] in [[Spain]]).&lt;ref&gt;Spain was especially heavily colonized by veterans, who Romanized the language and the architecture. Refer to Miranda (2002) under External links, Camp life, below.&lt;/ref&gt; The pattern was also used by [[Spanish colonization of the Americas|Spanish colonizers in America]] following strict rules by the Spanish monarchy for founding new cities in the [[New World]].

Many of the towns of [[England]] still retain forms of the word ''castra'' in their names, usually as the suffixes &quot;-caster&quot; or &quot;-chester&quot; -- [[Lancaster, England|Lancaster]], [[Colchester]], [[Tadcaster]], [[Chester]], [[Manchester]], [[Mancetter]], [[Uttoxeter]] and [[Ribchester]], for example. [[Castle]] has the same derivation, from the diminutive ''castellum'' or &quot;little fort&quot;, but does not always indicate a former Roman camp.

==Camp life==
Activities conducted in a castra can be divided into ordinary and &quot;the duty&quot; or &quot;the watch&quot;. Ordinary activity was performed during regular working hours. The duty was associated with operating the installation as a military facility. For example, none of the soldiers were required to man the walls all the time, but round-the clock duty always required a portion of the soldiers to be on duty at any time.

Duty time was divided into ''vigilia'', the eight watches into which the 24-hour day was divided so they stood guard for 3 hours that day.&lt;ref&gt;Roby under Secondary sources below.&lt;/ref&gt; The Romans used signals on brass instruments to mark time. These were mainly the ''[[buccina]]'' or ''bucina'', the ''[[cornu (horn)|cornu]]'' and the ''[[Roman tuba|tuba]]''. As they did not possess valves for regulating the pitch, the range of these instruments was somewhat limited. Nevertheless, the musicians (''Aenatores'', &quot;brassmen&quot;) managed to define enough signals for issuing commands. The instrument used to mark the passage of a watch was the ''buccina'', from which the trumpet derives. It was sounded by a ''buccinator''.

===Ordinary life===
[[File:Granary at Housesteads Roman Fort.jpg|200px|thumb|left|The pillars supported a raised floor to keep food dry and free from vermin in this granary at [[Housesteads Roman Fort#History|Housesteads Roman Fort]] (''Vercovicium'')]]
Ordinary camp life began with a ''buccina'' call at daybreak, the first watch of the day. The soldiers arose at this time and shortly after collected in the company area for breakfast and assembly. The [[centurion]]s were up before them and off to the ''principia'' where they and the ''[[equites]]'' were required to assemble. The regimental commanders, the tribunes, were already converging on the ''praetorium''. There the general staff was busily at work planning the day. At a staff meeting the ''Tribunes'' received the password and the orders of the day. They brought those back to the ''centuriones'', who returned to their company areas to instruct the men.

For soldiers, the main item of the agenda was a vigorous training session lasting about a watch long. Recruits received two, one in the morning and one in the afternoon.&lt;ref name=vegI&gt;Vegetius Book I, linked in Primary sources below.&lt;/ref&gt; Planning and supervision of training were under a general staff officer, who might manage training at several camps. According to Vegetius, the men might take a {{convert|32|km}} hike or a {{convert|6-8|km}} jog under full pack, or swim a river. Marching drill was always in order.

Each soldier was taught the use of every weapon and also was taught to ride. Seamanship was taught at naval bases. Soldiers were generalists in the military and construction arts. They practiced archery, spear-throwing and above all swordsmanship against posts (''pali'') fixed in the ground.&lt;ref name=vegI/&gt; Training was taken very seriously and was democratic. Ordinary soldiers would see all the officers training with them including the ''praetor'', or the Emperor, if he was in camp.

Swordsmanship lessons and use of the shooting range probably took place on the ''campus'', a &quot;field&quot; outside the ''castra'', from which English camp derives. Its surface could be lightly paved. Winter curtailed outdoor training. The general might in that case have sheds constructed, which served as field houses for training. There is archaeological evidence in one case of an indoor equestrian ring.

Apart from the training, each soldier had a regular job on the base, of which there were a large variety from the various kinds of clerks to the craftsmen. Soldiers changed jobs frequently. The commander's policy was to have all the soldiers skilled in all the arts and crafts so that they could be as interchangeable as possible. Even then the goal was not entirely achievable. The gap was bridged by the specialists, the ''optiones'' or &quot;chosen men&quot;, of which there were many different kinds. For example, a skilled artisan might be chosen to superintend a workshop.

[[File:Cohen 0008.jpg|thumb|right|An aureus of the late republic]]
The supply administration was run as a business using money as the medium of exchange.&lt;ref&gt;Verboven, pages 15-17, under External links, Camp life. The author states estimates of coinage passing hands at various locations. A soldier received pay less deductions for expenses. He could borrow from or invest with the first bankers, the ''argentarii'' or ''negotiatores nummularii'', whose business was to supply the legion with money for a percentage.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[aureus]] was the preferred coin of the late republic and early empire; in the late empire the [[Solidus (coin)|solidus]] came into use. The larger bases, such as ''Moguntiacum'', minted their own coins. As does any business, the base quaestorium required careful record keeping, performed mainly by the optiones. A chance cache of tablets from [[Vindolanda]] in Britain gives us a glimpse of some supply transactions. They record, among other things, the purchase of consumables and raw supplies, the storage and repair of clothing and other items, and the sale of items, including foodstuffs, to achieve an income. Vindolanda traded vigorously with the surrounding natives.&lt;ref&gt;A link to the Vindolanda tablets database with introductions, descriptions and bibliography is given under Primary sources below.&lt;/ref&gt;

Another feature of the camp was the military hospital (''valetudinarium'', later ''hospitium''). Augustus instituted the first permanent medical corps in the Roman army. Its physicians, the ''medici ordinarii'',&lt;ref&gt;See ''The Tombstone of Anicius Ingenuus'', a medicus ordinarius, under Primary sources below.&lt;/ref&gt; had to be qualified physicians. They were allowed medical students, practitioners and whatever orderlies they needed; i.e., the military hospitals were medical schools and places of residency as well.&lt;ref&gt;Scheidel page 14 under External links, Camp life.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{details|topic=on hospitals and physicians in the military|Medical community of ancient Rome}}

Officers were allowed to marry and to reside with their families on base. The army did not extend the same privileges to the men, who were not allowed to marry.&lt;ref&gt;Scheidel pages 2-8 under External links, Camp life.&lt;/ref&gt; However, they often kept common law families off base in communities nearby. The communities might be native, as the tribesmen tended to build around a permanent base for purposes of trade, but also the base sponsored villages (''vici'') of dependents and businessmen. Dependants were not allowed to follow an army on the march into hostile territory.

[[Military service]] was for about 25 years. At the end of that time, the [[veteran]] was given a certificate of honorable discharge (''honesta missio''). Some of these have survived engraved on stone. Typically they certify that the veteran, his wife (one per veteran) and children or his sweetheart were now Roman citizens, which is a good indication that troops, which were used chiefly on the frontier, were from peoples elsewhere on the frontier who wished to earn Roman citizenship. However, under [[Antoninus Pius]], citizenship was no longer granted to the children of rank-and-file veterans, the privilege becoming restricted only to officers.&lt;ref&gt;Duncan B. Campbell, &quot;Women in Roman forts: Residents, visitors or barred from entry?&quot;, Ancient Warfare, vol. IV (2010), issue 6, pp. 48-53, cf. p. 50&lt;/ref&gt;

Veterans often went into business in the communities near a base.&lt;ref&gt;Verboven describes the process. A veteran with a certain skill continued it as a contractor for the army. For example, a ''gladiarius'' or maker of swords, became a ''negotiator gladiarius'', a supplier of swords. There were a large number of such names: the ''negotiatores vestiarii'' for clothing, ''frumentarii'' for grain, ''salsari leguminari'' for the salted vegetable concession, and so on.&lt;/ref&gt; They became permanent members of the community and would stay on after the troops were withdrawn, as in the notable case of [[Saint Patrick]]'s family.

===Duties===
[[File:Hadrians Wall 05.JPG|thumb|The remains of a granary at Housesteads Roman Fort on [[Hadrian's Wall]].]]
Conducted in parallel with the ordinary activities was &quot;the duty&quot;, the official chores required by the camp under strict military discipline. The ''Legate'' was ultimately responsible for them as he was for the entire camp, but he delegated the duty to a tribune chosen as officer of the day. The line ''Tribunes'' were commanders of ''[[cohort (military unit)|Cohort]]es'' and were approximately the equivalent of colonels. The 6 tribunes were divided into units of two, with each unit being responsible for filling the position of officer of the day for two months. The two men of a unit decided among themselves who would take what day. They could alternate days or each take a month. One filled in for the other in case of illness. On his day, the tribune effectively commanded the camp and was even respected as such by the ''Legate''.

The equivalent concept of the duties performed in modern camps is roughly the detail. The responsibilities (''curae'') of the many kinds of detail were distributed to the men by all the methods considered fair and democratic: lot, rotation and negotiation. Certain kinds of ''cura'' were assigned certain classes or types of troops; for example, wall sentries were chosen only from ''Velites''. Soldiers could be temporarily or permanently exempted: the ''immunes''. For example, a ''Triarius'' was ''immunis'' from the ''curae'' of the ''Hastati''.

The duty year was divided into time slices, typically one or two months, which were apportioned to units, typically [[maniple (military unit)|maniple]]s or [[century|centuries]]. They were always allowed to negotiate who took the duty and when. The most common kind of ''cura'' were the posts of the sentinels, called the ''excubiae'' by day and the ''vigilae'' at night. Wall posts were ''praesidia'', gate posts, ''custodiae'', advance positions before the gates, ''stationes''.

In addition were special guards and details. One post was typically filled by four men, one sentinel and the others at ease until a situation arose or it was their turn to be sentinel. Some of the details were:
*guarding, cleaning and maintaining the ''principia''.
*guarding and maintaining the quarters of each [[tribune]].
*tending the horses of each cavalry ''[[turma]]''.
*guarding the ''praetorium''.&lt;ref&gt;Forman, Joan: &quot;The Romans&quot;, page15. Macdonald educational. 1975&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Military of ancient Rome}}
*[[Fortification]]
*[[List of topics related to ancient Rome]]
*[[Military history of ancient Rome]]
*[[Roman legion]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

===Primary sources===&lt;!-- AD dates included in author parameter to avoid CS1 date errors --&gt;
* {{cite wikisource|title=The War of the Jews|author=[[Josephus]]|others=Trans. [[William Whiston]]}}
* {{cite web | author=Population of Vindolanda (100 AD) | title=(the Tablets) | work=Vindolanda Tablets Online: The Roman Army: Activities | publisher=Centre for the Study of Ancient Documents, Academic Computing Development Team at Oxford University | url=http://vindolanda.csad.ox.ac.uk/tablets/TVII-2-5.shtml | format=shtml}}
* {{cite web | last=pseudo-Hyginus | title=De Munitionibus Castrorum | work=The Latin Library | publisher=Ad fontes Academy | url=http://www.thelatinlibrary.com/hyginus/hyginus6.shtml }} (Latin text.)
* {{cite web | last=Polybius | authorlink=Polybius | title=The Histories (English translation) Book VI | work=The Loeb Classical Library, Volume III Section VI | publisher= |url=http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Polybius/6*.html }} Web publication on Bill Thayer's ''Polybius'' site.
* {{cite web | author=Roman government (160 AD) | title=(Military Diploma) | work =Military Diploma of Discharge and Roman Citizenship | publisher =Metz, George W | url=http://www.legionxxiv.org/diploma160ad.htm }} Legion xxiv website.
* {{cite web | author=Unknown inscriber (3rd century AD) | title=(the Tombstone) | url=http://museums.ncl.ac.uk/archive/old_fotm/old_fotmo98/ | work=Tombstone of Anicius Ingenuus, Museum of Antiquities Website | publisher=Newcastle University }}
* {{cite web | author=Vegetius | title=Flavius Vegetius Renatus Epitoma Rei Militaris Book I | publisher=Armamentarium | url=http://museums.ncl.ac.uk/archive/arma/contents/text/technica/veg1.htm }} Selections, Latin and English juxtaposed by paragraph. Translator unknown.
* {{cite web | author=Publius Flavius Vegetius Renatus | authorlink=Publius Flavius Vegetius Renatus | others=Clarke, Lieutenant John (translator); unknown editor | title=The Military Institutions of the Romans (De Re Militari) | work=Digital Attic 2.0 | publisher=Brevik, Mads | year=2001 | url=http://www.pvv.ntnu.no/~madsb/home/war/vegetius/ }} Books I-III only. The unknown editor altered the translation &quot;to conform to modern usage&quot; and abbreviated the text. Access is by subtitle. Search only within subsection.

===Secondary sources===
* {{cite book | last=Campbell | first=Duncan B. | authorlink=Duncan_Campbell_(ancient_historian) | title=Roman Auxiliary Forts 27 BC-AD 378 | publisher=Osprey Publishing | location=Oxford | year=2009 | isbn=978-1-84603-380-3}}
* {{cite book | last=Johnson | first=Anne | title=Roman Forts of the 1st and 2nd centuries AD in Britain and the German Provinces, | publisher=Adam &amp; Charles Black | location=London | year=1983 | isbn=0-7136-2223-7}}
* {{cite book | last=Keppie | first=Lawrence | title=The Making of the Roman Army from Republic to Empire | publisher=Barnes and Noble Books | location=New York | year=1994 | isbn=1-56619-359-1}}
* {{cite book | last=Roby | first=Henry John | authorlink=Henry John Roby | title=A Grammar of the Latin Language from Plautus to Suetonius: Second Edition | publisher=Macmillan | year=1872 | location=London | url=https://books.google.com/?id=hRIAAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA453&amp;lpg=PA453&amp;dq=vigilia+roman+military+watch |page=453 }}

==External links==
{{Commons|Castra}}
Below are a number of links to sites reporting or summarizing current research or thinking. Many are reprints of articles made available to the public at no charge. The historical researcher will find their bibliographies of great interest.

===General===
* {{cite web | title=Fortress Study Group | work=Study Group devoted to the knowledge of Forts and Fortifications of all times and Greek and Roman ones: with a Journal ''Fort'' and a newsletter ''Casemate'' | publisher=Fortress Study Group | url=http://www.fsgfort.com/ }}
* {{cite web | title=Army Picture Index | work=Illustrated History of the Roman Empire | publisher=roman-empire.net | url=http://www.roman-empire.net/army/army-pictures.html }}
* {{cite web | last=Bell | first=Anders | title=Castra et urbs romana: An Examination of the Common Features of Roman Settlements in Italy and the Empire and a System to aid in the Discovery of their Origins. | work=CAC Undergraduate Essay Contest for 2000-2001 | publisher=Classical Association of Canada | year=2001 | url=http://cac-scec.ca/concours_essais/01Bell.html }}
* {{cite web | last=Lewis | first=Charlton T. |author2=Short, Charles | title=Castrum/Castra | work=A Latin Dictionary | publisher=The Perseus Digital Library | url=http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/ptext?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.04.0059%3Aentry%3D%237013 }}
* {{cite web | last=Ramsay | first=William | title=Castra | work=William Smith A Dictionary of Greek and Roman Antiquities | publisher=John Murray, republished on Bill Thayer's LacusCurtius site | year=1875 | url=http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/secondary/SMIGRA*/Castra.html }}
* {{cite web | title=The Roman Military in Britain | url=http://www.roman-britain.org/military/military_intro.htm | publisher=roman-britain.org }} Links to a Glossary.
*[http://www.romans-in-britain.org.uk/glo_military_glossary_a.htm The Romans in Britain, Glossary of Military terms]. Note that both Latin and Greek terms with the same meaning are included.

===Forts and fortifications===
* {{cite web | title=Antonine Wall Fort: Bearsden, New Kilpatrick, Strathclyde | url=http://www.roman-britain.org/places/bearsden.htm | publisher=roman-britain.org }}
* {{cite journal | last=Hanson | first=W.S. |author2=Friel, J.G.P. | title=Westerton: A Roman Watchtower on the Gask Frontier | journal= [[Proceedings of the Society of Antiquaries of Scotland]] | volume=125 | pages=499–519 | year=1995 | url=http://ads.ahds.ac.uk/catalogue/adsdata/PSAS_2002/pdf/vol_125/125_499_519.pdf |format=PDF}}
* {{cite web | title=Iron-Age Hillfort, Roman Stores Depot Brandon Camp, Leintwardine Herefordshire |  url=http://www.roman-britain.org/places/brandon_camp.htm | publisher= roman-britain.org }}
* {{cite web | last=Lendering | first=Jona | title=Haltern | url=http://www.livius.org/ha-hd/haltern/haltern.html | publisher=livius.org | work=Livius articles on ancient history }}
*{{cite web | title=Nidum: Roman Auxiliary Fort: Neath, West Glamorgan | url=http://www.roman-britain.org/places/nidum.htm | publisher=roman-britain.org }}
* {{cite web | title=Pinnata Castra: Roman Legionary Fortress &amp; Marching Camps: Inchtuthill, Tayside | url=http://www.roman-britain.org//places/pinnata-castra.htm | publisher=roman-britain.org }}
* {{cite web | title=Roman Fortress | work=Time trail | publisher=Exeter City Council | url=http://www.exeter.gov.uk/timetrail/02_romanfortress/growth.asp }}
* {{Cite book | first=William | last=Smith | author-link=William Smith (lexicographer) | contribution=Vallum | contribution-url=http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/secondary/SMIGRA*/Vallum.html | title=A Dictionary of Greek and Roman Antiquities | year=1875 |page=1183 | place=London | publisher=John Murray }}. Article republished on Bill Thayer's LacusCurtius site, which has the advantage of linking to ancient texts cited by Smith.
* {{cite web | author=Tribus | title=The Roman Camp in Bonn | url=http://www.eduvinet.de/tribus/roemlag/sache/rl.htm | publisher=Eduvinet Services }}
* {{cite web | title=The Roman Camp Sostra | url=http://bulgariancastles.com/bulgariancastles/en/fortress-sostra-en | publisher=bulgariancastles.com}}

===Camp life===
* {{cite journal | last=Campbell | first=Duncan B. | authorlink=Duncan_Campbell_(ancient_historian) | title=Women in Roman forts: Residents, visitors or barred from entry? | journal=Ancient Warfare|year=2010|volume=IV|issue=6|pages=48–53}}
* {{cite web | last=Miranda | first=Frank | title=Castra et Coloniae: The Role of the Roman Army in the Romanization and Urbanization of Spain | work=Quaestio: The UCLA Undergraduate History Journal | publisher=[[Phi Alpha Theta]]: History Honors Society, UCLA Theta Upsilon Chapter, UCLA Department of History | year=2002 | url=http://www.history.ucla.edu/undergrad/pat/journal2002/miranda.pdf | format=pdf }}
* {{cite web | last=Scheidel | first=Walter | authorlink=Walter Scheidel| title=Marriage, Families and Survival in the Roman Imperial Army: Demographic Aspects | work=Princeton/Stanford Working Papers in Classics | publisher=Princeton University |date=November 2005 | url=http://www.princeton.edu/~pswpc/pdfs/scheidel/110509.pdf | format=pdf }}
* {{Cite book | first=Koenraad | last=Verboven | editor-last=Lukas | editor-first=De Blois | editor2-last=Elio | editor2-first=Lo Cascio | editor2-link =Elio Lo Cascio | contribution=Good for Business. The Roman Army and the Emergence of a 'Business Class' in the Northwestern Provinces of the Roman Empire (1st century BCE - 3rd century CE) | contribution-url=http://www.ancienthistory.ugent.be/history/en/Verboven_Good_for_business.pdf | title=The Impact of the Roman Army (200 BC - AD 476). Economic, Social, Political, Religious and Cultural Aspects | year=2007 | pages=295–314 | place=Leiden &amp; Boston | publisher=Brill | isbn=90-04-16044-2 }}

{{Fortifications}}
{{Ancient Rome topics}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Ancient Roman city planning]]
[[Category:Castles by type]]
[[Category:Roman fortifications by type]]</text>
      <sha1>tobevmty2e5zdk60uvq4qnmom632izz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
