<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Chelsea Pensioner</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>715848</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750731717</id>
      <parentid>750731519</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-21T14:34:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cuchullain</username>
        <id>196153</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11532">[[Image:Chelsea-pensioners.jpg|thumb|200px|Chelsea pensioners in scarlet coats and tricorne hats at the Founder's Day parade in the [[Royal Hospital Chelsea]]]]
A '''Chelsea Pensioner''', or '''In-Pensioner''', is a resident at the [[Royal Hospital Chelsea]], a [[retirement home]] and nursing home for former members of the [[British Army]] located in [[Chelsea, London]]. The Royal Hospital Chelsea is home to some 300 retired British soldiers, male and female (since 2009), and is located on [[Royal Hospital Road]]. Historically, the phrase &quot;Chelsea Pensioner&quot; applied more widely, referring to both In-Pensioners and Out-Pensioners who live elsewhere.

==In- and Out-Pensioners==
[[File:William Hiseland.jpg|thumb|180px|Sergeant [[William Hiseland]], an [[English Civil War]] [[cavalier]] and one of the first pensioners to be admitted to the Royal Hospital in London]]
The Royal Hospital was founded by [[Charles II of England|King Charles II]] in 1682 as a retreat for veterans.&lt;ref name=guide3&gt;Guidebook, p. 3&lt;/ref&gt; The provision of a hostel rather than the payment of pensions was inspired by [[Les Invalides]] in Paris.&lt;ref name=guide3/&gt;

During the reign of [[King William III]] and [[Mary II of England|Queen Mary II]], the Royal Hospital was still under construction so they introduced a system for distribution of army [[pension]]s in 1689. The pension was to be made available to all former soldiers who had been injured in service, or who had served for more than 20 years.

By the time the Royal Hospital was completed, there were more pensioners than places available in the Royal Hospital. Eligible ex-soldiers who could not be housed in the Hospital were termed '''Out-Pensioners''', receiving their pension from the Royal Hospital but living outside it. '''In-Pensioners''', by contrast, surrender their army pension and live within the Royal Hospital.

In 1703 there were 51 Out-Pensioners. By 1815 this figure had risen to 36,757.

The Royal Hospital remained responsible for distributing army pensions until 1955, following which the phrase &quot;Out-Pensioner&quot; became less common, and &quot;Chelsea Pensioner&quot; was used largely to refer to &quot;In-Pensioners&quot;.

==Conditions for admission as an In-Pensioner==
To be eligible for admission as a Chelsea Pensioner a candidate must be a former soldier or non-commissioned officer of the British Army (including National Service) or a former officer of the British Army who served in the ranks for at least 12 years or was awarded a disablement pension while serving in the ranks. They must be over 65 years of age, be able to live independently on the Long Wards on arrival to the Royal Hospital Chelsea and be free of any financial obligation to support a spouse or family.&lt;ref name=Blog/&gt; 

==Life of In-Pensioners==
[[Image:MovingIn.jpg|thumb|300px|A ward within the Royal Hospital Chelsea]]
Applicants for the Royal Hospital Chelsea (RHC) are invited for a four day stay during which they get a taste of what life is like for a Chelsea Pensioner. If they enjoy their stay and it is felt that they will fit in they are invited to become a Chelsea Pensioner. Upon arrival at the Royal Hospital, each In-Pensioner is  measured up for their Blues (day-to-day uniform) and Scarlets (the famous uniform that they wear on parade). They are given their own room, or &quot;berth&quot; in a ward, and are allocated to a Company. Up until refurbishment works carried out in the 1950s, these rooms measured 6 x 6 feet. Work completed in 2015 has ensured that all In-Pensioner berths include en suite facilities, a writing desk, and natural light. On entry, In-Pensioners surrender their army pension, in return receiving board, lodging, clothing and full medical care.&lt;ref name=Blog/&gt;

In-Pensioners also have their own Club with a bar, lounges and restaurant and there are allotments for those who enjoy gardening. If an In-Pensioner becomes unwell they are moved into the Infirmary, which is a state of the art care home with nursing and a [[General Practitioner|G.P.]] medical centre.&lt;ref name=Blog&gt;[http://royalhospitalchelsea.blogspot.co.uk/2013/02/what-is-chelsea-pensioner.html 'What is a Chelsea Pensioner? - the Royal Hospital, Chelsea website]&lt;/ref&gt; The Royal Hospital Burial Ground is at [[Brookwood Cemetery]] in Surrey.

==Admission of women==
[[Image:Marjorie Cole.jpg|thumb||250px|Marjorie Cole, middle, one of many female Chelsea Pensioners at the Royal Hospital]]
Until 2009, only male candidates were admitted. It was announced in 2007 that female ex-service personnel would be admitted on the completion of modernisation of the long wards.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/london/6398069.stm Women to join Chelsea pensioners] [[BBC News]] 26 February 2007&lt;/ref&gt; In March 2009 the first women in the Hospital’s 317-year history were admitted as In-Pensioners:  Dorothy Hughes (aged 85) and Winifred Phillips (aged 82).
[[File:Dorothy Hughes Chelsea pensioner.JPG|thumb|150px|left|In-Pensioner Dorothy Hughes in 2013]]
Winifred Phillips (1926-2016) trained as a nurse and joined the [[Auxiliary Territorial Service]] in 1948 and enlisted in the [[Women's Royal Army Corps]] in 1949 while serving in [[Egypt]]. For the next 22 years she served in Singapore, Cyprus and Egypt reaching the rank of [[Warrant Officer Class 2#British Army|Warrant Officer Class 2]]. She wrote two books about becoming one of the first female Chelsea Pensioners: ''My Journey to Becoming the First Lady Chelsea Pensioner'' (2010), and ''Mum’s Army: Love and Adventure from the NAAFI to Civvy Street'' (2013). She never married.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kentonline.co.uk/deal/news/first-female-chelsea-pensioner-dies-90717/ 'First female Chelsea Pensioner Winifred Phillips dies aged 89' - ''Kent Online'' 14 February 2016]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.standard.co.uk/news/winifred-80-wins-battle-to-become-first-female-chelsea-pensioner-7198376.html 'Winifred, 80, wins battle to become first female Chelsea pensioner' - ''[[Evening Standard]]'' 6 April 2007]&lt;/ref&gt;

Dorothy Hughes joined the [[British Army]] in 1941, later working as part of 450 Heavy Anti Aircraft Battery in the London Division. In 1945 the Battery was deployed near Dover to defend against [[V-1 flying bomb]] attacks. She later worked with the Army Operational Research Group developing fuses in shells used against [[V-2 rocket]]s and was discharged from the Army in 1946 with the rank of Sergeant.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-1161487/The-ladies-red-Chelsea-Pensioners-welcome-female-recruits-300-year-history.html#ixzz17vaj6Ub5 ‘The ladies in red: Chelsea Pensioners welcome first female recruits in 300&gt;-year history’ ''[[Daily Mail]]'' 13 March 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/uk/article5898281.ece ‘Dorothy Hughes and Winifred Phillips become first female Chelsea Pensioners’ ''[[The Times]]’’ 13 March 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.chelsea-pensioners.co.uk/news|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090823002217/http://www.chelsea-pensioners.co.uk/news|archivedate=23 August 2009|title=First Women in Scarlets|publisher=News of the [[Royal Hospital Chelsea]]|accessdate=1 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/4944427/Now-I-feel-just-like-Cinderella-at-the-ball.html 'Now I feel just like Cinderella at the ball' ''[[Daily Telegraph]]’’ 5 March 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/london/7938801.stm Women joining Chelsea pensioners, [[BBC News]], 12 March 2009]&lt;/ref&gt;

The records at Royal Hospital show that another woman, a Mrs. [[Christian Davies]], was admitted to Chelsea Hospital circa 1717, and was awarded a pension for her service in the army and the wounds she received in the service of the King. She died in 1739 and was buried in the Royal Hospital Chelsea with full military honours.

==Clothing==
[[File:Arthur Portrait Cheslea Pensioner July 2007 007.jpg|150px|thumb|A Chelsea Pensioner in scarlet uniform.]]
Chelsea Pensioners are entitled to come and go from the Royal Hospital as they please, and are permitted to wear civilian clothing wherever they travel. However, within the Hospital, and in the surrounding area, they are encouraged to wear a blue uniform. If they travel further from the Royal Hospital, they should wear the distinctive [[Red coat (British army)|scarlet coats]] instead of the blue uniform. The scarlet coats are also worn for ceremonial occasions, accompanied by [[tricorne]] hats. (At other times a peaked hat, known as a [[shako]], is generally worn).

In uniform, the pensioners wear their medal ribbons and the insignia of the rank they reached while serving in the armed forces. They may also wear other insignia they earned during their service and many pensioners now wear parachute [[Parachutist Badge (United Kingdom)|jump wings]] and even [[Special Air Service|SAS]] jump wings.

==''Men In Scarlet'' album==
Seven Chelsea Pensioners at the Royal Hospital Chelsea released an album on 8 November 2010 in order to raise money for the Chelsea Pensioners' Appeal.  Featuring Dame [[Vera Lynn]], [[Katherine Jenkins]], [[The Soldiers]], and [[Janey Cutler]], the album is full of well known [[World War II|wartime]] songs and includes their traditional march, &quot;[[The Old Brigade]]&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.chelsea-pensioners.co.uk/men-in-scarlet|title=The Royal Hospital Chelsea - Men In Scarlet|accessdate=11 October 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

==Chelsea Football Club==
Nearby [[Chelsea F.C.|Chelsea Football Club]] has been affiliated with the Chelsea Pensioners for many years; the club's first nickname was the ''Pensioners'' and until the 1950s the club crest featured a Chelsea pensioner. Residents of the Hospital can be seen attending Chelsea's home games at [[Stamford Bridge (stadium)|Stamford Bridge]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | date=6 May 2010 | url=http://www.chelseafc.com/news-article/article/2044282 | title=Pensioners take a closer look | publisher=Chelseafc.com | accessdate=1 June 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

When Chelsea won the [[Premier League]] title in [[2004-05 in English football|2005]], Chelsea Pensioners formed a [[guard of honour]] as the players and management came out for the trophy presentation. This was done again when Chelsea won the title in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | date=8 May 2005 | url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/sport/football/2359287/Makelele-kicks-off-celebrations.html | title=Makelele kicks off celebrations | publisher=Daily Telegraph | accessdate=22 February 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In tribute to the trademark scarlet coats worn by the pensioners, Chelsea's kit for the [[2010–11 Chelsea F.C. season|2010-11]] season featured a red trim on the collars.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | date=14 April 2010 | url=http://www.thisislondon.co.uk/standard-sport/football/article-23824506-chelseas-blues-will-be-in-the-red-next-season.do | title=Chelsea's Blues will be in the red next season | publisher=London Evening Standard | accessdate=19 February 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== See also ==
* ''[[The Chelsea Pensioners reading the Waterloo Dispatch]]''

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.chelsea-pensioners.co.uk/ Chelsea Pensioners Website]
*[http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/documentsonline/RoyalHospitalChelsea.asp Selected service records of Chelsea pensioners available from the UK National Archives' website]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Chelsea Pensioner}}
[[Category:British ceremonial units]]
[[Category:British Army]]
[[Category:Retirement in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Military veterans' affairs in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Chelsea, London]]</text>
      <sha1>evr46dz3vn5daz727im085zsr43rdpl</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
