<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Convent of Christ (Tomar)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1573557</id>
    <revision>
      <id>747523951</id>
      <parentid>740883773</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-02T21:36:54Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>XPTO</username>
        <id>5145276</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Disambiguated: [[Médio Tejo]] → [[Médio Tejo Subregion]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="19519">{{Geobox|Building
&lt;!-- *** Heading *** --&gt;
| name                 = Convent of Christ
| native_name          = Convento de Cristo
| other_name           = 
| category             = [[Monastery]]
| native_category      = Mosteiro
&lt;!-- *** Image *** --&gt;
| image                = Tomar-Panorama-1967 08 02.jpg
| image_caption        = A view of the Convent and Castle complex of Tomar
| image_size           = 235
&lt;!-- *** Names **** --&gt; 
| official_name        = Convento de Cristo/Mosteiro de Cristo
| etymology            = [[Jesus Christ]]
| etymology_type       = Named for
| nickname             = 
&lt;!-- *** Symbols *** --&gt;
| flag                 = 
| symbol               = 
&lt;!-- *** Country *** --&gt;
| country              = {{flag|Portugal}}
| state_type           = Region
| state                = [[Centro Region, Portugal|Centro]]
| region_type          = Sub-region
| region               = [[Médio Tejo Subregion|Médio Tejo]]
| district             = [[Santarém (district)|Santarém]]
| municipality         = [[Tomar]]
&lt;!-- *** Locations *** --&gt;
| location             = Tomar (São João Baptista) e Santa Maria dos Olivais
| elevation            = 11
| prominence           = 
| lat_d                = 39
| lat_m                = 36
| lat_s                = 14
| lat_NS               = N
| long_d               = 8
| long_m               = 25
| long_s               = 9
| long_EW              = W
&lt;!-- *** Dimensions *** --&gt;
| length               = 
| length_orientation   = 
| width                = 
| width_orientation    = 
| height               = 
| depth                = 
| volume               = 
| area                 = 
&lt;!-- *** Features *** --&gt;
| author_type          = Architects
| author               = 
| style                = Manueline
| style1               = Plateresque
| style2               = Renaissance
| material             = 
&lt;!-- *** History &amp; management *** --&gt;
| established          = 1160
| established_type     = Origin
| established1         = 12th century
| established1_type    = Initiated
| established2         = 16th century
| established2_type    = Completion
| date                 = 
| date_type            = 
| owner                = Portuguese Republic
&lt;!-- *** Access *** --&gt;
| public               = Public
| visitation           = 
| visitation_date      = 
| access               = Terreiro de Gualdim Pais
&lt;!-- *** UNESCO etc. *** --&gt;
| whs_name             = Convent of Christ in Tomar
| whs_year             = 1983
| whs_number           = 265
| whs_region           = Europe and North America
| whs_criteria         = i, vi
| iucn_category        = 
&lt;!-- *** Free fields *** --&gt;
| free                 = [[IGESPAR|Instituto Gestão do Patrimonio Arquitectónico e Arqueológico]]
| free_type            = Management
| free1                = 
| free1_type           = Operator
| free2                = 
| free2_type           = 
| free3                = 
| free3_type           = 
| free4                = '''''National Monument'''''
| free4_type           = Status
| free5                = Decree 10 January 1907, DG, Série I, 14 (17 January 1907); Decree 16 June 1910, DG, Série, 136 (23 June 1910); ZEP/Zona &quot;non aedificandi&quot;, Dispatch Série II, 265 (14 November 1946); UNESCO World Heritage Site (1983)
| free5_type           = Listing
&lt;!-- *** Maps *** --&gt;
| map                  = 
| map_caption          = Location of the convent within the municipality of Tomar
| map_background       = 
| map_locator          = 
| map_locator_x        = 34
| map_locator_y        = 85
&lt;!-- *** Website *** --&gt; 
| commons              = Convent of Christ (Tomar)
| website              = 
&lt;!-- *** Footnotes *** --&gt;
| footnotes            =
}}
The '''Convent of Christ''' ({{lang-pt|Convento de Cristo/Mosteiro de Cristo}}) is a former [[Roman Catholic]] convent/monastery in the [[Freguesia (Portugal)|civil parish]] of [[Tomar (São João Baptista) e Santa Maria dos Olivais]], in the [[Centro Region, Portugal|Centrol region]] [[Concelho|municipality]] of [[Tomar]]. Originally a 12th-century [[Knights Templar|Templar]] stronghold, when the order was dissolved in the 14th century the Portuguese branch was turned into the [[Order of Christ (Portugal)|Knights of the Order of Christ]], that later supported Portugal's [[Age of Exploration|maritime discoveries]] of the 15th century. The Convent and Castle complex  is a historic and cultural monument which was listed in the list of [[UNESCO]] [[World Heritage]] list in 1983.

==History==

===Templars===
[[File:Convent of Christ - Tomar.jpg|thumb|235px|left|The main church of the Convent of Tomar constructed by the Knights Templar]]
[[File:TomarConvent-CloisterChurch1.jpg|thumb|235px|left|The Manueline nave, as seen from the Renaissance era cloisters]]
[[File:TomarConvent-Church1.jpg|thumb|235px|left|The elaborate pinnacles over the western facade of the church]]
[[File:TomarConvent-Cloisters2.jpg|thumb|235px|left|[[Renaissance]] Cloister of John III]]

The convent was founded by the [[Knights Templar|Order of Poor Knights of the Temple]] (or Templar Knights) in 1118.&lt;ref name=&quot;SIPA&quot;&gt;{{citation|url=http://www.monumentos.pt/Site/APP_PagesUser/SIPA.aspx?id=4718 |title=Convento de Cristo/Mosteiro de Cristo (IPA.00004718/PT031418120002) |publisher=SIPA – Sistema de Informação para o Património Arquitectónico |editor=SIPA |location=Lisbon, Portugal |language=Portuguese |first=Isabel |last=Mendonça |first2=Lina |last2=Marques |first3=Ricardo |last3=Branco |first4=Cecília |last4=Matias |year=2006 |accessdate=1 September 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its construction continued until the final part of the 12th century with the construction of the oratory, in one of the angles of the castle, completed by the Grand Master D. [[Gualdim Pais]] (sometime around 1160).&lt;ref name=SIPA/&gt; Around 1190 it was encircled and resisted the armies of caliph [[Yaqub, Almohad Caliph|Abu Yusuf al-Mansur]] who was successful in taking strongholds in the south.&lt;ref name=SIPA/&gt; (A plaque was erected near the entrance to the castle to commemorate this event).

During the second quarter of the 13th century, Tomar was transferred into the control of the Templars, becoming its seat.&lt;ref name=SIPA/&gt; The castle became an integral part of the defence system created by the Templars to secure the border of the young Christian Kingdom against the [[Moors]], which at the time occupied the area to approximately the [[Tagus|Tagus River]]. But, following the dissolution of the Templar Order, on 14 March 1319, and following the request of King [[Denis of Portugal]], [[Pope John XXII]] instituted the [[Order of Christ (Portugal)|Order of Christ]].&lt;ref name=SIPA/&gt; The seat of the former Knights Templar was converted in 1357 into the seat of this new order.&lt;ref name=SIPA/&gt;

The famous round church (''rotunda'') of the castle of Tomar was also built in the second half of the 12th century. The church, like some other templar churches throughout Europe, was modelled after the [[Dome of the Rock]] in [[Jerusalem]], which was believed by the [[crusaders]] to be a remnant of the [[Temple in Jerusalem|Temple of Solomon]]. The [[Church of the Holy Sepulchre]] of Jerusalem may also have served as model.

===Order of Christ===
Following the dissolution of the Templar Order, on 14 March 1319 (following the request of King [[Denis of Portugal]]), Pope John XXII instituted the [[Order of Christ (Portugal)|Order of Christ]].&lt;ref name=SIPA/&gt; The Templar order had been suppressed during most of [[Europe]] from  1312–1314, but in Portugal its members, assets, and partly its membership were transferred to the [[Order of Christ (Portugal)|Order of Christ]].&lt;ref name=SIPA/&gt; The seat of the former Knights Templar was converted in 1357 into the seat of this new order.&lt;ref name=SIPA/&gt; As a result, at about the first half of the 15th century, work was completed to adapt the Templar oratory, introducing an open choir to the western niche, about half-way up the wall.&lt;ref name=SIPA/&gt; What remains of this adaptation was the colonnade frame with interior arch.&lt;ref name=SIPA/&gt; At the same time the main palace was constructed.

During the internship of [[Henry the Navigator|Prince Henry the Navigator]] as its leader (1417-1450), the Order of Christ initiated the construction of two cloisters under the direction of master Fernão Gonçalves: the ''Claustro do Cemitério'' (''Cemetery Cloister'') and ''Claustro das Lavagens'' (''Washing Cloister'').&lt;ref name=SIPA/&gt; Prior to these large works, Henry began work on constructing the Chapel of São Jorge sometime in 1426 and was responsible for urban improvements in the town of Tomar.&lt;ref name=SIPA/&gt;

In 1484, King D. [[Manuel I of Portugal|Manuel]] (who became Master of the Order in 1484 and King of Portugal in 1492) ordered the construction of a sacristy (today the Hall of Passage), that connected the choir to the Chapel of São Jorge, linking the choir with the wall of the stronghouse.&lt;ref name=SIPA/&gt; By the end of the century, the convent's General Chapter, decided to expand the convent (sometime around 1492), with 3,500 [[Portuguese real|reis]] being spent on the public works in 1499: the chapterhouse, main altar, ironworks for the niche/archway, paintings and sculptures (for the same) and the choir were all expanded or remodelled.&lt;ref name=SIPA/&gt;

A new meeting of the Chapter to reform the Order, ordered by the King 1503, expropriated the old Vila de Dentro, within the walls and closed the ''Sun Gate'' and ''Almedina Gate''.&lt;ref name=SIPA/&gt; On 11 October 1504, Francisco Lopes was nominated as masterbuilder for the project, by King [[John III of Portugal|John III]], receiving 8$000 reis annually and 120 reis for meals. By 1506, D. Manuel decided to order the construction of the church's [[nave]].&lt;ref name=SIPA/&gt;

The successor of Manuel I, [[John III of Portugal|King John III]], demilitarised the order, turning it into a more religious order with a rule based on that of [[Bernard of Clairvaux]]. He also ordered the construction of a new cloister in 1557, which is one of the best examples of [[Renaissance architecture]] in Portugal.

In 1581, after a [[Struggle for the throne of Portugal|succession crisis]], the Portuguese Nobility gathered in the Convent of Christ in Tomar and officially recognised [[Philip II of Spain]] (Philip I of Portugal) as King. This is the beginning of the [[Iberian Union]] (1581–1640), during which the Crowns of Portugal and Spain were united in a [[dynastic union]]. The aqueduct of the Convent was built during this period (aqueduct completed in 1614).

==Architecture==
[[File:TomarChurchPlanCC3.jpg|thumb|235px|left|Floorplan of the church of the Convent of Christ. The Templar round church (late 12th century) is indicated in red, while the manueline nave (early 16th century) is in blue.]]
[[File:Tomar-Convento de Cristo-Portal da igreja-20140914.jpg|170px|thumb|The entrance of the Convent church in [[Manueline]] style.]]
[[File:RotundaTomar1.jpg|thumb|170px|Interior of the Round church decorated with late Gothic painting and sculpture.]]
The castle and Convent of Christ have examples of [[Romanesque architecture|Romanesque]], [[Gothic architecture|Gothic]], [[Manueline]] and [[Renaissance]] architectural styles.

===Castle===
The castle of Tomar was built around 1160 on a strategic location, over a hill and near river Nabão. It has an outer defensive wall and a [[citadel]] (''alcáçova'') with a [[keep]] inside. The Keep, a central tower of residential and defensive functions, was introduced in Portugal by the Templars, and the one in Tomar is one of the oldest in the country. Another novelty introduced in Portugal by the Templars (learned from decades of experience in Normandy and Brittany and elsewhere) are the round towers in the outer walls, which are more resistant to attacks than square towers. When the town was founded, most of its residents lived in dwellings located inside the protective outer walls of the castle.

===Church===

The Romanesque round church is a [[Roman Catholic Church]] from the castle (''charola'', ''rotunda'') was built in the second half of the 12th century by the Knights Templar. From the outside, the church is a 16-side polygonal structure, with strong buttresses, round windows and a bell-tower. Inside, the round church has a central, octagonal structure, connected by arches to a surrounding gallery ([[ambulatory]]). The general shape of the church is modelled after similar round structures in [[Jerusalem]]: the [[Mosque of Omar]] and the [[Church of the Holy Sepulchre]].

The [[capital (architecture)|capital]]s of the columns are still Romanesque (end of the 12th century) and depict vegetal and animal motifs, as well as a ''Daniel in the Lions' Den'' scene. The style of the capitals shows the influence of artists working on the [[Old Cathedral of Coimbra|Cathedral of Coimbra]], which was being built at the same time as the round church.

The interior of the round church is magnificently decorated with late gothic/manueline sculpture and paintings, added during a renovation sponsored by King Manuel I starting in 1499. The pillars of the central octagon and the walls of the ambulatory have polychrome statues of saints and angels under exuberant Gothic canopies, while the walls and ceilings of the ambulatory are painted with Gothic patterns and panels depicting the life of Christ. The paintings are attributed to the workshop of the court painter of Manuel I, the Portuguese [[Jorge Afonso]], while the sculptured decoration is attributed to Flemish sculptor ''Olivier de Gand'' and the Spaniard ''Hernán Muñoz''. A magnificent panel depicting the [[martyrdom]] of [[Saint Sebastian]], by Portuguese painter [[Gregório Lopes]], was painted for the Round Church and now hangs in the [[National Museum of Ancient Art]] in [[Lisbon]].
{{Clear}}

===Manueline nave===
[[File:Convento Cristo December 2008-10.jpg|thumb|left|235px|Detail of the round church, view from the nave]]
[[File:Convento_Cristo_December_2008-11.jpg|thumb|170px|right|The famous chapterhouse window, made by Diogo de Arruda in 1510-1513.]]
During the administration of [[Henry the Navigator|Prince Henry the Navigator]] (first half of the 15th century), a gothic nave was added to the round church of the Convent, thus turning the round church into a church [[apse]]. From 1510 onwards, [[Manuel I of Portugal|King Manuel I]] ordered the rebuilding of the nave in the style of the time, a mix of late gothic and renaissance that would be called [[Manueline|Manueline style]] by art historians. The architects involved were the Portuguese ''[[Diogo de Arruda]]'' and the Spaniard ''[[Juan de Castillo|João de Castilho]]''.

From the outside, the rectangular nave is covered by abundant Manueline motifs, including gargoyles, gothic pinnacles, statues and &quot;ropes&quot; that remind the ones used in the ships during the [[Age of Discovery]], as well as the Cross of the Order of Christ and the emblem of King Manuel I, the [[armillary sphere]]. The so-called Window of the Chapter House (''Janela do Capítulo''), a huge window visible from the Saint Barbara Cloister in the Western façade of the nave, carries most of the typical Manueline motifs: the symbols of the Order of Christ and of Manuel I, and fantastic and unprecedented elaborations of ropes, corals and vegetal motifs. A human figure in the bottom of the window probably represents the designer, Diogo de Arruda. This window of the Convent constitutes one of the masterworks of Manueline decoration. Above is a smaller circular window and a balustrade. The façade is divided by two string courses of knotted ropes. The round angle buttresses are decorated with gigantic garters (alluding to investiture of Manuel I by the [[Order of the Garter]] by the English king [[Henry VII of England|Henry VII]]).

The entrance of the church is done through a magnificent lateral portal, also decorated with abundant Manueline motifs and statues of the Virgin with the Child as well as the Prophets of the Old Testament. This portal was designed by João de Castilho around 1530.

In the interior, the Manueline nave is connected to the Romanesque round church by a large arch. The nave is covered by beautiful [[rib vault|ribbed vaulting]] and has a high choir that used to have Manueline choir stalls, unfortunately destroyed by [[Peninsular War|invading Napoleonic troops]] in the early 19th century. Under the high choir there is a room that used to be the sacristy of the church. Its window is the famous Chapter House Window already mentioned.

===Cloisters===
[[File:Convento Cristo December 2008-1.jpg|thumb|235px|left|[[Gothic architecture|Gothic]] Cloister of the Cemetery (first half of the 15th century).]]
The Convent of Christ has a total of eight [[cloister]]s, built in the 15th and 16th centuries. Some examples:
*'''Claustro da Lavagem''' (Washing Cloister): Two-storey gothic cloister built around 1433 under Henry the Navigator. The garments of the monks used to be washed in this cloister, hence the name.
*'''Claustro do Cemitério''' (Cloister of the Cemetery): Also built under Henry the Navigator, this gothic cloister was the burial site for the knights and monks of the Order. The elegant twin columns of the arches have beautiful capitals with vegetal motifs, and the walls of the [[ambulatory]] are decorated with 16th-century [[tile]]s. In a manueline tomb (circa 1523) rests ''Diogo da Gama'', brother of navigator [[Vasco da Gama]].
*'''Claustro de Santa Bárbara''' (Saint Barbara's Cloister): Built in the 16th century. The Chapter House Window and the West façade of the manueline nave of the church are visible from this cloister.
*'''Claustro de D. João III''' (Cloister of John III): Started under [[John III of Portugal|King John III of Portugal]], was finished during the reign of [[Philip I of Portugal]] (also King of Spain under the name of Philip II). The first architect was [[Diogo de Torralva]], who began the work in 1557, to be finished in 1591 by Philip II's architect, the Italian [[Filippo Terzi]]. This magnificent, two-storey cloister connects the dormitory of the monks to the church, and is considered one of the most important examples of [[Mannerist]] architecture in Portugal. The storeys are connected to each other by four elegant helicoidal stairways, located at each corner of the cloisters.

==See also==
* [[History of Medieval Arabic and Western European domes]]

==References==
;Notes
{{Reflist|30em}}
;Sources
* {{citation |title=Portugal/1 - Europa Romanica |first=Gerhard N |last=Graf |publisher=Ediciones Encuentro |location=Madrid, Portugal |year=1987}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Convento de Cristo}}
* [http://www.conventocristo.pt/en/ Official webpage]
* [http://3d.culturaonline.pt/Content/Common/VirtualTour/Index.htm?id=82e66d80-439e-4f29-bc9b-576e98efee57 Virtual tour]

{{World Heritage Sites in Portugal}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Convent Of The Order Of Christ}}
[[Category:12th-century Roman Catholic church buildings]]
[[Category:Romanesque architecture in Portugal]]
[[Category:Gothic architecture in Portugal]]
[[Category:Manueline architecture]]
[[Category:Renaissance architecture in Portugal]]
[[Category:Castles and fortifications of the Knights Templar]]
[[Category:Christianity in Portugal]]
[[Category:Convents in Portugal]]
[[Category:World Heritage Sites in Portugal]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Santarém District]]
[[Category:Tomar]]
[[Category:Order of Christ (Portugal)]]</text>
      <sha1>f5iuvz1agbugln1frtt1znyyv4bqu8u</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
