<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Craigie Castle</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>23436496</id>
    <revision>
      <id>735200037</id>
      <parentid>706975734</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-19T05:43:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* top */http&amp;rarr;https for [[Internet Archive]] (see [[WP:VPR/Archive 127#RfC: Should we convert existing Google and Internet Archive links to HTTPS?|this RfC]]) using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="26876">{{Infobox Military Structure
|name=Craigie Castle
|location=Craigie, [[South Ayrshire]], [[Scotland]]&lt;br&gt;UK {{gbmapping|NS4084831699}}
|coordinates= NS 408 316
|image= [[File:Craigie Castle - the Keep.JPG|300px]] 
|caption=The keep of Craigie Castle
|map_type= Scotland South Ayrshire
|latitude=55.552778
|longitude=-4.524722
|map_size=
|map_caption= Location within South Ayrshire
|type=
|built=12th century
|builder=
|controlledby=[[Clan Lindsay|Lindsay clan]]
|materials=Stone
|height=
|used=Until 17th century
|condition=Ruined
|ownership=
|open_to_public= No
}}
'''Craigie Castle''' (NGR  NS 40848 31699) in the old Barony of Craigie, is a ruined [[fortification]] situated about {{convert|4|mi}} southeast of [[Kilmarnock]] and {{convert|1|mi}} southeast of Craigie village, in the Civil Parish of Craigie, [[South Ayrshire]], [[Scotland]]. &lt;ref&gt;The Imperial gazetteer of Scotland. 1854. Vol.I. (AAN-GORDON) by Rev. John Marius Wilson. pp.307-308. https://archive.org/stream/imperialgazettee01wils#page/307/mode/1up&lt;/ref&gt; The castle is recognised as one of the earliest buildings in the county.&lt;ref&gt;Close (2012), page 232&lt;/ref&gt;  It lies about {{convert|1.25|mi|0}} west-south-west of Craigie church.&lt;ref&gt;Groome, page 295&lt;/ref&gt; Craigie Castle is protected as a category B [[listed building]],&lt;ref name=listed/&gt; and a [[scheduled monument]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://data.historic-scotland.gov.uk/pls/htmldb/f?p=2300:35:4217815429352558::NO::P35_SELECTED_MONUMENT:315 |title=Craigie Castle |publisher=Historic Scotland}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== History of Craigie Castle ==
Craigie Castle was originally built for the Lyndesay or [[Clan Lindsay|Lindsay clan]]. The castle passed to John Wallace of Riccarton through marriage about 1371 as the last heir was a daughter. This line of the Ayrshire Wallaces then lived at Craigie Castle until they moved to Newton Castle in Ayr in 1588. Craigie Castle was then left to fall into ruin.&lt;ref name=&quot;Clan Wallace website&quot;&gt;[http://www.ayrshirescotland.com/clans/wallace.html Clan Wallace website]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Love, Ayrshire, page 211&lt;/ref&gt; It was the belief of Mrs Frances Dunlop of Dunlop, a lineal descendent of William Wallace, that he was born at his grandfather's home of Craigie Castle. William only moved away after a number of years had passed due to the burgeoning size of the family and the lack of space at Craigie.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell (1817), Page 125&lt;/ref&gt;

===Descriptions of the castle===
[[File:Craigie Castle from Craigie Mains.JPG|left|thumb|200px|Craigie Castle from Craigie Mains farm]]
[[File:Craigie Castle Keep - East View.JPG|thumb|200px|The south facing wall of the keep showing high quality stonework]]
[[File:Craigie Castle - Entrance pend.JPG|thumb|200px|Part of a courtyard wall.]]
The present Gothic castellated ruins date mainly from the 15th century,&lt;ref&gt;Close, page 53&lt;/ref&gt; with some 12th or 13th century work. Another view is that the main part of the building was a [[hall house]] dating from the 12th or 13th century, incorporating an even earlier building&lt;ref&gt;Campbell, page 158&lt;/ref&gt; which may have been built by the predecessors of Walter Hose who held sway prior to Anglo-Norman control.&lt;ref name=&quot;C159&quot;/&gt;

The buildings were surrounded by ditches and natural lochans; enclosing an area of about {{convert|4|acre|m2}}. It had a high quality rib-vaulted hall consisting of three bays over an unvaulted basement, but architectural historians have found traces of an earlier hall which had a crenellated parapet rising flush with the main wall-face. In the centre of one wall was a round-arched doorway, and opposite this a late medieval fireplace, added in the 15th century, was built over another round-arched opening.

The castle contains one of the finest examples of a vaulted hall in Scotland, easily equal to any Scottish abbey or church. The only rivals of the same period are [[Tulliallan]], [[Bothwell]], and Auchendoun.&lt;ref&gt;Macgibbon and Ross, page 296&lt;/ref&gt; It has been stated that in its time Craigie was the most impressive building of its kind in Ayrshire.&lt;ref&gt;Cuthbertson, Pages 146-147&lt;/ref&gt;

Due to the condition of the structures it has proved difficult to determine the original plan, but the remains suggest that it was originally a simple rectangle of suitable size for a building such as an early hall-house. Craigie Castle may originally have been a hall-house of the late 12th or early 13th century with a wide crenellate parapet enclosing a [[saddleback roof]]. During the 15th century it seems that these crenellations were built over and a new hall fashioned on the walls of its predecessor.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.visitdunkeld.com/craigie-castle-ayrshire-scotland.html Tour Scotland]&lt;/ref&gt;

The ruins stand upon a knoll rising out of a plateau, between what appears to have been two marshes or lochans, and the ditches were originally cut between them. One ditch cuts the ridge 117m NE of the castle to form an outer bailey. The castle would have been effectively isolated from the 'mainland', and a significant barrier raised by the water to any potential besiegers at the period when the use of gunpowder was unknown. Two crumbling gables, portions of walls, and shreds of battlements remain, and in the 19th century several underground vaulted chambers survived, although partly filled with rubbish, and home to foxes and bats.&lt;ref&gt;Adamson, page 63&lt;/ref&gt; The entrance to the castle was at the south-west side by a drawbridge,&lt;ref name=&quot;M77&quot;&gt;Mackintosh, page 77&lt;/ref&gt; of which the abutment still survives.&lt;ref&gt;Canmore, RCAHMS&lt;/ref&gt; The entrance pend or arched passage had a circular watch-tower or bastion to defend it. Within the closing wall was a courtyard surrounded by buildings, and from this courtyard there was an entrance into the great hall, long blocked up.&lt;ref&gt;Mcgibbon and Ross, page 300&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Craigie Castle, Ayrshire - Plan.jpg|left|thumb|200px|A plan of the castle.]]
In 1895 Smith records that ''at a distance of 145 paces from to the north-east of the castle a deep trench has been cut in a north-west and south-east direction for a distance of 162 paces, to connect the two lochans. Near the south wall of the castle there is another trench, and a section of building is to be seen on the outside of it. On the west side there are the remains of a third trench.''&lt;ref&gt;Smith, pages 129&amp;ndash;130&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1863 Paterson records that the tower was undergoing some repairs at the end of the 17th century when a part of the roof fell in, after which the castle was completely abandoned. He praises the high degree of military science employed in the construction of the castle where besiegers would be exposed to raking crossfire even after crossing the ditches / moats and would be outflanked on nearly all sides.&lt;ref&gt;Paterson, Kyle, V.1., Part 1, pages 263&amp;ndash;264&lt;/ref&gt;

A 'Kragy' castle is marked on [[Timothy Pont]]'s map of c.1600. It is shown on an elevated area with a prominent entrance way, wooded policies and a surrounding [[Wiktionary:pale#Noun|pale]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Pont's map by Blaeu&quot;&gt;[http://www.nls.uk/maps/atlas/blaeu/page.cfm?id=85 Pont's map by Blaeu]&lt;/ref&gt;

Although now a minor road, the road running near the castle (B730) was the main route from Irvine to Dumfries via Sanquhar, with a nearby link to the Ayr&amp;ndash;Kilmarnock road; Craigie was therefore on one of the few reasonable standard communication routes in the area in the 18th and earlier centuries. The numerous [[Run rig|rigs]] on Roy's 1747 map show that the whole area was intensively cultivated at the time.&lt;ref&gt;[http://geo.nls.uk/roy/ Roy's map]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Crannog===
[[File:Map of Dunduff castle &amp; roads.jpg|thumb|upright|William Aiton's map of 1811 showing Craigie.]]
As late as the 19th century a likely [[crannóg]] was visible in the boggy hollow 'just to the south-west' of Craigie Castle; it was described as ''a slight rise in the meadow...mostly composed of stones''. When the hollow was drained an oar was found.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rcahms.gov.uk/ Canmore]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Smith, page 129&lt;/ref&gt;

===Moot hills===
Smith records [[moot hill]]s near Craigie village, Knockmarloch and Highlangside. The barony would originally have had a Moot or Justice Hill and a [[Dule Tree|gallows hill]].&lt;ref&gt;Smith, page 128&lt;/ref&gt;

===Borland Farms===
Two Borland Farms are now located near Craigie village and this may relate directly to Craigie Castle. The name 'Boarland' could possibly refer to the presence of wild boar, however a more likely origin is that a 'Boor' also meant a serf and Norman lords often apportioned lands near their castles for their servants.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bayne&quot;&gt;Bayne, John F. (1935). ''Dunlop Parish &amp;ndash; A History of Church, Parish, and Nobility''. Pub. T.&amp; A. Constable, pages 10&amp;ndash;16.&lt;/ref&gt; The Borland or Bordland also meant the land that was specifically used to furnish food for a castle.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mackenzie&quot;&gt;Mackenzie, W. Mackay (1927). ''The Mediaeval Castle in Scotland.'' Pub. Methuen &amp; Co. Ltd. P. 29.&lt;/ref&gt; A 'Boirland' is marked on the [[Timothy Pont]] map as far back as the late 16th&amp;nbsp;/&amp;nbsp;early 17th century.&lt;ref name=&quot;Pont's map by Blaeu&quot;/&gt;

===Listed status===
Craigie Castle was [[Listed building|listed]] at Category B by [[Historic Scotland]], an [[executive agency]] of the [[Scottish Government]], on 14 April 1971.&lt;ref name=listed&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hsewsf.sedsh.gov.uk/hslive/hsstart?P_HBNUM=976|title=Listed Building Report: Craigie Castle|year=2009|work=Statutory List of listed buildings in Scotland|publisher=[[Historic Scotland]]|accessdate=2009-07-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Such buildings are considered to be &quot;of regional or more than local importance&quot;, and gain legal protection against unauthorised demolition, extension or significant alteration.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.historic-scotland.gov.uk/index/heritage/historicandlistedbuildings/listing.htm|title=Historic Scotland – Looking after our heritage|year=2009|publisher=[[Historic Scotland]]|accessdate=2009-07-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.historic-scotland.gov.uk/index/heritage/historicandlistedbuildings/altering-a-listed-building.htm|title=Historic Scotland &amp;ndash; Looking after our heritage – Altering a listed building|year=2009|publisher=[[Historic Scotland]]|accessdate=2009-07-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Craigie Mains farm==
[[File:WallaceLindsay arms, Ayrshire, Craigie Castle.JPG|thumb|200px|The conjoined Lindsay and Wallace Coats of Arms with supporters.]]
[[File:LindsayWallace arms detail, Craigie Castle, Ayrshire.JPG|left|thumb|100px|Detail of the conjoined Wallace and Lindsay arms.]]
An armorial plaque from the castle ruins&lt;ref name=&quot;M77&quot;/&gt; is set in the wall of the steading (NS 4 062 3174). The naive peasantry at one time believed that the stone showed two wild men playing at [[draughts]].&lt;ref&gt;Paterson, Kyle, V.1., Part 1, page 264&lt;/ref&gt; It bears the impaled arms of the Lindsays and Wallaces.

James Kilpatrick of Craigie Mains was a great horseman who considerably improved the breeding lines of the Clydesdale horse&lt;ref&gt;Macintosh, page 295&lt;/ref&gt; and was famous throughout Britain and the World. Some his champions were 1918, Craigie Litigant; 1921, Craigie Excellence; 1924, Craigie McQuaid; 1925, Craigie Exquisite; 1929, Craigie Winalot; 1930, Craigie Beau Ideal; 1933, Craigie Realisation; 1935, Craigie Magnificent; 1939, Craigie Independent; 1941, Craigie Topsman; 1942, Craigie Chieftain; 1947, Craigie Supreme Commander; 1948, Craigie True Form. In 1951 Craigie Mains had about 80 head of horses.&lt;ref&gt;Strawhorn &amp; Boyd, Page 599&lt;/ref&gt; James Kilpatrick regularly exhibited his Clydesdales, colts and fillies in all their finery at the annual Craigie Agricultural Show in the 1900s.&lt;ref&gt;Wall, Page 56&lt;/ref&gt;

The famous 'Baron of Buchlyvie' was purchased for £700 by Mr Kilpatrick in 1902 and was the stud horse at the mains in 1903. Mr William Dunlop of Dunure Mains had a half share and after much disagreement the 'baron' ended up at Dunlop Mains, having been sold at auction or £9,500; an unheard of sum for a Clydsedale at the time. The mounted skelton of this horse is now on display at the Kelvingrove Art Gallery and Museum in Glasgow.&lt;ref&gt;Shaw, Page 177&lt;/ref&gt;

Matthew Anderson the 'Policeman Poet' wrote a poem in honour of Symington and Craigie. 

This is an extract -

{| cellpadding=10 border=&quot;0&quot; align=center
|-
| bgcolor=#f4f4f4|
&quot;The greatest place beneath the sky,&lt;br&gt;
For Clydesdale horse and Ayrshire Kye,&lt;br&gt;
In all the bliss of perfect joy,&lt;br&gt;
They roam the fields sae lovely.&lt;br&gt;
There's Craigie Mains and Laigh Langside,&lt;br&gt;
In them we feel a special pride,&lt;br&gt;
Their name and fame are World wide.&lt;br&gt;
Then hip, hurrah for Craigie!&quot;&lt;br&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;R45&quot;&gt;Reid, Page 45&lt;/ref&gt;
|}

== The Hoses and Lindsays of Craigie ==
In the 12th century Walter fitz Alan, Steward of Scotland, held these lands and Walter Hose held his fief from the Steward.&lt;ref name=&quot;C159&quot;&gt;Campbell, Page 159&lt;/ref&gt; In 1177 Walter Hose of Cragyn had given the church of Cragyn to the monks of Paisley. John, probably Walter's son, inherited and his son Thomas had no heir, resulting in his sisters Christiana and Matilda inheriting. Walter de Lyndesay, Knight, was the son of Christiana, the father being William Lyndesey of Crawfurd. The male line ended with John de Lyndesey, whose daughter married John Wallace of Riccarton.&lt;ref&gt;Paterson, Kyle, V.1, pages 282&amp;ndash;3&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Craigie Castle keep - West view.JPG|A view of the keep facing North
File:Craigie Castle - West Keep wall from the East.JPG|The keep from the South East 
File:Craigie Castle - Keep and Great Hall.JPG|The keep and great hall 
File:Craigie Castle - East keep wall.JPG|The South facing wall of the keep
File:Craigie castle view.jpg|Craigie Castle in 1850
&lt;/gallery&gt;

== The Wallaces of Craigie ==
[[File:Craigie Castle, Ayrshire.jpg|thumb|200px|Craigie Castle in the 1860s.]]
[[File:Craigie castle hall, Ayrshire - east view.jpg|thumb|200px|An east view of the Great Hall.]]
[[File:Craigie castle, Ayrshire - hall.jpg|thumb|200px|The Great Hall - detail.]]
John Wallace of Riccarton in the reign of [[David II of Scotland|David II]] had a charter of lands of Moorlecere in Forfarshire and was styled 'Wallayis of Richardtoun'. John married the heiress of Lindsay of Craigie circa 1371 and from this date Craigie was the chief residence of the family.&lt;ref&gt;Paterson, Kyle, V.1, Part 2, page 655&lt;/ref&gt;

John Wallace was Lieutenant-General to [[James II of Scotland|James II]], and fought at the [[Battle of Sark]] in 1447, killing the English General Magnus with his own hands. John was injured on the battlefield and died of his wounds at Craigie Castle about three months later.&lt;ref name=&quot;M77&quot;/&gt;

In the second half of the 15th century the Wallace family had [[Blind Harry]] write his poem ''[[The Actes and Deidis of the Illustre and Vallyeant Campioun Schir William Wallace|The Wallace]]'', which recorded the story of Sir William Wallace, albeit 150 years after his death.&lt;ref name=&quot;C586&quot;&gt;Coventry, Page 586&lt;/ref&gt;

An Adam Wallace was Comptroller of the Household of James III in 1468.&lt;ref&gt;Paterson, Kyle, V.1, page 285&lt;/ref&gt; John Wallace was killed at the [[Battle of Flodden]] in 1513; his brother Adam inherited and became oversmen of [[Prestwick]] in addition to Bailie of Kyle Stewart. In 1515 he was made alderman of Ayr and controlled the Royal Burgh for a decade.&lt;ref name=&quot;Strawhorn, page 28&quot;&gt;Strawhorn, page 28&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1559 Sir John Wallace accompanied the Earl of Glencairn, the Lords Boyd and Ochiltree, the Sheriff of Ayr, the Laird of Cessnock and others, with a body of 2500 men to Perth in support of the Covenanters or [[Scottish Reformation|reformers]].&lt;ref&gt;Paterson, Kyle, V.1. page 287&lt;/ref&gt;

Sir William Wallace commanded a cavalry under James VII (James II of England) and went into exile in France with him.&lt;ref name=&quot;M77&quot;/&gt; He was at the [[Battle of Killiecrankie]] and died circa 1700; his brother succeeded to the estates, much impoverished by Sir William's adherence to the Jacobite cause.&lt;ref&gt;Paterson, Kyle, V.1. page 294&lt;/ref&gt;

The Wallaces of Craigie became hereditary Bailies of Kyle Stewart and as such were the chief local representatives of the Crown. In 1489 John Wallace obtained a lease to mine coal near Kingcase in Prestwick.&lt;ref name=&quot;Strawhorn, page 28&quot;/&gt;

In 1527 Gilbert Kennedy, 2nd Earl of Cassillis was ambushed and murdered on the sand dunes at Prestwick. Adam Wallace was implicated in this essentially Campbell inspired feud, as his wife, Dame Isabelle, was said to have planned the assassination. The controversy resulted in a loss of prestige and influence.&lt;ref&gt;Strawhorn, page 29&lt;/ref&gt;

Sir Hugh Wallace was a supporter of the Royalist cause of Charles I and II, for which his estate was sequestered and only returned when [[Charles II of England|Charles II]] came to the throne. Sir Hugh had raised a regiment of foot at his own expense,&lt;ref name=&quot;M78&quot;/&gt; resulting in great debts, sale of lands and in 1626 the disposal of the heritable Kyle bailieship to the Crown for £10,000 Scots.&lt;ref&gt;Paterson, Kyle, V.1. page 290&lt;/ref&gt; Sir Hugh Wallace, the laird referred to below, was knighted by [[Charles I of England|Charles I]] and in 1669 Charles II conferred [[Wallace Baronets|a Baronetcy]] upon him. All his sons predeceased him and Thomas, a grandnephew inherited.&lt;ref&gt;Paterson, Kyle, V.1. page 292&lt;/ref&gt; He was most liberal in his ideas, fought with [[James Graham, 1st Marquess of Montrose|Montrose]] at the [[Battle of Philiphaugh]] and died about 1650.&lt;ref name=&quot;M78&quot;&gt;Macintosh, page 78&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Adamson, pages 63–65&quot;&gt;Adamson, pages 63&amp;ndash;65.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1770 Sir Thomas Wallace died and the baronetcy was inherited by his grandson Thomas Dunlop, who sold off the estate of Craigie in 1783,&lt;ref&gt;Strawhorn, page 58&lt;/ref&gt; moved to England and died within three years. He adopted the name Wallace, his mother being Frances Anne Wallace of Dunlop, Sir Thomas's daughter and sole heir; his father was John Dunlop of that Ilk. His son was Major-General Sir John Alexander Wallace who fought in India, Egypt, Spain and France and died in 1857.&lt;ref&gt;Paterson, Kyle, V.1. page 296&lt;/ref&gt;

The Wallaces married into a number of local aristocratic families, notably the Campbells of Loudoun and the Blairs of Blair. At Blair Castle above a door are the armorial bearings of the Blairs Of Blair and the Wallaces of Craigie, dated 1617. Bryce Blair married Annabel Wallace.&lt;ref&gt;Dobie, page 82&lt;/ref&gt;

In the 1560s the Wallace family acquired [[Fail Monastery]], however it was later granted to Walter Whytford and passed out of their hands.&lt;ref&gt;Love (2003), Page 209&lt;/ref&gt;

===Coat of arms===
[[File:LindsayWallace arms at Craigie Castle, Ayrshire.JPG|left|thumb|200px|Wallace and Lyndsay Coat of Arms and supporters.]]
Those of Sir John Alexander Wallace were quarterly : first and fourth, [[Gules]], a Lion rampant, [[Or (heraldry)|Or]], within an [[Orle (heraldry)|Orle]]; second and third, Gules, a fesse Cheque of three, [[Argent]] and [[Azure (heraldry)|Azure]]. The Supporters were two savages, proper, with Clubs erect. The family crest was an Ostrich neck and head erect, issuing out of an open crown, with a horseshoe in the mouth. The motto was [[wiktionary:esperanza#Noun|Esperanza]], Spanish for 'Hope'.&lt;ref&gt;Paterson, Kyle, V.1. pages 296&amp;ndash;7&lt;/ref&gt;

== The legend of the fall of the Wallaces of Craigie ==
The Lairds of Craigie are said to have cared little for the religious discipline of the [[presbyterian]]s, and the Laird of Craigie, Sir Hugh Wallace, allowed his tenants or servants to work on Sundays, and he himself traveled openly upon the Sabbath day. The other local ministers of the places involved wrote to the Laird's local minister, Mr. Inglish, about ''such open and scandalous breaches of the Sabbath''.

The Laird ignored the ministers' advice and when in church he actually threw his sword at the minister, the sword sticking in the wood at the back of the pulpit. The minister recovered and told the Laird that God will reduce your ''great stone house'' to a pile of stones and ''no one will be able to repair it; and your son, of whom you have great hopes, will die a fool''. Before long the castle was in need of repair, and when the stonemasons started work a great part of it fell down and had almost buried them all.&lt;ref name=&quot;M78&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Adamson, pages 63–65&quot;/&gt; The story may have a grain of truth as Sir Hugh, as stated, was an ardent supporter of the [[Episcopal polity|episcopalian]] sentiments of Charles I and II and was no friend of the Presbyterians.

==Craigie House==
[[File:Barnweill. View of Craigie Castle, etc..JPG|left|thumb|200px|A view of Craigie Castle in its landscape from Barnweill Kirk ruins.]]
[[File:Mrsdunlopofdunlop.jpg|thumb|150px|Mrs. [[Frances Anne Walker Dunlop|Frances Dunlop]] of [[Dunlop, East Ayrshire|Dunlop]], Patron and correspondent of [[Robert Burns and the Eglinton Estate|Robert Burns]].&lt;ref&gt;Hogg, page 107&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dougall, pages 111&amp;ndash;112&lt;/ref&gt; She was the daughter and sole heiress to Sir Thomas Wallace of Craigie.]]
In the 1730s, Craigie House (NGR NS 34970 21386) in Ayr was built as a replacement residence for Sir Thomas Wallace of Newton-on-Ayr Castle, the fifth baronet; nothing of Newton Castle, previously known as Sanquhar,&lt;ref&gt;[http://geo.nls.uk/roy/ Roy map]&lt;/ref&gt; now remains. In 1783 William Campbell, who made his fortune in India, purchased the principal portion of the Craigie estate. His brother, Richard Campbell of Craigie inherited the estate in 1823 and the property remained in the Campbell family for a number of generations.&lt;ref&gt;Paterson, Kyle, V.1, page 297&lt;/ref&gt; The family included lawyers and politicians, one being the Member for the [[Ayr Burghs (UK Parliament constituency)|Ayr Burghs]].&lt;ref&gt;Millar, page 58&lt;/ref&gt;

Craigie House and estate was purchased from the Campbell family by Ayr Town Council in 1940. The gardens that run from the centre of Ayr northeast alongside the River Ayr are open to the public free of charge, however the house is used as offices for the [[University of the West of Scotland]] and various building works are proposed for the gardens area.&lt;ref name=&quot;Clan Wallace website&quot;/&gt;

== Newton-on-Ayr Castle ==
The Wallaces constructed this castle (previously known as Sanquhar) circa the 15th century, however it became the property of Sir William Hamilton, Provost of Ayr; having been granted it in 1539 by the King. John Wallace of Craigie with forty others forcefully regained it in 1559; they were forced eventually to return it to the Hamiltons, however in 1558 the Wallaces confirmed their ownership and moved in shortly after. The castle was severely damaged in a storm in 1701 and was finally demolished in the second half of the 18th century. Nothing of the tower now remains.&lt;ref&gt;Love, page 17&lt;/ref&gt;

==Micro-history==
The Eglinton Hunt regularly visited Craigie's hill, cover, knowes and glens in the 1900s. A kill resulted in a meal for the dogs and the bushy tail presented to the first lady.&lt;ref&gt;Walls, Pages 57 &amp; 58&lt;/ref&gt;

The small loch below the manse was used as the curling pond in the 1900s; the [[curling house]] ruins are still standing (2009).&lt;ref&gt;Walls, Page 62&lt;/ref&gt;

in 1584 William Wallace of Ellerslie held the lands of Mains of Helentoun and Bogend, together with the tower, fortalice, and manor place of [[Helenton Loch|Helenton]], together with half of the mill.&lt;ref name=&quot;P749&quot;&gt;Paterson, Page 749&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Auchans, Ayrshire]] A Wallace castle

== References ==
;Notes
{{Reflist|3}}

;Sources
{{refbegin|3}}
# Adamson, Archibald R. (1875). ''Rambles Round Kilmarnock''. Kilmarnock : T. Stevenson.
# Campbell, Hugh (1817). ''The Wanderer in Ayrshire : A Tour''. Kilmarnock : Hugh Campbell. 
# Campbell, Thorbjørn (2003). ''Ayrshire. A Historical Guide.'' Edinburgh : Birlinn. ISBN 1-84158-267-0.
# Canmore Website
# Close, Robert (1992). ''Ayrshire and Arran: An Illustrated Architectural Guide''. Pub. Roy Inc Arch Scot. ISBN. 1873190-06-9.
# Close, Rob and Riches, Anne (2012). ''Ayrshire and Arran, The Buildings of Scotland''. New Haven : Yale University Press. ISBN 978-0-300-14170-2.
# Coventry, Martin (2010). ''Castles of the Clans''. Musselburgh : Goblinshead. ISBN 1-899874-36-4.
# Cuthbertson, David Cuningham (1945). ''Autumn in Kyle and the Charm of Cunninghame''. London : Jenkins.
# Dobie, James D. (ed Dobie, J.S.) (1876). ''Cunninghame, Topographized by Timothy Pont 1604–1608, with continuations and illustrative notices''. Glasgow : John Tweed.
# Dougall, Charles S. (1911). ''The Burns Country''. London : A &amp; C Black.
# Groome, Francis H. (1903). ''Ordnance Gazetteer of Scotland''. London : Caxton.
# Hogg, Patrick Scott (2008). ''Robert Burns. The Patriot Bard''. Edinburgh : Mainstream Publishing. ISBN 978-1-84596-412-2.
# Love, Dane (2003). ''Ayrshire : Discovering a County''. Ayr : Fort Publishing. ISBN. 0-9544461-1-9.
# Love, Dane (2005). ''Lost Ayrshire : Ayrshire's Lost Architectural Heritage''. Edinburgh : Birlinn Ltd. ISBN. 1-84158-3561-1.
# MacGibbon, T. and Ross, D. (1887&amp;ndash;92). ''The castellated and domestic architecture of Scotland from the twelfth to the eighteenth centuries'', 5v, Edinburgh.
# Macintosh, John (1894). ''Ayrshire Nights' Entertainments''. Kilmarnock : Dunlop and Drennan.
# Millar, A. H. (1885). ''The Castles and Mansions of Ayrshire''. Glasgow : The Grimsay Press. ISBN 1-84530-019-X.
# [[James Paterson (journalist)|Paterson, James]] (1847). (Edit). ''The Ballads and Songs of Ayrshire.'' Edinburgh : T. G. Stevenson.
# Paterson, James (1863&amp;ndash;66). ''History of the Counties of Ayr and Wigton''. V. &amp;ndash; III &amp;ndash; Cunninghame. Edinburgh: J. Stillie.
# Reid, Donald L. (2009). ''Discovering Matthew Anderson. Policeman-Poet of Ayrshire.'' Beith : Cleland Crosbie. ISBN 0-9522720-9-1
# Robertson, William (1889). ''Historical Tales and Legends of Ayrshire''. Pub. Hamilton, Adams &amp; Co.
# Shaw, James Edward (1953). ''Ayrshire 1745-1950. A Social and Industrial History of the county.'' Edinburgh : Oliver &amp; Boyd.
# Smith, John (1895). ''Prehistoric Man in Ayrshire''. London : Elliot Stock.
# [[John Strawhorn|Strawhorn, John]] (1994). ''The History of Prestwick''. Edinburgh : John Donald. ISBN 0-85976-405-2.
# Strawhorn, John and Boyd, William (1951). ''The Third Statistical Account of Scotland. Ayrshire.'' Edinburgh : Oliver &amp; Boyd.
# Walls, William (1926). ''Life, Love, and Light''. Edinburgh : Privately Published.
{{refend}}

{{commons category|Craigie Castle}}

==External links==
* [http://futuremuseum.co.uk/images/cache/Img871S1000.jpg Robert Byden's drawing of Craigie Castle]

{{coord|55.5529|N|4.5246|W|type:landmark_region:GB|display=title}}

[[Category:Castles in South Ayrshire]]
[[Category:Listed castles in Scotland]]
[[Category:Ruins in South Ayrshire]]
[[Category:History of South Ayrshire]]
[[Category:Category B listed buildings in South Ayrshire]]
[[Category:Scheduled Ancient Monuments in Scotland]]</text>
      <sha1>2dipzwaqkmtaekiaiebgoqsvz8ufh0k</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
