<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Daniel Shays</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>294829</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750974332</id>
      <parentid>750973317</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-22T16:22:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Billmckern</username>
        <id>1869658</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Undid revision 750973317 by [[Special:Contributions/50.200.231.209|50.200.231.209]] ([[User talk:50.200.231.209|talk]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18764">{{Infobox person
| name        = Daniel Shays
| image       = Daniel Shays (Shays' Rebellion).jpg
| caption     = From 1878's &quot;Our First Century&quot; by Richard Miller Devens.
| birth_date  = c.1747
| birth_place = [[Hopkinton, Massachusetts|Hopkinton]], [[Province of Massachusetts Bay|Massachusetts]]
| death_date  = {{death date|1825|9|29}}
| death_place = [[Sparta, New York|Sparta]], [[New York (state)|New York]], U.S.
| resting_place = Union Cemetery, Scottsburg, New York
| occupation  = [[farmer]], [[officer (armed forces)|military officer]]
| known_for     = [[American Revolutionary War|Revolutionary War]] Captain&lt;br /&gt;[[Shays' Rebellion]]
| networth =
| spouse      = Abigail Gilbert
| children    =
| residence   =
| alma_mater  =
| website     =
| signature   = DanielShays.svg
|module={{Infobox military person|embed=yes
|allegiance={{Flag|United States of America|1777}}
|branch={{Flagicon image|New England blank flag.svg}} [[List of militia units of Massachusetts|Massachusetts militia]]&lt;br/&gt;{{Flagicon image|Gadsden flag.svg}} [[Continental Army]]
|serviceyears=1775-1780
|rank=[[Captain (United States)|Captain]]
|unit={{Flagicon image|New England blank flag.svg}} [[5th Massachusetts Regiment]]
|battles=[[American Revolutionary War]]
*[[Boston campaign]]
**[[Battles of Lexington and Concord]]
*[[Battles of Saratoga]]
[[Shays' Rebellion]]
}}
}}

'''Daniel Shays''' (c. 1747 – September 29, 1825) was an [[United States|American]] soldier, revolutionary, and farmer famous for being one of the leaders of [[Shays' Rebellion]], a populist uprising against controversial debt collection and tax policies in [[Massachusetts]] in 1786 and 1787.

==Early life==
[[File:Daniel and Abigail Shays' Pelham, MA farmhouse.jpg|thumb|Daniel and Abigail Shays' Pelham, MA farmhouse, circa 1898. This &quot;Cape style&quot; home was typical amongst local farmers at the time. The house was destroyed and the surrounding lands flooded during the creation of the [[Quabbin Reservoir]] in the 1930s.]]
Daniel Shays was born in 1747 in [[Hopkinton, Massachusetts]], the son of two Irish immigrants, Patrick and Margaret (Dempsey) Shays. Daniel was the second of six siblings. He spent his early years as a landless farm laborer. In 1772, he married Abigail Gilbert, with whom he settled in [[Brookfield, Massachusetts]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Brown-2010-p220&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Brown, Lorri|chapter=Shays, Daniel (1747–1825)|editor=Danver Steven L.|title=Revolts, protests, demonstrations, and rebellions in American history: an encyclopedia|publisher=ABC-CLIO|year=2010|isbn=978-1-59884-221-0|page=220|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=A1C4W2IVHcMC&amp;pg=PA220}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Revolutionary War==
Shays joined the local militia during the American Revolution.  He rose to the rank of captain in the [[5th Massachusetts Regiment]] of the [[Continental Army]] by 1777.&lt;ref name=&quot;Brown-2010-p220&quot; /&gt; He was involved in the [[Boston campaign]], and fought at the [[Battle of Bunker Hill]].&lt;ref&gt;Richards, pf u. 95&lt;/ref&gt; He also fought in the [[Battle of Lexington]] and the [[Battle of Saratoga]]. He was wounded during the war and resigned from the military, unpaid, in 1780. Upon returning home, he discovered he was summoned to court for unpaid debts, which he still could not pay because he was not paid for military service.&lt;ref&gt;Zinn, pp. 71–72&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1780, Shays was presented with an ornamental sword by [[General Lafayette]], in honor of his military service. Shays later sold the sword for a few dollars to pay off his debts—an act which was frowned upon by his peers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Gross, Robert A.|chapter=The Uninvited Guest: Daniel Shays and the Constitution|editor=Gross, Robert A.|title=In Debt to Shays: The Bicentennial of an Agrarian Rebellion|publisher=University Press of Virginia|year=1993|isbn=978-0-8139-1354-4|page=1|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=HpSIYclyYogC&amp;pg=PA1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Shays' Rebellion==
[[File:Daniel Shays and Job Shattuck.jpg|thumb|275px|right|Contemporary engraving depicting Daniel Shays (left) and [[Job Shattuck]], another rebel leader; the artist intentionally rendered them in an unflattering way]]
{{Main|Shays' Rebellion}}

===Debt and tax burdens===
After returning from the war, Daniel Shays was alarmed to discover that many of his fellow veterans and farmers were in the same financial situation as he. Commoners' meetings revealed that veterans were treated unfairly upon release, and businessmen were trying to squeeze money out of smallholders in order to pay their own debts to European war investors. Many Massachusetts rural communities first tried to petition the legislature in Boston,&lt;ref&gt;Zinn, pp. 91–93&lt;/ref&gt; but the legislature was dominated by eastern merchant interests and did not respond substantively to those petitions.  The petitions and proposals often included a request to issue paper currency.  Such inflationary issues would depreciate the currency, making it possible to meet obligations made at high values with lower-valued paper.  The merchants, among them [[James Bowdoin]], were opposed, because they were generally lenders who stood to lose by such proposals.  As a result, these proposals were repeatedly rejected.&lt;ref&gt;Szatmary, pp. 38–42,45&lt;/ref&gt;  Governor [[John Hancock]], accused by some of anticipating trouble, abruptly resigned in early 1785.  When Bowdoin (a loser to Hancock in earlier elections) was elected governor that year, matters became more severe.  Bowdoin stepped up civil actions to collect back taxes, and the legislature exacerbated the situation by levying an additional property tax to raise funds for the state's portion of foreign debt payments.&lt;ref name=Richards87_8&gt;Richards, pp. 87–88&lt;/ref&gt;  Even comparatively conservative commentators like [[John Adams]] observed that these levies were &quot;heavier than the People could bear.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Richards, p. 88&lt;/ref&gt;

===Protests against the courts===
Protests in the rural Massachusetts turned into [[direct action]] in August 1786, after the state legislature adjourned without considering the many petitions that had been sent to Boston.&lt;ref&gt;Richards, pp. 6–9&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Szatmary, p. 38&lt;/ref&gt;  On August 29 a well-organized force of protestors, Shays among them, marched on [[Northampton, Massachusetts|Northampton]] and successfully prevented the county court from sitting.&lt;ref name=Morse208&gt;Morse, p. 208&lt;/ref&gt;  The leaders of this and later forces proclaimed that they were seeking relief from the burdensome judicial processes that were depriving the people of their land and possessions.  They called themselves ''Regulators'', a reference to the [[Regulator movement]] of [[North Carolina]] that sought to reform corrupt practices in the late 1760s.&lt;ref&gt;Szatmary, p. 56&lt;/ref&gt;  On September 2 Governor Bowdoin issued a proclamation denouncing such mob action, but took no military measures in response beyond planning militia response to future actions.&lt;ref name=Morse208/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Szatmary, pp. 79–80&lt;/ref&gt;   When the court in [[Worcester, Massachusetts|Worcester]] was shut down by similar action on September 5, the county militia (composed mainly of men sympathetic to the protestors) refused to turn out, much to Bowdoin's amazement.&lt;ref&gt;Szatmary, p. 80&lt;/ref&gt;

Shays, who had participated in the Northampton action, began to take a more active leadership role in the uprising in November.  On September 19, the [[Massachusetts Supreme Judicial Court|Supreme Judicial Court of Massachusetts]] indicted eleven leaders of the rebellion as &quot;disorderly, riotous, and seditious persons.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;zinn93&quot;&gt;Zinn, p. 93&lt;/ref&gt;  When the supreme judicial court was next scheduled to meet in [[Springfield, Massachusetts|Springfield]] on September 26, Shays in [[Hampshire County, Massachusetts|Hampshire County]] and [[Luke Day]] in what is now [[Hampden County, Massachusetts|Hampden County]] (but was then part of Hampshire County) organized an attempt to shut it down.  They were anticipated by [[William Shepard]], the local militia commander, who began gathering government-supporting militia the Saturday before the court was to sit.  By the time the court was ready to open, Shepard had 300 men protecting the Springfield courthouse.  Shays and Day were able to recruit a similar number, but chose only to demonstrate, exercising their troops outside Shepard's lines, rather than attempt to seize the building.&lt;ref&gt;Holland, pp. 245–247&lt;/ref&gt;  The judges first postponed the hearings, and then adjourned on the 28th without hearing any cases.  Shepard withdrew his force, which had grown to some 800 men (to the Regulators' 1,200), to the [[Springfield Armory|federal armory]], which was then only rumored to be the target of seizure by the activists.&lt;ref&gt;Holland, p. 247&lt;/ref&gt;

===Plan to seize the Springfield Armory===
On November 28 a posse of some 300 men rode to [[Groton, Massachusetts|Groton]] to arrest [[Job Shattuck]] and other protest leaders in the area.  Shattuck was chased down and arrested on the 30th, and was wounded by a sword slash in the process.&lt;ref&gt;Szatmary, pp. 92–93&lt;/ref&gt;  This action and the arrest of other protest leaders in the eastern parts of the state radicalized those in the west, and they began to organize an overthrow of the state government.  &quot;The seeds of war are now sown&quot;, wrote one correspondent in [[Shrewsbury, Massachusetts|Shrewsbury]],&lt;ref&gt;Szatmary, p. 94&lt;/ref&gt; and by mid-January rebel leaders spoke of smashing the &quot;tyrannical government of Massachusetts.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Szatmary, p. 97&lt;/ref&gt;

While government forces organized in the east, Shays, Day, and other rebel leaders in the west organized their forces, establishing regional regimental organizations that were run by democratically elected committees.  Their first major target was the federal armory in Springfield.&lt;ref&gt;Szatmary, pp. 98–99&lt;/ref&gt;  General Shepard had, however, pursuant to orders from Governor Bowdoin, taken possession of the armory and used its arsenal to arm a force of some 1,200 militia.&lt;ref&gt;Richards, pp. 27–28&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Holland, p. 261&lt;/ref&gt;

===Attack and collapse===
The insurgents were organized into three major groups, and intended to surround and simultaneously attack the armory.  Shays led one group east of Springfield near [[Palmer, Massachusetts|Palmer]], Luke Day had a second force across the Connecticut River in [[West Springfield, Massachusetts|West Springfield]], and the third force, under [[Eli Parsons]], was to the north at [[Chicopee, Massachusetts|Chicopee]].&lt;ref&gt;Richards, p. 28&lt;/ref&gt;  The rebels had planned their assault for January 25, but Luke Day changed this at the last minute, sending Shays a message indicating he would not be ready to attack until the 26th.&lt;ref&gt;Szatmary, p. 101&lt;/ref&gt;  Day's message was intercepted by Shepard's men, so the militia of Shays and Parsons, some 1,500 men, approached the armory on the 25th not knowing they would have no support from the west.&lt;ref name=&quot;Richards29&quot;&gt;Richards, p. 29&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:Springfield Armory.jpg|thumb|right|The [[Springfield Armory]] (building pictured is from the 19th century) was the first major target of the rebellion.]]
When Shays and his forces neared the armory, they found Shepard's militia waiting for them. Shepard first ordered warning shots fired over the approaching Shaysites' heads, and then ordered two cannons to fire [[grape shot]] at Shays's men.  Four Shaysites were killed and twenty wounded.  There was no musket fire from either side, and the rebel advance collapsed.&lt;ref&gt;Szatmary, p. 102&lt;/ref&gt;  Most of the rebel force fled north, eventually regrouping at [[Amherst, Massachusetts|Amherst]].  On the opposite side of the river, Day's forces also fled north, also eventually reaching Amherst.&lt;ref&gt;Szatmary, p. 103&lt;/ref&gt;

General [[Benjamin Lincoln]] had mustered 3,000 men at [[Worcester, Massachusetts|Worcester]] to deal with the rebels.  When he heard of the Springfield incident, they immediately began marching west.  Shays led the rebel force generally north and east to avoid Lincoln, eventually establishing a camp at [[Petersham, Massachusetts|Petersham]]; along the way they raided the shops of local merchants for supplies, taking some of them hostage.  Lincoln pursued them, reaching [[Pelham, Massachusetts|Pelham]], some {{convert|30|mi|km}} from Petersham, on February 2.&lt;ref&gt;Szatmary, pp. 103–104&lt;/ref&gt;  On the night of February 3–4, he led his militia on a forced march to Petersham through a bitter snowstorm.  Arriving early in the morning, they surprised the rebel camp so thoroughly that they scattered &quot;without time to call in their out parties or even their guards.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Szatmary, p. 105&lt;/ref&gt;  Although Lincoln claimed to capture 150 men, none of them were officers, leading historian Leonard Richards to suspect the veracity of the report.  Shays and some of the other leaders escaped north into New Hampshire and Vermont.&lt;ref&gt;Richards, pp. 31, 120&lt;/ref&gt;

Some four thousand people signed confessions acknowledging participation in the events of the rebellion (in exchange for amnesty); several hundred participants were eventually indicted on charges relating to the rebellion.  Most of these were pardoned under a general amnesty that only excluded a few ringleaders.  Eighteen men, including Shays, were convicted and sentenced to death.  Most of these were either overturned on appeal, pardoned, or had their sentences commuted.  Two of the condemned men, John Bly and Charles Rose, were hanged on December 6, 1787.&lt;ref&gt;Richards, pp. 38–41&lt;/ref&gt; Shays was pardoned in 1788 and he returned to Massachusetts from hiding in the Vermont woods.&lt;ref name=&quot;zinn95&quot;&gt;Zinn, p. 95&lt;/ref&gt;  He was, however, vilified by the Boston press, who painted him as an archetypal anarchist opposed to the government.&lt;ref&gt;Richards, p. 117&lt;/ref&gt;

==Later life==
Shays was later granted a pension by the federal government for the five years he served in the [[Continental Army]] without pay. Shays lived the last few years of his life in poverty, a heavy drinker. He supported himself on his pension and by working a small parcel of land.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gross-1993-p2&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Gross, Robert A.|chapter=The Uninvited Guest: Daniel Shays and the Constitution|editor=Gross, Robert A.|title=In Debt to Shays: The Bicentennial of an Agrarian Rebellion|publisher=University Press of Virginia|year=1993|isbn=978-0-8139-1354-4|page=2|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=HpSIYclyYogC&amp;pg=PA2}}&lt;/ref&gt; Shays died at age 78 in [[Sparta, New York]], and was  buried at the Union Cemetery in Scottsburg.&lt;ref name=&quot;Gross-1993-p2&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{FAG|946|Daniel Ogden Shays}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://nyhistoric.com/2011/10/captain-daniel-shays/ |title=Captain Daniel Shays |website=nyhistoric.com/ |publisher=New York Historic |access-date=August 13, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Rededicated grave marker==
The original gravestone for Shays contained an error; by dropping the &quot;s&quot;, Shays was incorrectly spelled as &quot;Shay&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Beagle |first=Ben |date=August 7, 2016 |title=Gravestone Rededication: Heroic rebel, formative figure in U.S. history, to gets his ‘S’ |url=http://www.thelcn.com/lcn01/gravestone-rededication-heroic-rebel-formative-figure-in-us-history-to-gets-his-s-20160807 |newspaper=Livingston County News |location=Geneseo, NY }}&lt;/ref&gt;  In 2016, Philip R. Shays, of [[Clarence Center, New York]], a descendant of Daniel Shays, led an effort to correct the error.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |agency=Associated Press |last=Szathmary |first=Zoe |date=August 12, 2016 |title=Leader of Shays' Rebellion to get a new stone on his upstate New York grave to fix a TYPO on his name |url=http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-3720040/Leader-Shays-Rebellion-getting-new-stone-NY-grave.html |newspaper=The Daily Mail |location=London, United Kingdom}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Because the original stone did not contain enough space to add a letter, a new marker was created.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;[http://www.thelcn.com/lcn01/gravestone-rededication-heroic-rebel-formative-figure-in-us-history-to-gets-his-s-20160807 Gravestone Rededication: Heroic rebel, formative figure in U.S. history, to gets his ‘S’]&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;  The new gravestone was dedicated in a ceremony on August 12.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |date=August 12, 2016 |title=Revolutionary War hero gets new headstone - with his name spelled correctly |url=http://13wham.com/news/local/revolutionary-war-hero-gets-new-headstone-with-his-name-spelled-correctly |newspaper=WHAM-TV |location=Rochester, NY}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:ShaysGraveDedicationsAug2016.jpg|1|Dedication ceremony for new Daniel Shays gravestone.
File:ShaysGravestoneSide A.jpg|2|Front side of rededicated gravestone for Daniel Shays.
File:ShaysGravestoneSide B.jpg|3|Reverse side of new gravestone for Daniel Shays.
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|3}}

==Sources==
* {{cite book|last=Holland|first=Josiah Gilbert|title=History of Western Massachusetts|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=aiBMAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA245#v=onepage&amp;f=false|publisher=S. Bowles|location=Springfield, MA|year=1855|oclc=505288328}}
* {{cite book|last=Morse|first=Anson|title=The Federalist Party in Massachusetts to the Year 1800|publisher=Princeton University Press|location=Princeton, NJ|oclc=718724|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=xCUmAAAAMAAJ&amp;pg=PA23#v=onepage&amp;f=false}}
* {{cite book|last=Richards|first=Leonard L|year=2002|title=Shays's Rebellion: The American Revolution's Final Battle|location=Philadelphia|publisher=University of Pennsylvania Press|isbn=978-0-8122-1870-1|oclc=56029217}}
* {{cite book | authorlink=David Szatmary | last=Szatmary | first=David P. | year=1980 | title=Shays's Rebellion: The Making of an Agrarian Insurrection | publisher=University of Massachusetts Press | isbn=978-0-87023-419-4}}
* {{cite book | last=Zinn | first=Howard | title=A People's History of the United States |publisher=HarperCollins|location=New York |year=2005 |isbn=978-0-06-083865-2 |oclc=61265580}}

==Additional reading==
* {{cite book|author=|chapter=Captain Daniel Shays|title=History of Pelham, Mass: from 1738 to 1898, including the early history of Prescott|publisher=Press of Carpenter and Morehouse (Original from Princeton University)|year=1898|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=5Iw-AAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA391}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Shays, Daniel}}
[[Category:American rebels]]
[[Category:American revolutionaries]]
[[Category:Agrarian politics]]
[[Category:People convicted of treason]]
[[Category:People sentenced to death in absentia]]
[[Category:Recipients of American gubernatorial pardons]]
[[Category:Continental Army soldiers]]
[[Category:American people of Irish descent]]
[[Category:People from Hopkinton, Massachusetts]]
[[Category:1747 births]]
[[Category:1825 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Sparta, New York]]
[[Category:American tax resisters]]</text>
      <sha1>gfgs7x3c5tu3n0gwd7jw8jns7hk1tbm</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
