<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Date Masamune</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>314088</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748713667</id>
      <parentid>748713251</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-09T22:09:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Materialscientist</username>
        <id>7852030</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted 1 [[WP:AGF|good faith]] edit by [[Special:Contributions/86.7.119.57|86.7.119.57]] using [[WP:STiki|STiki]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15821">{{Japanese name|Date}}
{{Infobox Officeholder 
| name= Date Masamune&lt;br&gt;伊達政宗
| image= Date Masamune02.jpg|200px
| caption=
| order= First Lord of [[Sendai Domain]]
| term_start=1600
| term_end=1636
| predecessor=
| successor= [[Date Tadamune]]
| birth_date = September 5, 1567
| birth_place = [[Yonezawa, Yamagata]], [[Japan]]
| death_date = {{Death date and age|1636|06|27|1567|09|5}}
| death_place = 
}}
{{nihongo|'''Date Masamune'''|伊達 政宗||September 5, 1567 – June 27, 1636}} was a regional strongman of Japan's [[Azuchi-Momoyama period]] through early [[Edo period]]. Heir to a long line of powerful [[daimyo]] in the [[Tōhoku region]], he went on to found the modern-day city of [[Sendai]]. An outstanding tactician, he was made all the more iconic for his missing eye, and Date was often called ''dokuganryū'' (独眼竜), or the &quot;one-eyed dragon&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;This name is derived from the nickname of the ancient Chinese general [[Li Keyong]] (李克用), who was also one-eyed.{{Citation needed|date=July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As a legendary warrior and leader, Masamune is a character in a number of [[Jidaigeki|Japanese period dramas]]. He was played by [[Ken Watanabe]] in the popular 1987 [[NHK]] [[Taiga drama|series]] ''[[Dokuganryū Masamune]].''

==Early Life==
Date Masamune was the eldest son of [[Date Terumune]], born in [[Yonezawa, Yamagata|Yonezawa]] Castle (in modern [[Yamagata Prefecture]]). At the age of 14 in 1581 Masamune led his first campaign, helping his father fight the Sōma family. In 1584, at the age of 17, Masamune succeeded his father, Terumune, who chose to retire from his position as daimyo.
The [[Date clan|Date family]] was founded in the early [[Kamakura period]] by Isa Tomomune, who originally came from the Isa district of [[Hitachi Province]] (now [[Ibaraki Prefecture]]). The family took its name from the Date district (now [[Fukushima Prefecture]]) of [[Mutsu Province]], which had been awarded to Isa Tomomune by [[Minamoto no Yoritomo]], the first [[Kamakura shogunate|Kamakura shogun]], for his assistance in the [[Genpei War]] (1180–85) and in Minamoto no Yoritomo’s struggle for power with his brother, [[Minamoto no Yoshitsune]]. Masamune's army was recognized by its black armor and golden headgear.

==Military campaign==
[[Image:DateMasammuneToPope.jpg|thumb|A letter written by Masamune to [[Pope Paul V]].]]
[[Image:Zuiho-den06s3200.jpg|thumb|Masamune's Grave at [[Zuihōden]] mausoleum.]]
Masamune is known for a few things that made him stand out from other daimyo of the time. In particular, his famous crescent-moon-bearing [[helmet]] won him a fearsome reputation. As a child, [[smallpox]] robbed him of sight in his right eye, though it is unclear exactly how he lost the organ entirely.&lt;ref&gt;In 1974, a Japanese research team recovered his body from his mauseoleum Zuihoden, which was destroyed by the [[U.S. Army]]'s attacks in 1945. According to the research report, his right eye retained some organs. There is also a wooden image of Masamune in the temple Zuiganji, Matsushima, made in 1652 at his wife Megohime's instructions. This statue has a right eye, though it is smaller than his left one.  [http://www.pref.miyagi.jp/bunkazai/siteibunkazai/miyagi-no-bunkazai/03Tyoukoku/ken/25masamune.htm]&lt;/ref&gt; Various theories behind the eye's condition exist. Some sources say he plucked out the eye himself when a senior member of the clan pointed out that an enemy could grab it in a fight. Others say that he had his trusted retainer [[Katakura Kagetsuna|Katakura Kojūrō]] gouge out the eye for him.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.geocities.jp/hosinoufo3/katakura-kojurou.html]; Some writers refer to this episode as a turning point for Masamune, such as Masashi Hosaka in ''Garyu-no-ten'', ISBN 978-4-396-63290-8.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Date clan had built alliances with neighboring clans through marriages over previous generations, but local disputes remained commonplace. Shortly after Masamune's succession in 1584, a Date retainer named [[Ōuchi Sadatsuna]] defected to the Ashina clan of the [[Aizu]] region. Masamune declared war on Ōuchi and the Ashina for this betrayal, and started a campaign to hunt down Sadatsuna. Formerly amicable alliances were cast aside as he began to attack and conquer the lands of Sadatsuna's allies in pursuit, even those of his kin in Mutsu and Dewa Provinces. In the winter of 1585, one of these allies, Hatakeyama Yoshitsugu, felt defeat was approaching and chose to surrender to the Date instead. Masamune agreed to accept the surrender, but on the heavy condition that the Hatakeyama give up most of their territory to the Date. This resulted in Yoshitsugu kidnapping Masamune's father Terumune during their meeting in Miyamori Castle, where Terumune was staying at during the time. The incident ended with both Yoshitsugu and Terumune killed as the fleeing Hatakeyama party clashed with the pursuing Date troops near the [[Abukuma River]].&lt;ref&gt;Ken-ichi Sato, ''Date Masamune Nazotoki-sanpo'', ISBN 978-4-046-00177-1&lt;/ref&gt; Various records of the event exist, although they present different accounts of its circumstances.

The Date fought many battles with their neighbours afterwards, and, after defeating the Ashina at the Battle of Suriagehara in 1589, Masamune made the Aizu domain his base of operations.
&lt;gallery&gt;
Date Masamune Battle Standard; Shimazu Matsuhisa (1616-1695) Banner.jpg|thumb|Date Masamune [[uma-jirushi]] (right)
Nabeshima Tadanao Battle Standard; Date Masamune (1567-1636) Large Battle Standard.jpg|thumb|Date Masamune (1567-1636) uma-jirushi (left)
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Service under Hideyoshi==
In 1590, [[Toyotomi Hideyoshi]] [[Siege of Odawara (1590)|seized Odawara Castle]] and compelled the [[Tōhoku region]] daimyos to participate in the campaign. Although Masamune refused Hideyoshi's demands at first, he had no real choice in the matter since Hideyoshi was the virtual ruler of Japan. Masamune still delayed, infuriating Hideyoshi. Expecting to be executed, Masamune, wearing his finest clothes and showing no fear, faced his angry overlord.  Not wanting further trouble, Hideyoshi spared his life, saying that &quot;He could be of some use&quot;.

After serving Hideyoshi for a time, he was given Iwatesawa castle and the surrounding lands as his home domain. Masamune moved there in 1591, rebuilt the castle, renamed it [[Iwadeyama, Miyagi|Iwadeyama]], and encouraged the growth of a town at its base. Masamune stayed at Iwadeyama for 13 years and turned the region into a major political and economic center. He and his men served with distinction in the [[Japanese invasions of Korea (1592–1598)|Korean invasions]] under Hideyoshi and, after Hideyoshi's death, he began to support [[Tokugawa Ieyasu]] — apparently at the advice of Katakura Kojūrō.

Tokugawa Ieyasu awarded Masamune the lordship of the huge and profitable [[Sendai Domain]], which made Masamune one of Japan’s most powerful daimyo. Tokugawa had promised Masamune a one million [[koku]] domain, but, even after substantial improvements were made, the land only produced 640,000 koku, most of which was used to feed the Edo region. In 1604, Masamune, accompanied by 52,000 vassals and their families, moved to what was then the small fishing village of [[Sendai, Miyagi|Sendai]]. He left his fourth son, Date Muneyasu, to rule Iwadeyama.  Masamune would turn Sendai into a large and prosperous city.

Although Masamune was a patron of the arts and sympathized with foreign causes, he was also an aggressive and ambitious daimyo. When he first took over the Date clan, he suffered a few major defeats from powerful and influential clans such as the Ashina. These defeats were arguably caused by recklessness on Masamune's part.

Being a major power in northern Japan, Masamune was naturally viewed with suspicion, as any potential rival would be viewed. Toyotomi Hideyoshi reduced the size of his land holdings after his tardiness in coming to the [[Siege of Odawara (1590)|Siege of Odawara]] against [[Hōjō Ujimasa]]. Later in his life, Tokugawa Ieyasu increased the size of his lands again, but was constantly suspicious of Masamune and his policies.

Although Tokugawa Ieyasu and other Date allies were always suspicious of him, Date Masamune for the most part served the Tokugawa and Toyotomi loyally. He took part in [[Japanese invasions of Korea|Hideyoshi's campaigns in Korea]], and in the [[Siege of Osaka|Osaka campaigns]]. When Tokugawa Ieyasu was on his deathbed, Masamune visited him and read him a piece of [[Zen]] poetry. Masamune was highly respected for his [[ethics]]; a still-quoted aphorism is, ''&quot;Rectitude carried to excess hardens into stiffness; benevolence indulged beyond measure sinks into weakness.&quot;''

==Patron of culture and Christianity ==
Masamune expanded trade in the otherwise remote, backwater Tōhoku region. Although initially faced with attacks by hostile clans, he managed to overcome them after a few defeats and eventually ruled [[Sendai Domain|one of the largest fiefdoms]] of the later [[Tokugawa shogunate]]. He built many palaces and worked on many projects to beautify the region. He is also known to have encouraged foreigners to come to his land. Even though he funded and promoted an envoy to establish relations with the Pope in Rome, he was likely motivated at least in part by a desire for foreign technology, similar to that of other lords, such as [[Oda Nobunaga]].  Further, once Tokugawa Ieyasu outlawed Christianity, Masamune reversed his position, and though disliking it, let Ieyasu persecute Christians in his domain.  For 270 years, Tōhoku remained a place of tourism, trade and prosperity. [[Matsushima]], for instance, a series of tiny islands, was praised for its beauty and serenity by the wandering [[haiku]] poet [[Matsuo Bashō]].

He showed sympathy for Christian missionaries and traders in Japan. In addition to allowing them to come and preach in his province, he also released the prisoner and missionary [[Luis Sotelo|Padre Sotelo]] from the hands of Tokugawa Ieyasu. Date Masamune allowed Sotelo as well as other missionaries to practice their religion and win converts in Tōhoku.

[[Image:Sanjuanbautista.jpg|thumb|230px|Replica of the [[galleon]] '''''Date Maru''''', or ''[[Japanese warship San Juan Bautista|San Juan Bautista]]'', in [[Ishinomaki, Miyagi|Ishinomaki]], [[Japan]].]]
Masamune's greatest achievement was funding and backing one of Japan's few journeys of far-flung diplomacy and exploration in this period. He ordered the building of the exploration ship ''Date Maru'' or [[San Juan Bautista (ship)|''San Juan Bautista'']], using foreign (European) [[ship-building]] techniques. He sent one of his retainers, [[Hasekura Tsunenaga]], Sotelo, and an embassy numbering 180 on a successful voyage to establish relations with the Pope in [[Rome]]. This expedition visited such places as the [[Philippines]], [[Mexico]], [[Spain]] and Rome, making it the first Japanese voyage to sail around the world. Previously, Japanese lords had never funded this sort of venture, so it was probably the first successful voyage.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nhk.or.jp/sonotoki/2007_12.html#02 その時歴史が動いた&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; At least five members of the expedition stayed in [[Coria del Río|Coria]] (Seville) of Spain to avoid the persecution of Christians in Japan. 600 of their descendants, with the surname Japón (Japan), are now living in Spain.

When the Tokugawa government banned Christianity, Masamune had to obey the law. However, some sources suggest that Masamune's eldest daughter, Irohahime, was a Christian.&lt;ref&gt;[[:ja:五郎八姫]]. She had to divorce with her husband [[Matsudaira Tadateru]], who was exiled for his defiant attitude toward his father Ieyasu Tokugawa. After this separation, Irohahime never remarried though her parents, Masamune and Megohime suggested a remarriage. Some historians thought that her attitude was due to her faith.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Family ==
* Father
** [[Date Terumune]]
* Mother
** Yoshihime, daughter of [[Mogami Yoshimori]] the daimyo of [[Dewa Province]]
* Wet Nurse
** Kitako (also known as Kita Katakura), older sister of his retainer [[Katakura Kojūrō]].
*Brother
** Masamichi (Kojīrō)
* Half-Siblings
** Hideo
** Senshihime
* Wife
** [[Megohime]], daughter of [[Tamura Kiyoaki]] owner of [[Miharu Castle]] in [[Mutsu Province]] &lt;!-- In [[Miharu, Fukushima]] or [[Miharu Domain]]? --&gt;
* Concubines
** Īsaka no Tsubone
** Shinzō no Kata
** Yoshimitsu-in
** Tenekei-in
** Jōgonin
** Hosshōin
** Kotobuki-in
* Prostitute {{Sic|hide=yes}}
** Kōnomae
* Children
** [[Date Hidemune]] (1591–1658), first holder of the [[Uwajima Domain]]
** [[Irohahime]] (1594–1661)
** [[Date Tadamune]] (1599–1658)
** Date Munekiyo (1600–1634)
** Date Muneyasu (1602–1639)
** Date Munetsuna (1603–1618)
** Date Munenobu (1603–1627)
** Date Munetaka (1607–1626)
** Mūhime (1608-1683)
** Takematsumaru
** Date Munezane (1613–1665)
** Minehime (1616-1632)
** Date Munekatsu (1621–1679)
** Sengikuhime(1626–1655)
* Illegitimate Children
** Tsuta
** Watari Munemoto (1600–1669)
*Cousins
** [[Date Shigezane]] (1568–1646)
* Uncle
** [[Mogami Yoshiaki]]
** [[Rusu Masakage]]

==In popular culture ==
{{see also|People of the Sengoku period in popular culture#Date Masamune|label 1=People of the Sengoku period in popular culture}}
[[Professional wrestling]] promotion [[Osaka Pro Wrestling]] featured two wrestlers using the [[ring name]]s [[Masamune (wrestler)|Masamune]] and Hideyoshi, who together form the [[tag team]] &quot;Sengoku&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.osaka-prowres.com/wrestler/?p=13 |script-title=ja:秀吉|work=[[Osaka Pro Wrestling]]|accessdate=2012-09-08|language=Japanese}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.osaka-prowres.com/wrestler/?p=28 |script-title=ja:政宗|work=[[Osaka Pro Wrestling]]|accessdate=2012-09-08|language=Japanese}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
[[File:Take ni Suzume.svg|thumb|right|120px|The emblem ([[Mon (badge)|''mon'']]) of the Date clan]]
{{Reflist}}

== Further reading ==
* Kobayashi Seiji 小林清治. ''Date Masamune'' 伊達政宗. Tokyo: Yoshikawa Kōbunkan 吉川弘文館, 1959.
* [[Colyer Meriwether|Meriwether, Colyer]]. (1893). [https://books.google.com/books?id=RrYUAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA3&amp;dq= &quot;Life of Date Masamune,&quot;] ''Transactions of the Asiatic Society of Japan,'' Vol. XXI.
* Owada Tetsuo 小和田哲男. ''Date Masamune: shiden'' 伊達政宗: 史伝. Tokyo: Gakken 学研, 2000.
* Ken-ichi Sato 佐藤憲一. ''Date Masamune's letters'' 伊達政宗の手紙. Tokyo: Sinchosensho 新潮選書, 1995.

== External links ==
{{Commons category}}
* [http://www.datemasamune.com The official website of the Date clan]
* [http://www.zuihoden.com/ Zuihoden — The mausoleum of Date Masamune.]  When he died, twenty of his followers killed themselves (committed [[junshi]]) to serve him in the next life. They lay in state at Zuihōden
* [http://www.mgu.ac.jp/%7Ejfmorris/SendaiHTM/Index.htm Aoba-jo (Sendai Castle) website]
* [http://www.costruzioni.net/images/StadiM11.jpg An example of Date-influenced architecture]
* [http://www.yonezawa-naoe.com/information/080813.html &quot;TEN-CHI-JIN&quot; General of UESUGI Clan NAOE KANETSUGU] - (Japanese)-Kabuto(Samurai Helmet) Papercraft

{{S-start}}
{{succession box | title=[[Sendai han|Lord of Sendai]] | before=none | after=[[Date Tadamune]]| years=1600–1636}}
{{S-end}}

{{People of the Sengoku period|state=autocollapse}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Date, Masamune}}
[[Category:Sendai]]
[[Category:1567 births]]
[[Category:1636 deaths]]
[[Category:Christianity in Japan]]
[[Category:Daimyo]]
[[Category:Smallpox survivors]]
[[Category:Warlords]]
[[Category:Date clan]]
[[Category:Politicians with physical disabilities]]
[[Category:Japanese people with disabilities]]</text>
      <sha1>bp5xijfs3zm2gud98196w6wl134g9k4</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
