<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>De Havilland Tiger Moth</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>528202</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750399412</id>
      <parentid>750392154</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-19T14:10:59Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Deeday-UK</username>
        <id>357569</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Survivors */ wording per style guide</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="49089">{{about||the earlier monoplane Tiger Moth|de Havilland DH.71 Tiger Moth|other de Havilland Moth aircraft|de Havilland Moth}}
{{lowercase|De Havilland Tiger Moth}}
{{redirect|Tiger Moth|the group of moths|Arctiidae||Tiger moth (disambiguation)}}

&lt;!-- This article is a part of [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft]]. Please see [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft/page content]] for recommended layout. --&gt;
{|{{Infobox Aircraft Begin
  |name =DH.82 Tiger Moth
  |image =DH 82A Tiger Moth - N81DH.jpg
  |caption =A Tiger Moth in 1989
}}{{Infobox Aircraft Type
  |type =[[Trainer (aircraft)|Trainer]]
  |manufacturer =[[de Havilland|de Havilland Aircraft Company]] &lt;br&gt; [[de Havilland Canada]]
  |designer =[[Geoffrey de Havilland]]
  |first flight =26 October 1931
  |introduced = February 1932 &lt;ref&gt;http://www.ww2warbirds.net/ww2htmls/dehatigerm.html&lt;/ref&gt;
  |retired = 1959
  |status = Retired from military service, still in civil use
  |primary user =[[Royal Air Force]]
  |more users =[[Royal Canadian Air Force]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Royal Australian Air Force]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Royal New Zealand Air Force]]&lt;!-- only 3 &quot;more users&quot;; 4 in total. See other military operators in article----&gt;
  |produced = 1931–1944
  |number built =8,868&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20070927194816/www.britishaircraft.co.uk/aircraftpage.php?ID=314 &quot;De Havilland Tiger Moth (D.H.82).&quot;] ''web.archive.org.'' Retrieved: 12 August 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;
  |unit cost =
  |variants with their own articles = [[Thruxton Jackaroo]]
  |developed from = [[de Havilland DH.60 Moth]]
}}
|}

The '''de Havilland DH.82 Tiger Moth''' is a [[List of years in aviation|1930s]] [[biplane]] designed by [[Geoffrey de Havilland]] and built by the [[de Havilland|de Havilland Aircraft Company]]. It was operated by the [[Royal Air Force]] (RAF) and many other operators as a primary [[trainer (aircraft)|trainer]] aircraft. In addition to the type's principal use for ''ab-initio'' training, the [[World War II|Second World War]] saw RAF Tiger Moth operating in other capacities, including [[Maritime patrol aircraft|maritime surveillance]], defensive anti-invasion preparations, and even some aircraft that had been outfitted to function as armed [[light bomber]]s.

The Tiger Moth remained in service with the RAF until it was succeeded and replaced by the [[de Havilland Canada DHC-1 Chipmunk|de Havilland Chipmunk]] during the early 1950s. Many of the military surplus aircraft subsequently entered into civil operation. Many nations have used the Tiger Moth in both military and civil applications, and it remains in widespread use as a recreational aircraft in several different countries. It is still occasionally used as a primary training aircraft, particularly for those pilots wanting to gain experience before moving on to other tailwheel aircraft. Many Tiger Moths are now employed by various companies offering trial lesson experiences. The de Havilland Moth club, founded 1975, is now an owners' association offering a mutual club and technical support.

==Development==
===Origins===
Among the reasons for which de Havilland came to peruse development of the Tiger Moth was the personal dissatisfaction of [[Geoffrey de Havilland]], the company's owner and founder, who sought to produce a light aircraft superior to two of his previous designs, the [[de Havilland Humming Bird]] and [[de Havilland DH.51]].&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 3&quot;/&gt; From earlier experience, de Havilland knew the difficulty and importance of correctly sizing such an aircraft to appeal to various sectors of the civil market, such as touring, [[Trainer (aircraft)|trainer]], [[flying club]] and [[private aviation]] customers; the firm had previously attained a measure of popularity with a scaled down version of the DH.51, designated as the ''DH 60'' [[de Havilland Gipsy Moth]].&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 3&quot;&gt;Jackson 1966, p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt;

The starting point for the Tiger Moth was in fact the successful Gypsy Tiger.&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 4&quot;&gt;Jackson 1966, p. 4.&lt;/ref&gt; Successively more capable engines had been developed and the company had produced a prototype to test the new [[de Havilland Gipsy|de Havilland Gipsy III]] engine. This prototype, a low-wing [[monoplane]] was initially a modification of the standard Gypsy Tiger; it later became the first aircraft to be referred to as the ''Tiger Moth''.&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 3 4&quot;&gt;Jackson 1966, pp. 3-4.&lt;/ref&gt; Improvements made upon the Tiger Moth monoplane were first incorporated into a military trainer variant of the [[de Havilland DH.60 Moth]], designated as the DH.60T Moth - in later parlance, the ''T'' came to stand for 'Tiger' in addition to 'Trainer'.&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 4&quot;/&gt; According to aviation author A.J. Jackson, development of the standard Tiger Moth version from the monoplane prototype had proceeded relatively straightforward after this point.&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 4&quot;/&gt;

The DH.60T Moth had several shortcomings, and thus was subject to several alterations, such as the adoption of shortened interplane struts in order to raise the wingtips after insufficient ground clearance was discovered while it was undergoing trials at [[RAF Martlesham Heath]].&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 4&quot;/&gt; As a result of the Martlesham trials, a favourable report for the type was produced, which in turn led to the type soon being formally adopted as the new basic trainer of the [[Royal Air Force]] (RAF). A single prototype, designated as the ''DH.82 Tiger Moth'', was ordered by the British [[Air Ministry]] under  [[List of Air Ministry specifications|Specification]] 15/31, which sought a suitable [[List_of_Latin_phrases_(A)#ab initio|''ab-initio'']] training aircraft.&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 4&quot;/&gt;

One of the main changes made from the preceding Moth series was necessitated by a desire to improve access to the front [[cockpit]], since the training requirement specified that the front seat occupant had to be able to escape easily, especially when wearing a [[parachute]].&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot;&gt;Bain 1992, p. 43.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 4&quot;/&gt; Access to the front cockpit of the Moth predecessors was restricted by the proximity of the aircraft's fuel tank directly above the front cockpit and the rear [[cabane strut]]s for the upper wing. The solution adopted was to shift the upper wing forward but sweep the wings back to maintain the centre of lift.&lt;ref&gt;[http://web.archive.org/web/20071023131701/www.classicaircraft.ca/flightline_frameset.htm &quot;de Havilland Tiger Moth 82A.&quot;]''web.archive.org.'' Retrieved: 12 August 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 4&quot;/&gt; Other changes included a strengthened structure, fold-down doors on both sides of the cockpit and a revised exhaust system.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot;/&gt;

On 26 October 1931, the first 'true' Tiger Moth, the prototype ''E6'', conducted its [[maiden flight]] at [[Stag Lane Aerodrome]], [[Edgware]], [[London]]; de Havilland Chief Test Pilot [[Hubert Broad]] was at the controls during this first flight.&lt;ref&gt;McKay 1988, p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 4&quot;/&gt; Shortly thereafter, construction of the first 35 production aircraft for the RAF, designated ''K2567-K2601'', commenced following the issuing of [[List of Air Ministry specifications|Specification]] T.23/31; in addition, two [[Float (nautical)|float]]-equipped [[seaplane]]s, ''S1675'' and ''S1676'', were also built according to Specification T.6/33.&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 4&quot;/&gt;

===Production===
[[File:Interior of De Havilland aircraft factory, Rongotai, Wellington, 1939 or 1940.jpg|thumb|[[Royal New Zealand Air Force]] Tiger Moth aircraft with blind flying hoods for instrument training, early in the war]]
The Tiger Moth quickly became a commercial success, various models of the aircraft were exported to more than 25 Air Forces of various overseas nations.&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 4&quot;/&gt; In addition to the military demand, aircraft were also produced for the civil market. At one point, the flow of orders for the Tiger Moth had effectively occupied almost the entirety of de Havilland's capacity to manufacture aircraft and little capacity could be spared to accommodate domestic customers.&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 4 5&quot;&gt;Jackson 1966, pp. 4-5.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1932, de Havilland also developed an affordable air taxi from the Tiger Moth; using almost all of the main components of the former in combination with a new plywood fuselage seating four people in an enclosed cabin, it was marketed as the [[de Havilland Fox Moth]].&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 15&quot;&gt;Jackson 1966, p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt; Following the end of all manufacturing, third parties would occasionally re-build Tiger Moths to a similar configuration to the Fox Moth, such as the [[Thruxton Jackaroo]].&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 15 16&quot;&gt;Jackson 1966, pp. 15-16.&lt;/ref&gt;

In late 1934, 50 Tiger Moths of a more refined design, sometimes referred to as the ''Tiger Moth II'', were delivered to the RAF; these aircraft saw the adoption of the [[de Havilland Gipsy Major]] engine, capable of generating 130 HP, and the use of [[plywood]] decking on the rear fuselage in place of traditional [[fabric]] covering the [[Longeron|stringers]].&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 5&quot;&gt;Jackson 1966, p. 5.&lt;/ref&gt; Throughout 1334-1936, production activity was centered upon meeting the demand for military trainers, including several contracts having been placed by the RAF to Specification T.7/35 along with export orders by seven overseas operators.&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 6&quot;&gt;Jackson 1966, p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt; Civil examples were also being produced at this time, both for British private customers and to export customers in countries such as [[Ceylon]], [[Greece]], [[Lithuania]], [[Rhodesia]], [[Peru]], and [[Switzerland]].&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 6 7&quot;&gt;Jackson 1966, pp. 6-7.&lt;/ref&gt;

After 1936, the gradual rate of acceleration of Tiger Moth manufacturing had reached the point where production capacity became finally able to exceed the demands from military customers alone.&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 7&quot;&gt;Jackson 1966, p. 7.&lt;/ref&gt; By the outbreak of the [[World War II|Second World War]], a total of 1,424 Tiger Moths had been completed by both domestic and overseas manufacturing efforts.&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 10&quot;/&gt; In 1941, de Havilland transferred principal manufacturing activity for the Tiger Moth from its [[Hatfield, Hertfordshire|Hatfield]] factory to [[Morris Motors|Morris Motors Limited]] at their facility in [[Cowley, Oxford]].&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 11&quot;&gt;Jackson 1966, p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt; In 1945, all activity on the British Tiger Moth production lines was terminated; by this point, Morris Motors had completed a total of 3,433 Tiger Moths.&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 11&quot;/&gt;

In 1937, overseas manufacturing of the type commenced, the first such firm being [[de Havilland Canada]] at their facility in [[Downsview]], [[Toronto]], [[Ontario]]; in addition to an initial batch of 25 Tiger Moths that were built for the [[Royal Canadian Air Force]] (RCAF), the Canadian firm began building fuselages which were exported to the UK for completion.&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 10&quot;&gt;Jackson 1966, p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt; Canadian-built Tiger Moths featured modifications to better suit the local climate, along with a reinforced tail wheel, hand-operated brakes (built by [[Bendix Corporation]]), shorter [[landing gear|undercarriage]] radius rods and the legs of the main landing gear legs being raked forwards as a safeguard against tipping forwards during braking. Furthermore, the cockpit had a large sliding canopy fitted along with [[exhaust system|exhaust]]-based heating; various alternative undercarriage arrangements were also offered.&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 11 12&quot;&gt;Jackson 1966, pp. 11-12.&lt;/ref&gt; By the end of Canadian production, de Havilland Canada had manufactured a total of 1,548 of all versions, including the ''DH.82C'' and Menasco-engined variants known as the ''Menasco Moth''; this also included 200 Tiger Moths that were built under wartime [[United States Army Air Forces]] (USAAF) [[Lend-Lease]] orders, which were designated for paperwork purposes as the ''PT-24'', before being delivered onwards to the RCAF.

Additional overseas manufacturing activity also occurred, most of which took place during wartime. [[de Havilland Australia]] assembled an initial batch of 20 aircraft from parts sent from the United Kingdom prior to embarking on a major production campaign of their own of the DH.82A, which resulted in a total of 1,070 Tiger Moths being constructed locally in Australia.&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 11&quot;/&gt; In late 1940, the first Australian-assembled Tiger Moth conducted ins first flight at [[Bankstown]], [[Sydney]]. Most Australian aircraft were delivered to the [[Royal Australian Air Force]] (RAAF), however several batches were exported, including 18 for the USAAF and 41 for the [[Indian Air Force|Royal Indian Air Force]] (RIAF).&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 11&quot;/&gt;

132 Tiger Moths were completed in [[New Zealand]] by [[de Havilland Aircraft of New Zealand]] .&lt;ref name=&quot;production figures&quot;/&gt;  23 aircraft were built in [[Sweden]] as the ''Sk.11'' by [[AB Svenska Järnvägsverkstädernas Aeroplanavdelning]], 91 Tiger Moths were built in [[Portugal]] by [[OGMA]], and another 38 in [[Norway]] by [[Kjeller Flyfabrikk]] (some sources say 37 so the first may have been assembled from a kit) in addition to a large number of aircraft that were assembled from kits shipped from the UK.&lt;ref name=&quot;production figures&quot;&gt;Hannah 1982, p. 66.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rimell 1992, p. 9.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 11&quot;/&gt;

===Design===
The de Havilland DH.82 Tiger Moth is a single-engine biplane light aircraft. It was developed principally to be used by private touring customers as well as for pilot instruction for both military and civil operators. It is typically powered by a [[de Havilland Gipsy]] III 120&amp;nbsp;hp engine; later models are often fitted with more powerful models of this engine, while some have been re-engined by third party companies.

One distinctive characteristic of the Tiger Moth design is its differential [[aileron]] control setup. The ailerons (on the lower wing only) on a Tiger Moth are operated by an externally mounted circular bellcrank, which lies flush with the lower wing's fabric undersurface covering. This circular bellcrank is rotated by metal cables and chains from the cockpit's control columns, and has the externally mounted aileron pushrod attached at a point 45° outboard and forward of the bellcrank's centre, when the ailerons are both at their neutral position. This results in an aileron control system operating, with barely any travel down at all on the wing on the outside of the turn, while the aileron on the inside travels a large amount upwards to counteract [[adverse yaw]].

From the outset, the Tiger Moth proved to be an ideal trainer, simple and cheap to own and maintain, although control movements required a positive and sure hand as there was a slowness to control inputs. Some instructors preferred these flight characteristics because of the effect of &quot;weeding&quot; out the inept student pilot.&lt;ref name=&quot;warbird&quot;/&gt;

==Operational history==
===Introduction===
[[File:De Havilland DH-82 Tiger Moth ExCC.jpg|thumb|Canadian DH.82C Tiger Moth showing characteristic canopy]]
The RAF ordered 35 dual-control ''Tiger Moth I''s which had the company designation  ''DH 82''.&lt;ref&gt;Bransom 1991, p. 41.&lt;/ref&gt; A subsequent order was placed for 50 aircraft powered by the [[de Havilland Gipsy Major]] I engine (130&amp;nbsp;hp) which was the ''DH 82A'' or to the RAF ''Tiger Moth II''. The Tiger Moth entered service at the [[RAF Central Flying School]] in February 1932. During the pre-war years increasing numbers of Tiger Moths were procured for the RAF and by overseas customers; by 1939, nearly 40 flying schools operating the type had been established, nine of which operated civil-registers models as well.&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 5 6&quot;&gt;Jackson 1966, pp. 5-6.&lt;/ref&gt;

From 1937 onwards, the Tiger Moth was made available to general flying clubs, production having been previously occupied by military customers. The type was quickly used to replace older aircraft in the civil trainer capacity, such as the older [[de Havilland DH.60 Moth|de Havilland Cirrus Moth]] and Gipsy Moth.&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 7&quot;/&gt; By the start of the Second World War, the RAF had around 500 Tiger Moths in service. In addition, nearly all civilian-opeated Tiger Moths throughout the [[Commonwealth of Nations|Commonwealth]] were quickly impressed into their respective air forces in order to meet the strenuous wartime demand for trainer aircraft.&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 10&quot;/&gt;

===Training===
The Tiger Moth became the foremost primary trainer throughout the Commonwealth and elsewhere. It was the principal type used in the British [[Commonwealth Air Training Plan]] where thousands of military pilots got their first taste of flight in this robust little machine. The RAF found the Tiger Moth's handling ideal for training future fighter pilots. Whilst generally docile and forgiving in the normal flight phases encountered during initial training, when used for aerobatic and formation training the Tiger Moth required definite skill and concentration to perform well — a botched manoeuvre could easily cause the aircraft to stall or spin. From 1941 onwards, all military and many civil Tiger Moths were outfitted with anti-spin [[Strake (aeronautics)|strake]]s positioned on the junction between the fuselafe and the [[leading edge]] of the tailplane, known as ''Mod 112''; later on, the [[aileron]] mass balances were removed for improved spin recovery performance.&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 10&quot;/&gt;

[[File:de havilland dh-82b queen bee lf858 arp.jpg|thumb|A 1944-built Queen Bee in 2008]]

In 1935, a radio-controlled gunnery target version of Tiger Moth appeared, often called the ''DH.82 Queen Bee''; it used a wooden fuselage based on that of the DH.60 Gipsy Moth (with appropriate structural changes related to cabane strut placement) with the wings of the Tiger Moth II.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=wN8DAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA551&amp;dq=Popular+Science+1935+plane+%22Popular+Mechanics%22&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=aJgvTv3XKdSgsQLVyIRv&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=9&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CEkQ6AEwCA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=true &quot;Radio Controls Robot Plane On Pilotless Flight.&quot;] ''Popular Mechanics'', October 1935.&lt;/ref&gt; There were nearly 300 in service at the start of the Second World War. It is believed the name &quot;[[Target drone|drone]]&quot; derived from &quot;Queen Bee&quot;.{{cn|date=July 2016}} These aircraft retained a normal front cockpit for test-flying or ferry flights, but had a radio-control system in the rear cockpit that operated the controls using pneumatically driven [[Servomechanism|servos]]. Four-hundred were built by de Havilland at Hatfield, and a further 70 by [[Scottish Aviation]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.captainnevillesflyingcircus.org.uk/page16.htm &quot;Queen Bee G-BLUZ, Aircraft History.&quot;] ''Captain Neville's Flying Circus.'' Retrieved: 31 August 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Coastal patrol===
In December 1939, owing to a shortage of [[maritime patrol aircraft]], six [[Flight (military unit)|flight]]s of Tiger Moths were operated by [[RAF Coastal Command]] for surveillance flights over coastal waters, known as &quot;scarecrow patrols&quot;. The aircraft operated in pairs and were armed only with a [[Very pistol]]. The intention was to force any encroaching [[U-boat]] to dive; one aircraft would then remain in the vicinity while the other would search for a naval patrol vessel which could be led back to the spot.&lt;ref&gt;Carter 2004, p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt; Because they were not radio equipped, each aircraft also carried a pair of [[homing pigeon]]s in a wicker basket to call for help in case of a forced landing at sea. A 25-pound (11.5 kilogram) bomb was sometimes carried, but there is no record of one being dropped in action.&lt;ref&gt;Lake 2010, pp. 7-8.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Anti-invasion preparations===
In the aftermath of Britain's disastrous campaign in France, in August 1940, three proposals for beach defence systems were put forward. 350 Tiger Moths were fitted with bomb racks to serve as [[light bomber]]s as a part of [[Operation Banquet]]. A more radical conversion involved the &quot;paraslasher&quot;, a scythe-like blade fitted to a Tiger Moth and intended to cut [[Fallschirmjäger (World War II)|parachutists']] canopies as they descended to earth. Flight tests proved the idea, but it was not officially adopted. The Tiger Moth was also tested as a dispenser of [[Paris Green]] rat poison for use against ground troops, with powder dispensers located under the wings.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rafmuseum.org.uk/research/collections/de-havilland-tiger-moth-ii/ &quot;de Havilland Tiger Moth II.&quot;] ''rafmuseum.org.'' Retrieved: 20 July 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Postwar===
[[File:DH.82A Tiger Moth Coupe G-ANSA Baginton 20.08.55 edited-2.jpg|thumb|Tiger Moth Coupe with spatted undercarriage at [[Coventry Airport]] in 1955]]
[[File:DH.82A Tiger Moth PH-NIS Hilversum 12.03.67 edited-3.jpg|thumb|left|Dutch Tiger Moth at [[Hilversum Airport]] in 1967, it has the extended fin area required by the Dutch authorities.]]
[[File:JamesAviation.jpg|thumb|Early aerial topdressing conversion of the Tiger Moth at the [[Museum of New Zealand Te Papa Tongarewa]] in 2009.]]
In the postwar climate, impressed Tiger Moths were restored to their former civil operations and owners.&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 12&quot;&gt;Jackson 1966, p. 12.&lt;/ref&gt; Accordingly, there were large numbers of surplus Tiger Moths that were made available for sale to flying clubs and individuals. There were also relatively few new light aircraft being manufactured at the time to take its place.&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 12 13&quot;&gt;Jackson 1966, pp. 12-13.&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, there were relatively due to the type being relatively inexpensive to operate and aforementioned actors, the Tiger Mouth was met with an enthusiastic reception across the civil market. Additionally, it was promptly was put to use for various new roles including aerial advertising, aerial ambulance, aerobatic performer, crop duster and glider tug.&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 12&quot;/&gt;

In the air racing market, a quantity of Tiger Moths were converted to a single seat configuration, often temporarily.&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 13&quot;/&gt; Several aircraft were extensively modified for greater speed; these changes may include the removal of the center-section fuel tank, alternative fuel tank configurations, all-new elevators, custom-designed [[fuel injector]]s, and the re-covering of the fuselage with lighter-weight fabric.&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 13 14&quot;&gt;Jackson 1966, pp. 13-14.&lt;/ref&gt; Three particular aircraft, ''G-APDZ'', ''G-ANZZ'', and ''G-ANMZ'', were accordingly rebuilt and were frequently used in international competitions; the design changes led to substantially improved performance during inverted flight.&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 14&quot;&gt;Jackson 1966, p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt;

Many ex-RAF examples were imported to the [[Netherlands]] during the post war era and used to equip the Dutch National Flying School at [[Ypenburg]].&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 14 15&quot;&gt;Jackson 1966, pp. 14-15.&lt;/ref&gt; These aircraft were required by the Dutch civil aviation authorities to be fitted with a larger dorsal fin, incorporating an extended forward fillet to the fin, to provide for additional area; this requirement was also extended to privately owned Tiger Moths in the Netherlands.&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 14&quot;/&gt;

The Tiger Moth might be confused at first glance with the Belgian-designed [[Stampe SV.4]] aerobatic aircraft which had a very similar design layout; both aircraft made use of a similar main landing gear configuration, a slightly sweepback wing, and an alike engine/cowling design. Several Tiger Moths were converted during the 1950s to a ''Coupe'' standard, which involved the installation of a sliding canopy over both crew positions, not unlike the Canadian-built [[Fleet Finch#Design and development|Fleet Finch]] biplane trainers which had worked beside the Tiger Moth in RCAF service as trainers in Canada during the type's wartime years.&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 13&quot;/&gt;

After the development of [[aerial topdressing]] in [[New Zealand]], large numbers of ex-[[Royal New Zealand Air Force]] Tiger Moths built in that country and in the United Kingdom were converted into [[agricultural aircraft]]; at the time, this was a pioneering use for aircraft.&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 12&quot;/&gt; In this role, the front seat was commonly replaced with a hopper to hold [[superphosphate]] for aerial topdressing. A large number were also used to deploy [[insecticide]] in the crop-sprayer role, for which several alternative arrangements, including perforated piping being installed underneath the meainplanes or the placement of rotary atomisers on the lower mainplane, were used.&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 12&quot;/&gt; From the mid-1950s onwards, these topdressers were gradually replaced by more modern types such as the [[PAC Fletcher]]; as such, a large number of New Zealand Tiger Moths in good flying condition were then passed to pilot owner enthusiasts.{{citation needed|date = May 2012}}

It has been claimed that more people have flown themselves in Tiger Moths than in any other plane.{{Citation needed|date = May 2012}}

[[Royal Navy]] Tiger Moths utilised as target tugs and &quot;air experience&quot; machines became the last military examples when that service purchased a batch of refurbished ex-civil examples in 1956.&lt;ref&gt;McKay 1998, p. 57.&lt;/ref&gt; One became the last biplane to land on an aircraft carrier ([[HMS Eagle (R05)|HMS ''Eagle'']]) in the [[English Channel]] during the Summer of 1967. On takeoff, the wind over the deck allowed the aircraft to fly but it was slower than the carrier, which turned hard to starboard to avoid a possible collision.{{citation needed|date = May 2012}} These planes remained in service until the early 1970s.{{citation needed|date = May 2012}}

The Tiger Moth had been often used as a stand-in for rarer aircraft in films, sometimes having been extensively modified to outwardly resemble the aircraft it was depicting.&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 16&quot;&gt;Jackson 1966, p. 16.&lt;/ref&gt; A trio of aircraft were converted by [[Croydon]]-based Film Aviation Services Ltd for use in the filming of the 1962 movie [[Lawrence of Arabia (film)|Lawrence of Arabia]]; one Tiger Moth became a replica of a [[Fokker D.VII]] while two aircraft resembled the [[Rumpler C.IV|Rumpler C.V]] to depict these types for the film.&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 16&quot;/&gt; Several Tiger Moth were used in the crash scenes in ''[[The Great Waldo Pepper]]'', standing in for the [[Curtiss JN-4|Curtiss JN-1]].{{citation needed|date = May 2012}}  Due to the popularity of the design and the rising cost of flyable examples, a number of replicas (scale and full-size) have been designed for the homebuilder, including the [[Fisher R-80 Tiger Moth]] and the [[RagWing RW22 Tiger Moth]].{{citation needed|date = May 2012}}

==Flying the Tiger Moth==
[[File:DH 82 A Tiger Moth D-EBKT.jpg|thumb|left|DH.82A Tiger Moth in 2005]]
The Tiger Moth responds well to control inputs, and is fairly easy to fly for a tail-dragger.  Its big &quot;parachute&quot; wings are very forgiving, and it stalls at a speed as slow as 25 knots with power. Its stall and spin characteristics are benign. It has some adverse yaw, and therefore requires rudder input during turns.&lt;ref name=RAAF&gt;&quot;Pilot's Notes for Tiger Moth Aircraft.&quot; ''R.A.A.F. Publication No. 416,'' February 1941.&lt;/ref&gt; The Tiger Moth exhibits the fundamental requirements of a training aircraft, in being &quot;easy to fly, but difficult to fly well&quot;; the aircraft's benign handling when within its limits make it easy for the novice to learn the basic skills of flight. At the same time techniques such as [[coordinated flight]] must be learnt and used effectively, and the aircraft will show up mishandling to an observant instructor or attentive pupil. As training progresses towards more advanced areas, especially [[aerobatics]], the skill required on the part of a Tiger Moth pilot increases. The aircraft will not, like some training aircraft, &quot;fly its way out of trouble&quot; but will instead stall or spin if mishandled. However the stall and spin remain benign, again showing up deficient piloting without endangering the aircraft or the crew. These characteristics were invaluable to military operators, who must identify between pilots with the potential to go on to fly [[fighter aircraft]], those more suited to lower-performance machines and those who must be relegated to non-pilot aircrew positions.{{citation needed|date=June 2014}}

Because the Tiger Moth has no electrical system, it must be started by hand. This needs to be done with care to prevent being struck by the propeller, which would result in serious injury. Being a tail-dragging biplane, taxiing also requires care. The pilot cannot see directly ahead, so the lower wing can hit obstructions, and it is susceptible to gusts of wind on its inclined, large, upper wing.&lt;ref name=RAAF/&gt;
[[File:dehav.dh82a.tigermoth.g-acdj.arp.jpg|thumb|A 1933-built Tiger Moth]]
The takeoff is uneventful, and it has a reasonable rate of climb. However, full power should not be maintained for more than a minute to avoid damaging the engine.&lt;ref name=RAAF/&gt;

The Tiger Moth's biplane design makes it strong, and it is fully aerobatic. However, it has ailerons only on its bottom wing, which makes its rate of roll relatively slow for a biplane, and as stated previously, the ailerons on a Tiger Moth normally operate with a heavy degree of designed-in differential operation (mostly deflecting up, hardly at all downwards) to avoid [[adverse yaw]] problems in normal flight. Most manoeuvres are started at about 90 to 110 knots, and it has a Velocity Never Exceeded (VNE) of 140 knots. It is important to lock the automatic slats (leading edge flaps) during aerobatic manoeuvres.&lt;ref name=RAAF/&gt;

There are two methods of landing. &quot;Wheeler&quot; landing involves pushing the plane on to the runway at a moderate speed with just the main wheels on the ground, with the tail held up until speed reduces. It does not tend to bounce. Unlike most tail draggers, slow speed [[Conventional landing gear|three point landings]] are quite difficult because there is not enough elevator authority to bring the tail down to the correct three point attitude.{{or|date=March 2015}} This means that the tail needs to be brought down sharply at just the right speed in order for the angular momentum{{or|date=March 2015}} to carry it down sufficiently.&lt;ref name=RAAF/&gt;

The open cockpit allows pilots to move their heads over the side to see the runway during approach and landing. As the aircraft is a tail dragger, it is essential to land it straight with no sideways movement, to avoid ground loops.&lt;ref name=RAAF/&gt;

One often undocumented feature is that the carburetor de-icing mechanism is activated automatically when the throttle is reduced. This means that when an engine is running poorly due to ice the pilot must reduce power even further and then wait for the ice to melt.&lt;ref name=RAAF/&gt;

==Variants==
[[File:WCAM Tiger Moth.jpg|thumb|[[de Havilland Canada]] DH.82C in [[British Commonwealth Air Training Plan|Commonwealth Air Training Plan]] &quot;trainer yellow&quot; at the [[Western Canada Aviation Museum]] (note the skis)]]

;DH.60T Moth Trainer/Tiger Moth
:Military training version of the De Havilland [[de Havilland Gipsy Moth|DH.60 Moth]]. First eight prototype DH.82 configuration aircraft were named Tiger Moth.&lt;ref&gt;Bransom 1991, p. 33.&lt;/ref&gt;
 
;DH.82 Tiger Moth (Tiger Moth I)
:Two-seat primary trainer aircraft. Powered by a 120 hp (89 kW) [[De Havilland Gipsy|de Havilland Gipsy III]] piston engine; renamed ''Tiger Moth I'' in RAF.

;DH.82A Tiger Moth (Tiger Moth II)
:Two-seat primary trainer aircraft. Powered by a 130 hp (97 kW) [[de Havilland Gipsy Major]] piston engine and fitted with a hood over the rear cockpit for blind flying instruction.  Named ''Tiger Moth II'' in RAF.

;DH.82B Tiger Moth III
:Improved variant with a [[de Havilland Gipsy Major|de Havilland Gipsy Major III]] engine, it had a wider fuselage and larger fin. First flown on 1 October 1939 only one was built. In some references the designation is erroneously applied to the Queen Bee.

;DH.82C Tiger Moth
:Cold weather operations version for the [[RCAF]]. Fitted with sliding perspex canopies, cockpit heating, brakes, tail wheels and metal struts. Wheels were moved forwards by 9.75&quot; to compensate for the installation of brakes by changing the angle of the undercarriage legs. Powered by a 145 hp (108 kW) de Havilland Gipsy Major piston engine. 1,523 built (including Menasco Moths and PT-24).

;DH.82C-2 Menasco Moth I
:DH.82C fitted with [[Menasco D-4 Super Pirate]] 125 hp inline inverted 4-cylinder engine due to shortages of Gipsy Major engines. Because of the reduction in power, they were used primarily as radio trainers. Externally distinguishable from 82C by opposite rotation of propeller and reversal of the cowling openings. 10 built.

;DH.82C-4 Menasco Moth II
:As DH.82C-2 but with reduced fuel capacity and further detail alterations. One example survives and is on display at [[Canada Aviation and Space Museum]] in [[Ottawa]]. 125 built.

;DH.82C-4 Menasco Moth III
:Fitted with American AT-1/AR-2 radio and intended as a radio trainer from outset but project cancelled when shortages of British radios and engines was resolved. The sole example, RCAF 4934 was converted from Menasco Moth II.&lt;ref name=&quot;Menasco serials&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ody.ca/~bwalker/RCAF_4900_4949_detailed.html|title=This web page has moved|work=ody.ca}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;DH.82 {{visible anchor|Queen Bee}}
:Unmanned radio-controlled target drone that used Tiger Moth wings and for economy a wooden fuselage based on that of the DH.60 Moth (but with the structural changes associated with the [[cabane strut]]s having been relocated as per the standard Tiger Moth)  was used. The Queen Bee was intended to be operated from either floats or wheels.  As of 2008, the sole remaining airworthy Queen Bee resided at [[RAF Henlow]], England. 405 were built.

;PT-24 Moth
:United States military designation for the DH.82C ordered for [[Lend-Lease]] to the [[Royal Canadian Air Force]]; 200 were built by de Havilland Canada.

;Thruxton Jackaroo
{{Main|Thruxton Jackaroo}}
:Four-seat cabin biplane, modified from existing DH.82A airframes by widening the gap between the fuselage longerons. 19 were converted in the United Kingdom.

;DH.83 Fox Moth
:Used many Tiger Moth components including wings (rerigged to remove sweep), tail and undercarriage with a new fuselage featuring an enclosed cabin for the passengers, and an open cockit for the pilot. Built in both the United Kingdom before the Second World War and in Canada after the war.

==Operators==
[[File:DH82A Tiger Moth A17-561 2.jpg|thumb|DH.82A Tiger Moth in [[RAAF]] markings]]
[[File:RMM Brussel Tiger Moth.JPG|thumb|Tiger Moth in British camouflage in a Belgian museum]]

===Military operators===
;{{AUS}}
*[[Royal Australian Air Force]]
*[[Royal Australian Navy]] - [[Fleet Air Arm (RAN)]].
;{{BEL}}
*[[Belgian Air Force]] (31 operated from 1945)
;{{BRA}}
*[[Brazilian Air Force]], 5 delivered in 1932 and 12 in 1935.
*[[Brazilian Naval Aviation]]
;{{flag|Burma|1948}}
*Burma Volunteer Air Force
*[[Burma Air Force]]
;{{flag|Canada|1921}}
*[[Royal Canadian Air Force]]
*[[Royal Canadian Navy]]
;{{flag|Ceylon}}
*[[Royal Ceylon Air Force]]
;{{flag|Democratic Republic of Congo|1960}}
*Force Aérienne Congolaise
;{{CZS}}
*[[Czechoslovakian Air Force]] - One aircraft in service from 1945 to 1948.
;{{DNK}}
*[[Royal Danish Air Force]]
;{{EGY}}
;{{FIN}}
*[[Finnish Air Force]]
;{{FRA}}
*[[French Air Force]]
;{{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
*''[[Luftwaffe]]'' (small numbers)&lt;ref&gt;Ketley and Rolfe 1996, p. 11.&lt;/ref&gt;
;{{flag|Greece}}
*[[Hellenic Air Force]]
;{{flagicon|British Raj}} {{IND}}
*[[Royal Indian Air Force]]
*[[Indian Air Force]]
;{{flag|Iran|1925}}
* [[Imperial Iranian Air Force]]- 99 imported and 10 built locally in 1938-39&lt;ref name=Iran&gt;http://www.artiklar.z-bok.se/Iran-2.html 26 November 2011&lt;/ref&gt;
;{{flag|Iraq|1924}}
*[[Iraqi Air Force]]
;{{ISR}}
* [[Israeli Air Force]]
* [[Sherut Avir]]
;{{JOR}}
*[[Royal Jordanian Air Force]]
;{{flag|Malaya}}
* Malaya Auxiliary Air Force
;{{NLD}}
*[[Royal Netherlands Air Force]]
*[[Dutch Naval Aviation Service]]
*[[Royal Netherlands East Indies Army Air Force]]{{citation needed|date=November 2011}}
;{{NZL}}
[[File:Tiger Moth Blue.jpg|thumb|DH.82A Tiger Moth in [[Royal Norwegian Air Force]] markings]]
*[[Royal New Zealand Air Force]]
**[[No. 1 Squadron RNZAF]]
**[[No. 2 Squadron RNZAF]]
**[[No. 3 Squadron RNZAF]]
**[[No. 4 Squadron RNZAF]]
**[[No. 42 Squadron RNZAF]]
;{{NOR}}
*[[Norwegian Army Air Service]]
;{{PAK}}
*[[Pakistan Air Force]]
;{{POL}}
*[[Polish Air Force]]{{citation needed|date=November 2011}}
*[[Polish Air Forces in France and Great Britain|Polish Air Force in Great Britain]]
;{{POR}}
*[[Portuguese Army|Portuguese Army Aviation]]
*[[Portuguese Naval Aviation]]
*[[Portuguese Air Force]]
;{{flag|Rhodesia}}
*[[Rhodesian Air Force]]
;{{flag|Saudi Arabia}}
*[[Royal Saudi Air Force]]
;{{flag|Spain|1931}}
*[[Spanish Republican Air Force]]
;{{flag|Spanish State}}
*[[Spanish Air Force]]
;{{flag|South Africa|1928}}
*[[South African Air Force]]
;{{flag|Southern Rhodesia}}
*[[Southern Rhodesian Air Force]]
;{{SRI}}
*[[Sri Lankan Air Force]]
;{{SWE}}
*[[Swedish Air Force]]
;{{THA}}
*[[Royal Thai Air Force]]
*[[Royal Thai Navy]]
;{{UK}}
*[[Royal Air Force]]
**[[No. 24 Squadron RAF]]
**[[No. 27 Squadron RAF]]
**[[No. 52 Squadron RAF]]
**[[No. 81 Squadron RAF]]
**[[No. 116 Squadron RAF]]
**[[No. 297 Squadron RAF]]
**[[No. 510 Squadron RAF]]
**[[No. 612 Squadron RAF]]
**[[No. 613 Squadron RAF]]
**[[No. 652 Squadron RAF]]
**[[No. 653 Squadron RAF]]
**[[No. 654 Squadron RAF]]
**[[No. 656 Squadron RAF]]
**[[No. 663 Squadron RAF]]
**[[No. 668 Squadron RAF]]
**[[No. 669 Squadron RAF]]
**[[No. 670 Squadron RAF]]
**[[No. 671 Squadron RAF]]
**[[No. 672 Squadron RAF]]
**[[No. 673 Squadron RAF]]
*[[Fleet Air Arm]]
;{{flag|United States|1912}}
*[[United States Army Air Forces]]
;{{URY}}
*[[Uruguayan Air Force]]
;{{YUG}}
*[[SFR Yugoslav Air Force]] - 24 aircraft&lt;ref&gt;Yugoslav Air Force 1942–1992, Bojan Dimitrijevic, Belgrade 2006&lt;/ref&gt;
**[[2nd Training Aviation Regiment]] (1945–1948)

===Civil operators===
The aircraft is operated by many private individuals and flying clubs.&lt;!-- no need to list individuals and flying clubs --&gt;

==Surviving aircraft==
[[File:De Havilland 82A Tiger Moth II.jpg|thumb|Tiger Moth II preserved at the [[Polish Aviation Museum]], 2006]]
[[File:De Havilland DH-82 Tiger Moth military airplane (Museu do Ar, Portugal).jpg|thumb|Portuguese de Havilland DH-82 Tiger Moth at the ''[[Museu do Ar]]'' (Portuguese Air Force Museum)]]
[[File:De Havilland Tiger Moth (A17-711) at the RAAF Museum.jpg|thumb|de Havilland Tiger Moth (A17-711) in Second World War training colours at the RAAF Museum.]]
[[File:Frontiers of Flight Museum December 2015 017 (de Havilland Tiger Moth).jpg|thumb|A de Havilland Tiger Moth at the [[Frontiers of Flight Museum]]]]

Numerous examples of the Tiger Moth are still flying today (an estimated 250).&lt;ref name=&quot;warbird&quot;&gt;http://www.warbirdalley.com/tiger.htm&lt;/ref&gt; The number of airworthy Tiger Moths has increased as previously neglected aircraft (or those previously only used for static display in museums) have been restored. 

A number of aircraft have been preserved as museum displays (amongst others) at the:
*[[Alberta Aviation Museum]], Edmonton, Canada{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[Aviodrome]] at [[Lelystad Airport]] in The Netherlands{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[Canadian Air and Space Museum]], [[Toronto]], Canada{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[Canada Aviation and Space Museum]], [[Ottawa]], Canada - two examples, 1 on display, 1 stored{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[Canadian Museum of Flight]], [[Langley, British Columbia (city)|Langley]], Canada{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[Canadian Warplane Heritage Museum]], [[Hamilton, Ontario|Hamilton]], Canada{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[Commonwealth Air Training Plan Museum]], [[Brandon, Manitoba]], Canada{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[EAA AirVenture Museum]], [[Oshkosh, Wisconsin|Oshkosh]], United States{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[Swedish Air Force Museum|Flygvapenmuseum]] at [[Malmen Airbase]] near [[Linköping]], Sweden{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[Heritage Park Historical Village|Heritage Park]], [[Calgary]], Canada (on loan from the [[Aero Space Museum of Calgary|Aero Space Museum Association of Calgary]]){{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[Indian Air Force Museum, Palam]] - 1 Airworthy Example for Historic Flight{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[Israeli Air Force Museum]], [[Hatzerim]], [[Israel]]{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[Luskintyre Airfield|Luskintyre Aviation Flying Museum]], [[Luskintyre]], NSW Australia - Tiger moth restorers and builders{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*Mackay Tiger Moth Museum, [[Mackay, Queensland|Mackay]], Australia{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[Malta Aviation Museum]] in Malta{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[de Havilland Aircraft Museum]] in [[London Colney]], England{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*{{Interlanguage link multi|Museo Aeronáutico &quot;Coronel (Aviador) Jaime Meregalli&quot;|es}} in Uruguay{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*{{Interlanguage link multi|Museo Nacional Aeronáutico y del Espacio|es}} in Chile{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[Museu Aeroespacial]], 25&amp;nbsp;km outside [[Rio de Janeiro]] in Brazil{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[Portuguese Air Force|Museu do Ar]], [[Sintra]], Portugal{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[Museum of New Zealand Te Papa Tongarewa]] in [[Wellington]], New Zealand{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[National Museum of Flight]] at [[RAF East Fortune]] in Scotland{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[National Museum of the United States Air Force]], [[Dayton, Ohio]], United States&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nationalmuseum.af.mil/Visit/MuseumExhibits/FactSheets/Display/tabid/509/Article/197392/de-havilland-dh-82a-tiger-moth.aspx &quot;de Havilland DH82A Tiger Moth.&quot;] ''National Museum of the US Air Force. Retrieved: 23 August 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Cole Palen]]'s [[Old Rhinebeck Aerodrome]] in [[Rhinebeck, NY|Rhinebeck]]/[[Red Hook, NY]], United States{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[PAF Museum, Karachi]], Pakistan{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[Polish Aviation Museum]] at the former [[Kraków-Rakowice-Czyżyny Airport]] in Poland{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[RAAF Museum]], [[RAAF Williams]] [[Point Cook, Victoria|Point Cook]], Australia{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[Reynolds-Alberta Museum]] in [[Wetaskiwin]], Canada{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[Royal Aero Club of Western Australia (Inc.)]], [[Jandakot Airport|Jandakot, Australia]]{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[Royal Museum of the Armed Forces and of Military History]], [[Brussels]], Belgium{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[Royal New Zealand Air Force Museum]], [[Wigram]], New Zealand - 1 airworthy aircraft for historic flight{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[Royal Newcastle Aero Club]], [[Rutherford, New South Wales|Rutherford]], NSW, Australia - scenic and aerobatic joyflights in VH-RNI{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[Saskatchewan Western Development Museum]], [[Moose Jaw]], Canada{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[Shuttleworth Collection]] at [[Old Warden]], England{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[List of aircraft of the SLAF#Surviving SLAF aircraft|Sri Lanka Air Force Museum]], [[Sri Lanka]]{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[Temora Aviation Museum]], [[Temora, New South Wales|Temora]], Australia{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[Vintage Wings of Canada]], [[Gatineau]], Qc. Canada{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[Western Canada Aviation Museum]] in [[Winnipeg]], Canada{{CN|date=October 2016}}
*[[Yugoslav Aeronautical Museum]], [[Serbia]]{{CN|date=October 2016}}

==Specifications (DH 82A)==
{{aircraft specifications|
|plane or copter?=plane
|jet or prop?=prop
|ref=''The Tiger Moth Story'',&lt;ref&gt;Bransom 1991, p. 261.&lt;/ref&gt; ''The de Havilland Tiger Moth''&lt;ref name = &quot;jackson 13&quot;&gt;Jackson 1966, p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt;
|crew= two, student &amp; instructor
|capacity=
|payload main=
|payload alt=
|length main= 23 ft 11 in
|length alt= 7.34 m
|span main= 29 ft 4 in
|span alt= 8.94 m
|height main= 8 ft 9 in
|height alt= 2.68 m
|area main= 239 ft²
|area alt= 22.2 m²
|airfoil=
|empty weight main= 1,115 lb
|empty weight alt= 506 kg
|loaded weight main=  1,825 lb
|loaded weight alt= 828 kg
|useful load main= 180 lbs
|useful load alt= 80 kg
|fuel capacity main= 19 imp gallons
|fuel capacity alt= 22 US gallons, 82 liters
|fuel capacity additional main= 10 imp gallon auxiliary tank
|fuel capacity additional alt= 12 US gallons, 45 liters
|max takeoff weight alt= 
|more general=
|engine (prop)= [[de Havilland Gipsy Major]] I inverted 4-cylinder inline
|type of prop=
|number of props=1
|power main= 130 hp
|power alt= 100 kW
|power original=
|max speed main=109 mph at 1,000 ft
|max speed alt= 97 kts, 175 km/h at 300 m
|cruise speed main= 67 mph
|cruise speed alt= 59 kts
|stall speed main= 
|stall speed alt= 
|never exceed speed main= 
|never exceed speed alt= 
|range main=  302 miles
|range alt=250 nm, 486 km
|ceiling main= 13,600 ft
|ceiling alt= 4,145 m
|climb rate main= 673 ft/min
|climb rate alt= 205 m/min
|loading main=
|loading alt=
|thrust/weight=
|power/mass main=
|power/mass alt=
|more performance=
|armament= 8x 20 lb bombs
|avionics=
}}

==See also==
* ''[[The English Patient]]'', an Academy Award-winning film featuring a Tiger Moth in a central role, along with a [[Boeing Stearman]].
{{Portal|Aviation|Canada}}
{{External media|topic= |width=20% |align=right |video1=[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4nZoSqPmDR8 Period instructional video on flying the Tiger Moth] |video2=[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=v_wIOAZ1lm0 In-cockpit footage of a preserved Tiger Moth conducting an instructional flight] |video3=[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oHhzIgbBjJ4 A Tiger Moth performing an aerobatic display routine] |video4=[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kyb3hGRfjfc Compilation of footage from the 2005 Annual International de Havilland Moth Club rally]}}
{{aircontent|
|related=
|similar aircraft=
* [[Boeing-Stearman Kaydet]]
* [[Bücker Bü 131|Bücker Bü 131 Jungmann]]
* [[Fleet Finch]]
* [[Focke-Wulf Fw 44]]
* [[Gotha Go 145]]
* [[Stampe SV.4]]
* [[Polikarpov Po-2]]
|sequence=
|lists=
*[[List of aircraft of the RAF]]
*[[List of aircraft of the RAAF]]
*[[List of aircraft of the RNZAF]]
*[[List of aircraft of the Spanish Republican Air Force]]
|see also=
*''[[Thunderbird 6]]'', a film which also features the Tiger Moth prominently.
}}

==References==
===Citations===
{{reflist|2}}
===Bibliography===
{{refbegin}}
* Bain, Gordon. ''De Havilland: A Pictorial Tribute''. London: AirLife, 1992. ISBN 1-85648-243-X.
* Bransom, Alan. ''The Tiger Moth Story, Fourth Edition''. Shrewsbury, UK: Airlife Publishing Ltd., 1991. ISBN 0-906393-19-1.
* Bransom, Alan. ''The Tiger Moth Story, Fifth Edition''. Manchester, UK: Crécy Publishing Ltd., 2005. ISBN 0-85979-103-3.
* Carter, Ian. ''Coastal Command 1939-1945: Photographs from the Imperial War Museum'', Ian Allan, 2004. ISBN 978-0-7110-3018-3.
* {{cite book|last=Hannah|first=Donald|authorlink=Donald Hannah|title=De Havilland Flypast Reference Library|publisher=Key Publishing|location=Lincs, UK|year=1982|isbn=0-946219 00-1}}
* Hotson, Fred. ''The De Havilland Canada Story''. Toronto: CANAV Books, 1983. ISBN 0-9690703-2-2.
* Jackson, A.J. '' The de Havilland Tiger Moth: Aircraft Profile No. 132''. Leatherhead, Surrey, UK: Profile Publications Ltd., 1966.
* Ketley, Barry and Mark Rolfe. ''Luftwaffe Fledglings 1935–1945: Luftwaffe Training Units and their Aircraft.'' Aldershot, UK: Hikoki Publications, 1996. ISBN 0-9519899-2-8.
* Lake, Deborah, [https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=EbveV8w0ofIC&amp;pg=PT12&amp;lpg=PT12 ''Growling Over the Oceans: Avro Shackleton: The Men and the Missions, 1951-1991.''] Souvenir Press Ltd, 2010. ISBN 978-0285638761.
* McKay, Stuart. ''Tiger Moth''. New York: Orion Books, 1998. ISBN 0-517-56864-0.
* {{cite book|last=Rimell|first=Ray|authorlink=Ray Rimell|title=Tiger Moth De Havilland DH82 Tiger Moth|series=Aeroguide Classics number 6|publisher=Limewrights Ltd|location=Essex, UK|year=1992|isbn=0-946958-38-6}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons|de Havilland Tiger Moth}}
{{refbegin}}
*[http://www.fliegendes-museum.de/Tiger_Moth.html Fliegendes Museum]
*[http://www.museoaeronautico.cl/espanol/pop-ficha.php?id=15 Tiger Moth preserved by Chile's Aviation Museum, at the official Museo's website]
*[http://wcam.mb.ca/945/de-havilland-dh-82c-tiger-moth/ Western Canada Aviation Museum: De Havilland Tiger Moth (D.H.82c)]
*[http://www.historicaircraft.org/British-Aircraft/pages/DeHavilland-QueenBee-1.html A photograph of a de Havilland DH.82B Queen Bee]
*[http://www.airforce.lk/news.php?news=194 Sri Lanka Air Force - Tiger Moth and Chipmunk news]
*[http://www.artiklar.z-bok.se/Iran-2.html Civil and Military Aviation in Iran 1924–1949]
{{refend}}

{{de Havilland aircraft}}
{{De Havilland Australia aircraft}}
{{De Havilland Canada}}
{{USAF trainer aircraft}}
{{Swedish trainer aircraft}}

[[Category:British military trainer aircraft 1930–1939]]
[[Category:De Havilland aircraft|Tiger Moth 82]]
[[Category:World War II British trainer aircraft]]
[[Category:Biplanes]]
[[Category:Single-engined tractor aircraft]]
[[Category:Glider tugs]]</text>
      <sha1>5uleaq5812ah0g64puzu5qcfzi50oac</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
