<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Defensive fighting position</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>401883</id>
    <revision>
      <id>747614181</id>
      <parentid>746972445</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-03T10:38:32Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cydebot</username>
        <id>1215485</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Robot - Speedily moving category Fortification by type to [[:Category:Fortifications by type]] per [[WP:CFDS|CFDS]].</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9426">{{Multiple issues|
{{refimprove|date=January 2013}}
{{globalize|date=May 2014}}
}}

[[Image:Foxhole - Lebanon - Beirut - July 1958.jpg|thumb|250px|right|U.S. Marine in a fighting hole, July 1958, in [[Lebanon]]]]
A '''defensive fighting position''' ('''DFP''') is a type of [[Earthworks (engineering)#Military use|earthwork constructed in a military context]], generally large enough to accommodate anything from one man to a small number of soldiers.

== Terminology ==
A '''foxhole''' is one type of defensive strategic position. It is a &quot;small pit used for cover, usually for one or two men, and so constructed that the occupants can effectively fire from it.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Bundessprachenamt. ''Militärisches Studienglossar. Englisch. Teil I, A-K.'' Hürth, 2001, p. 580.&lt;/ref&gt;

It is known more commonly within [[United States Army]] slang as a &quot;'''fighting position'''&quot; or as a &quot;'''ranger grave'''&quot;. It is known as a &quot;'''fighting hole'''&quot; in the [[United States Marine Corps]], a &quot;'''Gun-Pit'''&quot; in [[Australian Army]] [[terminology]], and a &quot;'''fighting pit'''&quot; in the [[New Zealand Army]].

In [[United Kingdom|British]] and [[Canada|Canadian]] military [[argot]] it equates to a range of terms including '''slit trench''', or '''fire trench''' (a trench deep enough for a man to stand in), a '''sangar''' (sandbagged fire position above ground) or '''shell scrape''' (a shallow depression that affords protection in the prone position), or simply—but less accurately—as a &quot;[[Trench warfare|trench]]&quot;. 

During the [[American Civil War]] the term &quot;'''rifle pit'''&quot; was recognized by both U.S. Army and [[Confederate Army]] forces.

==History==
[[Image:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-263-1580-06, Atlantikwall, Soldat der Legion &quot;Freies Indien&quot;.jpg|right|250px|thumb|An [[Indische Legion|Indian Wehrmacht volunteer]] in a Tobruk DFP along the [[Atlantic Wall]], 1944.]]
&lt;!--'Early in [[World War II]],' - Op Torch began 8 Nov 1942, 77 days after the mid point of the war, so we are talking about something that happened in the 2nd half of WW2; this is not early war.--&gt;During the fighting in [[North African Campaign|North Africa]] (1942-43), [[U.S. forces]] employed the ''slit trench''. This was a very shallow excavation allowing one man to lie horizontally while shielding his body from nearby [[Shell (projectile)|shell]] bursts and [[small arms]] fire.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first=Albert S |last=Brown |title=Anzio: Jan-May 1944 |work=World War II Memories of Staff Sergeant Albert S. Brown |publisher=Dogface Soldiers Memoirs |url= http://www.dogfacesoldiers.org/info/memoirs/brown/anzio.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;46-47&quot;&gt;{{cite book |first=Edwin V. |last=Westrate |title=Forward Observer |location=New York City |publisher=Stratford Press |year=1944 |pages=46–47}}&lt;/ref&gt; The slit trench soon proved inadequate in this role, as the few inches of dirt above the soldier's body could often be penetrated by bullets or shell fragments. It also exposed the user to assault by enemy [[tank]]s, which could crush the man inside a shallow slit trench by driving into it, then making a simple half-turn.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Edwin V. |last=Westrate |title=Forward Observer |location=New York City |publisher=Stratford Press |year=1944 |page=115}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After the [[Battle of Kasserine Pass]] (early 1943), U.S. troops increasingly adopted the modern ''foxhole'', a vertical, bottle-shaped hole that allowed a soldier to stand and fight with head and shoulders exposed.&lt;ref name=&quot;46-47&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |first=Edwin V. |last=Westrate |title=Forward Observer |location=New York City |publisher=Stratford Press |year=1944 |page=77}}&lt;/ref&gt; The foxhole widened near the bottom to allow a soldier to crouch down while under intense [[artillery]] fire or tank attack.&lt;ref name=&quot;46-47&quot; /&gt; Foxholes could be enlarged to two-soldier fighting positions, as well as excavated with firing steps for crew-served weapons or [[sump]]s for water drainage or live enemy [[grenade]] [[Bomb disposal|disposal]].

===Tobruk===
[[File:Tobruk at the CI Military Museum.JPG|left|100px|thumb|Tobruk protecting the entrance to the bunker that now houses the Channel Islands Military Museum. This turret from a [[Renault R35]] was originally employed on a Tobruk at Saint Aubin's Fort, Jersey.]]
[[Image:German turret at Omaha Beach.jpg|thumb|right|German VK 3001H prototype turret mounted on &quot;Tobruk&quot; at Omaha Beach, June 1944]]
The Germans used hardened fortifications in North Africa and later in other fortifications, such as the [[Atlantic Wall]], that were in essence foxholes made from concrete. The Germans knew them officially as ''Ringstände''; the Allies called them &quot;[[Tobruk]]s&quot; because they had first encountered the structures during the fighting in Africa.&lt;ref&gt;Zaloga, Steven J. ''D-Day Fortifications in Normandy'' (Osprey Publishing Ltd.) ISBN 1-84176-876-6 p.21&lt;/ref&gt;

Frequently, the Germans put a turret from an obsolete French or German tank on the foxhole. This gave the Tobruk enhanced firepower and the gunner protection from shrapnel and small arms.

==Modern==

Modern militaries publish and distribute elaborate field manuals for the proper construction of DFPs in stages. Initially, a shallow &quot;shell scrape&quot; is dug, much like a very shallow grave, which provides very limited protection. Each stage develops the fighting position, gradually increasing its effectiveness, while always maintaining functionality. In this way, a soldier can improve the position over time, while being able to stop at any time and use the position in a fight.

Typically, a DFP is a pit dug deep enough to stand in, with only the head exposed, and a small step at the bottom, called a fire step, that allows the soldier to crouch into to avoid fire and [[tank]] [[Continuous track|treads]]. The fire step usually slopes down into a deeper narrow slit called a [[grenade]] [[sump]] at the bottom to allow for live grenades to be kicked in to minimize frag damage.

When possible, DFPs are revetted with corrugated iron, star pickets and wire or local substitutes. Ideally, the revetting will also be dug in below ground level so as to minimise damage from fire and tank tracks. The revetting helps the DFP resist cave in from near misses from artillery or mortars and tank tracks.

Time permitting, DFPs can be enlarged to allow a [[machine gun]] crew and [[ammunition]] to be protected, as well as additional overhead cover via timbers.

In training, DFPs are usually dug by hand or in some cases by mechanical trench diggers. On operations, explosives, especially [[Shaped charge|shaped charges (&quot;beehives&quot;)]], may be used to increase the speed of development.

Developing and maintaining DFPs is a constant and ongoing task for soldiers deployed in combat areas. For this reason, in some armies, infantry is referred to as &quot;gravel technicians&quot;, as they spend so much time digging.

Because of the large expenditure in effort and materials required to build a DFP, it is important to ensure that the DFP is correctly sited. In order to site the DFP, the officer in charge (&quot;OIC&quot;) should view the ground from the same level that the intended user's weapons will be sighted from. Normally, the OIC will need to lie on his belly to obtain the required perspective. This ensures that the position will be able to cover the desired sector.

&lt;gallery&gt;
File:3rd Battalion 4th Marines dig in near Iraqi border 2003-03-20.JPEG|US Marines digging 'fighting holes' near the Iraqi border, 2003.
File:US_Navy_030209-N-5319A-005_Seabees_of_Naval_Mobile_Construction_Battalion_Seventy-Four_(NMCB-74)_have_only_ten_minutes_to_dig.jpg|US Navy Seabees digging 'hasty scrapes', 2003.
File:US Navy 030209-N-5319A-006 Construction Electrician 3rd Class Justin Vizcarrondo assigned to Naval Mobile Construction Battalion Seventy-Four (NMCB-74) uses an entrenching tool to dig a hasty scrape.jpg|US Navy Seabees near completed fighting position, 2003.
File:US Navy 101104-N-8816D-008 Chief Steelworker Corey Mead, assigned to Naval Mobile Construction Battalion (NMCB) 133, digs a fighting position during training.jpg|US Navy Seabees constructing a defensive machine gun position during training, 2010.
File:US Navy 081104-N-7367K-011 Seabees assigned to Naval Mobile Construction Battalion (NMCB) 1 keep guard the protective lines from a fighting position at forward operating base zero.jpg|US Navy Seabees with a completed defensive machine gun position during training, 2008.
File:US Navy 101017-N-4440L-022 Equipment Operator Constructionman Travis Love, assigned to the air detail of Naval Mobile Construction Battalion (NMCB).jpg|US Navy Seabees completed defensive machine gun position during training with camouflage netting and timber supports, 2010.
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
* [[Sangar (fortification)|Sangar]]
* [[Spider hole]]
* [[Shell scrape]]
* [[Tett turret]]
* [[Trench warfare]]
* [[All round defence|All-around defense/Perimeter defense]]
* [[Entrenching tool]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==References==
* {{cite book |first=Edwin V. |last=Westrate |title=Forward Observer |location=New York City |publisher=Stratford Press |year=1944}}

==External links==
*[http://digital.library.unt.edu/permalink/meta-dc-1005:2 U.S. WWII Newsmap, &quot;Foxholes are Life Savers&quot;], hosted by the [http://digital.library.unt.edu/ UNT Libraries Digital Collections]

{{Fortifications}}

[[Category:Military tactics]]
[[Category:Land warfare]]
[[Category:Fortifications by type]]</text>
      <sha1>7jww3ud0045c707oabhr178x351zous</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
