<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Dragon Skin</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>18890086</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738889469</id>
      <parentid>728510981</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-11T17:10:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GreenC bot</username>
        <id>27823944</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[User:Green Cardamom/WaybackMedic 2|WaybackMedic 2]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="25543">{{update|date=August 2010}}
{{use mdy dates|date=January 2012}}
[[File:PEO soldier Dragonskin.jpg|thumb|X-ray of Dragon Skin Body Armor]]

'''Dragon Skin''' is a type of [[ballistic vest]] formerly made by the now defunct company [[Pinnacle Armor]], currently produced in [[Missoula, Montana]] by North American Development Group LLC available for public, law-enforcement and military customers. Its characteristic two-inch-wide circular discs overlap like [[scale armour|scale armor]], creating a flexible vest that allows a good range of motion and is intended to absorb a high number of hits compared with other military [[body armor]]. The discs are composed of [[silicon carbide]] [[ceramic]] matrices and [[laminate]]s, much like the larger [[ceramic plate]]s in other types of bullet resistant vests.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.defensereview.com/dragon-skin-armor-passes-more-tests-dr-gary-roberts-and-test-lab-video/| title=Dragon Skin Armor Passes More Tests: Dr. Gary Roberts and 'Test Lab' Video|date=October 9, 2006|first=David|last=Crane}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The armor is currently available in one basic protection level: Dragon Skin Extreme (formerly SOV-2000), which until 2007 was certified to comply with the [[National Institute of Justice|NIJ]] [[Bulletproof vest#Performance standards|Standard-0101.06]] as a level III resistant body armor.&lt;ref name=&quot;DOJ&quot;&gt;{{cite web | publisher = Department of Justice| url = http://www.ojp.usdoj.gov/newsroom/2007/NIJ07057.htm| title = Department of justice announces findings on dragon skin body armor| accessdate = 2007-08-07 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20071014013721/http://www.ojp.usdoj.gov/newsroom/2007/NIJ07057.htm  |archivedate = 2007-10-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Defense Review&quot;&gt;{{cite web | work = Defense Review | url = http://www.defensereview.com/modules.php?name=News&amp;file=article&amp;sid=925 | title = Dragon Skin Body Armor (SOV-2000) Passes all NIJ Level III Tests at USTL | accessdate = 2006-09-28 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Dragon Skin has been worn by some [[Private military company|civilian contractors]] in [[Iraq]], some [[Special forces|special operations forces]] in Iraq and [[Afghanistan]],&lt;ref name=M927&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.military.com/opinion/0,15202,78927,00.html |title=Getting America's Best? |publisher=Military.com |date= |accessdate=2012-01-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; some [[SWAT]] teams,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ci.minneapolis.mn.us/council/2006-meetings/20060901/Docs/15_OP_6646.pdf |title=Microsoft Word - 08-23 OP 6646.doc |publisher=Ci.minneapolis.mn.us |date=2011-12-14 |accessdate=2012-01-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; nine [[General officer|generals]] in Afghanistan,&lt;ref name=M927/&gt;&lt;ref name=MSNBC550&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/18720550/print/1/displaymode/1098/ |title=Are U.S. soldiers wearing the best body armor? - NBC News Investigates |publisher=MSNBC |date= 2007-05-20|accessdate=2012-01-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[bodyguard]]s tasked with protecting generals,&lt;ref name=MSNBC550/&gt; and [[United States Secret Service|U.S. Secret Service]] personnel.&lt;ref name=M927/&gt; The [[Central Intelligence Agency]] (CIA) has also purchased Dragon Skin.&lt;ref name=MSNBC550/&gt;

== Structure ==
Dragon Skin armor is made of an overlapping series of high tensile strength ceramic discs encased in a glass fiber textile. Different layout configurations with variations in coverage are available.

Dragon Skin Extreme is made of overlapping approximately {{convert|0.25|in|mm|adj=on}} × {{convert|2|in|mm|adj=on}} ceramic discs encased in a fabric cover. In evaluating the Dragon Skin system, it is important to note that while the external measurements of the Dragon Skin panel are {{convert|11.5|in|mm}} × {{convert|13.5|in|mm}}, the area of level III coverage provided by the encased ceramic discs is {{convert|10|in|mm}} × {{convert|12|in|mm}}; the fabric edges are ''not'' intended to provide ballistic protection. Weight of the Dragon Skin Extreme armor providing {{convert|10|in|mm}} × {{convert|12|in|mm}} of level III protection was approximately {{convert|6.4|lb|kg|1|abbr=on}}.

== Testing ==

=== Television ===
In a test for the [[History (U.S. TV channel)|History Channel]]'s military show, ''[[Mail Call]]'', the vest repelled nine rounds of steel-core ammunition from an [[AK-47]] full automatic and 35 rounds of [[9×19mm Parabellum|9×19mm]] from a [[Heckler &amp; Koch MP5|Heckler &amp; Koch MP5A3]], all fired into a 10-by-12-inch area on the vest. On ''[[Test Lab]]'', also on the [[History (U.S. TV channel)|History Channel]], the vest withstood 120 rounds fired from a [[Type 56]] ([[7.62×39mm]]) rifle and [[Heckler &amp; Koch MP5]] (9×19mm). In another demonstration on the [[Discovery Channel]] series ''[[Future Weapons]]'', a Dragon Skin vest withstood numerous rounds (including steel core rounds) from an [[AK-47]], a [[Heckler &amp; Koch MP5|Heckler &amp; Koch MP5SD]], an [[M4 carbine]] ([[5.56×45mm NATO|5.56×45mm]]), and a point-blank detonation of an [[M67 grenade]]. While the vest was heavily damaged (mainly by the grenade), there was no penetration of the armor.

In 2007, [[NBC News]] had independent ballistics testing conducted of Dragon Skin versus [[Interceptor body armor]]. Retired four-star general [[Wayne A. Downing]] observed the tests and concluded that although the number of trials performed was limited, the Dragon Skin armor performed significantly better.&lt;ref name=MSNBC550/&gt;

In light of the May 2007 media investigations, senators [[Hillary Clinton]] and [[Jim Webb]] requested that [[Comptroller General of the United States]] [[David M. Walker (U.S. Comptroller General)|David M. Walker]] initiate a [[Government Accountability Office]] investigation into the army's body armor systems.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release |url=http://www.webb.senate.gov/newsroom/record.cfm?id=274656&amp; |title=Webb &amp; Clinton call for investigation into the effectiveness of body armor issued to our troops |author=[[Jim Webb|Webb, Jim]] |publisher=U.S. Senate |date=2007-05-18 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080606234120/http://webb.senate.gov/newsroom/record.cfm?id=274656 |archivedate=2008-06-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After being confronted with conflicting information by lawmakers who questioned the NBC test results and provided Army-supplied data of vest failures from a May 2006 test, the technical expert solicited by NBC to certify its test backed away from his staunch defense of Dragon Skin and stated that the vests &quot;weren't ready for prime time&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | publisher= military.com
 | url = http://www.military.com/NewsContent/0,13319,138277,00.html
 | title = Dragon Skin Backers Hammered on Hill
 | accessdate = 2007-06-10
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It was also featured on ''[[Time Warp (TV series)|Time Warp]]'' on the Discovery Channel.

=== Law enforcement ===

In [[Fresno, California]], a police department commissioned the purchase of Dragon Skin for its officers after a vest stopped all the bullets fired during a test, including .308 rounds from a rifle and 30 rounds from a 9mm MP5 fired from five feet away. The armor also stopped 40 rounds of PS-M1943 mild steel-core bullets from an AK-47 along with 200 9&amp;nbsp;mm [[full metal jacket bullet]] fired from a submachine gun.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fresno Bee Newspaper&quot;&gt;{{cite web | work = [[The Fresno Bee]] | url = http://www.fresnobee.com/local/story/12110759p-12860958c.html | title = Army ban puts Dragon Skin in the line of fire | accessdate = 2006-05-15 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20060504203223/http://www.fresnobee.com/local/story/12110759p-12860958c.html |archivedate = 2006-05-04}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Academic ===

Dragon Skin Level III armor was also tested the week of October 2, 2006 by Dr. Gary Roberts, [[Dental degree|DDS]], Stanford University Medical Center.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | author = Roberts, Gary, MD | url = http://www.tacticalforums.com/cgi-bin/tacticalubb/ultimatebb.cgi?ubb=get_topic;f=78;t=001286;p=1#000000 | title = Pinnacle Dragon Skin SOV-2000 Test | accessdate = 2006-10-09 }}&lt;/ref&gt; These tests were conducted for a local law enforcement agency, as a control sample a stand-alone Armored Mobility Incorporated (AMI) level III steel composite plate armor was used for comparison. Both types of armor were conditioned for 12 hours at {{convert|170|°F|°C}}, then moved to ambient air for approximately 90 minutes prior to being shot. The problems associated with the use of inelastic clay backing material have been well documented; as such, the armor was secured to a life-size curvilinear torso replica made of [[Ballistic gelatin|Perma-Gel]]. Each armor system was shot a minimum of 20 times with five rounds of each ammunition type fired against each armor system—one 90 degree perpendicular shot, two shots at 60 degrees obliquity, and two shots at 30 degrees obliquity, using each of the following loads fired at a distance of {{convert|10|ft|m}}:

* 5.56&amp;nbsp;mm 40 gr LeMas Urban Warfare (using a moly coated Nosler Ballistic Tip bullet) with a {{convert|3718|ft|m}} per second average velocity.
* 5.56&amp;nbsp;mm M855 62 gr FMJ with a {{convert|3054|ft|m}} per second average velocity.
* 7.62×39mm M43 123 gr steel-core FMJ with a {{convert|2307|ft|m}} per second average velocity.
* .30-06 M2 150 gr FMJ with a {{convert|2736|ft|m}} per second average velocity.

All of the above ammo was successfully stopped by both armor systems in this testing, with no armor failures or penetrations, even after receiving multiple hits.

=== Military testing ===
{{externalimage|image1 = [http://www.professionalsoldiers.com/files/dragon_skin_release_000121may07.pdf Official Army Test Results] &lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.professionalsoldiers.com/files/dragon_skin_release_000121may07.pdf |title=Project Manager Soldier Equipment Briefing on the May 2006 Evaluation of Pinnacle Armor SOV 3000 'Dragon Skin' | format=PDF | date= May 12, 2007 | accessdate=2012-01-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Dragon Skin became the subject of controversy with the [[United States Army|U.S. Army]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | publisher = TheState.com | url = http://www.thestate.com/mld/thestate/news/nation/14358966.htm | title = Dispute ties up body armor plan | accessdate = 2006-05-15 }}&lt;/ref&gt; over testing it against its Interceptor body armor. The Army claimed Pinnacle's body armor was not proven to be effective.  In test runs for the [[United States Air Force|Air Force]] there were multiple failures to meet the claimed level of protection.  This coupled with poor quality control (over 200 of the 380 vests delivered to USAF OSI were recalled due to improperly manufactured armor disks) and accusations of fraudulent claims of official NIJ rating which Pinnacle had not actually obtained at the time of purchase led to the termination of the USAF contract.  Pinnacle attempted to appeal this decision, but courts found in favor of the USAF.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | publisher = Armed Services Board of Contract Appeals | url=http://www.asbca.mil/Decisions/2009/55831.pdf | title=Opinion and Decision of the Armed Services Board of Contract Appeals in ASBCA No. 55831, Appeal of Pinnacle Armor, Inc. | format=PDF | date=16 July 2009 | accessdate = 2014-08-09 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On April 26, 2006 Pinnacle Armor issued a press release to address these claims and a product recall instigated by the [[United States Navy]].&lt;ref name=426-pr&gt;{{cite press release
 | publisher = Pinnacle Armor
 | url = http://www.pinnaclearmor.com/20060426-pr.php
 | title = Response to US Army's allegations of failed Air Force testing
 | accessdate = 2006-06-22
 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20060516081433/http://www.pinnaclearmor.com/20060426-pr.php
 |archivedate = 2006-05-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; The company stated that although vests were returned due to a manufacturing issue, a test on the Dragon Skin Level III armor was conducted by the United States [[Air Force Office of Special Investigations]] at a U.S Army Aberdeen Test Center in [[Aberdeen, Maryland]] in February 2006, which concluded that it &quot;did not fail any written contract specifications&quot; set forth by the Air Force,&lt;ref name=426-pr/&gt; which was further stated by Pinnacle Armor to require high ballistic performance due to the hostile environments in which AFOSI operates.&lt;ref name=426-pr/&gt;

Weapon review website Defense Review also published an article similarly dissenting, noting that in their test and review of the Dragon Skin armor, they had found that it was &quot;significantly superior in every combat-relevant way to U.S. Army PEO Soldier's and U.S. Army Natick Soldier Center (NSC)/Soldier Systems Center's Interceptor Body Armor&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | publisher = DefenseReview.com
 | url = http://www.defensereview.com/modules.php?name=News&amp;file=article&amp;sid=864
 | title = DefRev Sees Test Data: Dragon Skin Hands-Down Superior to Army's Interceptor
 | accessdate = 2006-05-15
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Pentagon stated that the test results were classified and neither side could agree to terms on another, more comprehensive test. The Army wanted to hold and inspect the vests for 1–2 weeks before shooting at them, and Pinnacle wanted them shot at right away from out of the box because they said they feared the Army tampering with them in order to save their currently cheaper body armor program.{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}}

On May 19, 2006 it was announced that the dispute had been resolved and the vests were going to be retested again by the Army to clear the dispute.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 | publisher = military.com
 | agency=Army News Service
 | url = http://www.military.com/features/0,15240,97959,00.html
 | title = Army Tests Pinnacle Armor &quot;Dragon Skin&quot; Vests
 | accessdate = 2006-05-23
}}&lt;/ref&gt;  On May 20, 2006 it was announced by ''[[The Washington Post]]'' (and other newspapers) in an article titled &quot;Potential Advance in Body Armor Fails Tests&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
 | work = [[The Washington Post]]
 | url = http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/05/19/AR2006051901606.html
 | title = Potential Advance in Body Armor Fails Tests
 | accessdate = 2006-07-08
 | first=Lolita C.
 | last=Baldor
 | date=May 20, 2006
}}&lt;/ref&gt; that the Dragon Skin vests had failed the retest according to their anonymous source. Official results of these tests were classified at the time but have since been released by the Army.

On June 6, 2006 in comments posted on an online discussion forum, Karl Masters, director of engineering for Program Manager - Soldier Equipment, said he recently supervised the retest and commented on it.  &quot;I was recently tasked by the army to conduct the test of the 30 Dragon Skin SOV-3000 level IV body armor purchased for T&amp;E [tests and evaluation],&quot; Masters wrote. &quot;My day job is acting product manager for Interceptor Body Armor. I'm under a gag order until the test results make it up the chain. I will, however, offer an enlightened and informed recommendation to anyone considering purchasing an SOV-3000 Dragon Skin—don't. I do not recommend this design for use in an AOR with a [[7.62×54mmR|7.62×54R]] AP threat and an ambient temperature that could range to 49°C (120 F). I do, however, highly recommend this system for use by insurgents...&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 | publisher=DefenseTech.org
 | url = http://www.defensetech.org/archives/002548.html
 | title = New Twist in Dragon Armor Tale
 | accessdate = 2006-08-07
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In response to these claims, Pinnacle Armor released a press release on June 30, 2006.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release
 | publisher = Pinnacle Armor|format= 2nd press release
 | url = http://www.pinnaclearmor.com/20060630-pr.php
 | title = Response to Karl Masters' (US Army) public statements regarding unfinished FAT testing
 | accessdate = 2006-08-07
}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Official results of these tests are classified.

According to the Army, the vests failed because the extreme temperature tests caused the discs to dislodge, thus rendering the vest ineffective. Pinnacle Armor affirms that their products can withstand environmental tests in accordance with military standards, as does testing by the Aberdeen Test Center.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.sftt.org/cgi-bin/csNews/csNews.cgi?database=Unlisted%202007%2edb&amp;command=viewone&amp;id=33 |title= CORRECTED VERSION: Two Dragon Skin Level IV Panels (Slightly Larger than the Standard ESAPI Plate) Took Four &amp; Five ESAPI-FAT Specification Shots Respectively, After High Temperature Exposure/Conditioning, and Defeated Every Shot |publisher= Soldiers for the Truth |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090617205535/http://www.sftt.org/cgi-bin/csNews/csNews.cgi?database=Unlisted%202007.db&amp;command=viewone&amp;id=33 |archivedate=2009-06-17}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In response to claims made by several U.S. senators, Dragon Skin and special interest groups, on Monday, May 21, 2007, the Army held a press conference where they released the results of the tests they claimed Dragon Skin failed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |last=Baldor |first= Lolita C. |url=http://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/20070521/ap_on_go_ca_st_pe/army_body_armor |title=Army says Dragon Skin armor falls short|agency= [[Associated Press|AP]]|date= May 21, 2007 |publisher=[[Yahoo! News]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sgt. Wood, Sara. [http://www.army.mil/-news/2007/05/22/3292-army-defends-body-armor-quality &quot;Army Defends Body Armor Quality&quot;]. [[United States Army]] press release, May 22, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dawson, Debi. [http://www.army.mil/-news/2007/05/22/3298-army-defends-interceptor-body-armor-as-the-best-for-the-best &quot;Army Defends Interceptor Body Armor as the Best for the Best&quot;]. [[United States Army]] press release, May 22, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dawson, Debi. [https://www.peosoldier.army.mil/mediaalerts/bodyarmor.asp &quot;Army Defends Interceptor Body Armor as the Best for the Best&quot;]. [[United States Army]], Program Executive Office Soldier press release.&lt;/ref&gt;

In April 2008 one of the Dragon Skin vests, with a serial number that identifies it as one of 30 vests bought by the Department of Defense for U.S. Army for testing in 2006, was listed and later bought from [[eBay]].  The seller, David Bronson, allegedly was connected to a U.S. Army testing facility. The U.S. [[Government Accountability Office]] (GAO), the [[United States Department of Justice|U.S. Department of Justice]], and the [[Federal Bureau of Investigation|F.B.I.]] are investigating the matter as of May 2008.  The buyer described the vest as having been shot at least 20 times, with not a single through-penetration.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Phillips |first=Preston |url=http://www.ksee24.com/news/local/18536329.html |title=EXCLUSIVE: &quot;Dragon Skin&quot; vest bought on eBay, amid federal investigation |publisher=KSEE 24 NEWS |date=2010-07-30 |accessdate=2012-01-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.capecodonline.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20080504/NEWS/805040344 |title=Body armor's Web of mystery |work=[[Cape Cod Times]] |date=2008-05-04 |accessdate=2012-01-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==U.S. Army bans privately purchased body armor==
On March 30, 2006 the Army banned all privately purchased commercial body armor in theater. Army officials told the [[Associated Press]] that the ban order was prompted by concerns that soldiers or their families were buying inadequate or untested commercial armor from private companies.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,189763,00.html |title=U.S. Army Bans Use of Privately Purchased Body Armor by Troops |publisher=FoxNews.com |date=2006-03-30 |accessdate=2012-01-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Army ban refers specifically to Pinnacle's Dragon Skin armor saying that the company advertising implies that Dragon Skin &quot;is superior in performance&quot; to the [[Interceptor Body Armor]] the military issues to soldiers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite  news|url=http://www.usatoday.com/news/washington/2006-03-30-bodyarmor_x.htm |title=Army bans use of privately bought armor|work= [[USA Today]]|agency=[[Associated Press|AP]]|date=March 30, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[United States Marine Corps|Marine Corps]] has not issued a similar directive, but Marines are &quot;encouraged to wear Marine Corps-issued body armor since this armor has been tested to meet fleet standards.&quot; [[NBC News]] learned that well after the Army ban that select [[elite forces]] assigned to protect generals and VIPs in [[Iraq]] and [[Afghanistan]] wore Dragon Skin.&lt;ref name=MSNBC550/&gt; General [[Peter W. Chiarelli]] made a statement that, &quot;he never wore Dragon Skin but that some members of his staff did wear a lighter version of the banned armor on certain limited occasions, despite the Army ban.&quot;&lt;ref name=MSNBC550/&gt;

[[Chris Kyle]] stated in his book ''[[American Sniper (book)|American Sniper]]'' that he wore Dragon Skin body armor after his third deployment which he received from his wife's parents as a gift.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Kyle |first=Chris |date=28 December 2011 |title=American Sniper |publisher=William Morrow and Company |page=143 |isbn=9780062082350 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Certification and subsequent decertification ==

In an interview with KSEE 24 News, an NBC affiliate, on November 14, 2006 and November 16, 2006, Pinnacle Armor detailed the five-year process that the NIJ and Pinnacle Armor went through to establish a test protocol and procedure for flexible rifle defeating armor, and then pass it for the certification.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| publisher = KSEE 24 News / Special Assignment:
| url = http://www.ksee24.com/special/default.aspx?preview=&amp;type=sa&amp;NStoryID=5672
| title = Dragon Skin Part I
}} and
{{cite web
| url = http://www.ksee24.com/special/default.aspx?preview=&amp;type=sa&amp;NStoryID=5678
| title = Dragon Skin Part II
}}Retrieved on 2006-11-18
&lt;/ref&gt;

On December 20, 2006, Pinnacle Armor said that they received the official letter from the National Institute of Justice (NIJ) that they had passed the Level III tests, and that Dragon Skin SOV-2000 was now certified for Level III protection.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| title = NIJ Certification
| url = https://www.justnet.org
| publisher = National Institute of Justice, U.S. Department of Justice
}} and
{{cite web
| title = Notice of Compliance with NIJ 2005 Interim Requirements
| url = http://www.defensereview.com/stories/pinnaclearmor/Compliance%20Letter%20Pinnacle%20Armor%20SOV2000%201-MIL3AF01%20level%20III.pdf
| publisher = Defense Review
}} and
{{cite news
| date = December 21, 2006
| title = Dragon Skin armor certified
| work = [[The Fresno Bee]]
}} and
{{cite web
| url = http://www.ksee24.com
| title = KSEE 24 News
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

The Air Force, which ordered the Dragon Skin vests partially based on claims it was NIJ certified at a time when it was not, has opened a criminal investigation into the firm Pinnacle Armor over allegations that it had fraudulently placed a label on their Dragon Skin armor improperly stating that it had been certified to a ballistic level it had not yet been. Murray Neal, the Pinnacle Armor chief executive, claimed that he was given verbal authorization by the NIJ to label the vests although he did not have written authorization.&lt;ref name=&quot;Govexec&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| last = Govexec
| url = http://www.govexec.com/story_page.cfm?articleid=37128
| title = Government Executive: Lawmakers say body armor firm made false claims
| accessdate = 2007-06-10
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

On August 3, 2007, the Department of Justice announced that the NIJ had reviewed evidence provided by the body armor manufacturer and has determined that the evidence is insufficient to demonstrate that the body armor model will maintain its ballistic performance over its six-year declared warranty period. Because of this, Dragon Skin has been found not in compliance with the NIJ's testing program and has been removed from the NIJ's list of bullet-resistant body armor models that satisfy its requirements.&lt;ref name=&quot;DOJ&quot; /&gt;  Pinnacle CEO Murray Neal responded that this move was unprecedented, political, and not about the quality of the vests because they are not saying they have failed any ballistics. He says it is about a dispute with the paperwork to deal with a warranty issue instead, in which the warranty period of Dragon Skin is longer than that of most other commercial vests.

===After passing tests at United States Test Laboratory===
On August 20, 2007, at the United States Test Laboratory in [[Wichita, Kansas]], nine Dragon Skin SOV-2000 (Level III) body armor panels were retested, for the purpose of validating Pinnacle Armor's six-year warranty. The panels tested were between 5.7 years old and 6.8 years old. All items met the NIJ Level III ballistic protection, confirming Pinnacle Armor's six-year warranty for full ballistic protection.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.defensereview.com/dragon-skin-passes-again-nij-certified-lab-test-validates-6-year-warranty/ &quot;Dragon Skin Passes Again: NIJ-Certified Lab Test Validates 6-Year Warranty&quot;]. ''Defense Review''.&lt;/ref&gt; Pinnacle resubmitted the SOV-2000 vest to the NIJ for certification based on this successful testing, but this application was rejected because the test had not been properly documented. In November 2007, Pinnacle sued to force the NIJ to recertify the SOV-2000 vest; their case was found to be without merit and summarily dismissed in November 2013.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.leagle.com/decision/In%20FDCO%2020131105500.xml/PINNACLE%20ARMOR,%20INC.%20v.%20U.S.&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
*[http://www.pinnaclearmor.com/body-armor/dragon-skin/ Dragon Skin] at [[Pinnacle Armor]]
*[https://www.peosoldier.army.mil U.S. Army's Program Executive Office Soldier]
*[http://www.professionalsoldiers.com/files/dragon_skin_release_000121may07.pdf Official results of the Army's Dragon Skin test.]
*[http://dragonskinarmor.com/ Dragonskin.com]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Dragon Skin (Body Armor)}}
[[Category:Personal armour]]</text>
      <sha1>480r7x5s8tub5f4l2uqcvamitb7l7x6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
