<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Evacuation of Karafuto and Kuriles</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>29600484</id>
    <revision>
      <id>746171363</id>
      <parentid>740522931</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-25T18:11:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>NFLisAwesome</username>
        <id>17084027</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Fate of Western residents and Allied prisoners in the area */ Tweaks</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8868">{{refimprove|date=November 2010}}
[[File:Sea of Okhotsk map.png|thumb|Location of [[Kuril Islands]] in the [[Pacific Ocean|Western Pacific]].]]

The '''evacuation of [[Karafuto]] (Sakhalin) and the [[Kuriles]]''' refers to the events that took place during the [[Pacific War|Pacific theater of World War II]] as the Japanese population left these areas, to August 1945 in the northwest of the main islands of [[Japan]].

The evacuation started under the threat of [[Soviet invasion of Manchuria (1945)|Soviet invasion]]. As Japanese civilians evacuated [[Korea]] and [[Manchuria]], they cleared out of the Karafuto and Kurile Islands according to the terms of the [[Potsdam Declaration]] that the terms of the [[1943 Cairo Declaration|Cairo Declaration]] would be carried out, and Japanese sovereignty would be limited to the ''[[Japanese archipelago|Home Islands]]'' of Honshū, Hokkaidō, Kyushu, Shikoku and such minor islands as the Allies determined.

==Timeline==

===Karafuto===
{{refimprove-section|date=October 2015}}
{{Main|Invasion of South Sakhalin}}
The operation began with the crossing of the Horonai (Poronai) Japanese frontier river post and bombardment of the [[Handenzawa]] Japanese land frontier post in [[Shikuka]] district, as well as the advance to the north of [[Koton, Sakhalin Oblast|Koton]] (now [[Pobedino]]), a powerful fortified district (FD). Severe fighting with heavy losses on both sides continued for over a week, with Soviet troops breaking the Japanese defenses on August 18. The Soviets also landed their naval forces deep behind enemy frontlines to aid their ground forces.

According to some of the 6,000 refugees already evacuated from the area, Soviet forces carried out fierce naval bombardment and artillery strikes against civilians awaiting evacuation as well as Japanese installations in [[Maoka]], [[Shikuka]] on August 10.&lt;ref name=&quot;ealey-2006&quot;/&gt; Nearly 1,000 civilians were killed by machine-gun fire in this attack.&lt;ref name=&quot;ealey-2006&quot;/&gt; [[switchboard operator|Telephone operator]]s in the city decided not to evacuate, instead maintaining contact with the [[Wakkanai, Hokkaidō|Wakkanai]] and [[Mainland Japan]] until the moment that Soviet forces destroyed the telephone and postal installations in the city.&lt;ref name=&quot;ealey-2006&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://japanfocus.org/-mark-ealey/1988/article.html |title=An August Storm: the Soviet-Japan Endgame in the Pacific War |first=Mark |last=Ealey |date=February 26, 2006 |publisher=The Asia-Pacific Journal: Japan Focus |accessdate=November 14, 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

On August 20, after Japan's surrender, fearing that they would be raped by the invading Soviet troops, nine of the twelve female operators poisoned themselves. Three were saved by male colleagues' intervention. The survivors at the post office were treated well by the Soviets.&lt;ref&gt; Murakawa, Miyuki [http://www.japantimes.co.jp/news/2015/01/12/national/mourners-mark-wwii-sakhalin-post-office-suicides/ ''[[The Japan Times]]'' Jan 12, 2015 Mourners mark WWII Sakhalin post office suicides] Retrieved July 29, 2015 &lt;/ref&gt;

On August 16, the coastguard ''[[Uragan-class guard ship|Zarnitsa]]'', four minesweepers, two transports, six gunboats and nineteen torpedo boats landed in Port [[Toro (Japan)|Toro]] (now [[Shakhtersk]]) with the 365th Separate Marine Battalion and one battalion of the 113th Infantry Brigade. The troops instantly engaged the Japanese in fierce battle and by morning of the next day had captured four populated areas and the port city of [[Esutoru]] (now [[Uglegorsk, Sakhalin Oblast|Uglegorsk]]), [[Anbetsu]] (now Vozvrashcheniye) and [[Yerinai]]).

During the [[Soviet assault on Maoka]], on August 20, a combined marine battalion and the 113th Infantry Brigade landed in Port [[Maoka]] (now [[Kholmsk]]). They were preceded by a group of scouts, landed secretly by a submarine, in the Maoka area to successfully complete their task. However, Japanese resistance was desperate, and the landing party had to fight particularly fiercely. Japanese fire set one of the coastguard vessels on fire, to which the Soviet response was intense naval bombardment of the city, causing more civilian deaths.{{cn|date=October 2015}}

The rest of the Japanese Maoka defenders retreated by Tei (now [[Polyakovo]]) and [[Futomato]] (now Chaplanovo) in [[Ikenohata]] county, between the mountains in the direction of [[Toyohara]] in order to make a last stand in the capital of the province or in [[Kawakami Sumiyama]] county for sustained guerrilla resistance.

On August 25, another 1,600 men landed in [[Korsakov (town)|Otomari]] (now [[Korsakov (town)|Korsakov]]). The Japanese garrison of 3,400 men laid down their arms with almost no resistance and surrendered. Some vessels of the last convoy, including civilian evacuees, had been sunk by Soviet submarines in the [[Aniva Gulf]].

===Kuriles===
{{Main|Invasion of the Kuril Islands}}
The rout of Japanese forces in [[Manchuria]] and [[Sakhalin]] created favorable conditions for invasion of the [[Kurile Islands]]. The key Japanese position was on [[Shumushu]] and [[Paramushiro]] Islands. On August 18, two coast guard ships, the mine layer ''[[Okhotsk]]'', four minesweepers, 17 transports and 16 special landing vessels with nearly 9,000 sailors, soldiers, and officers on board, approached Shumushu and Paramushiro to start the landing operation. The Japanese offered fierce resistance. Bloody battles took place in Shumushu and Paramushiro with varying success till August 23 when the Japanese garrison surrendered.

By the end of August, all the northern Kuriles were under the control of Soviet forces, including [[Uruppu]] Island. The Northern Pacific Flotilla occupied the rest of the islands to the south of Uruppu. Up to 60,000 Japanese officers and men were taken prisoner in the Kuriles. The landing operation in the Kuriles was the last of World War II.

In the [[Kuriles]] a similar pattern was repeated when Japanese civilians desperately retired from [[Shumushu]] and [[Paramushiro]] before the Soviet invasion (the Russians only sank one war vessel transporting some Japanese troops), but did not occur at the time in some islands such as [[Uruppu]] and [[South Kuriles]]. In these cases, Russian troops arrived in aggressive form to expel local citizens and confiscate local property.

==Fate of Western residents and Allied prisoners in the area==
Similar treatment faced the [[Germany|German]], [[Ukraine|Ukrainian]] and [[Poland|Polish]] citizens who resided in these provinces, the [[White Movement|White Russians]] in the area (living from ancient [[Russia]]n administration under the [[Treaty of Shimoda|Shimoda agreement]]), were arrested, accused of high treason and collaboration with an enemy power. Some were sent to [[gulag]]s in Eastern Siberia, others were executed. Similar things happened to White Russians living in Manchukuo, Kwantung or North Chosen (Korea).

Some versions (including the work of American researchers) allege that Japanese forces during wartime sent certain [[Western world|Western]] [[POW]]s ([[United States|Americans]], [[United Kingdom|British]], [[Netherlands|Dutch]], and the like) to detention camps in [[Karafuto]] and the [[Kuriles]] from other areas in [[Southeast Asia]] as well as to detention centers in [[Hokkaidō]] ([[Otaru]] POW center) and North [[Honshū]], [[Manchukuo]] or Chōsen (the Japanese name for what later became [[North Korea]]).

The final fate of the supposed [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] [[POW]]s when [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] forces arrived in these areas previously under Japanese administration, if unknown, is very similar to [[United States|Americans]] captured or interned in [[Vladivostok]] (during the [[Doolittle Raid]] or [[B-29]] strikes against [[Manchukuo]] industry) or [[Kamchatka]] (when Americans carried out some air strikes against North [[Kuriles]] Islands). Some reports also exist mentioning the possibly of identifying Americans interned in East [[Siberia]]n gulags in the same period, and possibly into the [[Cold War]] period. Such a topic still awaits in-depth research by historians and experts of the area.&lt;ref&gt;[http://memory.loc.gov/frd/tfrussia/tfrhtml/tfrsplit/tfr010.html]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Japan|Russia}}
* [[Battle of the Kuril Islands]]
* [[Invasion of South Sakhalin]]
* [[Japanese repatriation from Huludao]]
* [[Soviet assault on Maoka]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*http://memory.loc.gov/frd/tfrussia/tfrhtml/tfrsplit/tfr010.html
*http://hnn.us/roundup/comments/22336.html

[[Category:Karafuto]]
[[Category:Kuril Islands]]
[[Category:Japan in World War II]]
[[Category:1945 in Japan]]
[[Category:Evacuations|Karafuto and Kuriles]]
[[Category:History of Sakhalin]]
[[Category:Soviet World War II crimes]]
[[Category:War crimes in Japan]]
[[Category:Japan–Soviet Union relations]]</text>
      <sha1>f2jbcayfvi6ekk6zsk0y0dfbj2picui</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
