<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Fedor von Bock</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>450813</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749805002</id>
      <parentid>749218395</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-16T06:46:27Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cloptonson</username>
        <id>16228717</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Decorations and awards */ corrected title of Hungarian decoration to reflect state was then Kingdom of Hungary, not republic</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="41296">{{refimprove|date=October 2016}}{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2011}}
{{Infobox military person
|name = Fedor von Bock
|birth_name=Moritz Albrecht Franz Friedrich Fedor von Bock
|birth_date = {{Birth date|1880|12|03|df=yes}}
|death_date = {{death date and age|1945|05|04|1880|12|03|df=yes}}
|birth_place = [[Kostrzyn nad Odrą|Küstrin]], [[German Empire]]
|death_place = [[Oldenburg (Holstein)|Oldenburg]], [[Nazi Germany]]
|image = Wehrvonbockcopy1.jpg
|caption = ''Generaloberst'' Fedor von Bock, 1939
|nickname =&lt;!--- &quot;Holy Fire of Küstrin&quot;&lt;br&gt;&quot;Der Sterber&quot;{{sfn|Turney|1971}}---&gt;
|allegiance = {{flag|German Empire}} {{small|(1898–1918)}}&lt;br/&gt;{{flag|Weimar Republic}} {{small|(1918–1933)}}&lt;br/&gt;{{flag|Nazi Germany}} {{small|(1933–1945)}}
|serviceyears = 1898–1945
|rank = [[Field Marshal (Germany)|Field Marschal]]
|commands = [[Army Group North]], 1939&lt;br/&gt;[[Army Group B]], 1940&lt;br/&gt;[[Army Group Center]], 1941&lt;br/&gt;[[Army Group South]], 1942
|battles = 
;[[World War I]]
&lt;!---*[[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]]---&gt;
;[[World War II]]
*[[Invasion of Poland]] 
*[[Battle of France]]
*[[Operation Barbarossa]]
*[[Operation Typhoon]]
*[[Operation Blue]] 
*[[Battle of Voronezh (1942)]]
*[[Battle of Sevastopol]]
*[[Operation Braunschweig]]
|awards = ''[[Pour le Mérite]]''&lt;br/&gt;[[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross]]
|relations = &lt;!---[[Erich von Falkenhayn]] {{smaller|(uncle)}}&lt;br/&gt;[[Eugen von Falkenhayn]] {{smaller|(uncle)}}---&gt;
|signature = &lt;!--FedorvonBock signature.svg---&gt;
}}

'''Moritz Albrecht Franz Friedrich Fedor von Bock''' (3 December 1880 – 4 May 1945) was a [[Nazi Germany|German]] [[field marshal (Germany)|field marshal]] who served in the [[German Army (Wehrmacht)|German army]] during the [[Second World War]]. Bock served as the commander of [[Army Group North]] during the [[Invasion of Poland]] in 1939, commander of [[Army Group B]] during the [[Invasion of France (Nazi Germany)|Invasion of France]] in 1940, and later as the commander of [[Army Group Center]] during the attack on the [[Soviet Union]] in 1941; his final command was that of [[Army Group South]] in 1942.

Bock is best known for commanding [[Operation Typhoon]], the ultimately failed attempt to capture [[Moscow]] during the winter of 1941. The ''Wehrmacht'' offensive was slowed by stiff Soviet resistance around [[Mozhaisk]], and also by the ''[[Rasputitsa]]'', the season of rain and mud in Russia. Once the winter set in, the German armies quickly became unable to fight, with more casualties occurring due to the cold weather than battle.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt; The Soviet counteroffensive soon drove the German army into retreat, and Bock—who recommended an earlier withdrawal—was subsequently relieved of command by [[Adolf Hitler]].

A [[monarchist]], Bock personally despised [[Nazism]], and was not heavily involved in [[politics of Germany|politics]]. However, he also did not sympathize with plots to overthrow [[Adolf Hitler]], and never filed official protests over the treatment of civilians by the ''[[Schutzstaffel]]'' (SS). Bock was also uncommonly outspoken, a privilege Hitler extended to him only because he had been successful in battle.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;&gt;Battle of Russia, ''Battlefield: Battles that Won the Second World War—Series 2''. Universal Pictures Video. 2 May 2005&lt;/ref&gt; Bock—along with his second wife and his stepdaughter—were killed by a strafing British fighter-bomber on 4 May 1945 as they traveled by car toward [[Hamburg]].

==Early life==
Fedor von Bock was born in [[Küstrin]] (today Kostrzyn in [[Poland]]), a fortress city on the banks of the [[Oder River]] in the [[Province of Brandenburg]].{{sfn|Turney|1971|p=3}} He was born into a [[Prussia]]n [[Protestant]] [[Aristocracy (class)|aristocratic]] family which had given the [[Hohenzollerns]] military service for generations. His father—Karl Moritz von Bock—had served in the [[Franco-Prussian War]] of 1870-1871. His mother, Olga von Falkenhayn, was the sister of German generals [[Eugen von Falkenhayn|Eugen]] and [[Erich von Falkenhayn]], the latter who was the German chief of staff (1914-1916) during part of the First World War.

At the age of eight, Bock went to study at a military academy in Berlin. The education emphasized Prussian [[militarism]], and he quickly became adept in academic subjects such as [[modern languages]], [[mathematics]], and [[history]]. He spoke fluent French, and some English and Russian.{{sfn|Turney|1971|p=4}} At an early age, and largely due to his father, Bock developed an unquestioning loyalty to the state and dedication to the military profession. This upbringing would greatly influence his actions and decisions when he commanded armed forces during the [[World War II|Second World War]].{{sfn|Turney|1971|p=5}} At the age of 17, Bock became an officer cadet in the Imperial Foot Guards Regiment at Potsdam; he received an officer's commission a year later. He entered service with the rank of ''Sekondeleutnant''.

While not a brilliant theoretician, Bock was a highly determined officer. As one of the highest-ranking officers in the ''[[Reichswehr]]'', he often addressed graduating cadets at his [[alma mater]], which closed in 1920. His theme was always that the greatest glory that could come to a German soldier was to die for the [[Fatherland]].{{sfn|Turney|1971|p=6}} He quickly earned the nickname &quot;Holy Fire of Küstrin&quot;.{{sfn|Turney|1971|p=6}}

In 1905, Bock married Mally von Reichenbach, a young Prussian noblewoman, whom he had originally met in Berlin.{{sfn|Turney|1971|p=6}} They were married in a traditional military wedding at the Potsdam garrison. They had a daughter, born two years after the marriage. A year later, Bock attended the War Academy in Berlin, and after a year's study he joined the ranks of the General Staff. He soon joined the patriotic Army League (''Deutscher Wehrverein'') and become a close associate of other young German officers such as [[Walther von Brauchitsch]], [[Franz Halder]], and [[Gerd von Rundstedt]]. In 1908 he won promotion to the rank of ''[[Oberleutnant]]''.

==World War I==
By the time [[World War I]] began in 1914, Bock was a captain (''Hauptmann''). He served with the 4th Foot Guards Regiment as a battalion commander in January and February 1916, and was decorated with the coveted ''[[Pour le Mérite]]'' for bravery. Promoted to major, Bock was assigned as a divisional staff officer in Rupprecht's army group on the Western Front and became a friend of the Crown Prince of Germany. Two days before the Armistice of November 1918, he met the German Emperor [[William II, German Emperor|Wilhelm II]] at [[Spa, Belgium]], in an unsuccessful attempt to persuade him to return to Berlin to crush the [[German Revolution of 1918–1919|mutiny at Kiel]].

==Weimar Republic==
After the Treaty of Versailles was signed, limiting the German Army to 100,000 troops, Bock stayed on as an officer of the post-treaty ''Reichswehr'', and rose through the ranks. In the 1920s, Bock was together with [[Kurt von Schleicher]], [[Eugen Ott (ambassador)|Eugen Ott]], and [[Kurt von Hammerstein-Equord]] a member of a secret group known as ''Sondergruppe R'' selected by and responsible to [[Hans von Seeckt]] that was in charge of helping Germany evade the Part V of the [[Treaty of Versailles]], which had disarmed Germany.{{sfn|Wheeler-Bennett|1967|pp=93–92}} The officers of ''Sondergruppe R'' formed the liaison with Major Bruno Ernst Buchrucker, who led the so-called ''Arbeits-Kommandos'' (Work Commandos), which was officially a labor group intended to assist with civilian projects, but were in reality thinly disguised soldiers that allowed Germany to exceed the limits on troop strength set by Versailles.{{sfn|Wheeler-Bennett|1967|p=92}} Buchrucker's so-called [[Black Reichswehr|&quot;Black ''Reichswehr''&quot;]] became infamous for its practice of murdering all those Germans who were suspected of working as informers for the Allied Control Commission, which was responsible for ensuring that Germany was in compliance with Part V.{{sfn|Wheeler-Bennett|1967|p=93}} The killings perpetrated by the &quot;Black ''Reichswehr''&quot; were justifed under the so-called [[Vehmic court|''Femegerichte'']] (secret court) system.{{sfn|Wheeler-Bennett|1967|p=93}} These killings were ordered by the officers from ''Sondergruppe R''.{{sfn|Wheeler-Bennett|1967|p=93}} Regarding the ''Femegerichte'' murders, [[Carl von Ossietzky]] wrote: &quot;Lieutenant Schulz (charged with the murder of informers against the &quot;Black ''Reichswehr''&quot;) did nothing but carry out the orders given him, and that certainly Colonel von Bock, and probably Colonel von Schleicher and General Seeckt, should be sitting in the dock beside him&quot;.{{sfn|Wheeler-Bennett|1967|pp=93–94}}

Several times Bock perjured himself in court when he denied that the ''Reichswehr'' had had anything to do with the &quot;Black ''Reichswehr''&quot; or the murders they had committed.{{sfn|Wheeler-Bennett|1967|pp=93–94}} On 27 September 1923, Buchrucker ordered 4,500 men of the Black ''Reichswehr'' to assemble outside of Berlin as the first preparatory step toward a ''putsch''.{{sfn|Wheeler-Bennett|1967|p=111}} Bock, who was Buchrucker's contact with the ''Reichswehr'', was enraged, and in a stormy meeting berated Buchrucker for mobilizing the Black ''Reichswehr'' without orders.{{sfn|Wheeler-Bennett|1967|pp=111–112}} Bock stated the ''Reichswehr'' wanted no part in Buchrucker's ''putsch'' and that &quot;If Seeckt knew you were here, he would screw his monocle into his eye and say &quot;Go for him!&quot;&quot;{{sfn|Wheeler-Bennett|1967|p=112}} Despite Bock's orders to demobilize at once, Buchrucker went ahead with his ''putsch'' on 30 September 1923, which ended in total failure.{{sfn|Wheeler-Bennett|1967|p=112}}

In 1935, [[Adolf Hitler]] appointed Bock as commander of the Third Army Group.&lt;ref name =&quot;Current&quot;&gt;''Current Biography 1942'', pp. 89–91&lt;/ref&gt; Bock was one of the [[Military officer|officer]]s not removed from his position when Hitler reorganized the armed forces during the phase of German rearmament before the outbreak of the Second World War. He remained a monarchist, and was a frequent visitor to the former ''Kaiser'''s estate. Hitler reportedly said of him, &quot;Nobody in the world but Bock can teach soldiers to die.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Current&quot;/&gt; Bock himself told his troops, &quot;The ideal soldier fulfills his duty to the utmost, obeys without even thinking, thinks only when ordered to do so, and has as his only desire to die the honorable death of a soldier killed in action.&quot;&lt;ref name= &quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;&quot;Death on the Approaches&quot;, ''TIME'' Magazine, 8 December 1941&lt;/ref&gt; Bock commanded the invasion of Vienna in March 1938 for the [[Anschluss]] and then the [[Invasion of Czechoslovakia]], before leading German armies into action in the Second World War.

==World War II==

===Invasion of Poland===
By 25 August 1939, Bock was in command of [[Army Group North]] in preparation for the invasion and conquest of [[Poland]]. The objective of Army Group North was to destroy the Polish forces north of the [[Vistula]]. Army Group North was composed of ''General'' [[Georg von Küchler]]'s [[3rd Army (Wehrmacht)|3rd Army]], and ''General'' [[Günther von Kluge]]'s [[4th Army (Wehrmacht)|4th Army]]. These struck southward from East Prussia and eastward across the base of the [[Polish Corridor]], respectively.

On 10 September Bock ordered the forces under his command to burn Polish villages located behind the front line to the ground if they were fired upon from the settlement and &quot;if it proves impossible to identify the house from which the shots came&quot;. By the end of the military occupation of the country on 26 October 1939 531 towns and villages had been destroyed across Poland.{{sfn|Evans|2008|p=20}}

In five weeks, Poland was overrun by German and Soviet forces and Bock had linked Germany back to [[East Prussia]]. Following the success in Poland, Bock returned to Berlin to begin preparations for the upcoming campaign in the West.
[[File:Vonbock paris.jpg|right|thumb|250px|Fedor von Bock in [[Paris]], 1940.]]

===Invasion of France===
Shortly after the conquest of Poland, on 12 October 1939 Bock was given command of [[Army Group B]], with 29½ divisions, including three armoured divisions. These were tasked with advancing through the [[Low Countries]] and luring the northern units of the [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] armies into a pocket. Army Group B consisted of the [[18th Army (Wehrmacht)|18th]] and [[6th Army (Wehrmacht)|6th Armies]]. While his units were overrunning the Netherlands, in May 1940, Bock attempted to call on the exiled former ''Kaiser''—[[Wilhelm II]]—at Doorn, but Bock was unable to gain admittance: the German troops guarding the residence having been instructed to prevent such visits.{{sfn|Evans|2008|p=494}}

Bock participated in the [[Armistice with France (Second Compiègne)|Armistice with France]] in late June 1940.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Hitler/Jaeger File|publisher=Life Magazine|accessdate=2009-04-14| url=https://images.google.com/hosted/life/l?imgurl=445b83d2ad615cfb}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 19 July 1940, Bock was promoted to the rank of ''Generalfeldmarschall'' during the [[1940 Field Marshal Ceremony]].{{sfn|Wheeler-Bennett|1967|p=497}} For much of the summer of 1940, Bock alternated his time between his headquarters in Paris and his home in Berlin. At the end of August, Army High Command transferred Army Group B to East Prussia; this included Kluge's 4th Army. On 11 September, Bock relinquished command of his occupation area in France to ''Generalfeldmarshall'' [[Wilhelm Ritter von Leeb]].

===Invasion of Soviet Union===
[[File:Eastern Front 1941-06 to 1941-12.png|thumb|right|280px|[[Operation Barbarossa]]: the German invasion of the [[Soviet Union]], 21 June – 5 December 1941:
{{legend|#fff8d5|to 9 July 1941}}
{{legend|#ffd2b9|to 1 September 1941}}
{{legend|#ebd7ff|to 9 September 1941}}
{{legend|#ccffcd|to 5 December 1941}}]]

On 2 February, Bock met with Hitler and questioned whether the Russians could be forced to make peace even if the Red Army was brought to battle and defeated. Hitler airily assured Bock that Germany's resources were more than sufficient and that he was determined to fight.&lt;ref&gt;Pincus, Oscar. ''The War Aims and Strategies of Adolf Hitler'' pg. 173&lt;/ref&gt; In preparation for [[Operation Barbarossa]], on 1 April 1941 Army Group B was re-designated as [[Army Group Center]] in an official order from Army High Command which defined the organization of the invasion force.{{sfn|Turney|1971|p=37}} Deployed in Poland, Army Group Center was one of the three army formations which were to lead the invasion of the [[Soviet Union]]. It included the 4th and [[9th Army (Wehrmacht)|9th Armies]], the [[3rd Panzer Army|3rd]] and [[2nd Panzer Army|2nd Panzer Armies]] and [[Luftflotte 2|''Luftflotte'' 2]]. On the left flank of Bock's Army Group Center was [[Army Group North]], commanded by [[Wilhelm Ritter von Leeb]]; on the right flank was [[Army Group South]], commanded by [[Gerd von Rundstedt]].

Initially, the main objective of Army Group Center was to follow [[Napoleon I of France|Napoleon]]'s route north of the [[Pripyat Marshes]] straight to [[Moscow]]. However, against the strong vocal opposition of Bock, Hitler altered the plan, one of many changes he would make, both before the invasion and after it had already begun. Bock opposed any changes to the plan of attack on Moscow. He wanted to occupy Moscow as soon as he could, hopefully before the onset of winter.

The new task of Army Group Center was to drive towards the cities of [[Minsk]] and [[Smolensk]], and in great encirclements destroy the Soviet armies stationed there. Army Group Center would then drive toward [[Leningrad]], and along with Army Group North destroy the remnants of the Soviet armies in the [[Baltic states]] and seize valuable ports for the supply of the campaign. Only after the bulk of the Soviet army was destroyed in western Russia would Army Group Center then drive toward the Soviet capital. Hitler made this change conscious of the fact that despite capturing Moscow, Napoleon was defeated because he did not destroy the Russian army.&lt;ref name= &quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt;

At 03:15 on 22 June 1941, the first shots of Operation Barbarossa were fired; Germany invaded the Soviet Union without formally declaring the war. At the outset of the campaign Bock remained at his desk in his headquarters waiting for the first reports from the front. Within an hour of the attack, the first reports began to arrive at Army Group Center headquarters. Elements of [[Heinz Guderian]]'s force had crossed the [[Bug River]] and were bypassing the city of [[Brest-Litovsk]]. [[Hermann Hoth]]'s tanks were heading for [[Grodno]] on the [[Nieman River]] to seize the important river crossings. Several reconnaissance units from the 4th and 9th Armies had already crossed the Bug and [[Desna River|Desna]] Rivers.

At 07:00, Bock flew from [[Poznań|Posen]] to an [[advance airfield]] near the headquarters of XIII Infantry Corps. There, Lieutenant General [[Erich Jaschke]] gave Bock a summary of the progress of the invasion. Following this meeting, Bock visited Guderian's forward command post at Bokhaly. Guderian's Chief of staff (Colonel [[Kurt Freiherr von Liebenstein]]) greeted Bock, as Guderian had already crossed the Bug River several hours earlier with the [[18th Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|18th Panzer Division]]. Bock then visited [[Joachim Lemelsen]], who gave an agitated report from the front. The roads on the Soviet side of the Bug River were already becoming too soft to support the weight of tanks. As a result, several tank columns had to be rerouted to cross a bridge farther south at [[Koden]]. This rerouting caused severe traffic congestion, as some ten thousand vehicles converged on this single crossing. Despite this, the first day of the invasion had been spectacularly successful. Soviet resistance was reported as being light and complete surprise was achieved. All along the front rapid progress was being made.
[[File:Von bock hoth.jpg|left|thumb|upright|[[Hermann Hoth]] with Bock (left) in Russia during [[Operation Barbarossa]], 1941.]]

On the second day of ''Barbarossa'', Bock crossed the Bug River. Escorted by Major General [[Gustav Schmidt (general)|Gustav Schmidt]], he made his way to a company command post from where he observed German artillery firing on Soviet positions near Brest-Litovsk. Despite the fact that German tanks had already crossed deep into Soviet territory, the defenders of the city were holding out stubbornly. Later that day Bock was presented with reports that Soviet resistance was stiffening all long the front, especially on Guderian's southern flank. Meanwhile, Hoth's forces were advancing with much more ease through the Baltic states and [[Belarus]]. The first two days of Army Group Center's advance proved to be highly successful.

Hoth's army advanced so quickly that Bock immediately contacted [[Walter von Brauchitsch]], requesting the bypassing of Minsk in favor of attacking toward [[Vitebsk]] so that a drive could be made for Moscow. Initially, the change in plan was accepted but it was soon overruled by Hitler, who favored the encirclement and destruction of the large Soviet armies near Minsk. Bock wrote in his diary:

{{quote|The envelopment of Minsk is not decisive. Besides, I am sure that the enemy expects us to attack Minsk, the next natural objective, and will concentrate defense forces there.{{sfn|Turney|1971|pp=54–60}}}}

Differences between Bock's strategic intent and the intent of High Command repeatedly surfaced. Bock continued to favor a direct drive toward Moscow, bypassing Soviet armies and leaving them to be destroyed by infantry, which advanced well behind tank columns. Bock argued that if encirclement was truly necessary then instead of diverting his tanks north and south to encircle and destroy smaller Soviet armies, a larger encirclement should be made eastward toward the [[Daugava River|Dvina]]-[[Dnieper]] River basins.{{sfn|Turney|1971|pp=54–60}} Hitler decided against this plan, and insisted that the pockets containing Soviet armies must be destroyed before advancing deeper into Russia.

Bock, enraged by this decision, was quoted as saying:

{{quote|We are permitting our greatest chance of success to escape us by this restriction placed on our armor!{{sfn|Turney|1971|pp=54–60}}}}

He hesitantly gave the order to abandon the drive toward Vitebsk and assist in the destruction of the pockets. On 25 June, Bock moved his headquarters from Posen to [[Kobryn]], a town about {{convert|15|mi|km|abbr=on}} northeast of Brest-Litovsk. On 30 June, the 4th and 9th Armies met each other near [[Slonim]], trapping thousands of Soviet soldiers. However, many Soviet soldiers managed to escape eastward. Bock soon gave the order to disengage from the encirclement and prepare for a full-scale drive to the east. This order once again caused a confrontation between Bock and Brauchitsch.

On 3 July, Bock's forces were once again advancing eastward, with Guderian’s tanks crossing the [[Beresina]] and Hoth's tanks crossing the Duna. This day marked the furthest distance covered by Bock's troops in a single day, with over {{convert|100|mi|km|abbr=on}} traveled.{{sfn|Turney|1971|pp=54–60}} Four days later, Guderian's tanks crossed the Dnieper, the last great obstacle before Smolensk. However, Guderian was soon ordered by [[Günther von Kluge]] to withdraw back across the river. Bock soon reversed this order, and Guderian was allowed to re-cross the river. Bock protested Kluge's actions to High Command, to no avail.{{sfn|Turney|1971|pp=54–60}} On 11 July, Bock moved his headquarters again to [[Barysaw|Borisov]], a Soviet town near the Beresina River.

===Operation Typhoon===
On 9 September, Army High Command instructed Bock to prepare an operational order for the assault on Moscow. [[Operation Typhoon]] was the code-name given to this new attack, which was to begin no later than 30 September. Bock carefully supervised the planning and preparation of the operation, and a few days later it was approved by the High Command.

As part of the preparation for Operation Typhoon, Army Group Center would be reinforced and replenished with men and vehicles; it would be composed of three infantry armies (the [[2nd Army (Wehrmacht)|2nd]], 4th, and 9th) and three tank armies ([[2nd Panzer Army|2nd]], 3rd, and 4th ''Panzer''s). [[Colonel General]] [[Erich Hoepner]] would command the 4th ''Panzer'' Army, while the former two were outgrowths of Hoth's and Guderian's original ''Panzer'' Groups. The replenishment of Army Group Center for Operation Typhoon caused it to increase greatly in size: with almost 1.5&amp;nbsp;million soldiers, it was now larger than it was at the outset of [[Operation Barbarossa]]. Bock spent most of the remainder of September on inspection tours of his reinforced Army Group Center. On one occasion, Bock—along with [[Albert Kesselring]]—flew over Moscow.{{sfn|Turney|1971|p=87}}

On 29 September, Bock held a conference with his senior commanders [[Adolf Strauß|Strauss]], [[Hermann Hoth|Hoth]], Kluge, [[Maximilian von Weichs|Weichs]], [[Erich Hoepner|Hoepner]], Guderian, and Kesselring. During the meeting the main operational plan was reviewed, with Bock again stressing that Moscow must be taken by 7 November, before the onset of the [[General Winter|Russian winter]], and to coincide with the anniversary of the [[October Revolution|Russian Revolution]].{{sfn|Beevor|1998|p=34}} The following day, Operation Typhoon began with attacks from Guderian’s and Hoth’s armored forces. Several days later, the infantry armies began to move toward Moscow. With less than 150&amp;nbsp;km between the most advanced troops and Moscow, Bock estimated that his troops would enter the city in three to four weeks.{{sfn|Turney|1971|p=88}}

Almost immediately, Bock's forces encountered stiff Soviet resistance on the road to Moscow. The previous diversions of Army Group Center allowed the Soviets to reinforce the area between Smolensk and Moscow with the Russian 3rd, 10th, 13th, and 20th Armies, as well as elements of three other armies. However, the tactics and training of the ''Wehrmacht''—along with an element of surprise—resulted in significant gains despite the increasingly desperate measures employed by the Russians to stop the advance.

The 2nd ''Panzer'' Army—along with the XLVIII ''Panzer'' Corps—attacked important rail junctions near [[Oryol]] (Orel) and [[Bryansk]]. Hoepner's 4th ''Panzer'' Army soon crossed the [[Desna River]] and gained access to deep Russian territory. Meanwhile, Hoth's 3rd ''Panzer'' Army struck toward [[Rzhev]] on the [[Volga River]].

On 3 October, Guderian's forces captured Orel and subsequently gained access to a paved highway which led to Moscow, some {{convert|180|mi|km|abbr=on}} away. Meanwhile, elements of the 2nd ''Panzer'' Army reported that they had bypassed Bryansk and were heading toward [[Karachev]]. Bock ordered Guderian to press on toward [[Tula, Russia|Tula]], but within hours this order had been reversed by High Command. The reversal of the order called for Guderian to attack Bryansk where—along with [[Vyazma]]—two massive encirclements of Soviet forces were occurring. Bock argued that the area between Orel and Tula remained relatively free of Soviet forces and that Tula could be captured within hours. Ultimately, Bock agreed to divert Guderian's tanks toward Bryansk.

Cold rain soon began to fall over the northern sectors of Army Group Center's front, and the roads soon turned into [[Bog|quagmires]] as part of the [[Rasputitsa]]. Virtually the entire front became stuck; the only vehicles capable of negotiating the mud were tanks and other tracked vehicles. However, these moved at a snail's pace (sometimes less than {{convert|2|mi|km|abbr=on}} per day&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt;), and fuel consumption soared. This further aggravated the problem of already poor supply lines.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt; Trucks soon became stuck in the mud, as soldiers tried desperately to free them. As the temperature continued to drop, Guderian requested a supply of winter clothing and anti-freeze for the vehicles. However, the increase in partisan activity behind the lines, along with the deteriorating weather conditions, made it increasingly difficult for these vital supplies to reach the front. In one two-day period, partisans made over sixty attacks on German truck convoys, outposts, and railway lines.
&lt;!--- [[File:German soldiers moscow.jpg|thumb|225px|left|Soldiers of [[Army Group Center]] try to keep warm during the assault on [[Moscow]].]]--&gt;

Slight improvements in the weather soon made it possible for Bock's forces to continue to seal the pockets around Bryansk and Vyazma. The dual encirclements of Soviet forces around Vyazma and Bryansk yielded some of the largest Soviet casualties since the beginning of Operation Barbarossa: some 650,000 prisoners were taken during these two encirclements, after which the Soviet armies facing Bock's Army Group Center no longer had the advantage of superior numbers.&lt;ref name= &quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt; Bock was one of the few German officers to protest the systematic [[Nazi crimes against Soviet POWs|maltreatment of Soviet prisoners of war]], but took few steps to improve the conditions of those being held in the areas under his command.{{sfn|Evans|2008|p=185}}

The weather soon deteriorated again, with the roads once more turning into impassable, muddy quagmires. Since 30 September, Bock had lost some 35,000 men, 250 tanks and artillery pieces, and several hundred other vehicles, many of which were mired in the mud. Fuel and ammunition supplies became dangerously low. Despite these problems, the advance toward Moscow continued as Hitler became increasingly impatient. When advance units of the 4th ''Panzer'' Army reached [[Kaluga]] and [[Maloyaroslavets]], German forces were within {{convert|40|mi|km|abbr=on}} of Moscow. Guderian's advance in the south was much slower. An attempt by his forces to capture Tula had failed, with considerable losses of men and tanks. However, other units captured [[Stalinogorsk]] and [[Venev]], indicating the possibility of bypassing Tula.

As Bock's forces pressed on toward Moscow, panic struck in the capital. Hundreds of thousands of civilians began to evacuate the city while others were forced into emergency volunteer units. [[Martial law]] was instituted as looting and pillaging of deserted stores increased. Marshal [[Semyon Timoshenko]] was relieved of command in favor of [[Georgy Zhukov]], who had been organizing the defense of [[Leningrad]]. The main bulk of the Soviet government was evacuated to [[Samara, Russia|Kuibyshev]], {{convert|500|mi|km|abbr=on}} southeast of Moscow; however, Stalin remained in the capital after being reassured by Zhukov that the capital would not fall.&lt;ref&gt;''Blood and Steel: The Russian Front''. Cromwell Productions Ltd. 3 January 1999&lt;/ref&gt;

The further Bock's forces advanced, the stiffer Soviet resistance became. The paved roads leading to Moscow became craters under constant Russian artillery fire, rendering them impassable. This forced the German troops into the mud and Army Group Center soon became stuck once again. The goal of capturing Moscow by mid-October could no longer be achieved. However, the sheer weight of the German advance could not be fully stopped, and on 21 October units of the 9th Army captured [[Tver|Kalinin]].

As November arrived the mud soon turned into ice as temperatures dropped to -28°C (-20°F). While the ground hardened sufficiently enough to support vehicles, the cold weather added to the miseries of the German soldiers as many had not received winter clothing. Frostbite soon took its toll; many soldiers were severely affected and had to be evacuated.

On 20 November, Bock moved his field headquarters to an advanced forward position near the front lines. There he visited an artillery command post, where he could see the buildings of Moscow through his field glasses.{{sfn|Turney|1971|p=141}} Several days later, German forces crossed the [[Moscow-Volga Canal]] and reached [[Khimki]] but soon fell back due to Soviet resistance. On 29 November, elements of the 4th ''Panzer'' Army reached the western suburbs of Moscow. On 4 December, units of the 2nd Army reached [[Kuntsevo]], a western suburb of Moscow. Several units of Guderian's army bypassed [[Kolomna]] and reached the [[Moscow River]]. Meanwhile, the 3rd ''Panzer'' Army once again fought into Khimki. These were the last advances made by Army Group Center under Bock's command.{{sfn|Turney|1971|p=142}}

On 6 December, with the temperature at -45°C (-50°F), fresh Russian troops commanded by Zhukov launched a huge counterattack. All along the front near Moscow German troops retreated, destroying whatever equipment they could not salvage. Several days later, High Command ordered a halt to all offensive operations. Bock wrote in his diary:

{{quote|All along, I demanded of Army High Command the authority to strike down the enemy when he was wobbling. We could have finished the enemy last summer. We could have destroyed him completely. Last August, the road to Moscow was open; we could have entered the Bolshevik capital in triumph and in summery weather. The high military leadership of the Fatherland made a terrible mistake when it forced my army group to adopt a position of defense last August. Now all of us are paying for that mistake.{{sfn|Turney|1971|p=155}}}}

By 13 December, German forces had retreated more than {{convert|80|km|mi|abbr=on}} from the capital. On 18 December, Bock was relieved of his command of Army Group Center. The official pretext of this decision was health problems.{{sfn|Turney|1971|p=160}} However, this was just one case out of some 40 high-ranking officers being relieved of their command following the failure to capture Moscow.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt; Bock's command of Army Group Center marked the closest the German army ever got to Moscow; never again would the Soviet capital be threatened.

===Operation Blue===
Bock was unable to take Moscow in December 1941, and during the ensuing Soviet counteroffensive, he was dismissed from his post as Commander of [[Army Group Center]] when he reported sick. He was reassigned to lead [[Army Group South]] on 20 January 1942, after the death of ''Generalfeldmarshall'' [[Walter von Reichenau]] from a stroke.&lt;ref name=Adam&gt;{{Cite book |last=Adam |first=Wilhelm |first2=Otto |last2=Ruhle |translator=Tony Le Tissier |title=With Paulus at Stalingrad |publisher=Pen and Sword Books Ltd. |year=2015 |ISBN=9781473833869 |pages=2–3, 24–25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===1942 Summer Offensive, Eastern Front===
On 28 June 1942, Bock's offensive split the Russian front into fragments on either side of Kursk. Three armies (Weich's 2nd Army, Hoth's 4th Panzer, and Paulus' 6th Army)—along with 11 ''Panzer'' Divisions—fanned out toward Voronezh and the Don River. Paulus' ''Panzer'' Divisions reached the Don on either side of Voronezh on 5 July. The Russians created a &quot;Voronezh Front&quot; under [[Nikolai Vatutin|Vatutin]], who reported directly to Moscow. Bock wanted to eliminate Vatutin's forces before extending his own flank too deeply into the yawning void created by the strength and speed of the German offensive. Hitler was not pleased with Bock's plan to delay the push toward Stalingrad. On 7 July, Hitler split Army Group 'South' into Army Groups 'A' and 'B'.  Army Group 'A' was given to Field Marshal [[Wilhelm List]] to command.&lt;ref name=Adam/&gt;  On 13 July, Hitler relieved Bock as commander of Army Group B, replacing him with [[Maximilian von Weichs]]. Bock never again occupied a senior command position.{{sfn|Glantz|House|2009|p=192}}

===Death===
With the Soviets closing in on Berlin in 1945, Bock was informed by [[Erich von Manstein]] that [[Grand Admiral]] [[Karl Dönitz]] was forming a new government in [[Hamburg]]. Bock started off for that city immediately. On 4 May 1945, Bock's car was strafed on the road to [[Kiel]] by a British [[fighter plane]] and he was killed.{{citation needed|date=March 2016}}

==Decorations and awards==
&lt;!---* [[Order of the Crown (Prussia)|Order of the Crown]], 4th class (Prussia, 13 September 1911)
* [[Iron Cross]] of 1914
**2nd class – 18 September 1914
**1st class – 30 October 1916
* Knight's Cross of the Royal [[House Order of Hohenzollern]] with Swords (25 October 1916)
* [[Military Merit Cross (Austria-Hungary)|Military Merit Cross]], 3rd class with war decoration (Austria-Hungary, 24 June 1915)
* [[Order of the Iron Crown (Austria)|Order of the Iron Crown]], 3rd class with war decoration (Austria, 9 February 1917)
* [[Military Merit Cross (Mecklenburg-Schwerin)|Military Merit Cross]], 2nd class (Mecklenburg-Schwerin, 3 August 1917)
* [[Hanseatic Cross]]es of Hamburg (19 September 1917) and Bremen (30 January 1918)
* [[Order of the Zähringer Lion]], Knight 1st class with Swords (10 January 1918)
* [[Order of the Crown (Württemberg)|Order of the Crown]], Knight's Cross with Swords (Württemberg 25 January 1918)
* [[Pour le Mérite]] (1 April 1918)
* [[Order of Military Merit (Bulgaria)|Order of Military Merit]], Commander's Cross (Bulgaria, 2 August 1918)
* [[Service Award]] (1920)
* [[Silesian Eagle]], 1st and 2nd class (15 April 1921)
* [[Wehrmacht Long Service Award]], 1st class with 4th class; Oak Leaves added on 12 September 1939
* [[Anschluss Medal]]
* [[Sudetenland Medal]]
* [[Order of the Yugoslav Crown]], 1st class (June 1939)
* [[Clasp to the Iron Cross]], 1st and 2nd class (22 September 1939)---&gt;
* [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross]] on 30 September 1939 as ''[[Generaloberst]]'' and Commander-in-Chief of Heeresgruppe Nord{{sfn|Scherzer|2007|p=227}}
* Grand Cross of the [[Order of the Crown of Italy]] (27 August 1940)
* [[Order of Michael the Brave]] (Romania)
**3rd class – 29 July 1942
**1st class – September 1942
* Grand Cross of the [[Order of Merit of the Kingdom of Hungary]] with Swords (27 November 1942)
* Mentioned in the ''[[Wehrmachtbericht]]'' (7 August 1941, 19 September 1941, 18 October 1941, 30 May 1942)

==See also==
*[[Operation Barbarossa]]
*''[[Fall Blau]]''
*''[[Anschluss]]''
*[[Corruption within the Wehrmacht]]

==References==
{{Research help|Mil}}

{{Reflist|25em}}

==Sources==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book
  |last=Beevor
  |first=Antony
  |authorlink=Antony Beevor
  |title=[[Stalingrad (book)|Stalingrad, the Fateful Siege]]: 1942–1943
  |publisher=Penguin Putnam Inc
  |year=1998
  |location=Harmondsworth, United Kingdom
  |isbn=978-0-670-87095-0
  |ref=harv
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Evans
  |first=Richard J.
  |title=The Third Reich at War: 1939–1945
  |year=2008
  |publisher=Allen Lane
  |location=London
  |isbn=978-0-7139-9742-2
  |ref=harv
}}
* Gerbet, Klaus and Johnston, David. ''Generalfeldmarschall Fedor von Bock: The War Diary 1939–1945''. Schiffer Publishing. 1 January 2000
* {{Cite book
  |last1=Glantz
  |first1=David M.
  |last2=House
  |first2=Jonathan
  |date=2009
  |title=To the Gates of Stalingrad: Soviet-German Combat Operations, April-August 1942
  |publisher=University Press of Kansas
  |location=Lawrence, Kansas
  |isbn=978-0-7006-1630-5
  |ref=harv
}}
* Horner, D. M., Jukes, Geoffrey. ''The Second World War: The Eastern Front 1941–1945''. Osprey Publishing (25 July 2002)
* {{Cite book
  |last=Scherzer
  |first=Veit
  |year=2007
  |title=Die Ritterkreuzträger 1939–1945 Die Inhaber des Ritterkreuzes des Eisernen Kreuzes 1939 von Heer, Luftwaffe, Kriegsmarine, Waffen-SS, Volkssturm sowie mit Deutschland verbündeter Streitkräfte nach den Unterlagen des Bundesarchives
  |trans_title=The Knight's Cross Bearers 1939–1945 The Holders of the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross 1939 by Army, Air Force, Navy, Waffen-SS, Volkssturm and Allied Forces with Germany According to the Documents of the Federal Archives
  |language=German
  |location=Jena, Germany
  |publisher=Scherzers Miltaer-Verlag
  |isbn=978-3-938845-17-2
  |ref=harv
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Turney
  |first=Alfred W.
  |title=Disaster at Moscow: von Bock's Campaigns 1941–42
  |publisher=Cassell &amp; Co
  |year=1971
  |isbn=0-826-3-01-673
  |ref=harv
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Wheeler-Bennett
  |first=John
  |authorlink=John Wheeler-Bennett
  |year=1967
  |title=The Nemesis of Power The German Army in Politics 1918-1945
  |publisher=Macmillan
  |location=London
  |ISBN=978-1-4039-1812-3
  |ref=harv
}}
{{refend}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-mil}}
{{succession box
|before=none
|after=''Generalfeldmarschall'' [[Wilhelm Ritter von Leeb]]
|title=Commander of [[Army Group North|''Heeresgruppe Nord'']]
|years=27 August 1939 – 20 June 1941
}}
{{succession box
|before=none
|after=''Generalfeldmarschall'' [[Günther von Kluge]]
|title=Commander of [[Army Group Centre|''Heeresgruppe Mitte'']]
|years=22 June – 19 December 1941
}}
{{s-ach}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Claude Auchinleck|Sir Claude Auchinleck]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Time (magazine)|Cover of Time Magazine]]
|years=8 December 1941}}
{{s-aft|after=[[Husband E. Kimmel]]}}
{{s-bef|before=[[Harold Alexander, 1st Earl Alexander of Tunis|Sir Harold Alexander]]}}
{{s-ttl|title=[[Time (magazine)|Cover of Time Magazine]]
|years=21 September 1942}}
{{s-aft|after=[[William Francis Gibbs]]}}
{{s-end}}

{{GFMofWWII}}
{{Recipients of the Pour le Mérite and Knight's Cross}}
{{First and last recipients of the Knight's Cross}}
{{Authority control}}
{{Subject bar
| portal1=Biography
| portal2=Military of Germany
| portal3=World War I
| portal4=World War II
| commons=y
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bock, Fedor Von}}
[[Category:1880 births]]
[[Category:1945 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Kostrzyn nad Odrą]]
[[Category:People from the Province of Brandenburg]]
[[Category:German Protestants]]
[[Category:German untitled nobility]]
[[Category:German monarchists]]
[[Category:Field marshals of Nazi Germany]]
[[Category:German military personnel of World War I]]
[[Category:German military personnel killed in World War II]]
[[Category:German people of Russian descent]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Pour le Mérite (military class)]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of Michael the Brave, 1st class]]
[[Category:Military personnel referenced in the Wehrmachtbericht]]
[[Category:Knights First Class of the Order of the Zähringer Lion]]
[[Category:Knights of the House Order of Hohenzollern]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Military Merit Cross (Mecklenburg-Schwerin), 2nd class]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Hanseatic Cross (Hamburg)]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Hanseatic Cross (Bremen)]]
[[Category:Knights of the Order of the Crown (Württemberg)]]
[[Category:Commanders of the Order of Military Merit (Bulgaria)]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of the Yugoslav Crown]]
[[Category:Grand Crosses of the Order of Merit of the Republic of Hungary (military)]]
[[Category:Prussian Army personnel]]
[[Category:Generals of Infantry (Reichswehr)]]
[[Category:Recipients of the clasp to the Iron Cross, 1st class]]
[[Category:20th-century Freikorps personnel]]
[[Category:Deaths by airstrike during World War II]]</text>
      <sha1>0mvwrjdb1mwek0vrebltg3k4o57eh01</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
