<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Foster Air Force Base</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4045403</id>
    <revision>
      <id>720832395</id>
      <parentid>699360264</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-05-18T06:23:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>73.77.255.131</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Tactical Air Command */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="18376">{{for|the civil use of this facility and airport information|Victoria Regional Airport}}
{{Infobox military structure
| name = Foster Air Force Base&lt;br&gt;{{smaller|Foster Field}}
|ensign=[[File:Tactical Air Command Emblem.png|50px]]
| partof = Tactical Air Command
| location = [[Victoria County, Texas|Victoria County]], near [[Victoria, Texas]]
| coordinates = {{Coord|28|51|09|N|96|55|07|W|type:airport|display=inline}}
| image = [[File:Victoria Regional Airport TX 2006 USGS.jpg|300px]]
| caption = 2006 [[USGS]] airphoto
|pushpin_map= Texas
|pushpin_label=Foster AFB
|pushpin_mapsize=300
|pushpin_mark=Airplane_silhouette.svg
|latNS=N|latd=28|latm=51|lats=09
|longEW=W|longd=096|longm=55|longs=07
| type = [[Air Force Base]]
| code =
| built = 1941
| builder =
| materials =
| height =
| used = 1941-1945; 1953-1959
| demolished =
| condition =
| ownership =
| controlledby =
| garrison =
| commanders =
| occupants =
| battles =
| events =
}}
'''Foster Air Force Base''' (1941–1945, 1952–1959) is a former [[United States Air Force]] base, located approximately {{convert|6|mi|km}} east-northeast of [[Victoria, Texas]].  A flying training airfield during [[World War II]], it was part of [[Tactical Air Command]] during the [[Cold War]] as a tactical fighter and command base.

==History==
Named in memory of Lt. Arthur L. Foster (25 November 1888 - 10 February 1925), a native of [[Georgetown, Texas]], and a [[United States Army Air Corps]] instructor killed in a crash at [[Brooks City-Base|Brooks Field]], [[Texas]] in 1925. Foster's son received his training and commission at the base in the spring of 1942.&lt;ref name=&quot;Handbook&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tshaonline.org/handbook/online/articles/qcf13|title=Foster Army Air Field|last=Roell|first=Craig H.|publisher=The Handbook of Texas Online|accessdate=2009-04-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===World War II===
[[File:North American AT-6 formation Foster-aircraft.jpg|thumb|A twelve-ship formation over the Guadalupe River in the vicinity of Foster Field, Texas, Summer 1942]]
Foster Air Force Base was established as an advanced single-engine flying school for fighter pilots six miles (10&amp;nbsp;km) northeast of [[Victoria, Texas]], in the spring of 1941. A local funding campaign led by E. J. Dysart the previous spring had raised some $17,000 to locate the base at Victoria on a {{convert|1000|acre|km2|adj=on}} site as an economic asset. Subsequent government construction cost more than $4 million.&lt;ref name=&quot;Handbook&quot; /&gt; Leases were formally approved by the War Department on 4 March 1941, with construction beginning on 14 April 1941 by American-Friedman-Bitulithic Associates.&lt;ref name=&quot;Victoria, Texas 1942, Pages 1-2&quot;&gt;Victoria, Texas, &quot;''U.S. Honors Pioneer In Aviation Who Died Teaching Others to Fly''&quot;, Victoria Advocate, Sunday 22 February 1942, Volume 44, Number 230, Section 1, Pages 1-2.&lt;/ref&gt;

The airfield was activated on 15 May 1941 by the Gulf Coast Air Corps Training Center.  The mission of the new airfield was the training of aviation cadets in the advanced phase of flying training.  Foster was assigned to the Air Corps Advanced Flying School (Single Engine). In the advanced phase, the cadets flew advanced trainers, fighters and fighter-bombers. Pilot wings were awarded upon graduation and were sent on to group combat training. Graduates were usually graded as [[Flight Officer]]s (Warrant Officers); cadets who graduated at the top of their class were graded as Second Lieutenants.&lt;ref name=&quot;ATC&quot;&gt;Manning, Thomas A. (2005), History of Air Education and Training Command, 1942-2002, Office of History and Research, Air Education and Training Command, Randolph AFB, Texas.&lt;/ref&gt;

The initial class of cadets arrived in September 1941 and served under Lt. Col. Warren R. Carter, the first commander. WACs began to arrive the following May.  Cadets used [[North American AT-6 Texan]] trainers and [[Curtis P-40 Warhawk]] fighters to drill in aerial gunnery, though actual practice took place on ranges located on [[Matagorda Island]] and Matagorda Peninsula. In addition to these bombing ranges on Matagorda, at least ten auxiliary landing fields and a sub-base (Aloe AAF, built in 1943 5 miles southwest of Victoria) was controlled by Foster for emergency landings and aircraft overflow.&lt;ref name=&quot;Handbook&quot; /&gt;
[[File:Foster Field Texas 1943 Classbook.pdf|thumb|left|200px|Foster Field Texas 1943 Classbook]]
The field was formally dedicated to 1st Lt. Arthur L. Foster on Sunday, 22 February 1942, who was killed along with Maj. Lee O. Wright in the 1030 hrs. crash of a [[Curtiss JN-6H]], ''AS-44806'',&lt;ref&gt;http://www.aviationarchaeology.com/src/1940sB4/1925.htm&lt;/ref&gt; ~{{convert|2|mi|km}} E of [[Brooks City-Base|Brooks Field]], Texas on 10 February 1925. Foster's widow, Mrs. Ruth Young Foster, of [[San Antonio, Texas]], unveiled a plaque that read &quot;Dedicated to the memory of Lieut. Arthur Lee Foster, a pioneer in aviation who gave his life teaching others to fly.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Victoria, Texas 1942, Pages 1-2&quot;/&gt;

In 1943, the War Department constituted and activated the 77th Flying Training Wing (Advanced Single-Engine) at Foster and assigned it to the AAF Central Flying Training Command.  The 77th was a headquarters for advanced training at several bases of AAF Central Flying Training Command.

Many pilots returning from overseas service were taught to become aerial gunnery instructors at Foster Field. In addition to the pilot training mission, Foster also served as a medical evacuation facility for injured veterans. There were several housing facilities located on the base.&lt;ref name=&quot;Handbook&quot; /&gt;

On 1 January 1945 the 2539th Army Air Forces Base Unit took control of the ground station administrative functions. As World War II wound down Foster Field took control of several smaller facilities as they were being closed. On 1 September 1945 the mission at the airfield changed from pilot training to becoming a separation station. Foster Field itself was inactivated on 31 October 1945, being placed in standby status. On 15 November the facility was completely closed and eventually the Foster Field site returned to its prewar owners, the Buhler and Braman estates.&lt;ref name=&quot;Handbook&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ATC&quot; /&gt;

===United States Air Force===
The Air Force retained a recapture right, which it exercised at Foster and at many other former bases to accommodate the [[Korean War]] training surge. In the fall of 1951 the government purchased {{convert|1376|acre|km2}} at the site, and Foster Field was reactivated for single-engine jet training.&lt;ref name=&quot;Handbook&quot; /&gt; Foster Field was designated '''Foster Air Force Base''' on an inactive status on 1 September 1952, by Department of the Air Force General Order No. 38, dated 29 August 1952.&lt;ref name=&quot;Handbook&quot; /&gt;

====Air Training Command====
The facility was assigned to the [[United States Air Force]]'s Air Training Command. The 3580th Pilot Training Wing (Basic, Single-Engine) was assigned to the base on 1 May 1952 as the primary training organization as well as the base host unit.  The first cadets graduated in March 1953 after three months of duty using [[North American T-28 Trojan]] propeller and [[Lockheed T-33 Shooting Star]] jet trainers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Handbook&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ATC&quot; /&gt;

After the end of combat in Korea, Air Training Command returned various combat crew training responsibilities to [[Strategic Air Command]] and [[Tactical Air Command]] in 1954. The command was able to do this because bases like [[Greenville AFB]] and [[Laredo AFB]] had acquired sufficient facilities to assume their full share of the pilot training load.  Various bases were transferred to the combat commands, among these was the transfer of Foster AFB to TAC on 1 July 1954&lt;ref name=&quot;ATC&quot; /&gt;

====Tactical Air Command====
[[File:450th-Fighter-Wing-TAC.png|thumb|150px|left|Emblem of the 450th Fighter-Day Wing]]
[[File:322d-Fighter-Group-TAC.png|thumb|150px|left|322d Fighter-Day Group Patch]]
Foster Air Force Base was designated a permanent military installation on 1 July 1954.  Col. Frank L. Dunn became the new commander, replacing Col. C. C. Sonnkalb.&lt;ref name=&quot;Handbook&quot; /&gt;

Under Tactical Air Command, the '''450th Fighter-Bomber Wing''', was activated at Foster, on 1 July 1954, replacing and absorbing the assets of the 3580th PTW. Four operational squadrons (720th, 721st, 722d and 723d) were assigned to the 450th Fighter-Bomber Group, initially being equipped with the North American [[F-86F Sabre]].&lt;ref name=&quot;USAFHRA&quot;&gt;Ravenstein, Charles A., Air Force Combat Wings Lineage and Honors Histories 1947–1977, Office of Air Force History, 1984&lt;/ref&gt;  Its aircraft wore an approximation of the stars and stripes, with seven red and six white stripes on the trailing edge, and three stars in white on the blue forward portion of the fin.  They also were designated with a colored, scalloped nose chevron.&lt;ref name=&quot;F-100&quot;&gt;Donald, David. Century Jets: USAF Frontline Fighters of the Cold War. AIRtime, 2004. ISBN 1-880588-68-4.&lt;/ref&gt;

Along with the 450th, a second group, the '''322d Fighter-Day Group''' was assigned to Foster, and attached to the 450th FDW. The 322d consisted of the 450th, 451st and 452d Fighter-Bomber Squadrons, also flying the F-86F.&lt;ref name=&quot;USAFHRA&quot; /&gt;  Its aircraft wore a broad band on the fin with its playing card insignia superimposed.&lt;ref name=&quot;F-100&quot; /&gt;  The 450th FBG was an operational unit, while the 322d took over the training mission formerly performed by ATC prior to the transfer of the base to TAC.

With these two fighter groups assigned to the base, assigned personnel increased to about 6,000.&lt;ref name=&quot;Handbook&quot; /&gt;  The primary mission of the 450th FBW was to maintain tactical proficiency for combat operations and to prepare for overseas deployments as part of [[Ninth Air Force]].&lt;ref name=&quot;USAFHRA&quot; /&gt;

[[File:F-100s-450FDW-FosterAFB-Texas-1956.jpg|thumb|North American F-100s of the 450th Fighter-Day Group, about 1956.  North American F-100C-5-NA Super Sabre 54-1775 identifiable. This aircraft was lost in combat during the [[Vietnam War]] when assigned to the [[37th Tactical Fighter Wing]] at [[Phu Cat Air Base]] on 2 August 1968, its pilot was recovered.]]
[[File:F-100c-322fdw.jpg|thumb|Boeing [[B-50 Superfortress|KB-50D Superfortress]], ''48-123'', of the 622d Air Refueling Squadron (4505th ARW) carrying out first triple-point refueling operation with three North American F-100C Super Sabres (''54-1825'', ''53-1774'', ''54-1848'') of the 451st Fighter-Day Squadron (322d FDG), 1956]]
In early-1955, the 450th FBW began receiving new North American [[F-100 Super Sabre|F-100C/D Super Sabre]] aircraft, replacing the obsolescent F-86s.  The 450th FBW was the first operational Tactical Air Command wing to be equipped with the F-100.  With the change of equipment, the wing was redesignated as the '''450th Fighter-Day Wing''' on 8 March 1955, with all its subordinate groups and squadrons also being redesignated.&lt;ref name=&quot;USAFHRA&quot; /&gt;

On 8 July 1955, Foster AFB became the location of Headquarters, [[Nineteenth Air Force]]. under the command of MGEN Henry Viccellio.  Nineteenth AF had no units or aircraft permanently assigned. Its mission was planning and carrying out force protection and rapid response using temporarily attached units deployed to overseas crisis locations. From Foster, Nineteenth AF responded to the [[1958 Lebanon crisis]], when the United States sent in forces to sustain a pro-Western government after a conflict in [[Iraq]] threatened to spill across the border.&lt;ref name=&quot;USAFHRA&quot; /&gt;  Also, attached to Nineteenth AF, the 450th FDW carried out the first overseas deployment of a complete tactical force as a unit in a training flight to Europe in 1956. The next year three Foster-based F-100s flew the first TAC single-engine, nonstop, round-trip mission over a great distance when they &quot;attacked&quot; Panama in a training maneuver.&lt;ref name=&quot;Handbook&quot; /&gt;

On 1 July 1958, the 450th was redesignated as the '''450th Tactical Fighter Wing''' as part of a worldwide USAF renaming of its Fighter-Bomber and Fighter-Day units with a single mission designator.

===Closure===
On 28 August 1957, despite the fact that President [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]] appropriated funds for new construction at the base, the base was ordered closed by the spring of 1959, with the resident 450th TFW and both groups inactivating.&lt;ref name=&quot;Handbook&quot; /&gt;  This closure was due to budgetary constraints in the Air Force, however the closing came as a surprise to both Victorians and base commanders.&lt;ref name=&quot;Handbook&quot; /&gt;

Nineteenth Air Force was moved to [[Seymour Johnson AFB]], [[North Carolina]], effective 1 September 1958. The 450th TFW F-100 aircraft were reassigned to the 4th and 36th Tactical Fighter Wings, and all units assigned to Foster were inactivated by mid-December 1958.&lt;ref name=&quot;USAFHRA&quot; /&gt;

Despite a rigorous &quot;Save Foster&quot; campaign led in Washington by Senators [[Lyndon B. Johnson]] and [[Ralph Yarborough]] and Congressman [[Clark W. Thompson (Texas politician)|Clark W. Thompson]], the base closed on 31 December 1958.&lt;ref name=&quot;Handbook&quot; /&gt;  It was formally inactivated effective 1 January 1959 by Department of the Air Force General Order No. 7, dated February 9, 1959.&lt;ref name=&quot;Handbook&quot; /&gt;  The 450th was reactivated by SAC as a [[B-52 Stratofortress]] strategic bombardment wing in 1962 to replace the '''4136th Strategic Wing'''.&lt;ref name=&quot;USAFHRA&quot; /&gt;

===Previous names===
* Established as Victoria Army Airfield on 15 May 1941
* Foster Field, 15 January 1942 - 31 October 1945
* Foster Air Force Base, 1 May 1952 - 1 January 1959

===Major commands to which assigned===
* [[Gulf Coast Air Corps Training Center]], 15 May 1941
* [[Air Training Command|Air Corps Flying Training Command (later Army Air Forces Flying Training Command, Army Air Forces Training Command)]], 23 January 1942&lt;ref&gt;Gulf Coast Training Center was reassigned from Office, Chief of Air Corps and no longer a major command.&lt;/ref&gt; - 31 October 1945
* Air Training Command, 1 May 1952
* Tactical Air Command, 1 July 1954 - 1 January 1959

===Major units assigned===
* Air Corps Advanced Flying School (Single Engine) (later Army Air Forces Advanced Flying School, Army Air Forces Pilot School, Advanced (Single Engine), Army Air Forces Fighter Gunnery School), 15 May 1941 - 31 October 1945
* 75th Air Base Group, 4 September 1941 - June 1942
* 84th Air Base Group, 15 August 1941 - ''ca''. August 1942
* 65th Air Base Squadron (later 65th Base Headquarters and Air Base Squadron), 4 September 1941 - 30 April 1944
* 77th Flying Training Wing (Advanced Single Engine), 25 August 1943 - February 1945
:: 62d Single Engine Flying Training Group (originally 97th School Squadron), 4 September 1941 - 30 April 1944
:: 63d Single Engine Flying Training Group (originally 48th School Squadron), 4 September 1941 - 22 March 1944
* 2505th AAF Base Unit (77th Flying Training Wing), 1 May 1944 - February 1945
* 2539th AAF Base Unit (Pilot School, Advanced, Single Engine) (later 2539th AAFBU (Fighter Gunnery School), 2539th AAFBU (Standby)), 1 May 1944 -15 November 1945
* 3580th Pilot Training Wing (Basic, Single-Engine), 1 May 1952 - 1 July 1954
:: 3580th Pilot Training Group (Basic, Single-Engine), 1 May 1952 - 1 July 1954
:: 3580th Air Base Group, 1 May 1952 - 1 July 1954
:: 3580th Maintenance &amp; Supply Group, 1 May 1952 - 1 July 1954
* [[450th Tactical Fighter Wing|450th Fighter-Bomber Wing (later 450th Fighter-Day Wing, 450th Tactical Fighter Wing)]], 1 July 1954 - 18 December 1958
:: [[450th Fighter-Bomber Group|450th Fighter-Bomber Group (later 450th Fighter-Day Group)]], 1 July 1954 - 11 December 1957
:: 450th Air Base Group, 1 July 1954 - 1 January 1959
:: 450th Maintenance &amp; Supply Group, 1 July 1954 - 11 December 1957
* [[322d Fighter-Day Group]], 1 July 1954 - 18 November 1957
* [[Nineteenth Air Force]], 8 July 1955 - 1 September 1958
* 10th Communications Group, 8 October 1956 - 15 October 1957
* 512th Tactical Control Group (later 512th Command and Control Group), 8 October 1956 - 15 July 1958

===Major aircraft assigned===
* [[AT-6 Texan]], 1941–1945
* [[P-40 Warhawk]], 1941–1945
* [[F-86 Sabre]], 1954–1955
* [[F-100 Super Sabre]], 1955–1958

===Post military use===
The local economy suffered greatly from the closure of Foster AFB. In the summer of 1960, the [[General Services Administration]] approved the exchange of [[Aloe Army Airfield]] for Foster Field, and Victoria County Airport was moved to the latter site. The growth of the county airport slowly replaced the loss of Foster AFB as numerous businesses located there.&lt;ref name=&quot;Handbook&quot; /&gt;

Two of the largest businesses to locate at Victoria County Airport were the Devereux Foundation, a therapeutic-education center, and Gary Aircraft, which repaired surplus [[C-54 Skymaster]] (Douglas DC-4) aircraft in 1968. In 1976 Foster became the site of [[Victoria Regional Airport]], which provides passenger service and connections with major carriers.&lt;ref name=&quot;Handbook&quot; /&gt;

The Victoria Composite Squadron of the [[Civil Air Patrol]]'s Texas Wing continues to meet at the location.&lt;ref&gt;http://capvct.org/content/about.htm&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|Military of the United States|United States Air Force|World War II}}
* [[Texas World War II Army Airfields]]
* [[77th Flying Training Wing (World War II)]]

==Notes==
{{Commons category|Foster Air Force Base}}

===References===
{{reflist|2}}

===Bibliography===
{{Air Force Historical Research Agency}}
* Shaw, Frederick J. (2004), Locating Air Force Base Sites History’s Legacy, Air Force History and Museums Program, United States Air Force, Washington DC, 2004.
* Manning, Thomas A. (2005), History of Air Education and Training Command, 1942–2002.  Office of History and Research, Headquarters, AETC, Randolph AFB, Texas ASIN: B000NYX3PC

==External links==
{{Tactical Air Command}}
{{USAAF Training Bases World War II}}

[[Category:Buildings and structures in Victoria County, Texas]]
[[Category:1941 establishments in Texas]]
[[Category:Closed facilities of the United States Air Force]]
[[Category:Airfields of the United States Army Air Forces in Texas]]
[[Category:USAAF Central Flying Training Command]]
[[Category:American Theater of World War II]]
[[Category:1945 disestablishments in Texas]]
[[Category:1952 establishments in Texas]]
[[Category:1959 disestablishments in Texas]]</text>
      <sha1>ghgg9zozijmkxvc1nwmu70n1zmy2cff</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
