<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Great Polish Map of Scotland</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>35607197</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748242568</id>
      <parentid>707008826</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-07T05:00:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Background */clean up; http&amp;rarr;https for [[Google Books]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17631">[[File:West Coast of Scotland, Barony Castle Map, Peebleshire.JPG|thumb|300px|The Great Polish Map: the West Coast of Scotland viewed from [[Northern Ireland]]]]
The '''Great Polish Map of Scotland''' is a large (50&amp;nbsp;m x 40&amp;nbsp;m) three-dimensional, outdoor concrete scale model of [[Scotland]], located in the grounds of the [[Blackbarony|Barony Castle Hotel]], outside the village of [[Eddleston]] near [[Peebles]] in the [[Scottish Borders]].&lt;ref name=gfs&gt;{{cite web|author1=Bruce Gittings|author2=Royal Scottish Geographical Society|title=Polish Map of Scotland|url=http://www.scottish-places.info/features/featurefirst19323.html|work=Gazetteer for Scotland|publisher=The Editors of The Gazetteer for Scotland|accessdate=11 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; It is also known as the '''Mapa Scotland''' (derived from Polish ''mapa Szkocji'') or the '''Barony Map'''. The brainchild of Polish war veteran Jan Tomasik, it was built between 1974 and 1979 and is claimed to be the world's largest [[Raised-relief map|terrain relief model]].&lt;ref name=gfs /&gt; The sculpture is a [[listed building#Scotland|category B listed building]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://data.historic-scotland.gov.uk/pls/htmldb/f?p=2200:15:0::::BUILDING,HL:51957,polish%20map |title=Great Polish Map of Scotland |accessdate=24 July 2013 |publisher=Historic Scotland}}&lt;/ref&gt; and is being restored by a group calling itself ''Mapa Scotland''.&lt;ref name=mapascotland&gt;{{cite web|author=Mapa Scotland|title=Mapa Scotland website|url=http://www.mapascotland.org/| accessdate=24 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
{{further|Polish Armed Forces in the West}}
[[File:Barony Castle Hotel, Eddleston near Peebles, Scotland.JPG|thumb|Barony Castle Hotel in 2011]]
[[Black Barony]]'s connection with Polish Forces during the Second World War dates from early 1942, when the hotel, established in 1926, was requisitioned for use as the main [[Staff college|Staff College]] for training Polish officers in Scotland.&lt;ref name=&quot;mapascotland&quot; /&gt;

After the [[Battle of France|Fall of France]] in May 1940, the Polish Army in Scotland was reorganised as the [[I Corps in the West (Poland)|1st Polish Corps]] and entrusted by the [[War Office]] with the defence of a long stretch of the country's east coast between [[Arbroath]] (later extended to [[Montrose, Angus|Montrose]], 38 miles (61&amp;nbsp;km) north of [[Dundee]]) and [[Burntisland]] on the [[Firth of Forth]] against a possible invasion from [[German occupation of Norway|German-occupied Norway]].&lt;ref&gt;T. Ziarski-Kernberg, ''The Polish Community In Scotland'', Caldra House 2000, p.48&lt;/ref&gt; The Poles strengthened existing defences by installing anti-tank obstacles, building pill boxes and patrolling the coastline in armoured trains. In early 1942 they gave up responsibility for [[Angus]], taking over instead the defences of [[East Lothian]].&lt;ref&gt;G Barclay,''If Hitler Comes. Preparing for Invasion: Scotland 1940', Birlinn, 20013&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Maczek - graf 1 (cropped).jpg|thumb|left|General Maczek's grave in [[Breda#World War II|Breda]], one of the towns his forces liberated in 1944]]
Following the formation of the [[1st Armoured Division (Poland)|1st Polish Armoured Division]] in February 1942, Polish troops under the command of [[Stanisław Maczek|General Stanisław Maczek]] trained in [[Perthshire]], [[East Lothian]], [[Berwickshire]], and [[East Anglia]] before taking part in the [[Normandy landings]] of 1944. In the Normandy campaign they played a conspicuous part in the [[Falaise pocket|Battle of the Falaise Gap]],&lt;ref&gt;For the Poles' contribution at Falaise, see http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/ww2peopleswar/stories/46/a2450846.shtml&lt;/ref&gt; and in the liberation of the [[Netherlands]]&lt;ref&gt;For photographs from General Maczek's own picture diary from the campaign, see http://www.makers.org.uk/place/breda&lt;/ref&gt; and defeat of the [[Nazi Germany|Third Reich]]. After the war and the [[Eastern Bloc#Poland|Communist take-over in Poland]], many of the Polish soldiers in the West, including General Maczek, were unwilling to return to Poland, where their personal freedom was far from assured. Many settled in Britain, particularly in Scotland.&lt;ref&gt;T. Ziarski-Kernberg, ''The Polish Community In Scotland'', Caldra House 2000, p.11&lt;/ref&gt;

The large concrete map of Scotland was the idea of Jan Tomasik, a sergeant in the 1st Armoured Division, who during the war had been stationed in [[Galashiels]], about 14 miles (22&amp;nbsp;km) from the castle.&lt;ref name=&quot;mapascotland&quot; /&gt; He bought the hotel at Black Barony in 1968. In the early 1960s, finding his old wartime commander, like all Polish veterans, denied a war pension as a non-UK citizen, Tomasik employed Maczek in various jobs, including barman, in his Edinburgh hotel.&lt;ref name=Stachura&gt;{{cite book|last=Stachura|first=Peter|title=The Poles in Britain, 1940-2000: From Betrayal to Assimilation|year=2004|publisher=Frank Cass|isbn=0714684449|page=53|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=yjPjUBnucDcC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;dq=isbn%3A0714684449&amp;pg=PA53#v=onepage&amp;q=barman&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt; A friendship developed between the two men, and in the 1970s Tomasik provided a room for Maczek to enjoy summer breaks with his family in his newly refurbished hotel at Barony Castle.&lt;ref name=gfs /&gt; This has led to speculation that Maczek, with his tank commander's interest in topography, may have had some input into the map, though that has never been established on the basis of evidence.&lt;ref name=&quot;mapascotland&quot; /&gt;

The precise reasons why Tomasik created the map are unclear. It is known that Polish soldiers created an outline map of Poland on the ground at [[Douglas, South Lanarkshire|Douglas]] in Lanarkshire in 1940,&lt;ref&gt;http://www.ostrycharz.free-online.co.uk/Douglas.html Arrival of Strangers&lt;/ref&gt; in the very camp where Tomasik was stationed after arriving in Britain. It is also known that he was fascinated by a large scale-model map of Belgium, which he saw at the [[Expo 58|Brussels World's Fair]] of 1958 on his way to visit relations in Poland. This map appears to have been the direct inspiration for the map at Barony Castle, though it is also possible that the wartime model may have been an influence.&lt;ref name=&quot;mapascotland&quot; /&gt; Tomasik seems to have regarded the Barony map primarily as an added attraction for his hotel guests, expecting it also to draw sightseers. However, he is also on record as having said to hotel patrons that he wanted to show the country the Poles had defended during the war and was planning to invite [[George VI]]'s consort [[Queen Elizabeth The Queen Mother|Queen Elizabeth]] to open the map officially. He told them that the map was to be his legacy, describing it as &quot;a gift to the [[Scottish people]]&quot; for the hospitality the Scots had shown the Poles during the war years.&lt;ref name=&quot;mapascotland&quot; /&gt; Tomasik died in 1991.

==Construction==

The map was designed by Dr. Kazimierz Trafas, a young cartographer from the [[Jagiellonian University]] of [[Krakow]].&lt;ref name=gfs /&gt; Despite the tensions of the [[Cold War]], links between Scotland and Polish universities had been good since the late 1960s, when [[Threshold model|threshold analysis]] techniques in town and regional planning devised in Poland were refined and applied in Scotland for the Scottish Development Department.&lt;ref&gt;Boleslaw Malisz, Physical Planning for the Development of Satellite and New Towns: The Analysis of Urban Development Possibilities; Research Institute for Town Planning &amp; Architecture, Warsaw. Institute Papers 113 (1966); Jerzy Kowalowski, &quot;Threshold Analysis-an Economic Tool for Town and Regional Planning&quot;, ''Urban Studies'', June 1968 5: 132-143; Scottish Development Department, ''Threshold Analysis Manual'': Edinburgh, HMSO (1973)&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:The Great Polish Map Of Scotland (Mapa Scotland), Barony Castle.JPG|thumb|upright=1.35|right|The Great Map looking northwards from the Scottish border with England]]
On a visit to Poland, Tomasik discussed his idea of the map with [[Mieczysław Klimaszewski|Professor Klimaszewski]], head of the Jagiellonian University's Institute of Geography, vice-rector of the university and member of the Polish Council of State. Klimaszweski entrusted the task to Dr. Trafas who took charge of the project.&lt;ref name=&quot;mapascotland&quot; /&gt;

The 'Great Polish Map of Scotland', as it has been christened by the group planning to restore it, took six consecutive summers between 1974 and 1979 to construct, although the bulk of the work was accomplished by the late summer of 1976.&lt;ref name=&quot;mapascotland&quot; /&gt; In 1974, Trafas arrived in Scotland with his departmental colleague Roman Wolnik, surveyed the site and marked out the outline of the map to a scale of 1:10,000. The shapes of the mainland and islands were made with vertical shuttering and 300m, 600m and 900m contours laid in four-brick courses. Locations were correlated with a set of [[Collins Bartholomew|Bartholomew]]'s survey maps of Scotland by means of a reference grid.&lt;ref name=&quot;Janus Szewczuk&quot;&gt;[http://www.mapascotland.org/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/Szewczuk-Scotland-in-Scotland-translation-Jan.-20142.pdf Janus Szewczuk describes the building of the Great Map], Szkockja w Szkockja (Scotland in Scotland), published on mapascotland.org. Retrieved 16 March 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the following summer, Tomasik revisited Poland, returning with Trafas, Wolnik and three Krakow University employees hired under contract to provide the manual labour to construct the concrete map. The hotel manager Marek Raton, a son-in-law of Tomasik, and hotel maintenance man Bill Robson also worked on the project, especially the excavation of the surrounding pit. Some of the labour was supplied by hiring Polish exchange students visiting Britain.&lt;ref name=&quot;mapascotland&quot; /&gt; The body of the map was gradually built up by infilling the prepared outlines with cement. Mountain summits were marked by vertical rods, their heights exaggerated five times relative to the horizontal scale to increase the visual effect. This was a standard traditionally adopted for British military terrain maps.&lt;ref name=&quot;mapascotland&quot; /&gt; The topography was then finished off by manually sculpting the landforms according to the contours shown on the Bartholomew maps.&lt;ref name=&quot;mapascotland&quot; /&gt;

After the last visit of the Polish cartographers in 1977, hotel employees and members of the Tomasik family continued to work on the map intermittently over two more summers before it was completed in 1979.&lt;ref name=&quot;mapascotland&quot; /&gt; The surface was painted with forests, urban areas, major roads and lochs shown. A wall was built around the map to create an oval-shaped basin, 1.5m deep. This was then supplied with water diverted from a nearby stream to create the seas and [[loch]]s. The gravity-fed water also flowed through submerged pipes to the major river sources. The original plan to construct a metal walkway over the model to serve as a viewing platform never materialised.&lt;ref name=&quot;mapascotland&quot; /&gt;

Professor Trafas, the chief designer and builder of the map, died in 2004.&lt;ref name=&quot;Janus Szewczuk&quot; /&gt;

==Restoration==

After the sale of the hotel in 1985, parts of the map deteriorated slowly over the years and, while it remains generally substantial, some of the concrete is now in a fragile and ruinous condition.&lt;ref name=&quot;mapascotland&quot; /&gt; In 2010, a group of volunteers calling themselves Mapa Scotland was formed which secured [[category B listed]] for the map from [[Historic Scotland]] in 2012&lt;ref name=listed&gt;{{cite web|title=Great Polish Map of Scotland granted listed status|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-scotland-south-scotland-19622243|work=BBC News|publisher=BBC|date=17 September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; and aims to restore it to its original condition while promoting it as a heritage monument, educational resource and visitor attraction.&lt;ref&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/scotland/south_of_scotland/8664441.stm 'Team aims to restore 3D Scotland map at Borders castle'], BBC News, 6 May 2010. Retrieved 11 July 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TSR rivers flow&quot;&gt;[http://www.thesouthernreporter.co.uk/news/local-headlines/hopes-that-map-s-rivers-will-once-again-flow-lie-with-historic-scotland-1-2172760 'Hopes that map's rivers will once again flow lie with Historic Scotland'], The Southern Reporter, 18 March 2012. Retrieved 11 July 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=herald&gt;Herald Scotland article, 'Campaign to save 3D map of Scotland', 7 May 2012&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;scotsbarszcz&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Rescue plan mapped out|url=http://content.yudu.com/A1o18o/sb5/resources/index.htm?referrerUrl=|accessdate=15 July 2012|newspaper=scotsbarszcz.com/|date=June 2010|issue=Issue 5|page=6}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2011, they obtained a £20,000 grant from the [[Heritage Lottery Fund]], on the proviso they match this figure with funding from other sources and guarantee public access to the map.&lt;ref name=&quot;TSR rivers flow&quot; /&gt; The matched funding was secured in 2013 thanks to grants from the Barony Castle Hotel, Borders Council and others.
[[File:The Great Polish Map of Scotland.JPG|thumb|centre|600px|The Castle and the Map]]
The then Polish Consul General in Scotland, Tomasz Trafas, who happens to be a brother of Professor Trafas, said in a newspaper interview that the map is &quot;a rare symbol of the broader heritage and a symbol of the cultural links between Poland and Scotland since the 16th century that is worth preserving for the benefit of the local community and wider nation&quot;.&lt;ref name=herald /&gt;

In May 2012, the [[Member of the Scottish Parliament|MSP]] for [[Midlothian South, Tweeddale and Lauderdale (Scottish Parliament constituency)|Midlothian South, Tweeddale and Lauderdale]], [[Christine Grahame]], proposed a parliamentary motion (which was debated in September 2012) that the Scottish Parliament should recognise &quot;the historic significance of The Great Polish Map of Scotland&quot;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.scottish.parliament.uk/msps/currentmsps/Christine-Grahame-MSP.aspx Christine Grahame MSP (see Recent Motions tab)], Recent Motions, Motion S4M-03061. Scottish Parliament website.&lt;/ref&gt; and support the project.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bordertelegraph.com/news/roundup/articles/2012/07/03/431401-debate-to-ensure-borders-map-is-not-consigned-to-history 'Debate to ensure Borders map is not consigned to history'], Border Telegraph (Galashiels), 3 July 2012. Retrieved 11 July 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Peeblesshire News, 'MSP's backing for model restoration', 1 June 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TSR Grahame push&quot; /&gt;

==Size==
The Great Polish Map of Scotland measures approximately {{convert|50|x|40|m|ft}}.&lt;ref name=gfs /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;TSR Grahame push&quot;&gt;[http://www.thesouthernreporter.co.uk/news/local-headlines/grahame-joins-push-to-restore-wartime-reminder-that-could-put-borders-on-map-1-2327343 'Grahame joins push to restore wartime reminder that could put Borders on map'], The Southern Reporter (Selkirk), 3 June 2012. Retrieved 11 July 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; It exceeds the surface area of the solid terrain model of [[British Columbia]] in the Crystal Garden, [[Victoria, British Columbia|Victoria]]&amp;mdash;{{convert|74|x|40|ft|m}}&amp;mdash;claimed to be the largest in the world&lt;ref name=stm&gt;{{cite web|title=World's largest physical terrain model|url=http://www.solidterrainmodeling.com/bc.htm|publisher=Solid Terrain Modeling, Inc.|accessdate=11 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; (Mapa Scotland point out that the Scottish map is 2.8 times larger&lt;ref name=&quot;TSR Grahame push&quot; /&gt;). The 'land' area alone of the Great Polish Map of Scotland is 780 square metres.&lt;ref name=&quot;mapascotland&quot; /&gt;

==Gallery==
&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:Forth Estuary and Fife, Mapa Scotland, Barony Castle.JPG|[[Forth Estuary]] and [[Fife]]
Image:Galloway, Mapa Scotland, Barony Castle.JPG|[[Galloway]]
Image:Outer Hebrides, Mapa Scotland, Barony Castle.JPG|[[Outer Hebrides]]
Image:Ben Nevis, Barony Castle Map, Peebleshire.JPG|[[Ben Nevis]]
Image:Ochil Hills, Mapa Scotland, Barony Castle.JPG|[[Ochil Hills]]
Image:Isle of Arran, Mapa Scotland, Barony Castle.JPG|[[Isle of Arran]]
Image:Mapa Scotland, Barony Castle, Scottish Borders.JPG|The map being prepared for restoration
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
* [[1st Armoured Division (Poland)]]
* [[Scottish people#Poland|Scots in Poland]]

==References==
{{Div col}}
{{Reflist}}
{{Div col end}}

== External links ==
{{commonscat|Great Polish Map of Scotland (sculpture)|&lt;br/&gt;Great Polish Map of Scotland (sculpture)}}
* [http://www.mapascotland.org/ Official '''''Mapa Scotland''''' website] — ''the organization preserving and restoring The Great Polish Map of Scotland''.
* [http://www.mapascotland.org/galleries/ ''Mapa Scotland'' — galleries of slideshows] — ''vintage era and contemporary restoration''.
* [http://canmore.rcahms.gov.uk/en/site/101352/details/black+barony+gardens/ Rcahms.gov.uk: Aerial images of the map]
* [http://www.facebook.com/mapascotland Facebook — Mapa Scotland]
* [http://www.peebles-theroyalburgh.info/ '''''www.peebles-theroyalburgh.info''''' — '''''Official Peebles Town Website'''''.]

{{Coord|55.71198|N|3.21660|W|region:GB_type:landmark|display=title|format=dms}}

[[Category:Maps of Scotland]]
[[Category:Concrete sculptures in the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Outdoor sculptures in Scotland]]
[[Category:Polish contemporary art]]
[[Category:Polish military memorials and cemeteries]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures completed in 1975]]
[[Category:Listed monuments and memorials in Scotland]]
[[Category:Category B listed buildings in the Scottish Borders]]
[[Category:Installation art works]]
[[Category:1975 in art]]
[[Category:1975 in Poland]]
[[Category:1975 in Scotland]]
[[Category:Foreign relations of Scotland]]
[[Category:Poland–United Kingdom relations]]</text>
      <sha1>kqk0x44gyp6fyrgp7s7wp164uqt1p3t</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
