<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Herero and Namaqua genocide</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>858003</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749082995</id>
      <parentid>749078971</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-12T08:08:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Urchu</username>
        <id>29557852</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="60194">{{Genocide}}
The '''Herero and Namaqua genocide''' was a campaign of racial extermination and collective punishment that the [[German Empire]] undertook in [[German South-West Africa]] (modern-day [[Namibia]]) against the [[Herero people|Herero]] and [[Nama people]]. It is considered one of the first [[genocide]]s of the 20th century.&lt;ref&gt;Olusoga, David and Erichsen, Casper W (2010).  ''The Kaiser's Holocaust. Germany's Forgotten Genocide and the Colonial Roots of Nazism''. Faber and Faber. ISBN 978-0-571-23141-6&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title=The Holocaust: Theoretical Readings | publisher=Rutgers University Pressc | last=Levi | first=Neil | author2=Rothberg, Michael | year=2003 | page=465 | isbn=0-8135-3353-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=mamdani&gt;Mahmood Mamdani (2001) ''When Victims Become Killers: Colonialism, Nativism, and the Genocide in Rwanda'', Princeton University Press, Princeton ISBN 978-0-691-05821-4&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;OFAA20060831&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://afraf.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/abstract/106/422/113|title = Reparations for the Herero Genocide: Defining the limits of international litigation|author = Allan D. Cooper|work = Oxford Journals African Affairs|date = 2006-08-31}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.dw-world.de/dw/article/0,1564,1084266,00.html |title=Remembering the Herero Rebellion |publisher=[[Deutsche Welle]] |date=2004-11-01 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20050225073749/http://www.dw-world.de/dw/article/0,1564,1084266,00.html |archivedate=February 25, 2005 }}&lt;/ref&gt; It took place between 1904 and 1907 during the [[Herero Wars]].

In January 1904, the Herero people, led by [[Samuel Maharero]] and [[Nama people|Nama]] captain [[Hendrik Witbooi (Namaqua chief)|Hendrik Witbooi]], rebelled against [[German colonial empire|German colonial rule]]. In August, German general [[Lothar von Trotha]] defeated the Herero in the [[Battle of Waterberg]] and drove them into the desert of [[Omaheke Region|Omaheke]], where most of them died of dehydration. In October, the Nama people also rebelled against the Germans, only to suffer a similar fate.

In total, between 24,000 and 100,000 Herero and 10,000 Nama died.&lt;ref name=sarkin/&gt;&lt;ref name=moses&gt;A. Dirk Moses (2008)  ''Empire, Colony, Genocide: Conquest, Occupation and Subaltern Resistance in World History'', Berghahn Books, NY ISBN 978-1-84545-452-4&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dominik J. Schaller (2008) ''From Conquest to Genocide: Colonial Rule in German Southwest Africa and German East Africa'', p. 296, Berghahn Books, NY ISBN 1-84545-452-9&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sara L. Friedrichsmeyer, Sara Lennox, and Susanne M. Zantop (1998) ''The Imperialist Imagination: German Colonialism and Its Legacy'', p. 87, University of Michigan Press ISBN 978-0-472-09682-4&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Walter Nuhn 1904&quot;&gt;Walter Nuhn (1989) ''Sturm über Südwest. Der Hereroaufstand von 1904'', Bernard &amp; Graefe-Verlag, Koblenz ISBN 3-7637-5852-6.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Marie-Aude Baronian, Stephan Besser, Yolande Jansen (2007) [https://books.google.com/books?id=LItBN2keNpQC&amp;pg=PA33&amp;dq=Herero+starvation ''Diaspora and Memory: Figures of Displacement in Contemporary Literature, Arts and Politics''], p. 33, Rodopi ISBN 978-1-4294-8147-2&lt;/ref&gt; The first phase of the genocide was characterized by widespread death from starvation and dehydration due to the prevention of the retreating Herero from leaving the [[Namib Desert]] by German forces. Once defeated, thousands of Herero and Nama were imprisoned in concentration camps, where the majority died of disease, abuse, and exhaustion.&lt;ref&gt;Gewald, Colonization, genocide and resurgence pp 167, 209, Olusoga, Namibia: genocide and the second reich&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1985, the [[United Nations]]' [[Whitaker Report (United Nations)|Whitaker Report]] classified the aftermath as an attempt to exterminate the Herero and Nama peoples of [[South-West Africa]], and therefore one of the earliest attempts at genocide in the 20th century. In 2004, the German government recognized and apologized for the events, but ruled out financial compensation for the victims' descendants.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC08142004&quot;&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/3565938.stm|title = Germany admits Namibia genocide|date = 14 August 2004|accessdate = 2008-04-23|publisher = [[BBC News]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; In July 2015, the German government and the speaker of the Bundestag officially called the events a &quot;genocide&quot; and &quot;part of a race war&quot;. However it has refused to consider reparations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Tejas|first1=Aditya|title=German Official Says Namibia Herero Killings Were 'Genocide' And Part Of 'Race War'|url=http://www.ibtimes.com/german-official-says-namibia-herero-killings-were-genocide-part-race-war-2000764|publisher=International Business Times|accessdate=13 July 2015|date=9 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Deutsche Kolonialverbrechen: Bundesregierung nennt Herero-Massaker erstmals &quot;Völkermord&quot;|url=http://www.spiegel.de/politik/deutschland/namibia-massaker-bundesregierung-spricht-von-voelkermord-a-1043117.html|publisher=Spiegel Online|accessdate=13 July 2015|language=German|date=13 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
[[File:Lothar von Trotha.jpg|thumb|Lieutenant General [[Lothar von Trotha]]]]
[[File:Theodor Lutwein &amp; Samuel Maharero (1895).png|thumb|Theodor Leutwein (seated left), [[Zacharias Zeraua]] (2nd from left) and [[Manasseh Tyiseseta]] (seated, fourth from left), in 1895.]]
[[File:Witboi.jpg|thumb|Nama captain Hendrik Witbooi]]
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-2006-0137, Deutsch-Südwestafrika, Witbooi bei dt. Verwaltungsbeamten.jpg|thumb|Theodor Leutwein [[Toast (honour)|toasting]] Hendrik Witbooi in 1896.]]
[[File:Hererowars.jpg|thumb|German ''[[Schutztruppe]]'' in combat with the Herero in a painting by [[Richard Knötel]].]]
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-R27576, Deutsch-Südwestafrika, Herero-Aufstand.jpg|thumb|Central figure Lieutenant General Lothar von Trotha, the ''Oberbefehlshaber'' (Supreme Commander) of the protection force in German South-West Africa, in Keetmanshoop during the Herero uprising, 1904.]]

The Herero were originally a group of cattle herders living in the central-eastern region of German South-West Africa, presently modern Namibia. The area occupied by the Herero was known as [[Damaraland]]. The Nama were pastorals and traders living to the South of the Herero.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Kaiser's Holocaust|last=Olusoga|first=David|publisher=faber &amp; faber|year=2011|isbn=978-0-571-23142-3|location=|pages=22}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1883, during the [[scramble for Africa]], [[Franz Adolf Eduard Lüderitz]] purchased a stretch of coast near the [[Angra Pequena]] bay from the reigning chief. The terms of the purchase were fraudulent, but the German government nonetheless established a [[protectorate]] over it.&lt;ref name=gewald&gt;Jan-Bart Gewald (1998) ''Herero heroes: a socio-political history of the Herero of Namibia, 1890–1923'', James Currey, Oxford ISBN 978-0-8214-1256-5&lt;/ref&gt; At that time, it was the only overseas German territory deemed suitable for white settlement.&lt;ref&gt;Peace and freedom, Volume 40, Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, page 57, The Section, 1980&lt;/ref&gt;

Chief of the neighbouring Herero, [[Maharero|Kamaharero]] rose to power by uniting all the Herero.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}} Faced with repeated attacks by the Khowesin, a subtribe of the [[Khoikhoi]] under [[Hendrik Witbooi (Namaqua chief)|Hendrik Witbooi]], he signed a protection treaty on 21 October 1885 with [[German Empire|Imperial Germany]]'s colonial governor [[Heinrich Ernst Göring]] (father of [[Nazi]] [[Luftwaffe]] commander [[Hermann Göring]]) but did not cede the land of the Herero. This treaty was renounced in 1888 due to lack of German support against Witbooi but it was reinstated in 1890.&lt;ref name=&quot;KDM&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://klausdierks.com/Biographies/Biographies_M.htm|title=Biographies of Namibian Personalities, M. Entry for Maharero|last=Dierks|first=Klaus|authorlink=Klaus Dierks|publisher=klausdierks.com|date=2004|accessdate=10 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Herero leaders repeatedly complained about violation of this treaty, as Herero women and girls were raped by Germans, a crime that the German authorities were reluctant to punish.&lt;ref&gt;Marcia Klotz (1994) ''White women and the dark continent: gender and sexuality in German colonial discourse from the sentimental novel to the fascist film'', Thesis (Ph. D.) — Stanford University, p. 72: &quot;Although records show that Herero leaders repeatedly complained that Germans were raping Herero women and girls with impunity, not a single case of rape came before the colonial courts before the uprising because the Germans looked upon such offences as mere peccadilloes.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1890 Kamaharero's son, [[Samuel Maharero|Samuel]], signed a great deal of land over to the Germans in return for helping him to ascend to the Ovaherero throne, and to subsequently be established as paramount chief.&lt;ref name=&quot;KDM2&quot;&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://klausdierks.com/Biographies/Biographies_M.htm
|title=Biographies of Namibian Personalities, M. Entry for Samuel Maharero
|date=2004
|last=Dierks
|first=Klaus
|authorlink=Klaus Dierks
|publisher=klausdierks.com
|accessdate=10 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; German involvement in tribal fighting ended in tenuous peace in 1894.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}} In that year, [[Theodor Leutwein]] became governor of the territory, which underwent a period of rapid development, while the German government sent the ''[[Schutztruppe]]'' (imperial colonial troops) to pacify the region.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC290801&quot;&gt;[http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/1514856.stm &quot;A bloody history: Namibia's colonisation&quot;], [[BBC News]], 29 August 2001&lt;/ref&gt;

===German colonial policy===

Under German colonial rule, natives were routinely used as [[Slavery|slave]] labourers, and their lands were frequently confiscated and given to colonists, who were encouraged to settle on land taken from the natives; that land was stocked with cattle stolen from the Herero and Namas,&lt;ref name=bridgman&gt;Bridgman, Jon M. (1981) [https://books.google.com/books?id=k1bRcJ885fAC ''The Revolt of the Hereros''], California University Press  ISBN 978-0-520-04113-4&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|19, 34, 50, 149}}&lt;ref&gt;[[E.D. Morel]] (1920) [https://books.google.com/books?id=RygbAAAAYAAJ ''The Black Man's Burden''], pp 55, 64 &amp; 66, B.W. Huebsch, New York&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=hull&gt;[[Hull, Isabel V.]] (2005) [https://books.google.com/books?id=B5gFxsbWXTYC ''Absolute Destruction: Military Culture and the Practices of War in Imperial Germany''], Cornell University Press, NY ISBN 978-0-8014-4258-2&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|8, 22}}&lt;ref&gt;Bley, Helmut (1996) ''Namibia under German Rule'', pp. 10 &amp; 59, LIT, Hamburg ISBN 978-3-89473-225-7&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Baranowski, Shelley (2011) ''Nazi Empire: German Colonialism and Imperialism from Bismarck to Hitler'', pp. 47–9, 55–6 &amp; 59, Cambridge University Press ISBN 978-0-521-85739-0&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Steinmetz&gt;Steinmetz, George (2007) ''The Devil's Handwriting: Precoloniality and the German Colonial State in Qingdao, Samoa, and Southwest Africa'', University of Chicago Press ISBN 978-0-226-77244-8&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|147–149, 185–186, 209}} causing a great deal of resentment. Over the next decade, the land and the cattle that were essential to Herero and Nama lifestyles passed into the hands of German settlers arriving in South-West Africa.&lt;ref name=&quot;bridgman&quot;/&gt;{{rp|57}}

===Revolts===
In 1903, some of the Nama tribes rose in revolt under the leadership of Hendrik Witbooi.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC290801&quot; /&gt; A number of factors led the Herero to join them in January 1904.

One of the major issues was land rights. The Herero had already ceded over a quarter of their {{convert|130000|km2|sqmi}} to German colonists by 1903,&lt;ref name=bridgman/&gt;{{rp|60}} before the [[Otavi Mining and Railway Company|Otavi railway line]] running from the African coast to inland German settlements was completed.&lt;ref name=chalk/&gt;{{rp|230}} Completion of this line would have made the German colonies much more accessible and would have ushered a new wave of Europeans into the area.&lt;ref name=drechsler&gt;Drechsler, Horst (1980) ''Let Us Die Fighting: the struggle of the Herero and Nama against German imperialism (1884–1915)'', Zed Press, London ISBN 978-0-905762-47-0&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|133}}

Historian Horst Drechsler states that there was discussion of the possibility of establishing and placing the Herero in native reserves and that this was further proof of the German colonists' sense of ownership over the land. Drechsler illustrates the gap between the rights of a European and an African; the German Colonial League held that, in regards to legal matters, the testimony of seven Africans was equivalent to that of a colonist.&lt;ref name=drechsler/&gt;{{rp|132, 133}} Bridgman writes about racial tensions underlying these developments; the average German colonist viewed native Africans as a lowly source of cheap labour, and others welcomed their extermination.&lt;ref name=bridgman/&gt;{{rp|60}}

A new policy on debt collection, enforced in November 1903, also played a role in the uprising. For many years, the Herero population had fallen in the habit of borrowing money from colonist traders at extreme interest rates. For a long time, much of this debt went uncollected and accumulated, as most Herero had no means to pay. To correct this growing problem, Governor Leutwein decreed with good intentions that all debts not paid within the next year would be voided.&lt;ref name=bridgman/&gt;{{rp|59}} In the absence of hard cash, traders often seized cattle, or whatever objects of value they could get their hands on, to recoup their loans as quickly as possible. This fostered a feeling of resentment towards the Germans on the part of the Herero people, which escalated to hopelessness when they saw that German officials were sympathetic to the traders who were about to lose what they were owed.&lt;ref name=bridgman/&gt;{{rp|60}}

In 1903 the Herero learned of a plan to divide their territory with a railway line and set up reservations where they would be concentrated; this was also one of the reasons for the revolt.&lt;ref&gt;Samuel Totten, Paul Robert Bartrop, Steven L. Jacobs (2007) ''Dictionary of Genocide: A-L'', p.184, Greenwood Press, Westport, Conn. ISBN 978-0-313-34642-2&lt;/ref&gt;

The Herero judged the situation intolerable, and revolted in early 1904, killing between 123 and 150 Germans, including seven [[Boer]]s and three women,&lt;ref name=bridgman/&gt;{{rp|74}} in what Nils Ole Oermann calls a &quot;desperate surprise attack&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;Geoff Eley and James Retallack, (2004) ''Wilhelminism and Its Legacies: German Modernities, Imperialism, and the Meanings of Reform, 1890–1930'', p.171, Berghahn Books, NY ISBN 978-1-57181-223-0&lt;/ref&gt;

The timing of their attack was carefully planned. After successfully asking a large Herero tribe to surrender their weapons, Governor Leutwein was convinced that they and the rest of the native population were essentially pacified and so withdrew half of the German troops stationed in his colony.&lt;ref name=bridgman/&gt;{{rp|56}} Led by Chief [[Samuel Maharero]], the Herero surrounded [[Okahandja]] and cut links{{Clarify|date=June 2014|reason=Blockaded roads or what?}} to [[Windhoek]], the colonial capital. Maharero then issued a manifesto in which he forbade his troops to kill any Englishmen, Boers, uninvolved tribes, women and children in general, or German missionaries.&lt;ref name=bridgman/&gt;{{rp|70}}

Leutwein was forced to request reinforcements and an experienced officer from the German government in [[Berlin]].&lt;ref name=clark&gt;{{Cite book|last=Clark|first=Christopher|authorlink=Christopher Clark|title=Iron Kingdom: The Rise and Downfall of Prussia 1600–1947|year=2006|publisher=Belknap Press of Harvard|location=Cambridge|pages=776|isbn=0-674-02385-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|604}} Lieutenant-General [[Lothar von Trotha]] was appointed Supreme Commander ({{lang-de|Oberbefehlshaber}}) of South-West Africa on 3 May 1904, arriving with an expeditionary force of 14,000 troops on 11 June.

Leutwein was subordinate to the Colonial Department of the Prussian Foreign Office, which reported to Chancellor [[Bernhard von Bülow]] while General Trotha reported to the military [[German General Staff]], which was only subordinate to [[Wilhelm II, German Emperor|Emperor Wilhelm II]].

Leutwein wanted to defeat the most determined Herero rebels and negotiate a surrender with the remainder to achieve a political settlement.&lt;ref name=clark/&gt;{{rp|605}} Trotha, however, planned to crush the native resistance through military force. He stated that:
{{quote|My intimate knowledge of many central African tribes (Bantu and others) has everywhere convinced me of the necessity that the Negro does not respect treaties but only brute force.&lt;ref name=gewald/&gt;{{rp|173}}}}

==Genocide==
General Trotha stated his proposed solution to end the resistance of the Herero people in a letter, before the Battle of Waterberg:&lt;ref name=mamdani/&gt;{{rp|11}}

{{quote|I believe that the nation as such should be annihilated, or, if this was not possible by tactical measures, have to be expelled from the country&amp;nbsp;... This will be possible if the water-holes from Grootfontein to Gobabis are occupied. The constant movement of our troops will enable us to find the small groups of this nation who have moved backwards and destroy them gradually.}}
Trotha's troops defeated 3,000–5,000 Herero combatants at the [[Battle of Waterberg]] on 11–12 August 1904 but were unable to encircle and annihilate the retreating survivors.&lt;ref name=clark/&gt;{{rp|605}}

{{Genocide of Indigenous peoples}}

The pursuing German forces prevented groups of Herero from breaking from the main body of the fleeing force and pushed them further into the desert. As exhausted Herero fell to the ground, unable to go on, German soldiers acting on orders killed men, women, and children.&lt;ref name=totten/&gt;{{rp|22}} Jan Cloete, acting as a guide for the Germans, witnessed the atrocities committed by the German troops and deposed the following statement:&lt;ref name=drechsler/&gt;{{rp|157}}
{{quote|I was present when the Herero were defeated in a battle in the vicinity of Waterberg. After the battle all men, women, and children who fell into German hands, wounded or otherwise, were mercilessly put to death. Then the Germans set off in pursuit of the rest, and all those found by the wayside and in the sandveld were shot down and bayoneted to death. The mass of the Herero men were unarmed and thus unable to offer resistance. They were just trying to get away with their cattle.}}

A portion of the Herero escaped the Germans and went to the [[Omaheke Desert]], hoping to reach British territory of [[Bechuanaland]]; fewer than 1,000 reached Bechuanaland, where they were granted asylum.&lt;ref&gt;Nils Ole Oermann  (1999) ''Mission, Church and State Relations in South West Africa under German Rule 1884–1915'', p. 97, Franz Steiner Verlag, Stuttgart ISBN 978-3-515-07578-7&lt;/ref&gt; To prevent them from returning, Trotha ordered the desert to be sealed off.&lt;ref&gt;Ulrich van der Heyden; Holger Stoecker (2005) ''Mission und Macht im Wandel politischer Orientierungen: Europaische Missionsgesellschaften in politischen Spannungsfeldern in Afrika und Asien zwischen 1800–1945'', p. 394, Franz Steiner Verlag, Stuttgart ISBN 978-3-515-08423-9&lt;/ref&gt;  German patrols later found [[skeletons]] around holes {{Convert|13|m|ft}} deep that had been dug in a vain attempt to find water. Some sources also state that the German colonial army systematically poisoned desert water wells.&lt;ref name=totten&gt;Samuel Totten, William S. Parsons, Israel W. Charny (2004)  [https://books.google.com/books?id=5Ef8Hrx8Cd0C&amp;pg=PA51&amp;dq=Herero+Poisoned+wells ''Century of Genocide: Critical Essays and Eyewitness Accounts''], Routledge, NY ISBN 978-0-203-89043-1&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=totten/&gt;{{rp|22}}&lt;ref name=kroll&gt;Dan Kroll (2006) ''Securing Our Water Supply: Protecting a Vulnerable Resource'', p. 22, PennWell Corp/University of Michigan Press ISBN 978-1-59370-069-0&lt;/ref&gt; Maherero and 500–1,500 men crossed the Kalahari into Bechuanaland where he was accepted as a vassal of the [[Tswana people|Batswana]] chief [[List of rulers of Tawana|Sekgoma]].&lt;ref&gt;[[Thomas Tlou]] (1985)  ''A History of Ngamiland, 1750 to 1906 : The Formation of an African State'', Macmillan Botswana, Gaborone, Botswana ISBN 978-0-333-39635-3&lt;/ref&gt;

On 2 October, Trotha issued a warning to the Herero {{#tag:ref|translated from German: &quot;Ich, der große General der Deutschen Soldaten, sende diesen Brief an das Volk der Herero. Die Herero sind nicht mehr deutsche Untertanen. Sie haben gemordet und gestohlen, haben verwundeten Soldaten Ohren und Nasen und andere Körperteile abgeschnitten, und wollen jetzt aus Feigheit nicht mehr kämpfen. Ich sage dem Volk: Jeder, der einen der Kapitäne an eine meiner Stationen als Gefangenen abliefert, erhält tausend Mark, wer Samuel Maharero bringt, erhält fünftausend Mark. Das Volk der Herero muss jedoch das Land verlassen. Wenn das Volk dies nicht tut, so werde ich es mit dem Groot Rohr dazu zwingen. Innerhalb der Deutschen Grenzen wird jeder Herero mit und ohne Gewehr, mit oder ohne Vieh erschossen, ich nehme keine Weiber oder Kinder mehr auf, treibe sie zu ihrem Volke zurück, oder lasse auf sie schießen. Dies sind meine Worte an das Volk der Herero. Der große General des mächtigen Deutschen Kaisers.&quot;
:&quot;Dieser Erlaß ist bei den Appells den Truppen mitzuteilen mit dem Hinzufügen, daß auch der Truppe, die einen der Kapitäne fängt, die entsprechende Belohnung zu teil wird und daß das Schießen auf Weiber und Kinder so zu verstehen ist, daß über sie hinweggeschossen wird, um sie zum Laufen zu zwingen. Ich nehme mit Bestimmtheit an, daß dieser Erlaß dazu führen wird, keine männlichen Gefangenen mehr zu machen, aber nicht zu Grausamkeiten gegen Weiber und Kinder ausartet. Diese werden schon fortlaufen, wenn zweimal über sie hinweggeschossen wird. Die Truppe wird sich des guten Rufes der deutschen Soldaten bewußt bleiben.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Bundesarchiv Potsdam, Akten des Reichskolonialamtes, RKA, 10.01 2089, Bl. 23, Handschriftliche Abschrift der Proklamation an das Volk der Herero und des Zusatzbefehls an die Kaiserliche Schutztruppe, 2. Oktober 1904&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://sundoc.bibliothek.uni-halle.de/diss-online/04/05H118/t8.pdf Der Einsatz der Telegraphie im Krieg gegen Afrikaner], p. 195&lt;/ref&gt;|group=DE}}:
{{quote|I, the great general of the German soldiers, send this letter to the Herero. The Herero are German subjects no longer. They have killed, stolen, cut off the ears and other parts of the body of wounded soldiers, and now are too cowardly to want to fight any longer. I announce to the people that whoever hands me one of the chiefs shall receive 1,000 marks, and 5,000 marks for Samuel Maherero. The Herero nation must now leave the country. If it refuses, I shall compel it to do so with the 'long tube' (cannon). Any Herero found inside the German frontier, with or without a gun or cattle, will be executed. I shall spare neither women nor children. I shall give the order to drive them away and fire on them. Such are my words to the Herero people.&lt;ref&gt;Puaux, René (2009) [https://books.google.com/books?id=AFp5QKRGrtgC&amp;pg=PA16&amp;lpg=PA16&amp;dq=proclamation+Trotha+Herreros&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=5AA_ny-hHN&amp;sig=C-eOvxAILRVOCWDCUdwoc1MKxT4&amp;hl=pt-PT&amp;ei=AmR-TJizJ4SD4Qb4nYWzBw&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CBsQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=proclamation%20Trotha%20Herreros&amp;f=false ''The German Colonies; What Is to Become of Them?''], BiblioBazaar, Charleston, SC ISBN 978-1-113-34601-8&lt;/ref&gt;}}

He further gave orders that:

{{quote|This proclamation is to be read to the troops at roll-call, with the addition that the unit that catches a captain will also receive the appropriate reward, and that the shooting at women and children is to be understood as shooting above their heads, so as to force them to run [away]. I assume absolutely that this proclamation will result in taking no more male prisoners, but will not degenerate into atrocities against women and children. The latter will run away if one shoots at them a couple of times. The troops will remain conscious of the good reputation of the German soldier.&lt;ref name=hull/&gt;{{rp|56}}}}

Trotha gave orders that captured Herero males were to be executed, while women and children were to be driven into the desert where their death from starvation and thirst was to be certain; Trotha argued that there was no need to make exceptions for Herero women and children, since these would &quot;infect German troops with their diseases&quot;, the insurrection Trotha explained &quot;is and remains the beginning of a racial struggle&quot;.&lt;ref name=clark/&gt;{{rp|605}} Regardless, German soldiers regularly raped young Herero women before killing them or letting them die in the desert.&lt;ref&gt;Samuel Totten,Paul Robert Bartrop,Steven L. Jacobs (2007) ''Dictionary of Genocide: M-Z'', Greenwood&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|272}} After the war, Trotha argued that his orders were necessary, writing in 1909 that &quot;If I had made the small water holes accessible to the womenfolk, I would run the risk of an African catastrophe comparable to the [[Battle of Berezina|Battle of Beresonia]].&quot;&lt;ref name=totten/&gt;{{rp|22}}

The German general staff was aware of the atrocities that were taking place; its official publication, named ''Der Kampf'', noted that:
{{quote|This bold enterprise shows up in the most brilliant light the ruthless energy of the German command in pursuing their beaten enemy. No pains, no sacrifices were spared in eliminating the last remnants of enemy resistance. Like a wounded beast the enemy was tracked down from one water-hole to the next, until finally he became the victim of his own environment. The arid Omaheke [desert] was to complete what the German army had begun: the extermination of the Herero nation.&lt;ref&gt;Tilman Dedering, {{&quot;'}}A Certain Rigorous Treatment of all Parts of the Nation': The Annihilation of the Herero in German South West Africa, 1904&quot;, in Mark Levene; Penny Roberts (1999) ''The Massacre in History'', pp. 204–222, Berghahn Books, NY ISBN 978-1-57181-934-5&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Helmut Bley  (1971) ''South-West Africa under German rule, 1894–1914'', p. 162, Northwestern University Press, Evanston ISBN 978-0-8101-0346-7&lt;/ref&gt;}}

[[Alfred von Schlieffen]] (Chief of the [[German Empire|Imperial]] [[German General Staff]]) approved of Trotha's intentions in terms of a &quot;racial struggle&quot; and the need to &quot;wipe out the entire nation or to drive them out of the country&quot;, but had doubts about his strategy, preferring their surrender.&lt;ref&gt;Manus I. Midlarsky (2005) ''The Killing Trap: Genocide in the Twentieth Century'' [Hardcover]  p. 32, Cambridge University Press ISBN 978-0-511-13259-9&lt;/ref&gt;

Governor Leutwein, later relieved of his duties, complained to Chancellor von Bülow about Trotha's actions, seeing the general's orders as intruding upon the civilian colonial jurisdiction and ruining any chance of a political settlement.&lt;ref name=clark/&gt;{{rp|606}} According to Professor [[Mahmood Mamdani]] from [[Columbia University]], opposition to the policy of annihilation was largely the consequence of the fact that colonial officials looked at the Herero people as a potential source of labour, and thus economically important.&lt;ref name=mamdani/&gt;{{rp|12}} For instance, Governor Leutwein wrote that:
{{quote|I do not concur with those fanatics who want to see the Herero destroyed altogether&amp;nbsp;... I would consider such a move a grave mistake from an economic point of view. We need the Herero as cattle breeders&amp;nbsp;... and especially as labourers.&lt;ref name=gewald/&gt;{{rp|169}}}}

Having no authority over the military, Chancellor Bülow could only advise Emperor Wilhelm II that Trotha's actions were &quot;contrary to Christian and humanitarian principle, economically devastating and damaging to Germany's international reputation.&quot;&lt;ref name=clark/&gt;{{rp|606}}
Upon the arrival of new orders at the end of 1904, prisoners were herded into [[concentration camps]], where they were given to private companies as slave labourers or exploited as human guinea pigs in medical experiments.&lt;ref name=sarkin&gt;Jeremy Sarkin-Hughes (2008) ''Colonial Genocide and Reparations Claims in the 21st Century: The Socio-Legal Context of Claims under International Law by the Herero against Germany for Genocide in Namibia, 1904–1908'', p. 142, Praeger Security International, Westport, Conn. ISBN 978-0-313-36256-9&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Naomi Baumslag  (2005) ''Murderous Medicine: Nazi Doctors, Human Experimentation, and Typhus'', p. 37, Praeger Publishers, Westport, CT ISBN 978-0-275-98312-3&lt;/ref&gt;

===Concentration camps===
{{See also|Shark Island Concentration Camp}}
[[File:Herero chained.jpg|thumb|Herero chained during the 1904 rebellion]]
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-2003-0005, Deutsch-Südwest-Afrika, Kriegsgefangene Herero.jpg|thumb|Herero prisoners of war in 1904.]]
[[File:Blubk bluish.jpg|thumb|Cover of the 1918 British Bluebook, originally available through [[HMSO|His Majesty's Stationery Office]]. In 1926, except for archive copies, it was withdrawn and destroyed following a &quot;decision of the then Legislative Assembly&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.namibian.com.na/indexx.php?archive_id=52767&amp;page_type=archive_story_detail&amp;page=4465 {{&quot;'}}Stolen' Blue Book was just misplaced&quot;] (23 April 2009) ''The Namibian'', accessed 17 Dec 2011&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |last=Gewald, Jan-Bart |title=Herereo Heroes: A Socio-Political History of the Herero of Namibia 1890–1923 |publisher=Ohio University Press |year=1999 |page=242 |quote=&quot;Of late it has been claimed that the infamous 'Blue Book' which detailed the treatment of Africans in GSWA was little more than a piece of propaganda put about to further South Africa's territorial ambitions and Britain's position at the negotiating table. Granted that the book was used to strengthen Britain's position vis-a-vis Germany, it must however be borne in mind that the bulk of the evidence contained in the 'Blue Book' is little more than the literal translation of German texts published at the time which were the findings of a German commission of inquiry into the effects of corporal punishment.&quot; Thus, when the Blue Book was withdrawn from the public after Germany and England came to an agreement about how to share access to GSWA minerals, this was not censorship; it was just business}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Survivors of the massacre, the majority of whom were women and children, were eventually put in places like [[Shark Island Concentration Camp]], where the German authorities forced them to work as slave labour for German military and settlers. All prisoners were categorised into groups fit and unfit for work, and pre-printed death certificates indicating &quot;death by exhaustion following privation&quot; were issued.&lt;ref&gt;Wolfram Hartmann, Jeremy Silvester, Patricia Hayes (1999) ''The Colonising Camera: Photographs in the Making of Namibian History'', p. 118, University of Cape Town Press; Ohio University Press ISBN 978-1-919713-22-9&lt;/ref&gt; The British government published their well-known account of the German genocide of the Nama and Herero peoples in 1918.&lt;ref&gt;Jan-Bart Gewald, Jeremy Silvester (1 June 2003) ''Words Cannot Be Found: German Colonial Rule in Namibia : An Annotated Reprint of the 1918 Blue Book'' (Sources on African History, 1), Brill Academic Publishers, Leiden ISBN 978-90-04-12981-8&lt;/ref&gt;

Many Herero died later of disease, exhaustion, and malnutrition.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |title=The Dark Side of Democracy: Explaining Ethnic Cleansing |last=Michael Mann |page=105 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=New York|year=2004|isbn=978-0-521-83130-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|author=Raffael Scheck |title=Hitler's African Victims: The German Army Massacres of Black French Soldiers in 1940 |page=83 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |year=2006|isbn=978-0-521-85799-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Estimates of the mortality rate at the camps are between 45%&lt;ref name=&quot;HBV&quot;&gt;Clarence Lusane (2002) ''Hitler's Black Victims: The Historical Experiences of European Blacks, Africans and African Americans During the Nazi Era'' (Crosscurrents in African American History), pp. 50–51, Routledge, New York ISBN 978-0-415-93121-2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Helmut Walser Smith 2008 199&quot;&gt;{{citation |title=The Continuities of German History: Nation, Religion, and Race across the Long Nineteenth Century |author=Helmut Walser Smith |page=199 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |year=2008|isbn=978-0-521-89588-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; and 74%.&lt;ref name=Steinmetz/&gt;{{rp|196–216}}&lt;ref name=&quot;HBV&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Helmut Walser Smith 2008 199&quot;/&gt;

Food in the camps was extremely scarce, consisting of rice with no additions.&lt;ref name=rao&gt;Aparna Rao (2007) [https://books.google.com/books?id=c6Bo5vWPw4EC&amp;pg=PA92 ''The Practice of War: Production, Reproduction and Communication of Armed violence''], Berghahn Books ISBN 978-1-84545-280-3&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|92}} As the prisoners lacked pots and the rice they received was uncooked, it was indigestible; horses and oxen that died in the camp were later distributed to the inmates as food.&lt;ref name=hull/&gt;{{rp|75}} [[Dysentery]] and lung diseases were common.&lt;ref name=hull/&gt;{{rp|76}} Despite those conditions, the Herero were taken outside the camp every day for labour under harsh treatment by the German guards, while the sick were left without any medical assistance or nursing care.&lt;ref name=hull/&gt;{{rp|76}}

Shootings, hangings, beatings, and other harsh treatment of the forced labourers (including use of [[sjambok]]s) were common.&lt;ref name=hull/&gt;{{rp|76}}&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |title=Rethinking Resistance: Revolt and Violence in African History |page=282 |last=Klaas van Walraven |publisher=Brill Academic Publishers |year=2003|isbn=978-1-4175-0717-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; A 28 September 1905 article in the South African newspaper ''[[Cape Argus]]'' detailed some of the abuse with the heading: &quot;In German S. W. Africa: Further Startling Allegations: Horrible Cruelty&quot;. In an interview with Percival Griffith, &quot;an accountant of profession, who owing to hard times, took up on transport work at [[Angra Pequena]], [[Lüderitz]]&quot;, related his experiences.
{{quote|There are hundreds of them, mostly women and children and a few old men&amp;nbsp;... when they fall they are sjamboked by the soldiers in charge of the gang, with full force, until they get up&amp;nbsp;... On one occasion I saw a woman carrying a child of under a year old slung at her back, and with a heavy sack of grain on her head&amp;nbsp;... she fell. The corporal sjamboked her for certainly more than four minutes and sjamboked the baby as well&amp;nbsp;... the woman struggled slowly to her feet, and went on with her load. She did not utter a sound the whole time, but the baby cried very hard.&lt;ref name=&quot;preventgenocide&quot; /&gt;}}

During the war, a number of people from the [[Cape Province|Cape]] (in modern-day [[South Africa]]) sought employment as transport riders for German troops in Namibia. Upon their return to the Cape, some of these people recounted their stories, including those of the imprisonment and genocide of the Herero and Namaqua people. Fred Cornell, a British aspirant diamond prospector, was in Lüderitz when the Shark Island concentration camp was being used. Cornell wrote of the camp:
{{quote|Cold - for the nights are often bitterly cold there - hunger, thirst, exposure, disease and madness claimed scores of victims every day, and cartloads of their bodies were every day carted over to the back beach, buried in a few inches of sand at low tide, and as the tide came in the bodies went out, food for the sharks.&lt;ref name=&quot;preventgenocide&quot; /&gt;}}

Shark Island was the worst of the German South West African camps.&lt;ref&gt;Thomas Pakenham (1991) ''The Scramble for Africa, 1876–1912'', page 615, Random House, New York ISBN 978-0-394-51576-2&lt;/ref&gt; Lüderitz lies in southern Namibia, flanked by desert and ocean. In the harbour lies Shark Island, which then was connected to the mainland only by a small causeway. The island is now, as it was then, barren and characterised by solid rock carved into surreal formations by the hard ocean winds. The camp was placed on the far end of the relatively small island, where the prisoners would have suffered complete exposure to the strong winds that sweep Lüderitz for most of the year.

German Commander Von Estorff wrote in a report that approximately 1700 prisoners (including 1203 Nama) had died by April 1907. In December 1906, four months after their arrival, 291 Nama died (a rate of more than nine people per day). Missionary reports put the death rate at 12–18 per day; as many as 80% of the prisoners sent to Shark Island eventually died there.&lt;ref name=&quot;preventgenocide&quot;&gt;[http://www.preventgenocide.org/prevent/news-monitor/2001sept.htm News Monitor for September 2001] Prevent Genocide International&lt;/ref&gt;

There are accusations of Herero women being coerced into sex slavery as a means of survival.&lt;ref name=mamdani/&gt;{{rp|12}}&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |newspaper=Mail &amp; Guardian |date=13 March 1998 |url=http://www.raceandhistory.com/Science/germanynamibia.htm |title=The Tribe Germany Wants to Forget }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Trotha was opposed to contact between natives and settlers, believing that the insurrection was &quot;the beginning of a racial struggle&quot; and fearing that the colonists would be infected by native diseases.&lt;ref name=clark/&gt;{{rp|606}}

[[Benjamin Madley]] argues that although Shark Island is referred to as a concentration camp, it functioned as an extermination camp or death camp.&lt;ref&gt;Benjamin Madley (2005) &quot;From Africa to Auschwitz: How German South West Africa Incubated Ideas and Methods Adopted and Developed by the Nazis in Eastern Europe&quot;, ''European History Quarterly'' Vol. 35, pp. 429–432: &quot;Operational from 1905 to 1907,  Haifischinsel, or Shark Island, was the twentieth century's first death camp. Though referred to as a Konzentrationslager in Reichstag debates, it functioned as an extermination centre.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Madley, p. 446: &quot;Colonial Namibia's death camp at Shark Island was different from Spanish and British concentration camps in that it was operated for the purpose of destroying human life. Thus, it served as a rough model for later Nazi ''Vernichtungslager'', or annihilation camps, like Treblinka and Auschwitz, whose primary purpose was murder.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[Isabel V. Hull]] (2006) ''Absolute Destruction: Military, Culture And the Practices of War in Imperial Germany'', Cornell University Press, Ithaca, NY ISBN 978-0-8014-4258-2; see footnote #64, pp. 81–82:{{&quot;'}}Sterblichkeit in den Kriegsgefangenlargern,' Nr. KA II.1181, copy of undated report compiled by the Schutztruppe Command, read in Col. Dept. 24 Mar. 1908, BA-Berlin, R 1001. Nr. 2040, pp. 161–62. The other annual average death rates (for the period Oct. 1904 to Mar. 1907) were as follows: Okahandja, 37.2%; Windhuk, 50.4%; Swakopmund, 74%; Shark Island in Lüderitzbucht, 121.2% for Nama, 30% for Herero. Traugott Tjienda, headsman of the Herero at Tsumbe and foreman of a large group of prisoners at the Otavi lines for two years, testified years later to a death rate of 28% (148 dead of 528 labourers) in his unit, Union of South Africa, 'Report on the Natives', 101.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;

===Medical experiments and scientific racism===
{{Further information|Nazi eugenics|Racial hygiene|Scientific racism|Craniometry}}
Prisoners were used for medical experiments and their illness or recoveries was used for research &lt;ref&gt;German Colonialism: A Short History
Sebastian Conrad, page 129,Cambridge University Press 2008&lt;/ref&gt;

Experiments on live prisoners were made by Dr Bofinger, who injected Herero that were suffering from scurvy with various substances including arsenic and opium; afterwards he researched the effects of these substances via autopsy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=CSqc0CsnL-AC&amp;pg=PA226&amp;lpg=PA226&amp;dq=Dr+Bofinger+nazi&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=yj62aS24Bv&amp;sig=24WYGhPbwiJhF9iBXQJ7rhg8i7A&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=LEGgU6niOcXd4QS9wIC4Dg&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=Dr%20Bofinger%20nazi&amp;f=false|title=The Kaiser's Holocaust: Germany's Forgotten Genocide and the Colonial Roots of Nazism|page=225|author=Casper Erichsen; David Olusoga|publisher=Faber and Faber|year=2010|location=London|isbn=978-0-571-23141-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Experimentation with dead body parts of the prisoners was rife. Zoologist Leopard Schultze noted taking &quot;body parts from fresh native corpses&quot; for which was according to him a &quot;welcome addition&quot;, and that he could use prisoners for that purpose.&lt;ref&gt;H. Glenn Penny, Matti Bun (2003) ''Worldly Provincialism: German Anthropology in the Age of Empire'', p. 175, University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor ISBN 978-0-472-11318-7&lt;/ref&gt;

An estimated 300 skulls &lt;ref&gt;http://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-15127992&lt;/ref&gt; were sent to Germany for experimentation, in part from concentration camp prisoners.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.taz.de/Deutsche-Kolonialgeschichte/!5110825/|title=Der verleugnete Völkermord|date=29 September 2011|work=Die Tageszeitung}}&lt;/ref&gt; In October 2011, after 3 years of talks, the first 20 of an estimated 300 skulls stored in the museum of the [[Charité]] were returned to Namibia for burial.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nzz.ch/berliner-charite-schaedel-namibia-1.12737688|title=Schädel für die Rassenlehre|date=30 September 2011|work=Neue Zürcher Zeitung}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.timeslive.co.za/scitech/2011/09/27/germans-return-skulls-to-namibia|title=Germans return skulls to Namibia|date=27 September 2011|work=The Times}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2014, 14 additional skulls were repatriated by the University of Freiburg.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.pr.uni-freiburg.de/pm/2014/pm.2014-03-04.18-en|title=Repatriation of Skulls from Namibia University of Freiburg hands over human remains in ceremony|date=4 March 2014|publisher=University of Freiburg}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Number of victims===
A census performed in 1905 revealed that 25,000 Herero remained in [[German South-West Africa]].&lt;ref name=chalk&gt;Frank Robert Chalk, Kurt Jonassohn (1990) [https://books.google.com/books?id=UgzAi1DD75wC&amp;dq=The+history+and+sociology+of+genocide&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=EiRUTZfzEMSfOt3b_JMJ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCYQ6AEwAA ''The History and Sociology of Genocide : Analyses and Case Studies''],  Montreal Institute for Genocide Studies, Yale University Press 1990 ISBN 978-0-300-04446-1&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the ''Whitaker Report'', the population of 80,000 Herero was reduced to 15,000 &quot;starving refugees&quot; between 1904 and 1907.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.preventgenocide.org/prevent/UNdocs/whitaker/section5.htm UN Whitaker Report on Genocide, 1985, paragraphs 14 to 24, pages 5 to 10] Prevent Genocide International&lt;/ref&gt; In ''Colonial Genocide and Reparations Claims in the 21st Century'': ''The Socio-Legal Context of Claims under International Law by the Herero against Germany for Genocide in Namibia'' by Jeremy Sarkin-Hughes, a number of 100,000 victims is given. German author Walter Nuhn states that in 1904 only 40,000 Herero lived in German South-West Africa, and therefore &quot;only 24,000&quot; could have been killed.&lt;ref name=&quot;Walter Nuhn 1904&quot;/&gt;

Newspapers reported 65,000 victims when announcing that Germany recognized the genocide in 2004.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Germany admits Namibia genocide|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/3565938.stm|accessdate=20 February 2016|agency=BBC|date=14 August 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=German minister says sorry for genocide in Namibia|url=http://www.theguardian.com/world/2004/aug/16/germany.andrewmeldrum|accessdate=20 February 2016|agency=The Guardian|date=16 Aug 2004}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
[[File:Kirche denkmal nam.jpg|250px|thumb|right|Reiterdenkmal in [[Windhoek]] before its relocation in 2009]]
With the closure of concentration camps, all surviving Herero were distributed as labourers for settlers in the German colony. From that time on, all Herero over the age of seven were forced to wear a metal disc with their labour registration number,&lt;ref name=mamdani/&gt;{{rp|12}} and banned from owning land or cattle, a necessity for pastoral society.&lt;ref name=rao/&gt;{{rp|89}}

About 19,000 German troops were engaged in the conflict, of which 3,000 saw combat. The rest were used for upkeep and administration. The German losses were 676 soldiers killed in combat, 76 missing, and 689 dead from disease.&lt;ref name=hull/&gt;{{rp|88}} The [[Reiterdenkmal, Windhoek|Reiterdenkmal]] ({{lang-en|Equestrian Monument}}) in Windhoek was erected in 1912 to celebrate the victory and to remember the fallen Germans with no mention of the killed indigenous population. It remains a bone of contention in independent Namibia.&lt;ref name=&quot;centenary&quot;&gt;{{cite news
|url=http://www.namibian.com.na/news-articles/national/full-story/archive/2012/january/article/monuments-centenary-remembered/
|title=Monument's centenary remembered
|last=Bause
|first=Tanja
|date=30 January 2012
|newspaper=[[The Namibian]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The campaign had cost Germany 600 million marks. The normal annual subsidy to the colony was 14.5 million marks.&lt;ref name=hull/&gt;{{rp|88}}&lt;ref&gt;Klaus Epstein (1959) [http://www.jstor.org/discover/10.2307/558886?uid=3737864&amp;uid=2&amp;uid=4&amp;sid=21106532384193 &quot;Erzberger and the German Colonial Scandals&quot;], ''English Historical Review'', pp. 637–63&lt;/ref&gt; In 1908, [[diamond]]s were discovered in the territory, and this did much to boost its prosperity, though it was short-lived.&lt;ref name=chalk/&gt;{{rp|230}}

In 1915, at the start of [[World War I]], the German colony was taken over and occupied in the [[South-West Africa campaign|South-West Africa Campaign]] by the [[Union of South Africa]], acting on behalf of the [[British Empire|British Imperial Government]]. South Africa received a [[League of Nations Mandate]] over [[South-West Africa]] in 1919 under the [[Treaty of Versailles]].

===Recognition===
In 1985, the United Nations' [[Sub-Commission on the Promotion and Protection of Human Rights#Whitaker Report|Whitaker Report]] classified the massacres as an attempt to exterminate the Herero and Nama peoples of [[South-West Africa]], and therefore one of the earliest cases of genocide in the 20th century.&lt;ref&gt;Israel W. Charny (1999) ''Encyclopedia of Genocide'', pp. 288–289, ABC-CLIO, Santa Barbara, CA ISBN 978-0-87436-928-1&lt;!--forewords by Desmond M. Tutu and Simon Wiesenthal--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1998, German President [[Roman Herzog]] visited Namibia and met Herero leaders. [[Munjuku Nguvauva II|Chief Munjuku Nguvauva]] demanded a public apology and compensation. Herzog expressed regret but stopped short of an apology. He pointed out that international law requiring reparation did not exist in 1907, but he undertook to take the Herero petition back to the German government.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nytimes.com/1998/05/31/world/its-past-on-its-sleeve-tribe-seeks-bonn-s-apology.html &quot;Its Past on Its Sleeve, Tribe Seeks Bonn's Apology&quot;] (31 May 1998) ''New York Times'', p.3&lt;/ref&gt;

The Herero filed a lawsuit in the United States in 2001 demanding reparations from the German government and [[Deutsche Bank]], which financed the German government and companies in Southern Africa.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/3388901.stm|title = Germany regrets Namibia 'genocide'|publisher = [[BBC News]]|date = 2004-01-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/business/1561463.stm|title = German bank accused of genocide|publisher = [[BBC News]]|date = 2001-09-25}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 16 August 2004, at the 100th anniversary of the start of the genocide, a member of the German government, [[Heidemarie Wieczorek-Zeul]], Germany's [[Federal Ministry for Economic Cooperation and Development (Germany)|Minister for Economic Development and Cooperation]], officially apologised and expressed grief about the genocide, declaring in a speech that:
{{quote|We Germans accept our historical and moral responsibility and the guilt incurred by Germans at that time.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.windhuk.diplo.de/Vertretung/windhuk/en/03/Commemorative__Years__2004__2005/Seite__Speech__2004-08-14__BMZ.html|title = Speech at the commemorations of the 100th anniversary of the suppression of the Herero uprising, Okakarara, Namibia, 14 August 2004|publisher = Deutsche Botshaft Windhuk/German Embassy in Windhuk|date = 2004-08-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

She ruled out paying special compensations, but promised continued economic aid for Namibia which currently amounts to $14M a year.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC08142004&quot; /&gt;

The Trotha family travelled to [[Omaruru, Namibia|Omaruru]] in October 2007 by invitation of the royal Herero chiefs and publicly apologised for the actions of their relative. Wolf-Thilo von Trotha said,
{{quote|We, the von Trotha family, are deeply ashamed of the terrible events that took place 100 years ago. Human rights were grossly abused that time.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/7033042.stm|title = German family's Namibia apology|publisher = [[BBC News]]|date = 2007-10-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Repatriation===

Peter Katjavivi, a former Namibian ambassador to Germany, demanded in August 2008 that the skulls of Herero and Nama prisoners of the 1904–08 uprising, which were taken to Germany for scientific research to &quot;prove&quot; the superiority of white Europeans over Africans, be returned to Namibia. Katjavivi was reacting to a German television documentary which reported that its investigators had found over 40 of these skulls at two German universities, among them probably the skull of a Nama chief who had died on Shark Island near Lüderitz.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.namibian.com.na/indexx.php?archive_id=44655&amp;page_type=archive_story_detail&amp;page=5161 &quot;Katjavivi demands Herero skulls from Germany&quot;], (24 July 2008) ''The Namibian''&lt;/ref&gt; In September 2011 the skulls were returned to Namibia.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-15127992|title = Germany returns Namibian skulls|publisher = [[BBC News]]|date = 2011-10-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Media===
*A BBC Documentary [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IEUc1lAA1k4 ''Namibia - Genocide &amp; the second reich''] explores the Herero/Nama genocide and the circumstances surrounding it.
*In the documentary {{YouTube|l3P_gvFVuXA|''100 Years of Silence''}}, filmmakers Halfdan Muurholm and Casper Erichsen portray a 23-year-old Herero woman, who is aware of the fact that her great-grandmother was raped by a German soldier. The documentary explores the past and the way Namibia deals with it now.&lt;ref&gt;{{YouTube|l3P_gvFVuXA|&quot;Documentary 100 Years of Silence&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*''Mama Namibia'', a historical novel by Mari Serebrov, provides two perspectives of the 1904 genocide in German South-West Africa. The first is that of Jahohora, a 12-year-old Herero girl who survives on her own in the veld for two years after her family is killed by German soldiers. The second story in ''Mama Namibia'' is that of Kov, a Jewish doctor who volunteered to serve in the German military to prove his patriotism. As he witnesses the atrocities of the genocide, he rethinks his loyalty to the Fatherland.&lt;ref&gt;Serebrov, Mari (2013) ''Mama Namibia'', Windhoek, Namibia: Wordweaver Publishing House ISBN 978-99916-889-6-1&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[Thomas Pynchon]]'s novel ''[[V.]]'' (1963) had a chapter set in [[Shark Island Concentration Camp]] in 1904.
*Jackie Sibblies Drury's play, ''We Are Proud To Present a Presentation About the Herero of Namibia, Formerly Known as Southwest Africa, From the German Sudwestafrika, Between the Years 1884–1915'', is about a group of actors developing a play about the Herero and Namaqua Genocide.&lt;ref&gt;J.S. Drury (2014) [http://www.amazon.com/Present-Presentation-Formerly-Southwest-Sudwestafrika/dp/1472585097 ''We are Proud&amp;nbsp;...''], Bloomsbury Methuen Drama ISBN 978-1-4725-8509-7&lt;/ref&gt;

===Continuity between the Herero genocide and the Holocaust===
{{refimprove section|date=June 2014}}The Herero genocide has commanded the attention of historians who study complex issues of continuity between the Herero genocide and the [[Holocaust]].&lt;ref&gt;David Johnson; Prem Poddar (2008) ''A Historical Companion to Postcolonial Literatures — Continental Europe and its Empires'', p. 240, Edinburgh University Press ISBN 978-0-7486-3602-0&lt;/ref&gt; It is argued that the Herero genocide set a precedent in Imperial Germany that would later be followed by [[Nazi Germany]]'s establishment of [[Extermination camp|death camps]].&lt;ref&gt;Andrew Zimmerman (2001) ''Anthropology and antihumanism in Imperial Germany'', p. 244, University of Chicago Press ISBN 978-0-226-98346-2&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.socialistaction.org/news/199904/Namibia.html |title=Imperialism and Genocide in Namibia |work=[[Socialist Action (United States)|Socialist Action]] |date=April 1999 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to Benjamin Madley, the German experience in South West Africa was a crucial precursor to Nazi colonialism and genocide. He argues that personal connections, literature, and public debates served as conduits for communicating colonialist and genocidal ideas and methods from the colony to Germany.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |author=Benjamin Madley |title=From Africa to Auschwitz: How German South West Africa Incubated Ideas and Methods Adopted and Developed by the Nazis in Eastern Europe |journal=European History Quarterly |year=2005 |volume=35 |issue=3 |pages=429–64 |doi=10.1177/0265691405054218}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tony Barta, an honorary research associate at [[La Trobe University#Melbourne (Bundoora)|La Trobe University]], argues that the Herero genocide was an inspiration for [[Adolf Hitler|Hitler]] in his war against the [[Jews]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Identity Politics in the Age of Genocide: The Holocaust and Historical Representation|page=97|author=David B. MacDonald|year=2007|publisher=Routledge|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=X5d8AgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT66&amp;source=gbs_toc_r&amp;cad=3#v=snippet&amp;q=Herero%20Genocide&amp;f=false|isbn=1-134-08571-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to [[Clarence Lusane]], [[Eugen Fischer]]'s medical experiments can be seen as a testing ground for later medical procedures used during the Nazi Holocaust.&lt;ref name=&quot;HBV&quot;/&gt; Fischer later became chancellor of the University of Berlin, where he taught medicine to Nazi physicians. [[Otmar Freiherr von Verschuer]] was a student of Fischer, Verschuer himself had a prominent pupil, [[Josef Mengele]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|url=http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/bulletin_of_the_history_of_medicine/summary/v085/85.3.kater.html|title=The Nazi Symbiosis: Human Genetics and Politics in the Third Reich|author=Michael H. Kater|year=2011|journal=Bulletin of the History of Medicine|doi=10.1353/bhm.2011.0067|volume=85|pages=515–516}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=IjUUAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA41&amp;lpg=PA41&amp;dq=joseph+mengele+eugen+fischer&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=WQ-dst-Oon&amp;sig=SH-hI4ZcrjXbZh18ilJUYzl_cwY&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=p52gU9vODoTf4QSbrYHgAw&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=Otmar%20von%20Verschuer&amp;f=false|title=Sterilized by the State: Eugenics, Race, and the Population Scare in Twentieth-Century North America|author=Randall Hansen, Desmond King|year=2013|publisher=Cambridge University Press|page=158|isbn=1-107-43459-9}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Franz Ritter von Epp]], who was later responsible for the liquidation of virtually all Bavarian Jews and [[Romani people|Roma]]{{dubious|not supported by wikibio|date=September 2012}}&lt;!--You'll have to take it up with Kiernan because that's what he writes in his book. Scroll to p. 36 in the Google Books link--&gt; as governor of Bavaria, took part in the Herero genocide as well.&lt;ref&gt;Ben Kiernan (2007) [https://books.google.com/books?id=XR91bs70jukC ''Blood and Soil, a World History of Genocide and Extermination from Sparta to Darfur''], p. 36, Yale University Press ISBN 978-0-300-10098-3&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Mahmood Mamdani]] argues that the links between the Holocaust and the Herero genocide are beyond the execution of an annihilation policy and the establishment of concentration camps and that there are ideological similarities in the conduct of both genocides. Focusing on a written statement by General Trotha translated as:
{{quote|I destroy the African tribes with streams of blood&amp;nbsp;... Only following this cleansing can something new emerge, which will remain.&lt;ref name=gewald/&gt;{{rp|174}}}}

Mamdani takes note of the similarity between the aims of the General and the Nazis. According to Mamdani in both cases there was a [[Social Darwinism|Social Darwinist]] notion of &quot;cleansing&quot;, after which &quot;something new&quot; would &quot;emerge&quot;.&lt;ref name=mamdani/&gt;{{rp|12}}

==See also==
{{Portal|Human rights|Namibia|Germany}}
* [[Genocides in history]]
* [[List of genocides by death toll]]
* [[Research Materials: Max Planck Society Archive]]

==Original German texts==
{{Reflist|group=DE}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Bibliography and documentaries==
* [http://faculty.unlv.edu/anderson/ Rachel Anderson], [http://faculty.unlv.edu/anderson/publications/hererogenocide.html ''Redressing Colonial Genocide Under International Law: The Hereros' Cause of Action Against Germany''], 93 California Law Review 1155 (2005).
* ''Exterminate all the Brutes'', [[Sven Lindqvist]], London, 1996.
* ''A Forgotten History-Concentration Camps were used by Germans in South West Africa'', Casper W. Erichsen, in the ''Mail and Guardian'', Johannesburg, 17 August 2001.
* ''Genocide &amp; The Second Reich'', [[BBC Four]], [[David Olusoga]], October 2004
* German Federal Archives, Imperial Colonial Office, Vol. 2089, 7 (recto)
* &quot;The Herero and Nama Genocides, 1904–1908&quot;, J.B. Gewald, in ''Encyclopedia of Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity'', New York, Macmillan Reference, 2004.
* ''Herero Heroes: A Socio-Political History of the Herero of Namibia 1890–1923'', J.B. Gewald, Oxford, Cape Town, Athens, OH, 1999.
* ''Let Us Die Fighting: the Struggle of the Herero and Nama against German Imperialism, 1884–1915'', Horst Drechsler, London, 1980.
* [[Isabel V. Hull|Hull, Isabel]] (2005) &quot;The Military Campaign in German Southwest Africa, 1904–1907. ''Bulletin of the German Historical Institute'' Issue 37, pp. 39–49.
* Zimmerer, Jürgen (2005) &quot;Annihilation in Africa: The 'Race War' in German Southwest Africa (1904–1908) and its Significance for a Global History of Genocide.&quot; ''Bulletin of the German Historical Institute'' Issue 37, pp.&amp;nbsp;51–57.
* Absolute Destruction: Military Culture And the Practices of War in Imperial Germany by Isabel V. Hull Cornell University Press 2006
* [[Mohamed Adhikari]], &quot;'Streams Of Blood And Streams Of Money': New Perspectives on the Annihilation of the Herero and Nama Peoples Of Namibia, 1904–1908,&quot; Kronos: Journal Of Cape History 2008 34: 303–320
* The war and massacre is significantly featured in ''The Glamour of Prospecting'', a contemporary account by Frederick Cornell of his attempts to prospect for diamonds in the region.  In the book he describes his first hand accounts of witnessing the concentration camp on Shark Island and other aspects of the genocide. {{cite book | url=https://archive.org/details/glamourprospect00corngoog | title=The Glamour of Prospecting: Wanderings of a South African Prospector in Search Of Copper, Gold, Emeralds, and Diamonds | publisher=T. Fisher Unwin Ltd | author=Fred C. Cornell | year=1920 | location=London}}

== External links ==
{{commons category|Herero and Namaqua Revolt}}
* [http://www.windhuk.diplo.de/Vertretung/windhuk/en/03/Commemorative__Years__2004__2005/Seite__Speech__2004-08-14__BMZ.html Official German apologies]

{{German colonial campaigns}}
{{Genocide topics}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Herero And Namaqua Genocide}}
[[Category:Herero and Namaqua genocide| ]]
[[Category:1904 in Africa]]
[[Category:1904 in German South-West Africa]]
[[Category:African resistance to colonialism]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1904]]
[[Category:Ethnic cleansing in Africa]]
[[Category:Genocide of indigenous peoples]]
[[Category:Genocides]]
[[Category:German South-West Africa]]
[[Category:German war crimes]]
[[Category:Germany–Namibia relations]]
[[Category:Guerrilla wars]]
[[Category:Herero people]]
[[Category:Herero Wars]]
[[Category:History of colonialism]]
[[Category:Medical experimentation on prisoners]]
[[Category:Rebellions in Africa]]
[[Category:Wars involving Germany]]</text>
      <sha1>dbtdefb5298o5mr4n8s7up6xdwb8o25</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
