<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>HMS Alarm (1758)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>14257984</id>
    <revision>
      <id>739098740</id>
      <parentid>739063018</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-12T19:32:36Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Acad Ronin</username>
        <id>70274</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Off America */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="11633">{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2012}}
{|{{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
|Ship image= 
|Ship caption=
}}
{{Infobox ship career
|Hide header=
|Ship country=Great Britain
|Ship flag=[[Image:British-White-Ensign-1707.svg|60px|RN Ensign]]
|Ship name=HMS ''Alarm''
|Ship ordered=
|Ship builder=Barnard, [[Harwich]]
|Ship laid down=
|Ship launched=19 September 1758
|Ship acquired=
|Ship commissioned=
|Ship decommissioned=
|Ship in service=
|Ship out of service=
|Ship renamed=
|Ship struck=
|Ship reinstated=
|Ship honours=
|Ship captured=
|Ship fate=Broken up September 1812
|Ship status=
|Ship notes=
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
|Hide header=
|Header caption=
|Ship class=[[Niger class frigate|''Niger''-class]] [[fifth-rate]] [[sailing frigate|frigate]]
|Ship tons burthen=683 [[Builder's Old Measurement|bm]]
|Ship length={{convert|125|ft|m|abbr=on}}
|Ship beam={{convert|35|ft|6|in|m|abbr=on}}
|Ship draught=
|Ship draft=
|Ship hold depth=
|Ship sail plan=[[Full-rigged ship]]
|Ship propulsion=
|Ship complement=
|Ship armament=*Upperdeck: 26 × 12-pounder guns
*[[Quarterdeck|QD]]: 4 × 6-pounder guns
*[[Forecastle|Fc]]: 2 × 6-pounder guns
|Ship notes=
}}
|}
{{otherships|HMS Alarm}}

'''HMS ''Alarm''''' was a 32-gun [[fifth rate]] [[Niger class frigate|''Niger''-class]] [[frigate]] of the [[Royal Navy]], and was the first Royal Navy ship to bear this name.  [[Copper sheathing|Copper-sheathed]] in 1761, she was the first ship in the Royal Navy to have a fully copper-sheathed hull.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/systems/ship/copper-sheathing.htm  Copper sheathing], Global Security.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.oldcopper.org/victory%20copper.htm Oldcopper.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
===Experiments with copper sheathing===
''Alarm'' initially saw deployment in the [[West Indies]], where she experimentally had her hull sheathed in a thin layer of copper.  Firstly it was intended to reduce the considerable damage caused by the [[Teredo navalis|teredo woodworm]] , and secondly the well-established toxic property of copper was expected to lessen the speed-killing [[barnacle]] growth which always occurred on ships' hulls.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.corrosion-doctors.org/Corrosion-History/Lessons.htm Historic corrosion lessons]&lt;/ref&gt;  ''Alarm''’s hull was first covered with soft stuff, which was hair, yarn and brown paper, and then covered with a layer of copper plates.

After a two-year deployment to the West Indies, ''Alarm'' was beached in order to examine the effects of the experiment. The copper had performed very well in protecting the hull from invasion by worm, and in preventing the growth of weed, for when in contact with water, the copper produced a poisonous film, composed mainly of oxychloride, that deterred these marine creatures. Furthermore, as this film was slightly soluble it gradually washed away, leaving no way in which marine life could attach itself to the ship.  Satisfied that the copper had had the desired effect, the [[Admiralty]] introduced copper sheathing on a number of frigates.

In 1776 ''Alarm'' was resurveyed.  It was soon discovered that the sheathing had become detached from the hull in many places because the iron nails which had been used to fasten the copper to the timbers had been ‘much rotted’. Closer inspection revealed that some nails, which were less corroded, were insulated from the copper by brown paper which was trapped under the nail head. The copper had been delivered to the dockyard wrapped in the paper which was not removed before the sheets were nailed to the hull. The obvious conclusion therefore, and the one which had been highlighted in a separate report to the Admiralty in as early as 1763, was that iron should not be allowed direct contact with copper in a sea water environment if severe corrosion of the iron was to be avoided. Later ships were designed with this in mind.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bruzelius.info/nautica/shipbuilding/Peacock(1874)_p5.html On the Preservation of the Bottom of Iron Ships]&lt;/ref&gt; The Admiralty had largely suspended the programme of fitting ships with copper sheathing after the 1763 report, and had not shown any further interest in developing effective copper sheathing until 1775.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.se/~pa/publ/pallas.pdf History of HMS Pallas and her class]&lt;/ref&gt; In the meantime the copper sheathing was removed from ''Alarm'', and several other test vessels until an effective solution to the corrosion problem could be developed.

Later in her career she was commanded by a young [[John Jervis, 1st Earl of St Vincent|John Jervis]], from 1769 onwards.  He sailed for the Mediterranean in May and arrived in [[Genoa]] on 7 September.  Aboard ''Alarm'' at this time was Samuel Hood, son of [[Alexander Hood (Royal Navy officer)|Alexander Hood]], and one of the many members of the [[Sir Samuel Hood, 1st Baronet|Hood family]] to serve at sea.  Samuel Hood served aboard ''Alarm'' from November 1765 to July 1772, in the post of [[purser]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hmshood.com/history/family.htm History of the Hood family]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Near loss===
On the return voyage to England, on 6 April 1770,&lt;ref name=LL170470&gt;{{cite journal |url=http://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015010961657;view=1up;seq=68 |title=(untitled) |journal=Lloyd's List |issue=3568 |date=17 April 1770 }}&lt;/ref&gt; she was saved by [[Georges René Le Peley de Pléville]] from being wrecked off [[Marseilles]].  The ''Alarm'' had been battered by a storm in the evening and ran aground on the coast of [[Provence]] amongst boulders, and was in imminent danger of breaking up.  Pléville quickly mustered the harbour pilots and rushed to the relief of the English.  By the time he was able to board her, the ''Alarm'' had already almost heeled over many times, and began to run aground.  Pléville ordered a manœuvre that got her afloat again and brought her into harbour at Marseilles.  In gratitude for Pléville's actions, the [[Admiralty]] sent Jervis and ''Alarm'' back to Marseilles in December to deliver a letter which read

{{quote |Sir, the quality of the service which you have rendered to the frigate Alarm gives rise to the noble envy and admiration of the English. Your courage, your prudence, your intelligence, your talents have merited a crown on your efforts from Providence. Success has been your reward, but we pray you to accept as a homage rendered to your merit and as a pledge of our esteem and recognition, that which captain Jervis is charged with rendering back to you. In the name and order of my lords, Stephans}}

The present was a piece of [[wikt:silverware|silverware]] in the form of an [[urn]], on which were engraved [[dolphin]]s and other maritime attributes, with a model of the ''Alarm'', and a richly engraved lid surmounted by a [[Triton (mythology)|triton]]. Remarkable in its elegance of form and high level of finish and workmanship, this vase bore the [[English Coat of Arms]], and had the following inscription, intended to preserve the memory of the event which had merited the present:

{{quote|Georgio-Renato Pleville Le Pelley, nobili normano Grandivillensi, navis bellicœ portusque Massiliensis pro prœfecto, ob navim regiam in litiore gallico pericli - tantem virtute diligentiâque suâ servatam septem vin rei navalis Britannicœ. M.DCCLXX. ([Presented] to Georges-René Pléville Le Pelley, noble [[Normans|Norman]] of Granville, commander of a warship and of the port of Marseilles, because he saved from destruction a Royal Navy vessel which was about to be lost on the French coast - the seven lords of the British Admiralty [presented] this [for] the great courage and diligence he showed.  1770)}}

Thinking that he could not receive a gift from a foreign sovereign, de Pléville only accepted the urn after having been duly authorised to do so by the king of France.  Jervis was also extremely grateful to de Pléville, and eager for the chance to reward him.  He wrote to his sister from ''Alarm'', anchored at [[Mahón|Mahon]] on 27 December 1770:

{{quote |I was twenty-four hours in the Bay of Marseilles, about a fortnight ago; just time enough to receive the warm embraces of the man to whose bravery and friendship I had, some months before, been indebted for my reputation, the preservation of the lives of the people under my command, and of the Alarm.  You would have felt infinite pleasure at the scene of our interview.&lt;ref&gt;Memoirs of the Admiral the Right Hon&lt;s&gt;r&lt;/s&gt; The Earl of St. Vincent, G.C.B. &amp; C.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Ten years later, de Pléville's devotion to the safety of the ''Alarm'' gained another reward, when his son — a young naval officer — was captured on board a frigate at the end of a battle in 1780 and taken to England. There, the British Admiralty sent him back to France without requiring a prisoner-exchange, after having authorised him to choose three other French naval officers to go with him.

The Admiralty were also greatly pleased by Jervis’ actions in this matter, allowing his further promotion. From 1771 to May 1772, the ship became the “home” of the [[Prince William Henry, Duke of Gloucester and Edinburgh|Duke of Gloucester]], who was spending time in the [[Mediterranean]] because of ill health. ''Alarm'' then returned to England for paying off.

===Off America===
On 9 March 1783, ''Alarm'' was involved in one of the last naval battles of the [[American Revolutionary War]], when ''Alarm'', {{HMS|Sibyl|1779|2}} and the [[sloop-of-war|sloop of war]] {{HMS|Tobago|1777|2}} intercepted two American frigates, [[USS Alliance (1778)|USS ''Alliance'']] and [[USS Duc de Lauzun (1782)|USS ''Duc de Lauzun'']]. The American ships were transporting [[bullion]] to the [[United States|Continental forces]] and both sides were unaware that peace had been ratified over a month before. After a short battle between ''Sibyl'' and the American ships, the Americans escaped. ''Alarm'' did not actively participate in the battle herself.

In 1796, ''Alarm'' violated [[Trinidad]]’s neutrality, so contributing to [[Spain]]’s declaration of war on the side of [[Revolutionary France]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://pantrinbago.com/Histdic2.htm Trinidad history]&lt;/ref&gt; In February 1797, ''Alarm'' was among the vessels of the British flotilla that [[Invasion of Trinidad (1797)|captured Trinidad]].

==Fate==

''Alarm'' shared with {{HMS|Amphion|1798|2}} in the head-money that was finally paid in March 1829,&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|date=24 February 1829|issue=18553|startpage=353}}&lt;/ref&gt; for the capture of a Spanish gunboat, ''Nuestra Senora del Corvodorvya'' (alias ''Asturiana''), on 25 November 1799. 

''Alarm'' continued in service for a number of years, finally being broken up in September 1812 at [[Portsmouth]] having spent 34 years in service.

==Citations and references==
;Citations
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}
;References
*{{Colledge}}
* Brian Lavery, ''The Ship of the Line — Volume 1: The development of the battlefleet 1650–1850.'' Conway Maritime Press, 2003. ISBN 0-85177-252-8.
* Robert Gardiner, ''The First Frigates'', Conway Maritime Press, London 1992. ISBN 0-85177-601-9.
* David Lyon, ''The Sailing Navy List'', Conway Maritime Press, London 1993. ISBN 0-85177-617-5.
* Rif Winfield, ''[[British Warships in the Age of Sail]], 1714 to 1792'', Seaforth Publishing, London 2007. ISBN 978-1-84415-700-6.
*[http://www.royalnavalmuseum.org/info_sheets_john_jervis.htm Biography: John Jervis at the Royal Navy Museum website]

{{Niger class frigate}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Alarm (1758)}}
[[Category:Frigates of the Royal Navy]]
[[Category:Harwich-built ships]]
[[Category:1758 ships]]
[[Category:Maritime incidents in 1770]]</text>
      <sha1>coklhhf64jinfl2kahjv6stbwrer7ke</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
