<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>HSC-14</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>21647602</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738430483</id>
      <parentid>722345267</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-08T22:30:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>97.121.142.193</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* 2013 */ created links for NAF Atsugi, NAS North Island and the MH-60S. Added info regarding current CVW and CVN assignment</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20858">{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2013}}
{{Refimprove|date=April 2009}}
{{Infobox military unit
|unit_name=Helicopter Sea Combat Squadron 14 
|image= [[File:Helicopter Sea Combat Squadron 14 (US Navy) emblem 2015.png|200px]]
|caption= HSC-14 insignia
|dates= 10 July 1984 - present
|country= {{flag|United States of America}}
|allegiance=
|branch= {{nowrap|[[File:United States Department of the Navy Seal.svg|30px|United States Navy Seal]] [[United States Navy]]}}
|type= Helicopter Squadron
|role=
|size= 250 Personnel
|command_structure= [[CVW-9]]
|current_commander= Commander Edward Weiler 
|garrison= [[Naval Air Station North Island]]
|ceremonial_chief=
|colonel_of_the_regiment=
|nickname= &quot;Chargers&quot;
|patron=
|motto= &quot;Day and Night, Lightning Strikes!&quot;
|colors= Blue / Gold
|march=
|mascot=
|battles=


|anniversaries=
}}

Helicopter Sea Combat Squadron 14 (HSC-14) &quot;Chargers&quot; is an aviation unit of the [[United States Navy]] based at at [[Naval Air Station North Island]], [[California]] [[United States of America|(USA)]]. HSC-14 was established as Helicopter Anti-Submarine Squadron 14 (HS-14) in 1984 and was redesignated HSC-14 in 2013. The squadron is equipped with the [[Sikorsky SH-60 Seahawk|Sikorsky MH-60S Seahawk]].

== Mission ==
HSC-14 flies the MH-60S Seahawk helicopter, an all-weather, day and night multi-mission helicopter. The primary mission of the squadron is [[Anti-Surface Warfare]](ASUW). Additionally, the squadron is trained and equipped to conduct [[Search and rescue]] (SAR), [[MEDEVAC]], [[Combat Search and Rescue]] (CSAR), [[United States Navy SEALs|Naval Special Warfare operations (NSW)]], Anti-ship Missile Defense (ASMD) and Fleet Logistics support, including [[VERTREP]].

== Command history ==
HS-14 was established on 10 July 1984 at [[Naval Air Station North Island]] in San Diego, California and originally flew the Sikorsky [[SH-3 Sea King|SH-3H &quot;Sea King&quot;]] helicopter. Assigned to [[CVW-2|Carrier Air Wing TWO]] from 1984 to 1993, the Chargers deployed aboard the [[USS Ranger (CV-61)]]. In 1989, while deployed off the coast of Vietnam in the South China Sea, HS-14 participated in one of the largest rescue operations ever by a deployed helicopter squadron when they rescued 37 Vietnamese refugees who were trapped aboard a foundering boat.

[[File:SH-3H Sea Kings HS-14 in flight 1990.JPEG|thumb|left|SH-3H Sea Kings of HS-14 in 1990.]]

In 1991, HS-14 participated in [[Gulf War#Operation Desert Shield|Operation Desert Shield]] and [[Gulf War|Desert Storm]]. During Desert Storm, the Chargers participated in an operation that resulted in the capture of four Iraqi commandos on a small island off the coast of Kuwait. Additionally, HS-14 played an important role in the destruction of one Iraqi gunboat and two anti-shipping mines. In 1992, the squadron deployed in support of Operation [[Operation Southern Watch|SOUTHERN WATCH]] to the Northern Persian Gulf and to the coast of Somalia in support of Operation [[Unified Task Force|RESTORE HOPE]]. In December 1992, the squadron surged to support the first eleven days of Operation RESTORE HOPE with such determination and efficiency that the operational commander wrote, &quot;without HS-14, the first ten days of RESTORE HOPE simply could not have happened.&quot;

In May 1993, the squadron moved 175 men and women, seven aircraft, and all their support equipment from San Diego to [[Mayport, Florida]] in four days. The cross-country move was executed to embark on board the [[USS Constellation (CV-64)]] for her transit around South America to San Diego. During this transit, the squadron participated in coordinated ASW with several South American navies.

In October 1993, the Chargers began the transition from the Sea King to the [[Sikorsky SH-60 Seahawk|SH-60F Seahawk]] helicopter. Soon afterward, military downsizing dictated the decommissioning of HS-12, a sister squadron in Japan. For HS-14, this meant an accelerated transition schedule and training program to complete a homeport change to Atsugi, Japan by October 1994. The squadron's progress in this endeavor was rewarded with a personal visit from then [[Chief of Naval Operations]], Admiral Frank B. Kelso.

HS-14 executed back-to-back deployments to the [[Persian Gulf]] in 1998 and 1999, participating in [[Operation Southern Watch|Operation SOUTHERN WATCH]]. Additionally, the squadron began its annual participation in the bilateral exercises [[FOAL EAGLE]] and [[ANNUALEX]] . In 1998, the Chargers made the {{USS|Kitty Hawk|CV-63|2}} their permanent sea-based home, traveling to Hawaii aboard the {{USS|Independence|CV-62}} in July for the complicated cross-deck move.

[[File:SH-60F Seahawk HS-14 dropping torpedo 1996.jpg|thumb|A HS-14 SH-60F Seahawk drops a torpedo in 1996.]]

In early 2002, the HS-14 supported [[Operation Enduring Freedom]] in Afghanistan by deploying a detachment on board USS ''Kitty Hawk''. During this deployment, ''Kitty Hawk'' served as a mobile staging base for elite U. S. Army special operations units. In March 2003, as the situation in Iraq escalated, HS-14 and ''Kitty Hawk'' received orders to participate in Operation [[2003 invasion of Iraq|IRAQI FREEDOM]]. The Chargers were assigned to provide an [[United States Navy SEALs|NSW]] capability to forward operating bases in support of SEAL operations. The squadron also affected the recovery of a [[CVW-5]] strike fighter pilot who was downed in hostile territory.

After returning from the Persian Gulf, HS-14 participated in several training and operational deployments, including the historic PULSE EX 2004. This exercise represented a shift in naval policy from set &quot;work-up&quot; periods and deployment schedules to a rapid-responding, surge capable force. During PULSE EX the Navy deployed six carriers simultaneously around the world to demonstrate the projection of power available under the new doctrine. It was during this deployment that an [[S-3 Viking|S-3B Viking]] from [[CVW-14]] crashed on the remote and rugged island of Kita Iwo Jima. HS-14 deployed two Seahawks within three hours to Iwo Jima to conduct search and recovery operations. Working closely with USAF Pararescuemen from the 33rd RQS, the {{USS|Lake Champlain|CG-57}} and the {{USS|Gary|FFG-51}}, HS-14 was able to locate the wreckage, salvage parts of the aircraft and return the remains of the Viking crew. This accomplishment was noted in a personal letter from President Bush to the wife of one of the fallen aviators.

In the fall of 2004, an HS-14 detachment deployed two HH-60H helicopters on board the {{USNS|GySgt. Fred W. Stockham|T-AK-3017}} in support of Operation [[Operation Enduring Freedom – Philippines|Enduring Freedom Philippines]]. The overall effort proved to be a success and established the HS community as a leading participant in the [[Global War on Terrorism]]. In the first week of December 2004, typhoons Imbudo and Namando struck the Philippines, causing extensive damage. Helicopters of HS-14 provided humanitarian assistance. The squadron was able to provide immediate relief to the most stricken victims of the typhoons and rescue over 100 refugees. At the same time, another HS-14 detachment was deployed on board the guided-missile cruiser {{USS|Vincennes|CG-49}} to support several 7th Fleet ASW exercises, operating in conjunction with the [[Japan Maritime Self-Defense Force|Japanese Maritime Self-Defense Force]] (JMSDF). Additionally, the squadron operated a third detachment out of Atsugi, Japan.

After being deployed or detached eleven out of twelve months in 2004, the HS-14 operated from {{USS|Kitty Hawk|CV-63}} in January 2005, operating off the southeast coast of Japan. In February 2005, the squadron deployed for routine training operations in the Okinawa Fleet Operations Areas. Simultaneously, HS-14 deployed a one-plane detachment and 18 personnel to the destroyer {{USS|Cushing|DD-985}} to operate with Destryoer Squadron 15 in bilateral ASW operations with the [[South Korean Navy]].

After some rest and relaxation in Hong Kong, {{USS|Kitty Hawk|CV-63|6}} headed north toward Korea for Operation [[Foal Eagle]]. HS-14 spent most of the year deployed and participating in exercises such as Talisman Saber, [[Orange Crush]], [[JASEX]], [[SHAREM]], [[MULTI-SAIL]], and ANNUALEX.

==2006==
June 2006 marked the start of another eventful summer deployment aboard the {{USS|Kitty Hawk|CV-63|6}} for HS-14. Before deploying, HS-14 earned the &quot;Golden Wrench Award&quot; for having the most outstanding maintenance department in the airwing. This marked the third time the Chargers had taken home the award, more than any other squadron in CVW-5. With maintenance operating at full potential and the flight crews ready to fight, the Chargers were ready to start the cruise.

The deployment began with a short port call to Otaru, Japan, a suburb of Sapporo on the Japanese island of Hokkaido. After Otaru, ''Kitty Hawk''{{'}}s [[Carrier Strike Group Five]] joined up with [[Carrier Strike Group Nine]], led by the {{USS|Abraham Lincoln|CVN-72}}, and the {{USS|Ronald Reagan|CVN-76|6}} [[Carrier Strike Group]], along with Marine Corps, Air Force, and various foreign militaries for the largest operation in over a decade, [[Valiant Shield]]. This exercise involved more than 30 ships, 280 aircraft, and 22,000 sailors, marines, and airmen, and focused on the strike groups' ability to maintain a very robust air strike schedule while being attacked by multiple submarine and surface threats. HS-14 performed incredibly, scoring many simulated torpedo attacks on the American, Australian, and Singaporean attacking subs, while allowing almost no attacks against the carrier ''Kitty Hawk''.

While defending the carrier from simulated submarine attacks, HS-14 also had a dedicated Combat Search and Rescue detachment working out of Guam. This detachment focused on joint operations with the [[HS-2]] while conducting Naval Special Warfare insertions and extractions. The detachment also gave the crews a chance to learn different techniques when operating in low light, tactical environments. HS-14 worked with several other units from different services and countries during the remainder of the year. Further exercises included &quot;Allies in the Outback&quot;, ANNUALEX, and an Atsugi CSAR Detachment.

==2007==
[[File:US Navy 050815-N-5387K-138 An HH-60H Seahawk, assigned to the Chargers of Helicopter Anti-Submarine Squadron Fourteen (HS-14), prepares to land.jpg|thumb|A HS-14 HH-60H in 2005.]]

In 2007, HS-14 sent a four helicopter detachment to [[Kadena Air Base]] on the island of Okinawa, Japan to practice weapons employment and terrain flying. The crews were able to take advantage of the area's weapons ranges and fired two [[AGM-114 Hellfire|AGM-114B ''Hellfire'']] missiles and three Mk 46 practice torpedoes. Additionally, HS-14 practiced joint operations with multiple commands and services. HS-14 practiced anti-submarine warfare tracking and attacking techniques with the [[Lockheed P-3 Orion|P-3C Orion]] aircraft from [[VP-4|Patrol Squadron 4]]. HS-14 was also able to practice fast roping, rappelling, and High Altitude Low Opening and static-line paradrops with the 1st of the 1st Airborne Rangers, U.S. Army. The 320th Tactics Squadron also worked with HS-14 practicing similar techniques.

''Kitty Hawk'', began another deployment in May, making stops in Guam, Sydney, Brisbane, Guam again, and Kuala Lumpur. HS-14 participated in multiple exercises during the deployment, including Talisman Saber, Valiant Shield, and Malabar 2007. During a port call in Muroran, Northern Japan, in October, HS-14 detached two [[SH-60|HH-60Hs]] and four aircrews to [[Misawa Air Base]] for FLIR/[[AGM-114 Hellfire|''Hellfire'']] training. The detachment rejoined the ''Kitty Hawk'' prior to ANNUALEX 19G, the naval portion of a larger U.S./Japanese exercise. Following the exercise, Carrier Strike Group Five made international headlines when it was denied entrance to the port of Hong Kong for the Thanksgiving Holiday. HS-14 returned to Atsugi in early December.

==2008==
HS-14 began 2008 with another weapons detachment to Kadena Air Base in Okinawa, beginning in early February. The detachment used four helicopters to fire Hellfire missiles, drop torpedoes, and conduct ASW, CSAR, NSW, and close air support (CAS) training with Marines, Air Force, and Army personnel.

Detachment &quot;B&quot; joined the guided missile destroyer {{USS|Lassen|DDG-82}} in January 2008 and conducted independent operations until March. HS-14's main body embarked aboard ''Kitty Hawk'' for sea trials in March, followed by workups in April, including a port call at Hong Kong. Detachment A embarked aboard the guided missile cruisers {{USS|Shiloh|CG-67}} and {{USS|Cowpens|CG-63}} from February through May. [[Carrier Strike Group Five]] left Yokosuka in May, marking ''Kitty Hawk''{{'}}s final departure from Japan. Detachment A rejoined the main squadron aboard ''Kitty Hawk'' for this cruise, while Detachment B returned to NAF Atsugi. The strike group visited Guam in June, then proceeded to Pearl Harbor, Hawaii.

At the end of the port call, HS-14 Detachment A &quot;Misfits&quot; debarked ''Kitty Hawk'' and embarked aboard the guided missile frigate {{USS|Rodney M. Davis|FFG-60}} as its air department for exercise [[RIMPAC]] 2008. HS-14 Det. A conducted intensive ASW operations in a separate surface action group, providing support as a &quot;pouncing&quot; aircraft, as well multiple logistics flights in support of the ship. HS-14's main body aboard the ''Kitty Hawk'' provided similar support to Carrier Strike Group Five.

Following [[RIMPAC]], the ''Kitty Hawk'' proceeded to San Diego as the carrier was replaced by {{USS|George Washington|CVN-73}}. Before arriving in San Diego, HS-14 provided [[VERTREP]] for ''Kitty Hawk''{{'}}s ammunition offload. The squadron moved over 900 loads in two days.

[[CVW-5]] flew off ''Kitty Hawk'' for the final time off the coast of California on 6 August. HS-14 provided photographic platforms for the flyoff, then flew off to [[Naval Air Station North Island]] on the 7th. When HS-14 landed at North Island that morning, it marked 14 years since the squadron was forward deployed to Japan. After ''Kitty Hawk'' tied up at NAS North Island, [[CVW-5]] immediately began crossdeck operations required to establish itself aboard the {{USS|George Washington|CVN-73|6}}. For two weeks in August, HS-14 was divided between the ''Kitty Hawk'', the ''George Washington'', and [[HS-4]]'s squadron spaces ashore.

The ''George Washington'' pulled out of San Diego with CVW-5 embarked on 21 August. HS-14 flew aboard that afternoon, and following a Blue Water Certification and workups over the next couple weeks, the GW began its trek west. The following month consisted of heavy flight operations for HS-14, to get CVW-5 and the ''George Washington'' Air Department working together as a cohesive team. ''George Washington'' arrived at  Yokosuka on 25 September.

2008 Fall Cruise began on 30 September. HS-14 left a CSAR detachment back aboard NAF Atsugi for the month of October. Along with Detachment B, the composite detachment managed to qualify several pilots and aircrew in CSAR Syllabus. HS-14's main body continued to provide ASW and SAR service to USS George Washington as the Strike Group visited Pusan, South Korea, and Guam. Following the Guam port visit, Detachment A left GW to embark guided-missile cruiser {{USS|Cowpens|CG-63|2}}, while Detachment B departed Japan aboard {{USS|Lassen|DDG-82}}. Both ships joined the GW Strike Group for ANNUALEX 20G, an exercise involving US and Japanese surface, subsurface, and air units. During the exercise, HS-14 provided round the clock ASW coverage, with GW based helos covering days and detachment helos covering nights. The squadron scored numerous submarine kills, helping to validate the detachment concept. HS-14 and CVW-5 returned to Atsugi on 21 November, marking nearly nine months of underway time for the air wing in 2008.

== 2009 ==

During the 2009 Summer Deployment HS-14 participated in [[Exercise Talisman Saber|TALISMAN SABRE 2009]].  While the main body of HS-14 supported the air wing on the West coast of Australia, Detachment Bravo, on {{USS|Mustin|DDG-89}} conducted continuous ASW missions in support of multinational operations.  In conjunction with two permanent Detachments, the Chargers sent a temporary detachment to Darwin, Australia to work with [[Special Operations Command (Australia)|Australia Special Forces]]. As the Summer Deployment wound down, HS-14 celebrated both their 25th birthday on 10 July marking 25 years of service and 50,000 hours Class &quot;A&quot; mishap free.

During the Fall Deployment (October – November 2009), HS-14 flew over 500 additional Class &quot;A&quot; mishap free hours.  While Chargers on board {{USS|George Washington|CVN-73}} worked ASW for [[Exercise Talisman Saber|Talisman Sabre]], Detachment Bravo conducted actual ASW operations tracking a [[Oscar class submarine|Russian Oscar]].  For the squadron's unequaled performance in its primary mission areas of Anti-Submarine Warfare (ASW) and Anti-Surface Warfare (ASU) they were awarded with the 2009 Captain Arnold Jay Isbell Trophy for Anti-Submarine and Anti-Surface Warfare Excellence.

== 2010 ==

From 19 February to 5 March, HS-14 sent a detachment to [[Kadena AFB]], Okinawa, Japan.  During this detachment the squadron flew over 250 hours enhancing their readiness for the 2010 Deployment.

== 2011 ==
HS-14 and [[HSL-51]] conducted humanitarian flights over Japan since 11 March 2011 as part of [[Operation Tomodachi]] from [[Naval Air Facility Misawa]].&lt;ref&gt;http://www.dvidshub.net/news/67650/hs-14-and-hsl-51-join-forces-support-operation-tomodachi&lt;/ref&gt;

== 2013 ==
[[File:MH-60S of HSC-14 over Range Support Craft 1 in February 2015.JPG|thumb|A MH-60S of HSC-14 off San Diego in February 2015.]]
In March 2013, HS-14 left [[Carrier Air Wing Five]] (CVW-5) at [[NAF Atsugi]], Japan, and conducted a permanent duty station change to [[NAS North Island]]. HS-14 transitioned to the [[SH-60|MH-60S Seahawk]] helicopter and was redesignated Helicopter Sea Combat Squadron FOURTEEN (HSC-14) in July.  HSC-14 is currently assigned to [[Carrier Air Wing Nine]] (CVW-9) which deploys aboard {{USS|John C. Stennis|CVN 74}}

== HS-14 Achievements ==
HS-14 celebrated over thirteen years and 50,000 mishap-free flight hours in August 2009. The squadron's impressive history is highlighted by many awards including
*Navy Unit Commendation Medal - 1991 ([[Gulf War|OPERATION DESERT STORM]]), 1998 ([[USS Independence (CV-62)]])
*Meritorious Unit Commendation Medal - 1989, 1994, and 1996 while attached to [[CVW-2]], [[USS Ranger (CV 61)]], and the [[USS Independence (CV 62)]] Battle Group
*Seven Battle Efficiency Awards - 1989, 1992, 1998, 1999, 2003, 2004, and 2010
*Armed Forces Expeditionary Medal - 1987, 1989, 1991, 1992, 1998, 1999, and 2003
*Joint Meritorious Unit Award - 1993
*Humanitarian Service Medal - 2001 ([[USS Gary (FFG-51)]])
*Southwest Asia Service Medal -1991
*Nine Chief of Naval Operations Safety Awards - 1989, 1991, 1992, 1993, 1998, 1999, 2001, 2006, and 2010
*Two consecutive DESRON SEVEN &quot;Golden Arrow&quot; Awards
*Nine Arnold J. Isbell Awards for ASW and ASUW excellence - 1993, 1999, 2001, 2002, 2003, 2005, 2007, 2009, and 2010
*Admiral John S. Thatch Award for ASW excellence - 2003
*Three [[CVW-5]] Maintenance Excellence &quot;Golden Wrench&quot; Awards – 2nd Qtr. 03, 2nd Qtr. 04, 4th Qtr. 04, 1st Qtr. 06

==See also==
{{Portal|United States Navy|Military of the United States}}
{{Wikipedia books|United States Navy Aircraft Squadrons}}
* [[History of the United States Navy]]
* [[List of United States Navy aircraft squadrons]]
* [[Carrier Strike Group Eleven]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.navy.mil/search/display.asp?story_id=7283 CVW-5 Completes 2003 Cruise]
* [http://www.news.navy.mil/search/display.asp?story_id=24298 HS-14 Provides ASW Support to Kitty Hawk during Valiant Shield 2006]
* [http://www.chinfo.navy.mil/navpalib/ships/carriers/histories/cv63-kittyhawk/cv63-kittyhawk.html A Brief History of USS Kitty Hawk]
* [http://navycompass.com/content/view/716/561/ CVW-5 To Arrive at NAS North Island]
* [http://www.tailhook.org/Awards%20CNAF.html HS-14 wins 2004 Battle &quot;E&quot;]
* [http://www.c7f.navy.mil/news/2009/07-july/27.htm HS-14 'Chargers' Celebrate Silver Anniversary]
* [https://www.cnic.navy.mil/Atsugi/Commands/CarrierAirWingFiveCVW-5/HS-14/index.htm HS-14 Official Website]
* [https://www.cnic.navy.mil/Atsugi/CVW-5/HS-14/History/index.htm HS-14 History]
* [https://www.cvw5.navy.mil/ CVW-5 Official Website]

{{US Navy navbox}}
{{United States Navy Aircraft Squadrons}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:HSC-14}}
[[Category:Helicopter anti-submarine squadrons of the United States Navy]]
[[Category:Helicopter sea combat squadrons of the United States Navy]]</text>
      <sha1>mtia294rzoomti7uqydl9n5h6dznl7s</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
