<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Indian National Army</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>173386</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750757043</id>
      <parentid>747377714</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-21T17:23:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>193.188.122.58</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="98760">{{about|the Second Indian National Army under Subhash Chandra Bose|the organisation under Mohan Singh|First Indian National Army|the modern Indian military|Indian Armed Forces|the army of the British Raj|British Indian Army}}
{{Use Indian English|date=September 2016}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2016}}
{{Infobox military unit
|unit_name=Indian National Army
|image=
|caption=Soldiers of the Indian National Army
|dates= August 1942&amp;nbsp;– September 1945
|country={{flag|Azad Hind}}
|role= [[Guerrilla]], [[infantry]], [[special operations]]
|size=43,000 (approximate)
|founder=[[Mohan Singh Deb]]
|ceremonial_chief= [[Subhash Chandra Bose]]
|commander=[[Major General]] [[Mohammad Zaman Kiani]]
|motto=''Ittehad, Itmad aur Qurbani'' &lt;br/&gt;(Unity, Faith and Sacrifice in [[Urdu language|Urdu]])
|march= ''[[Kadam Kadam Badaye Ja]]''
&lt;!--|identification_symbol= [[File:Flag of Azad Hind.svg|80px]]
|identification_symbol_label=Flag--&gt;
|battles= [[World War II]]
*[[Burma Campaign]]
**[[Battle of Ngakyedauk]]
**[[Battle of Imphal]]
**[[Battle of Kohima]]
**[[Battle of Pokoku]]
**[[Battle of Central Burma]]
}}
The '''Indian National Army''' ('''INA'''; ''Azad Hind Fauj'');{{IPAc-en|ˈ|ɑː|z|ɑː|ð|_|ˈ|h|i|n|ð|_|ˈ|f|ɔː|dʒ}} (''Lit'': Free-Indian Army) was an armed force formed by Indian nationalists in 1942 in [[Southeast Asia]] during [[World War II]]. Its aim was to secure [[Indian Independence movement|Indian independence]] from [[British Raj|British rule]]. It formed an alliance with [[Imperial Japan]] in the latter's campaign in the [[South-East Asian theatre of World War II|Southeast Asian theatre of WWII]].&lt;ref name=Fayviiii&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=viii}}&lt;/ref&gt; The army was [[First Indian National Army|first formed]] in 1942 under [[Mohan Singh Deb|Mohan Singh]], by Indian PoWs of the [[British Indian Army|British-Indian Army]] captured by Japan in the [[Malayan campaign]] and [[Battle of Singapore|at Singapore]].&lt;ref name=Lebraviiitox&gt;{{Harvnb|Lebra|2008|p=Foreword, ppviii-x}}&lt;/ref&gt; This first INA collapsed and was disbanded in December that year after differences between the INA leadership and the Japanese military over its role in Japan's war in Asia.&lt;ref name=Lebra2008p99/&gt; It was revived under the leadership of [[Subhas Chandra Bose]] after his arrival in Southeast Asia in 1943. The army was declared to be the army of Bose's ''[[Arzi Hukumat-e-Azad Hind]]'' (the Provisional Government of Free India).&lt;ref name=Fayp212to213&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=212,213}}&lt;/ref&gt; Under Bose's leadership, the INA drew ex-prisoners and thousands of civilian volunteers from the [[Non-resident Indian and person of Indian origin|Indian expatriate]] population in [[British Malaya|Malaya]] (present-day Malaysia) and [[Burma]].&lt;ref name=Lebrapxv&gt;{{Harvnb|Lebra|2008|p=xv}}&lt;/ref&gt; This second INA fought along with the [[Imperial Japanese Army]] against the British and [[Commonwealth of Nations|Commonwealth]] forces in the campaigns in Burma, [[Battle of Imphal|in Imphal]] and [[Battle of Kohima|at Kohima]], and later against the successful [[Burma Campaign]] of the [[Allies of World War II|Allies]].&lt;ref name=Fayp283and284/&gt;&lt;ref name=Fayp330&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=330}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After the INA's initial formation in 1942, there was concern in the British-Indian Army that further Indian troops would defect. This led to a reporting ban and a propaganda campaign called &quot;[[Jiffs]]&quot; to preserve the loyalty of the [[Sepoy]].&lt;ref name=Fayp423&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=423}}&lt;/ref&gt; Historians like [[Peter W. Fay]] who have written about the army, however, consider the INA not to have had significant influence on the war.&lt;ref name=Fay138/&gt; The end of the war saw a large number of the troops repatriated to India where some faced [[Indian National Army trials|trials for treason]]. These trials became a galvanising point in the [[Indian Independence movement]].&lt;ref name=Sarkar420&gt;{{Harvnb|Sarkar|1983|p=420}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Bombay mutiny]] in the [[Royal Indian Navy]] and other mutinies in 1946 are thought to have been caused by the nationalist feelings that were caused by the INA trials.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fay 1993 p=496,498,499&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|pp=496,498,499}}&lt;/ref&gt; Historians like [[Sumit Sarkar]], [[Peter Cohen (historian)|Peter Cohen]], Fay and others suggest that these events played a crucial role in hastening the end of British rule.&lt;ref name=Chaudhuri1953&gt;{{Harvnb|Chaudhuri|1953|p=349}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Sarkar411&gt;{{Harvnb|Sarkar|1983|p=411}}&lt;/ref&gt; A number of people associated with the INA during the war later went on to hold important roles in public life in India as well as in other countries in Southeast Asia, most notably [[Lakshmi Sehgal]] in India, and [[John Thivy]] and [[Janaki Athinahappan]] in Malaya.&lt;ref name=Lebra2008p219/&gt;

The legacy of the INA is controversial. It was associated with Imperial Japan and the other Axis powers, and accusations were levelled against INA troops of being involved and complicit in [[Japanese war crimes]].&lt;ref name=Fay423to424&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|pp=423–424,453}}&lt;/ref&gt; The INA's members were viewed as [[Collaboration with the Axis Powers during World War II|Axis collaborators]] by British soldiers and Indian PoWs who did not join the army,&lt;ref name=Toye1959pxiv/&gt; but after the war they were seen as patriots by many Indians.&lt;ref name=Toye1959pxiv&gt;{{Harvnb|Toye|1959|p=Philip Mason, in Foreword, p. xiv}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although they were widely commemorated by the [[Indian National Congress]] in the immediate aftermath of Indian independence, members of the INA were denied the status of [[freedom fighter]] by the Government of India, unlike those in the Gandhian movement.&lt;ref name=Cohenp132&gt;{{Harvnb|Cohen|1971|p=132}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, the army remains a popular and passionate topic in popular Indian culture and in Indian politics.&lt;ref name=Lebrapxv/&gt;&lt;ref name=Toye1959pxiv/&gt;&lt;ref name=Fayp228&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|pp=228}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==First INA==
{{Main|First Indian National Army}}
{{See also|Mohan Singh|I Fujiwara|Indian Independence League|Thirty Comrades}}
[[File:Fujiwara Kikan.jpg|left|200px|thumb|Major [[Iwaichi Fujiwara]] greets [[Mohan Singh (general)|Mohan Singh]]. ''Circa'' April 1942.]]
Before the start of World War II, Japan and South-East Asia were major refuges for exiled Indian nationalists. Meanwhile, Japan had [[F Kikan|sent intelligence missions]], notably under [[Major|Maj.]] [[Iwaichi Fujiwara]], into South Asia to gather support from the Malayan sultans, overseas Chinese, the Burmese resistance and the [[Indian independence movement]]. The Minami Kikan successfully recruited [[Thirty Comrades|Burmese nationalists]], while the F Kikan was successful in establishing contacts with Indian nationalists in exile in [[Thailand]] and [[British Malaya|Malaya]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Lebra|1977|p=23}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Lebra|1977|p=24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At the outbreak of World War II [[South-East Asian theatre of World War II|in South-East Asia]], 70,000 Indian troops were stationed in Malaya. In Japan's spectacular [[Malayan Campaign]] a large number of Indian prisoners-of-war were captured, including nearly 45,000 after the [[Battle of Singapore|fall of Singapore]] alone.&lt;ref name=Toye2007p4&gt;{{Harvnb|Toye|2007|p=4}}&lt;/ref&gt; The conditions of service within the British-Indian Army and the social conditions in Malaya had led to dissension among these troops.&lt;ref name=Faye56and224and226&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=56,224,226}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Toye30&gt;{{Harvnb|Toye|1959|p=30}}&lt;/ref&gt; From these prisoners, the [[First Indian National Army]] was formed under [[Mohan Singh (general)|Mohan Singh]]. Singh was an officer in the British-Indian Army who was captured early in the Malayan campaign. His nationalist sympathies found an ally in Fujiwara and he received considerable Japanese aid and support.&lt;ref name=Toye7and8&gt;{{Harvnb|Toye|1959|p=7,8}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ethnic Indians in Southeast Asia also supported the cause of Indian independence and had formed local leagues in Malaya before the war. These came together with encouragement from Japan after the occupation, forming the [[Indian Independence League]] (IIL).&lt;ref name=Fay91and108&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=91,108}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although there were a number of prominent local Indians working in the IIL, the overall leadership came to rest with [[Rash Behari Bose]], an Indian revolutionary who had lived in self-exile in Japan since World War I.&lt;ref name=Faye108&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=108}}&lt;/ref&gt; The League and INA leadership decided that the INA was to be subordinate to the IIL. A working council&amp;nbsp;– composed of prominent members of the League and the INA leaders&amp;nbsp;– was to decide on decisions to send the INA to war.&lt;ref name=Lebra2008p77&gt;{{Harvnb|Lebra|2008|p=77}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Indian leaders feared that they would appear to be Japanese puppets, so a decision was taken that the INA would go to battle only when the [[Indian National Congress]] called it to do so.&lt;ref name=Fay94&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=94}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Fay111&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=111}}&lt;/ref&gt; Assurances of non-interference— later termed the [[Bidadary resolutions]]— were demanded of Japan; these would have amounted to a treaty with an independent government.&lt;ref name=Toye2007p4/&gt; Japan did not immediately agree to these demands. Differences also existed between Rash Behari and the League, not least because Rash Behari had lived in Japan for considerable time and had a Japanese wife and a son in the Imperial Japanese Army.&lt;ref name=Lebra2008p49&gt;{{Harvnb|Lebra|2008|p=49}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the other hand, Mohan Singh expected military strategy and decisions to be autonomous decisions for the INA, independent of the league.&lt;ref name=Fay150&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=150}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In November and December 1942, concern about Japan's intentions towards the INA led to disagreement between the INA and the League on the one hand and the Japanese on the other.&lt;ref name=Lebra2008p99&gt;{{Harvnb|Lebra|2008|p=99}}&lt;/ref&gt; The INA leadership resigned along with that of the League (except Rash Behari). The unit was dissolved by Mohan Singh in December 1942, and he ordered the troops of the INA to return to PoW camps.&lt;ref name=Toye45&gt;{{Harvnb|Toye|1959|p=45}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Fay149&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=149}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mohan Singh was expected to be shot.&lt;ref name=Toye45/&gt;

Between December 1942 and February 1943, Rash Behari struggled to hold the INA together.&lt;ref name=Fay151&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=151}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 15 February 1943, the army itself was put under the command of [[Lieutenant Colonel|Lt. Col.]] [[M.Z. Kiani]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://wn.com/Lt_Col_M_Z_Kiani | title=MZ kiani | publisher=World news | accessdate=12 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; A policy forming body was formed with Lt. Col [[J.R. Bhonsle|Lt. Col J.R. Bhonsle]] (Director of the Military Bureau) in charge and clearly placed under the authority of the IIL. Under Bhonsle served [[Shah Nawaz Khan (general)|Lt. Col. Shah Nawaz Khan]] as Chief of General Staff, [[P.K. Sahgal|Major P.K. Sahgal]] as Military Secretary, [[Raja Habib ur Rahman Khan|Major Habib ur Rahman]] as commandant of the Officers' Training School and [[A.C. Chatterji|Lt. Col. A.C. Chatterji]]  (later Major A.D. Jahangir) as head of enlightenment and culture.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fay151&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Lebra2008p98&gt;{{Harvnb|Lebra|2008|p=98}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Second INA==

===Subhas Bose===
{{main|Subash Chandra Bose}}
{{See also|Indian Legion|Azad Hind Radio}}

Suggestions that [[Subhash Chandra Bose]] was the ideal person to lead a rebel army into India came from the very beginning of F Kikan's work with captured Indian soldiers. Mohan Singh himself, soon after his first meeting with Fujiwara, had suggested that Bose was the right leader of a nationalist Indian army.&lt;ref name=Toye2007p2&gt;{{Harvnb|Toye|2007|p=2}}&lt;/ref&gt; A number of the officers and troops&amp;nbsp;– including some who now returned to prisoner-of-war camps and some who had not volunteered in the first place&amp;nbsp;– made it known that they would be willing to join the INA only if it was led by Subhas Bose.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lebra197727&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Lebra|1977|p=27}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bose was a hard-line radical nationalist. He had joined the Gandhian movement after resigning from a prestigious post in the [[Indian Civil Service]] in 1922, quickly rising in the Congress and being incarcerated repeatedly by the Raj.&lt;ref name=Toye1959p80&gt;{{Harvnb|Toye|1959|p=80}}&lt;/ref&gt; By late 1920s he and [[Jawaharlal Nehru|Nehru]] were considered the future leaders of the Congress.&lt;ref name=Toye2007prebelleader&gt;{{Harvnb|Toye|2007|p=The Rebel President}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the late 1920s, he was amongst the first Congress leaders to call for complete independence from Britain (''Purna Swaraj''), rather than the previous Congress objective of India becoming a [[British dominion]].&lt;ref name=Toye2007prebelleader/&gt; In Bengal, he was repeatedly accused by Raj officials of working with the [[Revolutionary movement for Indian independence|revolutionary movement]]. Under his leadership, the Congress youth group in Bengal was organised into a quasi-military organisation called the [[Bengal Volunteers]].&lt;ref name=Sengupta23and24&gt;{{Harvnb|Sengupta|2012|p=23,24}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bose deplored [[Gandhi]]'s pacifism; Gandhi disagreed with Bose's confrontations with the Raj.&lt;ref name=Toye2007prebelleader/&gt; The Congress's working committee, including Nehru, was predominantly loyal to Gandhi.&lt;ref name=Toye2007prebelleader/&gt; While openly disagreeing with Gandhi, Bose won the presidency of Indian National Congress twice in the 1930s. His second victory came despite opposition from Gandhi. He defeated Gandhi's favoured candidate, [[Bhogaraju Pattabhi Sitaramayya]], in the popular vote, but the entire working committee resigned and refused to work with Bose.&lt;ref name=&quot;Toye1959p100&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Toye|1959|p=88}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bose resigned from the Congress presidency and founded his own faction, the [[All India Forward Bloc]].&lt;ref name=Fayp197&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=197}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At the start of World War II, Bose was placed under house-arrest by the Raj.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.revolutionarydemocracy.org/rdv7n1/Bose.htm | title=Subhas Chandra Bose in Nazi Germany | publisher=South Asia Forum Quarterly | work=Sisir K. Majumdar | year=1997 | accessdate=12 August 2011 | pages=10–14}}&lt;/ref&gt; He escaped in disguise and made his way through Afghanistan and Central Asia. He came first to the Soviet Union and then to Germany, reaching Berlin on 2 April 1941.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lebra2008p219&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Lebra|2008|p=107}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Toye1959p100&quot;/&gt; There he sought to raise an army of Indian soldiers from prisoners of war captured by Germany,&lt;ref name=Syonan&gt;{{Harvnb|Tojo|1943|p=}}&lt;/ref&gt; forming the [[Free India Legion]] and the [[Azad Hind Radio|''Azad Hind'' Radio]].&lt;ref name=Toye1959p117to119&gt;{{Harvnb|Toye|1959|p=117 to 119}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Japanese ambassador, [[Oshima Hiroshi]], kept Tokyo informed of these developments.&lt;ref name=Lebra2008p231&gt;{{Harvnb|Lebra|2008|p=231}}&lt;/ref&gt; From the very start of the war, the Japanese intelligence services noted from speaking to captured Indian soldiers that Bose was held in extremely high regard as a nationalist and was considered by Indian soldiers to be the right person to be leading a rebel army.&lt;ref name=Toye2007p2/&gt;

In a series of meetings between the INA leaders and the Japanese in 1943, it was decided to cede the leadership of the IIL and the INA to Bose. In January 1943, the Japanese invited Bose to lead the Indian nationalist movement in East Asia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.s1942.org.sg/s1942/indian_national_army/subhas.htm | title=Total Mobilisation | publisher=National Archives of Singapore | accessdate=12 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; He accepted and left Germany on 8 February. After a three-month journey by submarine and a short stop in Singapore, he reached Tokyo on 11 May 1943. In Tokyo, he met [[Hideki Tojo]], the Japanese prime minister, and the Japanese High Command. He then arrived in Singapore in July 1943, where he made a number of radio broadcasts to Indians in Southeast Asia exhorting them to join in the fight for India's independence.&lt;ref name=Fayp223&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=223}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Revival===
On 4 July 1943, two days after reaching Singapore, Bose assumed the leadership of the IIL and the INA in a ceremony at Cathay Building. Bose's influence was notable. His appeal re-invigorated the INA, which had previously consisted mainly of prisoners of war: it also attracted Indian expatriates in South Asia. He famously proclaimed:&lt;ref name=TOIBloodFreedom&gt;{{cite news
| author =  India Today
| publisher = India Today
|url=http://indiatoday.intoday.in/education/story/subhas-chandra-bose-10-things-you-should-definitely-know-about-him/1/414974.html
| title= Subhas Chandra Bose: 10 things you should definitely know about the legend
| accessdate=2015-10-24
| date=2015-01-23
}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{quote|Give me blood! I will give you freedom&amp;nbsp;...}}

&quot;Local civilians joined the INA, doubling its strength. They included barristers, traders and plantation workers, as well as  [[Khudabadi Sindhi Swarankar]] who were working as shop keepers; many had no military experience.&quot;&lt;ref name=Belle199&gt;{{Harvnb|Belle|2014|p=199}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| publisher = National Archives of Singapore| url=http://www.s1942.org.sg/s1942/indian_national_army/revival.htm| title= Historical Journey of the Indian National Army
| accessdate=2007-07-07
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Carl Vadivella Belle estimates under Bose's dynamic appeal, membership of the IIL peaked at 350,000, while almost 100,000 local Indians in South-east Asia volunteered to join the INA, with the army ultimately reaching a force of 50,000.&lt;ref name=&quot;Belle199&quot;/&gt; [[Hugh Toye]]— a British Intelligence officer and author of a 1959 history of the army called ''[[The Springing Tiger]]''— and American historian Peter Fay (author of a 1993 history called ''The Forgotten Army'')  have reached similar estimates of troop strength. The first INA is considered to have comprised about 40,000 troops, of whom about 4,000 withdrew when it was disbanded in December 1942. The Second INA started with 12,000 troops.&lt;ref name=Toye1959p286&gt;{{Harvnb|Toye|1959|p=286}}&lt;/ref&gt; Further recruitment of former Indian Army personnel added about 8,000–10,000. About 18,000 Indian civilians also enlisted during this time.&lt;ref name=Sareen1986p125&gt;{{Harvnb|Sareen|1986|p=125}}&lt;/ref&gt; Belle estimates almost 20,000 were local Malayan Indians, while another 20,000 were ex-British-Indian Army members who volunteered for the INA.&lt;ref name=&quot;Belle199&quot;/&gt; 
[[File:Gandhi and Subhas Bose.jpg|thumb|300px|right| [[Subhas Bose]] with [[Mohandas Gandhi]] at a Congress meeting, c 1930.]]
The exact organisation of the INA and its precise troop strength is not known, since its records were destroyed by the withdrawing ''Azad Hind'' Government before Rangoon  [[Burma Campaign#Race for Rangoon|was recaptured]] by Commonwealth forces in 1945.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=556}}&lt;/ref&gt; The order of battle described by Fay (constructed from discussions with INA-veterans), nonetheless, is similar to that described of the first INA by Toye in ''The Springing Tiger''. The 1st Division, under M.Z. Kiani, drew a large number of ex-Indian army prisoners of war who had joined Mohan Singh's first INA. It also drew prisoners of war who had not joined in 1942. It consisted of the 2nd Guerrilla Regiment (the [[Gandhi Brigade (regiment)|Gandhi Brigade]]) consisting of two battalions under Col. Inayat Kiani; the 3rd Guerrilla Regiment (the [[Azad Brigade]]) with three battalions under Col. Gulzara Singh; and the 4th Guerrilla Regiment (or [[Nehru Brigade]]) commanded by the end of the war by Lt. Col [[Gurubaksh Singh Dhillon]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=263}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 1st Guerrilla Regiment&amp;nbsp;– the [[Subhas Brigade]]&amp;nbsp;– under Col. Shah Nawaz Khan was an independent unit, consisting of three infantry battalions. A special operations group was also to be set up called the ''[[Bahadur group]]'' (Valiant), to operate behind enemy lines.&lt;ref name=Toye1959138&gt;{{Harvnb|Toye|1959|p=138}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A training school for INA officers, led by Habib ur Rahman, and the ''Azad'' School for the civilian volunteers were set up to provide training to the recruits. A youth wing of the INA, composed of 45 young Indians personally chosen by Bose and known as the [[Tokyo Boys]], was also sent to Japan's Imperial Military Academy, where its members trained as fighter pilots. A separate [[Rani of Jhansi Regiment|all-female unit]] was also created under [[Lakshmi Sahgal]]. This unit was intended to have combat-commitments.&lt;ref name=Gordonp496&gt;{{Harvnb|Gordon|1990|p=496}}&lt;/ref&gt; Named ''Jhansi ki Rani'' (&quot;Jhansi Queens&quot;) Regiment (after the legendary rebel Queen [[Lakshmibai]] of the [[1857 rebellion]]), it drew female civilian volunteers from Malaya and Burma. The 1st Division was lightly armed. Each battalion was composed of five companies of infantry. The individual companies were armed with six [[antitank rifle]]s, six [[Bren gun]]s and six [[Vickers machine gun]]s. Some NCOs carried [[hand grenade]]s. Men going forward on duty were issued British stocks of hand grenades by senior officer of the ''Bahadur'' groups attached to each unit. Mortars were available, but Fay points out these were not available at battalion level.&lt;ref name=Fay297&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=297}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{clarify|date=October 2015|reason=Where were they available?}}&lt;!-- Fay does not clarify this. --&gt;

The 2nd Division was organised under Colonel Abdul Aziz Tajik.&lt;ref name=Fay317&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=317}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was formed largely after the [[U Go offensive|Imphal offensive]] had started and drew large remnants of the what remained of the [[Hindustan Field Force]] of the First INA. The 2nd Division consisted of the 1st Infantry Regiment, which later merged with the 5th Guerrilla Regiment to form the INA's 2nd Infantry Regiment under Col [[Prem Sahgal]]. The 1st Infantry Regiment drew a large number of civilian volunteers from Burma and Malaya and was equipped with largest share of the heavy armament that the INA possessed.&lt;ref name=Fay318&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=318}}&lt;/ref&gt; An additional 3rd Division of the INA was composed chiefly of local volunteers in Malaya and Singapore. This unit disbanded before Japan surrendered. A motor transport division was also created, but it was severely limited by lack of resources. In 1945, at the end of the INA, it consisted of about 40,000 soldiers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|pp=525–6}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Unlike Mohan Singh, whose assumption of the rank of [[General]] had generated opposition, Bose refused to take a rank.&lt;ref name=Bayly&amp;Harper2005p322&gt;{{Harvnb|Bayly|Harper|2005|p=322}}&lt;/ref&gt; Both the soldiers of the INA and civilians addressed Bose as ''Netaji'' (&quot;Dear leader&quot;). In October 1943, Bose proclaimed the formation of the ''[[Arzi Hukumat-e-Azad Hind]]'', or the Provisional Government of Free India (also known as ''Azad Hind'' or Free India). The INA was declared to be the army of ''Azad Hind''.

==Operations==
[[File:INA Parade.jpg|thumb|right|Military parade of the INA at the Padang
on 5 July 1943]] &lt;!-- FAIR USE of INA_Parade.jpg: see image description page at http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:INA_Parade.jpgfor rationale --&gt; 
{{Main|Battles and operations of the Indian National Army}}
{{See also|India in World War II}}
On 23 October 1943, ''Azad Hind'' declared war against Britain and the United States.&lt;ref name=Singh16&gt;{{Harvnb|Singh|2003|p=16}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its first formal commitment came with the opening of the Japanese offensive towards [[Manipur]], code named ''[[Operation U-Go|U-Go]]''. Bose moved the advanced headquarters of ''Azad Hind'' to Rangoon in anticipation of success. The INA's own strategy was to avoid set-piece battles, for which it lacked armament as well as manpower.&lt;ref name=Fay292and298&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=292,298}}&lt;/ref&gt; Initially it sought to obtain arms and increase its ranks by inducing British-Indian soldiers to defect. The latter were expected to defect in large numbers. Col Prem Sahgal, once military secretary to Subhas Bose and later tried in the first [[Red Fort trials]], explained the INA strategy to Peter Fay&lt;ref name=Fay139&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=139}}&lt;/ref&gt;&amp;nbsp;– although the war itself hung in balance and nobody was sure if the Japanese would win, initiating a popular revolution with grass-roots support within India would ensure that even if Japan ultimately lost the war, Britain would not be in a position to re-assert its colonial authority. It was planned that, once Japanese forces had broken through British defences at [[Imphal]], the INA would cross the hills of [[North-East India]] into the [[Gangetic plain]], where it would work as a guerrilla army.&lt;ref name=Fay268&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=268}}&lt;/ref&gt; This army was expected to live off the land, with captured British supplies,support, and personnel from the local population.&lt;ref name=Fay262&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=262}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===1944===
{{See also|Battle of the Admin Box|U Go Offensive|Battle of Imphal|Battle of Kohima}}
The plans chosen by Bose and [[Masakazu Kawabe]], chief of Burma area army, envisaged the INA being assigned an independent sector in the ''U-Go'' offensive. No INA units were to operate at less than battalion strength.&lt;ref name=Toye1959p161&gt;{{Harvnb|Toye|1959|p=161}}&lt;/ref&gt; For operational purposes, the Subhas Brigade was placed under the command of the Japanese General Headquarters in Burma. Advance parties of the ''Bahadur'' Group also went forward with advanced Japanese units.&lt;ref name=Toye159&gt;{{Harvnb|Toye|1959|p=159}}&lt;/ref&gt; As the offensive opened, the INA's 1st Division, consisting of four guerrilla regiments, was divided between ''U Go'' and the diversionary ''[[Second Arakan Offensive|Ha-Go]]'' offensive in [[Rakhine State|Arakan]].&lt;ref name=Toye1959p161/&gt;&lt;ref name=Toye162&gt;{{Harvnb|Toye|1959|p=162}}&lt;/ref&gt; One battalion reached as far as Mowdok in [[Chittagong]] after breaking through the [[British West African Division]].&lt;ref name=Sareen1996p184&gt;{{Harvnb|Sareen|1996|p=184}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Bijil112&gt;{{Harvnb|van Der Bijil|2013|p=112}}&lt;/ref&gt; A Bahadur Group unit, led by  Col. [[Shaukat Malik]], took the border enclave of [[Moirang]] in early April.&lt;ref name=Toye1959p198&amp;215&gt;{{Harvnb|Toye|1959|p=198,215}}&lt;/ref&gt; The main body of the 1st Division was however committed to the ''U-Go'', directed towards Manipur. Led by Shah Nawaz Khan, it successfully protected the Japanese flanks against Chin and Kashin guerrillas as [[Renya Mutaguchi]]'s three divisions crossed the [[Chindwin river]] and the [[Naga Hills]], and participated in the main offensive through [[Tamu, Myanmar|Tamu]] in the direction of Imphal and [[Kohima]].&lt;ref name=Fayp283and284&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=283,284}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Toyep189to191&gt;{{Harvnb|Toye|1959|pp=189–191}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 2nd Division, under M.Z. Kiani, was placed to the right flank of the 33rd Division attacking Kohima. However, by the time Khan's forces left Tamu, the offensive had been held, and Khan's troops were redirected to Kohima. After reaching Ukhrul, near Kohima, they found Japanese forces had begun their withdrawal from the area. The INA's forces suffered the same fate as Mutaguchi's army when the siege of Imphal was broken. With little or nothing in the way of supplies, and with additional difficulties caused by the monsoon, Allied air dominance, and Burmese irregular forces, the 1st and 2nd divisions began withdrawing alongside the 15th Army and [[Burma Area Army]]. During the withdrawal through Manipur, a weakened Gandhi regiment held its position against the advancing [[Maratha Light Infantry]] on the Burma–India road while the general withdrawal was prepared.&lt;ref name=Fay289&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|pp=289–292}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Toye138and162&gt;{{Harvnb|Toye|1959|p=138,162,203,210}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 2nd and 3rd INA regiments protected the flanks of the Yamamoto force successfully at the most critical time during this withdrawal,&lt;ref name=&quot;Toye1959207&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Toye|1959|p=207}}&lt;/ref&gt; but wounded and diseased men succumbed to starvation along the route. Commonwealth troops following the Japanese forces found INA dead along with Japanese troops who had died of starvation.&lt;ref name=Toye180&gt;{{Harvnb|Toye|1959|p=180}}&lt;/ref&gt; The INA lost a substantial amount of men and materiel in this retreat. A number of units were disbanded or used to feed into new divisions.&lt;ref name=Fay417&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=417}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===1945===
{{See also|Battle of Pokoku|Battle of Meiktila and Mandalay}}
As the Allied [[Burma campaign]] began the following year, the INA remained committed to the defence of Burma and was a part of the Japanese defensive deployments. The Second Division was tasked with the defence of [[Irrawaddy Delta|Irrawaddy]] and the adjoining areas around Nangyu, and offered opposition to [[Frank Messervy|Messervy]]'s 7th Indian Division when it attempted to cross the river at Pagan and Nyangyu during [[Battle of Pokoku and Irrawaddy River operations|Irrawaddy operations]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Fayp330&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Fay539&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=539}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later, during the [[Battle of Meiktila and Mandalay|Battles of Meiktila and Mandalay]], the forces under Prem Sahgal were tasked with defending the area around [[Mount Popa]] from the British 17th Division, which would have exposed the flank of [[Heitarō Kimura]]'s forces attempting to retake Meiktila and Nyangyu. The division was obliterated, at times fighting tanks with hand grenades and bottles of petrol.&lt;ref name=Fay358&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=358}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Toye1959p229&gt;{{Harvnb|Toye|1959|p=229}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many INA soldiers realised that they were in a hopeless position. Many surrendered to pursuing Commonwealth forces. Isolated, losing men to exhaustion and to desertion, low on ammunition and food, and pursued by Commonwealth forces, the surviving units of the second division began an attempt to withdraw towards Rangoon. They broke through encircling Commonwealth lines a number of times before finally surrendering at various places in early April 1945.&lt;ref name=Fay539/&gt;&lt;ref name=Singh32and33&gt;{{Harvnb|Singh|2003|p=32,33}}&lt;/ref&gt; As the Japanese situation became precarious, the ''Azad Hind'' government  withdrew from Rangoon to Singapore, along with the remnants of the 1st Division and the Rani of Jhansi Regiment. Nearly 6,000 troops of the surviving units of the INA remained in Rangoon under [[A. D. Loganathan]]. They surrendered as Rangoon fell and helped keep order until the Allied forces entered the city.&lt;ref name=Toye261&gt;{{Harvnb|Toye|1959|p=261}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As the Japanese withdrawal from Burma progressed, other remnants of the INA began a long march over land and on foot towards Bangkok. In what has been called an &quot;epic retreat to safety&quot;,&lt;ref name=Belle204&gt;{{Harvnb|Belle|2014|p=204}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bose walked with his troops, refusing to leave them despite Japanese soldiers finding him transport.&lt;ref name=Toye1959p248/&gt; The withdrawing forces regularly suffered casualties from Allied planes strafing them and in clashes with [[Aung San]]'s Burmese resistance, as well as from Chinese guerrillas who harassed the Japanese troops.&lt;ref name=Toye1959p248&gt;{{Harvnb|Toye|1959|p=248}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bose returned to Singapore in August to what remained of the INA and ''Azad Hind''. He wished to stay with his government at Singapore to surrender to the British, reasoning that a trial in India and possible execution would ignite the country, serving the independence movement. He was convinced not to do so by the ''Azad Hind'' cabinet.&lt;ref name=BoseHMOp&gt;{{Harvnb|Bose|2013|p=undefined}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the time of Japan's surrender in September 1945, Bose left for [[Dalian]] near the Soviet border in [[Manchukuo|Japanese-occupied China]] to attempt to contact the advancing Soviet troops, and was [[Death of Subhash Chandra Bose|reported to have died]] in an air crash near Taiwan.&lt;ref name=Fay372&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|pp=372–373}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Fay384&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=384}}&lt;/ref&gt; The remaining INA troops surrendered under the command of M.Z. Kiani to British-Indian forces at Singapore.&lt;ref name=Bose2006p143&gt;{{Harvnb|Bose|2006|p=143}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==End of the INA==

===Repatriation to India===
{{See also|CSDIC(I)}}
[[File:Surrendered Indian National Army troops at Mount Popa.jpg|thumb|250px|Troops of the Indian National Army who surrendered at Mount Popa. ''Circa'' April 1945.]]
Even before the end of the war in South Asia, the INA prisoners who were falling into Allied hands were being evaluated by forward intelligence units for potential trials.&lt;ref name=Fay436&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=436}}&lt;/ref&gt; Almost fifteen hundred had been captured in the battles of Imphal and Kohima and the subsequent withdrawal,&lt;ref name=Lebra2008p200&gt;{{Harvnb|Lebra|2008|p=200}}&lt;/ref&gt; while larger numbers surrendered or were captured during the 14th Army's Burma Campaign. A total of 16,000 of the INA's 43,000 recruits were captured, of whom around 11,000 were interrogated by the [[CSDIC(I)|Combined Services Directorate of Investigation Corps]] (CSDIC).&lt;ref name=Fay459&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=459}}&lt;/ref&gt; The number of prisoners necessitated this selective policy which anticipated trials of those with the strongest commitment to Bose's ideologies. Those with lesser commitment or other extenuating circumstances would be dealt with more leniently, with the punishment proportional to their commitment or war crimes.&lt;ref name=Singh38/&gt; For this purpose, the field intelligence units designated the captured troops as ''Blacks'' with strongest commitment to ''Azad Hind''; ''Greys'' with varying commitment but also with enticing circumstances that led them to join the INA; and ''Whites'', those who were pressured into joining the INA under the circumstances but with no commitment to ''Azad Hind'', INA, or Bose.&lt;ref name=Singh39&gt;{{Harvnb|Singh|2003|p=39}}&lt;/ref&gt;

By July 1945, a large number had been shipped back to India. At the time of the fall of Japan, the remaining captured troops were transported to India via Rangoon. Large numbers of local Malay and Burmese volunteers, including the recruits to the Rani of Jhansi regiment, returned to civilian life and were not identified.&lt;ref name=Singh38&gt;{{Harvnb|Singh|2003|p=38}}&lt;/ref&gt; Those repatriated passed through transit camps in Chittagong and [[Calcutta]] to be held at detention camps all over India including Jhingergacha and Nilganj near Calcutta, Kirkee outside Pune, [[Attock]], [[Multan]] and at Bahadurgarh near Delhi. Bahadurgarh also held prisoners of the Free India Legion.&lt;ref name=Fay436/&gt; By November, around 12,000 INA prisoners were held in these camps; they were released according to the &quot;colours&quot;.&lt;ref name=Fay436/&gt; By December, around 600 whites were released per week. The process to select those to face trial started.&lt;ref name=Fay436/&gt;

The British-Indian Army intended to implement appropriate internal disciplinary action against its soldiers who had joined the INA, whilst putting to trial a selected group in order to preserve discipline in the Indian Army and to award punishment for criminal acts where these had occurred.&lt;ref name=&quot;Singh44and45&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Singh|2003|p=44,45}}&lt;/ref&gt; As news of the army spread within India, it began to draw widespread sympathy support and admiration from Indians.  Newspaper reports around November 1945 reported executions of INA troops,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| publisher = Hindustan Times. 2 November 1945
| url=http://www.hindustantimes.com/news/specials/Netaji/images/nov_2_45.gif
| title=Many INA already executed.
| accessdate=2007-09-02
}}&lt;/ref&gt; which worsened the already volatile situation. Increasingly violent confrontations broke out between the police and protesters at the mass rallies being held all over India, culminating in public riotings in support of the INA men.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Chaudhuri|1953|p=351}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Sarkar419&gt;{{Harvnb|Sarkar|1983|p=419}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Fay499&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=499}}&lt;/ref&gt; This public outcry defied traditional communal barriers of the subcontinent, representing a departure from the divisions between Hindus and Muslims seen elsewhere in the independence movement and [[Pakistan independence movement|campaign for Pakistan]].&lt;ref name=Singh39and40&gt;{{harvnb|Singh|2003|pp=39,40}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Red Fort trials===
{{Main|Indian National Army trials}}
Between November 1945 and May 1946, approximately ten courts-martial were held in public at the [[Red Fort]] in Delhi. [[Claude Auchinleck]], the [[Commander-in-Chief, India|Commander-in-Chief]] of the British-Indian army, hoped that by holding public trials in the Red Fort, public opinion would turn against the INA if the media reported stories of torture and collaborationsim, helping him settle a political as well as military question.&lt;ref name=Singh42-43&gt;{{harvnb|Singh|2003|pp=42,43}}&lt;/ref&gt; Those to stand trials were accused variously of murder, torture and ''Waging war against the King-Emperor''. However, the first and most celebrated joint courts-martial&amp;nbsp;– those of Prem Sahgal, Gurubaksh Singh Dhillon and Shah Nawaz Khan&amp;nbsp;– were not the story of torture and murder Auchinleck had hoped to tell the Indian press and people. The accusations against them included alleged murder of their comrades-in-arms in the INA whilst in Burma. Historians point out the murders alleged were actually courts-martial of captured deserters they had presided over. If it was accepted that the three were part of a genuine combatant army (as the legal defence team later argued), they had followed due process of written INA law and of the normal process of conduct of war in execution of the sentences.&lt;ref name=Toyexix&gt;{{harvnb|Toye|1959|pp=Mason, in foreword pp-xix 41}}&lt;/ref&gt; Indians rapidly came to view the soldiers who enlisted as patriots and not enemy-collaborators. [[Philip Mason]], then Secretary of the War Department, later wrote that &quot;in a matter of weeks&amp;nbsp;... in a wave of nationalist emotion, the INA were acclaimed heroes who fought for the freedom of India.&quot;&lt;ref name=Toyexviii&gt;{{harvnb|Toye|1959|pp=Mason, in foreword, pp-xviii}}&lt;/ref&gt; The three accused were from the three major religions of India: Hinduism, Islam, and Sikhism. Indians felt the INA represented a true, secular, national army when judged against the British-Indian Army, where caste and religious differences were preserved amongst ranks.&lt;ref name=&quot;Singh39and40&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Singh74&gt;{{harvnb|Singh|2003|pp=74}}&lt;/ref&gt; The opening of the first trial saw violence and a series of riots in a scale later described as &quot;sensational&quot;.&lt;ref name=Chaudhuri1953/&gt; The Indian National Congress and the [[All-India Muslim League|Muslim League]] both made the release of the INA prisoners an important political issue during the campaign for independence in 1945–46.&lt;ref name=Chaudhury1953p1&gt;{{harvnb|Chaudhuri|1953|p=1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lahore in Diwali 1946 remained dark as the traditional earthen lamps lit on Diwali were not lit by families in support of prisoners.&lt;ref name=Singh79&gt;{{harvnb|Singh|2003|pp=79}}&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to civilian campaigns of non-cooperation and non-violent protest, protest spread to include mutinies within the British-Indian Army and sympathy within the British-Indian forces. Support for the INA crossed communal barriers to the extent that it was the last major campaign in which the Congress and the Muslim League aligned together; the Congress [[Flag of India|tricolour]] and the green flag of the League were flown together at protests.&lt;ref name=Sengupta77&gt;{{harvnb|Sengupta|2012|pp=77}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Congress quickly came forward to defend soldiers of the INA who were to be court-martialled.&lt;ref name=Singh44&gt;{{harvnb|Singh|2003|pp=44}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[INA Defence Committee]] was formed by the Indian Congress and included prominent Indian legal figures, among whom were Jawaharlal Nehru, [[Bhulabhai Desai]], [[Kailashnath Katju]] and [[Asaf Ali]].&lt;ref name=Sengupta77/&gt; The trials covered arguments based on military law, constitutional law, international law, and politics. Much of the initial defence was based on the argument that they should be treated as prisoners of war as they were not paid mercenaries but ''bona fide'' soldiers of a legal government&amp;nbsp;– Bose's ''Arzi Hukumat-e-Azad Hind''.&lt;ref name=Fay80&gt;{{harvnb|Fay|1993|pp=79, 80}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nehru argued that &quot;however misinformed or otherwise they had been in their notion of patriotic duty towards their country&quot;, they recognized the free Indian state as their sovereign and not the British sovereign.&lt;ref&gt;Stephen P. Cohen &quot;Subhas Chandra Bose and the Indian National Army&quot; ''Pacific Affairs'' Vol. 36, No. 4 (Winter, 1963) pp 411–429&lt;/ref&gt; Peter Fay point out that at least one INA prisoner&amp;nbsp;– [[Burhan-ud-Din of Chitral|Burhanuddin]]&amp;nbsp;– may have deserved to be accused of torture, but his trial had been deferred on administrative grounds.&lt;ref name=Singh41&gt;{{harvnb|Singh|2003|pp=41}}&lt;/ref&gt; Those charged after the first celebrated courts-martial only faced trial for torture and murder or abetment of murder. Charges of treason were dropped for fear of inflaming public opinion.&lt;ref name=Fayp497&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=497}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In spite of aggressive and widespread opposition to continuation of the court martial, it was completed. All three defendants were found guilty in many of the charges and sentenced to deportation for life. The sentence however was never carried out. Immense public pressure, demonstrations, and riots forced Claude Auchinleck to release all three defendants. Within three months, 11,000 soldiers of the INA were released after cashiering and forfeiture of pay and allowance.&lt;ref name=Chaudhuri1953/&gt;&lt;ref name=Childs&gt;{{Harvnb|Childs|2000|p=28}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the recommendation of [[Louis Mountbatten, 1st Earl Mountbatten of Burma|Lord Mountbatten]] and with the agreement of Jawaharlal Nehru, former soldiers of the INA were not allowed to join the new [[Indian Armed Forces]] as a condition for independence.&lt;ref name=Ganguly/&gt;

==Post 1947==
Within India, the INA continues to be an emotive and celebrated subject of discussion.&lt;ref name=LebraROJR107&gt;{{Harvnb|Lebra|2008b|p=107}}&lt;/ref&gt; It continued to have a strong hold over the public psyche and the sentiments of the armed forces until as late as 1947.&lt;ref name=Green68&gt;{{Harvnb|Green|1948|p=68}}&lt;/ref&gt; It has been suggested that Shah Nawaz Khan was tasked with organising INA troops to train Congress volunteers at Jawaharlal Nehru's request in late 1946 and early 1947. After 1947, several members of the INA who were closely associated with Subhas Bose and with the INA trials were prominent in public life.&lt;ref name=&quot;Lebra2008p219&quot;/&gt; A number of them held important positions in independent India, serving as ambassadors immediately after independence: [[Abid Hasan (diplomat)|Abid Hasan]] in Egypt and Denmark, [[A. C. N. Nambiar]] in the [[Federal Republic of Germany]], [[Mehboob Hasan]] in Canada, [[Cyril John Stracey]] in the Netherlands, and [[N. Raghavan]] in Switzerland.&lt;ref name=Gordon369&gt;{{Harvnb|Gordon|1990|p=369}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mohan Singh was elected to the [[Rajya Sabha]], the upper house of the Indian Parliament. He worked for the recognition of the members of Indian National Army as &quot;freedom fighters&quot; in the cause of the nation's independence in and out of Parliament.&lt;ref name=Lebra1971p243&gt;{{Harvnb|Lebra|1971|p=243}}&lt;/ref&gt; Shah Nawaz Khan served as Minister of State for [[Indian Railways|Rail]] in the [[First Nehru ministry|first Indian cabinet]].&lt;ref name=Ram2010p197&gt;{{Harvnb|Ram|2010|p=197}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lakshmi Sahgal, Minister for Women's Affairs in the ''Azad Hind'' government, was a well known and widely respected public figure in India.&lt;ref name=LebraROJpxii&gt;{{Harvnb|Lebra|2008b|p=xii}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1971, she joined the [[Communist Party of India (Marxist)]] and was later elected the leader of the [[All India Democratic Women's Association]].&lt;ref name=Gupta2006p444&gt;{{Harvnb|Gupta|2006|p=444}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Forbes1999p276&gt;{{Harvnb|Forbes|1999|p=276}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Joyce Lebra]], an American historian, wrote that the rejuvenation of the [[Dravida Munnetra Kazhagam]], then a fledgling [[Tamils|Tamil]] political party in southern India, would not have been possible without participation of INA members.&lt;ref name=LebraROJ111&gt;{{Harvnb|Lebra|2008b|p=111}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Lakshmi Sahgal.jpg|thumb|200px|right| [[Lakshmi Sahgal]] in later life, at a political meeting in India]]
Some accounts suggest that the INA veterans were involved in training civilian resistance forces against the [[Nizam of Hyderabad|Nizam]]'s [[Razakars (Hyderabad)|Razakars]] prior to the execution of [[Operation Polo]] and annexation of Hyderabad.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| author =Menon, P
| work=The Hindu
| url=http://www.tribuneindia.com/2007/20070510/1857/main12.htm
|title=The States
| accessdate=2007-09-03
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
There are also suggestions that some INA veterans led Pakistani irregulars during the [[First Kashmir war]]. Mohammed Zaman Kiani served as Pakistan's political agent to [[Gilgit]] in late 1950s.&lt;ref name=Gordon369/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| publisher = Provisional Assembly of The Punjab (Lahore-Pakistan). Govt of Pakistan
| url=http://pap.gov.pk/legislators/last/dist2.htm
|title= Taj Muhammad Khanzada. Legislators from Attock.
| accessdate=2007-09-19
|archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20071101134400/http://pap.gov.pk/legislators/last/dist2.htm &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-11-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Of the very few ex-INA members who joined the Indian Armed Forces after 1947 [[R. S. Benegal]], a member of the Tokyo Boys, joined the [[Indian Air Force]] in 1952 and later rose to be an [[air commodore]].&lt;ref name=BenegalForeword&gt;{{Harvnb|Benegal|2013|p=Foreword}}&lt;/ref&gt; Benegal saw action in both [[1965 War|1965]] and [[Indo-Pakistani War of 1971]], earning a [[Maha Vir Chakra]], India's second highest award for valour.&lt;ref name=BharatRakshak&gt;{{cite web
| work= Bharat Rakshak
| url=http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/IAF/Database/Record/view.php?srnum=4220
|title=Air Commodore Ramesh Sakharam Benegal
| accessdate=2015-09-18
}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Malik Munawar Khan Awan|Malik Munawar Khan]], commander of 2nd Guerilla Battalion during INA's Imphal campaign, later joined Pak Army and commanded [[Pakistani Special Forces]] during [[Operation Gibraltar]] in 1965.

Among other prominent members of the INA, [[Ram Singh Thakur]], composer of a number of songs including the INA's regimental march [[Kadam Kadam Badaye Ja]], has been credited by some for the modern tune of the [[Indian national anthem]].&lt;ref name=Rediff&gt;{{cite web
| work= Rediff on the net
| url=http://www.rediff.com/news/feb/22anthem.htm
|title=Who composed the score for Jana Gana Mana? Gurudev or the Gorkha?
| accessdate=2015-09-18
}}&lt;/ref&gt; In independent [[Pakistan]]

Gurubaksh Singh Dhillon and Lakshmi Sahgal were later awarded theIndian civilian honours of [[Padma Bhushan]] and [[Padma Vibhushan]] respectively by the Indian Government in the 1990s.&lt;ref name=Raman2009p176&gt;{{Harvnb|Raman|2009|p=176}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=GopalGandhi2007p392&gt;{{Harvnb|Gandhi|2007|p=392}}&lt;/ref&gt; Lakshmi Sahgal was nominated for the [[President of India|Indian presidential election]] by communist parties in 2002. She was the sole opponent of [[A. P. J. Abdul Kalam]], who emerged victorious.&lt;ref name=KochanekandHardgravep74&gt;{{Harvnb|Kochanek|Hardgrave|2007|p=74}}&lt;/ref&gt; Subhas Bose himself was posthumously awarded [[Bharat Ratna]] in 1992, but this was later withdrawn over the controversy over the [[Death of Subhas Chandra Bose|circumstances of his death]].&lt;ref name=TOI&gt;{{cite web
| work= Times of India
| url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/home/sunday-times/Why-was-the-Bharat-Ratna-Award-given-to-Netaji-Subhash-Chandra-Bose-withdrawn-by-the-Supreme-Court-in-1992/articleshow/1353901.cms
|title=Why was the Bharat Ratna Award given to Netaji Subhash Chandra Bose withdrawn by the Supreme Court in 1992?
| accessdate=2015-09-18
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Malaya, notable members of the INA were involved in founding the [[Malaysian Indian Congress]] (MIC) in 1946; [[John Thivy]] was the founding president.&lt;ref name=Ooip136&gt;{{Harvnb|Ooi|2004|p=136}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Janaky Athi Nahappan]], second-in-command of the Rani of Jhansi Regiment, was also a founding member of the MIC and later became a noted welfare activist and a distinguished senator in the [[Dewan Negara]] of the [[Malaysian Parliament]]. The consolidation of trade unions in the form of [[National Union of Plantation Workers]] was led by ex-INA leaders.&lt;ref name=LebraROJ111/&gt; [[Rasammah Bhupalan]], also of the Rani of Jhansi Regiment, later became a well-known welfare-activist and a widely respected champion for [[women's rights]] in [[Malaysia]].&lt;ref name=LebraROJp103&gt;{{Harvnb|Lebra|2008b|p=103}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Relations==
{{See also|India in World War II}}

===Japanese Army===
The army's relationship to the Japanese was an uncomfortable one. Officers in the INA distrusted the Japanese. Leaders of the first INA sought formal assurances from Japan before committing to war. When these did not arrive, Mohan Singh resigned after ordering his army to disband; he expected to be sentenced to death. After Bose established ''Azad Hind'', he tried to establish his political independence from the regime that supported him. (He had led protests against the [[Mukden Incident|Japanese expansion into China]], and supported [[Chiang Kai-shek]] during the 1930s) ''Azad Hind'' depended on Japan for arms and materiel but sought to be as financially independent as possible, levying taxes and raising donations from Indians in Southeast Asia&quot;.&lt;ref name=Belle200&gt;{{Harvnb|Belle|2014|p=200}}&lt;/ref&gt; On the Japanese side, members of the high command had been personally impressed by Bose and were willing to grant him some latitude; more importantly, the Japanese were interested in maintaining the support of a man who had been able to mobilise large numbers of Indian expatriates&amp;nbsp;– including, most importantly, 40,000 of the 45,000 Indians captured by the Japanese at Singapore.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press_release | url=http://www.history.co.uk/explore-history/ww2/burma.html | title=Capture of INA | accessdate=12 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, Faye notes that interactions between soldiers in the field was different. Attempts to use Shah Nawaz's troops in road building and as porters angered the troops, forcing Bose to intervene with Mutaguchi. After the withdrawal from Imphal, the relations between both junior non-commissioned officers and between senior officers had deteriorated. INA officers accused the Japanese Army high command of trying to deceive INA troops into fighting for Japan. Conversely, Japanese soldiers often expressed disdain for INA soldiers for having changed their oath of loyalty. This mutual dislike was especially strong after the withdrawal from Imphal began; Japanese soldiers, suspicious that INA defectors had been responsible for their defeat, addressed INA soldiers as &quot;shameless one&quot; instead of &quot;comrade&quot; as previously had been the case.&lt;ref name=Toye203&gt;{{Harvnb|Toye|1959|p=203}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Azad Hind'' officials in Burma reported difficulties with the Japanese military administration in arranging supply for troops and transport for wounded men as the armies withdrew. Toye notes that local IIL members and ''[[Azad Hind Dal]]'' (local ''Azad Hind'' administrative teams) organised relief supplies from Indians in Burma at this time. As the situation in Burma became hopeless for the Japanese, Bose refused requests to use INA troops against Aung San's [[Burma National Army]], which had turned against Japan and was now allied with Commonwealth forces.&lt;ref name=Toye1959p231&gt;{{Harvnb|Toye|1959|p=231}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Destruction of INA Memorial 1945.jpg|right|thumb|200px|INA memorial in Singapore after demolition by Indian Army [[sapper]]s. ''Circa'' September 1945.]] &lt;!-- FAIR USE of Destruction_of_INA_Memorial_1945.jpg: see image description page at http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Destruction_of_INA_Memorial_1945.jpg for rationale --&gt;

===British-Indian Army===
{{See also|Jiffs}}
The first interaction of the INA with the British-Indian forces was during the months during the [[First Arakan offensive]], between December 1942 and March 1943. The morale of ''Sepoys'' during this time was low and knowledge about the INA was minimal. The INA's special services agents led a successful operation during this time in encouraging the Indian troops to defect to the INA. By the end of March 1945, however, the ''Sepoys'' in the British-Indian Army were reinvigorated and perceived the men of the INA to be savage turncoats and cowards. Senior British officers in the Indian Army considered them &quot;rabble&quot;.&lt;ref name=Toyexix/&gt; Historians [[Christopher Bayly]] and Tim Harper mention that sepoys in field units shot captured or wounded INA men, relieving their British officers of the complex task of formulating a formal plan for captured men.&lt;ref name=Marston2014p118&gt;{{Harvnb|Marston|2014|p=118}}&lt;/ref&gt; After Singapore was retaken, Mountbatten ordered the INA's war memorial to its fallen soldiers to be blown up.&lt;ref name=Fayp523&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=523}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As the story of the INA unfolded in post-war India, the view of Indian soldiers on the INA&amp;nbsp;– and on their own position during the war&amp;nbsp;– also changed.&lt;ref name=Edwards93&gt;{{Harvnb|Edwards|1963|p=93}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Raj observed with increasing disquiet and unease the spread of pro-INA sympathies within the troops of the British-Indian forces.&lt;ref name=Sarkar419/&gt; In February 1946, while the trials were still going on, a general strike by ratings of the Royal Indian Navy rapidly [[Bombay Mutiny|deteriorated into a mutiny]] incorporating ships and shore establishments of the RIN throughout India. The mutineers raised slogans invoking Subhas Bose and the INA, demanding and end to the trials. The mutiny received widespread public support.&lt;ref name=James598/&gt; In some places in the British-Indian Army, non-commissioned Officers started ignoring orders from British superiors. In [[Madras]] and [[Pune]] British garrisons faced revolts from within the ranks of the British-Indian Army. These were suppressed by force.&lt;ref name=James598&gt;{{Harvnb|James|2000|p=598}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=James596&gt;{{Harvnb|James|2000|p=596}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the conclusion of the first trial, when the sentences of deportation were commuted, Fay records Claude Auchinleck as having sent a &quot;personal and secret&quot; letter to all senior British officers, explaining:&lt;ref name=Fay517&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=517}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{quote|...&amp;nbsp;practically all are sure that any attempt to enforce the sentence would have led to chaos in the country at large, and probably to mutiny and dissension in the Army, culminating in its dissolution.}}

==Influence==

===WWII===

Fay concludes that the INA was not significant enough to beat the British-Indian Army by military strength. He also writes that the INA was aware of this and formulated its own strategy of avoiding set-piece battles, gathering local and popular support within India and instigating revolt within the British-Indian Army to overthrow the Raj.&lt;ref name=Fay138&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=138}}&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, the [[Forward Bloc]] underground movement within India had been crushed well before the offensives opened in the Burma–Manipur theatre, depriving the army of any organised internal support.&lt;ref name=Sarkar411/&gt; However,despite its small numerical strength and lack of heavy weapons, its special services group played a significant part in halting the [[First Arakan Offensive]] while still under Mohan Singh's command.&lt;ref name=Baylyl&amp;Harperforgottenarmiesp273&gt;{{Harvnb|Bayly|Harper|2005|p=273}}&lt;/ref&gt; The propaganda threat of the INA and lack of concrete intelligence on the unit early after the fall of Singapore made it a threat to Allied war plans in Southeast Asia, since it threatened to destroy the ''Sepoys''' loyalty to a British-Indian Army that was demoralised from continuing defeats.&lt;ref name=Fay410&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=410}}&lt;/ref&gt; There were reports of INA operatives successfully infiltrating Commonwealth lines during the Offensive. This caused British intelligence to begin the &quot;[[Jiffs]]&quot; propaganda campaign and to create &quot;''Josh''&quot; groups to improve the morale and preserve the loyalty of the sepoys as consolidation began to prepare for the defence of Manipur.&lt;ref name=Aldrich163&gt;{{Harvnb|Aldrich|2000|p=163}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Aldrich159&gt;{{Harvnb|Aldrich|2000|p=159}}&lt;/ref&gt; These measures included imposing a complete news ban on Bose and the INA that was not lifted until four days after the fall of Rangoon two years later.&lt;ref name=Fay218&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=218}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Sareen2004p40&gt;{{Harvnb|Sareen|2004|p=40}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the Japanese ''U-Go'' offensive towards Manipur in 1944, the INA played a crucial (and successful) role in diversionary attacks in Arakan and in the Manipur Basin itself, where it fought alongside Mutaguchi's 15th Army.&lt;ref name=Faye289&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=289}}&lt;/ref&gt; INA forces protected the flanks of the assaulting Yamamoto force at a critical time as the latter attempted to take Imphal.&lt;ref name=&quot;Toye1959207&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=Toye1959210&gt;{{Harvnb|Toye|1959|p=210}}&lt;/ref&gt;  During the Commonwealth Burma Campaign, the INA troops fought in the battles [[Battle of Irrawaddy|of Irrawaddy]] [[Battle of Meiktilla|and Meiktilla]],&lt;ref name=Fay316&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=316,317}}&lt;/ref&gt; supporting the Japanese offensive and tying down Commonwealth troops.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=332,333}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Slim|1961|p=425}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Indian independence===
{{See also|Bombay Mutiny}}
The first INA trial, which was held in public, became a rallying point for the independence movement from the autumn of 1945.&lt;ref name=Sarkar420/&gt;&lt;ref name=Sarkar411/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Fay 1993 p=496,498,499&quot;/&gt; The release of INA prisoners and the suspension of the trials came to be the dominant political campaign, superseding the campaign for freedom.&lt;ref name=BoseandJalal134&gt;{{Harvnb|Bose|Jalal|2004|p=134}}&lt;/ref&gt; Christopher Bayly notes that the &quot;INA was to become a much more powerful enemy of the British empire in defeat than it had been during its ill-fated triumphal march on Delhi.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Marston2014p118&quot;/&gt; The Viceroy's journal describes the autumn and winter of 1945–46 as &quot;The Edge of a Volcano&quot;.&lt;ref name=Sarkar411/&gt; The setting of the trial at Red Fort was taken by Indian public as a deliberate taunt by the British Raj over the vanquished INA, recalling the INA's battle cries of unfurling the Indian tricolour over the Red Fort.&lt;ref name=Toyexix/&gt; Many compared the trials to that of [[Bahadur Shah Zafar]], the last Mughal emperor tried in the same place after the failed [[1857 uprising]].&lt;ref name=Fay472&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=472}}&lt;/ref&gt; Support for the INA grew rapidly and their continued detention and news of impending trials was seen an affront to the movement for independence and to Indian identity itself.&lt;ref name=Singh99&gt;{{Harvnb|Singh|2003|p=99}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was further feared that the Congress would exploit the INA to gain mass support against the Raj and possibly start an armed struggle with weapons smuggled from Burma.&lt;ref name=Singh41/&gt;&lt;ref name=Marston129&gt;{{Harvnb|Marston|2014|p=129}}&lt;/ref&gt; Nehru was suspected of using INA men to train Congress volunteers.&lt;ref name=Singh41/&gt; The political effects of the INA trials were enormous and were felt around India as late as 1948, much to the chagrin of the Congress government in independent India,&lt;ref name=&quot;Green68&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Green|1948|p=54}}&lt;/ref&gt; which feared that pro-INA sympathies could help alternative sources of power.&lt;ref name=Jamesp596to598&gt;{{Harvnb|James|2000|pp=596–598}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Historians like [[Sumit Sarkar]], [[Sugata Bose]], [[Ayesha Jalal]] conclude that the INA trials and its after-effects brought a decisive shift in British policy towards independence Indian .&lt;ref name=BoseandJalal134/&gt;&lt;ref name=Sarkar412/&gt; Particularly disturbing was the overt and public support for the INA by the soldiers of the Indian Army and the mutinies.&lt;ref name=BoseandJalal134/&gt;&lt;ref name=Sarkar412&gt;{{Harvnb|Sarkar|1983|p=412}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Congress's rhetoric preceding the 1946 elections gave the Raj reasons to fear a revival of the [[Quit India Movement]] of 1942.&lt;ref name=Sarkar412/&gt; It was soon realised that the Indian Army could not be used to suppress such a movement as it had in 1942, principally because of nationalistic and political consciousness in the forces which was ascribed to the INA.&lt;ref name=Sarkar411/&gt;&lt;ref name=Hyam106/&gt; Gandhi noted:&lt;ref name=BoseandJalal134/&gt;
{{quote|...&amp;nbsp;the whole nation has been roused, even the regular forces have been stirred into a new political consciousness and begun to think in terms of independence&amp;nbsp;...}}

Facing problems in the British mainland and unable to muster enough forces of collaboration or coercion, the [[Cabinet mission of 1946]] was sent to negotiate the transfer of power.&lt;ref name=Sengupta84/&gt; Some historians cite Auchinleck's own assessment of the situation to suggest this shortened the Raj by at least fifteen to twenty years.&lt;ref name=Hyam106&gt;{{Harvnb|Hyam|2007|p=106}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Clement Attlee]], the British prime minister, reflecting on the factors that guided the British decision to relinquish the Raj in India, is said to have cited the effects of the INA and Bose's activities on the British-Indian Army and the [[Royal Indian Navy Mutiny|Bombay Mutiny]] as being the most important.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| author = Bhat D
| publisher = The Tribune
| url=http://www.tribuneindia.com/2006/20060212/spectrum/main2.htm
| title= RIN mutiny gave a jolt to the British
| accessdate=2007-09-02
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===British colonies===
{{See also|Royal Air Force mutiny}}
After the war ended, the story of the INA and the Indian Legion was seen as so inflammatory that, fearing mass revolts and uprisings across its empire, the British Government forbade the [[BBC]] from broadcasting their story.&lt;ref name=ThomsonBBC&gt;{{cite news
| author = Thomson M
| publisher = bbc.co.uk
| url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/3684288.stm
| title= Hitler's secret Indian Army
| accessdate=2007-09-02
| date=2004-09-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; The use of Indian troops for the restoration of Dutch and French rule in [[Vietnam]] and [[Indonesia]] fed into the already growing resentment within the forces.&lt;ref name=McMillan155&gt;{{Harvnb|McMillan|2006|p=155}}&lt;/ref&gt; Indian troops sent to suppress [[Sukarno]]'s agitations in Indonesia in 1946 rapidly identified with the nationalist sentiments in the previous Dutch colony.&lt;ref name=Sengupta84&gt;{{Harvnb|Sengupta|2012|p=84}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[South East Asia Command]] reported growing sympathy for the INA and dislike of the Dutch.&lt;ref name=Sengupta83and84&gt;{{Harvnb|Sengupta|2012|p=83,84}}&lt;/ref&gt; There were similar pro-nationalist sentiments among Indian troops sent to Vietnam, Thailand and Burma. This led to the realisation by 1946 that the British-Indian Army, the bulwark of the policing force in the British colonies, could not be used as an instrument of British power.&lt;ref name=Sengupta85&gt;{{Harvnb|Sengupta|2012|p=85}}&lt;/ref&gt; INA-inspired strikes emerged throughout Britain's colonies in Southeast Asia. In January 1946, [[Royal Air Force Mutiny|protests]] started at [[Royal Air Force]] bases in Karachi and spread rapidly to Singapore. This was followed by a full-scale mutiny by a British Army unit in Singapore. In British Malaya, men of the Parachute Regiment refused to obey orders from their officers.&lt;ref name=Sengupta82&gt;{{Harvnb|Sengupta|2012|p=82}}&lt;/ref&gt; Authors like Nilanjana Sengupta attribute these to a combination of dissatisfaction over pay and work conditions and conflicts of comradeship over the INA trials.&lt;ref name=Sengupta83&gt;{{Harvnb|Sengupta|2012|p=83}}&lt;/ref&gt; Former INA members in Malaya identified closely with the left-wing organisations in opposing British colonial authority. The majority of prominent left-wing union leaders in Malaya after the war were members of the INA.  The activities of the trade unions in the newly established Tamil schools were particularly influential, leading to the establishment of an inspector system by the British to supervise the curriculum and teaching in these schools.&lt;ref name=LebraROJ111/&gt; Joyce Lebra notes that the INA had a particularly strong unifying influence over ethnic Indians residing in Malaya. Lebra concludes that the experience of the INA was useful in challenging British authority in the post-war period in Malaya, and in improving the socio-economic conditions of the Indian community.&lt;ref name=LebraROJ111/&gt;

==Controversies==
{{Main|Controversies surrounding the Indian National Army}}
British and Commonwealth troops viewed the recruits as traitors and [[Collaboration with the Axis Powers during World War II|Axis collaborators]].&lt;ref name=Fay417/&gt;&lt;ref name=Fay547&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|pp=547}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Fay5&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=5}}&lt;/ref&gt; Almost 40,000 Indian soldiers in Malaya did not join the army and remained as PoWs. Many were sent to work in the [[Death Railway]], suffered hardships and nearly 11,000 died under Japanese internment.&lt;ref name=Menon1997p225&gt;{{Harvnb|Menon|1997|p=225}}&lt;/ref&gt; Many of them cited the oath of allegiance they had taken to the King among reasons not to join a Japanese-supported organisation, and regarded the recruits of the INA as traitors for having forsaken their oath. Commanders in the British-Indian Army like Wavell later highlighted the hardships this group of soldiers suffered, contrasting them with the troops of the INA.&lt;ref name=Menon1997p225/&gt; Many British soldiers held the same opinion.,&lt;ref name=Toye1959pxiv/&gt; Hugh Toye and Peter Fay point out that the First INA consisted of a mix of recruits joining for various reasons, such as nationalistic leanings, Mohan Singh's appeals, personal ambition or to protect men under their own command from harm.&lt;ref name=Fay207&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=207}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fay notes some officers like Shah Nawaz Khan were opposed to Mohan Singh's ideas and tried to hinder what they considered a collaborationist organisation.&lt;ref name=Fay87to100&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|pp=87–100}}&lt;/ref&gt;  However, both historians note that Indian civilians and former INA soldiers all cite the tremendous influence of Subhas Bose&amp;nbsp;and his appeal to patriotism&amp;nbsp; in rejuvenating the INA. Fay discusses the topic of loyalty of the INA soldiers, and highlights that in Shah Nawaz Khan's trial it was noted that officers of the INA warned their men the possibility of having to fight the Japanese after having fought the British, to prevent Japan exploiting post-war India.&lt;ref name=Aldrich163/&gt;&lt;ref name=Fay461to463&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|pp=461–463}}&lt;/ref&gt; Carl Vadivella Belle suggests in 2014 that among the local Indians and ex-British-Indian Army volunteers in Malaya, there was a proportion who joined on the threat of conscription to Japanese labour troop. Recruitment also offered local Indian labourers security from continual semi-starvation of the estates and served as a barrier against Japanese tyranny.&lt;ref name=Belle199/&gt;

INA troops were alleged to engage in or be complicit in torture of Allied and Indian prisoners of war.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fay423to424&quot;/&gt; Fay in his 1993 history analyses war-time press releases and field counter-intelligence directed at ''Sepoys''. He concludes that the ''Jiffs'' campaign promoted the view that INA recruits were weak-willed and traitorous Axis collaborators, motivated by selfish interests of greed and personal gain.  He concludes that the allegations of torture were largely products of the ''Jiffs'' campaign.&lt;ref name=Fay417/&gt;&lt;ref name=Fay426&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=426}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Fay290&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|pp=290–292}}&lt;/ref&gt; He supports his conclusion by noting that isolated cases of torture had occurred, but allegations of widespread practice of torture were not substantiated in the charges against defendants in the Red Fort trials.&lt;ref name=Fay427&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=427}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Fay461&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=461}}&lt;/ref&gt; Published memoirs of several veterans, including that of [[William Slim]], portray the INA troops as incapable fighters and as untrustworthy.&lt;ref name=Fay293&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|pp=293}}&lt;/ref&gt; Toye noted in 1959 that individual desertions occurred in the withdrawal from Imphal.&lt;ref name=Toyep203&gt;{{Harvnb|Toye|1959|pp=203}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fay concluded that stories of INA desertions during the battle and the initial retreat into Burma were largely exaggerated.&lt;ref name=Fay290to293&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|pp=290–293}}&lt;/ref&gt; The majority of desertions occurred much later, according to Fay, around the battles at Irrawaddy and later around Popa. Fay specifically discusses Slim's portrayal of the INA, pointing out what he concludes to be inconsistencies in Slim's accounts.&lt;ref name=Fay289to291&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|pp=289–291}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fay also discusses memoirs of Shah Nawaz, where Khan claims INA troops were never defeated in battle. Fay criticises this too as exaggerated. He concludes the opinions held by Commonwealth war veterans such as Slim were an inaccurate portrayal of the unit, as where those of INA soldiers themselves.&lt;ref name=&quot;Fay290&quot;/&gt; Harkirat Singh notes that British officers' personal dislike for Subhas Chandra Bose may have prejudiced their judgement of the INA itself.&lt;ref name=Singh41/&gt;

In independent India, the treatment of former INA soldiers by government and omission of the INA and the Red Fort trials from historical records of the period leading up to Indian independence in 1947 have come in from criticisms.&lt;ref name=SundayGuardian&gt;{{cite news
| author = Kumar, Navtan
| publisher = Sunday Guardian| url=http://www.sunday-guardian.com/investigation/sarkari-historians-ignored-the-ina| title= Sarkari historians ignored the INA
| accessdate=2015-10-23
| date=2015-04-18
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Indian activists like [[Samar Guha]], historians like [[Kapil Kumar]],&lt;ref name=SundayGuardian/&gt; as well as Indian parliamentarians&lt;ref name=Loksabhadebates1993p609&gt;{{harvnb|Lok Sabha|1993|p=609}}&lt;/ref&gt; allege that official histories of the independence movement largely omit events surrounding the INA&amp;nbsp;– especially the Red Fort trials and the Bombay Mutiny&amp;nbsp;– and ignore their significance in rejuvenating the independence movement and guiding British decisions to relinquish the Raj.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cohenp132&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=TOIShaikh&gt;{{cite news
| author = Shaikh, Sajid
| publisher = timesofindia.indiatimes.com| url=http://articles.timesofindia.indiatimes.com/2001-10-06/ahmedabad/27243040_1_mann-ina-netaji| title= INA's soldier lives in oblivion in Vadodara
| accessdate=2007-07-07
| date=2001-10-06
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=IndiaToday1/&gt; A history of the army and of ''Azad Hind'', written by Indian historian [[Pratul Chandra Gupta]] in 1950s at the request of the [[Indian Government]], was subsequently classified and not released until 2006.&lt;ref name=TOIPurabiRoy&gt;{{cite news
| author = Roy, Saugata
| publisher = Times of India| url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/city/kolkata/Netaji-became-my-guiding-light-my-only-inspiration/articleshow/46963427.cms| title= 'Netaji became my guiding light, my only inspiration'
| accessdate=2015-11-10
| date=2015-04-17
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Further criticisms have been made in recent years over the denial till 1980s of the &quot;freedom fighter's pension&quot; awarded to those in the Gandhian movement,&lt;ref name=Kunj1998p6&gt;{{harvnb|Kunju|1998|p=6}}&lt;/ref&gt; and over the general hardships and apathy surrounding the conditions of former INA soldiers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| author = Pratibha Chauhan
| publisher = Tribune News Service
| url=http://www.tribuneindia.com/1999/99may01/head6.htm
| title=INA hero gets shabby treatment.
| accessdate=2007-09-02
}}&lt;/ref&gt; This includes, for example, the circumstances surrounding the death and funeral of Ram Singh Thakuri, the composer of the INA's anthem [[Subh Sukh Chain|''Quami tarana'']]'', kadam kadam badaye ja''. These have been compounded by a number of conspiracy-theories and news reports in the past on agreements between the Indian political leadership to hand over its leader Subhas Chandra Bose as a [[war criminal]] if he was found to be alive.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| publisher = Hindustan Times. 17 November 1970
| url=http://www.hindustantimes.com/news/specials/Netaji/images/nov_17_70.gif
| title=Radhakrishnan met Netaji in Moscow, says witness.
| accessdate=2007-09-02
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| publisher = Hindustan Times. 23 January 1971
| url=http://www.hindustantimes.com/news/specials/Netaji/images/jan_23_71.gif
| title=Gandhi, others had agreed to hand over Netaji.
| accessdate=2007-09-02
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Sahgalinterview&gt;{{cite web
| author = Shahira Naim
| publisher = The Tribune
| url=http://www.tribuneindia.com/2005/20050612/spectrum/main1.htm
| title=The Bose I knew is a memory now&amp;nbsp;— Lakshmi Sahgal.
| accessdate=2007-09-02
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Indian government refused to declassify secret documents on Bose and the INA held in Indian archives for almost sixty years citing concerns of India's relations with foreign countries. This decision was revisited in October 2015 by [[Narendra Modi]] government. However, some files are said to have been destroyed altogether.&lt;ref name=TOI3&gt;{{cite web
|author1=Niyogi, Subhro  |author2=Sinha, Arunav
| publisher = Times of India
| url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/india/Was-Netaji-alive-till-1964/articleshow/49005391.cms
| title= Was Netaji alive till 1964?.
| accessdate=2015-10-23
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later historians have argued that, given the political aim and nature of the entire ''Azad Hind'' movement and especially the Indian National Army, Nehru's aim may have been to prevent politicisation of the army and assert civilian authority over the military.&lt;ref name=Ganguly&gt;{{cite web
| author = Sumit Ganguly
| publisher = Columbia University Press
| url=http://www.ciaonet.org/book/anderson/anderson10.html#note29
| title= Explaining India's Transition to Democracy.
| accessdate=2007-09-03
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

More recent controversies have risen from limited declassified Indian documents that revealed that the Nehru government kept Subhas Bose's family under strict surveillance for more than twenty years after Indian independence.&lt;ref name=IndiaToday1&gt;{{cite web
| author = Sandeep Unnithan
| publisher = India Today
| url=http://indiatoday.intoday.in/story/jawaharlal-nehru-netaji-subash-chandra-bose-spy-exclusive/1/429400.html
| title= Jawaharlal Nehru spied on Subhas Chandra Bose's family for 20 years
| accessdate=2015-09-19
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=TOI2&gt;{{cite web
| author = Himanshi Dhawan
| publisher = Times of India
| url=http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/india/Papers-reveal-Jawarharlal-Nehrus-hand-in-snooping-on-Netaji-Subhas-Chandra-Boses-kin/articleshow/46893279.cms
| title= Papers reveal Jawarharlal Nehru's hand in snooping on Netaji Subhas Chandra Bose's kin
| accessdate=2015-09-19
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Further controversy relates to the fate of the [[INA treasure controversy|''Azad Hind'' fortune]] Bose is said to have been travelling with it during in his last known journey. The treasure, a considerable amount of gold  ornaments and gems, is said to have been recovered from Bose's belongings following the fatal plane crash in Formosa that reportedly killed him.&lt;ref name=Indiatoday2/&gt; Despite repeated warnings from Indian diplomats in Tokyo, Nehru is said to have disregarded allegations that men previously associated with ''Azad Hind'' misappropriated the funds for personal benefit. Some of these are said to have travelled to Japan repeatedly with the approval of Nehru government and were later given government roles implementing Nehru's political and economic agenda.&lt;ref name=Indiatoday2/&gt; A very small portion of the alleged treasure was repatriated to India in the 1950s.&lt;ref name=Indiatoday2&gt;{{cite web
| author = Kavitha Muralidharan
| publisher = India Today
| url=http://indiatoday.intoday.in/story/netaji-subash-chandra-bose-wealth-lost/1/438113.html
| title= Who shrunk Netaji's fortune?
| accessdate=2015-09-19
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Commemorations==
{{See also|INA Martyr's Memorial|Former Indian National Army Monument}}
[[File:Former Indian National Army Monument.JPG|thumb|right|200px|The [[Commemorative plaque|plaque]] erected by the National Heritage Board at [[Esplanade Park]], marking the INA Monument site in [[Singapore]]]]

The INA is memorialised in the ''Swatantrata Sainani Smarak'', which is located at the [[Salimgarh Fort]] in [[Delhi]], adjacent to the Red Fort.&lt;ref name=Mehta2006p272&gt;{{Harvnb|Mehta|2006|p=272}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news | url=http://www.roseindia.net/travel/india/delhi/salimgarh-fort-delhi.shtml | title=On I-Day eve, India forgets INA memorial | work=Rose India | accessdate=12 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its exhibits include the Indian National Army uniform worn by Colonel Prem Sahgal, riding boots and coat buttons of Colonel Gurbaksh Singh Dhillon and photographs of Subhas Chandra Bose. A separate gallery holds material and photographs from excavations carried out by the [[Archaeological Survey of India]] inside the fort in 1995. The [[INA Martyr's Memorial|Indian National Army Memorial]] at Moirang, Manipur, commemorates the place where the flag of ''Azad Hind'' was raised by Col. Shaukat Hayat Malik. Moirang was the first Indian territory captured by the INA.

The INA War Memorial at Singapore commemorating the &quot;Unknown Warrior&quot; of the INA was unveiled by Bose in July 1945. Situated at the [[Esplanade Park]], it was destroyed on Mountbatten's orders when Allied troops reoccupied the city. In 1995, the National Heritage Board of Singapore, with financial donations from the Indian community in Singapore, erected the  [[Former Indian National Army Monument]] at the site where the old memorial stood . The site is now officially one of the historical sites of Singapore.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| publisher = National Heritage Board of Singapore| url=http://www.museum.org.sg/PE/sites_trails/civic_district_trail.html| title=Heritage Sites and Trails in Singapore| accessdate=2007-07-07
|archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20070928221937/http://www.museum.org.sg/PE/sites_trails/civic_district_trail.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-09-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The INA's [[battle cry]], ''[[Jai Hind]]'', was declared the &quot;national greeting&quot; of India by Nehru and remains a popular nationalist greeting.&lt;ref name=Desai2011&gt;{{Harvnb|Desai|2011|p=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Today it is used by all Indian prime ministers to conclude their [[Independence Day (India)|Independence Day]] speeches.&lt;ref name=Desai2011/&gt; The cry became independent India's [[Jai Hind Post-mark|first commemorative post mark]] on 15 August 1947.&lt;ref name=Bayanwala/&gt; The first [[Postage stamps and postal history of India|postage stamps]] issued by Independent India are called the ''Jai Hind'' series of stamps, showing the [[Indian flag]] with the letters ''Jai Hind'' in the top right hand corner.&lt;ref name=Bayanwala&gt;{{cite web
| author = Ashok Kumar Bayanwala
| publisher = Stamps of india
| url=http://stampsofindia.com/readroom/b002.htm
| title=Art in miniature
| accessdate=2011-08-11
}}&lt;/ref&gt; These were a part of t issued on 15 August 1947.&lt;ref name=Footprint&gt;{{cite news
| author =  Bhaskaran, S.T.
| work=The Hindu
| url=http://www.hindu.com/2000/12/16/stories/13161109.htm
| title= Footprints of history
| accessdate=2007-10-16
| location=Chennai, India
| date=2000-12-16
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Commemorative postage stamps were also issued by the Indian government in 1968 and 1993 respectively to commemorate the 25th and the 50th anniversaries of the establishment of ''Azad Hind'' at Singapore.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
| author =  Healey, Beth
| publisher = New York Times
|url=http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1D8173FF930A35751C1A96F948260
| title= Pastimes; Stamps
| accessdate=2007-10-16
| date=1989-12-03
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[India Posts|Department of Posts]] also includes the six unused [[Azad Hind stamps|''Azad Hind'' stamps]] in its commemorative book ''India's Freedom Struggle through India Postage Stamps''.&lt;ref name=Footprint/&gt; The ''Azad Hind Fauj Marg'' (Azad Hind Fauj Road) in [[New Delhi]] is named after the INA and houses the [[Netaji Subhas Institute of Technology]].&lt;ref name=DHNSIT&gt;{{cite web
| author = Mayank Verma
| publisher = Deccan Herald
| url=http://www.deccanherald.com/content/458948/sulahkul-vihar-residents-await-development.html
| title= Sulahkul Vihar residents await development
| accessdate=2011-08-11
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In popular culture==
{{Main|Indian National Army in popular culture}}
The Indian National Army remains a significant topic of discussion in the popular history of India; it is an emotive topic which has been the subject of numerous works of literature, art, and visual media within India and outside. Some of the earliest works in print media were created at the time of the INA trials. These include works of fiction like ''Jai Hind, the Diary of a Rebel Daughter of India'' published in 1945 by Amritlal Seth. The book, a work of fiction narrating the story of a recruit of the Rani of Jhansi Regiment, is believed to be loosely based on the story of Lakshmi Sahgal.&lt;ref name=Forbes214&gt;{{Harvnb|Forbes|1999|p=214}}&lt;/ref&gt; In later decades works by authors like [[Amitav Ghosh]], such as his book ''[[The Glass Palace]]'', have used the backdrop of the ''Azad Hind'' and the Japanese occupation of Burma for the narrative of the story.&lt;ref name=&quot;east&quot;&gt;Urquhart, James. (7 August 2000) The Independent ''Monday Book: A 'Doctor Zhivago' for the Far East&amp;nbsp;— Review of The Glass Palace.''&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[The Day of the Scorpion]]'' and ''[[The Towers of Silence]]'', the second and third books in [[Paul Mark Scott|Paul Scott]]'s ''[[Raj Quartet]]'', mention ''Jiffs'' in the political and social context in which the term found use in the [[Fourteenth Army (United Kingdom)|Eastern Army]] during the war.  The 1984 British TV series ''[[The Jewel in the Crown (TV series)|The Jewel in the Crown]]'', based on Scott's quartet, also includes the role of the INA as part of the political backdrop of the story.&lt;ref name=Fayp4&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In visual media, the INA has been the subject of a number of documentaries. ''The War of The Springing Tiger'' made by [[Granada Television]] for [[Channel 4]] in 1984 examined the role of the Indian National Army in the Second World War, the motivation of its soldiers and explored its role in the independence movement.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Fay|1993|p=ix}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| publisher = British Film Institute|
url=http://ftvdb.bfi.org.uk/sift/title/391314?view=synopsis|
title=Synopses The War of The Springing Tiger
| accessdate=2007-07-09
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
In 1999 Film India released a documentary, ''The Forgotten Army''. Directed by [[Kabir Khan (director)|Kabir Khan]] and produced by Akhil Bakshi, it followed what was called the ''Azad Hind Expedition'' between 1994 and 1995, retracing the route taken by the INA from Singapore to Imphal, before ending at Red Fort. Amongst the members of expedition team were Gurubaksh Singh Dhillon, Lakshmi Sahgal and Captain S.S. Yadava, an INA veteran and once the general secretary of the All India INA Committee. The documentary went on to win the Grand Jury Prize at the Film South Asia festival in 1999.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| author =Dutt, Nirupama
| publisher = Indian Express|
url=http://www.indianexpress.com/res/web/pIe/ie/daily/19980622/17351114.html|
title=A forgotten army marches again
| accessdate=2007-07-07
}}&lt;/ref&gt;
The [[National Archives of Singapore]] digitised its available resources in 2007 as ''Historical Journey of the Indian National Army''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| publisher = National Archives of Singapore| url=http://www.s1942.org.sg/s1942/indian_national_army/index.htm| title= Historical Journey of the Indian National Army
| accessdate=2007-07-07
}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 2004, the [[Indian Legion]] in Europe was the subject of a BBC magazine article authored by Mike Thomson, but it did not attempt to distinguish the differences between the Legion and the INA.&lt;ref name=ThomsonBBC/&gt; The ''[[Hindustan Times]]'', a large broadsheet in India, dedicates a part of its website to INA resources as ''Indian National Army in East Asia.''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
| author = Das Sitanshu
| publisher = Hindustan Times| url=http://www.hindustantimes.com/news/specials/Netaji/indiannationalarmy.htm| title=Indian National Army in East Asia
| accessdate=2007-07-07
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Indian cinema]] has also seen a number of films in many different [[Languages of India|Indian languages]], where the INA is a significant part of the narrative. These include ''Pahla Admi'' by [[Bimal Roy]] and ''Samadhi'' by Ramesh Saigal, both produced in 1950 based on fictional INA veterans.&lt;ref name=Bose146&gt;{{Harvnb|Bose|2006|p=146}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Dhawan&gt;{{cite web
| author =Dhawan, M.L.
| publisher = www.tribuneindia.com|
url=http://www.tribuneindia.com/2007/20070510/1857/main12.htm|
title=Freedom struggle through Hindi films
| accessdate=2007-07-09
}}&lt;/ref&gt; More recently, ''[[Indian (1996 film)|Indian]]'', a 1996 [[Tamil language|Tamil]] film directed by [[S. Shankar]], incorporates a lead character in its story who is a veteran of the INA. [[Shyam Benegal]] produced ''[[Netaji: The Forgotten Hero]]'' in 2004, which traces the last five years of Subhas Chandra Bose. Benegal describes the story of the INA in small details in his film whilst focusing on its leader.&lt;ref name=Dhawan/&gt; The film was also widely noted for [[A. R. Rahman]]'s music.  The INA's marching song, ''Kadam Kadam Badaye Ja'', has since become a famous patriotic song in India. Today it is in use as the regimental quick march of the [[Parachute Regiment (India)|Indian Parachute regiment]].&lt;ref name=Gaur185&gt;{{Harvnb|Gaur|2006|p=185}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Battaglione Azad Hindoustan]]
* [[Ekla Chalo Re]], a poem by [[Rabindranath Tagore]], publicized by Subhas Chandra Bose
* [[Indian Legion]]
* [[Rani of Jhansi Regiment]]
* [[Arzi Hukumat-e-Azad Hind]]
* [[Burma National Army]]
* [[All India Forward Bloc]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}
{{refbegin|2}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Aldrich
 | given1 = Richard J
 | year = 2000
 | title = Intelligence and the War Against Japan: Britain, America and the Politics of Secret Service
 | url =
 | publisher = Cambridge University Press
 | isbn = 0-521-64186-1
}}.
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Bayly
 | given1 = Christopher
 | surname2 = Harper
 | given2 = Tim
 | year = 2005
 | title = Forgotten Armies: Britain's Asian Empire and the War with Japan
 | url =
 | publisher = Penguin Books (UK) Ltd
 | isbn = 978-0-14-192719-0
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Belle
 | given1 = Carl Vadivelle
 | year = 2014
 | title = Tragic Orphans: Indians in Malaysia
 | url =
 | publisher = Institute of South-East Asian Studies
 | isbn =  978-981-4519-03-8
}}

* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Benegal
 | given1 = Ramesh Sakharam
 | year = 2013
 | title = Burma to Japan with Azad Hind: A War Memoir 1941–1945
 | url =
 | publisher = Lancer Publishers
 | isbn =  978-1-935501-11-4
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = van Der Bijil
 | given1 = Nick
 | year = 2013
 | title = Sharing the Secret: The History of the Intelligence Corps 1940–2010
 | url =
 | publisher = Pen and Sword Books
 | isbn = 978-1-84884-413-1
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Bose
 | given1 = Sugata
 | surname2 = Jalal
 | given2 = Ayesha
 | year = 2004
 | title = Modern South Asia: History, Culture, Political Economy
 | url =
 | publisher = Taylor &amp; Francis ltd
 | isbn = 978-0-415-30787-1
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Bose
 | given1 = Sugata.
 | year = 2006
 | title = A Hundred Horizons: Indian Ocean in the age of Global Empire
 | url =
 | publisher = Harvard University Press.
 | isbn = 0-674-02157-6
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Bose
 | given1 = Sugata
 | year = 2013
 | title = His Majesty's Opponent
 | url =
 | publisher = Harvard University Press
 | isbn = 0-674-04754-0
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Chaudhuri
 | given1 = Niradh C.
 | year = 1953
 | title = Subhas Chandra Bose-His Legacy and Legend
 | url = http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0030-851X%28195312%2926%3A4%3C349%3ASCBLAL%3E2.0.CO%3B2-V
 | publisher = Pacific Affairs, Vol. 26, No. 4. (Dec., 1953), pp. 349–357
 | isbn =
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Childs
 | given1 = David.
 | year = 2000
 | title = Britain Since 1945: A Political History
 | url =
 | publisher = Routledge.
 | isbn =0-415-24804-3
 | issn =
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Cohen
 | given1 = Stephen C.
 | year = 1971
 | title = The Indian Army: Its Contribution to the Development of a Nation
 | url =
 | publisher = University of California Press
 | isbn = 978-0-19-565316-8
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Cohen
 | given1 = Stephen C.
 | year = 1983
 | title = (in Book Reviews) Pacific Affairs, Vol. 56, No. 2. pp. 350–352
 | url =
 | publisher = New York, Columbia University Press, 
| isbn = 0-231-03995-6
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Desai
 | given1 = Meghnad
 | year = 2011
 | title = Rediscovery of India
 | url =
 | publisher = Penguin Books UK
 | isbn =  978-81-8475-566-4
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Edwards
 | given1 = Michael
 | year = 1963
 | title = The last years of British India
 | url =
 | publisher = London Cassell
 | isbn =  
}}
*{{Citation
 | surname1 = Fay
 | given1 = Peter W.
 | year = 1993
 | title = The Forgotten Army: India's Armed Struggle for Independence, 1942–1945
 | url =
 | publisher = Ann Arbor, University of Michigan Press.
 | isbn = 0-472-08342-2
}}
*{{Citation
 | surname1 = Forbes
 | given1 = Geraldine.
 | year = 1999
 | title = Women in Modern India. (Vol. 4)
 | url =
 | publisher = Cambridge University Press.
 | isbn = 978-0-521-65377-0
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Gandhi
 | given1 = Gopal
 | year = 2007
 | title = A Frank Friendship: Gandhi and Bengal : a Descriptive Chronology
 | url =
 | publisher = Seagull Boks
 | isbn = 978-1-905422-63-0
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Gaur
 | given1 = Mahendra
 | year = 2006
 | title = Indian Affairs Annual 2006
 | url =
 | publisher = Gyan Publishing House
 | isbn = 81-7835-529-9
}}
*{{Citation
 | surname1 = Ghosh
 | given1 = K.K.
 | year = 1969
 | title = The Indian National Army: Second Front of the Indian Independence Movement
 | url =
 | publisher = Meerut, Meenakshi Prakashan
 | isbn =
}}
*{{Citation
 | surname1 = Green
 | given1 = L.C.
 | year = 1948
 | title = The Indian National Army Trials. The Modern Law Review, Vol. 11, No. 1. (Jan., 1948), pp. 47–69.
 | url = 
 | publisher = London, Blackwell.
 | isbn = 
}}.
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Gordon
 | given1 = Leonard A.
 | year = 1990
 | title = Brothers against the Raj: ''A Biography of Indian Nationalists Sarat and Subhas Chandra Bose.''
 | url =
 | publisher = Rupa &amp; Co.
 | isbn = 978-81-7167-351-3
}}
*{{Citation
 | surname1 = Green
 | given1 = L.C.
 | year = 1948
 | title = The Indian National Army Trials. The Modern Law Review, Vol. 11, No. 1. (Jan., 1948), pp. 47–69
 | url =
 | publisher = London, Blackwell.
 | isbn =
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Gupta
 | given1 = Om
 | year = 2006
 | title = Encyclopaedia of India, Pakistan and Bangladesh.
 | url =
 | publisher = Gyan Publishing House
 | isbn= 81-8205-389-7
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Hyam
 | given1 = Ronald | year = 2007
 | title = Britain's Declining Empire: The Road to Decolonisation, 1918–1968
 | url =
 | publisher = Cambridge University Press.
 | isbn =  978-0-521-86649-1
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = James
 | given1 = Lawrence
 | year = 2000
 | title = Raj: The Making and Unmaking of British India
 | url =
 | publisher = St. Martin's Griffin.
 | isbn = 978-0-312-26382-9
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Kochanek
 | given1 = Stanley
 | surname2 = Hardgrave
 | given2 = Robert
 | year = 2007
 | title = India: Government and Politics in a Developing Nation
 | url =
 | publisher = Thomson Wadworth
 | isbn = 978-0-495-00749-4
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Kunju
 | given1 = N.
 | year = 1998
 | title = Free India's Army: Problems at 50
 | url =
 | publisher = Reliance Publishing House
 | isbn = 81-7510-087-7
}}.
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Lebra
 | given1 = Joyce C.
 | year = 1977
 | title = Japanese trained armies in South-East Asia
 | url =
 | publisher = New York, Columbia University Press
 | isbn = 0-231-03995-6
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Lebra
 | given1 = Joyce C.
 | year = 1971
 | title = Jungle alliance, Japanese and the Indian National Army.
 | url =
 | publisher = Asia Pacific Press
 | isbn = 0-231-03995-6
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Lebra
 | given1 = Joyce C.
 | year = 2008
 | title = Indian National Army and Japan
 | url =
 | publisher = Institute of South-East Asian Studies
 | isbn = 978-981-230-806-1
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Lebra
 | given1 = Joyce C.
 | year = 2008b
 | title = Women against the Raj- The Rani of Jhansi Regiment.
 | url =
 | publisher = Institute of South-East Asian Studies
 | isbn = 978-981-230-808-5
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Lok Sabha
 | given1 = 
 | year = 1993
 | title = Parliamentary debates
 | url =
 | publisher = Lok Sabha Secretariat
 | isbn = 
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Marston
 | given1 = Daniel
 | year = 2014
 | title = The Indian Army and End of the Raj
 | url =
 | publisher =  Cambridge University Press
 | isbn =  978-0-521-89975-8
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Mehta
 | given1 = Vinod
 | year = 2006
 | title = Delhi and NCR city guide
 | url =
 | publisher = Outlook Publishing (India).
 | isbn = 0-231-03995-6
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Menon | given1 = V.P.
 | year = 1997
 | title = The Transfer of Power in India
 | url =
 | publisher = Orient Blackswan.
 | isbn = 978-81-250-0884-2
}}
*{{Citation
 | surname1 = McMillan
 | given1 = R
 | year = 2006
 | title = The British Occupation of Indonesia: 1945–1946 Britain, The Netherlands and the Indonesian Revolution
 | url =
 | publisher = Routledge.
 | isbn = 0-415-35551-6
}}
*{{Citation
 | surname1 = Moreman
 | given1 = T.R.
 | year = 2005
 | title = The Jungle, the Japanese and the British Commonwealth Armies at War 1941–1945: Fighting Methods, Doctrine and Training for Jungle Warfare
 | url =
 | publisher = London and New York: Frank Cass.
 | isbn = 0-7146-4970-8
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Ooi
 | given1 = Keat Gin (Editor)
 | year = 2004
 | title = Southeast Asia: A Historical Encyclopedia, from Angkor Wat to East Timor, (Vol 1)
 | url =
 | publisher = ABC-CLIO
 | isbn = 1-57607-770-5
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Ram
 | given1 = Indrani Jagjivan
 | year = 2010
 | title = Milestones:A memoir
 | url =
 | publisher = Penguin Books India
 | isbn =  978-0-670-08187-5
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Raman
 | given1 = Sita Anantha
 | year = 2009
 | title = Women in India: A Social and Cultural History
 | url =
 | publisher = ABC-CLIO
 | isbn =  978-0-313-01440-6
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Sareen
 | given1 = Tilak Raj.
 | year = 1986
 | title = Japan and the Indian National Army
 | url =
 | publisher = Agram Prakashan
 | isbn = 
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Sareen
 | given1 = Tilak Raj.
 | year = 1996
 | title = Japan and the Indian National Army
 | url =
 | publisher = Mounto Publishing House
 | isbn = 
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Sengupta
 | given1 = Nilanjana
 | year = 2012
 | title = A Gentleman's Word: The Legacy of Subhas Chandra Bose in Southeast Asia
 | url =
 | publisher = ISEAS Publishing
 | isbn = 978-981-4379-75-5
}}
*{{Citation
 | surname1 = Singh
 | given1 = Harkirat
 | year = 2003
 | title = INA Trials and the Raj
 | url =
 | publisher = Atlantic publishers.
 | isbn = 81-269-0316-3
}}
*{{Citation
 | surname1 = Slim
 | given1 = W.
 | year = 1961
 | title = Defeat Into Victory
 | url =
 | publisher = New York, David McKay.
 | isbn = 1-56849-077-1
}}
*{{Citation
 | surname1 = Sarkar
 | given1 = Sumit
 | year = 1983
 | title = Modern India, 1885–1947
 | url =
 | publisher =  Delhi:Macmillan
 | isbn = 978-0-333-90425-1
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Tojo
 | given1 = Hideki (Premier) .
 | year = 1943
 | title = Axis War Makes Easier Task of Indians. Chandra Bose's Berlin Speech. Syonan Simbun
 | url =
 | publisher = Domei
 | isbn =
}}
*{{Citation
 | surname1 = Sareen
 | given1 = Tilak Raj
 | year = 2004
 | title = Indian National Army
 | url =
 | publisher = Gyan Publishing House.
 | isbn = 81-212-0833-5
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Toye
 | given1 = Hugh
 | year = 1959
 | title = The Springing Tiger: A Study of the Indian National Army and of Netaji
 | url =
 | publisher = Allied Publishers
 | isbn = 978-81-8424-392-5
}}
* {{Citation
 | surname1 = Toye
 | given1 = Hugh
 | year = 2007
 | title = Subhash Chandra Bose
 | url =
 | publisher = JAICO Publishing house
 | isbn = 81-7224-401-0
}}

{{refend}}

==Further reading==
* &quot;History of the Indian National Army (1966)&quot; by  Kalyan Kumar Ghosh
* &quot; The Indian National Army and Japan (June 2008)&quot; by Joyce C Lebra
*''The Springing Tiger:A study of a Revolutionary'' by Hugh Toye
* ''Jungle alliance, Japan and the Indian National Army'' / Joyce C. Lebra, Singapore, Donald Moore for Asia Pacific Press,1971
* ''Burma: The Forgotten War'', [[Jon Latimer]], London: John Murray, 2004. ISBN 978-0-7195-6576-2
* ''Japan's Greater East Asia Co-prosperity Sphere in World War II: selected readings and documents'' / edited and introduced by Joyce C. Lebra, Kuala Lumpur; New York: Oxford University Press, 1975
* ''Brothers Against the Raj --- A biography of Indian Nationalists Sarat and Subhas Chandra Bose'' / Leonard A. Gordon, Princeton University Press, 1990
* ''A Concise History of India'' / Barbara D. Metcalf and Thomas R. Metcalf
* ''A History of India'' / Hermann Kulke and Dietmar Rothermund
* ''The Glass Palace'' / Amitav Ghosh, London: HarperCollins, 2001

==External links==
* [http://en.banglapedia.org/index.php?title=Indian_National_Army From Banglapedia]
* [http://www.kamat.com/kalranga/itihas/bose.htm Article on Bose]
* [http://www.yorozubp.com/netaji/ Speeches of Netaji]
* [http://www.s-asian.cam.ac.uk/govt.html Centre of South Asian Studies, University of Cambridge]
* [http://dblife.cs.wisc.edu/person/S._C._Bose Centre of South Asian Studies, University of Wisconsin]
* [http://www.hindustantimes.com/news/specials/Netaji/netajihomepage.shtml Mystery behind Netaji's Disappearance – 2]
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/3684288.stm BBC Report: Hitler's secret Indian army]
* {{YouTube|XZ-Cjv1rnTM|Kadam kadam bhadaye ja – The INA song}}
{{Azad Hind Fauj}}
{{Subhas Chandra Bose}}
{{Indian independence movement}}
{{World War 2}}

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Subhas Chandra Bose]]
[[Category:Indian National Army| ]]
[[Category:Indian independence movement]]
[[Category:Indian diaspora in Singapore]]
[[Category:South-East Asian theatre of World War II]]
[[Category:Disbanded armies]]
[[Category:National liberation armies]]
[[Category:Military units and formations in British Malaya in World War II]]</text>
      <sha1>e0uvvmpva8r5s1rsumnqelpvfwfn3xv</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
