<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>John B. Floyd</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1209774</id>
    <revision>
      <id>735864427</id>
      <parentid>733719261</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-23T16:15:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>206.206.158.208</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Civil War */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17782">{{refimprove|date=October 2013}}
{{Infobox US Cabinet official
|name=John Buchanan Floyd
|image=John Buchanan Floyd.jpg
|order=31st
|title=[[Governor of Virginia]]
|term_start=January 1, 1849
|term_end=January 16, 1852
|predecessor=[[William Smith (Virginia governor)|William Smith]]
|successor=[[Joseph Johnson (Virginia politician)|Joseph Johnson]]
|order2=24th
|title2=[[United States Secretary of War]]
|term_start2=March 6, 1857
|term_end2=December 29, 1860
|president2=[[James Buchanan]]
|predecessor2=[[Jefferson Davis]]
|successor2=[[Joseph Holt]]
|office3=Member of the [[Virginia House of Delegates]]
|term3=1847-1849&lt;br&gt;1853
|birth_date={{birth date|1806|6|1|mf=y}}
|birth_place=[[Blacksburg, Virginia]], US
|death_date={{death date and age|1863|8|26|1806|6|1}}
|death_place=[[Abingdon, Virginia]], US
|party=[[United States Democratic Party|Democratic]]
|spouse=Sally Buchanan Preston
|alma_mater=[[University of South Carolina|South Carolina College]]
|profession=Lawyer, Politician
|allegiance= {{flag|Confederate States of America|1863}}
|branch={{flagicon|Virginia|1861}} Provisional Army of Virginia&lt;br /&gt;{{army|CSA}}
|serviceyears=1861 - 1863
|rank=[[File:Confederate States of America General.png|35px]] [[Brigadier General (CSA)]]
|battles=[[American Civil War]]
*[[Battle of Kessler's Cross Lanes]]
*[[Battle of Carnifex Ferry]]
*[[Battle of Fort Donelson]]
}}
'''John Buchanan Floyd''' (June 1, 1806 – August 26, 1863) was the [[List of Governors of Virginia|31st]] [[Governor of Virginia]], [[U.S. Secretary of War]], and the [[Confederate States Army|Confederate]] general in the [[American Civil War]] who lost the crucial [[Battle of Fort Donelson]].

==Early life==
John Buchanan Floyd was born at [[Smithfield (Blacksburg, Virginia)|Smithfield]] estate, [[Blacksburg, Virginia]]. He was the son of [[John Floyd (Virginia politician)|John Floyd]] (1783–1837), who served as a representative in [[U.S. House of Representatives|Congress]] from 1817 to 1829 and [[governor of Virginia]] from 1830 to 1834.

After graduating from [[South Carolina College]] in 1826 (by some accounts 1829), Floyd practiced law in his native state and at [[Helena, Arkansas]], where he lost a large fortune and his health in a cotton-planting venture. In 1839, he returned to Virginia and settled in [[Washington County, Virginia|Washington County]], which he represented in the [[Virginia House of Delegates]] in 1847–49 and again in 1853. From 1849 to 1852, he was governor of [[Virginia]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.politicalgraveyard.com/bio/fleury-flye.html|title=The Political Graveyard: Index to Politicians: Fletman to Flye|first=Lawrence|last=Kestenbaum|publisher=|accessdate=2 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; As governor, he recommended to the legislature the enactment of a law laying an import tax on the products of states that refused to surrender fugitive slaves owned by Virginian masters.

He married his cousin, Sally Preston, daughter of [[Francis Preston]] and they had no children.&lt;ref&gt;Floyd, Nicholas Jackson. Biographical genealogies of the Virginia-Kentucky Floyd families: with notes of some collateral branches. Williams and Wilkins company (Virginia), 1912 page 77&lt;/ref&gt; It is claimed that he did have a daughter, Josephine, who married [[Robert James Harlan]] in the 1852. Harlan was a slave of Kentucky politician [[James Harlan (congressman)|James Harlan]] and may have been James' son.  In the 1850s, Robert Harlan was living as a free person in Cincinnati, Ohio.&lt;ref&gt;Gatewood, Willard B. Aristocrats of Color: The Black Elite, 1880-1920. Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1990, p 118&lt;/ref&gt;

==Secretary of War==
[[File:Buchanan Cabinet.jpg|thumb|left|300px|''President Buchanan and his Cabinet''&lt;br /&gt;From left to right: [[Jacob Thompson]], [[Lewis Cass]], John B. Floyd, [[James Buchanan]], [[Howell Cobb]], [[Isaac Toucey]], [[Joseph Holt]] and [[Jeremiah S. Black]], (c. 1859)]]
In March 1857, Floyd became [[United States Secretary of War|Secretary of War]] in the cabinet of [[President of the United States|President]] [[James Buchanan]], where his lack of administrative ability was soon apparent, including the poor execution of the [[Utah War|Utah Expedition]]. Floyd is implicated in the scandal of the &quot;Abstracted Indian Bonds&quot; which broke at the end of 1860 as the Buchanan Administration was reaching its end. His wife's nephew Godard Bailey, who worked in the Interior Department and who removed bonds from the Indian Agency safe during 1860, was also implicated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://hdl.handle.net/2027/nyp.33433022848331|title=Abstracted Indian trust bonds ...Report ... [and Supplemental report]|publisher=[Washington,|accessdate=2 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Among the recipients of the money was Russell, Majors &amp; Waddell,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nytimes.com/1861/02/13/news/robbery-indian-bonds-report-special-congressional-committee-culpability.html|title=THE ROBBERY OF INDIAN BONDS.; Report of the Special Congressional Committee. Culpability of Secretary Floyd, Mr.Russell, and Mr. Bailey. THE NEGOTIATIONS BETWEEN MR. RUSSELL AND MR. BAILEY. MR. BAILEY'S CONFESSION. A UNITED STATES SENATOR THE MEDIUM THROUGH WHICH THE FRAUD IS DISCLOSED. AUDITOR FULLER THE CAUSE OF THE EXPOSURE OF THE FRAUD. THE DISPOSITION OF THE BONDS. HOW THE BONDS WERE DISPOSED OF. THE APPEARANCE OF MR. RUSSELL BEFORE THE COMMITTEE. RUSSELL'S BUSINESS MAN MAKES HIMSELF SCARCE. `USSELL BEFORE THE COMMITTEE. THE ACCEPTANCES ISSUED BY THE SECRETARY OF WAR. WHAT WAS DONE WITH THE ACCEPTANCES. FURTHER LIGHT ON GOV. FLOYD'S PROCEEDINGS. MR. RUSSELL'S ESTIMATE. PECULIAR RECORDS IN THE WAR DEPARTMENT. PAYMENTS TO RUSSELL, MAJORS &amp; WADDELL. COMMENTS ON GOV. FLOYD'S LETTER. IMPORTANT TESTIMONY OF SENATOR BENJAMIN-- BUCHANAN NOTIFIED OF GOV. FLOYD'S SYSTEM OF ISSUING ACCEPTANCES. INTERVIEW WITH GOV. FLOYD. GOV. FLOYD CONTINUES HIS OLD HABIT. RECOMMENDATIONS FOR NEW LEGISLATION.|date=13 February 1861|work=The New York Times|accessdate=2 July 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; a government contractor that held, among its contracts, the pony express. In December 1860, on ascertaining that Floyd had honored heavy drafts made by government contractors in anticipation of their earnings, the president requested his resignation. Several days later Floyd was indicted for malversation in office, although the indictment was overruled in 1861 on technical grounds. There is no proof that he profited by these irregular transactions; in fact, he went out of the office financially embarrassed.{{Citation needed|date=May 2012}}

Although he had openly opposed [[secession]] before the election of [[Abraham Lincoln]], his conduct after the election, especially after his breach with Buchanan, fell under suspicion, and he was accused in the press of having sent large stores of government arms to Federal arsenals in the South in the anticipation of the Civil War.

[[Ulysses Grant|Grant]] in his postwar ''Personal Memoirs'' said:

{{Quotation|Floyd, the Secretary of War, scattered the army so that much of it could be captured when hostilities should commence, and distributed the cannon and small arms from Northern arsenals throughout the South so as to be on hand when treason wanted them.|''Personal Memoirs of Ulysses S. Grant''}}

After his resignation, a congressional commission in the summer and fall of 1861 investigated Floyd's actions as Secretary of War. All of his records of orders and shipments of arms from 1859 to 1860 were examined. It is recorded that in response to John Brown's raid on Harper's Ferry he bolstered the Federal arsenals in some Southern states by over 115,000 muskets and rifles in late 1859. He also ordered heavy ordnance to be shipped to the Federal forts in Galveston Harbor, Texas, and the new fort on Ship Island off the coast of Mississippi.&lt;ref&gt;[[Official Records of the American Civil War|Official Records]], Series III, Vol. I.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the last days of his term, he apparently had an intention to send these heavy guns, but his orders were revoked by the president.

His resignation as secretary of war, on December 29, 1860, was precipitated by the refusal of Buchanan to order Major [[Robert Anderson (Civil War)|Robert Anderson]] to abandon [[Fort Sumter]], which eventually led to the start of the war. On January 27, 1861, he was indicted by the [[District of Columbia]] [[grand jury]] for conspiracy and fraud. Floyd appeared in criminal court in Washington, D.C., on March 7, 1861, to answer the charges against him. According to ''[[Harper's Weekly]]'', the indictments were thrown out.

{{Quotation|THE INDICTMENTS AGAINST FLOYD QUASHED. The indictments against Ex-Secretary Floyd have been quashed in the Court at Washington, on the ground—first, that there was no evidence of fraud on his part; and second, that the charge of malfeasance in the matter of the Indian bonds was precluded from trial by the act of 1857, which forbids a prosecution when the party implicated has testified before a Committee of Congress touching the matter.|''Harper's Weekly''|March 30, 1861}}

==Civil War==
[[File:GenJBFloyd.jpg|thumb|General John B. Floyd]]
After the secession of Virginia, Floyd was commissioned a [[Major General (CSA)|major general]] in the Provisional Army of Virginia, but on May 23, 1861, he was appointed a [[Brigadier General (CSA)|brigadier general]] in the [[Confederate States Army]] (CSA). He was first employed in some unsuccessful operations in the [[Kanawha County, West Virginia|Kanawha Valley]] of western Virginia under [[Robert E. Lee]], where he was both defeated and wounded in the arm at the [[Battle of Carnifex Ferry]] on September 10.

General Floyd blamed Brigadier General [[Henry A. Wise]] for the Confederate loss at the [[Battle of Carnifex Ferry]], stating that Wise refused to come to his aid.&lt;ref name=gazette&gt;Civil War Daily Gazette Confederate General Henry Wise Relieved of Duty; &quot;Contraband&quot; Allowed in Navy. http://civilwardailygazette.com/2011/09/25/confederate-general-henry-wise-relieved-of-duty-contraband-allowed-in-navy/ Retrieved November 21, 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Virginia House of Delegates|Virginia Delegate]] [[Mason Mathews]], whose son [[Alexander F. Mathews]] was Wise's aide-de-camp, spent several days in the camps of both Wise and Floyd to seek resolution to an escalating feud between the two generals. Afterward he wrote to [[President of the Confederate States of America|President]] [[Jefferson Davis]] urging that both men be removed, stating &quot;I am fully satisfied that each of them would be highly gratified to see the other annihilated.&quot; &lt;ref name=Rice&gt;Rice, Otis K. 1986. A History of Greenbrier County. Greenbrier Historical Society, p. 264&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Rebellion&gt;Cowles, Calvin Duvall (1897). &quot;The War of Rebellion: A compilation of the official records of the Union and Confederate Armies. Government Print Office: 1897. Retrieved from http://ebooks.library.cornell.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?c=moawar&amp;cc=moawar&amp;idno=waro0005&amp;node=waro0005%3A3&amp;view=image&amp;seq=880&amp;size=100&lt;/ref&gt; Davis subsequently removed Wise from his command of the western Virginia region, leaving Floyd as the region's unquestioned superior officer.&lt;ref name=gazette/&gt;

In January 1862, he was dispatched to the [[Western Theater of the American Civil War|Western Theater]] to report to General [[Albert Sidney Johnston]] and was given command of a division. Johnston sent Floyd to reinforce [[Fort Donelson]] and assume command of the post there. Floyd assumed command of Fort Donelson on February 13 just two days after the Union army had arrived at that spot, also becoming the third post commander within a week. Fort Donelson protected the crucial [[Cumberland River]] and, indirectly, the manufacturing city of [[Nashville, Tennessee|Nashville]] and Confederate control of [[Middle Tennessee]]. It was the companion to [[Battle of Fort Henry#Fort Henry|Fort Henry]] on the nearby [[Tennessee River]], which, on February 6, 1862, was captured by [[Union Army]] Brigadier General [[Ulysses S. Grant]] and river gunboats. Floyd was not an appropriate choice to defend such a vital point, having political influence, but virtually no military experience. General Johnston had other experienced, more senior, generals ([[P.G.T. Beauregard]] and [[William J. Hardee]]) available and made a serious error in selecting Floyd. Floyd had little military influence on the [[Battle of Fort Donelson]] itself, deferring to his more experienced subordinates, Brigadier Generals [[Gideon J. Pillow]] and [[Simon Bolivar Buckner, Sr.|Simon Bolivar Buckner]]. As the Union forces surrounded the fort and the town of [[Dover, Tennessee|Dover]], the Confederates launched an assault on February 15 in an attempt to open an escape route. Although successful at first, indecision on General Pillow's part left the Confederates in their trenches, facing growing reinforcements for Grant.

{{Quotation|General Floyd, the commanding officer, who was a man of talent enough for any civil position was no soldier, and possibly, did not possess the elements of one. He was further unfitted for command for the reason that his conscience must have troubled him and made him afraid. As Secretary of War, he had taken a solemn oath to maintain the Constitution of the United States and uphold the same against all enemies. He had betrayed that trust.|''Personal Memoirs of Ulysses S. Grant''}}

Early in the morning of February 16, at a [[council of war]], the generals and field officers decided to surrender their army. Floyd, concerned that he would be arrested for treason if captured by the Union Army, turned his command over to Pillow, who immediately turned it over to Buckner. Colonel [[Nathan Bedford Forrest|N. B. Forrest]] and his entire Tennessee cavalry regiment escaped while Pillow escaped on a small boat across the Cumberland. The next morning Floyd escaped by steamboat with the [[36th Virginia Infantry|36th Virginia]] and [[51st Virginia Infantry]] regiments, two artillery batteries and elements of the other units from his old command. He safely reached Nashville, having escaped just before Buckner surrendered to Grant in one of the greatest strategic defeats of the Civil War. He never satisfactorily explained upon what principles he appropriated all the transportation on to the use of his particular command&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|series=Battles and Leaders of the Civil War| title=The Capture of Fort Donelson|first= Lew, Major-General, USV|last=Wallace|volume=1|page=426}}&lt;/ref&gt; Floyd was relieved of his command by [[President of the Confederate States|Confederate President]] [[Jefferson Davis]], without a court of inquiry, on March 11, 1862. He resumed his commission as a major general of Virginia Militia, but his health soon failed and he died a year later at [[Abingdon, Virginia]], where he is buried in Sinking Spring Cemetery.

==In memoriam==
[[Floyd County, Georgia|Floyd County]] in northwest Georgia, home to the cities of Rome and Cave Spring, is named for his ancestor, [[United States Congressman]] [[John Floyd (Georgia politician)|John Floyd]].

[[Camp Floyd]], a U.S. Army post near [[Fairfield, Utah]] from July 1858 to July 1861, was originally named after Floyd.

==See also==
* [[List of American Civil War generals (Confederate)]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==

{{more footnotes|date=April 2008}}
* Eicher, John H., and [[David J. Eicher]], ''Civil War High Commands.'' Stanford: Stanford University Press, 2001. ISBN 978-0-8047-3641-1.
* Gott, Kendall D. ''Where the South Lost the War: An Analysis of the Fort Henry—Fort Donelson Campaign, February 1862''. Mechanicsburg, PA: Stackpole Books, 2003. ISBN 0-8117-0049-6.
* Sifakis, Stewart. ''Who Was Who in the Civil War.'' New York: Facts On File, 1988. ISBN 978-0-8160-1055-4.
* U.S. War Department. [http://ehistory.osu.edu/osu/sources/records/list.cfm ''The War of the Rebellion'']: ''a Compilation of the [[Official Records of the American Civil War|Official Records]] of the Union and Confederate Armies''. Washington, DC: U.S. Government Printing Office, 1880–1901.
* [[Ezra J. Warner (historian)|Warner, Ezra J.]] ''Generals in Gray: Lives of the Confederate Commanders.'' Baton Rouge: Louisiana State University Press, 1959. ISBN 978-0-8071-0823-9.
*{{EB1911}}

==External links==
*[http://encyclopediavirginia.org/Floyd_John_B_1806-1863 John B. Floyd in ''Encyclopedia Virginia'']
*[http://ead.lib.virginia.edu/vivaead/published/lva/vi01966.html A Guide to the Executive Papers of Governor John Buchanan Floyd, 1849-1851] at [http://www.lva.virginia.gov/ The Library of Virginia]

{{s-start}}
{{s-off}}
{{succession box
| before= [[William Smith (Virginia governor)|William Smith]]
| title= [[Governor of Virginia]]
| years= 1849–1852
| after= [[Joseph Johnson (Virginia politician)|Joseph Johnson]]
}}
{{U.S. Cabinet official box
| before= [[Jefferson Davis]]
| after= [[Joseph Holt]] 
| years= 1857–1860 
| president= [[James Buchanan]]
| department= Secretary of War}}
{{s-end}}
{{Governors of Virginia}}
{{USSecWar}}
{{Buchanan cabinet}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Floyd, John Buchanan}}
[[Category:1806 births]]
[[Category:1863 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Blacksburg, Virginia]]
[[Category:American people of Welsh descent]]
[[Category:Virginia Democrats]]
[[Category:Confederate States Army generals]]
[[Category:Members of the Virginia House of Delegates]]
[[Category:Governors of Virginia]]
[[Category:United States Secretaries of War]]
[[Category:People of Virginia in the American Civil War]]
[[Category:People from Abingdon, Virginia]]
[[Category:People of the Utah War]]
[[Category:Buchanan administration cabinet members]]
[[Category:Democratic Party state governors of the United States]]
[[Category:19th-century American politicians]]</text>
      <sha1>jebfpj85rc9bh8hhx0egbuwbp29pkk1</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
