<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Military history of India</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1876147</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750148208</id>
      <parentid>749208087</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-18T02:15:41Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GreenC bot</username>
        <id>27823944</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>1 archive template merged to {{[[template:webarchive|webarchive]]}} ([[User:Green_Cardamom/Webarchive_template_merge|WAM]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="93754">{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2013}}
{{Use Indian English|date=January 2016}}
{{HistoryOfSouthAsia}}
The earliest known reference to armies in what today is India are millennia ago in the [[Vedas]] and the epics [[Ramayana]] and [[Mahabaratha]]. From the ancient period to the 19th century, a succession of [[List of Indian monarchs|powerful dynasties and empires]] came to be and some were challenged by lesser Indian rulers who also struggled for land and power through warring. The British [[Colonial India|colonised]] India during the 19th century.

The predecessors to the contemporary [[Army of India]] were many: the [[sepoy]] [[regiment]]s, native cavalry, irregular horse and [[Indian Army Corps of Engineers|Indian sapper and miner companies]] raised by the three [[Presidencies of British India|British presidencies]]. The Army of India was raised under the [[British Raj]] in the 19th century by taking the erstwhile presidency armies, merging them, and bringing them under the Crown. The British Indian Army fought in both World Wars.

The armed forces succeeded the [[:Category:Military of British India|military of British India]] following India's independence in 1947. After [[World War II]], many of the wartime troops were discharged and units disbanded. The reduced armed forces were partitioned between India and Pakistan. The Indian armed forces fought [[Indo-Pakistani Wars|in all three wars against Pakistan]] and a [[Sino-Indian War|war with the People's Republic of China]]. India also fought in the [[Kargil War]] with Pakistan in 1999, the [[high altitude|highest altitude]] [[mountain warfare]] in history. The Indian Armed Forces have participated in several [[United Nations]] peacekeeping operations and are presently the second largest contributor of troops to the peacekeeping force.

==The Vedic period==
[[File:EpicIndia.jpg|thumb|Map of India during the time of the [[Ramayana]] and [[Mahabharata]].]]
[[File:Rāma going into battle.jpg|thumb|left|[[Rāma]] going into battle.]]
[[File:Kurukshetra.jpg|thumb|left|Manuscript illustration of the [[Battle of Kurukshetra]].]]
The [[Rigvedic tribes]] of [[Indo-Aryans]] were led by their kings (''[[raja]]'') and engaged in wars with each other and other tribes. They used [[bronze]] weapons and [[horse]]-drawn spoke-wheeled [[chariot]]s described prominently in the [[Rigveda]]. The main share from the booty obtained during [[cattle raid]]s and battles went to the chief of the tribe. The warriors belonged to the [[Kshatriya]] [[varna (Hinduism)|varna]].

The [[Vedas]] and other associated texts dating to the post-Rigvedic ([[Iron Age]]) [[Vedic civilisation|Vedic period]] (ca. 1100–500 BC) contain the earliest written references to armies in India. The earliest known application of [[war elephant]]s dates to this period; the animals are mentioned in several [[Vedic Sanskrit]] hymns.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.history-of-india.net/mahajanapadas.htm ]{{dead link|date=August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The two great epics of India, the [[Ramayana]] and the [[Mahabharata]], center on conflicts between the emerging [[Mahajanapadas]] and refer to military formations, theories of warfare and esoteric weaponry. They discuss standing armies that used in war [[chariot]]s, war elephants and even [[Vimana|flying machines]]. The Ramayana describes in great detail the fortifications of [[Ayodhya]]. The [[Mahabharata]] describes various military techniques such as [[Chakravyuha]] used in the [[Kurukshetra War]].

==The Magadha dynasties==

===Shishunaga dynasty===
{{Main article|Shishunaga dynasty}}
[[File:00-machines-of-war-catapult-1708x900.jpg|thumb|[[Ajatashatru]] used [[catapults]] against the [[Licchavi (kingdom)|Licchavi]]s.]]
The [[expansionist]] King [[Bimbisara]] conquered [[Anga]] in what is now [[West Bengal]] and strengthened the military of [[Magadh]]'s capital, [[Rajagriha]]. [[Ajatashatru]] built a new fort at [[Pataliputra]], Magadh's new capital, to launch an attack on [[Licchavi (clan)|Licchavis]] across the [[Ganges|Ganges River]]. [[Jain]] texts tell that he used two new weapons, a [[catapult]] and a covered [[chariot]] with swinging [[Mace (club)|mace]] that has been compared{{by whom|date=September 2011}} to modern [[tank]]s.

=== Nanda dynasty ===
{{Main article|Nanda Empire}}
[[File:The phalanx attacking the centre in the battle of the Hydaspes by Andre Castaigne (1898-1899).jpg|thumb|left|The [[phalanx]] attacking the centre in the battle of the Hydaspes by [[André Castaigne]] (1898-1899).]]

The [[Nanda dynasty]] originated from the region of Magadha in ancient India during the 4th century BC. At its greatest extent, the empire ruled by the Nanda Dynasty extended from Bengal in the east, to Punjab in the west and as far south as the Vindhya Range.

In 327 BC [[Alexander the Great]] began his foray into Punjab. King Ambhi, ruler of Taxila, surrendered the city to Alexander.  Alexander fought an epic battle against the Indian monarch Porus in the Battle of Hydaspes (326). After victory, Alexander made an alliance with Porus and appointed him as satrap of his own kingdom. East of Porus' kingdom, near the Ganges River, was the powerful kingdom of Magadha, under the [[Nanda Dynasty]].

According to [[Plutarch]], at the time of Alexander's [[Battle of the Hydaspes]] River, the size of the Nanda's army further east numbered 200,000 infantry, 80,000 cavalry, 8,000 chariots, and 6,000 war elephants, which was discouraging for Alexander's men and stayed their further progress into India.

=== Maurya dynasty ===
{{Main article|Maurya Empire}}
[[File:Maurya Dynasty in 265 BCE.jpg|thumb|The [[Maurya Empire]] at its largest extent under [[Ashoka the Great]].]]
According to [[Megasthenes]], who served as an ambassador from the [[Seleucid Empire]], [[Chandragupta Maurya]] built an army consisting of 30,000 [[cavalry]], 9,000 [[war elephant]]s, and 600,000 [[infantry]]. Chandragupta conquered much of Indian subcontinent, establishing an empire from the [[Arabian Sea]] to the [[Bay of Bengal]]. He then defeated the [[Seleucid Empire]] of Greece under [[Seleucus I Nicator]] to conquer the regions to the east of the [[Indus River]]. He then turned south, taking over much of what is now Central India. His military was administered by six chairs, one for each of the four arms of the army (infantry, cavalry, elephants, and chariots), one chair for the navy, and one for logistics and supply.

Infantry at this time was most commonly armed with a [[longbow]] made of [[bamboo]] and a single- or double-handed broadsword probably similar to the [[khanda (sword)|khanda]]. Other foot soldiers could be armed with a large animal hide tower shield and a spear or javelins. Cavalry carried spears. Elephants were mounted, usually bareback (rarely with a [[howdah]] at this time, as it is a Greek invention), by archers or javelin throwers, with a [[mahout]] around the animal's neck. Chariots by this time were in definite decline, but remained in the army due to their prestige.

In 185 BC, the last [[Maurya]]n ruler was assassinated by [[Pushyamitra Shunga]], the Commander-in-Chief of the Mauryan armed forces.

=== Shunga dynasty ===
{{Main article|Shunga dynasty}}
War and conflict characterized the Shunga period. They are known to have warred with the Kalingas, Satavahanas, the Indo-Greeks, and possibly the Panchalas and Mathuras.

Extent of the Shunga Empire's wars with the Indo-Greek Kingdom figure greatly in the history of this period. From around 180 BCE the [[Indo-Greek]] ruler [[Demetrius I of Bactria]] conquered the Kabul Valley and is theorized to have advanced into the trans-Indus. The Indo-Greek [[Menander I]] is credited with either joining or leading a campaign to Pataliputra with other Indian rulers; however, very little is known about the exact nature and success of the campaign. The net result of these wars remains uncertain.

[[Pushyamitra]] is recorded to have performed two Ashvamedha Yagnas and Shunga imperial inscriptions have extended as far as Jalandhar. Scriptures such as the Divyavadhana note that his rule extended even farther to Sialkot, in the Punjab. Moreover, if it was lost, Mathura was regained by the Shungas around 100 BCE (or by other indigenous rulers: the Arjunayanas (area of Mathura) and Yaudheyas mention military victories on their coins (&quot;Victory of the Arjunayanas&quot;, &quot;Victory of the Yaudheyas&quot;), and during the 1st century BCE, the Trigartas, Audumbaras and finally the Kunindas also started to mint their own coins). Accounts of battles between the Greeks and the Shunga in Northwestern India are also found in the Mālavikāgnimitram, a play by Kālidāsa which describes a battle between Greek cavalrymen and Vasumitra, the grandson of Pushyamitra, on the Indus river, in which the Indians defeated the Greeks and Pushyamitra successfully completed the Ashvamedha Yagna.

The Indo-Greeks and the Shungas seem to have reconciled and exchanged diplomatic missions around 110 BCE, as indicated by the Heliodorus pillar, which records the dispatch of a Greek ambassador named Heliodorus, from the court of the Indo-Greek king Antialcidas, to the court of the Shunga emperor Bhagabhadra at the site of Vidisha in central India.

==The Golden age==
Classical Indian texts on archery in particular and [[History of Indian martial arts|martial arts]] in general are known as [[Dhanurveda]]. Several classics of the genre date from this period.

===Satavahana dynasty===
{{Main article|Satavahana dynasty}}
[[File:Indian ship on lead coin of Vashishtiputra Shri Pulumavi.jpg|thumb|Indian ship on lead coin of [[Vasisthiputra Sri Pulamavi]], testimony to the seafaring and naval capabilities of the Satavahanas during the 1st–2nd century CE.]]
According to some interpretations of the [[Puranas]], the [[Satavahana dynasty|Satavahana]] family belonged to the Andhra-jati (&quot;tribe&quot;) and was the first [[Deccan Plateau|Deccanese]] dynasty to build an empire in daksinapatha (southern region). The Satavahanas (also called Andhra and Shalivahan) rose to power in modern [[Telangana]], [[Andhra Pradesh]] and [[Maharashtra]] around 200 BCE and remained in power for about 400 years. Almost the whole of present-day [[Telangana]], Maharashtra, [[Madhya Pradesh]], [[Chhattisgarh]], [[Odisha]], [[Goa]], [[Karnataka]], and [[Andhra Pradesh]] came under Satavahana rule. Their first capital was [[Koti Lingala]], as well as [[Paithan]], then called Pratishthan.

[[Simuka]], the dynasty's founder, conquered [[Maharashtra]], [[Malwa]] and part of [[Madhya Pradesh]]. His successor and brother [[Kanha (Satavahana dynasty)|Kanha]] (or Krishna) further extended his kingdom to the west and the south. He was succeeded by Satakarni I, who defeated the [[Shunga dynasty]] of North India. His successor, [[Gautamiputra Satakarni]], defeated the invading [[Indo-Scythians]], [[Indo-Parthians]] and [[Indo-Greeks]]. His empire extended up to Banavasi in the south, and included Maharashtra, [[Konkan]], [[Saurashtra (region)|Saurashtra]], [[Malwa]], west [[Rajasthan]] and Vidharbha. Later, Satavahana rulers lost some of these territories. Satavahana power revived briefly under [[Yajna Sri Satakarni]] but declined after his death.

===Mahameghavahana dynasty===
{{Main article|Mahameghavahana dynasty}}
The [[Mahameghavahana dynasty]] was an ancient ruling dynasty of Kalinga after the decline of the Mauryan Empire. The third ruler of the dynasty, [[Khārabēḷa]], conquered much of India in a series of campaigns at the beginning of the common era. Kaḷingan military might was reinstated by Khārabēḷa. Under Khārabēḷa's generalship, the Kaḷinga state had a formidable maritime reach with trade routes linking it to the then-Simhala (Sri Lanka), Burma (Myanmar), Siam (Thailand), Vietnam, Kamboja (Cambodia), Borneo, Bali, Samudra (Sumatra) and Yawadvipa (Java). Khārabēḷa led many successful campaigns against states of Magadha, Anga, Satavahanas and the South Indian regions of Pandyan Empire (modern Andhra Pradesh) and expanded Kaḷinga as far as the Ganges and the Kaveri.

The Kharavelan state had a formidable maritime empire with trading routes linking it to Sri Lanka, Burma, Thailand, Vietnam, Cambodia, Borneo, Bali, Sumatra and Java. Colonists from Kalinga settled in Sri Lanka, Burma, as well as the Maldives and Maritime Southeast Asia. Even today Indians are referred to as Keling in Malaysia because of this.

The main source of information about Khārabeḷa is his famous seventeen line rock-cut Hātigumphā inscription in a cave in the Udayagiri hills near Bhubaneswar, Odisha. According to the inscription, he attacked Rajagriha in Magadha, thus defeating the [[Indo-Greek]] king [[Demetrius I of Bactria]] to retreat to Mathura.

===Gupta dynasty===
{{See also|Gupta Empire#Military organization|l1=Military organisation of the Gupta Empire}}
[[File:QtubIronPillar.JPG|thumb|The [[iron pillar of Delhi]], erected by [[Chandragupta II]] the Great after he defeated the Vahilakas.]]
''Siva-Dhanur-veda'' discusses the military of the [[Gupta Empire]]. The Guptas relied heavily on armoured war elephants; horses were used little if at all. The use of [[chariot]]s had declined heavily by the time of the Guptas, as they had not proved very useful against the [[Greeks]], [[Scythians]], and other invaders. Guptas utilised heavy [[cavalry]] clad in mail armour and equipped with [[Mace (club)|maces]] and lances, who would have used shock action to break the enemy line. They also employed on [[infantry]] archers. Their longbow was composed of bamboo or metal and fired a long bamboo cane arrow with a metal head; iron shafts were used against armoured elephants. They also sometimes used fire arrows. Archers were frequently protected by infantry equipped with shields, javelins, and longswords. The Guptas also maintained a [[navy]], allowing them to control regional waters.
&lt;!--[[File:RudrasimhaIII.jpg|thumb|300px|Coin of [[Rudrasimha III]], the last [[Western Satrap]] ruler.]] --&gt;

[[Samudragupta]] seized the kingdoms of Shichchhatra and [[Padmavati Pawaya|Padmavati]] early in his reign. Later, he took the Kota kingdom and attacked the tribes in [[Malwa|Malvas]], the [[Yaudheya]]s, the [[Arjunayana]]s, the [[Madura]]s and the [[Abhira]]s. He also subjugated the remants of the [[Kushan Empire]]. By his death in 380, he had conquered over twenty kingdoms.

4th century CE Sanskrit poet Kalidasa, credits [[Chandragupta II]] with having conquered about twenty one kingdoms, both in and outside India. After finishing his campaign in the East and West India, he proceeded northwards, subjugated the Parasikas,{{citation needed|date=August 2015}} then the [[Hunas]] and the [[Kambojas]] tribes located in the west and east Oxus valleys respectively.{{citation needed|date=August 2015}}  Chandragupta II controlled the whole of the [[Indian subcontinent]]; the Gupta empire was the most powerful empire in the world during his reign, at a time when the Roman Empire in the west was in decline.

[[Skandagupta]] faced with invading [[Indo-Hephthalites]] or [[White Huns]], from the northwest. Skandagupta had warred against the Huns during the reign of his father, and was celebrated throughout the empire as a great warrior. He crushed the Huns invasion in 455, and managed to keep them at bay; however, the expense of the wars drained the empire's resources and contributed to its decline

==The Classical age==

===Empire of Harsha===
Emperor [[Harsha]] (606–647) ruled the [[Empire of Harsha]] covering northern India for over forty years. His father, a king of [[Thanesar]], had gained prominence by successful wars against the [[Huna people|Huns]]. Harsha had plans to conquer the whole of India, and carried on wars for thirty years with considerable success. By 612 he had built up a vast army with which he conquered nearly all [[North India]] up to the [[Narmada river]]. In 620 he invaded the [[Deccan Plateau]] but was repelled by [[Pulakeshin II]].

===The Chalukyas and Pallavas===
[[File:8th century Kannada inscription on victory pillar at Pattadakal.jpg|thumb|upright|Old [[Kannada]] inscription on a [[Chalukya]] victory pillar, Virupaksha Temple, [[Pattadakal]], 733–745 CE]]
In [[South India]], the [[Chalukyas]] and the [[Pallavas]] gained prominence. The [[Chalukya]] ruler Pulakeshin II's expansionism started with minor campaigns against the [[Alupas]], [[Western Ganga dynasty|Gangas]] and others. He defeated the Pallava king [[Mahendravarman]] and conquered the [[Chera dynasty|Cheras]] and the [[Pandya]]s. His greatest military success, the defeat of Harshavardhana (also known as Harsha), depleted his treasury, forcing him to end his expansionist campaigns.

The Pallava king [[Narasimhavarman]] vowed to avenge Mahendravarman's defeat by Pulakeshin II. He invaded [[Vatapi]] with an army headed by his general Paranjothi. He defeated the Chalukyas, killing Pulakeshin II in 642. Clashes between the Chalukyas and the Pallavas continued for a century, until the Chalukya king [[Vikramaditya II]] won a decisive victory against the Pallavas in 740. The [[Rashtrakutas]] overthrew the Chalukya empire in 750. During the 970s, [[Tailapa II]] overthrew the [[Rashtrakuta]]s and recovered most of the [[Chalukya Empire]], except for [[Gujarat]]. The Chalukyas of this period are known as the Kalyani Chalukyas, as [[Basavakalyan|Kalyani]] was their capital. They clashed intermittently with the [[Cholas]].

===The Chola Empire===
[[File:Battle of kedah.jpg|thumb|left|Depiction of the siege of [[Kedah]] by Beemasenan's naval infantry.]]
The [[Cholas]] were the first rulers of the Indian subcontinent to maintain a navy and use it to expand their dominion overseas. [[Vijayalaya Chola]] defeated the Pallavas and captured [[Thanjavur]]. In the early 10th century the Chola king [[Parantaka I]] defeated the [[Pandyan]] king [[Maravarman Rajasimha II]] and invaded [[Sri Lanka]]. The [[Rashtrakuta]] ruler [[Krishna III]] defeated and killed Parantaka I's son [[Rajaditya]] in about 949.

[[Uttama Chola]] reigned 970-85. Inscriptions tell that at least from his time, Chola warriors wore waist coats of armour. Hence, one regiment was called ''Niyayam-Uttama-Chola-tterinda-andalakattalar''. Paluvettaraiyar Maravan Kandanar served as a general under Uttama and his predecessor, [[Sundara Chola|Sundara]].

[[Rajaraja Chola]] began his military career with the conquest of the Cheras in the [[Kandalur War]]. He captured the Pandya ruler Amara Bhujanga, the town of [[Vizhinjam]], and a part of Sri Lanka. In the 14th year of his reign (998–999) he conquered the [[Gangas]] of [[Mysore]], the [[Nolambas]] of [[Bellary]] and Eastern Mysore, Tadigaipadi, [[Vengi]], [[Coorg]], the Pandyas and the Chalukyas of the Deccan. During the next three years, he subdued [[Quilon]] and the northern kingdom of [[Kalinga (India)|Kalinga]] with the help of his son [[Rajendra Chola I]]. Rajendra later completed the conquest of Sri Lanka, crossed the [[Ganges]], and marched across [[Kalinga (India)|Kalinga]] to [[Bengal]]. He sent out a great naval expedition that occupied parts of [[Java]], [[Malay Peninsula|Malaya]], and [[Sumatra]]. The Cholas were brought down by the [[Hoysalas]] from the west and Pandyas from the south.

===The Gurjar-Pratiharas, Palas and Rashtrakutas===
[[File:Statue of Gurjar Samraat Mihir Bhoj Mahaan in Bharat Upvan ofAkshardham Mandir New Delhi.jpg|thumb|A statue of the [[Gurjara-Pratihara]] ruler [[Samraat Mihir Bhoj]].]]
The Arab scholar Sulaiman described the Emperor of the [[Rashtrakuta dynasty]] as one of the 4 great Kings of the World in the 9th century.&lt;ref&gt;A Comprehensive History Of Ancient India (3 Vol. Set) by P.N Chopra p.203&lt;/ref&gt;
In middle of 9th century, the [[Pala Empire|Palas]] under [[Devapala (Pala dynasty)|Devapala]] attacked the [[Gurjara-Pratihara]]s. Led by [[Mihira Bhoja|Mihir Bhoja]], the Pratiharas and their allies defeated [[Narayan Pala]].

There were many battles between the Gurjar Pratiharas under Bhoj and the [[Rashtrakutas]] under [[Krishna II]] with mixed results. When the Rashtrakuta king [[Indra III]] attacked [[Kanauj]], [[Mahipala I]], Mihir Bhoj's successor, fled; he later returned.

[[Al-Masudi]] wrote that in 915, during Mahipala's rule, the Pratiharas were at war with the Muslims in the west and the Rashtrakutas in the south, and that the Gurjar Pratiharas had four armies of about 80,000 men each.

===Arab conquest of Sindh===
In 712, an Arab general, named Muhammad bin Qasim Al-Thaqafi (Arabic: محمد بن قاسم) (c. 31 December 695–18 July 715), attacked and conquered [[Chach of Alor|Sindh kingdom]] which is mainly situated in Indus valley area (after partition, now in modern-day [[Pakistan]]); by the time [[Sindh]] was ruled by [[Raja Dahir]] of [[Rai Dynasty]] and this dynasty was at war with Arabs. Though they defeated several [[Muslim conquests on the Indian subcontinent|Arab invasions]] before 712 CE, this time being deprived of local Buddhist people's support, Sindh was captured and the first step of Islamic foundation in India was created. [[Chach Nama]] ({{lang-sd|چچ نامو}}), written by Kàzí Ismáíl briefly discusses the events.However, the south Indian Emperor [[Vikramaditya II]] of the [[Chalukya dynasty]] and the Pratiharas defeated the Arabs during the [[Caliphate campaigns in India]](738 CE) when they tried to move eastward.

Indian inscriptions confirm this invasion but record the Arab success only against the smaller states in [[Gujarat]]. They also record the defeat of the Arabs at two places. The southern army moving south into Gujarat was defeated at Navsari by the south Indian Emperor [[Vikramaditya II]] of the [[Chalukya]] dynasty who sent his general [[Pulakeshin]] to defeat the Arabs.[2] The army that went east, reached Avanti whose ruler [[Gurjara Pratihara]] [3] [[Nagabhata I]] utterly defeated the invaders. Arab forces failed to make any substantial gains in India and in the [[Caliphate campaigns in India]] (730 CE), their army was severely defeated by the Indian kings. As a result, Arabs' territory got restricted to [[Sindh]] in modern [[Pakistan]].[1]

===Ghaznavid invasion===

In the early 11th century, [[Mahmud of Ghazni]] conquered the Rajput Hindu Shahi kingdom in the North-west frontier in Afghanistan and Pakistan, and his raids into northern India weakened the [[Pratihara]] kingdom, which was drastically reduced in size and came under the control of the [[Chandelas]]. Mahmud sacked some temples across northern India, including the temple at Somnath in Gujarat, but his permanent conquests were limited to the Punjab. The early 11th century also saw the reign of the [[polymath]] king [[Raja Bhoj]], the Paramara ruler of [[Malwa]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Ap&quot;&gt;John Merci, Kim Smith; James Leuck (1922). &quot;Muslim conquest and the Rajputs&quot;. The Medieval History of India pg 67-115&lt;/ref&gt;

==The Medieval era==
[[File:Group of Indian Armoir Weapons 1900.jpg|thumb|left|Group of Indian Armoir]]

===Delhi Sultanate===
The [[Delhi Sultanate]], under the [[Khilji dynasty]], repelled several invasions by the [[Mongol Empire]]. [[Zafar Khan (General)|Zafar Khan]], a general serving [[Alauddin Khilji]], defeated the Mongols near [[Jalandhar]] in 1297. In 1299, Zafar Khan fought back a Mongol army of 200,000 soldiers but was killed in the process. Its last [[sultan]], [[Ibrahim Lodi]], died fighting the forces of [[Babur]] in the [[first battle of Panipat]] in 1526, ending the sultanate and paving the way for the foundation of the Mughal Empire

===The Rajputs===
[[File:RajaRaviVarma MaharanaPratap.jpg|thumb|right|Portrait of Maharana Pratap based on miniature made available to artist from the [[Udaipur]] palace.]]
After Babur's victory over Ibrahim Lodi, the [[Mewar]] ruler [[Rana Sanga]] led a combined Rajput army of 20,000 intending to defeat [[Babur]] and capture [[Delhi]]. The Mughals had superior [[artillery]], which prevailed against the Rajput [[cavalry]]. A [[Tomar clan|Tomar]] general betrayed Rana Sanga, resulting in his defeat by Babur at the [[Battle of Khanua]] (16 March 1527). During the reign Rana Sanga's son Rana Udai Singh II, Babur's grandson [[Akbar]] conquered [[Chittor]], the capital of [[Mewar]].

In the [[Battle of Haldighati]] (21 June 1576) between Akbar and [[Rana Pratap Singh]], the Mughal army of 80,000 was headed by a Rajput, [[Raja Man Singh]], and Akbar's son [[Jahangir|Salim]]. The Rajput army's strength was 20,000. Rana Pratap escaped with the help of his estranged brother Sakti Singh. His legendary horse [[Chetak (horse)|Chetak]] was killed in the battle. Later, Rana Pratap organized a small army of [[Bhil]] tribals funded by a Gurjar businessman called Bhamashah and started a [[guerrilla warfare|guerrilla war]] against Akbar. He retook large parts of Mewar but could not retake Chittor.

===Muzaffarid dynasty===
[[File:Death of Sultan Bahadur in front of Diu against the Portuguese 1537 Akbar Nama end of 16th century.jpg|thumb|left|The death of [[Bahadur Shah of Gujarat]] at [[Siege of Diu|Diu]] in 1537.&lt;ref name=&quot;Percival 14&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Y-08AAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA14 |title=The Cambridge history of the British Empire, Volume 2; by Arthur Percival Newton p.14 |publisher=Books.google.com |date= |accessdate=2012-03-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
Sultan Muzaffar Shah I, the Governor of [[Gujarat]], established the [[Muzaffarid dynasty of Gujarat|Muzaffarid dynasty]] in 1391. It expanded rapidly and peaked under [[Mahmud Begada|Sultan Mahmud I]], who lost the [[Battle of Diu (1509)|Battle of Diu]] to the Portuguese in 1509.

===Calicut===
Ruled by the [[Zamorin]], the small [[Hindu]] [[Nair]] kingdom of [[History of Kozhikode|Calicut]] ([[Malabar (Northern Kerala)|Malabar]]) welcomed the [[Portugal|Portuguese]] in 1498 as traders but then fought several naval wars with Portugal in the 16th century. The office of Muslim naval chief in [[Kozhikode|Calicut]] was known as the [[Kunhali Marakkar]].

===Vijayanagara Empire===
[[File:Ancient sentry post atop boulder at Vijayanagara.jpg|thumb|A sentry post, [[Vijayanagara|Vijayanagar]] area.]]
[[File:Panaromic view of the natural fortification and landscape at Hampi.jpg|thumb|Natural fortress at [[Vijayanagara]].]]
The Italian traveler Niccolo de Conti wrote of the Emperor of the [[Vijayanagara Empire]] as the most powerful ruler of India in the 15th century.&lt;ref&gt;Columbia Chronologies of Asian History and Culture, John Stewart Bowman p.271, (2013), Columbia University Press, New York, ISBN 0-231-11004-9&lt;/ref&gt;
In 1509, the [[Bahamani]] Sultan declared [[war]] against the [[Vijayanagara Empire]]. His large coalition army was defeated by [[Krishnadevaraya]] in a battle in which the Sultan was wounded. In 1510, Krishnadevaraya launched a counteroffensive against the Sultan at Kovelaconda; Yusuf Adil Shahi of [[Bijapur Sultanate|Bijapur]] died in the battle. In 1512, Krishnadevaraya captured [[Raichur]] and [[Gulbarga]] after defeating Barid-i-Mamalik, the titular head of the [[Bahmani Sultanate]], who escaped to [[Bidar]]. Later, Bidar also fell to Krishnadevaraya, who restored the Bahmani Sultan to his throne under the terms of their peace treaty.

Between 1512 and 1514, Krishnadevaraya subjugated the Palaigar of [[Ummattur]], who had rebelled against his brother. During this campaign, the [[Gajapati Kingdom|Gajapati]] of [[Odisha]] attacked Vijayanagara and occupied two northeast provinces: [[Udayagiri and Khandagiri Caves|Udayagiri]] and [[Kondavidu]]. Krishnadevaraya recaptured these lands between 1513 and 1518.

On 26 January 1565, the neighboring kingdoms of [[Ahmednagar]], [[Berar Sultanate|Berar]], [[Bidar]], [[Bijapur Sultanate|Bijapur]] and [[Golconda]] came together to defeat the Vijayanagar decisively in the [[Battle of Talikota]]. The surviving Vijaynagar forces fled with a large treasury to re-establish their headquarters at [[Vellore Fort]] in [[Tamil Nadu]] and [[Chandragiri]] ([[Andhra Pradesh]]) near [[Tirupati (city)|Tirupathi]]. It would be here that the British would seek a land grant to establish the [[English East India Company]] Fort St. George in [[Madras]].

Later, the Vijayanagara's southern Telugu governors, in present-day [[Tamil Nadu]], became independent. They became the [[Gingee Nayaks]] in [[Gingee Fort]], the [[Tanjore Nayaks]], and the [[Nayaks of Madurai]].

===Ahom Kingdom===
[[Ahom Kingdom]] (1228–1826) was a kingdom and tribe which rose to prominence in present-day [[Assam]] early in the thirteenth century. They ruled much of Assam from the 13th century until the establishment of British rule in 1838.&lt;ref&gt;
http://www.britannica.com/topic/Ahom&lt;/ref&gt; The Ahoms brought with them a tribal religion and a language of their own, however they later merged with the [[Hindu]] religion.&lt;ref&gt;
https://books.google.com/books?id=Wk4_ICH_g1EC&amp;pg=PA305&amp;dq=ahom+maintained+independence&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0CEEQ6AEwB2oVChMI35LjnayIyQIVSc9jCh1udgnU#v=onepage&amp;q=ahom%20maintained%20independence&amp;f=false&lt;/ref&gt; From thirteenth till seventeenth century, repeated attempts were made by the Muslim rulers of Delhi to invade and subdue Ahoms, however the Ahoms managed to maintain their independence and ruled themselves for nearly 600 years.&lt;ref&gt;
https://books.google.com/books?id=WfSmsuO6QugC&amp;pg=PA8&amp;dq=ahom+maintained+independence+aurangzeb&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0CCAQ6AEwAWoVChMIiuzp4ayIyQIVxR-mCh2EKgh6#v=onepage&amp;q=ahom%20maintained%20independence%20aurangzeb&amp;f=false&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;
https://books.google.com/books?id=AWL1pa8TUFYC&amp;pg=PA590&amp;dq=ahom+maintained+independence&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0CBsQ6AEwAGoVChMI35LjnayIyQIVSc9jCh1udgnU#v=onepage&amp;q=ahom%20maintained%20independence&amp;f=false&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mughal Empire===
{{See also|Mughal Empire}}
[[File:Cavalry soldier of Mughal Empire.jpg|thumb|left|Cavalry soldier of Mughal Empire]]

The [[Mughal Empire]] began in 1526 with the overthrow of Ibrahim Lodi and encompassed most of South Asia by the late 17th and early 18th centuries. Allied with the [[Maharaja]], it extended from [[Bengal]] in the east to [[Kabul]] in the west, [[Kashmir]] in the north to the [[Kaveri]] basin in the south,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://sun.menloschool.org/~sportman/westernstudies/first/1718/2000/eblock/mughal/ |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080225145650/http://sun.menloschool.org/~sportman/westernstudies/first/1718/2000/eblock/mughal/ |archivedate=2008-02-25 |title=Mughal Empire}}&lt;/ref&gt; a territory of over 4 million km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; at its height. Its population at that time has been estimated at between 110 and 130 million.&lt;ref&gt;John F Richards, [http://www.amazon.com/dp/0521566037/ ''The Mughal Empire''], Vol I.5, ''New Cambridge History of India'', Cambridge University Press, 1996&lt;/ref&gt; In the year 1540, then [[Mughal Emperor]] [[Humayun]] was defeated by [[Sher Shah Suri]], and forced to retreat to [[Kabul]]. Suris and their adviser, the Hindu Emperor [[Hem Chandra Vikramaditya]], also called Hemu, ruled North India from 1540 to 1556. Hemu established a 'Hindu' Empire briefly from Delhi in 1556.

The &quot;classic period&quot; of the Empire started in 1556 with the accession of [[Akbar the Great]] and ended with the death of Emperor [[Aurangzeb]] in 1707,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/islam/history/mughalempire_1.shtml |title=Religions - Islam: Mughal Empire (1500s, 1600s) |publisher=BBC |date=7 September 2009 |accessdate=2012-03-14}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/religion/religions/islam/history/mughalempire_5.shtml |title=Religions - Islam: Mughal Empire (1500s, 1600s) |publisher=BBC |date=7 September 2009 |accessdate=2012-03-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; although the dynasty continued for another 150 years. During this period, the Empire was marked by centralized administration and active culture. Following 1725 the empire declined rapidly, weakened by wars of succession; famine and local revolts fueled by it; the growth of religious intolerance; the rise of the [[Maratha Empire]]; and finally [[British colonialism]]. The last Mughal emperor, [[Bahadur Shah II]], whose rule was restricted to the city of [[Delhi]], was imprisoned and exiled by the British after the [[Indian Rebellion of 1857]].

===The Marathas===
{{Main article|Maratha Empire}}
{{Further|Maratha Army|Maratha Navy}}
{{see also|First Anglo-Maratha War|Second Anglo-Maratha War|Third Anglo-Maratha War}}
{| class=&quot;toccolours&quot; style=&quot;float:right; margin:0 0 1em 1em;&quot;
| style=&quot;background:#f8eaba; text-align:center;&quot;|
&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
; The Marathas
&lt;/div&gt;
|-
|
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Marathas India (1758).jpg|Political map of Indian Subcontinent in 1758. The [[Maratha Empire]] ''(orange)'' was the last Hindu empire of India.
File:Maratha Armour.jpg|Maratha Helmet and Armor 
&lt;/gallery&gt;
|-
|
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Francis Holman, Commodore James in the Protector, with the Revenge and the grab Bombay in the bay off the Suvarnadrug fort at Gheriah, India, April 1755 (18th century).jpg|A depiction of a British naval attack in 1755 against the Maratha Navy at [[Suvarnadurg]].&lt;ref&gt;Biddulph, Colonel John. The Pirates of the Malibar and an Englishwoman in India Two Hundred Years Ago. London: Smith, Elder &amp; Co, 1907&lt;/ref&gt;
File:Mahratta Light Horseman.jpg|Maratha Light Horseman
File:Arms of Maratha History of India 1906.jpg|Arms of Maratha
&lt;/gallery&gt;
|}

In 1674, [[Shivaji|Shivaji Bhosale]] carved an independent Maratha zone around [[Pune]], Maharashtra, from the [[Bijapur Sultanate]] and, with that began the emergence of the Marathas as the most important power in India that filled the vacuum created by the decline of the Mughal Empire.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite web
|url=http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/285248/India/46984/Political-and-economic-decentralization-during-the-Mughal-decline#toc46986
|title=Regional states, c. 1700–1850
|publisher=Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.
}}
&lt;/ref&gt; Shivaji established an effective civil and military administration. After a lifetime of conquest and [[guerrilla warfare]] with the Mughal emperor [[Aurangzeb]], Shivaji died in 1680, leaving behind a kingdom of great but ill-defined extent. This was followed by a period of instability ending with Aurangzeb's death.

Shivaji was the second king in Indian history to maintain an active navy. [[Kanhoji Angre]], the first Maratha naval chief under Shivaji's grandson [[Shahuji]], controlled illegal entries into Maratha territory by [[Netherlands|Dutch]], [[British Empire|English]] and [[Portugal|Portuguese]] commercial ships on the Western coast of India in the early 18th century. He remained undefeated until his death in 1729.{{citation needed|date=October 2013}}

Although the descendants of Shivaji continued to rule, the office of the [[Peshwa]], or the [[Prime Minister]], became the focus of Maratha power and patronage. The Peshwas were the effective rulers of the Maratha state and oversaw the period of greatest Maratha expansion, brought to an end by the Maratha's defeat by an [[Afghanistan|Afghan]] army at the [[Third Battle of Panipat]] in 1761. The Marathas recovered their position as the dominant power in India by 1772 until the last Peshwa, [[Baji Rao II]], was defeated by the British in the [[Third Anglo-Maratha War]]. With the defeat of the [[Maratha Empire|Marathas]], no native power represented a threat for the British any longer.&lt;ref&gt;
https://books.google.com/books?id=uzOmy2y0Zh4C&amp;pg=PA271&amp;dq=1818+british+india+maratha&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=3kB1UorJLYSlkQXwvYDoDw&amp;ved=0CEgQ6AEwBQ#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false
&lt;/ref&gt; The end of the last Anglo-Maratha War marked the era of British paramountcy over India.&lt;ref&gt;
https://books.google.com/books?id=aZ2F6BE6n2QC&amp;pg=PA82&amp;dq=1818+british+india+maratha&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=3kB1UorJLYSlkQXwvYDoDw&amp;ved=0CDkQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false
&lt;/ref&gt;

The Marathas also developed a potent '''''[[Maratha Navy|Navy]]''''' circa 1660s, which at its peak, dominated the territorial waters of the western coast of India from [[Mumbai]] to [[Savantwadi]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Sridharan|first1=K|title=Sea: Our Saviour|publisher=New Age International (P) Ltd.|isbn=81-224-1245-9|url=https://books.google.co.in/books?id=9PiwJF7V4EQC&amp;pg=PA43&amp;dq=kanhoji+angre&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=kanhoji%20angre&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;  It would engage in attacking the [[Company Rule in India|British]], [[Portuguese India|Portuguese]], [[Dutch India|Dutch]], and [[Siddi]] Naval ships and kept a check on their naval ambitions. The [[Maratha Navy]] dominated till around the 1730s, was in a state of decline by 1770s, and ceased to exist by 1818.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Sharma|first1=Yogesh|title=Coastal Histories: Society and Ecology in Pre-modern India|publisher=Primus Books|isbn=978-93-80607-00-9|pages=66|url=https://books.google.co.in/books?id=FTTGWSme30YC&amp;pg=PA66&amp;dq=maratha+dhulap+navy&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;q=maratha%20dhulap%20navy&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Travancore Kingdom===
King [[Marthanda Varma]] inherited the small feudal state of [[Venad]] in 1723 and built it into [[Travancore]], one of the most powerful kingdoms in southern India, with the help of the [[British East India Company]]. Marthanda Varma led the Travancore forces during the [[Travancore-Dutch War]] of 1739–46, which culminated in the [[Battle of Colachel]]. Marthanda Varma went on to conquer most of the petty principalities of the native rulers who had allied with the Dutch against him.

During [[Dharma Raja]]'s reign, [[Tipu Sultan]] invaded Travancore, but commander-in-chief [[Raja Kesavadas]] led Travancore to victory despite being outnumbered. This attack led to Travancore joining the British against Tipu in the Third Battle of Carnatic. Pazhsi Raja, [[Velu Thampi Dalava]] and [[Paliath Achan]], later leaders of Travancore, fought the [[British East India Company]] but lost. Travancore became a British ally in 1805 following a treaty between Colonel Charles Macaulay and Diwan Velu Tampi. It remained so until 1947 when it became part of the newly independent [[Union of India]].{{citation needed|date=January 2012}}

===Mysore Kingdom===
[[File:Rocket warfare.jpg|thumb|left|A painting showing [[Tipu Sultan]]'s army fighting the British with rocket brigades, probably the first instance of rocket warfare in the [[Indian subcontinent]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Missiles mainstay of Pak's N-arsenal|url=http://articles.timesofindia.indiatimes.com/2008-04-21/india/27784965_1_cruise-missile-missile-program-hatf-viii|work=The Times of India|accessdate=30 August 2011|date=21 April 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
[[Hyder Ali]], the ''de facto'' ruler of [[Mysore]], was one of the first Indian rulers to resist the British, allying instead with France. He was one of the first Indian rulers to use [[rocket]]s, employing them to defeat a top British unit.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Rockets: History and Theory|publisher=White Sands Missile Range|accessdate=30 August 2011 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080208121415/http://www.wsmr.army.mil/pao/FactSheets/rkhist.htm|archivedate=8 February 2008|url=http://www.wsmr.army.mil/pao/FactSheets/rkhist.htm}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Sikh Empire===
[[File:RanjitSingh by ManuSaluja.jpg|thumb|[[Ranjit Singh|Maharaja Ranjit Singh]], the founder of the [[Sikh Empire]].]]
Maharaja [[Ranjit Singh]] was a [[Sikh]] ruler of the sovereign country of [[Punjab region|Punjab]] and the [[Sikh Empire]]. His father [[Maha Singh]] led [[Sukerchakia]], a [[misl]] within the [[Sikh Confederacy]]. Born in 1780 in [[Gujranwala]], Ranjit Singh succeeded his father at the age of 12. He united the Sikh factions into the [[Sikh Empire]] and took the title &quot;Maharaja&quot; on 13 April 1801, to coincide with [[Baisakhi]]. [[Lahore]] was his capital from 1799. In 1802 he conquered [[Amritsar]], a holy city of the Sikh religion. In 1822 Ranjit Singh hired European mercenaries for the first time to train a part of his troops. He modernized his army, creating a military force whose power delayed the eventual British colonization of Punjab. The result was a powerful and heavily armed state. The [[Battle of Jamrud]] in 1837 was a major setback for Ranjit Singh: his general [[Hari Singh Nalwa]] was killed, the [[Khyber Pass]] was established as the western limit of the Sikh Empire's influence.

Ranjit Singh died in 1839, and his empire crumbled under internal strife and poor governance by his heirs. On the east of his realm [[Gulab Singh of Jammu and Kashmir|Gulab Singh]] extended Sikh authority in the [[Himalayas]] until stopped by the [[Qing Dynasty|Qing Empire]] in the [[Sino-Sikh war]] (1841–1842). After the [[First Anglo-Sikh War]] (1845–46), Punjab effectively ceased to be an independent state. The [[British Empire]] annexed the Sikh Empire following the [[Second Anglo-Sikh War]] (1848–49).

==Colonial era==
{{Main article|Colonial India}}

===Company rule===
The [[British Indian Army]] was raised to guard the factories of the [[British East India Company]]. Following the fall of French [[Pondicherry district|Pondichéry]] in 1793, this was divided into Presidency armies of [[Bengal]], [[Madras]] and [[Bombay]] in 1795. The Dutch trained the [[Nair]] Brigade, the military of Travancore.

[[File:The capture of the king of delhi by Captain Hodson.jpg|thumb|left|Capture of [[Bahadur Shah Zafar]] and his sons by [[William Stephen Raikes Hodson|William Hodson]] at Humayun's tomb on 20 September 1857.]]
During the [[Sepoy Mutiny]] of 1857–58, some units of the Bengal Native Infantry and Cavalry revolted against the British East India Company. The rebels received less support than they had expected from members of the Bombay and Madras Armies. A number of atrocities took place, among them the [[Siege of Cawnpore]]. The mutiny ultimately failed because of lack of resources and coordination among the rebels. Reprisals by the victorious British Army, assisted by Sikh and Afghan regulars and irregulars, were ruthless.

===The British Raj===
{| class=&quot;toccolours&quot; style=&quot;float:right; margin:0 0 1em 1em;&quot;
| style=&quot;background:#f8eaba; text-align:center;&quot;|
&lt;div class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
; British Rule
&lt;/div&gt;
|-
|
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:29TH BOMBAY NATIVE INFANTRY on Firing Exercise 1885 Simkin.jpg|Bombay Native Infantry
File:Members_of_a_Nair_brigade.jpg|Members of a Nair brigade in the service of the British, as painted by the Swiss artist [[Paul Aimé Vallouy]].
&lt;/gallery&gt;
|-
|
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Gurkhas NavyAndArmyIllustrated1896.jpg|Gurkha Soldiers (1896). The centre figure wears the dark green dress uniform worn by all Gurkhas in British service, with certain regimental distinctions.
File:A Group in Camp, 39th Bengal Infantry.jpg|[[39th Garhwal Rifles]] in a camp.
&lt;/gallery&gt;
|}
Following the Sepoy Mutiny, British rule in India was reorganised under the [[British Raj]], made up of areas directly administered by the United Kingdom and [[princely states]] under the [[paramountcy]] of the [[British Crown]]. Under terms of treaties with the Crown, these princely states were allowed some local autonomy in exchange for protection and representation in international affairs by the United Kingdom. The Raj included present-day India, Pakistan, and [[Bangladesh]].

After 1857, the Presidency Armies were abolished in favour of a reconstituted British Indian Army under the control of the [[British Crown]] and the [[Viceroy of India|Viceroy]]. Many units were disbanded or reorganised, and new units of Sikhs, Gurkhas, and irregular horsemen were introduced. The majority of the Madras Native Infantry and Cavalry had their class compositions changed to North Indian tribes, considered more &quot;martial&quot; than the darker, shorter &quot;thambis&quot; who made up the majority of the Madras Presidency Army. Indian sepoys were banned from serving as officers or in the artillery corps. Recruiting focused more on Sikhs and Gurkhas, whom the British viewed as loyal. New caste-based and religion-based regiments were formed.

The British Indian Army consisted of members of all the major religious groups in India: [[Hindus]], [[Sikhs]], [[Christians]], and [[Muslims]]. The number of Sikhs in the army grew steadily with time as British commanders came to believe they were more loyal and martial, an impression reinforced by their conduct during the Sepoy Mutiny. The Sikhs, for their part, aligned with the British to prevent a resurgence of Mughal rule; Sikhs had been persecuted under the Mughal Empire.

The [[Indian Air Force]] was established in 1932.

====World War I====
{{main article|Indian Army during World War I}}
[[File:Indian Army QF 3.7 inch gun battery Jerusalem 1917.jpg|thumb|Indian Army gunners (probably 39th Battery) with [[3.7 inch Mountain Howitzer]]s, Jerusalem 1917.]]
During [[World War I]], over 800,000 volunteered for the army, and more than 400,000 volunteered for non-combat roles, compared with the pre-war annual recruitment of about 15,000 men.&lt;ref&gt;Pati, p.31&lt;/ref&gt; The Army saw action on the [[Western Front (World War I)|Western Front]] within a month of the start of the war, at the [[First Battle of Ypres]] where [[Khudadad Khan]] became the first Indian to be awarded a [[Victoria Cross]]. After a year of front-line duty, sickness and casualties had reduced the Indian Corps to the point where it had to be withdrawn. Nearly 700,000 Indians fought the Turks in the Mesopotamian campaign. Indian formations were also sent to East Africa, Egypt, and Gallipoli.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|url=http://www.mgtrust.org/ind1.htm|title=Participants from the Indian subcontinent in the First World War|publisher=Memorial Gates Trust|accessdate=2009-09-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{main article|Middle Eastern theatre of World War I}}

Indian Army and [[Imperial Service Troops]] fought during the [[Sinai and Palestine Campaign]]'s [[Sinai and Palestine Campaign#Suez Canal Campaign (1915–1916)|defence of the Suez Canal]] in 1915, at [[Battle of Romani|Romani]] in 1916 and to [[Battle of Jerusalem (1917)|Jerusalem]] in 1917. India units [[Occupation of the Jordan Valley (1918)|occupied the Jordan Valley]] and after the [[Spring Offensive]] they became the major force in the [[Egyptian Expeditionary Force]] during the [[Battle of Megiddo (1918)|Battle of Megiddo]] and in the [[Desert Mounted Corps]]' advance to [[Damascus]] and on to [[Aleppo]]. Other divisions remained in India guarding the [[North-West Frontier (military history)|North-West Frontier]] and fulfilling internal security obligations.

One million Indian troops served abroad during the war. In total, 74,187 died,&lt;ref name=&quot;CWrepdirect&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cwgc.org/document.asp?menuid=5&amp;submenuid=24&amp;id=6&amp;menuname=%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20Annual%20report&amp;menu=subsub |title=Commonwealth War Graves Commission Annual Report 2007–2008 Online |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070926220138/http://www.cwgc.org/document.asp?menuid=5&amp;submenuid=24&amp;id=6&amp;menuname=%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20%20Annual%20report&amp;menu=subsub |archivedate=2007-09-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; and another 67,000 were wounded.&lt;ref&gt;Sumner, p.7&lt;/ref&gt; The roughly 90,000 soldiers who lost their lives fighting in World War I and the [[Third Anglo-Afghan War|Afghan Wars]] are commemorated by the [[India Gate]].

====World War II====
{{main article|List of Indian divisions in World War II}}
[[File:Newly-arrived Indian troops.jpg|thumb|left|Newly arrived Indian troops parade on the quayside at Singapore, November 1941.]]
[[File:Surrendered Indian National Army troops at Mount Popa.jpg|thumb|Troops of the [[Indian National Army]] who surrendered at [[Mount Popa]], c. April 1945.]]

In 1939, the British Indian Army's strength was about 189,000, with about 3,000 British officers and 1,115 Indian officers. The army was expanded greatly to fight in [[World War II]]: by 1945, the strength of the Army had risen to about 2.5 million, with about 34,500 British officers and 15,740 Indian officers. The Army took part in campaigns in France, East Africa, North Africa, [[Syria]], [[Tunisia]], [[British Malaya|Malaya]], [[Burma]], Greece, [[Sicily]] and Italy. Particularly significant contributions came in the campaigns in Abyssinia and North Africa, against the Italians; at [[Second Battle of El Alamein|El Alamain]] and in Italy, against the Germans; and in the [[Burma Campaign]] against Japan. The army ultimately suffered 179,935 casualties: 24,338 killed, 64,354 wounded, 11,762 missing, and 79,481 taken [Prisoner of war].

During the war, Indian nationalist expatriates in Southeast Asia and the Japanese Army formed the [[Indian National Army]] (INA) to fight for Indian independence from Britain. For manpower, it relied on the approximately 45,000 Indian troops of the Indian Army whom the Japanese captured when Singapore fell in February 1942. [[Subhas Chandra Bose]] was parachuted in to lead the INA in 1943, and he greatly expanded the INA to include the mainly Tamil civilian Indian community in Malaya. He also negotiated a combat role for the INA from the reluctant Japanese, who were more inclined to use it intelligence and propaganda work. In 1944, INA units participated in the Japanese Army`s offensives against British positions in the Arakan and the Imphal Plain. Not being a military man Bose - or &quot;Netaji&quot; (''respected leader'') naively believed that Indian soldiers of the Indian Army who deployed against the INA would flock to its standard. But these Indian troops stood fIrm, and actually defeated the INA. Despite this, Bose insisted that the INA be given an independent sector on the Irrawaddy in February 1945. Despite the desperate efforts of some INA troops, their sector was overrun, and desertions became commonplace. Militarily, the INA was finished. After the war, however, it made a political impact, due to the British decision to publicly court-martial three INA commanders. This was a miscalculation, because Indian nationalist politicians, who had previously come out against the INA, now whipped up popular sentiment for the release of the INA accused. Realizing their error, the British acquiesced. In this way, the INA was another sign that the Raj's days were numbered.

==Republic of India==
{{main article|History of the Republic of India}}

===Major wars===
The Republic of India has fought three [[Indo-Pakistani Wars|wars and one major incursion battle with Pakistan]] and one border war with China.

====First Indo-Pak war, 1947====
{{main article|Indo-Pakistani War of 1947}}
[[File:Indian soldiers fighting in 1947 war.jpg|thumb|right|Indian army in the Indo-Pakistani War of 1947]]
This is also called the '''First Kashmir War'''. The war started in October 1947 when Pakistan feared that the [[Maharajah]] of the [[princely state]] of [[Kashmir and Jammu]] would accede to India. Following partition, states were left to choose whether to join India or Pakistan or to remain independent. Jammu and Kashmir, the largest of the princely states, had a predominantly Muslim population ruled by the Hindu [[Maharaja]] [[Hari Singh]]. Tribal forces with support from the army of Pakistan attacked and occupied parts of the princely state forcing the Maharajah to sign the [[Instrument of Accession (Jammu and Kashmir)|Agreement to the accession]] of the princely state to the [[Dominion of India]] to get Indian military aid. The UN Security Council passed the [[United Nations Security Council Resolution 47|Resolution 47]] on 22 April 1948. The fronts solidified gradually along what came to be known as the [[Line of Control]]. A formal cease-fire was declared at 23:59 on the night of 1 January 1949.&lt;ref name=&quot;Offl_Hist_1947&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=History of Operations in Jammu and Kashmir 1947–1948 |last1=Prasad|first1=S.N.|last2=Dharm Pal |year=1987 |publisher=History Department, Ministry of Defence, Government of India. (printed at Thomson Press (India) Limited) |location=New Delhi |isbn= |page=418 |url=|accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|379}} India gained control of about two-third of the state (including [[Kashmir valley]], [[Jammu]] and [[Ladakh]]) whereas Pakistan gained roughly a third of {{nowrap|Kashmir ([[Azad Kashmir]] and [[Gilgit–Baltistan]]).}}&lt;ref name=&quot;South Asia in World Politics&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
|last1=Hagerty 
|first1=Devin 
|title=South Asia in World Politics
|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=kJ6PZ7g3Yw0C&amp;pg=PA460&amp;dq=indo+Pakistani+war+of+1947+india+gained+two+third+Kashmir&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwixvL3ar6vLAhVHSI4KHaaZAC0Q6AEIHDAD#v=onepage&amp;q=indo%20Pakistani%20war%20of%201947%20india%20gained%20two%20third%20Kashmir&amp;f=false
|accessdate=2016-03-06
|year=2005
|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield 
|isbn=9780742525870
|page=161}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Kingfisher History Encyclopedia&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
|title=The Kingfisher History Encyclopedia
|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=kJ6PZ7g3Yw0C&amp;pg=PA460&amp;dq=indo+Pakistani+war+of+1947+india+gained+two+third+Kashmir&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwixvL3ar6vLAhVHSI4KHaaZAC0Q6AEIHDAD#v=onepage&amp;q=indo%20Pakistani%20war%20of%201947%20india%20gained%20two%20third%20Kashmir&amp;f=false
|accessdate=2016-03-06
|year=2004
|publisher=Kingfisher 
|isbn=9780753457849
|page=460}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;New Zealand Defence Quarterly&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
|title=New Zealand Defence Quarterly, Issues 24-29
|url=https://books.google.com/books?redir_esc=y&amp;id=fBcqAQAAIAAJ&amp;focus=searchwithinvolume&amp;q=invasion+1965
|accessdate=2016-03-06
|year=1999
|publisher=New Zealand. Ministry of Defence }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Perspectives on Kashmir: the roots of conflict in South Asia&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
|last1=Thomas 
|first1=Raju 
|title=Perspectives on Kashmir: the roots of conflict in South Asia
|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=xrPtAAAAMAAJ&amp;dq=indo+Pakistani+war+of+1947+india+gained+two+third+Kashmir+pakistan+azad+kashmir&amp;focus=searchwithinvolume&amp;q=India+held+two-third+of+Jammu+and+Kashmir+and+Pakistan+held+other+one+third
|accessdate=2016-03-06
|year=1992
|publisher=Westview Press 
|isbn=9780813383439
|page=25}}&lt;/ref&gt; Most neutral assessments, agree that [[India]] was the victor of the [[Indo-Pakistani War of 1947|war]] as it was able to conquer about two-third of the Kashmir including [[Kashmir valley]], [[Jammu]] and [[Ladakh]].&lt;ref name=&quot;New Zealand Defence Quarterly&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;War bellies: the critical relationship between resolve and domestic audiences&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|last1=Brozek
|first1=Jason 
|title=War bellies: the critical relationship between resolve and domestic audiences
|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=TP9XiqMu_BoC&amp;pg=PA142&amp;lpg=PA142&amp;dq=1947+first+kashmir+war+won+by+india+according+to+mids+classification&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=LOdw1JLewu&amp;sig=Cu64WyD1AubZWmDS1lVEkYxeOmo&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=wyqaVeGTCZaMuASLoYmwAw&amp;ved=0CA0Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=1947%20first%20kashmir%20war%20won%20by%20india%20according%20to%20mids%20classification&amp;f=false
|accessdate=2016-03-06
|year=2008
|publisher=University of Wisconsin--Madison
|isbn=978-1109044751
|page=142}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Global Rise of Asian Transformation: Trends and Developments in Economic Growth Dynamics&quot;&gt;
{{cite book
|last1=Hoontrakul
|first1=Pongsak 
|title=The Global Rise of Asian Transformation: Trends and Developments in Economic Growth Dynamics
|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=RrKYBgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA37&amp;lpg=PA37&amp;dq=war+of+1947+victorius+India+defeated+Pakistan&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=RLj-g6-hmT&amp;sig=wJloFas13nTcxlFmflu82zFn0LE&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjyg7z_yqvLAhXOCY4KHeduDkIQ6AEIDTAA#v=onepage&amp;q=Indo-Pakistan%20war%20of%201947%20victorious%20India%20defeated%20Pakistan&amp;f=false
|accessdate=2016-03-06
|year=2014
|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan
|edition=illustrated
|isbn=9781137412355
|page=37}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Operation Polo, 1948====
{{main article|Operation Polo}}
[[File:Op Polo Surrender.jpg|thumb|left|thumb|Maj. Gen. [[General El Edroos|El Edroos]] (right) surrenders to Maj. Gen. [[Joyanto Nath Chaudhuri]] at [[Secunderabad]].]]
After the war with Pakistan, India turned its attention to the independent [[Hyderabad State]]. India perceived the nearby independent Muslim state and potential Pakistani ally as a threat. In a five-day operation, India invaded and annexed Hyderabad.

====Invasion of Goa, 1961====
{{main article|Invasion of Goa}}
In 1961 tension rose between India and Portugal over the Portuguese-occupied territory of [[Goa]], which India claimed for itself. After Portuguese police cracked down violently on a peaceful, unarmed demonstration for union with India, the Indian government decided to invade. A lopsided air, sea, and ground campaign resulted in the speedy surrender of Portuguese forces.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.goacom.com/culture/history/history4.html |title=Goa's Freedom Movement |publisher=Goacom.com |date= |accessdate=2012-03-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; Within 36 hours, 451 years of Portuguese colonial rule was ended, and Goa was annexed by India. Portuguese losses were 31 killed, 57 wounded, and 3,306 captured. Indian losses were 34 killed and 51 wounded.&lt;ref name=&quot;Major K C Praval&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Praval |first=Major K.C. |title=Indian Army after Independence |publisher=Lancer |location=New Delhi |isbn=978-1-935501-10-7 |pages=214}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Sino-Indian war, 1962====
{{main article|Sino-Indian War}}
India fought a month-long border war against China in 1962. Neither nation deployed air or naval resources during a conflict heavy with mountain combat. China ended the war by declaring a unilateral ceasefire after it had taken all the territory it had claimed.

The defeat prompted India to make major changes in its military. The Department of Defence Production was established to create an indigenous defence production base, which would be self-reliant and self-sufficient. Since 1962, 16 new ordnance factories have been built under the program.{{citation needed|date=March 2016}}

====Second Indo-Pak war, 1965====
{{main article|Indo-Pakistani War of 1965}}
[[File:Brig.Hari Singh at Barkee Capture.jpg|thumb|right|Lt. Col. [[Hari Singh (soldier)|Hari Singh]] of the India's [[Indian 1st Armoured Division|18th Cavalry]] posing outside a captured Pakistani police station (Barkee) in Lahore District.]]
 
[[File:18Cav on move.jpg|thumb|[[M4 Sherman|Sherman]] tanks of [[18th Cavalry]] (Indian Army) on the move during the 1965 Indo-Pakistani War.]]

This war started following Pakistan's [[Operation Gibraltar]], which was designed to infiltrate forces into [[Jammu and Kashmir]] to precipitate an insurgency against rule by India. India retaliated by launching a full-scale military attack on [[West Pakistan]]. The seventeen-day war caused thousands of casualties on both sides and also witnessed the largest tank battle since World War II. The hostilities between the two countries ended after a ceasefire was declared following diplomatic intervention by the Soviet Union and USA and the subsequent issuance of the [[Tashkent Declaration]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Lyon2008&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Lyon|first=Peter|title=Conflict between India and Pakistan: an encyclopedia|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=vLwOck15eboC&amp;pg=PR11|accessdate=30 October 2011|year=2008|publisher=ABC-CLIO|isbn=978-1-57607-712-2|page=82}}&lt;/ref&gt; Though ruled to be militarily inconclusive, both India and Pakistan claimed victory. Most neutral assessments, however, agree that India had the [[Indo-Pakistani War of 1965#Assessment of losses|upper hand over Pakistan when the ceasefire was declared]].&lt;ref name=&quot;USLib&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://memory.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/r?frd/cstdy:@field(DOCID+pk0152)|title=Pakistan :: The Indo-Pakistani War of 1965|work=[[Library of Congress Country Studies]], United States of America|date=April 1994|accessdate=2 October 2010}} Quote: Losses were relatively heavy—on the Pakistani side, twenty aircraft, 200 tanks, and 3,800 troops. Pakistan's army had been able to withstand Indian pressure, but a continuation of the fighting would only have led to further losses and ultimate defeat for Pakistan.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hagerty&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last = Hagerty|first = Devin|title = South Asia in world politics|publisher = Rowman &amp; Littlefield, 2005|page=26|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ln3qChyrmIQC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=isbn:0742525872&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=aXEOUoW3HdCtrAfhnYGADA&amp;redir_esc=y#v=snippet&amp;q=outfought%20their%20Pakistani&amp;f=false|isbn = 0-7425-2587-2}} Quote: The invading Indian forces outfought their Pakistani counterparts and halted their attack on the outskirts of Lahore, Pakistan's second-largest city. By the time the United Nations intervened on 22 September, Pakistan had suffered a clear defeat.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Wolpert|first=Stanley|title=India|year=2005|publisher=University of California Press|location=Berkeley|isbn=0520246969|page=235|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=HmkL1tp2Nl4C&amp;q=won+a+clear+victory#v=snippet&amp;q=won%20a%20clear%20victory&amp;f=false|edition=3rd ed. with a new preface.}} Quote: India, however, was in a position to inflict grave damage to, if not capture, Pakistan's capital of the Punjab when the cease-fire was called, and controlled Kashmir's strategic Uri-Poonch bulge, much to Ayub's chagrin.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Dennis |last=Kux |title=India and the United States : Estranged democracies, 1941–1991|year=1992|publisher=National Defense University Press|location=Washington, DC|isbn=0788102796|page=238|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=zcylFXH9_z8C&amp;q=India+had+most+to+celebrate#v=snippet&amp;q=pakistan%20made%20gains&amp;f=false}} Quote: India had the better of the war.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Asia: Silent Guns, Wary Combatants|url=http://content.time.com/time/subscriber/article/0,33009,834413-2,00.html|accessdate=30 August 2013|newspaper=Time|date=1 October 1965}} Quote: India, by contrast, is still the big gainer in the war. Alternate link: http://content.time.com/time/subscriber/printout/0,8816,834413,00.html&lt;/ref&gt; As Pakistan lost more territory than it gained during the war and failed to achieve its goal of capturing Kashmir, many impartial observers have viewed the result as a defeat for Pakistan and an Indian [[strategic victory]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Profile of Pakistan&quot;&gt;[http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/3453.htm Profile of Pakistan]&amp;nbsp;– [[U.S. Department of State]], [http://globetrotter.berkeley.edu/people5/Coll/coll-con5.html Failure of U.S.'s Pakistan Policy]&amp;nbsp;– Interview with [[Steve Coll]]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Speech of Bill McCollum&quot;&gt;[https://fas.org/news/pakistan/1994/940912.htm Speech of Bill McCollum] in [[United States House of Representatives]] 12 September 1994&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Devin T. Hagerty p. 26&quot;&gt;South Asia in World Politics By Devin T. Hagerty, 2005 Rowman &amp; Littlefield, ISBN 0-7425-2587-2, p. 26&lt;/ref&gt;

===Indo-Sino Conflict of 1967===
{{main article|Cho La incident}}

The 1967 Sino-Indian skirmish also known as the [[Cho La incident]] (1{{snd}}10 October 1967) was a [[military conflict]] between [[India]] and [[China]] in the Himalayan [[Kingdom of Sikkim]], then an Indian [[protectorate]]. The Chinese [[People's Liberation Army]] infiltrated Sikkim&lt;ref name=Elleman&gt;{{cite book|title=Beijing's Power and China's Borders: Twenty Neighbors in Asia |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=CnDlcP6L8iEC&amp;pg=PA317 |page=317 |publisher=M.E. Sharpe |author1=Bruce Elleman |author2=Stephen Kotkin |author3=Clive Schofield |isbn=978-0-7656-2766-7 |year=2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; on 1{{nbsp}}October 1967, but was repulsed by the [[Indian Army]] by 10{{nbsp}}October. During the Cho La and [[Nathu La incident]]s, Indian losses were 88 killed in action and 163 wounded,&lt;ref name=Chengappa/&gt; while Chinese casualties were 340 killed in action and 450 wounded.&lt;ref name=Chengappa&gt;{{cite book|first=Bidanda M. |last=Chengappa |title=India-China relations: post conflict phase to post cold war period |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=BiluAAAAMAAJ |date=2004 |publisher=A.P.H. Pub. Corp. |isbn=978-81-7648-538-8 |page=63}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;shodhganga.inflibnet.ac.in&quot;&gt;http://shodhganga.inflibnet.ac.in/bitstream/10603/30868/6/06_chapter%202.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ssbmadeeasy.com&quot;&gt;http://www.ssbmadeeasy.com/2014/09/india-china-relationships-reasons-for-frequent-boder-disputes-and-indian-response.html&lt;/ref&gt;

The end of the battle saw the Chinese Army forced to leave Sikkim after being defeated by Indian troops.&lt;ref name=Hoontrakul&gt;{{cite book
|last=Hoontrakul |first=Pongsak |title=The Global Rise of Asian Transformation: Trends and Developments in Economic Growth Dynamics |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=RrKYBgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA37 |year=2014 |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |edition=illustrated |isbn=9781137412355 |page=37}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.millenniumpost.in/NewsContent.aspx?NID=11769 |title=50 years after Sino-Indian war |newspaper=Millennium Post |date=16 May 1975 |accessdate=12 July 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Kirantis’ khukris flash at Chola in 1967&quot;&gt;{{cite news|title=Kirantis’ khukris flash at Chola in 1967 |newspaper=Hindustan Times |accessdate=22 July 2015 |url=http://www.hindustantimes.com/chandigarh/kirantis-khukris-flash-at-chola-in-1967/article1-1239765.aspx}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Third Indo-Pak war, 1971====
{{main article|Indo-Pakistan War of 1971}}
{{further|Bangladesh Liberation War}}
[[File:1971 Instrument of Surrender.jpg|thumb|upright=1.2|Pakistan's Lt. Gen. [[A. A. K. Niazi]] signing the [[Pakistani Instrument of Surrender|instrument of surrender]] in [[Dhaka]] on 16 Dec' 1971, in the presence of India's [[Jagjit Singh Aurora|Lt. Gen. Aurora]]. Standing behind them are officers of India's Army, Navy and Air Force. The [[Indo-Pakistani War of 1971|1971 War]] directly involved participation of all three arms of Indian Armed Forces.]]

[[File:Ussdiablo.jpg|thumb|Pakistan's [[PNS Ghazi]], the Pakistani submarine which sank off during the 1971 Indo-Pakistani War under mysterious circumstances&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Till|first=Geoffrey |title=Seapower: a guide for the twenty-first century|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ZcejlMRYNAAC&amp;pg=PA179&amp;dq=PNS+Ghazi&amp;ei=LKdDSKG0H4KijgGs1qG-BQ&amp;sig=9YcFuLJttkAY3wIH965XTx6eU1Y#v=onepage&amp;q=PNS%20Ghazi&amp;f=false|accessdate=2010-05-28|year=2004|publisher=Frank Cass Publishers|location=Great Britain|isbn=0-7146-8436-8|page=179}}&lt;/ref&gt; on the Visakhapatnam coast.]]

This war was unique in the way that it did not involve the issue of Kashmir, but was rather precipitated by the crisis created by the political battle between Sheikh Mujib, Leader of East Pakistan and Yahya-Bhutto, leaders of West Pakistan brewing in erstwhile [[East Pakistan]] culminating in the declaration of Independence of Bangladesh from the state system of Pakistan. Following [[Operation Searchlight]] and the [[1971 Bangladesh atrocities]], about 10 million Bengalis in East Pakistan took refuge in neighbouring India.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
  |last = Christophe Jaffrelot, Gillian Beaumont
  |title = A History of Pakistan and Its Origins
  |publisher = Anthem Press, 2004
  |isbn = 1-84331-149-6 |id=ISBN 9781843311492}}&lt;/ref&gt;
India intervened in the ongoing [[Bangladesh Liberation War|Bangladesh liberation movement]].&lt;ref name=&quot;LATimes, 2002&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://articles.latimes.com/2002/mar/30/local/me-passings30.1 |title=Gen. Tikka Khan, 87; 'Butcher of Bengal' Led Pakistani Army |author=Times Staff and Wire Reports |date=30 March 2002 |newspaper=Los Angeles Times |accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Daily Star, 2011&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.thedailystar.net/magazine/2011/07/03/musing.htm|title=A Lamp Glows for Indira Gandhi |author=Syed Badrul Ahsan|date=15 July 2011 |work=Volume 10, Issue 27 |publisher=The Daily Star |accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; After a large scale [[Operation Chengiz Khan|pre-emptive strike]] by Pakistan, full-scale hostilities between the two countries commenced.

Pakistan attacked at several places along India's western border with Pakistan, but the [[Indian Army]] successfully held their positions. The [[Indian Army]] quickly responded to the Pakistan Army's movements in the west and made some initial gains, including capturing around {{convert|5795|sqmi|km2}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Shuja Nawaz 2008&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Nawaz |first=Shuja |title=Crossed Swords: Pakistan, Its Army, and the Wars Within |date=2008 |publisher=Oxford University Press |isbn=978-0-19-547697-2 |page=329}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=LCaAQCnO3QQC&amp;pg=PA81&amp;dq=5000+miles+square+indian+army+1971#v=onepage&amp;q=5000%20miles%20square%20indian%20army%201971&amp;f=false|title=Benazir, a Profile&amp;nbsp;– M. G. Chitkara|accessdate=27 July 2012|isbn=9788170247524|author1=Chitkara|first1=M. G|year=1996}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;https&quot;&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=Ek00fuXVz1wC&amp;pg=PA117&amp;dq=5000+miles+indian+army+1971#v=onepage&amp;q=5000%20miles%20indian%20army%201971&amp;f=false|title=Kashmir in Conflict: India, Pakistan and the Unending War&amp;nbsp;– Victoria Schofield|date=18 January 2003|accessdate=27 July 2012|isbn=9781860648984|author1=Schofield|first1=Victoria}}&lt;/ref&gt; of Pakistan territory (land gained by India in Pakistani Kashmir, [[Punjab, Pakistan|Pakistani Punjab]] and [[Sindh]] sectors but gifted it back to Pakistan in the [[Simla Agreement]] of 1972, as a gesture of goodwill). Within two weeks of intense fighting, Pakistani forces in [[East Pakistan]] [[Instrument of Surrender (1971)|surrendered]] to the joint command of Indian and Bangladeshi forces following which the [[People's Republic of Bangladesh]] was created.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leonard, 2006&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last = Leonard |first = Thomas |title = Encyclopedia of the developing world |publisher = Taylor &amp; Francis|year= 2006 |isbn = 978-0-415-97662-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; This war saw the highest number of casualties in any of the India-Pakistan conflicts, as well as the largest number of [[prisoners of war]] since the Second World War after the surrender of more than 90,000 Pakistani military and civilians.&lt;ref name=&quot;BBC Troubled relations&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/hi/english/static/in_depth/south_asia/2002/india_pakistan/timeline/1971.stm |title=The 1971 war |author=Unspecified author |work=India – Pakistan:Troubled relations |publisher=BBC |accessdate=30 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the words of one Pakistani author, &quot;Pakistan lost half its navy, a quarter of its air force and a third of its army&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Ali|first=Tariq|title =Can Pakistan Survive? The Death of a State|url=https://books.google.com/?id=moJPPgAACAAJ&amp;dq=Can+Pakistan+Survive%3F|publisher =Verso Books|year=1997|isbn=0-86091-949-8 |id=ISBN 9780860919490}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Siachen war, 1984====
{{main article|Siachen conflict}}
In the late 1970s and early 1980s, Pakistan began organising tourist expeditions on the [[Siachen Glacier]], disputed territory with India. Irked by this development, in April 1984 India initiated successful [[Operation Meghdoot|Operation ''Meghdoot'']] during which it gained control over all of the [[Siachen Glacier]]. [[India]] has established control over all of the {{convert|70|km|mi}} long Siachen Glacier and all of its tributary glaciers, as well as the three main passes of the [[Saltoro Mountains|Saltoro Ridge]] immediately west of the glacier—[[Sia La]], [[Bilafond La]], and [[Gyong La]].&lt;ref name=Wirsing&gt;{{cite book  |last = Wirsing  |first = Robert  |title = Pakistan's security under Zia, 1977–1988: the policy imperatives of a peripheral Asian state  |publisher = Palgrave Macmillan, 1991  |isbn = 9780312060671}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Child&gt;{{cite book  |last = Child  |first = Greg  |title = Thin air: encounters in the Himalayas  |publisher = The Mountaineers Books, 1998  |isbn = 9780898865882}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to [[TIME magazine|''TIME'' magazine]], India gained more than {{convert|1000|sqmi|km2|sigfig=1}} of territory because of its military operations in Siachen.&lt;ref name=&quot;:1&quot;&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,958254-2,00.html | publisher=Time.com | title=The Himalayas War at the Top Of the World | date=July 31, 1989 | first=Edward W. | last=Desmond/Kashmir}}&lt;/ref&gt; It still maintains a military base there.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://edition.cnn.com/2002/WORLD/asiapcf/south/05/20/siachen.kashmir/| title=Siachen: The world's highest cold war| accessdate=2006-04-10| first=Nick| last=Easen | work=CNN | date=20 May 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt; Pakistan tried in 1987 and in 1989 to re-take the glacier but was unsuccessful. The conflict ended with Indian Victory.&lt;ref name=Kapur&gt;{{cite book|last=Kapur|first=S. Paul|title=Dangerous Deterrent: Nuclear Weapons Proliferation and Conflict in South Asia|publisher=Stanford University Press|isbn=978-0804755504|page=118}}&lt;/ref&gt; Ceasefire since 2003.{{citation needed|date=March 2016}}

====Kargil War, 1999====
{{main article|Kargil War}}
[[File:Sheeju mig21.JPG|thumb|IAF [[MiG-21]]s were used extensively in the [[Kargil war]].]]
Commonly known as the Kargil War, or Operation Vijay in India, this conflict between the two countries was mostly limited. During early 1999, Pakistani troops infiltrated across the [[Line of Control]] (LoC) and occupied Indian territory mostly in the [[Kargil district]]. India responded by launching a major military and diplomatic offensive to drive out the Pakistani infiltrators.&lt;ref name=Stanley&gt;{{cite book |last=Wolpert |first=Stanley |title=India and Pakistan: Continued Conflict or Cooperation? |publisher=University of California Press |date=14 Aug 2010 |pages=73 |chapter=Recent Attempts to Resolve the Conflict|isbn=9780520271401}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two months into the conflict, Indian troops had slowly retaken most of the ridges that were encroached by the infiltrators.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.lrb.co.uk/v23/n08/ali_01_.html|title=Bitter Chill of Winter|first=Tariq|last=Ali |authorlink=Tariq Ali|newspaper= [[London Review of Books]]=| accessdate=2009-05-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | author=Colonel Ravi Nanda | title=Kargil: A Wake Up Call | publisher=Vedams Books | year=1999 | isbn=81-7095-074-0}} [https://www.vedamsbooks.com/no14953.htm Online summary of the Book] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070928055430/https://www.vedamsbooks.com/no14953.htm |date=28 September 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; According to official count, an estimated 75%–80% of the intruded area and nearly all high ground was back under Indian control.&lt;ref name=&quot;VP Malik&quot;&gt;[http://www.dailytimes.com.pk/default.asp?page=story_26-7-2002_pg4_12 Kargil: where defence met diplomacy] - India's then [[Chief of Army Staff of the Indian Army|Chief of Army Staff]] VP Malik, expressing his views on Operation Vijay. Hosted on ''[[Daily Times (Pakistan)|Daily Times]]''; [http://www.stanford.edu/group/sjir/3.1.06_kapur-narang.html The Fate of Kashmir By Vikas Kapur and Vipin Narang] Stanford Journal of International Relations; [http://www.ipcs.org/ipcs/displayReview.jsp?kValue=102 Book review of &quot;The Indian Army: A Brief History by Maj Gen Ian Cardozo&quot;] - Hosted on IPCS&lt;/ref&gt;
Fearing large-scale escalation in military conflict, the international community, led by the [[United States]], increased diplomatic pressure on Pakistan to withdraw forces from remaining Indian territory.&lt;ref name=Stanley/&gt;&lt;ref name=Dettman&gt;{{cite book |last=R. Dettman |first=Paul |title=India Changes Course: Golden Jubilee to Millennium |publisher=Greenwood Publishing Group |year=2001 |pages=119–120 |chapter=Kargil War Operations|isbn=9780275973087}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
Faced with the possibility of international isolation, the already fragile [[Economy of Pakistan|Pakistani economy]] was weakened further.&lt;ref name=&quot;Samina Ahmed&quot;&gt;[http://belfercenter.ksg.harvard.edu/publication/1209/diplomatic_fiasco.html Samina Ahmed. &quot;Diplomatic Fiasco: Pakistan's Failure on the Diplomatic Front Nullifies its Gains on the Battlefield&quot;] (Belfer Center for International Affairs, [[Kennedy School of Government]])&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.salon.com/news/feature/1999/10/13/reacts/print.html|title=Coup d'itat: Pakistan gets a new sheriff|author=Daryl Lindsey and Alicia Montgomery|work=salon.com|accessdate=19 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The morale of Pakistani forces after the withdrawal declined as many units of the [[Northern Light Infantry]] suffered heavy casualties.&lt;ref name=&quot;Summary&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.ccc.nps.navy.mil/research/kargil/war_in_kargil.pdf|format=PDF|title=War in Kargil - The CCC's summary on the war|work=|publisher=| accessdate=2009-05-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://belfercenter.ksg.harvard.edu/publication/1002/friend_for_all_seasons.html Samina Ahmed. &quot;A Friend for all Seasons.&quot;] (Belfer Center for International Affairs, [[Kennedy School of Government]])&lt;/ref&gt; The government refused to accept the dead bodies of many officers,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rediff.com/news/1999/jul/11karg1.htm|title=Rediff On The NeT: Pakistan refuses to take even officers' bodies|work=rediff.com|accessdate=19 June 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.indianembassy.org/pic/PR_1999/July_1999/PR_July_15_1999.html &quot;press release issued in New Delhi regarding bodies of two Pakistan Army Officers&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; an issue that provoked outrage and protests in the Northern Areas.&lt;ref&gt;Second-Class Citizens by M. Ilyas Khan, [[The Herald (Pakistan)]], July 2000. [http://www.warbirds.in/downloads/HeraldKargil.pdf Online scanned version of the article]([[PDF]])&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hinduonnet.com/thehindu/thscrip/print.pl?file=2006092505001100.htm&amp;date=2006/09/25/&amp;prd=th&amp; Musharraf and the truth about Kargil] - [[The Hindu]] 25 September 2006&lt;/ref&gt; Pakistan initially did not acknowledge many of its casualties, but [[Nawaz Sharif]] later said that over 4,000 Pakistani troops were killed in the operation and that Pakistan had lost the conflict.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hindu Sharif&quot;&gt;{{cite web| url=http://hindu.com/2003/08/17/stories/2003081702900800.htm|title=Over 4000 soldier's killed in Kargil: Sharif|work=[[The Hindu]]|publisher=| accessdate=2009-05-20}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Kapur2&gt;{{cite book|last=Kapur|first=S. Paul|title=Dangerous Deterrent: Nuclear Weapons Proliferation and Conflict in South Asia|year=2007|publisher=Stanford University Press|isbn=978-0804755498|edition=23rd|page=227}}&lt;/ref&gt;
By the end of July 1999, organized hostilities in the Kargil district had ceased&lt;ref name=Dettman/&gt; and [[Kargil War]] finally came to end with a decisive Indian military and diplomatic victory.&lt;ref name=&quot;India Changes Course: Golden Jubilee to Millennium&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=R. Dettman |first1=Paul |title=India Changes Course: Golden Jubilee to Millennium |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=8p19H4UwE_AC&amp;pg=PA130&amp;dq=kargil+war+indian+victory&amp;hl=en#v=snippet&amp;q=%20indian%20victory&amp;f=false
|accessdate=2016-02-19 |edition=first |year=2001 |publisher=Praeger Publishers |location= United states of America|language=English |isbn= |oclc= |doi= |id= |pages=130, 131, 133, 153
|chapter=Kargil&quot;war&quot;repercussions}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;South Asian Security and International Nuclear Order&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last1=Carranza |first1=Mario Esteban |title=South Asian Security and International Nuclear Order |date=2009 |publisher=Ashgate |isbn=978-0-7546-7541-9 |pages=82, 90 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=JjtcVRsL4JIC&amp;pg=PA82&amp;dq=Kargil+War+India+won+diplomatic+and&amp;hl=en#v=onepage&amp;q=won%20the%20kargil%20war&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=6f2opVxRGDcC&amp;pg=PA2002&amp;dq=India+won+kargil&amp;hl=en Arming without Aiming: India's Military Modernization By Stephen P. Cohen, Sunil Dasgupta pg. 2002]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Religion and Politics in Comparative Perspective: The One, The Few, and The Many&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|last1=Wilcox
|first1=Clyde
|title=Religion and Politics in Comparative Perspective: The One, The Few, and The Many
|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=6HFq0eyEK4QC&amp;pg=PA259&amp;dq=India+won+kargil&amp;hl=en#v=snippet&amp;q=India%20won%20a%20military%20and%20victory%20&amp;f=false
|accessdate=2016-02-19 
|edition=illustrated, reprint
|year=2002
|publisher=Cambridge University Press
|isbn=978-0-275-97308-7
|page=259
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;India's emerging security strategy, missile defense, and arms control&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|title=India's emerging security strategy, missile defense, and arms control
|publisher=DIANE Publishing
|accessdate=2016-02-19
|isbn=978-1-4289-8261-1
|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=cA2ecrVgayoC&amp;dq=India+won+kargil&amp;q=decisive+indian+victory+kargil
|page=25
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Berlitz: India Pocket Guide&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|first1=Berlitz
|title=Berlitz: India Pocket Guide
|date=2013
|publisher=Apa Publications (UK) Limited
|accessdate=2016-02-19
|isbn=978-1-78004-757-7
|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=GfkxBgAAQBAJ&amp;dq=decisive+indian+victory+kargil&amp;q=decisive+indian+victory+kargil#v=snippet&amp;q=decisive%20indian%20victory%20kargil&amp;f=false
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Wars, Proxy-wars and Terrorism: Post Independent India&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|last1=Wilson 
|first1=Peter 
|title=Wars, Proxy-wars and Terrorism: Post Independent India
|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=qYK0BhcgwaQC&amp;q=decisive+kargil&amp;hl=en#v=snippet&amp;q=decisive%20kargil&amp;f=false
|accessdate=2016-02-19
|year=2003
|publisher=Mittal Publications 
|isbn=978-81-7099-890-7
|page=143
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The India-Pakistan Military Standoff: Crisis and Escalation in South Asia&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|last1=Davis
|first1=Zachary
|title=The India-Pakistan Military Standoff: Crisis and Escalation in South Asia
|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=0dXHAAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA5&amp;dq=kargil+war+indian+victory&amp;hl=en
|accessdate=2016-02-19
|year=2011
|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan US
|isbn=978-0-230-10938-4
|page=5
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;India's Nuclear Bomb: The Impact on Global Proliferation&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|last1=Perkovich
|first1=George 
|title=India's Nuclear Bomb: The Impact on Global Proliferation
|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=UDA9dUryS8EC&amp;pg=PA479&amp;dq=kargil+war+indian+victory&amp;hl=en
|accessdate=2016-02-19
|year=2001
|publisher=University of California Press
|isbn=978-0-520-23210-5
|page=479
}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Global Rise of Asian Transformation: Trends and Developments in Economic Growth Dynamics&quot;&gt;{{cite book
|last1=Hoontrakul
|first1=Pongsak 
|title=The Global Rise of Asian Transformation: Trends and Developments in Economic Growth Dynamics
|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=RrKYBgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA37&amp;dq=kargil+war+indian+victory&amp;hl=en#v=onepage&amp;q=kargil%20war%20victorious%20India%20defeated%20pakistan&amp;f=false
|accessdate=2016-02-19
|year=2014
|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan
|edition=illustrated
|isbn=978-1-137-41235-5
|page=37}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Other operations ===

====The Mizo National Front, 1966====
{{main article|March 1966 Mizo National Front uprising}}
In March 1966, [[Mizo people|Mizo]] rebels in [[Assam]] declared independence and attacked government offices and military posts. The uprising was suppressed weeks later, and eventually [[Mizoram]] was made a separate state of India.

====The Chola incident, 1967====
A Sino-Indian skirmish known today as the [[Chola incident]] took place in October 1967. The [[People's Liberation Army]] made a brief incursion into [[Sikkim]] but retreated within 48 hours.

====Operation Blue Star, 1984====
{{main article|Operation Blue Star}}
In June 1984, then-Prime Minister [[Indira Gandhi]] ordered an attack on Sikh separatists belonging to the [[Khalistan movement]] who had holed up in the [[Harmandir Sahib|Golden Temple]] in Amritsar. The operation resulted in 500-1,500 civilian deaths and heavy damage to the [[Akal Takht]].

==== Sri Lanka mission, 1987–1990 ====
{{main article|Sri Lankan Civil War#Indian involvement}}
The [[Indian Peace Keeping Force]] (IPKF) carried out a mission in northern and eastern [[Sri Lanka]] in 1987–1990 to disarm the [[Tamil Tigers]] per the [[Indo-Sri Lanka Accord]]. It was a difficult battle for the Indian Army, which was not trained for an unconventional war. After losing approximately 1,200 in personnel and several T-72 tanks, India ultimately abandoned the mission in consultation with Sri Lankan government. In what was labeled as ''Operation Pawan'', the Indian Air Force flew about 70,000 sorties to and within Sri Lanka.

==== Operation Cactus, 1988 ====
[[File:IAF IL-76 Hawaii.JPG|thumb|left|An [[Indian Air Force]] [[Ilyushin Il-76]] transport aircraft of the model used to paradrop Indian troops in [[Malé]].]]
{{main article|Operation Cactus}}
In November 1988, the [[Maldives]] Government appealed India for military help against a [[mercenary]] invasion. On the night of 3 November, the Indian Air Force airlifted the Para Special forces from [[Agra]] and flew them non-stop over 2,000&amp;nbsp;km to Maldives. The paracommandos landed at [[Hulule]], secured the airfield, and restored government rule at [[Malé]] within hours and without bloodshed.

=== Missile program ===
[[File:Akash SAM.jpg|thumb|right|An Akash missile being test fired from the Integrated Test Range (ITR), [[Chandipur, India|Chandipur]], [[Odisha]].]]
India has well developed{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}} missile capabilities with roots in the [[Indian Space Program]]. The Integrated Guided Missile Development Program ([[IGMDP]]) was formed in 1983 with the aim of achieving self-sufficiency in missile development and production. Presently it comprises six core missile programs:
* [[Agni missile|Agni ballistic missile]]
* [[Prithvi missile|Prithvi ballistic missile]]
* [[Akash missile|Akash surface-to-air missile]]
* [[Trishul Missile|Trishul surface-to-air missile]]
* [[Nag Missile|Nag anti-tank guided missile]]
* [[Nirbhay Missile|Nirbhay cruise missile]]

Currently the [[DRDO]] is developing [[Surya (missile)]], an advanced series of [[ICBM]] that the government reports would have a range of more than 10,000&amp;nbsp;km. This would put its range on par with advanced missiles in the United States, Russia, and Israel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release | title = Development of Ballistic Missile Defence System: Year End Review | publisher = [[Ministry of Defence (India)]] | date = 28 December 2007 | url = http://pib.nic.in/release/release.asp?relid=34262 | accessdate = 2008-01-26 | quote = }}&lt;/ref&gt; India is the fourth country in the world to develop a successful{{Citation needed|date=September 2011}} missile defence shield, the [[Indian Ballistic Missile Defense Program]].

=== Nuclear program ===
{{See also|India and weapons of mass destruction}}

[[File:ShaktiBomb.jpg|thumb|''Shakti I'': a [[thermonuclear device]] detonated on 11 May 1998 as part of the [[Pokhran-II]] tests. The [[nuclear yield]] was reported to be 45 kt.&lt;ref name=toi&gt;{{cite web|title=Forces gung-ho on N-arsenal|url=http://epaper.timesofindia.com/Repository/ml.asp?Ref=VE9JTS8yMDA5LzA4LzI4I0FyMDE1MDA|publisher=Times of India|accessdate=21 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]

In 1974, India tested a nuclear weapon with a yield of up to 15 [[kiloton]]s. The test was codenamed [[Smiling Buddha]]. On 11 and 13 May 1998, India conducted a total of five underground nuclear tests and declared itself a [[List of countries with nuclear weapons|nuclear state]].

== Recent developments ==
The Indian military ranks [[List of countries by number of active troops|third]] in terms of number of troops after the U.S. and China. The [[paramilitary]] unit of the Republic of India is the world's largest paramilitary force at over one million strong. Eager to portray itself as a potential [[superpower]], India began an intense phase of upgrading its armed forces in the late 1990s. India focuses on developing indigenous military equipment rather than relying on other countries for supplies. Most of the Indian naval ships and submarines, military armoured vehicles, missiles, and ammunition are indigenously designed and manufactured.

=== Military collaborations with other countries ===
[[File:IA T-90 in action.jpg|thumb|left|Indian T-90 ''Bhishma'' tanks during a training exercise in the [[Thar Desert]], [[Rajasthan]]. Note the two different turret armour arrays.]]
In 1997, India agreed to participate in the development of Russia's &quot;Prospective Air Complex for Tactical Air Forces&quot; program. One of the primary objectives of the program was to develop a 5th generation [[fighter aircraft]]; the [[Su-47]] prototype flew its first successful test flight in 1997. The [[BrahMos]], a [[supersonic]] cruise missile jointly developed with Russia, was successfully test fired in 2001. India is also collaborating with [[Israel]] to develop [[Unmanned Aerial Vehicle]]s.

India has focused recently on purchasing the technology behind military equipment rather than equipment itself. Recent examples include purchases of [[Sukhoi Su-30 MKI]] multi-role fighter aircraft and [[T-90]] main battle tanks from Russia and diesel-powered Scorpene submarines from France. In 2004, India purchased US$5.7 billion worth of military equipment from other countries, making it the developing world's leading arms purchaser.

=== Disasters ===

On 28 April 2000, ammunition worth {{INRConvert|3.93|b}} was destroyed in a fire at the [[Bharatpur, India|Bharatpur]] ammunition depot. Another fire at the [[Pathankot]] sub-depot resulted in loss of ammo worth {{INRConvert|280|m}}. On 24 May 2001, another blaze at the Birdhwal sub-depot destroyed ammunition worth {{INRConvert|3.78|b}}.

=== Awards ===
[[File:Ashoka Chakra Award.jpg|thumb|The [[Ashoka Chakra]]]]

India's highest awards for military conduct in a time of war are, in descending order, the [[Param Vir Chakra]], [[Maha Vir Chakra]], and [[Vir Chakra]]. The peacetime equivalents are respectively the [[Ashoka Chakra Award|Ashoka Chakra]], [[Kirti Chakra]] and [[Shaurya Chakra]]. The latter two awards were formerly known as ''Ashoka Chakra, Class II'' and ''Ashoka Chakra, Class III'' respectively. The peacetime awards have occasionally been bestowed on civilians. For meritorious service, the awards are the Param Vishisht Seva Medal, the Athi Vishisht Seva Medal, and the Vishisht Seva Medal.

== See also ==
* [[Indian Army Day]]
* [[History of India]]
* [[History of the Indian Navy]]
* [[:Category:Military history of India during World War II|Military history of India during World War II]]
* [[Military of India]]
* [[Michel Joachim Marie Raymond|Monsieur Raymond]] (1755–1798), French Adventurer, General and friend of the [[Nizam]] of India

==Further reading==
* Jaywant D. Joglekar, &quot;Decisive Battles India Lost (326 B. C. to 1803 A. D.)&quot; (2006)
* Cohen, Stephen P. and Sunil Dasgupta, eds. ''Arming Without Aiming: India's Military Modernization'' (2010) [http://www.amazon.com/Arming-Without-Aiming-Military-Modernization/dp/081570402X/ excerpt and text search]
* Davis, Zachary S. ''The India-Pakistan Military Standoff: Crisis and Escalation in South Asia'' (2011) [http://www.amazon.com/India-Pakistan-Military-Standoff-Escalation-Initiatives/dp/0230109381/ excerpt and text search]; focus on 2000-01 confrontation
* Deshpande, Anirudh. ''British Military Policy in India, 1900-1945: Colonial Constraints and Declining Power'' (2005)
* Holmes, James R. et al. ''Indian Naval Strategy in the Twenty-first Century'' (2009) [http://www.amazon.com/Indian-Naval-Strategy-Twenty-first-Century/dp/0415586003/ excerpt and text search]
* Khan, Iqtidar Alam. ''Gunpowder and Firearms: Warfare in Medieval India'' (2004)
* Marston, Daniel P. and Chandar S. Sundaram. ''A Military History of India and South Asia: From the East India Company to the Nuclear Era'' (2006)
* Roy, Kaushik. ''From Hydaspes to Kargil: A History of Warfare in India from 326 BC to AD 1999'' (2004)
* Roy, Kaushik. ''The Oxford Companion to Modern Warfare in India'' (2009)
* Sandhu, Gurcharn Singh. ''Military History of Medieval India'' (2003)
* Sundaram, Chandar S., ‘Warfare—South Asia’, in W.H. McNeill and P. Stearns, eds., the Berkshire Encyclopaedia of World History, 2005, vol. 5, pp.&amp;nbsp;1991–6, (2005)
* Sundaram, Chandar S., &quot;A Paper Tiger: the Indian National Army in battle, 1944-1945&quot;, War &amp; Society, 13(1), pp.&amp;nbsp;35–59 (1995)
* Thapliyal, P., and Uma Prasad. ''Warfare in Ancient India: Organizational and Operational Dimensions'' (2010)

==External links==
{{commons category}}
* [http://acdis.illinois.edu/students/courses-current/focal-point-seminar/Cohen-India.html/ The Irrelevance of India's Rise as a Military Power]- video of lecture by Stephen P. Cohen, Brookings Institution, hosted by the Program in Arms Control, Disarmament, and International Security (ACDIS), University of Illinois, 15 October 2009
* [http://www.keele.ac.uk/socs/ks45/PageHistory/Club/bracey/Kushan/Military/notes.htm Notes]
* [http://defencejournal.com/sept99/martial-races.htm The Role of Muslims Martial Races of Today: Pakistan in British-Indian Army in World War-II by Brig (Retd) Noor A Husain].
* [http://www.india-defence.com/ India Defence]- Defence And Military Portal
* [http://www.indianjawan.com/ Indian Jawan]- A Tribute To The Indian Soldier
* [http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/LAND-FORCES/Army/Link3.html Indian army history]
* [http://indianairforce.nic.in/history1.htm Indian Air Force history]
* [http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/IAF/History/index.html Indian Air Force History (Bharat-Rakshak.com)]
* [http://www.members.dca.net/fbl/indexsurname.html Soldiers of the British and Indian armies 1840 to 1920]
* [http://dl.lib.brown.edu/libweb/collections/askb/ Anne S. K. Brown Military Collection, Brown University Library] Military history and graphics, c. 1790–1918

== Notes ==
{{Reflist|30em}}

=== Official war histories ===
Official war histories written by the History Division, Ministry of Defence, [[Government of India]]:
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20051123011951/http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/LAND-FORCES/Army/History/1962War/PDF/index.html Sino-Indian war, 1962] 
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20051217085236/http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/LAND-FORCES/Army/History/1965War/PDF/index.html Indo-Pak war, 1965] 
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20051123012016/http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/LAND-FORCES/Army/History/1971War/PDF/index.html Indo-Pak war, 1972]

{{Military of India}}
{{India topics}}
{{Asia in topic|Military history of}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Military History Of India}}
[[Category:Military history of India| ]]
[[Category:History of Sindh]]</text>
      <sha1>ninryn6y2x1lfaimlz9s41lhkl1vqs3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
