<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Mills bomb</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>444180</id>
    <revision>
      <id>751109384</id>
      <parentid>743965505</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-23T12:13:35Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>87.112.27.13</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Rifle grenade */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10663">{{more footnotes|date=January 2010}}

{{Infobox Weapon|is_explosive=yes
| name=Mills bomb
|image=[[File:N°5-MkII N°23-MkII N°36-MkI.jpg|300px]] 
|caption=Mills bombs. From left to right : N°5, N°23, N°36.
|origin=United Kingdom
|design_date=1915
|service=1915–1980s
|type=[[Hand grenade]]
|filling=[[Baratol (explosive)|Baratol]]
|detonation=Percussion cap and time delay fuse: 7 seconds,&lt;br /&gt; later reduced to 4
|number=70 million +
|weight= {{convert|765|g|lboz|abbr=on}}
|fill_weight = 71
|length=95.2mm
|diameter={{convert|61|mm|in|abbr=on}}
|variants=No. 5, No. 23,&lt;br /&gt; No. 36, No. 36M
|}}

'''Mills bomb''' is the popular name for a series of prominent British [[hand grenade]]s. They were the first modern fragmentation grenades used by the British Army.

==Overview==
[[William Mills (inventor of the Mills bomb)|William Mills]], a [[hand grenade]] designer from [[Sunderland A.F.C.|Sunderland]], patented, developed and manufactured the &quot;Mills bomb&quot; at the Mills Munition Factory in [[Birmingham]], England, in 1915.&lt;ref&gt;{{US patent|1178092}} U.S. copy of the 1915/1916 Mills grenade patent&lt;/ref&gt; The Mills bomb was inspired by an earlier design by Belgian captain Leon Roland. Roland and Mills were later engaged in a patent lawsuit.&lt;ref name=&quot;Sheffield2007&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=G. D. Sheffield|title=War on the Western Front|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=2tZK2eEqM_gC&amp;pg=PA196|year=2007|publisher=Osprey Publishing|isbn=978-1-84603-210-3|page=196}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Mills bomb was adopted by the [[British Army]] as its standard hand grenade in 1915, and designated the No. 5.&lt;ref name=&quot;listA&quot;&gt;{{cite web
| title = www.firstworldwar.com - Who's Who - Sir William Mills
| url = http://www.firstworldwar.com/bio/mills.htm
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Mills bomb underwent numerous modifications.  The No. 23 was a variant of the No. 5 with a rodded base plug which allowed it to be fired from a rifle.  This concept evolved further with the No. 36, a variant with a detachable base plate to allow use with a rifle discharger cup. The final variation of the Mills bomb, the No. 36M, was specially designed and waterproofed with [[shellac]]&lt;ref name=&quot;listA&quot; /&gt; for use initially in the hot climate of [[Mesopotamia]] in 1917, but remained in production for many years.  By 1918 the No. 5 and No. 23 were declared obsolete and the No. 36 (but not the 36M) followed in 1932.

The Mills was a classic design; a grooved [[cast iron]] &quot;pineapple&quot; with a central striker held by a close hand lever and secured with a pin. According to Mills's notes, the casing was grooved to make it easier to grip and not as an aid to fragmentation, and in practice it has been demonstrated that it does not shatter along the segmented lines. The Mills was a defensive grenade: after throwing the user had to take cover immediately. A competent thrower could manage 15 metres (49&amp;nbsp;feet) with reasonable accuracy,{{fact|date=August 2016}} but the grenade could throw lethal fragments farther than this. The British Home Guard were instructed that the throwing range of the No. 36 was about 30 yards with a danger area of about 100 yds.&lt;ref&gt;Capt. A. Southworth, M.B.E (1944)[http://met.open.ac.uk/group/jwl/hg_manual/25.htm Home Guard Pocket Manual] p47&lt;/ref&gt;

At first the grenade was fitted with a seven-second fuse, but during combat in the [[Battle of France]] in 1940 this delay proved to be too long, giving defenders time to escape the explosion, or even to throw the grenade back, and was reduced to four seconds.

The heavy segmented bodies of &quot;pineapple&quot; type grenades result in an unpredictable pattern of fragmentation. After the Second World War Britain adopted grenades that contained segmented coiled wire in smooth metal casings. The No. 36M Mk.I remained the standard grenade of the [[British Armed Forces]] and was manufactured in the UK until 1972, when it was completely replaced by the [[M61 grenade|L2]] series. The 36M remained in service in some parts of the world such as [[India]] and [[Pakistan]], where it was manufactured until the early 1980s. Mills bombs were still being used in combat as recently as 2004 e.g. the incident which killed US Marine [[Jason Dunham]] and wounded two of his comrades.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://usmcronbo.tripod.com/id89.htm |title=Cpl Jason Dunham |publisher=Usmcronbo.tripod.com |date= |accessdate=23 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Models&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.passioncompassion1418.com/decouvertes/english_grenades_gb.html|title=Passion &amp; Compassion 1914-1918 : WW1 militaria and technical documentation - english grenades|author=Bernard Plumier|work=passioncompassion1418.com}}&lt;/ref&gt;==
*The '''No. 5 Mk. 1''' was the first version. The explosive filler was loaded through a small circular plug on the upper half, the detonator assembly was loaded through the bottom through the baseplug, and the pull-ring striker was screwed in to the fuze well at the top. The lever was protected by metal &quot;ears&quot; flanking the top that could be used to locate it in darkness. It was first issued in May, 1915 but wasn't in general issue until mass production caught up a year later in 1916. The '''Mk. 2''' had a redesigned stronger safety lever.
*The '''No. 23''', the rifle-grenade model, first appeared in 1917. '''The No. 23 Mk. 1''' had a redesigned, narrower baseplug that was centrally threaded underneath so it could attach the rifle rod. The '''Mk. 2''' and '''Mk. 3''' were product-improved versions designed to make it cheaper and easier to produce.
*The improved '''No. 36 Mk. 1''' was first introduced in May, 1918. It was wider in the middle, had larger lever &quot;ears&quot;, and had an optional gas-check disk to allow it to be launched out of a blank-propelled cup-discharger. The shellac-coated &quot;[[Mesopotamian campaign|Mesopotamian]]&quot; variant ('''No. 36M''') was designed to keep moisture and humidity out of the detonator's fuze. The No. 36M Mk. 1 was the British army's standard hand-grenade from the 1930s to the 1970s.

==Identification marks==
*A green band around the middle originally indicated an [[Amatol]] filling (1915–1920s), while it later indicated a [[Baratol]] or [[Trotyl]] filling (1920s–1970s).
*A pink band around the middle indicates an [[Ammonal]] or Alumatol filling. (Alumatol is defined by the ''[[iarchive:dictionaryofexpl00marsrich|Dictionary of Explosives, pub 1920]]''&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://archive.org/details/dictionaryofexpl00marsrich|title=Dictionary of Explosives|last=Marshall|first=Arthur|publisher=Blakiston|year=1920|isbn=|location=Philadelphia, USA|pages=}}&lt;/ref&gt; as 'a mixture of ammonium nitrate, TNT and 'a small quantity' of aluminium power.) A red band around the base plug on the bottom indicated the detonator was already installed and that the grenade was live.
*Three red X's along each side indicates that it is the waterproofed No.36M model.

==Rifle grenade==

The Mills bomb was developed into a rifle grenade by attaching a metallic rod to its base. This rod-type rifle-grenade had an effective range of about 150 yards. The operating procedure was to insert the Mills bomb rod down the barrel of a standard rifle, put a special blank cartridge in the rifle chamber, place the rifle stock on the ground, then pull the Mills Bomb safety pin, releasing the safety spoon and immediately fire the rifle. If the soldier did not launch the grenade quickly, the grenade's fuse would time out and explode. The British soon developed a simple cradle attached to the rifle's bayonet fixing to hold the safety-spoon in place and prevent accidental detonations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://inert-ord.net/rod02h/mills23/index.html|title=British Mills No.23 Rod Grenade - Inert-Ord.Net|first=Copyright 2001-2005|last=Inert-Ord.Net|publisher=|accessdate=5 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, it was  found that the repeated launching of rod-type grenades caused damage to the rifle's barrel.
 
The British subsequently developed a cup-type launcher to replace the rod-type rifle-grenade. In this design, a can-shaped launcher was attached to the muzzle of the rifle and a gas check disc was screwed onto the base of the grenade before the grenade was placed in the launcher. The safety pin could then be removed as the launcher cup kept the safety-spoon in place. The operator inserted the blank cartridge into the rifle before setting the stock, angled on the ground to absorb the recoil of the weapon. When the cartridge was fired it pushed the grenade out of the cup releasing the spoon. The cup-type launcher could launch the grenade about 200 yards. Lee–Enfield rifles equipped with the cup launcher were modified with copper wire wrapped around the stock, to prevent the wood from cracking under the increased recoil. If necessary, both the rod and the gas check grenade could be thrown as a standard hand-grenade.

==Gallery==
&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Mills N°5 MkII.jpg|N°5 Mk II Mills bomb
File:Mills N°5- Eclatée.jpg|Cutaway view of N°5 Mills bomb
File:Mills N°23 MkII.jpg|N°23 Mk II Mills bomb
File:Mills Bomb SGM-1.JPG|36M Grenade dated 1940
File:Mills Bomb SGM-2.JPG|Base of 36M grenade dated 1940
File:Mills N°36 PGM.jpg|36M Mills bomb 
Image:Mills N°36 SGM-2.jpg|Mills bomb 36M, dating from 1942
File:N°23 MkII-Version Fusil.jpg|Mills bomb N°23 Mk II, with rod for launch by rifle.
File:N°36+ plaque de base.jpg|Drawing of the Mills N°36 rifle grenade, with its gascheck disk for use with cup-launcher.
File:Tromblon Lance-Grenade, Blunderbuss Grenade Launcher, Musée Somme 1916, pic-040.JPG|Lee-Enfield cup-launcher photographed at the 1916 Somme Battlefield Museum. Albert, France.
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
* [[Kugelhandgranate]]
* [[F1 grenade (France)]]

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Mills bomb}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20080821194219/http://www.wwiitechpubs.info/barrack/inf-uk/inf-uk-grnd-mills-36m/inf-uk-grnd-mills-36m-br.html World War II Tech Pubs Briefing] 
*
* [http://www.millsgrenades.co.uk/No36m_mk1_grenades_1946-1972.htm Photos of late production 36M grenades - including examples made in 1966, 1970 and 1972]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20071218214944/http://maic.jmu.edu/ordata/FullImage.asp?Image=images%5CE%5CE3981U02.JPG Cross section of a Mills Bomb] 
{{WW1and2 British Grenades}}
{{GreatWarBritishWeapons}}
{{WW2 Brit Comm Infantry Guns}}
{{WWIUSInfWeaponsNav}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Mills Bomb}}
[[Category:World War I grenades of the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:World War II infantry weapons of the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:World War II grenades of the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Hand grenades of the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Rifle grenades]]
[[Category:Fragmentation grenades]]</text>
      <sha1>f4bmt72y8l8mxoylou9oo5am5x19agp</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
