<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Mine planter (U.S. Army)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>25385436</id>
    <revision>
      <id>734870682</id>
      <parentid>712363242</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-08-17T06:09:53Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Bibliography */http&amp;rarr;https for [[Internet Archive]] (see [[WP:VPR/Archive 127#RfC: Should we convert existing Google and Internet Archive links to HTTPS?|this RfC]]) using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="24549">{|{{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
|Ship image=[[Image:MGRandolph.jpg|300px]]
|Ship caption=Army M 1 Mine Planter &quot;Hull No. 480&quot; the USAMP MP-7 ''Major General Wallace F. Randolph''.{{sfn|Colton|2011}}
Records (#742), Special Collections Department, J. Y. Joyner Library, East Carolina University, Greenville, North Carolina, USA.
}}
|}

'''Mine planter''' and the earlier &quot;torpedo planter&quot; was a term used for mine warfare ships into the early days of [[World War I]]. In later terminology, particularly in the United States, a mine planter was a ship specifically designed to install [[controlled mines]] or contact mines in coastal fortifications. This type of ship diverged in both function and design from a ship operating as a naval [[minelayer]]. Though the vessel may be seagoing it is not designed to lay large numbers of mines in open sea. A mine planter was designed to place mines in exact locations so that they might be fired individually or as a group from shore when observers noted a target to be at or near a designated mine's position. The terms and types of specialized ship existed from the 1860s where &quot;torpedoes&quot; were made famous in the [[American Civil War]] until the demise of large, fixed coastal fortifications brought on by the changes of [[World War II]].

==History and Terminology - United States==
The earliest mines were the &quot;torpedos&quot; associated with harbor defenses. Thus the vessels required to place the torpedoes were termed ''torpedo planters'' with the equipment evolving with the mines. For example, the record of the Sixtieth Congress there is mention of &quot;procurement of one torpedo planter and two launches for the Hawaiian Islands&quot; in connection with submarine mines in Hawaiian Island defenses.{{sfn|United States Congress|1908}} In the United States and some other countries there was a coastal defense &quot;[[Torpedo Service|torpedo service]]&quot; that required vessels capable of placing the devices and associated firing cables as early as the late 19th Century. By 1904 the first vessels specifically designed for this work were under construction in the United States.{{sfn|Jackson|2013}}

The outbreak of naval warfare in World War I saw extensive use of sea mines. The first naval ships destined to be minelayers were first termed mine planters as seen in Navy ship references.{{sfn|Naval History &amp; Heritage Command|1998}}  The term appears to be used interchangeably in naval usage during that period.{{sfn|Naval History &amp; Heritage Command|2005}} For example, in an address to the U.S. Navy ships of Mine Squadron One at Portland, England Admiral Sims used the term &quot;mine layer&quot; while the introduction speaks of the men assembled from the &quot;mine planters&quot;.{{sfn|Sims|1918}} As the distinct difference between &quot;planting&quot; individual mines and &quot;laying&quot; mine barrages by dropping large numbers of mines at sea emerged the term minelayer began to apply to the naval vessels engaged and built for this type of operation.{{sfn|Naval History &amp; Heritage Command|2006}}

In the coastal defense system the usage of mine planter was continued. In the United States 1918 saw the creation of the [[Mine Planter Service (U.S. Army)|U. S. Army Mine Planter Service]] (USAMPS).  The designation of mine planter was continued for the largest specialized ships of that service until the effective end of the service in the closing years of World War II. During that time the formal usage of Mine Planter was applied to the ships and their names were prefixed by U.S. Army Mine Planter (USAMP). The USAMPS was formally ended in 1954 by Congress in the Warrant Officer Personnel Act some five years after its vessels had been dispersed.{{sfn|Warrant Officer Historical Foundation|2014}}

===Mine Planter Design and Function===
The earliest U.S. vessels involved in the work were not specially designed for the purpose. Vessels capable of handling heavy loads over the side were drafted into the function. Some were small tugs and other commercial types. The ship required suitable rigging to lift the mines and anchors along with associated cables over the side for planting. Adequate deck space was also required for safe work and to carry the mines. Stability was also a factor as some of the small vessels had shown themselves to be less than stable with such loads.{{sfn|Jones|1939|pp=456—458}} By the early days of the 20th Century the Army's experience with some of these vessels indicated a need for a design specifically adapted to the work. By 1904 the first of these ships were under construction.

===Mine Planter - Collateral Duties===
The planters and associated vessels performed a number of duties beyond tending the minefields. Target towing was a specific task assigned to the vessels. They also served as observation platforms during demonstration or exercise firing of either the fortification guns or mines. In the later, cable capable vessels, they laid telephone and other communication cables within the coastal fortification systems. During Army's summer camp for [[United States Army Reserve|Army Reserve]], [[National Guard of the United States|National Guard]] and [[ROTC]] or occasional official visits they served as cruise vessels for tours and occasional entertainment. The ships were assigned transportation duty as required and when available to support Coast Artillery missions.

==U.S. Army Mine Planters==

===Mine Planters &amp; Associated Ships 1904 - 1909===
The first specialized Army mine planters were built in 1904 with a second group in 1909. These ships were designed to plant mines but lacked full, specialized capability to lay and maintain the minefield control cables. Some of these ships are noted in official documents as &quot;torpedo planters&quot; showing the evolution of terminology. Ships under [[Signal Corps (United States Army)|Signal Corps]] direction assisted. One of the ships, '' Joseph Henry'', was taken into the Coast Artillery Corps for that purpose.
[[Image:USAMP RINGGOLD which planted practice groups of mines inthe Columbia River during the 1920's. - NARA - 299666.jpg|250px|thumb|right|USAMP ''Major Samuel Ringgold'', built 1904. (National Archives and Records Administration)]]

* ''Col. George Armistead''
* ''Col. Henry J. Hunt''
* ''Gen. Henry Knox''
* ''Maj. Samuel Ringgold''
* ''Gen. Royal T. Frank''  (Became Army small transport serving in Hawaii, sunk by Japanese submarine I-71, 28 January 1942){{sfn|Kube-McDowell|2009}}{{sfn|Burritt|1942}}{{sfn|Hackett|Kingsepp|2010}}
* ''Gen. Samuel M. Mills'' (transferred to U.S. Coast Guard 29 April 1922, named  USCGC ''Pequot'' (WARC-58) on 1 May 1922, served as a cable ship until decommissioned 5 December 1946){{sfn|Kube-McDowell|2009}}{{sfn|U.S. Coast Guard, Historian|''Pequot''}}
* ''Gen. E. O. C. Ord''
* ''Gen. John M. Schofield''{{sfn|Kube-McDowell|2009}}

Cable ships ''Cyrus W. Field'' and ''Joseph Henry'' were associated with mine cable work and next generation mine planter development that incorporated cable capability into the new ships.{{sfn|Jackson|2013}}{{sfn|Gardner}} ''Joseph Henry'' was taken into the Mine Planter Service. The ''Cyrus W. Field'' appears listed only in association with mine cable work and with the mine planters in archival records.{{sfn|U.S. National Archives and Records Administration}}

* ''Joseph Henry'' (Became Greek cable ship ''Thalis o Milisios'' now at the Maritime Museum at Faliro, Athens){{sfn|Jackson|2013}}
* ''Cyrus W. Field'' (Remained with Signal Corps doing mine and other cable work.)

===Mine Planters 1917 - 1919===
A year after the 1918 establishment of the Mine Planter Service the next generation of vessels specifically designed to plant and maintain the mines and cables composing the mine battery of those harbor defense systems was added to the  fleet.  A year later, 1920, saw a major reduction in Army and the transfer of six of these new ships to the [[U.S. Lighthouse Service]] and later [[U.S. Coast Guard]] service.

Six of these vessels became [[United States Lighthouse Service]] vessels and were then brought into the [[United States Coast Guard]] as seen in the link.

* ''Gen. William M. Graham''{{sfn|Kube-McDowell|2009}}
* ''Col. George F. E. Harrison''
* ''Gen. Absalom Baird''
* ''Gen. J. Franklin Bell'' / ''Brig. Gen. John J. Hayden''
* ''Brig. Gen. Edmund Kirby'' ([http://www.uscg.mil/History/webcutters/Ilex_1924.pdf ''Ilex,'' (WAGL-222)])
* ''Gen. Wallace F. Randolph'' ([http://www.uscg.mil/History/webcutters/Lupine_1927.pdf ''Lupine'' (WAGL-230)])
* ''Gen. John P. Storey'' ([http://www.uscg.mil/history/webcutters/Acacia1927.pdf ''Acacia'' (WAGL-200)])
* ''Col. Albert Todd'' ([http://www.uscg.mil/History/webcutters/Lotus_1924.pdf ''Lotus'' (WAGL-229)])
* ''Col. Garland N. Whistler'' ([http://www.uscg.mil/History/webcutters/Spruce_1923.asp ''Spruce'' (WAGL-246)])
* ''Col. John V. White'' ([http://www.uscg.mil/history/webcutters/Speedwell1923.pdf ''Speedwell'' (WAGL-245)])

===Mine Planter 1937===

* ''Lt. Col. Ellery W. Niles'' (Became [[Army Signal Corps]] cable ship, then R/V ''F.V. Hunt'' and finally sunk as reef as ''Cayman Salvage Master''){{sfn|Jackson|2009}}

Only one ship of this class was built. She was the first fully capable cable ship and mine planter with diesel electric power. The USAMP ''Ellery W. Niles'', captioned in a photo as &quot;The last word in mine planters&quot;{{sfn|Jackson|2013}}{{sfn|Jackson|2009}}  and a major change into a more modern and capable form. After a tour of the East Coast ''Niles'' went on to serve on the West Coast based in San Francisco.{{sfn|Chappell}}

===Mine Planters 1942 - 1943===
[[Image:Miantonomah (MMA 13).jpg|thumb|300px|''Col. Horace F. Spurgin'' (MP-14) probably around the time of turn over to U.S. Navy. (Photo from ''All Hands'' magazine, March 1950.)]]
The requirement for more ships capable of planting the mines and installing and maintaining the control and communications cables of the coastal fortifications was underway on the entry of the United States into WW II. Sixteen new vessels were planned or started by that time at the [[Marietta Manufacturing]] yard at [[Point Pleasant, West Virginia]]. Those ships were delivered to the Mine Planter Service during 1942 and 1943, designated the M 1 Mine Planter and given MP numbers.{{sfn|Colton|2011}}{{sfn|Jackson|2013}}

* [[USAMP General Henry Knox (MP-1)|USAMP ''General Henry Knox'' (MP-1)]] ([http://www.navsource.org/archives/11/0108.htm USS ''Picket'' (ACM-8)] then USCGC [http://www.uscg.mil/History/webcutters/Willow1947.pdf ''Willow'' (WAGL / WLB-332)])
* [[USAMP Colonel Henry J. Hunt (MP-2)|USAMP ''Colonel Henry J. Hunt'' (MP-2)]] ([http://www.navsource.org/archives/11/0106.htm USS ''Bastion'' (ACM 6)] then USCGC [http://www.uscg.mil/History/webcutters/Jonquil_1946.pdf ''Jonquil'' (WAGL / WLB-330)])
* [[USAMP Colonel George Armistead (MP-3)|USAMP ''Colonel George Armistead'' (MP-3)]] ([http://www.navsource.org/archives/11/0105.htm USS ''Barbican'' (ACM-5)] then [http://www.uscg.mil/History/webcutters/Ivy_1947.pdf USCGC ''Ivy'' (WLB-329/WAGL-329)])
* ''Gen. Samuel M. Mills'' (MP-4) (&quot;remained in Army service into the 1950s; became Liberian ''Gran Canaria'' until scrapped in 1975&quot;){{sfn|Grover|1987|pp=121—130}}
* [[USAMP 1st Lt. William G. Sylvester (MP-5)|USAMP ''1st Lt. William G. Sylvester'' (MP-5)]] ([http://www.navsource.org/archives/11/0107.htm USS ''Obstructor'' (ACM 7)] then USCGC [http://www.uscg.mil/History/webcutters/Heather_1947.pdf ''Heather'' (WABL / WLB-331)])
* ''Brig. Gen. Henry L. Abbott'' (MP-6) (&quot;became American fishing vessel ''Nautilus''; foundered in 1975&quot;){{sfn|Grover|1987|pp=121—130}}
* [[Major General Wallace F. Randolph (ship)|USAMP ''Major General Wallace F. Randolph'' (MP-7)]] ([http://www.navsource.org/archives/11/0115.htm ''Nausett'' (MMA 15)])
* [[USAMP Colonel John Storey (MP-8)|USAMP ''Colonel John Storey'' (MP-8)]] ([http://www.navsource.org/archives/11/0103.htm USS ''Barricade'' (ACM 3)] then USCGC [http://www.uscg.mil/History/webcutters/Magnolia_1946.pdf ''Magnolia'' (WAGL / WLB-328)])
* ''Maj. Gen. Arthur Murray'' (MP-9) ([http://www.navsource.org/archives/11/0109.htm USS ''Trapper'' (ACM 9)] then USS [http://patriot.net/~eastlnd2/o_arc.htm ''Yamacraw'' (ARC 5)] then USCGC [https://www.uscg.mil/history/webcutters/Yamacraw_1947.pdf ''Yamacraw'' (WARC-333)]
* ''Maj. Gen. Erasmus Weaver'' (MP-10) ([http://www.navsource.org/archives/11/0112.htm USS ''Canonicus'' (ACM-12 / MMA 12)]){{sfn|Grover|1987|pp=121—130}}
* ''Maj. Samuel Ringgold'' (MP-11) ([http://www.navsource.org/archives/11/0114.htm ''Monadnock'' (ACM-14 / MMA 14)] not commissioned. Note that the NavSource [http://www.navsource.org/archives/11/11011401.jpg photo] shows the format of the USAMP name: '''U.S. Army MP-11 ''Ringgold'''''.)
* ''Brig. Gen. Royal T. Frank'' (MP-12) ([http://www.navsource.org/archives/11/0111.htm ''Camanche'' (ACM-11 / MMA 11)])
* ''Col. Alfred A. Maybach'' (MP-13) ([http://www.navsource.org/archives/11/0116.htm ''Puritan'' (ACM-16 / MMA 16)])
* ''Col. Horace F. Spurgin''  (MP-14) ([http://www.navsource.org/archives/11/0113.htm USS ''Miantonomah'' (ACM-13 / MMA 13)])
* ''Col. Charles W. Bundy'' (MP-15) ([http://www.navsource.org/archives/11/0101.htm USS ''Chimo'' (ACM 1)])
* ''Col. George Ricker'' (MP-16) ([http://www.navsource.org/archives/11/0102.htm USS ''Planter'' (ACM 2)])

==Other Army Mine Vessels==
The mine planting process required assistance by other, smaller vessels. Some, almost as capable as the planters were termed Junior Mine Planter. The Junior Mine Planters were often commercial designs with a number being conversions or special built during the war. They occasionally show up as &quot;Mine Planter&quot; with the &quot;Junior&quot; dropped. One, the ''General Richard Arnold'', a 1909 tug, sank in the process of rescuing another mine vessel.{{sfn|SeacoastNH}} A specialized vessel, the Distribution Box Boat (DB Boat), was designed to install and maintain the distribution boxes from which individual cables branched to each mine in a mine group. A number of the later Distribution Box Boats ended up in the Navy, often becoming known simply as &quot;Box Boats&quot; or &quot;Box L&quot; boats working as small service vessels or still working in harbor defense.{{sfn|Collins|2009}}{{sfn|Hartshorn|2012}} Mine Yawls and other small craft assisted in both mine work and all the other duties fitting small vessels within the fortifications in which individual forts or batteries were often separated by large bodies of water.

==End of the mission==
The entire concept of massive fixed fortifications was shown to be obsolete in the early days of World War II. By the end of the war the Coast Artillery Corps mission was already shifting to air defense and coast fortifications were being stripped. The Mine Planter Service ships appear to be engaged more in of their collateral duties than working the minefields.

===Mine Planter Disposition===
One of the M 1 (1942–43) ships, the ''General Samuel M. Mills'' of 1942, was retained by the Army and assigned to other missions while another was sold directly to commercial interests and became a fishing vessel.{{sfn|Grover|1987|pp=121—130}}

====U.S. Navy====
By early 1944 most of the 1942-43 ships were being transferred to the U. S. Navy to be converted into a class termed the Auxiliary Minelayer (ACM/MMA) with some of those vessels already working in the European Theater or headed to Japan when the war ended.{{sfn|Priolo|Radigan|2014}}

====U.S. Coast Guard====
Mine planters were designed to handle heavy mines over the side rather than dropping mines astern from racks or rails as is usual in naval minelayers. As a result many of these vessels had particular applicability to the [[U.S. Coast Guard]] buoy tending role. A number of the pre WW II ships became the Coast Guard ''Speedwell'' class through the [[U.S. Lighthouse Service]] (USLHS) after a 1920 reduction in the Army.{{sfn|U.S. Coast Guard, Historian|''Speedwell''}} Several became small cable ships. A number of the WW II constructed vessels followed their predecessors of the USLHS/USCG in going from Navy to the Coast Guard as postwar buoy tenders.

==Mine planting vessels of other nations==
Other nations using precisely placed, cable connected mines in controlled mine fields for coastal defense required vessels similar in function. The 1945 ''Mine Disposal Handbook'' shows controlled mines being in the inventory for the United States, Britain, Germany, Italy and Japan.{{sfn|U.S. Navy Bomb Disposal School|1945}} An example of an analogous vessel is Japan's larger [[Hashima-class cable layer]] that was also designed for mine planting.

==See also==
* [[Mine Planter Service (U.S. Army)]]
* [[United States Army Coast Artillery Corps]]
* [[Seacoast defense in the United States]]
* [[Controlled mines]]
* [[Submarine mines in U.S. harbor defense]]
* [[USCG seagoing buoy tender]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==Bibliography==
{{refbegin|2}}
*{{cite journal |last=Burritt |first=Ida Calhoun |year=1942 |title=U. S. A. T. ''Royal T. Frank'' - Requiescat in Pace (with photo) |journal=The Field Artillery Journal |volume=32 |issue=December |pages=911—912 |publisher=United States Field Artillery Association |url=http://sill-www.army.mil/firesbulletin/archives/1942/DEC_1942/DEC_1942_FULL_EDITION.pdf |accessdate=30 October 2014|ref=harv}}
*{{cite web |last=Chappell |first=Gordon |title=Forts Under the Sea: Submarine Mine Defense of San Francisco Bay |publisher=The California State Military Museum |date= |year= |url=http://californiamilitaryhistory.org/Mines.html |accessdate=30 October 2014|ref=harv}}
*{{cite web |last=Collins |first=J. |title=The History of SubRon 14 The USS ''Hunley''  AS31 |publisher=ThistleGroup |date= 3 September 2009  |url=http://thistlegroup.net/holyloch/hunley.htm |accessdate=30 October 2014|ref=harv}}
*{{cite web |last=Colton |first=T.  |title=U.S. Army Mine Craft |publisher=T. Colton |date=December 19, 2011 |url=http://shipbuildinghistory.com/history/smallships/armyminecraft.htm |accessdate=30 October 2014 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite web |last=Gardner |first=FQC |title=Random Recollections; 17. OFFICER IN CHARGE OF THE TORPEDO DEPOT |publisher= |date= |year= |url=http://home.earthlink.net/~sgeubank/random/17.html |accessdate=30 October 2014|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last=Grover |first=David |title=U.S. Army Ships and Watercraft of World War II |publisher=[[Naval Institute Press]] |year=1987 |isbn=0-87021-766-6 |lccn=87015514  |ref=harv}}
*{{cite web |last=Hackett |first=Bob |last2=Kingsepp |first2=Sander |title=HIJMS Submarine I-171: Tabular Record of Movement (date Japan time) |publisher=SENSUIKAN! |date= |year=2010 |url=http://www.combinedfleet.com/I-171.htm |accessdate=30 October 2014|ref=harv}}
*{{cite web |last=Hartshorn |first=Derick S. |title=Mineman Memories - Little Creek, VA Harbor Defense Unit |publisher= |date=11 April 2012  |url=http://www.hartshorn.us/Navy/navy-14.htm |accessdate=30 October 2014|ref=harv}}
*{{cite web |last=Jackson |first=Ramon  |title=Army Ships -- The Ghost Fleet - Coast Artillery Corps - Army Mine Planter Service |publisher= |date=20 November 2013 |url=http://patriot.net/~eastlnd2/army-amps.htm |accessdate=30 October 2014|ref=harv}}
*{{cite web |last=Jackson |first=Ramon  |title=R/V ''F. V. Hunt'' |publisher= |date=1 December 2009 |url=http://patriot.net/~eastlnd2/Misc.htm#Hunt |accessdate=30 October 2014|ref=harv}}
*{{cite journal |last=Jones |first=Henry L. |year=1939 |title=History of Army Mine Planters |journal=Coast Artillery Journal |volume= LXXXII |issue=September-October |page= |publisher=United States Coast Artillery Association |url= |accessdate=30 October 2014|ref=harv}}
*{{cite web |last=Kube-McDowell |first=Michael  |title=Army Vessels of New York Shipbuilding Co. |publisher=A Place Called Yorkship |date=23 July 2009 |url=http://yorkship.us/HTML/army.htm |accessdate=30 October 2014|ref=harv}}
*{{cite web |last=Naval History &amp; Heritage Command  |title=USS ''San Francisco'' (Cruiser #5, C-5, later CM-2) |publisher=Naval History &amp; Heritage Command |date=11 October 1998 |url=http://www.history.navy.mil/photos/sh-usn/usnsh-s/c5.htm |accessdate=30 October 2014 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite web |last=Naval History &amp; Heritage Command |date=23 March 2005  |title=USS ''Saranac'' (ID # 1702), 1918-1919. |publisher=Naval History &amp; Heritage Command |url=http://www.history.navy.mil/photos/sh-usn/usnsh-s/id1702.htm |accessdate=30 October 2014 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite web |last=Naval History &amp; Heritage Command |date=15 January 2006 |title=Photo #: NH 41736—U.S. Navy Mine Layers |publisher=Naval History &amp; Heritage Command |url=http://www.history.navy.mil/photos/images/h41000/h41736c.htm |accessdate=30 October 2014 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite web |last=Priolo |first=Gary P. |last2=Radigan |first2=Joe |title=Auxiliary Minelayer (ACM / MMA) Index |publisher=NavSource |date= |year=2014 |url=http://www.navsource.org/archives/11/01idx.htm |accessdate=30 October 2014 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite web |last=SeacoastNH |title=Mine Planter Richard Arnold Sinks |publisher=SeacoastNH |date= |year= |url=http://www.seacoastnh.com/Maritime-History/The-Shipyard/Mine-Planter-Richard-Arnold-Sinks/ |accessdate=30 October 2014|ref=harv}}
*{{Citation |last=Sims |first=W.S. |contribution=Speech of Admiral W. S. Sims, U. S. Navy |year=1918 |title=The Northern Barrage—Mine Force—United States Atlantic Fleet  |pages=107—108 |place=Annapolis, Maryland |publisher=U.S. Naval Institute |url=https://archive.org/stream/northernbarragem00annarich#page/106/mode/2up |accessdate=30 October 2014|ref=harv}}
*{{cite web |last=U.S. Coast Guard, Historian |title=''Pequot'', 1922 (WARC-58) ex-''General Samuel M. Mills'' |publisher=United States Coast Guard|year=|url=http://www.uscg.mil/history/webcutters/Pequot.pdf |accessdate=30 October 2014|ref={{sfnref|U.S. Coast Guard, Historian|''Pequot''}}}}
*{{cite web |last=U.S. Coast Guard, Historian |title=''Speedwell'', 1923 (WAGL-245) ex-''Colonel John V. White'' |publisher=United States Coast Guard|year=|url=http://www.uscg.mil/history/webcutters/Speedwell1923.pdf |accessdate=30 October 2014|ref={{sfnref|U.S. Coast Guard, Historian|''Speedwell''}}}}
*{{cite web |last=United States Congress |title=Sixtieth Congress Sess. I Ch. 202, p. 396 |publisher=United States Congress |year=1908 |url=https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/9/9e/United_States_Statutes_at_Large_Volume_35_Part_1.djvu/page414-2550px-United_States_Statutes_at_Large_Volume_35_Part_1.djvu.jpg |accessdate=30 October 2014|ref=harv}}
*{{cite web |last=U.S. National Archives and Records Administration |title=Records of United States Regular Army Mobile Units, 1821-1942 - 391.2.6 Records of U.S. Army mine planters |publisher= |date= |year= |url=http://www.archives.gov/research/guide-fed-records/groups/391.html#391.2.6 |accessdate=30 October 2014|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |title=Mine Disposal Handbook |last=U.S. Navy Bomb Disposal School |first= |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=1945 |publisher=U.S. Navy (portions reproduced at Historic Naval Ships Association |location= |isbn= |page= |pages= |url=http://www.maritime.org/doc/minedisposal/#part1 |accessdate=28 July 2013 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite web |last=Warrant Officer Historical Foundation |title=Army Warrant Officer History—&quot;The Legacy of Leadership as a Warrant Officer&quot;—Part I - 1918 to 1996 |publisher=Warrant Officer Historical Foundation |year=2014 |url=https://warrantofficerhistory.org/Hist_of_Army_WO.htm |accessdate=30 October 2014|ref=harv}}

{{refend}}

==External links==
* [http://www.fortmiles.org/intel/firepower/batteries/batt8.html Ft. Miles: Army Mine Planters]
* [http://leav-www.army.mil/wocc/History/ History of the Army Warrant Officer]
* [http://shipbuildinghistory.com/history/smallships/armyminecraft.htm Shipbuilding History: U.S. Army Mine Craft]
* [http://patriot.net/~eastlnd2/army-amps.htm Army Ships -- The Ghost Fleet: Coast Artillery Corps Army Mine Planter Service]
* [http://www.gwpda.org/naval/tdbkma01.htm Royal Navy &quot;Observation Mines, 1914&quot; (some detail of the process at that time)]
* [http://www.hampton.lib.nh.us/hampton/history/military/fort.htm Memories Of Defending New Hampshire’s Seacoast By Paul Snyder]

 &lt;!-- non-breaking space to keep AWB drones from altering the space before the navbox--&gt;

{{Warship types of the 19th &amp; 20th centuries}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Mine Planter (Ship)}}
[[Category:Ships of the United States Army]]
[[Category:Minelayers]]
[[Category:Mine warfare vessels of the United States Army]]
[[Category:Mine planters of the United States Army]]</text>
      <sha1>ti5ihy3nlat7k409p6mrkqxsa2z7bfn</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
