<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Mitsubishi J8M</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>460022</id>
    <revision>
      <id>721743566</id>
      <parentid>721743558</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-05-23T20:11:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contribs/72.48.215.133|72.48.215.133]] to version by John of Reading. [[WP:CBFP|Report False Positive?]] Thanks, [[WP:CBNG|ClueBot NG]]. (2663868) (Bot)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20641">&lt;!-- This article is a part of [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft]]. Please see [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft/page content]] for recommended layout. --&gt;
{|{{Infobox Aircraft Begin
  |name = J8M
  |image = J8M Shusui Sword Stroke Komet J8M-10.jpg
  |caption = 
}}{{Infobox Aircraft Type
  |type = [[Interceptor aircraft|Interceptor]]
  |manufacturer = [[Mitsubishi]]
  |designer = 
  |first flight = 7 July 1945
  |introduced = 
  |retired =
  |status =
  |primary user = [[Imperial Japanese Army Air Service|IJA Air Service]]
  |more users = [[Imperial Japanese Navy Air Service|IJN Air Service]]
  |produced = 1944-1945
  |number built = 7 &lt;ref&gt;Francillon, 1979, p. 407&lt;/ref&gt;
  |unit cost = 
  |developed from = [[Messerschmitt Me 163]]
  |variants with their own articles = [[Yokosuka MXY8]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Yokosuka MXY9]]
  |developed into =
}}
|}

The '''Mitsubishi J8M ''Shūsui''''' ([[Japanese language|Japanese]]: 三菱 J8M 秋水, literally &quot;Autumn Water&quot;, used as a poetic term meaning &quot;Sharp Sword&quot; deriving from the swishing sound swords make) was a [[Empire of Japan|Japanese]] [[World War II]] [[Rocket engine|rocket]]-powered [[interceptor aircraft]] closely based on the [[Nazi Germany|German]] [[Messerschmitt Me 163]] ''Komet''.
Built as a joint project for both the [[Imperial Japanese Navy Air Service|Navy]] and the [[Imperial Japanese Army Air Service|Army Air Services]], it was designated '''J8M''' (Navy) and '''Ki-200''' (Army).

==Design and development==
The J8M1 was intended to be a licence-built copy of the Messerschmitt Me 163 ''Komet''. Difficulties in shipping an example to Japan meant that the aircraft eventually had to be reverse-engineered from a flight operations manual and other limited documentation. A single prototype was tested before the end of World War II.

The Japanese were quite aware of the results of the [[strategic bombing]] of Germany, and knew that the [[B-29 Superfortress]] would be bombing Japan and the resultant problems which would arise from trying to combat this. Japanese military attachés had become aware of the ''Komet'' during a visit to the [[Bad Zwischenahn]] airfield of [[Erprobungskommando#Erprobungskommando 16|''Erprobungskommando'' 16]], the ''[[Luftwaffe]]'' evaluation squadron charged with service test of the revolutionary rocket-propelled interceptor. They negotiated the rights to licence-produce the aircraft and its [[Walter HWK 109-509|Walter HWK 509A]] rocket engine. The engine license alone cost the Japanese 20 million ''[[Reichsmarks]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Green|1971|p=114.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The agreement was for Germany to provide the following by spring 1944:
* Complete blueprints of the Me 163B ''Komet'' and the HWK 509A engine.
* One complete ''Komet''; two sets of sub-assemblies and components.
* Three complete HWK 509A engines.
* Inform Japan of any improvements and developments of the ''Komet''.
* Allow the Japanese to study the manufacturing processes for both the ''Komet'' and the engine.
* Allow the Japanese to study ''Luftwaffe'' operational procedures for the ''Komet''.

The broken-down aircraft and engine were sent to [[Kobe]], Japan in early 1944. It is probable that the airframe was on the Japanese submarine ''[[Japanese submarine RO-501|RO-501]]'' (ex-''[[Unterseeboot 1224|U-1224]]''), which left [[Kiel]], Germany on 30 March 1944 and was sunk in the mid-Atlantic on 13 May 1944 by the hunter-killer group based on the [[escort carrier]] {{USS|Bogue|CVE-9|6}}. Plans and engines were on the Japanese submarine ''[[Japanese submarine I-29|I-29]]'', which left [[Lorient]], France on 16 April 1944 and arrived in [[Singapore]] on 14 July 1944, later sunk by the [[submarine]] {{USS|Sawfish|SS-276|6}} on 26 July 1944, near the [[Philippines]], after leaving Singapore.

The Japanese decided to attempt to copy the Me 163 using a basic instructional manual on the ''Komet'' in the hands of naval mission member Commander Eiichi Iwaya who had travelled to Singapore in the ''I-29'' and flown on to Japan when the submarine docked.

From its inception, the project was a joint [[Imperial Japanese Army Air Service]] (JAAF)/[[Imperial Japanese Navy Air Service]] (JNAF) venture. The JAAF wanted a new design to be drawn up. The JNAF, on the other hand, felt the design should mimic the German ''Komet'' because it had already proven to be a stable aerodynamic body. It was the JNAF which won and issued the ''19-shi'' specification in July 1944 for the design of the rocket-powered defence fighter. The contract went to Mitsubishi ''Jukogyo'' KK, which would produce both the JNAF version the J8M1 ''Shūsui'' and the JAAF version Ki-200.

The project was headed by [[Mijiro Takahashi]]. The JAAF, however decided to undertake their own design to meet the ''19-shi'' specifications, working at their ''Rikugun Kokugijitsu Kenkyujo'' (JAAF Aerotechnical Institute) in secret.

At the 1st Naval Air Technical Arsenal in [[Yokosuka]], in association with Mitsubishi and Yokosuka Arsenal, work began to adapt the Walter HWK 509A engine to Japanese manufacturing capabilities and techniques. This was also where efforts were underway to produce a glider version of the J8M to provide handling data. While working on this glider, the MXY8 ''Akigusa'' (秋草, &quot;Autumn Grass&quot;), Mitsubishi completed a mock-up of the J8M1 in September 1944.

Both the JAAF and JNAF approved its design and construction and a [[prototype]] was built. In December 1944, the MXY8 was completed and, on 8 December 1944, at the Hyakurigahara Airfield, Lieutenant-Commander Toyohiko Inuzuka took the controls of the MXY8. Once in the air, Inuzuka found the MXY8 almost perfectly emulated the handling characteristics of the ''Komet''. Two additional MXY8 gliders were constructed in the naval yard at Yokosuka, one being delivered to the ''Rikugun Kokugijitsu Kenkyujo'' (JAAF Aerotechnical Institute) at Tachikawa for evaluation. The JNAF initiated the construction of another prototype, production designation Ku-13. This was to use water ballast to simulate the weight of an operational J8M complete with engine and weapons. This variant was to be built by Maeda Aircraft Institute, while the JAAF version was to be constructed by ''Yokoi Koku KK'' (Yoki Aircraft Co). The JNAF also proposed a more advanced trainer, designated the MXY9 ''Shūka'' (秋火, &quot;Autumn Fire&quot;) which would be powered by a {{convert|2|kN|abbr=on}} thrust Tsu-11 ducted-fan engine. The war, however, ended before this model could be built.

Mitsubishi and partners [[Nissan]] and [[Fuji Heavy Industries|Fuji]] proceeded with development of the airframe and Yokosuka Arsenal was adapting the engine for Japanese production, designated the Ro.2. The Japanese succeeded in producing prototypes that outwardly looked very much similar to the ''Komet''. The J8M1 had a wet weight that was {{convert|400|kg|abbr=on}} lighter, the aircraft having a [[plywood]] main [[Spar (aviation)|spar]] and wooden vertical tail. The designers had also dispensed with the armoured glass in the [[cockpit]] and the aircraft carried less ammunition and slightly less fuel.

The Ki-200 and the J8M1 differed only in minor items, but the most obvious difference was the JAAF's Ki-200 was armed with two 30&amp;nbsp;mm (1.18&amp;nbsp;in) [[Type 5 cannon]] (with a rate of fire of 450 rounds per minute and a muzzle velocity of {{convert|720|m/s|abbr=on}}, while the J8M1 was armed with two 30&amp;nbsp;mm (1.18&amp;nbsp;in) Ho-105 cannon (rate of fire 400 rounds per minute, muzzle velocity {{convert|750|m/s|abbr=on}}. The Ho-105 was the lighter of the two and both offered a higher velocity than the [[MK 108 cannon]] of the Me 163 (whose muzzle velocity was {{convert|520|m/s|abbr=on}}.
The Toko Ro.2 (KR10) rocket motor did not offer the same thrust rating as the original, and Mitsubishi calculated that the lighter weight of the J8M1 would not offset this. Performance would not be as good as that of the ''Komet'', but was still substantial.&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Green|1971|p=120.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The engine still used the German propellants of [[T-Stoff]] oxidizer and [[C-Stoff]] fuel (hydrogen peroxide/methanol-hydrazine), known in Japan as ''Ko'' and ''Otsu'' respectively.

A total of 60 of the training version (Ku-13, Ki-13, MXY-8, MXY-9) were produced by [[Yokosuka]], [[Yokoi]]{{disambiguation needed|date=September 2012}} and [[Maeda Aircraft Corporation|Maeda]]. Seven of the operational version (J8M1/Ki-200) were built by [[Mitsubishi]].

==Operational history==

[[File:Mitsubishi J8M Shusui Sword Stroke Komet J8M-17.jpg|thumb|J8M-17{{clarify|date=November 2011}}&lt;!-- what is the &quot;-17&quot;...? --&gt;]]	

On 8 January 1945, one of the two J8M1 prototypes was towed aloft, water ballast added in place of the [[fuel tank]] and rocket engine to test its [[aerodynamics]]. The test flights confirmed the design. [[Flight training|Training]] courses for JAAF and JNAF pilots began on the Ku-53 [[Military glider|glider]], which shared a similar configuration to the J8M1. The 312th Naval Air Group was selected to operate the first J8M1. Mitsubishi, Fuji Hikoki, and Nissan Jidosha all had tooling for mass production well into the advanced stages, ready to produce both the J8M1 and the J8M2 variant, which differed from the J8M1 in sacrificing one of the Type 5 cannon for a small increase in fuel capacity. The first J8M1 prototype to be equipped with the Toko Ro.2 (KR10) was ready in June 1945. They were then transferred from the Nagoya plant to Yokoku for final checks before powered flight testing, after final glide tests with the engine installed.

The J8M took to the air for its first powered flight on 7 July 1945,&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Green|1971|p=123.}}&lt;/ref&gt; with [[Lieutenant Commander]] Toyohiko Inuzuka at the controls; after his &quot;sharp start&quot; rocket-powered takeoff, Inuzuka successfully jettisoned the dolly upon becoming airborne and began to gain speed, climbing skywards at a 45° angle. At an altitude of {{convert|400|m|ft|abbr=on}}, the engine stopped abruptly and the J8M1 stalled. Inuzuka managed to glide the aircraft back, but clipped a small building at the edge of the airfield while trying to land, causing the aircraft to burst into flames. Inuzuka died the next day.&lt;ref name=&quot;Tiger p36-7&quot;&gt;{{Harvnb|Yamazaki|2005|pp=36–37.}}&lt;/ref&gt; While Mitsubishi and naval technicians sought to find the cause of the accident, all future flights were grounded. The engine cutout had occurred because the angle of climb, coupled with the fuel tanks being half-filled for this first flight, caused a shifting of the fuel, which in turn caused an auto cutout device to activate because of an air lock in the [[fuel line]]. Requests to continue flight testing were denied pending the modification of the [[fuel pump]]s in the aircraft. The sixth and seventh prototypes were to be fitted with the modified Ro.2 engine.

Full-scale production readiness was almost at hand and in fact, component construction was already underway. Flight testing was to resume, despite another explosion of the fuel mixture during a ground test days after the crash, in late August 1945 and the J8M2 design was finalized. But on 15 August 1945, the war ended for the Japanese and all work on the J8M ceased. The end of the war also spelled the end of the JAAF's Ki-202 ''Shūsui-Kai'' (Modified ''Shusui''), whose design had begun in secret months before. The Ki-202 was to offer improved flight endurance over the Ki-200 and was slated to be the priority fighter for the JAAF in 1946, but no metal was cut before Japan's surrender.

Germany tried to send another ''Komet'' in [[German submarine U-864|''U-864'']], but the submarine was sunk near [[Bergen]] by British submarine {{HMS|Venturer|P68|6}} in February 1945.

As with many other Japanese fighter types combating air raids over Japan, the Ki-200 was considered for use in [[aerial ramming|ramming]] attacks against B-29's.  The envisioned mission profile was to make one or two firing passes and then, with the remaining energy, conduct a ramming attack. Any fuel left on board would most likely detonate, increasing the effectiveness of the attack, but also meaning the pilot had little chance of survival.  Nevertheless, the cost was deemed to be worth it and plans were being drawn up to form a &quot;Hagakure-Tai&quot; (Special Attack Unit), similar to the German [[Sonderkommando Elbe]], when the war ended.

==Variants==
;J8M1
;J8M2 ''Shūsui'' Model 21(?)
:Long-range version for Navy, identical to J8M1, but armament reduced to a single 30&amp;nbsp;mm (1.18&amp;nbsp;in) cannon.
;J8M3 ''Shūsui'' Model 22 ([[Rikugun Ki-202 Shūsui-kai]])
:Long-range version for Army and Navy, with fuselage and wingspan lengthened to 7.10&amp;nbsp;m (23&amp;nbsp;ft 3&amp;nbsp;in) and 9.75&amp;nbsp;m (32&amp;nbsp;ft 0&amp;nbsp;in) respectively. Powered by 19.6&amp;nbsp;kN (4,410&amp;nbsp;lbf) Tokuro-3, projected maximum speed 900&amp;nbsp;km/h (560&amp;nbsp;mph).
;[[Yokosuka MXY-8]] &quot;''Akigusa''&quot; (Yokoi Ku-13)
:Training glider using J8M airframe for Navy and Army.
;[[Yokosuka MXY-9]] &quot;''Shuka''&quot;
:Training version using J8M airframe, powered by [[Tsu-11]] thermojet engine.

==Operators==
;{{JPN}}
* [[Imperial Japanese Army Air Service]]
* [[Imperial Japanese Navy Air Service]]

==Survivors==
In November 1945, two aircraft were taken from [[Yokosuka]] to the [[United States]] for evaluation aboard [[USS Barnes (CVE-20)|USS ''Barnes'']]. FE-300/T2-300 (USA ident) (Japanese ident 403) is now exhibited at the [[Planes of Fame Museum]] in [[Chino, California]].

The other was at [[Naval Air Station Glenview|NAS Glenview]] in October 1946 (identity unknown), but was scrapped.

In the 1960s, a nearly complete (but badly damaged) fuselage was discovered in a cave in Japan. This was on display at a Japanese Air Self Defense Forces base near [[Gifu, Gifu|Gifu]] until 1999, when it was restored and completed by Mitsubishi for display in the company's internal Komaki Plant Museum.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.j-aircraft.com/misc/SURVIVE.HTM &quot;List of surviving Japanese aircraft.&quot;] ''j-aircraft.com.'' Retrieved; 27 October 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Gallery===
&lt;gallery widths=&quot;180px&quot; heights=&quot;150px&quot;&gt;
File:J8M1 Shu Sui.JPG
File:Mitsubishi-J8M1.jpg
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Comparative Specifications==
{| class=&quot;wikitable left&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center; width: 100%&quot;
|- style=&quot;vertical-align:top; background-color:#ccc;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;4&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center;&quot; | '''Specifications''' &lt;ref name=&quot;Dyer&quot;&gt;Dyer 2009, pp. 96–100.&lt;/ref&gt;
|- style=&quot;vertical-align:top;&quot;
! style=&quot;width:14%&quot; | 
! style=&quot;width:14%&quot; | J8M1
! style=&quot;width:14%&quot; | J8M2
! style=&quot;width:14%&quot; | Ki-200
|- style=&quot;vertical-align:top;&quot;
|-
| style=&quot;; text-align:left;&quot; | Manufacturer: || colspan=&quot;3&quot; | [[Mitsubishi Heavy Industries|Mitsubishi Jukogyo K.K]]
|-
| style=&quot;; text-align:left;&quot;  | Type: || colspan=&quot;3&quot; | Interceptor
|-
| style=&quot;; text-align:left;&quot; | Crew: || colspan=&quot;3&quot; | 1
|-
| style=&quot;; text-align:left;&quot; | Span: || {{convert|9.50|m|ft|abbr=on|0}} || || {{convert|9.47|m|ft|abbr=on|0}}
|-
| style=&quot;; text-align:left;&quot; | Length: || {{convert|6.03|m|ft|abbr=on|0}} || || {{convert|5.88|m|ft|abbr=on|0}}
|-
| style=&quot;; text-align:left;&quot; | Height: || {{convert|2.68|m|ft|abbr=on|0}} || || {{convert|2.68|m|ft|abbr=on|0}}
|-
| style=&quot;; text-align:left;&quot; | Wing area: || {{convert|17.72|sqm|sqft|abbr=on|0}} || || {{convert|17.69|sqm|sqft|abbr=on|0}}
|-
| style=&quot;; text-align:left;&quot; | Wing loading: || 219.22&amp;nbsp;kg/m² (44.9&amp;nbsp;lb/ft²) || 219.70&amp;nbsp;kg/m² (45&amp;nbsp;lb/ft²) || 
|-
| style=&quot;; text-align:left;&quot; | Empty weight: || {{convert|1,445|kg|lb|abbr=on|0}} || {{convert|1,510|kg|lb|abbr=on|0}} || {{convert|1,505|kg|lb|abbr=on|0}}
|-
| style=&quot;; text-align:left;&quot; | Loaded: || {{convert|3,000|kg|lb|abbr=on|0}} || {{convert|3,650|kg|lb|abbr=on|0}}
|-
| style=&quot;; text-align:left;&quot; | Maximum: || {{convert|3,870|kg|lb|abbr=on|0}} || {{convert|3,900|kg|lb|abbr=on|0}} || {{convert|3,870|kg|lb|abbr=on|0}}
|-
| style=&quot;; text-align:left;&quot; | Useful load: || {{convert|1,545|kg|lb|abbr=on|0}} || {{convert|2,140|kg|lb|abbr=on|0}} || 
|-
| style=&quot;; text-align:left;&quot; | Fuel capacity: || colspan=&quot;3&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;| [[T-Stoff]] = {{convert|1,181|l|impgal|abbr=on|0}} &lt;br&gt; [[C-Stoff]] = {{convert|522|l|impgal|abbr=on|0}}
|-
|- style=&quot;vertical-align:top; text-align:center; background-color:#ccc;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;4&quot; | '''Armament'''
|-
| style=&quot;; text-align:left;&quot; | Gun: || 2x [[Type 5 cannon|Type 5 30mm cannon]] || 2x [[Ho-155 cannon|Ho-155]] 30mm cannon or 2x [[Type 5 cannon|Type 5 30mm cannon]] || 1x [[Type 5 cannon|Type 5 30mm cannon]]
|-
| style=&quot;; text-align:left;&quot; | Capacity: || colspan=&quot;3&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;| 53 rounds per gun
|-
|- style=&quot;vertical-align:top; text-align:center; background-color:#ccc;&quot;
| colspan=&quot;4&quot; | '''Performance'''
|-
| style=&quot;; text-align:left;&quot; | Powerplant: || colspan=&quot;3&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;| One Toku-Ro.2 (KR10) bi-fuel rocket motor developing {{convert|1,500|kg|lb|abbr=on|0}} of thrust
|-
| style=&quot;; text-align:left;&quot; | Liquid-propellant: || colspan=&quot;3&quot; align=&quot;center&quot;| [[T-Stoff]] = 80% [[Hydrogen Peroxide]] + 20% [[Oxyquinoline]] and [[Pyrophosphate]]s &lt;br&gt; [[C-Stoff]] = 30% [[Hydrazine Hydrate]] + 70% [[Methanol]], [[Water]] and [[Potassium]]-[[Copper]] [[Cyanide]]s
|-
| style=&quot;; text-align:left;&quot; | Max speed: || colspan=&quot;3&quot; align=&quot;center | {{convert|900|km/h|mph|abbr=on|0}} at {{convert|10,000|m|ft|abbr=on|0}}
|-
| style=&quot;; text-align:left;&quot; | Cruise speed: || {{convert|699|km/h|mph|abbr=on|0}} || || {{convert|351|km/h|mph|abbr=on|0}}
|-
| style=&quot;; text-align:left;&quot; | Landing speed: || {{convert|150|km/h|mph|abbr=on|0}} || ||
|-
| style=&quot;; text-align:left;&quot; | Range: || 3 min 06 seconds&lt;br&gt; of powered flight || || 2 min 30 seconds&lt;br&gt; of powered flight
|-
| style=&quot;; text-align:left;&quot; | Max range: || 5 min 30 secconds&lt;br&gt; of powered flight || || 7 min&lt;br&gt;of powered flight
|-
| style=&quot;; text-align:left;&quot; | Climb: || {{convert|2,000|m|ft|abbr=on|0}}&lt;br&gt;in 40 seconds &lt;br&gt;{{convert|4,000|m|ft|abbr=on|0}}&lt;br&gt;in 2 minutes 08 seconds &lt;br&gt;{{convert|8,000|m|ft|abbr=on|0}}&lt;br&gt;in 3 minutes 08 seconds &lt;br&gt;{{convert|10,000|m|ft|abbr=on|0}}&lt;br&gt;in 3 minutes 50 seconds || || {{convert|10,000|m|ft|abbr=on|0}}&lt;br&gt;in 3 minutes 40 seconds
|-
| style=&quot;; text-align:left;&quot; | Rate of climb: || {{convert|43.47|m/s|ft/min|abbr=on|0}} || || {{convert|45.45|m/s|ft/min|abbr=on|0}}
|-
| style=&quot;; text-align:left;&quot; | Celling: || colspan=&quot;3&quot; | {{convert|12,000|m|ft|abbr=on|0}}
|-
|}

==See also==
{{aircontent|
|related=
* [[Messerschmitt Me 163]]
* [[Mitsubishi Ki-202]]
* [[Mizuno Shinryu]]
* [[Yokosuka MXY8]]
* [[Yokosuka MXY9]]
|similar aircraft=
|lists=
*[[List of military aircraft of Japan]]
*[[List of fighter aircraft]]
*[[List of rocket aircraft]]
|see also=
}}

==References==
;Notes
{{reflist}}
;Bibliography
{{refbegin}}
* Butler, Phil. ''War prizes: An Illustrated Survey of German, Italian and Japanese Aircraft brought to Allied countries During and After the Second World War''. Leicestershire, UK: Midland, 1994. ISBN 0-904597-86-5.
* Dyer, Edward M. III. ''Japanese Secret Projects: Experimental Aircraft of the IJA and IJN 1939-1945.'' Hinckley, UK: Midland Publishing, 2009. ISBN 978-1-85780-317-4.
* Ethell, Jeffrey L. ''Komet: The Messerschmitt 163''. London: Ian Allan, 1978. ISBN 0-7110-0827-2. (This book shows U-852 or U-68 being used to carry the Me 163.)
* Francillon, Ph.D., René J. ''Japanese Aircraft of the Pacific War''. London: Putnam &amp; Company Ltd., 1970 (2nd edition 1979). ISBN 0-370-30251-6.
* Green, William. ''Rocket Fighter'' (Ballantine's Illustrated History of World War II, Weapons Book No. 20). New York: Ballantine Books, Inc., 1971. ISBN 0-345-02163-0.
* Green, William. ''War Planes of the Second World War: Fighters, Volume Three''. London: Macdonald, 1961 (Seventh impression 1973). ISBN 0-356-01447-9.
* Yamashita, Takeo (ed). ''秋水」と日本陸海軍ジェット、ロケット機''. Tokyo: Model Art Co. Ltd., 1998.
* Yamazaki, Akio. &quot;Tail of the Tiger: Japan's 'Shushi' Interceptor&quot;. ''[[Air Enthusiast]]'', No. 115, January/February 2005, pp.&amp;nbsp;36–41. Stamford, UK: Key Publishing.
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Mitsubishi J8M}}
* [http://www.ijnafpics.com/jbwj8m1.htm JNAF pics.1]
* [http://www.ijnafpics.com/jbwj8m2.htm JNAF pics.2]
* [http://uboat.net/forum/read.php?f=3&amp;i=44254&amp;t=44254 U-boat forum]

{{Mitsubishi aircraft}}
{{Japanese Army Aircraft Designation System}}
{{Japanese Navy Land Based Fighters}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Mitsubishi J8m}}
[[Category:Japanese fighter aircraft 1940–1949|J8M, Mitsubishi]]
[[Category:Mitsubishi aircraft|J8M]]
[[Category:Rocket-powered aircraft]]
[[Category:Tailless aircraft]]
[[Category:World War II Japanese fighter aircraft|J8M, Mitsubishi]]</text>
      <sha1>qyhhjftjssf7dt5of2qr4yzzhnbz7qd</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
