<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Nancy Wake</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>206392</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749242589</id>
      <parentid>740105478</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-13T07:20:08Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[User:AnomieBOT/docs/TemplateSubster|Substing templates]]: {{ill}}. See [[User:AnomieBOT/docs/TemplateSubster]] for info.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="33248">{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2011}}
{{Infobox military person
|name=Nancy Grace Augusta Wake
|image=Nancy Wake (1945).jpg
|caption=Nancy Wake circa 1945
|birth_date={{birth date|1912|8|30|df=yes}}
|death_date={{death date and age|2011|8|7|1912|8|30|df=yes}}
|birth_place= [[Wellington]], New Zealand
|death_place= [[London]], England
|nickname=Hélène (SOE)&lt;br/&gt;Andrée (French Resistance/SOE Identity)&lt;br/&gt;White Mouse (Gestapo in France)&lt;br/&gt;Witch (Operation:)
|nationality= [[United Kingdom]], [[Australia]], [[New Zealand]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/schoolstv/australians/wake.htm Profile of Nancy Wake]&lt;/ref&gt;
|allegiance={{flag|France}}&lt;br/&gt;{{UK}}
|branch=[[Special Operations Executive]]&lt;br/&gt;[[First Aid Nursing Yeomanry]]
|serviceyears=1943–1945 (SOE)
|rank=[[First Aid Nursing Yeomanry|Captain]]
|unit=[[SOE F Section networks|Freelance]]
|commands=
|battles= [[World War II]]
|awards= [[Companion of the Order of Australia]]&lt;br/&gt;[[George Medal]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Légion d'Honneur|Officier de la Légion d'Honneur]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Croix de guerre 1939–1945|Croix de guerre]] (France)&lt;br/&gt;[[Medal of Freedom]] (United States)&lt;br/&gt;[[RSA Badge in Gold]] (New Zealand)}}

'''Nancy Grace Augusta Wake''' [[Companion of the Order of Australia|AC]], [[George Medal|GM]] (30 August 1912 – 7 August 2011) served as a British [[Special Operations Executive]] agent during the later part of [[World War II]]. She became a leading figure in the [[Maquis (World War II)|maquis]] groups of the [[French Resistance]] and was one of the [[Allies of World War II|Allies]]' most decorated servicewomen of the war. After the fall of France in 1940, she became a courier for the French Resistance and later joined the escape network of Captain [[Ian Garrow]]. By 1943, Wake was the [[Gestapo]]'s most wanted person, with a 5 million-[[franc]] price on her head.

After reaching [[Great Britain|Britain]], Wake joined the [[Special Operations Executive]]. On the night of 29/30 April 1944, Wake was parachuted into occupied France [[Auvergne (province)|Auvergne]], becoming a liaison between London and the local maquis group headed by Captain Henri Tardivat in the [[Forest of Tronçais]]. From April 1944 until the liberation of France, her 7,000+ ''[[Maquis (World War II)|maquisards]]'' fought 22,000 German soldiers, causing 1,400 casualties, while suffering only 100 themselves.

==Early life==
Born in Roseneath, [[Wellington]], New Zealand, on 30 August 1912, Wake was the youngest of six children. In 1914, her family moved to Australia and settled at [[North Sydney, New South Wales|North Sydney]].&lt;ref name=Dennis&gt;{{harvnb|Dennis|Grey|Morris|Prior|1995|p=626}}&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly thereafter, her father, Charles Augustus Wake, returned to New Zealand, leaving her mother Ella Wake (née Rosieur; 1874–1968) to raise the children.

In Sydney, she attended the North Sydney Household Arts (Home Science) School (see [[North Sydney Technical High School]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=FitzSimons|first=Peter|title=Nancy Wake A Biography of Our Greatest War Heroine|year=2002|isbn=978-0-7322-7456-6}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the age of 16, she ran away from home and worked as a nurse. With £200 that she had inherited from an aunt, she journeyed to [[New York City]], then [[London]] where she trained herself as a journalist. In the 1930s, she worked in [[Paris]] and later for [[Hearst Corporation|Hearst]] newspapers as a [[Europe]]an correspondent. She witnessed the rise of [[Adolf Hitler]] and the [[Nazism|Nazi movement]] and &quot;saw roving Nazi gangs randomly beating Jewish men and women in the streets&quot; of [[Vienna]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|journal=New York Times|title= Obituary for Nancy Wake|date= 14 August 2011|page= A18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Wartime service and Special Operations Executive==
In 1937, Wake met wealthy French industrialist Henri Edmond Fiocca (1898–1943), whom she married on 30 November 1939. She was living in [[Marseille, France]] when [[Germany]] invaded. After the fall of France in 1940, she became a courier for the [[French Resistance]] and later joined the escape network of Captain [[Ian Garrow]]. In reference to Wake's ability to elude capture, the [[Gestapo]] called her the White Mouse. The Resistance exercised caution with her missions; her life was in constant danger, with the Gestapo tapping her phone and intercepting her mail.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wake Bio&quot;/&gt;

In November 1942, [[Wehrmacht]] troops occupied the southern part of France after the Allies' [[Operation Torch]] had started. This gave the Gestapo unrestricted access to all papers of the [[Vichy France|Vichy régime]] and made life more dangerous for Wake.{{citation needed|date=January 2013}} By 1943, Wake was the Gestapo's most wanted person, with a 5 million-[[franc]] price on her head. When the network was betrayed that same year, she decided to flee Marseille. Her husband, Henri Fiocca, stayed behind; he was later captured, tortured and executed by the Gestapo.&lt;ref name=diggerinfo&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.diggerhistory.info/pages-heroes/white_mouse.htm|title=The White Mouse| archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100811085020/http://www.diggerhistory.info/pages-heroes/white_mouse.htm| archivedate=11 August 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Wake described her tactics: &quot;A little powder and a little drink on the way, and I'd pass their (German) posts and wink and say, 'Do you want to search me?' God, what a flirtatious little bastard I was.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Australian&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.theaustralian.com.au/news/features/fearless-matriarch-of-resistance/story-e6frg6z6-1226111207166 | title=Fearless matriarch of resistance | publisher=News Limited | work=The Australian | date=9 August 2011 | accessdate=24 June 2015 | author=Leech, Graeme | quote=It was perilous work despite her cover as the wife of a respectable businessman. She lived on her sharp wits.  &quot;I'd see a German officer on the train or somewhere, sometimes dressed in civvies, but you could pick 'em. So, instead of raising suspicions I'd flirt with them, ask for a light and say my lighter was out of fuel,&quot; she recalled.  She told how she would get beautifully dressed and hang around making dates with Germans to get information.  &quot;A little powder and a little drink on the way, and I'd pass their posts and wink and say, 'Do you want to search me?' God, what a flirtatious little bastard I was.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Wake had been arrested in [[Toulouse]],{{when|date=December 2012}} but was released four days later. An acquaintance (Scarlet Pimpernel) managed to have her let out by making up stories about her supposed infidelity to her husband.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite AV media | url=http://www.rte.ie/radio1/doconone/2011/0907/646867-curious-ear-doconone-nancy-wake/ | title=Nancy Wake and Harry Potter | publisher=Raidió Teilifís Éireann | date=9 August 2011 | medium=Radio | location=Ireland | quote=The story of an extraordinary woman: Nancy Wake, WWII spy, French Resistance leader and saboteur who was determined to 'bugger up' the NAZIs.}}&lt;/ref&gt; She succeeded, on her sixth attempt, in crossing the [[Pyrenees]] to [[Spain]]. Until the war ended, she was unaware of her husband's death and subsequently blamed herself for it.&lt;ref name=guardian_obituary /&gt;

After reaching [[Great Britain|Britain]], Wake joined the [[Special Operations Executive]].  [[Vera Atkins]], who also worked in the SOE, recalls her as &quot;a real Australian [[Bombshell (sex symbol)|bombshell]]. Tremendous vitality, flashing eyes. Everything she did, she did well.&quot;  Training reports record that she was &quot;a very good and fast shot&quot; and possessed excellent fieldcraft. She was noted to &quot;put the men to shame by her cheerful spirit and strength of character.&quot;&lt;ref name=guardian_obituary /&gt;

On the night of 29/30 April 1944, Wake was parachuted into the [[Auvergne (province)|Auvergne]], becoming a liaison between London and the local [[Maquis (World War II)|maquis]] group headed by Captain Henri Tardivat in the [[Forest of Tronçais]]. Upon discovering her tangled in a tree, Captain Tardivat greeted her remarking, &quot;I hope that all the trees in France bear such beautiful fruit this year,&quot; to which she replied, &quot;Don't give me that French shit.&quot;&lt;ref name=diggerinfo/&gt;&lt;ref name=telegraph_obituary&gt;{{cite news|title=Nancy Wake|url=http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/obituaries/military-obituaries/special-forces-obituaries/8689765/Nancy-Wake.html|publisher=The Daily Telegraph| accessdate=9 August 2011|location=London|date=8 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Her duties included allocating arms and equipment that were parachuted in and minding the group's finances. Wake became instrumental in recruiting more members and making the maquis groups into a formidable force, roughly 7,500 strong. She also led attacks on German installations and the local Gestapo HQ in [[Montluçon]].&lt;ref name=telegraph_obituary /&gt;  At one point Wake discovered that her men were protecting a girl who was a German spy.  They did not have the heart to kill her in cold blood, but when Wake insisted she would perform the execution, they capitulated.&lt;ref name=&quot;nazi_spy&quot;&gt;{{cite news | url=https://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=1301&amp;dat=19871102&amp;id=wCtWAAAAIBAJ&amp;sjid=uuQDAAAAIBAJ&amp;pg=5867,1447818&amp;hl=en | title=Of Mouse and Men | work=The Sydney Morning Herald | date=2 November 1987 | accessdate=24 June 2015 | location=Sydney | pages=8 | quote=There was also a moment that we don't see, but one that brought a telling moment in the documentary ''The White Mouse'', shown late at night couple of weeks ago by the ABC. In the closing stages of the Resistance war, the Maquis captured a German agent, a girl. They were reluctant to execute her, simply because she was a woman. &quot;If you won't shoot her, I will,&quot; Nancy Wake told them. &quot;The men changed their mind. They weren't going to let me carry out my threat.&quot; &quot;But they did organise a proper firing squad. I was having my breakfast. The girl had admitted to me that she was a spy and she was very proud of the fact. I had given her some clothes and showed her where to wash. As she passed me on the way to the firing squad, I said 'I'm very sorry we can't keep you, If we had anywhere to put you we would. But, I'm sorry, you are going to be shot.' &quot;As she passed me, she took all her clothes and spat at me, and then she walked naked to the firing squad showing 'Zieg Heil!'. She was a dedicated Nazi. Oh, I'd have shot her. God yes, with the greatest of pleasure.&quot;}}&lt;/ref&gt;

From April 1944 until the liberation of France, her 7,000+ ''[[Maquis (World War II)|maquisards]]'' fought 22,000 German soldiers, causing 1,400 casualties, while suffering only 100 themselves. Her French companions, especially Henri Tardivat, praised her fighting spirit, amply demonstrated when she killed an SS sentry with her bare hands to prevent him from raising the alarm during a raid.  During a 1990s television interview, when asked what had happened to the sentry who spotted her, Wake simply drew her finger across her throat.
&quot;They'd taught this [[Judo chop|judo-chop]] stuff with the flat of the hand at SOE, and I practised away at it. But this was the only time I used it – whack – and it killed him all right. I was really surprised.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;The Australian&quot;/&gt;

On another occasion, to replace codes her wireless operator had been forced to destroy in a German raid, Wake rode a bicycle for more than {{convert|500|km|mi}} through several German checkpoints.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wake Bio&quot;&gt;{{cite book| author=Peter FitzSimons| title=Nancy Wake, Australia's Greatest War Heroine| publisher= Harper Collins Australia| year= 2001| ISBN =0 7322 6919 9}}&lt;/ref&gt; During a German attack on another maquis group, Wake, along with two American officers, took command of a section whose leader had been killed. She directed the use of [[suppressive fire]], which facilitated the group's withdrawal without further losses.&lt;ref name=guardian_obituary&gt;{{cite news| title=Nancy Wake obituary| url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/aug/08/nancy-wake-obituary| publisher=The Guardian| accessdate=9 August 2011| location=London| first=David| last=Stafford| date=8 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Post-war==
Immediately after the war, Wake was awarded the [[George Medal]],&lt;ref name=&quot;GM&quot;/&gt; the United States [[Medal of Freedom]], the [[Médaille de la Résistance]], and thrice the [[Croix de guerre 1939–1945|Croix de Guerre]]. She learned that the Gestapo had tortured her husband to death in 1943 for refusing to disclose her whereabouts. After the war, she worked for the Intelligence Department at the [[British Air Ministry]] attached to embassies in Paris and [[Prague]].

Wake stood as a [[Liberal Party of Australia|Liberal]] candidate&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://trove.nla.gov.au/ndp/del/article/18109078?searchTerm=&amp;searchLimits=l-publictag=Nancy+Wake|newspaper=[[The Sydney Morning Herald]]|title=Maquis Heroine tries Politics|date=30 March 1949|page=2|publisher=[[Fairfax Media]]|accessdate=11 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; in the [[Australian federal election, 1949|1949 Australian federal election]] for the Sydney seat of [[Division of Barton|Barton]], running against [[Herbert Evatt|Dr. Herbert Evatt]], then Deputy Prime Minister, [[Attorney-General]] and [[Minister for External Affairs]] in the [[Ben Chifley]] [[Australian Labor Party|Labor]] government. While Chifley lost government to [[Robert Menzies]], Wake recorded a 13 percent swing against Evatt,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://psephos.adam-carr.net/countries/a/australia/1949/1949repsnsw.txt|title=Barton, NSW|work=Voting by constituency: Legislative election 1949|date=10 December 1949|accessdate=11 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; with Evatt retaining the seat with 53.2 per cent of the vote on a [[two-party preferred]] basis. Wake ran against Evatt again at the [[Australian federal election, 1951|1951 federal election]]. By this time, Evatt was [[List of Australian Leaders of the Opposition|Deputy Leader of the Opposition]]. The result was extremely close. However, Evatt retained the seat with a margin of fewer than 250 votes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://psephos.adam-carr.net/countries/a/australia/1951/1951repsnsw.txt|title=Barton, NSW|work=Voting by constituency: Legislative election 1951|date=28 April 1951|accessdate=11 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Evatt slightly increased his margin at subsequent elections before relocating to the safer seat of [[Division of Hunter|Hunter]] by 1958.

Wake left Australia just after the 1951 election and moved back to England.  She worked as an intelligence officer in the department of the Assistant Chief of Air Staff at the Air Ministry in Whitehall. She resigned in 1957 after marrying a RAF officer, John Forward, in December of that year. They returned to Australia in the early 1960s.&lt;ref name=telegraph_obituary /&gt; Maintaining her interest in politics, Wake was endorsed as a Liberal candidate at the [[Australian federal election, 1966|1966 federal election]] for the Sydney seat of [[Division of Kingsford Smith|Kingsford Smith]]. Despite recording a swing of 6.9 per cent against the sitting Labor member Daniel Curtin, Wake was again unsuccessful.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://psephos.adam-carr.net/countries/a/australia/1966/1966repsnsw.txt|title=Kingsford-Smith, NSW|work=Voting by constituency: Legislative election 1966|date=26 November 1966|accessdate=11 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Around 1985, Wake and John Forward left Sydney to retire to [[Port Macquarie]].

In 1985, Wake published her autobiography, ''The White Mouse''. The book became a bestseller and has been reprinted many times.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Wake, Nancy|title=The White Mouse|publisher=Sun Books|year=1985|isbn=0-330-35605-4}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After 40 years of marriage, her husband John Forward died at Port Macquarie on 19 August 1997; the couple had no children.

In 2001, Wake left Australia for the last time and emigrated to London.&lt;ref name=Grauniad /&gt;  She became a resident at the Stafford Hotel in St James' Place, near Piccadilly, formerly a British and American forces club during the war. She had been introduced to her first &quot;bloody good drink&quot; there by the general manager at the time, Louis Burdet. He had also worked for the Resistance in Marseilles. In the mornings she would usually be found in the hotel bar, sipping her first gin and tonic of the day. She was welcomed at the hotel, celebrating her 90th birthday there, where the hotel owners absorbed most of the costs of her stay. In 2003, Wake chose to move to the [[Royal Star and Garter Home, Richmond|Royal Star and Garter Home for Disabled Ex-Service Men and Women]], in [[Richmond, London]], where she remained until her death.&lt;ref name=telegraph_obituary /&gt;

Wake died on Sunday evening 7 August 2011, aged 98, at Kingston Hospital after being admitted with a chest infection.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dailytelegraph.com.au/news/war-heroine-nancy-wake-dies/story-e6freuy9-1226110701605|title=War heroine Nancy Wake dies|publisher=[[Daily Telegraph (Australia)]]|year=2011|accessdate=8 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; She had requested that her ashes be scattered at [[Montluçon]] in central France.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.theaustralian.com.au/news/nation/the-wartime-heroics-of-nancy-wake-saved-thousands-of-lives/story-e6frg6nf-1226110719801|title=The heroics of Nancy Wake saved thousands of lives and played a crucial role in the outcome of the war|work=The Australian|agency=Australian Associated Press|date=8 August 2011|accessdate=9 August 2011|quote=One operation included an attack on the local Gestapo headquarters in Montluçon, central France, where she requested her ashes be scattered.}}&lt;/ref&gt; Her ashes were scattered near the village of [[Verneix]], which is near Montluçon, on 11 March 2013.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=War hero Nancy Wake's ashes scattered in France|url=http://www.abc.net.au/news/2013-03-11/nancy-wakes-ashes-scattered-in-france/4564500|accessdate=11 March 2013|newspaper=ABC News|date=11 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Her obituary was included in (and inspired the title for) ''The Socialite who Killed a Nazi with Her Bare Hands: And 144 Other Fascinating People who Died this Year'', a collection of New York Times obituaries published in 2012.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/12/10/the-socialite-who-killed-obits_n_2272034.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==Honours==
Wake was appointed a Chevalier (knight) of the [[Legion of Honour]] in 1970 and was promoted to Officer of the Legion of Honour in 1988.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://naa12.naa.gov.au/scripts/PhotoSearchItemDetail.asp?M=0&amp;B=11635960&amp;SE=|title=Nancy Wake promoted to Officer of the Legion of Honour}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Initially, she refused offers of decorations from Australia, saying: &quot;The last time there was a suggestion of that I told the government they could stick their medals where the monkey stuck his nuts. The thing is if they gave me a medal now, it wouldn't be love so I don't want anything from them.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;fighttimes.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.fighttimes.com/magazine/magazine.asp?article=79 |title=Nancy Wake |publisher=Fighttimes.com |accessdate=2013-06-17}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was not until February 2004 that Wake was made a [[Companion of the Order of Australia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;AC&quot;/&gt;

In April 2006, she was awarded the [[Royal New Zealand Returned and Services' Association]]'s highest honour,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rsa.org.nz/remem/rsa_hist_badge.html|title=RSA History: The Badge|work=Remembrance|publisher=[[Royal New Zealand Returned and Services' Association]]|year=2011|accessdate=11 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; the RSA Badge in Gold.&lt;ref name=&quot;RSA&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.rsa.org.nz/review/art2006december/article_3.htm|title=Nancy Wake presented with Badge in Gold|work=RSA Review|publisher=Royal New Zealand Returned and Services' Association|date=December 2006|accessdate=11 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; Wake's medals are on display in the Second World War gallery at the [[Australian War Memorial]] Museum in Canberra.&lt;ref name=Dennis/&gt;

On 3 June 2010, a &quot;heritage pylon&quot; paying tribute to Wake was unveiled on [[Oriental Parade]] in Wellington, New Zealand, near the place of her birth.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.capitaltimes.co.nz/article/3093/HeronlyregretnotkillingmoreNazis.html |title=Her only regret: not killing more Nazis |publisher=Capitaltimes.co.nz |date=2013-03-27 |accessdate=2013-06-17 |deadurl=unfit |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/*/http://www.capitaltimes.co.nz/article/3093/HeronlyregretnotkillingmoreNazis.html |archivedate= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Stuff.co.nz_3774823&quot;&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.stuff.co.nz/national/3774823/White-Mouse-war-legend-back-where-she-started |title=White Mouse war legend back where she started |date=4 June 2010 |work=[[The Dominion Post (Wellington)|The Dominion Post]] |accessdate=27 October 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===List of honours===
{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot;
|-
! Ribbon !! Issuing authority !! Description !! Date awarded !! Notes/citation
|-
|[[File:OrderAustraliaRibbon.png|80px|Ribbon of the AC]] || [[Commonwealth of Australia]] || [[Companion of the Order of Australia]]|| 22 February 2004 || The award recognises the significant contribution and commitment of Nancy Wake, stemming from her outstanding actions in wartime, in encouraging community appreciation and understanding of the past sacrifices made by Australian men and women in times of conflict, and to a lasting legacy of peace.&lt;ref name=&quot;AC&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.itsanhonour.gov.au/honours/honour_roll/search.cfm?aus_award_id=1056736&amp;search_type=quick&amp;showInd=true|title=WAKE, Nancy: Companion of the Order of Australia|work=Search Australian Honours|publisher=[[Commonwealth of Australia]]|date=22 February 2004|accessdate=11 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|[[File:GeorgeMedalRibbon.jpg|80px|Ribbon of the GM]] || [[United Kingdom]] || [[George Medal]]  || 17 July 1945 || FANY: Special operations in France&lt;ref name=&quot;GM&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.itsanhonour.gov.au/honours/honour_roll/search.cfm?aus_award_id=1073847&amp;search_type=quick&amp;showInd=true|title=WAKE, Nancy: George Medal|work=Search Australian Honours|publisher=[[Commonwealth of Australia]]|date=17 July 1945|accessdate=11 June 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''Supplement to the London Gazette'', 17 July 1945, p. 3676&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM REL22576.001&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=George Medal : Ensign N G A Wake, First Aid Nursing Yeomanry (Special Operations Executive)|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/collection/REL22576.001/|website=AWM Collection|publisher=Australian War Memorial|accessdate=16 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|- 
|[[File:1939-45 Star.jpg|80px|Ribbon of the 1939–1945 Star]] || [[Commonwealth of Nations]]  || [[1939–1945 Star]]  || || &lt;ref name=&quot;AWM REL22576.002&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=1939-45 Star : Ensign N G A Wake, First Aid Nursing Yeomanry (Special Operations Executive)|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/collection/REL22576.002/|website=AWM Collection|publisher=Australian War Memorial|accessdate=16 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|[[File:France and Germany Star BAR.svg|80px|Ribbon of the France &amp; Germany Star]] || Commonwealth of Nations || [[France and Germany Star]] || || &lt;ref name=&quot;AWM REL22576.003&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=France and Germany Star : Ensign N G A Wake, First Aid Nursing Yeomanry (Special Operations Executive)|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/collection/REL22576.003/|website=AWM Collection|publisher=Australian War Memorial|accessdate=16 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|[[File:Defence Medal BAR.svg|80px|Ribbon of the Defence Medal]] || [[United Kingdom]] || [[Defence Medal (United Kingdom)|Defence Medal]] ||  || &lt;ref name=&quot;AWM REL22576.003&quot;/&gt;
|-
|[[File:War Medal 1939–1945 (UK) ribbon.png|80px|Ribbon of the War Medal]] || United Kingdom || [[War Medal 1939–1945]] ||  || &lt;ref name=&quot;AWM REL22576.003&quot;/&gt;
|-
|[[File:Legion Honneur Chevalier ribbon.svg|80px|Ribbon of the Legion of Honor – Chevalier]] || [[France|French Republic]] || Chevalier de la [[Légion d'Honneur]] || 1970 || &lt;ref name=&quot;AWM REL22576.006&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=French Officer of the Legion of Honour : Ensign N G A Wake, First Aid Nursing Yeomanry (Special Operations Executive)|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/collection/REL22576.001/|website=AWM Collection|publisher=Australian War Memorial|accessdate=16 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|[[File:Legion Honneur Officier ribbon.svg|80px|Ribbon of the Legion of Honor – Officier]] || [[France|French Republic]] || Officier de la [[Légion d'Honneur]] || 1988 ||&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM REL22576.006&quot;/&gt;
|-
|[[File:Ruban de la croix de guerre 1939-1945.PNG|80px|Ribbon de la croix de guerre]] || French Republic || [[Croix de Guerre]] || || with two Palms and a Star&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM REL22576.006&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM REL22576.007&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=French Croix de Guerre : Ensign N G A Wake, First Aid Nursing Yeomanry (Special Operations Executive)|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/collection/REL22576.007/|website=AWM Collection|publisher=Australian War Memorial|accessdate=16 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|[[File:Medal of Freedom stripe bronsepalme.svg|80px|Ribbon of the PMOF]]  || [[United States of America]] || [[Medal of Freedom]]  ||  || with Bronze Palm. ''(Only 987 issued with Bronze Palm during WWII)''&lt;ref name=&quot;AWM REL22576.008&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=United States Medal of Freedom : Ensign N G A Wake, First Aid Nursing Yeomanry (Special Operations Executive)|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/collection/REL22576.008/|website=AWM Collection|publisher=Australian War Memorial|accessdate=16 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.omsa.org/photopost/showphoto.php?photo=5528 OMSA Info on Medal of Freedom]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|[[File:Ruban de la Médaille de la Résistance.PNG|80px|Ribbon de la Médaille de la Résistance]] || French Republic || [[Médaille de la Résistance]] ||  || &lt;ref name=&quot;AWM REL22576.009&quot;&gt;{{cite web|title=French Medaille de la Resistance : Ensign N G A Wake, First Aid Nursing Yeomanry (Special Operations Executive)|url=http://www.awm.gov.au/collection/REL22576.009/|website=AWM Collection|publisher=Australian War Memorial|accessdate=16 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| || [[New Zealand]] || Badge In Gold || 15 November 2006 ||[[Royal New Zealand Returned and Services' Association]]&lt;ref name=&quot;RSA&quot;/&gt;
|}

==Biographies==
In 1956, Australian author [[Russell Braddon]] wrote ''Nancy Wake: The Story of a Very Brave Woman'' (ISBN 978 0 7524 5485 6).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Braddon, Russell|title=Nancy Wake: The Story of a Very Brave Woman|isbn=978 0 7524 5485 6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Nancy Wake wrote her own account (first published 1985) with the original title &quot;The White Mouse&quot; (The autobiography of the woman the Gestapo called the White Mouse) (ISBN 0725107553).

In 2001, Australian author [[Peter FitzSimons]] wrote ''Nancy Wake, A Biography of Our Greatest War Heroine'' (ISBN 0 7322 6919 9), a bestselling comprehensive biography of Wake.&lt;ref name=Grauniad&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2004/feb/23/books.australia|title=A belated salute for war heroine|publisher=The Guardian|first=David|last=Fickling|date=23 February 2004|accessdate=8 August 2011|location=London}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2011, German author {{Interlanguage link multi|Michael Jürgs|de}} wrote ''Codename Hélène: Churchills Geheimagentin Nancy Wake und ihr Kampf gegen die Gestapo in Frankreich.'' (translated: ''Codename Hélène: Churchill's secret agent Nancy Wake and her fight against the [[Gestapo]] in France'').&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=Bertelsmann, München |year=2012|ISBN= 9783570101421 |url=http://www.amazon.de/dp/3570101428 |publisher=Blick ins Buch}}&lt;/ref&gt; The book was published in October 2012.

==Portrayal==
Seasons 1 and 2 of the 1980s British television series ''[[Wish Me Luck]]'' were based on her exploits and much of the dialogue was copied from her autobiography.

An Australian television mini-series was released in 1987 titled ''[[Nancy Wake (miniseries)|Nancy Wake]]'' based on the 1956 biography by Russell Braddon. It was released as ''True Colors'' in the US. Wake was played by Australian actress [[Noni Hazlehurst]] and made an appearance herself in the role of Madame Fouret. Wake was also made a consultant for the film, but only after the script had been written. She criticized the script upon reading it, and again at the launch of the mini-series. Wake was disappointed that the film was changed from an 8-hour resistance story to a 4-hour love story. The producers said that they did not have the budget for the longer version and that it was difficult to cover all Wake's exploits in the reduced time frame. Wake also candidly criticized aspects that she felt were not a true depiction of events, and continued for the rest of her life to criticize the script.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news |url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/europe/resistance-heroine-who-led-7000-men-against-the-nazis-2334156.html |work=Independent |date=9 August 2011 |title=Resistance heroine who led 7,000 men against the Nazis |first=John |last=Lichfield}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Sebastian Faulks]]'s 1999 novel ''[[Charlotte Gray (novel)|Charlotte Gray]]'' is thought to be based on Wake's war-time exploits,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Australia WWII heroine Nancy 'White Mouse' Wake dies|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-pacific-14441032|website=BBC News Asia-Pacific|publisher=British Broadcasting Corporation|accessdate=16 February 2015|date=8 August 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt; as well as those of [[Pearl Cornioley]], a British secret-service agent.{{citation needed|date=December 2012}}

Wake was featured in a 2012 article in ''[[Military Officer]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news
|title = The white mouse
|first = Mark
|last = Cantrell
|magazine = Military Officer
|issue = 3
|volume = 10
|location = Arlington, Virginia
|publisher = Military Officers Association of America
|url = http://www.qg.com/smartools/ebook/hosted.rails?issue=921b599846bb4dbdb348e8f7b860ef123c397f47fa3740cc8cb3e8f7b860ef12
|pages = 92–96
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Rachael Blampied]] portrayed Nancy Wake in the [[TVNZ]] docu-drama ''Nancy Wake: The White Mouse''.&lt;ref name=&quot;TVNZ&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url=http://tvnz.co.nz/nancy-wake-the-white-mouse/6011188 | title=Nancy Wake: The White Mouse | publisher=Television New Zealand | accessdate=April 27, 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
* Braddon, Russell. ''Nancy Wake: The Story of a Very Brave Woman'', Quality Book Club, Cassell &amp; Co. Ltd: [[London]], 1956.
* Braddon, Russell. ''Nancy Wake'', Pan Books, London; Sydney, 1958.
* Braddon, Russell. ''Woman in Arms: The Story of Nancy Wake'', Collins, London, 1963.
* {{citation|last=Dennis|first=Peter|last2=Grey |first2=Jeffrey |authorlink2=Jeffrey Grey |last3=Morris |first3=Ewan |last4=Prior |first4=Robin|title=The Oxford Companion to Australian Military History|year=1995|publisher=Oxford University Press|location=Oxford|isbn=0-19-553227-9}}
* FitzSimons, Peter. ''Nancy Wake: A Biography of Our Greatest War Heroine'', [[HarperCollins]], [[Pymble, New South Wales]], 2002,ISBN 0-00-714401-6.
* Wake, Nancy. ''Autobiography of the Woman the Gestapo Called the White Mouse'', [[Macmillan Publishers|Macmillan]]: [[South Melbourne, Victoria|South Melbourne]], 1985, ISBN 0-7251-0755-3.
* [http://www.rte.ie/radio1/doconone/curious-ear-doconone-nancy-wake.html RTE 1 radio documentary, &quot;Nancy Wake and Harry Potter&quot;, first broadcast 9-Aug-2011]
* &quot;Son and heir in Labor stronghold&quot;, ''[[Sydney Morning Herald]]'', 12 October 2006 [http://www.smh.com.au/news/obituaries/son-and-heir-in-labor-stronghold/2006/10/11/1160246193075.html]
* &quot;Finally, Nancy gets her gong&quot;, ''Sydney Morning Herald'', 3 March 2004 [http://www.smh.com.au/articles/2004/03/03/1078191357342.html?from=storyrhs]
* &quot;Her only regret:not killing more Nazis&quot;, ''Capital Times'', Wellington, 2 June 2010, accessible at Internet Archive [https://web.archive.org/web/*/http://www.capitaltimes.co.nz/article/3093/HeronlyregretnotkillingmoreNazis.html]
* &quot;White Mouse war legend back where she started&quot;, ''The Dominion Post'', Wellington, 4 June 2010 [http://www.stuff.co.nz/national/3774823/White-Mouse-war-legend-back-where-she-started]

==External links==
{{wikinews|Allied WWII spy Nancy Wake dies aged 98}}
* [http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0363b.htm Biography]
* [http://www.mickjoffe.com/Nancy_Wake 1997 Interview with Nancy Wake]
* [http://www.nzedge.com/heroes/wake.html NZ Edge]
* [http://www.awm.gov.au/people/332.asp Australian War Memorial Biography]
* [http://naa12.naa.gov.au/scripts/PhotoSearchSearchResults.asp?I=undefined&amp;browseagain=undefined&amp;refnum=&amp;seriesno=&amp;pagesize=10&amp;Pheading=undefined&amp;Sheading=undefined&amp;S=2&amp;F=1&amp;O=0&amp;T=I&amp;C=29&amp;M=1&amp;K=nancy%20wake Australian National Archives Photos of Nancy Wake]

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Wake, Nancy}}
[[Category:1912 births]]
[[Category:2011 deaths]]
[[Category:Infectious disease deaths in England]]
[[Category:Female resistance members of World War II]]
[[Category:Female wartime spies]]
[[Category:French Resistance members]]
[[Category:New Zealand military personnel of World War II]]
[[Category:Special Operations Executive personnel]]
[[Category:Women in World War II]]
[[Category:Companions of the Order of Australia]]
[[Category:Recipients of the George Medal]]
[[Category:Officiers of the Légion d'honneur]]
[[Category:New Zealand recipients of the Légion d'honneur]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Medal of Freedom]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Croix de guerre 1939–1945 (France)]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Resistance Medal]]
[[Category:People from London]]
[[Category:People from Wellington City]]</text>
      <sha1>m5cxsvb33gxkyjwlryj53m3opaddg1v</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
