<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>New Orleans-class cruiser</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>211968</id>
    <revision>
      <id>742235510</id>
      <parentid>741964665</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-02T14:01:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Llammakey</username>
        <id>21878292</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>copyedit</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16492">{{about|the cruisers built in the 1930s|the class of protected cruisers acquired in the 1890s|New Orleans-class cruiser (1896)}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2012}}
{{refimprove|date=December 2007}}
{|{{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
|Ship image=[[File:USS New Orleans (CA-32).jpg|300px]]
|Ship caption=USS ''New Orleans''
}}
{{Infobox ship class overview
|Name=''New Orleans'' class
|Builders=
|Operators=[[File:US flag 48 stars.svg|20px]] [[United States Navy]]
|Class before={{sclass-|Portland|cruiser|4}}
|Class after={{USS|Wichita|CA-45|6}}
|Subclasses=
|Built range=
|In commission range=15 February 1934 – 10 February 1947
|Total ships building=
|Total ships planned=7
|Total ships completed=7
|Total ships cancelled=
|Total ships active=
|Total ships laid up=
|Total ships lost=3
|Total ships retired=4
|Total ships preserved=
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
|Hide header=
|Header caption=
|Ship type=[[Heavy cruiser]]
|Ship displacement=* {{convert|9,950|LT|t}}
*{{convert|12,463|LT|t}} (loaded)
|Ship length={{convert|588|ft|2|in|m|abbr=on}}
|Ship beam={{convert|61|ft|9|in|m|abbr=on}}
|Ship draft={{convert|19|ft|5|in|m|abbr=on}}
|Ship power=
|Ship propulsion=*4 × Parsons/[[Westinghouse Electric (1886)|Westinghouse]] geared turbines
*8 × [[Babcock &amp; Wilcox]] [[boilers]]
*4 × screws
*{{convert|107000|HP|abbr=on|-2}}
|Ship speed={{convert|32.7|kn}}
|Ship range=
|Ship complement=708 officers and enlisted
|Ship sensors=
|Ship EW=
|Ship armament=
* 9 × [[8&quot;/55 caliber gun|8-inch/55 caliber guns]]
* 8 × [[5&quot;/25 caliber gun|5-inch/25 caliber guns]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Fahey&quot;&gt;Fahey 1941 p. 9&lt;/ref&gt;
* 8 × [[M2 Browning machine gun|.50 caliber machine guns]]
|Ship armor=*[[Belt armor|Belt]] {{convert|3|–|5|in|mm|abbr=on|0}}
*[[Deck (ship)|Deck]] {{convert|1.25|–|2.25|in|mm|abbr=on|0}}
*[[Gun turret|Turrets]] {{convert|1.5|–|8|in|mm|abbr=on|0}}
*[[Barbette]]s {{convert|5|in|mm|abbr=on|0}} ({{convert|6.5|in|mm|abbr=on|0}} in CA-38)
*[[Conning tower]] {{convert|5|in|mm|abbr=on|0}}
|Ship aircraft=
|Ship aircraft facilities=
|Ship notes=
}}
|}

The '''''New Orleans''-class cruisers''' were a class of seven [[heavy cruiser]]s built for the [[United States Navy]] (USN) in the 1930s. Originally called the ''Astoria''-class cruiser, the class was renamed after {{USS|Astoria|CA-34|2}} was sunk and the surviving ships of the class underwent substantial reconstruction.

These ships participated in the heaviest surface battles of the [[Pacific War]]. ''Astoria'', ''Quincy'', and ''Vincennes'' were all sunk in the [[Battle of Savo Island]], and three others were heavily damaged in subsequent battles in the [[Naval Battle of Guadalcanal|Guadalcanal]] campaign.
Only ''Tuscaloosa'', which spent most of the war in the Atlantic, got through the war without being damaged. Collectively, ships of the class earned 64 battle stars. The four surviving ships were laid up immediately after the end of the war, and sold for scrap in 1959.

==Design==
The ''New Orleans''-class design was a test bed for innovations in cruiser design, which is why there were three distinct designs within this class.
* Design #1: ''New Orleans'', ''Astoria'', and ''Minneapolis''.
* Design #2: ''Tuscaloosa'' and ''San Francisco''.
* Design #3: ''Quincy'' and ''Vincennes''.

This class was the direct ancestor for all subsequent USN gun cruisers. From them came the {{sclass-|Brooklyn|cruiser|5}}, {{sclass-|Wichita|cruiser|5}}, {{sclass-|Cleveland|cruiser|5}}, and the {{sclass-|Baltimore|cruiser|0}} cruisers. While the [[Washington Naval Treaty]] was still being observed, new technology was implemented in the ''New Orleans'' class because the USN knew that if and when war came, they would need this knowledge to build ships (which were already in the planning stage) beyond the treaty limits. The USN came to the conclusion that no 10,000-ton cruiser could adequately perform the roles given.

Originally {{USS|Tuscaloosa|CA-37|2}} was the lead ship of this class, but {{USS|Astoria|CA-34|2}}, {{USS|New Orleans|CA-32|2}} and {{USS|Minneapolis|CA-36|2}}, laid down as {{sclass-|Portland|cruiser|0}} ships, were reordered to the ''Tuscaloosa'' design in 1930; {{USS|Portland|CA-33|2}} and {{USS|Indianapolis|CA-35|2}} were being built in civilian rather than Navy yards and were completed as originally designed.

Three ships of the class (''Astoria'', ''Quincy'', and ''Vincennes'') were lost in the Battle of Savo Island in 1942. Immediately following the [[Guadalcanal campaign]] the remaining ships of the class went through major overhauls in order to lessen top heaviness due to new electrical and radar systems (as well as more anti-aircraft weaponry) which was being added as technology advanced. In doing so, the ships took on a new appearance, most notably in the bridge area and became known as the  ''New Orleans'' class. The four survivors were decommissioned shortly after the war ended, and scrapped in 1959–1961.

==Armor==
[[File:New Orleans class heavy cruiser ONI identification 1943.jpg|thumb|1943 [[Office of Naval Intelligence|ONI]] identification image for the ''New Orleans'' class]]
The ''New Orleans'' class was the last series of US cruisers, completed to the  limitations of the Washington Naval Treaty of 1922. As completed, the single ship  ''Wichita'' class (and subsequent heavy cruisers) exceeded the 10,000-ton standard.  

Design of these ships began in early 1929, based on the three preceding classes: The {{sclass-|Pensacola|cruiser|5}}, the {{sclass-|Northampton|cruiser|5}} and the ''Portland'' classes. All of the cruisers of the ''New Orleans'' class were outwardly similar but the displacement among these ships varied by some 600 tons. The [[Bureau of Construction and Repair]] authorized a contemporary {{convert|8|in|adj=on|0}} gun cruiser design of smaller size, but one which allocated considerably more tonnage towards protection. The ''New Orleans'' class was noteworthy for its protection. The hull was {{convert|12|ft}} shorter than a ''Northampton'', with a shorter armor belt that protected only the machinery and other internal spaces, allowing its thickness to be increased to {{convert|5|in}}. The machinery bulkheads were given {{convert|3.5|in}} and the deck armor was strengthened to {{convert|2.5|in}}. For the first time in US cruisers, [[barbette]] and [[Gun turret|turret]] armor was sufficient to withstand 8-inch shellfire. The turrets were faced with 8 inches of armor, {{convert|2.75|in}} on the sides and {{convert|1|in}} on the roof. The barbettes were protected with 5 inches of armor on all ships except {{USS|San Francisco|CA-38|2}}, whose barbettes were fitted with {{convert|6.5|in}} of armor.

[[Magazine (artillery)|Magazine]] protection was increased to {{convert|4|in}}. Magazine protection was further increased by placing them well below the waterline.  Otherwise only an internal splinter belt and the armor deck protected the magazines. While this allowed an exceptional degree of armored protection for the vitals against shellfire, there was little protected hull volume, and the deep magazines were more exposed to underwater damage ({{USS|New Orleans|CA-32|2}} learned this the hard way at the [[Battle of Tassafaronga]]).  Protection represented approximately 15% of normal displacement as opposed to the only 5.6% in the ''Pensacola''s and 6% in the ''Northampton'' and ''Portland'' classes. Unfortunately, fuel bunkerage had to be reduced, which resulted in a smaller operational range.

== Armament ==
The main armament on the class centered on nine [[8&quot;/55 caliber gun|8 in/55 caliber Mark 14 guns]] (Mark 9 guns until replaced in World War II), mounted in triple turrets. ''New Orleans'' was fitted with [[8&quot;/55 caliber gun|Mark 14 Mod 0 guns]], ''Minneapolis'' with the [[8&quot;/55 caliber gun|Mark 15 Mod 1 guns]] and the remaining ships of the class received Mark [[8&quot;/55 caliber gun|12 Mod 0 guns]]. The turret face configurations were also different with the Mark 14 guns being housed in rounded face turrets and the Mark 12 and 15 guns in a flat faced turret.  The 8 in guns had a range of {{convert|31700|yd|m|-2}} with a muzzle velocity of {{convert|2800|ft/s|m/s|-1}}. The [[armor-piercing round]] weighed {{convert|260|lb}} and could penetrate five inches of armor plating at {{convert|10000|yd|m|-3}}. Secondary armament for the class consisted of eight [[List of naval guns|5 in/25 caliber dual purpose guns]], which could be used against surface and aerial targets, as well as [[Heavy machine gun|.50 caliber water-cooled machine guns]] to augment the [[List of naval guns|5 in guns]]. When the US entered the war in December 1941, the ''New Orleans'' class and other &quot;Treaty&quot; cruisers were rushed into battle with little modification and lacking in air defense. The [[Empire of Japan|Japanese]] proved at [[Attack on Pearl Harbor|Pearl Harbor]] that this war would be decided with air power. As soon as available, the [[1.1&quot;/75 caliber gun|quadruple 1.1 in machine guns]] and the [[Switzerland|Swiss]]-designed [[Oerlikon 20 mm cannon|20 mm Oerlikon cannon]] (which would replace the .50 caliber guns) were fitted, as well as early [[radar]] units and [[Fire-control system|fire control directors]]. As the war progressed, developments in radar abilities gave the [[Allies of World War II|Allies]] an increasingly decisive advantage over the enemy. In late 1942, the arrival of the  [[Bofors 40 mm gun|40 mm Bofors]] (in twin and quadruple mountings)[[Bofors 40 mm gun|,]] replaced the quadruple 1.1-inch autocannons, which had proved ineffective. By late 1945, even after the removal of many non-essential items (half of their spotter planes as well as a crane and a catapult became non-essential due to advances in radar) the ships became dangerously over weight because of new weaponry and electrical and radar equipment. The threat from the air was so intense this condition had to be tolerated.

== Appearance and performance ==
Outwardly, the ''New Orleans'' ships had a distinctive appearance and were considered very good-looking vessels, though the 1942–43 refits of the surviving ships changed the appearance substantially.  The forward superstructure had the bridge wings cut back, and all of the large size windows were plated in with just a few port holes taking their place.  The open bridge above the wheel house was enlarged by 100 percent by extending it forward.  In addition several gun tubs were created for the 40 mm Bofors mounts both around the main mast, and aft. The [[forecastle]] deck extended back to the second funnel and the main [[superstructure]] was constructed without the ungainly [[tripod mast]] seen on the previous cruisers. The [[Bow (ship)|bow]] was a raked type, similar to those of British cruisers. The two funnels were situated closer together with a large search light tower in between. Aircraft handling facilities were moved further aft and a larger second conning station erected above the hangar. A single mainmast was erected there, between two huge pedestal cranes which handled both spotter planes and small craft. The main 8-inch turrets, although armored, were actually smaller with a more effective angular faceplate. By enlarging the forecastle deck, the secondary battery of 5-inch guns were mounted closer together, facilitating a more efficient ammunition delivery. Power was provided by eight [[Babcock &amp; Wilcox]] high-pressure [[steam boilers]] that produced {{Convert|107000|hp|kW|-2|abbr=on|lk=in}} for the four [[steam turbine|Westinghouse gearing steam turbines]]. The turbines were shafted to four screws, giving this class a rated speed of {{convert|33|kn|km/h|0|lk=in}}. The cruisers' range – using {{convert|3269|LT|lk=in}} of bunker oil – was approximately {{convert|14000|nmi|km|-3|lk=in}} at {{convert|10|kn|km/h|0}} or {{convert|5280|nmi|km|-1}} at {{convert|20|kn|km/h|0}}. Their range could be extended by refueling from a tanker or another ship fitted to transfer oil while underway. The ''New Orleans'' cruisers performed peacetime exercises well with no serious shortcomings being found. While many changes were implemented to improve their performance and especially their protection, the 10,000-ton limit of the Washington Naval Treaty was not exceeded. The new cruisers were considered successful in their own right but could not be considered equal to some foreign contemporaries, which were often considerably larger.

==Ships in class==
{| class=&quot;sortable wikitable&quot;
|-
!Ship name
!Hull no.
!Builder
!Laid down
!Launched
!Commission
!Decommission
!Fate
|-
|{{USS|New Orleans|CA-32|2}}
|CA-32
|[[New York Navy Yard]]
|14 March 1931
|12 April 1933
|15 February 1934
|10 February 1947
|Struck 1 March 1959; Sold for scrap; 22 September 1959
|-
|{{USS|Astoria|CA-34|2}}
|CA-34
|[[Puget Sound Naval Shipyard]]
|1 September 1930
|16 December 1933
|28 April 1934
|{{n/a}}
|Sunk, [[Battle of Savo Island]] 9 August 1942
|-
|{{USS|Minneapolis|CA-36|2}}
|CA-36
|[[Philadelphia Navy Yard]]
|27 June 1931
|6 September 1933
|19 May 1934
|10 February 1947
|Struck 1 March 1959; Sold for scrap, 14 August 1959
|-
|{{USS|Tuscaloosa|CA-37|2}}
|CA-37
|[[New York Shipbuilding Corporation]], [[Camden, New Jersey]]
|3 September 1931
|15 November 1933
|17 August 1934
|13 February 1946
|Struck 1 March 1959; Sold for scrap, 25 June 1959
|-
|{{USS|San Francisco|CA-38|2}}
|CA-38
|[[Mare Island Navy Yard]]
|9 September 1931
|9 March 1933
|10 February 1934
|10 February 1946
|Struck 1 March 1959; Sold for scrap, 9 September 1959
|-
|{{USS|Quincy|CA-39|2}}
|CA-39
|rowspan=2|[[Bethlehem Steel Corporation]], [[Fore River Shipyard]], [[Quincy, Massachusetts]]
|15 November 1933
|19 June 1935
|9 June 1936
|rowspan=2 {{n/a}}
|Sunk, [[Battle of Savo Island]] 9 August 1942
|-
|{{USS|Vincennes|CA-44|2}}
|CA-44
|2 January 1934
|21 May 1936
|24 February 1937
|Sunk, [[Battle of Savo Island]] 9 August 1942
|}

== World War II ==
For almost four years, the ships of the ''New Orleans'' class were assigned to the most urgent of front line duties, and thus, became involved in more than their share of deadly action. ''Astoria'', ''Quincy'' and ''Vincennes'' were quickly sunk in the Battle of Savo Island, 8 – 9 Aug 1942.  Although  three of their number were lost, the ships proved to be well designed. ''New Orleans'', ''Minneapolis'' and ''San Francisco'' were also seriously damaged in early war engagements in the [[Pacific War|Pacific]]. These engagements included the [[Naval Battle of Guadalcanal]], in which ''San Francisco'' engaged enemy ships at point blank range, and the [[Battle of Tassafaronga]] where ''Minneapolis'' and ''New Orleans'' took heavy damage and losses from [[Type 93 torpedo|Long Lance torpedo]]es. Damage control work and skillful seamanship kept these ships afloat to continue to fight through the end of the war.

''New Orleans''-class cruisers were found at every major naval skirmish of World War II in the Pacific despite the fact there were only four of the seven units remaining after the first year of war. They were some of the most used and hardest fought ships of the US Navy during the war. Three ships of this class were among the [[most decorated US ships of World War II]]. ''San Francisco'' earned&lt;ref name=&quot;Wiper 2000 58&quot;&gt;{{cite book|last=Wiper|first=Steve|title=New Orleans Class Cruisers|year=2000|publisher=Classic Warships Publishing|location=Tucson, Az|pages=58}}&lt;/ref&gt; 17 [[Service star|Battle Stars]] and a [[Presidential Unit Citation (United States)|Presidential Unit Citation]], ''New Orleans'' earned&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Brown|first=Herbert C.|title=Hell at Tassafaronga|year=2001|publisher=Morris Publishing|location=Kearney, NE|pages=199}}&lt;/ref&gt; 17 Battle Stars, and ''Minneapolis'' earned&lt;ref name=&quot;Wiper 2000 58&quot;/&gt; 17 Battle Stars as well. As a class, they earned a total of 64 Battle Stars and a Presidential Unit Citation.&lt;ref name=&quot;Wiper 2000 58&quot;/&gt;

== See also ==
* {{sclass-|New Orleans|cruiser (1896)|1}}

== References ==
{{reflist|30em}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|New Orleans class cruiser}}
* [http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/systems/ship/ca-32.htm Global Security.org – New Orleans class cruiser]
* [http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/systems/ship/ca-32-specs.htm Global Security.org – New Orleans class cruiser specifications]

{{New Orleans class cruiser}}
{{WWIIUSShips}}

[[Category:Cruiser classes]]
[[Category:New Orleans-class cruisers| ]]
[[Category:World War II cruisers of the United States| ]]</text>
      <sha1>jh54qkc90ytnb2fb3lnvjrr8xtx3gtx</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
