<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Nikolai Vatutin</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>754133</id>
    <revision>
      <id>751184678</id>
      <parentid>749055712</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-23T22:20:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dchris1990</username>
        <id>26603665</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Kiev and the Korsun-Cherkassy pocket */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="17901">{{Multiple issues|
{{Lead too short|date=November 2008}}
{{refimprove|date=July 2014}}
}}

{{Infobox military person
|name=Nikolai Vatutin
|native_name=Никола́й Фёдорович Вату́тин
|native_name_lang=rus
|image=Николай Ватутин, 1943 год.jpg
|image_size=260px
|caption=Vatutin in 1943
|birth_date={{birth date|df=yes|1901|12|16}}
|death_date = {{Death date and age|df=yes|1944|4|15|1901|12|16}}
|birth_place= [[Valuysky District|Chepuhino]], [[Voronezh Governorate]] (now in [[Belgorod Oblast]]), [[Russian Empire]]
|death_place=[[Kiev]], [[Ukrainian SSR]], [[Soviet Union]]
|nickname=
|allegiance={{USSR}}
|branch=
|serviceyears=1920–1944
|rank=[[General of the Army (Soviet Union)|Army General]]
|unit=
|commands=
{{plainlist|
*[[Voronezh Front]]
*[[Southwestern Front (Soviet Union)|Southwestern Front]]
*[[1st Ukrainian Front]]
}}
|battles=
{{plainlist|
*[[Battle of Stalingrad]]
*[[Battle of Kursk]]
*[[Dnieper–Carpathian Offensive]]
}}
|awards={{Hero of the Soviet Union}}{{Order of Lenin}}{{Order of Lenin}}&lt;br&gt;
[[Order of the Red Banner]]&lt;br&gt;
[[Order of Suvorov]] 1st class &lt;br&gt;
[[Order of Kutuzov]] 1st class
|relations=Tatiana Romanovna Vatutina (wife)&lt;br /&gt;Jelena (daughter, 1930–2016)&lt;br /&gt;Viktor (son, 1932–?)
|children= Elena (1930–?)&lt;br /&gt;Viktor (1932–?)
|laterwork=
|signature = Nikolay Vatutin Signature 1939.png
}}
'''Nikolai Fyodorovich Vatutin''' ({{lang-ru|Никола́й Фёдорович Вату́тин}}; 16 December 1901 – 15 April 1944) was a [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] military commander during [[World War II]]. Vatutin was responsible for many [[Red Army]] operations in [[Ukraine]] as commander of the [[Southwestern Front (Soviet Union)|Southwestern Front]],&lt;ref&gt;Keegan, pp. 106–107&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Voronezh Front]] during the [[Battle of Kursk]]&lt;ref&gt;Keegan, pp. 124–125&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[1st Ukrainian Front]] during the liberation of [[Kiev]].&lt;ref&gt;Keegan, pp. 126–127&lt;/ref&gt; He was ambushed and mortally wounded in February 1944 by the [[Ukrainian Insurgent Army]].

==Before World War II==
Vatutin was born in [[Valuysky District|Chepuhino]] village in [[Voronezh Governorate]] (now [[Valuysky District|Vatutino]] in [[Belgorod Oblast]]), into a peasant family of [[Russians|Russian]] ethnicity.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.warheroes.ru/hero/hero.asp?Hero_id=1059 Герой Советского Союза Ватутин Николай Фёдорович :: Герои страны]. Warheroes.ru. Retrieved on 16 May 2016.&lt;/ref&gt; Commissioned in 1920 to the [[Red Army]], he fought against the Ukrainian peasant partisans of [[Nestor Makhno]]. The following year, he became a member of the [[Communist party]], and served  diligently in junior command positions. Starting in 1926, he spent the next decade alternating service with studies in the elite [[Frunze Military Academy]] and the [[General Staff Academy (Russia)|General Staff Academy]]. The 1937–1938 [[Great Purge|purge]] of Red Army commanders opened the road to promotion – in 1938, he received the rank of [[Comdiv|Komdiv]], and was appointed Chief of Staff of the important [[Kiev Military District|Kiev Special Military District]]. Throughout this period, Vatutin combined military service with intensive Party activities.

In 1939, Vatutin planned operations for the [[Soviet invasion of Poland]] with [[Germany]], and served as Chief of Staff of the Red Army Southern Group. In 1940, under the command of [[Georgy Zhukov]], this group [[Soviet occupation of Bessarabia and Northern Bukovina|seized Bessarabia]] from [[Romania]]. As a reward for these non-combat campaigns, Stalin promoted Vatutin to the rank of [[Lieutenant General]] and appointed him to the critical post of Chief of the [[Operational Directorate]] of the [[General Staff]]. Vatutin was, however, not up to his new appointment: while innovative and hard-working, he lacked any combat experience and his knowledge of operational art and strategy was too abstract. Still, his peasant roots, relative youthful age, and party zeal made him one of Stalin's few favorites in the Soviet military. Vatutin, together with the rest of the Red Army high command, failed to prepare the army for the [[Operation Barbarossa|German attack]] of 22 June 1941.

On 30 June 1941, he was appointed Chief of Staff of the [[North-Western Front]], (''see [[Soviet Fronts in World War II]]'') which enabled him to exercise his better qualities. In this role Vatutin did not try to claim success for himself in battles, but made a point of identifying and promoting talented subordinates. He was notable for his audacity. At that stage&lt;!--copyeditor's note:kindly clarify at what stage of the war are talking about? --&gt; of the war, most of the Soviet generals, shattered by defeats, were reluctant to carry out offensive operations, but Vatutin thrived on attack.

==The Battles in the North==
The Northwestern Front was defending [[Saint Petersburg|Leningrad]] against approaches by the [[German Army Group North]], spearheaded by armored corps led by [[Erich von Manstein]]. Vatutin took command of the Soviet forces near [[Novgorod]] and rallied them for offense, attempting to encircle a large German force. He surprised Manstein, put him on the defensive, and forced the entire German Army Group North to regroup its troops to halt the Soviet offensive.{{citation needed|date=December 2013}} The [[Wehrmacht]] lost the precious summer season needed for an effective attack on Leningrad, while the Red Army got additional time to strengthen the fortifications of the city. Due to this, the Germans failed in their best shot to capture Leningrad, one of the key German strategic failures during the early phase of war.{{dubious|date=December 2013}} Vatutin's immediate operational results were far less impressive. Vatutin overestimated the capacities of his troops and created overly ambitious objectives, while his coordination of his forces and control over the unfolding of the battle were poor. Additionally, he did not take into account the difficult terrain which benefited German defenses and slowed his attack. Vatutin's casualty figures were staggering, in one army nearly reaching 60%. The ineptitude of his subordinate commanders exacerbated Vatutin's own shortcomings. One striking exception to this pattern of deficiency was the brilliance of [[Ivan Chernyakhovsky]], an obscure young Colonel in command of the 28th tank division. The men had much in common, most prominently their penchant for unorthodox approaches to military art; they soon became close friends.

In January 1942, during the Soviet [[Soviet Offensive (1941-1942)|winter offensive]] following the Red Army victory in the [[Battle of Moscow]], Vatutin's forces trapped two German corps in [[Demyansk]], and achieved the first large Soviet encirclement of German forces. The German and Soviet armies were equal in size. During the battle, Vatutin employed innovative tactics and actions, while the Germans responded more conventionally. The Red Army was unable to destroy the German defenses, mainly due to the weakness of the Soviet air-force. In April 1942, Vatutin finally breached the German lines, just as a German relief force arrived. However, post-World War II American experts have evaluated the result of this operation as a draw. The German command drew self-congratulatory and misleading lessons from their narrow escape, concluding that they could overcome Soviet encirclements with supplies from the air while mounting a relief operation. This thinking contributed to the Wehrmacht disaster at [[Battle of Stalingrad|Stalingrad]].

==Voronezh and Stalingrad==
From early May to July 1942, Vatutin served briefly as deputy of the Chief of the General Staff of the Red Army until the [[German Army Group South]] embarked on its huge strategic offense, &quot;[[Operation Blau]]&quot;. Initially, the German assault focused on [[Voronezh]]. They wanted to  breach the Soviet front line at the [[Battle of Voronezh (1942)|Battle of Voronezh]] and then attack the [[Soviet Southern Front]] and [[Soviet Southwestern Front|Southwestern Front]] from the rear. On  1 July 1942, Stalin sent Vatutin as an all-powerful [[Stavka]] representative, to the critical [[Bryansk Front]], which within a few days was renamed as [[Voronezh Front]] and placed under Vatutin's command.

During the battle, Vatutin again met [[Ivan Chernyakhovsky]], now the newly appointed commander of the 18th Tank Corps of the 60th Army. The German attack was on the verge of breaching the Soviet front line when Cherniakhovsky's corps arrived by train. Cherniakhovsky unloaded one of his brigades and, without waiting for the rest of his troops, led that brigade against the German forces, throwing them back. After this action, Vatutin asked Stalin to give command of the 60th army to Cherniakhovsky. Initially, Stalin opposed the request, mostly because he had  reservations about appointing such a young general to lead a field army. However, Vatutin finally convinced Stalin to promote Cherniakhovsky, who would rapidly rise to become one of the major Red Army field commanders.

Although the Germans captured the city, their attempt to breach Vatutin's front line failed. Following this, the Germans abandoned their initial plan, and shifted their efforts toward [[Stalingrad]]. On 22 October 1942, Vatutin received command of the newly formed [[Southwestern Front (Soviet Union)|Southwestern Front]] and played an important role in planning the Soviet counter-offensive and the following encirclement of the [[6th Army (Wehrmacht)|German 6th Army]] in the [[Battle of Stalingrad]]. In December 1942, to secure the Soviet ring around Stalingrad, Vatutin's forces encircled and destroyed two-thirds of the 130,000-strong [[Italian Army in Russia|Italian 8th Army]] in operation [[Operation Saturn#Operation Little Saturn: December 1942|Little Saturn]], contributing to the defeat of Manstein's [[Operation Wintergewitter]] (&quot;Winter Storm&quot;), the relief effort for the 6th Army.

==Kharkov and Kursk==
In January 1943, Vatutin's Southwest Front drove the Germans from the [[Eastern Ukraine]]. His actions enabled the Voronezh Front under General [[Filipp Golikov]] to capture [[Kharkov]], but he overextended his depleted troops and did not pay enough attention to the changing strategic situation. In February 1943, Manstein, using the forces extricated from the Caucasus, managed to surprise and defeat Vatutin south of Kharkov, leading to the encirclement of Golikov's advance troops in Kharkov, and the recapture of the city in the [[Third Battle of Kharkov]]. Stavka removed Golikov from his command, but did not see Vatutin's debacle as significant. For his audacity, Stalin awarded Vatutin the rank of [[Army General (Soviet Union)|Army General]].

On 28 March 1943, Vatutin took command of the Voronezh Front, preparing for the momentous [[Battle of Kursk]]. At Kursk, he rejected conventional echeloning of armies; his innovative deployment allowed him to not only skillfully conduct the defense against the technically superior Germans, but also to quickly switch from defense to offense. Following the Soviet victory at Kursk, [[Belgorod]] was recaptured.

==Kiev and the Korsun-Cherkassy pocket==
Vatutin now aspired to retake [[Kiev]]. He regrouped his forces and surprised Manstein, sweeping tank forces through swampland and scattering the Germans from the unexpected direction. On 6 November 1943, [[Battle of Kiev (1943)|Kiev was retaken]]. Vatutin relentlessly exploited his victory in Kiev, and pushed deep into the German defenses, destroying the German defensive line. However, Vatutin overextended his armies, and Manstein used his reserve forces in the [[XLVIII Panzer Corps (Germany)|XLVIII Panzerkorps]] to counterattack. In the battle of [[Radomyshl]] (6–15 November 1943) and the battle of the Meleni pocket (16–23 December 1943) Manstein unleashed successful counterattacks which took terrain back and inflicted heavy losses on the Red Army forces.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|first=Steven H.|last=Newton|title=Panzer Operations: The Eastern Front Memoir of General Raus, 1941–1945|location=Cambridge, MA.|publisher=Da Capo Press|year=2005|pages=256–262|isbn=0-306-81409-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Regaining the initiative in winter weather, in January Vatutin's front and the 2nd Ukrainian Front of Army General [[Ivan Konev]] carried out the sudden encirclement of the [[Korsun-Cherkassy Pocket|Korsun]] [[Salients, re-entrants and pockets|salient]] at the Dneiper River in the [[Korsun–Shevchenkovsky Offensive|Korsun-Shevchenko operation]]. Although Vatutin started the operation two days after Konev and his striking formation, and the [[6th Guards Tank Army|6th Tank Army]] was only recently formed, he achieved the element of surprise by committing his tanks to the battle from the first echelon and once again attacking from unexpected terrain. This allowed the 6th Tank Army to penetrate deep into German defenses and, on 3 February, it linked with the advancing armor of Konev's front and trapped 56,000 German troops. By 17 February, Vatutin and Konev's forces had eliminated the [[Korsun-Cherkassy Pocket]], although many of the encircled troops managed to escape.

==Death==
[[File:Vatutin.jpg|thumb|upright=1.2|Vatutin as Commander-First Ukrainian Front in January 1944]]
On 28 February 1944 Vatutin, regrouping for a new operation and heading to [[Slavuta]] ([[Khmelnytskyi Oblast]]), was ambushed by [[Ukrainian Insurgent Army]] (UPA) insurgents far behind the front lines near the village of Mylyatyn in [[Ostroh Raion]] ([[Rivne Oblast]]). He succumbed to his injuries from [[sepsis]] in a hospital at Kiev six weeks later. Vatutin's brothers, Afanasy Fyodorovich and Semyon Fyodorovich, were killed in action in February and March 1944; his mother, Vera Yefimovna, buried her three sons in two months.&lt;ref&gt;Russian: Каманин, Н.П., &quot;Летчики и космонавты&quot;, М, 1971, p.269 Some sources give the date of the attack as 29 February and the date of Vatutin's death as 15 April.&lt;/ref&gt; Nikolai Vatutin was given a state funeral in [[Kiev]]. He was succeeded by [[Georgy Zhukov]].

==Legacy==
His influence on the Red Army strategic planning, operational, and tactical techniques continued even after his death. Following the post-[[Cold War]] decline in Germanocentric analyses of the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]], Vatutin has won recognition among Western military experts as one of World War II's most creative commanders.{{Citation needed|date=August 2010}}

In 2015, Vatutin's daughter announced that her father had been buried in Kiev by Khrushchev against her family's wishes, and that his surviving family (who live either in Russia or in the Czech Republic) will attempt to obtain permission to rebury him in Moscow. The primary reason was stated to be their dislike for the new Ukrainian government's association with Stepan Bandera, whose followers had killed Vatutin. Originally, a press release from the [[Just Russia]] party had falsely claimed that the initiative to move his body had come from the Kiev authorities.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.svoboda.org/content/article/26947111.html Генерал Ватутин Киеву не мешает]. ''Radio Svoboda''. 12 April 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rferl.org/content/ukraine-soviet-general-vatutin-monument-dispute/26950621.html Dispute Rages Over Soviet General's Grave In Ukraine]. ''Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty''. 11 April 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; The rebury didn't materialise and Vatutin remains buried in front of his statue near the [[Ukrainian parliament]].&lt;ref&gt;{{ru icon}} [http://m.ria.ru/world/20160630/1455332485.html Monument to General Vatutin continue to stand outside the building in Kiev, Rada], [[RIA Novosti]] (30 June 2016)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Popular culture==
*Vatutin is supposedly related to a [[KGB]] officer in [[Tom Clancy]]'s novel ''[[The Cardinal of the Kremlin]]''.{{citation needed|date=December 2013}}
*The battle of the Korsun Salient is the basis for the award-winning computer wargame ''[[Decisive Battles of WWII: Korsun Pocket]]''.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Cited sources==
*Keegan, John (ed.) (1996) ''Atlas of the Second World War''. ISBN 0 7230 0939 2

==Further reading==
* [[David Glantz]], &quot;Vatutin&quot; in Harold Shukman, ed., ''Stalin's Generals'' (New York, NY, 1993), pp.&amp;nbsp;287–298.
* David Glantz, [[Jonathan House|Jonathan M. House]], ''When Titans Clashed: How the Red Army Stopped Hitler'' (Lawrence, KS, 1995).
* David Glantz, Jonathan M. House, ''The Battle of Kursk'' (Lawrence, KS, 1999).
* David Glantz, ''The Battle for Leningrad, 1941–1944'' (Lawrence, KS, 2002).

==External links==
{{Commons category|Nikolai Vatutin}}
* {{ua icon}} [http://www.istpravda.com.ua/research/2010/12/11/8433/ Як загинув Микола Ватутін? Документальна правда про поранення, лікування та смерть (Ukrainian Pravda, 11.12.2010)]

{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2016}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Vatutin, Nikolai}}
[[Category:1901 births]]
[[Category:1944 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Valuysky District]]
[[Category:People from Voronezh Governorate]]
[[Category:Communist Party of the Soviet Union members]]
[[Category:Army generals (Soviet Union)]]
[[Category:Russian people of World War II]]
[[Category:General Staff Academy (Soviet Union) alumni]]
[[Category:Frunze Military Academy alumni]]
[[Category:Heroes of the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:Soviet military personnel killed in World War II]]
[[Category:Deaths from sepsis]]
[[Category:Burials at Mariinsky Park]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of the Red Banner]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of Kutuzov, 1st class]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Order of Suvorov, 1st class]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Czechoslovak War Cross]]
[[Category:Ukrainian Insurgent Army]]</text>
      <sha1>rstllxdnx0m55oa9o2x1xeyfhaw1pjv</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
