<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Oberkommando der Wehrmacht</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>53892</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750915296</id>
      <parentid>748533328</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-22T05:59:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>K.e.coffman</username>
        <id>22615369</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>link [[Geoffrey P. Megargee|Geoffrey Megargee]] using [[:en:User:Edward/Find link|Find link]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15464">{{Refimprove|date=April 2016}}
{{redirect|OKW}}
{{italic title}}
{{Infobox military unit
|unit_name = Oberkommando der Wehrmacht
|image = [[File:Chef des Oberkommandos der Wehrmacht als Generalfeldmarschall.svg|centre|150px]]
|caption = {{longitem|style=line-height:1.25em;padding:0 0.25em 0.5em; |Command flag of the Chief of the OKW with the rank of ''[[Generalfeldmarschall]]'' (1941–1945)}}
|dates = 4 February 1938 – 8 May 1945
|country = {{flag|Nazi Germany}}
|branch = ''[[Wehrmacht]]''
|role = [[German General Staff]]
|size = |command_structure = 
|garrison = Wünsdorf, near [[Zossen]]
|garrison_label = Headquarters
|motto = |colors = |colors_label = |march = |mascot = |equipment = |equipment_label = 
|battles = {{nowrap|[[European theatre of World War II|World War II in Europe]]}}
|anniversaries = |decorations = |battle_honours = 
|disbanded = 
&lt;!---Commanders---&gt;
|commander1 = [[Wilhelm Keitel]]
|commander1_label = {{nowrap|Chief of the OKW}}
&lt;!---Insignia---&gt;
|identification_symbol = |identification_symbol_label = 
}}

The '''''Oberkommando der Wehrmacht''''' ('''OKW''', &quot;Supreme Command of the Armed Forces&quot;) was part of the command structure of the ''[[Wehrmacht]]'' (armed forces) of [[Nazi Germany]] during [[World War II]]. Created in 1938, the OKW had nominal oversight over the [[German Army (Wehrmacht)|German Army]], the ''[[Kriegsmarine]]'' (German navy) and the ''[[Luftwaffe]]'' (German air force).

Rivalry with the armed services branch commands, mainly with the ''[[Oberkommando des Heeres]]'' (OKH), prevented the OKW from becoming a unified [[German General Staff]] in an effective chain of command. However, it did coordinate operations between the three services. During the war, the OKW, subordinate to [[Adolf Hitler]] as Supreme Commander of the Wehrmacht, acquired more and more operational powers. By 1942, OKW had responsibility for all theaters except for the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]] against the [[Soviet Union]]. Hitler manipulated the bipolar system to keep ultimate decisions in his own hands.&lt;ref&gt;G.P. Megargee, &quot;Triumph of the Null: Structure and Conflict in the Command of German Land Forces, 1939-1945,&quot; ''War in History'' (1997) 4#1 pp 60-80, online.&lt;/ref&gt;

== Genesis ==
[[File:Chef OKW Version 1.svg|thumb|Command flag of the Chief of the OKW 1938–1941]]

The OKW was established by decree of 4 February 1938 on the occasion of the [[Blomberg-Fritsch Affair]], which had led to the dismissal of [[German Reich|Reich]] War Minister and Commander-in-chief of the Wehrmacht, Generalfeldmarschall [[Werner von Blomberg]]. Hitler took the chance to get rid of his critics within the armed forces. The [[Ministry of the Reichswehr|Reich War Ministry]] was dissolved and replaced with the OKW led by devoted General [[Wilhelm Keitel]] in the rank of a Reich Minister, with [[Alfred Jodl]] as Chief of the Operations Staff. Nevertheless, all Supreme Commanders of the armed service branches, like OKH Chief General [[Walther von Brauchitsch]], had direct access to Hitler and were able to circumvent Keitel's command. The appointments made to the OKW and the motive behind the reorganization are commonly thought to be Hitler's desire to consolidate power and authority around his position as [[Führer]] and [[Chancellor of Germany|Reich Chancellor]] ''(Führer und Reichskanzler)'', to the detriment of the military leadership of the ''Wehrmacht''.

== Organization ==

By June 1938, the OKW comprised four departments:
* ''Wehrmacht-Führungsamt'' (WFA, renamed ''Wehrmachtführungsstab'' (Wfst) in August 1940) - operational orders. Chief: Colonel-General [[Alfred Jodl]], 1 September 1939 - 8 May 1945
** ''Abteilung Landesverteidigungsführungsamt'' (WFA/L) a subdepartment through which all details of operational planning were worked out, and from which all operational orders were communicated to the OKW. Chief: Major General [[Walter Warlimont]], 1 September 1939 - 6 September 1944; Major General [[Horst Freiherr Treusch von Buttlar-Brandenfels]], 6 September 1944 - 30 November 1944; General [[August Winter]], 1 December 1944 - 23 April 1945
** ''Abteilung Wehrmachtpropaganda'' - propaganda troops. Chief: Major General [[Hasso von Wedel (General)|Hasso von Wedel]], 1 September 1939 - 8 May 1945
** ''Heeresstab'' -  army staff. Chief: General [[Walther Buhle]], 15 February 1942 - 8 May 1945
** ''Inspekteur der Wehrmachtnachrichtenverbände'' -  Chief of Staff, Wehrmacht signal corps
* ''[[Abwehr|Amt Ausland/Abwehr]]'' - foreign intelligence.&lt;ref&gt;Also known by title ''Amtsgruppe Auslandsnachrichten und Abwehr''&lt;/ref&gt; Chief: Admiral [[Wilhelm Canaris]], 1 September 1939 - 12 February 1944; Colonel [[Georg Hansen]], 13 February 1944 - 1 June 1944; ''SS-Brigadeführer'' [[Walter Schellenberg]], 1 June 1944 - 4 May 1945; ''SS-Obersturmbannführer'' [[Otto Skorzeny]], 5–8 May 1945 
** Chief of Staff
** ''Zentralabteilung'' - central department. Chief: Major General [[Hans Oster]], 1 September 1939 - January 1944
** ''Abteilung Ausland'' - foreign
*** ''Gruppe I: Außen- und Wehrpolitik'' - foreign and defence policy
*** ''Gruppe II: Beziehung zu fremden Wehrmächten'' - relations with foreign militaries
*** ''Gruppe III: Fremde Wehrmachten, Meldesammelstelle des OKW'' - foreign militaries
*** ''Gruppe IV: Etappenorganisation der Kriegsmarine''
*** ''Gruppe V: Auslandspresse'' - foreign media
*** ''Gruppe VI: Militärische Untersuchungsstelle für Kriegsvölkerrecht'' - research service for international laws of war
*** ''Gruppe VII: Kolonialfragen'' - colonial matters
*** ''Gruppe VIII: Wehrauswertung'' - defence analysis
** ''Abteilung Nachrichtenbeschaffung'' - intelligence. Chief: Colonel [[Hans Piepenbrock]], 1 September 1939 - March 1943; Colonel [[Georg Hansen]], March 1943 - February 1944
*** ''Gruppe H: Geheimer Meldedienst Heer'' - army intelligence service
*** ''Gruppe M: Geheimer Meldedienst Marine'' - naval intelligence service
*** ''Gruppe L: Geheimer Meldedienst Luftwaffe'' - air intelligence service
*** ''Gruppe G: Technische Arbeitsmittel'' - technical equipment
*** ''Gruppe wi: Geheimer Meldedienst Wirtschaft'' - economic intelligence service
*** ''Gruppe P: Presseauswertung'' - media analysis
*** ''Gruppe i: Funknetz Abwehr Funkstelle'' - radio communications
** ''Abteilung Sonderdienst'' - special service. Chief: Colonel [[Erwin von Lahousen]], 1 September 1939 - July 1943; Colonel [[Wessel Freytag von Loringhoven]], July 1943 - June 1944
*** ''Gruppe I: Minderheiten'' - minorities
*** ''Gruppe II: Sondermaßnahmen'' - special measures
** ''Abteilung Abwehr'' - counter-intelligence. 
*** ''Führungsgruppe W: Abwehr in der Wehrmacht'' - counter-intelligence in the military
*** ''Gruppe Wi: Abwehr Wirtschaft'' - economic counter-intelligence
*** ''Gruppe C: Abwehr Inland'' - inland counter-intelligence
*** ''Gruppe F: Abwehr Ausland'' - foreign counter-intelligence
*** ''Gruppe D: Sonderdienst'' - special service
*** ''Gruppe S: Sabotageabwehr'' - counter-sabotage
*** ''Gruppe G: Gutachten'' - evaluation
*** ''Gruppe Z: Zentralarchiv'' - central archives
** ''Auslands(telegramm)prüfstelle'' - foreign communications
*** ''Gruppe I: Sortierung'' - sorting
*** ''Gruppe II: Chemische Untersuchung'' - chemical testing
*** ''Gruppe III: Privatbriefe'' - private mail
*** ''Gruppe IV: Handelsbriefe'' - commercial mail
*** ''Gruppe V: Feldpostbriefe'' - military mail
*** ''Gruppe VI: Kriegsgefangenenbriefe'' - POWs' mail
*** ''Gruppe VII: Zentralkartei'' - central register
*** ''Gruppe VIII: Auswertung'' - analysis
*** ''Gruppe IX: Kriegsgefangenen-Brief-Auswertung'' - analysis of POWs' mail
* ''Wirtschafts und Rüstungsamt'' - supply matters &lt;ref&gt;Also known by title ''Wehrwirtschaftsstab''.&lt;/ref&gt;
* ''[[Amtsgruppe Allgemeine Wehrmachtsangelegenheiten]]'' - miscellaneous matters.
** ''Abteilung Inland'' - inland
** ''Allgemeine Abteilung'' - general
** ''Wehrmachtsfürsorge- und versorgungsabteilung'' - supplies
** ''Wehrmachtsfachschulunterricht'' - education
** ''Wissenschaft'' - science
** ''Wehrmachtsverwaltungsabteilung'' - administration
** ''General zu besonderen Verfügung für Kriegsgefangenenwesen'' - prisoners of war
** ''Abteilung Wehrmachtverlustwesen'' (WVW) - casualties
*** ''[[Deutsche Dienststelle (WASt)|Wehrmachtauskunftstelle für Kriegerverluste und Kriegsgefangene]]'' (WaSt) - information centre for war casualties and prisoners of war

The WFA replaced the ''Wehrmachtsamt'' (Armed Forces Office) which had existed between 1935 and 1938 within the Reich War Ministry, headed by General Wilhelm Keitel. Hitler promoted Keitel to Chief of the OKW (''Chef des OKW''), i.e. Chief of the Supreme Command of the Armed Forces. As head of the WFA, Keitel appointed [[Max von Viebahn]] although after two months he was removed from command, and this post was not refilled until the promotion of Alfred Jodl. To replace Jodl at ''Abteilung Landesverteidigungsführungsamt'' (WFA/L), [[Walther Warlimont]] was appointed.&lt;ref&gt;Warlimont being replaced in September 1944 due to ill health by General [[August Winter]].&lt;/ref&gt; In December 1941 further changes took place with ''Abteilung Landesverteidigungsführungsamt'' (WFA/L) being merged into the ''Wehrmacht-Führungsamt'' and losing its role as a subordinate organization. These changes were largely cosmetic however as key staff remained in post and continued to fulfill the same duties.

The OKW directed the operations of the German Armed Forces during World War II. The OKW was almost always represented at daily situation conferences ''(Lagevorträge)'' by Jodl, Keitel, and the officer serving as Hitler's adjutant. During these conferences situation reports prepared by the head of WFA/L would be delivered to Hitler and then discussed. Following these discussions, Hitler would issue further operational orders. These orders were then relayed back to WFA/L by Jodl along with the minutes of the meeting. These would then be converted into orders for issuance to the appropriate commanders.

== Operation ==

Officially, the OKW served as the military general staff for the Third Reich, coordinating the efforts of the Army, Navy, and Air Force (''Heer'', ''Kriegsmarine'', and ''Luftwaffe''). In practice, the OKW acted as Hitler's personal military staff, translating his ideas into military orders, and issuing them to the three services while having little control over them. However, as the war progressed the OKW found itself exercising increasing amounts of direct command authority over military units, particularly in the West. This created a situation such that by 1942 the OKW held the ''[[de facto]]'' command of Western forces while the Army High Command (''Oberkommando des Heeres'', OKH) exercised ''de facto'' command of the [[Eastern Front (WWII)|Eastern Front]]. It was not until 28 April 1945 (two days before [[Death of Adolf Hitler|his suicide]]) that Hitler placed OKH under OKW, giving OKW command of forces on the Eastern Front.&lt;ref&gt;Howard D. Grier. ''Hitler, Dönitz, and the Baltic Sea'', Naval Institute Press, 2007, ISBN 1-59114-345-4. [https://books.google.com/books?id=u4IbqxEQeBMC&amp;sig=ACfU3U1y5qvHJPiPkpX74WKLzPbPX7KK5g&amp;pg=PA121#PPA121,M1 p. 121]&lt;!--Last  sentence only--&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

Setting different parts of the Nazi bureaucracy to compete for his favor in areas where their administration overlapped was a standard tactic employed by Hitler to reinforce his authority; and just as in other areas of government, there was a rivalry between the OKW and the OKH. Since most German operations during World War II were Army controlled (with ''Luftwaffe'' support), the OKH demanded control over German military forces. Nevertheless, Hitler decided against the OKH and in favor of the OKW overseeing operations in many land theaters. As the war progressed more and more influence moved from the OKH to the OKW, with [[Norway]] being the first &quot;OKW [[theater (warfare)|war theater]]&quot;. More and more areas came under complete control of the OKW. Finally only the Eastern Front remained the domain of the OKH. However, as the Eastern Front was by far the primary battlefield of the German military, the OKH was still influential, particularly when on 19 December 1941 Hitler himself succeeded Walther von Brauchitsch as commander-in-chief of the OKH (''Oberbefehlshaber des Heeres'') during the [[Battle of Moscow]].

The OKW ran military operations on the Western front, in [[North Africa]], and in [[Italy]]. In the west, operations were further split between the OKW and ''[[Oberbefehlshaber West]]'' (OBW, Commander in Chief West), who was ''Generalfeldmarschall'' [[Gerd von Rundstedt]] (succeeded by Field Marshal [[Günther von Kluge]]).

There was even more fragmentation since the Kriegsmarine and Luftwaffe operations had their own commands (''[[Oberkommando der Marine]]'' (OKM) and ''[[Oberkommando der Luftwaffe]]'' (OKL)) which, while theoretically subordinate, were largely independent from the OKW or the OBW.

During the entire period of the war, the OKW was led by Keitel, who reported directly to Hitler, from whom most operational orders actually originated as ''Oberster Befehlshaber der Wehrmacht'' (Supreme Commander of the Armed Forces). [[Albrecht von Hagen]], a member of the [[July 20 plot|failed assassination attempt]] on Hitler on 20 July 1944, was stationed here to be responsible for the courier service between military posts in Berlin and Hitler's secret military headquarters known as the [[Wolfsschanze|Wolf's Lair]].

== International Military Tribunal ==

During the [[Nuremberg Trials]], the OKW was indicted but acquitted of being a criminal organization like the [[Waffen-SS]]. [[Wilhelm Keitel]] and  [[Alfred Jodl]] were convicted and sentenced to [[Hanging|death by hanging]]. Jodl was posthumously acquitted of the main charges against him in 1952, six years after the sentence was carried out.

During the subsequent [[High Command Trial]] in 1947/48, several OKW members were charged with [[war crime]]s, especially for the [[Commissar Order]] to shoot [[Red Army]] political commissars in German-occupied countries, the killing of [[Prisoner-of-war|POW]]s and participation in the [[Holocaust]]. Eleven defendants received prison sentences ranging from three years including time served to lifetime imprisonment, two were acquitted on all counts, and one committed suicide during the trial.

== Notes and references ==
{{reflist}}

== Further reading ==
* Megargee, G.P. &quot;Triumph of the Null: Structure and Conflict in the Command of German Land Forces, 1939-1945,&quot; ''War in History'' (1997) 4#1 pp 60–80, online in EBSCO.
*Seaton, A. ''The German Army, 1939–1945'' (St. Martin’s Press, 1982)
* Stone, David. ''Twilight of the Gods: The Decline and Fall of the German General Staff in World War II'' (2011). 
* Wilt, A. ''War from the Top: German and British Decision Making During World War II'' (Indiana U. Press, 1990)

==External links==
*[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bLJol2jcOIE &quot;Not the Stuff of Legend: The German High Command in World War II&quot;] – lecture by Dr. [[Geoffrey P. Megargee|Geoffrey Megargee]], author of ''Inside Hitler's High Command'', available at the official YouTube channel [[U.S. Army Heritage and Education Center]]

{{Authority control}}

[[Category:Military units and formations established in 1938]]
[[Category:Wehrmacht]]
[[Category:Nazi Germany]]
[[Category:German High Command during World War II]]</text>
      <sha1>l022bi430pgzgg3xc68nxznkcshzzl6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
