<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Osan Air Base</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1648794</id>
    <revision>
      <id>746116674</id>
      <parentid>734676677</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-25T10:15:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* In fiction and literature */http&amp;rarr;https for [[Google Books]] and [[Google News]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="32645">{{Infobox military structure
|name=Osan Air Base
|ensign=[[File:Pacific Air Forces.png|60px]]
|partof=[[Pacific Air Forces]] (PACAF)
|location=  [[Pyeongtaek]], [[Gyeonggi Province]], [[South Korea]]
|coordinates={{Coord|37|05|26|N|127|01|47|E|name=Osan AB}}  
|image=  [[File:Osan Air Base 51 FW F-16 A-10 Flyby.jpg|border|300px]]
|caption=  American 51st Fighter Wing's [[F-16C Fighting Falcon]]s and [[A-10A Thunderbolt II]]s flying over Osan Air Base in June 2009.
|pushpin_map= South Korea
|pushpin_label=Osan AB
|pushpin_mark=Airplane_silhouette.svg
|latNS=N|latd=37|latm=05|lats=26
|longEW=E|longd=127|longm=01|longs=47
|pushpin_mapsize=230
|pushpin_map_caption=Location of Osan Air Base, South Korea
|type=
|code=
|built=1952
|builder=
|materials=
|height=
|used=1952–present
|demolished=
|condition=
|ownership= {{flag|United States of America}}
|controlledby= {{air force|USA}}&lt;br /&gt;[[File:Roundel of the Republic of Korea Air Force.svg|24px]] [[Republic of Korea Air Force|ROK Air Force]]
|garrison=   [[File:51st Fighter Wing.png|60px]]&lt;br /&gt;[[51st Fighter Wing]] (USAF)
|commanders=
|occupants=
|battles=
|events=
}}
{{Infobox airport
| name = Airfield information
| IATA = OSN
| ICAO = RKSO
| elevation-f = 40
| elevation-m = 12
| website = [http://www.osan.af.mil/ www.osan.af.mil]
| r1-number = 09/27
| r1-length-m = 2,744
| r1-length-f = 9,004
| r1-surface = Concrete
| footnotes = Source: [[DAFIF]]&lt;ref name=&quot;WAD&quot;&gt;[http://www.worldaerodata.com/wad.cgi?airport=RKSO Airport information for RKSO] from [[DAFIF]] (effective October 2006)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;GCM&quot;&gt;{{GCM|OSN|source=DAFIF}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
[[File:Osanab-aerial.jpg|thumb|Osan AB, South Korea, 2007]]

'''Osan Air Base''' ('''K-55'''; {{lang-ko|오산공군기지}}; [[Hanja]]: {{lang|ko|烏山空軍基地}}), is a [[United States Air Force base]]  located near [[Songtan Station]] in the county of [[Pyeongtaek]], [[South Korea]], {{convert|64|km|abbr=on}} south of [[Seoul]]. Despite its name, Osan AB is not within [[Osan]] City, which is {{convert|7.5|km|abbr=on}} to the north. The base is the home of the [[Pacific Air Forces]]' [[51st Fighter Wing]], and a number of tenant units, including the headquarters for [[Seventh Air Force]]. The base is also the headquarters of the [[Republic of Korea Air Force|ROK Air Force]] Operations Command.  Osan Air Base is also the departure and arrival point for U.S. government-contracted &quot;[[Patriot Express]]&quot; flights bringing service members and their family members to South Korea from [[Seattle–Tacoma International Airport|Seattle-Tacoma International Airport]] in the [[U.S. state]] of [[Washington (state)|Washington]], [[Misawa Air Base]] and [[Yokota Air Base]] in [[Japan]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usfk.mil/usfk/hot-topic.patriot.express.470|work=United States Forces Korea|title=Patriot Express}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As the most forward deployed permanently based wing in the Air Force, and equipped with A-10 Thunderbolt IIs and F-16 Fighting Falcons, the 51st Fighter Wing is charged with executing combat operations, receiving follow-on forces and defending the base from attack. As the air component to [[United States Forces Korea]] and Combined Forces Command, 7th Air Force provides the command and control structures and personnel necessary to deliver precise, persistent, combined air and space power in defense of the [[Republic of Korea]].

Osan Air Base is one of two major U.S. Air Force installations operated by U.S. Forces Korea, the other being [[Kunsan Air Base]].

== Units ==
Major units at Osan Air Base are:
*[[United States Air Force]]
** [[51st Fighter Wing]]
*** 51st Operations Group (Tail Code: OS)
**** [[25th Fighter Squadron]] (25 FS) (OA-10)
**** [[36th Fighter Squadron]] (36 FS) (F-16C/D)
**** [[51st Operations Support Squadron (OSS)]]
*** 51st Mission Support Group
**** [[51st Logistics Readiness Squadron (LRS)]]
**** [[51st Security Forces Squadron (SFS)]]
**** [[51st Force Support Squadron (FSS)]]
**** [[51st Communications Squadron (CS)]]
**** [[51st Civil Engineer Squadron (CES)]]
*** 51st Maintenance Group
**** [[51st Maintenance Operations Squadron (MOS)]]
**** [[51st Maintenance Squadron (MXS)]]
**** [[51st Aircraft Maintenance Squadron (AMXS)]]
**** [[51st Munitions Squadron (MUNS)]]  
*** 51st Medical Group 
**** [[51st Medical Support Squadron (MDSS)]] 
**** [[51st Aerospace Medicine Squadron (AMDS)]]
**** [[51st Medical Operations Squadron (MDOS)]]
**** [[51st Dental Squadron (DS)]]
**** [[51st Bioenvironmental Engineering (BE)]]
** 7th Air Force
** [[731st Air Mobility Squadron]]
** Detachment 1, 33d Rescue Squadron
** 3d Battlefield Coordination Detachment&lt;ref&gt;[http://8tharmy.korea.army.mil/3bcd/index.html The United States Army | 3rd BCD-K]. 8tharmy.korea.army.mil (2009-04-09). Retrieved on 2013-07-12.&lt;/ref&gt; 
** 607th Air and Space Operations Center
*** 621st Air Control Squadron (621 ACS) (Tac C2)
*** 607th Support Squadron
** 607th Air Support Operations Group
*** [[604th Air Support Operations Squadron]]
** [[607th Weather Squadron]]
** 607th Air and Space Communications Squadron
** [[5th Reconnaissance Squadron|5th Recon Squadron]]
** 694th Intelligence, Surveillance, and Reconnaissance Group
*[[United States Army]]
** 6th Battalion, [[52nd Air Defense Artillery Regiment (United States)|52nd Air Defense Artillery]] (Charlie and Delta Batteries)
** [[35th Air Defense Artillery Brigade (United States)|35th Air Defense Artillery Brigade]]
** US Army Contracting Command Korea
*[[Republic of Korea Air Force]]
**Air Force Operations Command ({{lang|ko|[[:ko:공군작전사령부|공군작전사령부]]}}) 
** Air Defense Artillery Command ({{lang|ko|[[:ko:공군방공유도탄사령부|공군방공유도탄사령부]]}}) 
**Air Force Northern Combat Command ({{lang|ko|[[:ko:공군북부전투사령부|공군북부전투사령부]]}}) 
** Air Defense &amp; Control Command ({{lang|ko|[[:ko:공군방공관제사령부|공군방공관제사령부]]}})
***1st Master Control and Reporting Center Group ({{lang|ko|제31중앙방공통제전대}})

== History ==
[[File:F-51-67thfbs-korea.jpg|thumb|North American F-51D-25-NT Mustangs of the 67th Fighter-Bomber Squadron (18th FBG). AF Serial No. 44-84916 and 44-75000 identifiable.]]
[[File:18fbg-f-86.jpg|thumb|North American F-86F-25-NH Sabre AF Serial No. 52-5371 of the 18th Fighter-Bomber Group, 1953. Aircraft marked as Wing Commander's.]]

=== Korean War ===
Osan Air Base is one of two major airfields operated by the U.S. Air Force in the Republic of Korea and the only base on the peninsula entirely planned and built from scratch by Aviation Engineers (SCARWAF) units attached to the U.S. Air Force during the [[Korean War]].

Osan AB also was the site of the &quot;Battle of Bayonet Hill&quot; on 7 February 1951, on and around Hill 180 where the Air Component Command's Hardened Theater Air Control Center (HTACC) and the headquarters of the 51st Fighter Wing are currently located. The battle took place during the U.S. Eighth Army's [[Operation Thunderbolt (1951)|Operation Thunderbolt]]. Captain [[Lewis Millet]] led a bayonet charge of his soldiers of Company E, 27th Infantry Regiment, 25th Infantry Division up the hill against an unknown number of Chinese Communist Forces (CCF) ensconced on its crest. &quot;Easy&quot; Company routed the CCF, and Captain Millett received the [[Medal of Honor]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Ham IV |first=Walter T. |title=Battle of Hill 180 remembered on 60th anniversary |url=http://www.usfk.mil/usfk/(A(GwMzqRwXzAEkAAAAODM2NDg0N2EtODZjYS00NzgwLWE4MzctNThhNGE1MWMzNWVkTLZou97PY9LKShcF7_woodZpAJM1)S(u2e0xb55yruj5f55w1k0l2rb))/news.battle.of.hill.180.remembered.on.60th.anniversary.printview.748 |work=USFK General News |publisher=Eighth Army Public Affairs |accessdate=January 30, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Subsequent to the battle, the CCF were driven back north of the 38th parallel, and resulted in the return of [[Fifth Air Force]] tactical fighter units to peninsula. Aviation engineers, meanwhile, surveyed locations in the ROK to build an air base capable of supporting jet fighters. They decided upon the area southwest of Osan-Ni. Established in November 1951, the base originally was named Osan-Ni AB (and still referred to by its &quot;K-55&quot; airfield designation from the Korean War). The name &quot;Osan-Ni&quot; was chosen for practical reasons – it was the only village shown on most military maps of the time, and it was easy to pronounce.

The 839th Aviation Engineer Battalion began construction of base support facilities and infrastructure early in 1952. On July 9, 1952, the 839th, joined by the 840th and 841st Engineer battalions (Reserve engineer units called up for active duty, the 840th from Tennessee and the 841st from Florida), started work to lay the airfield's runway, taxiway and parking ramps. (These units were under the 934th Engineer Aviation Group, which was under the 417th Engineer Aviation Brigade, which was under the 5th Air Force). Monsoon rains, though, impeded initial efforts to fill the rice paddies and begin airfield construction. The delay forced engineers to work 24 hours a day, seven days a week beginning in August. Three engineer aviation battalions were assigned the task of building Osan; the 839th, 840th, and 841st EABs. They completed laying a 9,000-foot, {{convert|8|in|mm|adj=mid|-thick}} concrete runway in {{frac|2|1|2}} months. With the taxiway also completed, and parking ramps nearing completion, the 18th Fighter-Bomber Wing and one of its F-51 combat squadrons arrived on December 26, 1952. With the wing's other two squadrons arriving shortly thereafter, the wing converted to the F-86F.

In February 1953, the 18th FBW began flying air superiority missions from Osan-Ni AB which continued through the remainder of the Korean War.

=== Cold War ===
With the Armistice Agreement signed on July 27, 1953, the 18th FBW remained at Osan-Ni AB for defensive purposes until November 1954. Meanwhile, plans called for HQ Fifth Air Force (Advance) to move from [[Seoul National University]] to [[Yongsan Garrison]] in Seoul. This plan was changed, and in January 1954, the headquarters relocated to Osan-Ni AB, and established the base as the major hub of operations for U.S. air power in the ROK.

As the Armistice took hold, the U.S. Air Force redeployed all but one tactical fighter wing from the peninsula, and in November 1954, after Fifth Air Force relocated to [[Tokyo]], the 314th Air Division replaced its former advanced headquarters at Osan-Ni AB. The 58th Fighter-Bomber Wing moved from Taegu AB to Osan-Ni AB in March 1955, and became the only permanently assigned tactical fighter wing on the peninsula. On September 18, 1956, the base was redesignated Osan AB, its current name.

In July 1958, the U.S. Air Force inactivated the 58th Fighter-Bomber Wing. At this time, the Eisenhower Administration promulgated a nuclear deterrence strategy. Osan AB thus became the main base of operations for air-to-ground [[MGM-1 Matador|Matador tactical missiles]] when the [[310th Fighter Squadron|310th Tactical Missile Squadron]] and 58th Support Squadron were activated under the 58th Tactical Missile Group.

Concurrently, Fifth Air Force complemented this strategy by instituting rotational deployments of fighter aircraft units to Osan and Kunsan ABs from its Far East bases and the U.S. to bolster the defense of the Republic of Korea as it steadily trained and equipped the ROK Air Force. Although the Matador missiles were relocated in 1962, fighter deployments continued throughout the 1960s.

Other than a major reconstruction of the runway in 1959, the base still retained its Korean War-vintage facilities and infrastructure. There was no money spent on improving the facilities. Besides the new focus was on [[Cuba]] with the [[Cuban Missile Crisis|Missile Crisis]] and Europe in the new Cold War flare up. Korea was forgotten. On base the barracks were still the corrugated iron barracks of the Korean War and the base simply stagnated with the 6314th Air Base Wing in charge of not only Osan, but also Kunsan as well.This condition changed modestly beginning in 1968.

Starting in September 1964, Osan AB was home to the [[Military Air Transport Service]] (MATS), 36th Air Rescue Service (ARS), Detachment 4. The unit flew the [[HH-43]]B Huskie which was dubbed &quot;Pedro.&quot; Two HH-43B Pedros were assigned to Osan AB – aircraft 60-251 and 60-252 as of September 64. Assigned under the [[Air Rescue Service]] (ARS) based in the Pacific Air Force (PACAF) region. The MATS, 36th ARS, Det 4 became Provisional Air Rescue Component (PARC), Det 9 on 25 July 1965 and remained with this designator until 8 January 1966.

MATS was redesignated as the [[Military Airlift Command]] (MAC) in 1969 and in December 1969, the designator changed to MAC, PARRC, Det 4. The unit designator of MAC, 41st ARRW (Air Rescue and Recovery Wing), Det 9 was also maintained from February 1969 through June 1970.

=== ''Pueblo'' crisis ===
The North Korean attack on the [[USS Pueblo (AGER-2)|USS ''Pueblo'']] and seizure of its crew on January 23, 1968, precipitated deployment of 1,000 Air Force personnel, on temporary duty status, to Osan AB in support of operation 'Palace Dog III'. Airmen stationed at bases in the US, and Asia (including Vietnam) began arriving on January 25, within 48 hours of the attack. Many found that they would have temporary quarters in Korean War vintage tents in below zero weather conditions without cold weather clothing. The developing crisis underscored the importance of the installation at Osan, and led to the infusion of funds for improving existing facilities and the construction of new structures including aircraft shelters and control tower. Security was upgraded in support of the increased tactical operations at the base. From January to March, over 6,500,000 pounds of cargo was shipped by rail to Osan. Conventional munitions transported in converted coal cars, arrived 24 hours a day. The build-up was massive.

On 22 March the 318th Fighter Interceptor Squadron deployed to Osan AB from [[McChord AFB]], [[Washington (U.S. state)|Washington]]. This marked the first time in history that [[Aerospace Defense Command]] (ADC) [[F-106]] fighter interceptors had flown to a critical overseas area, using in-flight refueling along with tactical air units.

Although the ''Pueblo'' crisis subsided with the crew's release in on December 23, 1968, fighter unit deployments occurred on a regular basis. On April 15, 1969, the North Koreans again triggered a period of tension when it shot down a U.S. Navy [[EC-121]] Warning Star flying in international airspace over the [[Sea of Japan]]. F-106s from the 95th Fighter Interceptor Squadron, 21st Air Division (later 20th Air Division) of [[Dover AFB]], [[Delaware]] deployed to Osan AB from 15 November 1969 – 1 May 1970. Attached to [[Fifth Air Force]] ADVON, 15 November 1969 – 1 May 1970.

The response by the U.S. resulted in another increase of fighter forces on the peninsula, and eventually set the stage for return of permanently assigned fighter units to the ROK.

=== Vietnam War ===
[[File:F-4-osan.jpg|thumb|Three 36th Fighter Squadron [[McDonnell Douglas]] F-4E-37-MC Phantoms in flight. AF Serial No. 68-0328 and 68-0365 identifiable.]]
Throughout this period, the U.S. Air Force was deeply committed to the [[Vietnam War]].

At Osan, the major USAF units were 6145th Air Force Advisory Group acting as a training/logistical support unit to the ROKAF; the 314th Air Division; and the 6314th Support Wing. The 611th Military Airlift Command Support Squadron (611th MASS) at Kimpo would later move to Osan.

However, as the U.S. withdrew incrementally from [[South Vietnam]] and [[Thailand]], Pacific Air Forces repositioned its force structure which led to substantial changes for the U.S. Air Force on the ROK. On March 15, 1971, the 3rd Tactical Fighter Wing was activated at Kunsan AB. At Osan AB, PACAF activated the 51st Air Base Wing to assume host-unit responsibilities at Osan AB on November 1, 1971. Two weeks later, on November 13, 1971, the 3rd TFW's 36th Tactical Fighter Squadron moved to Osan AB.

Total withdrawal of U.S. forces from South Vietnam by 1974 resulted in another important change for Osan AB. On September 30, 1974, the 51st ABW was redesignated as the 51st Composite Wing (Tactical), and assigned the 36th TFS with its F-4D/Es and 19th Tactical Air Support Squadron with its OV-10As.

=== 1970s/1980s ===
With Osan AB serving as the nucleus for more than 20 U.S. Air Force activities on the peninsula, it experienced a period of facility and infrastructure changes during the 1970s. Although many of the Korea-War vintage structures remained, new dormitories were built, and a new headquarters complex completed in 1974 for the 314th AD and 51st CW(T) replaced 71 Quonset huts that were destroyed by fire three years earlier. In 1979 and 1980, construction of on-base family housing and additional community-support facilities gave the base a sign of stability.

Establishment of the Combined Forces Command in 1978 further set the future of Osan AB. The evolving role of U.S. Air Force's CFC mission in the ROK led to activation of Headquarters Seventh Air Force on September 8, 1986. It replaced the 314th AD as the U.S. Air Force component command.

Construction on Osan AB during the 1980s was dictated largely by mission changes and enhancements, and the threat from North Korea. Introduction of the F-16 in 1988 led to construction of hardened aircraft shelters, a new on-base munitions storage area, and upgrades to unaccompanied personnel housing.

The presence of U-2 aircraft was classified until 1978, though the planes could be seen at takeoff and landing.  &quot;Black Cat&quot; was the name given to mechanics who worked on U-2's, which were called &quot;Black Birds.&quot;  The latter nickname may have been transferred from the SR-71.

=== Post Cold War ===
[[File:Osan A-10.jpg|thumb|An [[A-10 Thunderbolt II]] taxis into a hardened &quot;hot pit&quot; refueling shelter at Osan Air Base]]
While the face of Osan AB slowly changed in replacing its 40-year-old Korean War-vintage structures, the base experienced a lengthy period with little or no military construction program projects. However, other funding sources allowed base officials to add community-type facilities. Arrival of the 25th Fighter Squadron and its A/OA-10s in October 1993 and two [[MIM-104 Patriot]] batteries in May 1994 also necessitated some new construction. Other than these events, base officials primarily concentrated on improvements in facility protection due to the threat from North Korea's reliance on medium-range [[SCUD]] missiles. Annual runway repairs furthermore only attested to the aging of Osan AB as the base witnessed only modest changes in its structural appearance during the 1990s.

It was not until 1998 that HQ PACAF renewed emphasis on improving the base's support structure. Increasing infrastructure failures seriously detracted the 51st Fighter Wing from conducting its deterrence mission. HQ PACAF subsequently provided the base with funds under the &quot;Fix Korea Initiative.&quot;  More than $200 million was invested in upgrading or replacing the water, sewage and electrical distribution systems over the following six years. Additionally, mid- and long-range plans for the base foresaw a dramatic facelift of Osan AB that included new on-base family housing, new community-support facilities, and replacement of many industrial structures that supported the 51st FW mission.

[[File:U-2 taxies 2006-06-20 F-8409K-002.jpg|thumb|The improved [[Lockheed U-2|U-2S Dragon Lady]], Block 20, aircraft taxis to the runway at Osan Air Base]]
As the ROK's military grew and matured into a formidable force by the late 1990s, political and military leaders from both countries reexamined the role of U.S. forces based on the peninsula. A major change in U.S. strategic policy coinciding with the &quot;9-11&quot; terrorist attack on the Twin Towers in New York required a &quot;transformation&quot; of global U.S. military commitments and basing. The military had to adapt from a fixed, in-garrison-type force to a mobile, responsive force. For its part, U.S. Forces in Korea studied how technological advances in weaponry could mitigate a reduction in personnel while the ROK military forces carried out an increasing role to protect its sovereignty. The result of this effort led to the landmark agreement known as the Land Partnership Plan in 2002 and the Security Policy Initiative in 2003 between the U.S. and the ROK governments. These decisions reflected a realignment in the roles and missions of USFK that forecast a significant reshaping and growth at Osan AB through 2011. Currently, the 607th Combat Operations Squadron (COS), led by Lt Col Dale R. Addington, has been dissolved.

In December 2009, South Korea's [[JoongAng Daily]] newspaper reported that the [[RQ-170 Sentinel]] was to replace U-2's operating from Osan Air Base in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=U.S. to base new unmanned spy plane in Korea |url=http://joongangdaily.joins.com/article/view.asp?aid=2914210 |publisher=JoongAng Daily|date=19 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On December 1, 2014, a lockdown in the high school and middle school occurred as an active shooter drill went off.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title= Lockdown on U.S. military school in Osan, South Korea |url=http://abcnews.go.com/International/wireStory/us-base-skorea-lockdown-amid-shooting-report-27269724 |publisher=ABCNews |date=1 Dec 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On May 28, 2015, the United States Air Force says that as many as 22 people have been inadvertently exposed to the [[anthrax]] virus during a laboratory training exercise.[https://uk.news.yahoo.com/us-army-says-22-possibly-exposed-anthrax-korea-005404630.html#x8mTJaq]

===Major USAF units assigned===
* [[18th Wing|18th Fighter-Bomber Wing]] (December 1952 – November 1954)
* 30th Weather Squadron (January 1954 – May 1957)*
* [[Fifth Air Force]] (January – September 1954)
* [[314th Air Division]] (March 1955 – November 1978, April 1979 – September 1986)
* 335th Fighter-Bomber Squadron (February 1955)**
* 334th Fighter-Bomber Squadron (March 1955)**
* [[58th Special Operations Wing|58th Fighter-Bomber Wing]] (March 1955 – July 1958)
* [[58th Special Operations Wing|58th Tactical Missile Group]] (July 1958 – March 1962)
* [[51st Fighter Wing]] (November 1971–present)
* [[Seventh Air Force]] (September 1986–present)
* [[American Forces Network|Defense Media Agency-American Force Network Osan]] (September 1957–present)
:&lt;nowiki&gt;*&lt;/nowiki&gt; Detached from the 2143d Air Weather Wing based at Tageu AB (K-2), South Korea
:&lt;nowiki&gt;**&lt;/nowiki&gt; Detached from the [[4th Fighter Wing|4th Fighter-Bomber Wing]] based at Chitose AB, Japan

Kunsan has provided support for [[P-51|F-51D Mustang]], [[F-86 Sabre]], [[F-84 Thunderjet]], [[F-4 Phantom II]], [[F-106 Delta Dart]], [[OV-10 Bronco]], [[A-10 Thunderbolt II]], and [[F-16 Fighting Falcon]] operations.

== Amenities ==

===Life In Osan===
[[File:US Navy 050313-N-7027P-086 Joint Reception Personnel assigned to Osan Air Force Base, Korea, in-process Soldiers, Sailors, Marines and Airmen from various commands in preparation for Reception, Staging, Onward movement, and Int.jpg|thumb|right|240px|Joint Reception Personnel assigned to Osan Air Force Base, in preparation for  [[Foal Eagle|RSO&amp;I/Foal Eagle]].]]

Most U.S. military members assigned to Osan AB serve a 1-year unaccompanied tour. If they elect to participate in the [[Korea Area Incentive Program|Korea Assignment Incentive Program]], their tour is extended by one year, they receive a taxable bonus of $300 per month, but they lose the ability to have assignment preference due to a short tour and lose short tour credit. Roughly five percent of the military authorizations at Osan AB are designated as command-sponsored two-year accompanied tours, typically for senior ranking personnel and/or jobs which require a tour of longer than 12 months, due to military necessity. If an individual is placed in one they may bring their families at government expense. Housing on-base, even for command sponsored families, is still limited despite an aggressive family housing construction program. Those authorized to live off-base will receive an [[Basic Allowance for Housing#OHA|overseas housing allowance]]. There is an elementary school, named Osan American Elementary School; a middle school, named Osan Middle School as well as high school, known as Osan American High School. These schools are for command-sponsored children of military members. Contractors (even command sponsored) should be prepared to pay upwards of $20,000 a year for this privilege.

Some families choose to come without command sponsorship; these family members may use the facilities (including schools) on a space available basis.  If family members come, they will be able to receive the local OHA rate, whether or not the servicemember makes the list to move off base and regardless of rank.  The government will not pay for their transportation to Korea, in most cases.

Under normal circumstances, unaccompanied airmen live in one of the many [[barracks|dormitories]] on-base and eat in the dining facility, thereby receiving a meal deduction from their basic allowance for subsistence. Airmen receive [[United States Military Pay|cost of living adjustments (COLA)]] if living off base, and partial COLA if living in the dorms, which varies by rank, living situation, and dependents. [[Pay Grade|E-7s]] and above may live off-base if senior NCO or officer dormitory space is not available; in some cases this has also been extended to lower ranking NCOs, depending on dormitory occupancy availability and policies in place at the time. Unless command sponsored, [[Pay Grade|E-6s]] and below may not have personal motor vehicles. There are many taxis both on and off-base to accommodate them; additionally, the compact nature of Osan AB lends itself to walking and bicycling.

For single and unaccompanied airmen, one of the attractions of a one-year assignment to Osan AB is the opportunity to follow their Osan tour with an assignment at the base of their choice, called a &quot;follow-on assignment.&quot; If a position is open at the desired location, unaccompanied airmen in Korea (or other unaccompanied locations) have priority over other airmen in filling that position. This benefit is not available to those serving accompanied tours with family, or to those who extend their tours; those airmen must use the normal assignment selection process for their next assignment.

There are many bars and clubs off base, mostly in the Shinjang-dong district and many base members spend much leisure time at them. If the bars do not abide by certain standards, the Osan Military Beverage Control Board may place them off limits to military members. This is usually done when the bar is involved in certain unlawful activities, particularly prostitution.  Town Patrol,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5SJ6-hUiVpE Osan's Town Patrol - Part 1 - Mission ] on [[YouTube]]&lt;/ref&gt; a section of the 51st Security Forces Squadron, patrols the area immediately outside the base in cooperation with the [[Law enforcement in South Korea|Korean National Police]], to ensure the safety of military members and enforce military law and regulations upon U.S. military members. On July 5, 2012, however, the Town Patrol arouse controversy by handcuffing three Pyeongtaek citizens in a dispute over illegal parking near by the base.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Osan incident shows rules for USFK town patrols are not clear-cut |url=http://www.stripes.com/news/pacific/korea/osan-incident-shows-rules-for-usfk-town-patrols-are-not-clear-cut-1.185414 |publisher=[[Stars and Stripes (newspaper)|Stars and Stripes]]|date=11 August 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; After inciting protests from civic groups, three members of the Osan Town Patrol were suspended from their duties, [[James D. Thurman|Gen. James D. Thurman]], Commander of USFK, made a public apology for the incident.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=U.S. General Apologizes for Dispute in Seoul |url=http://www.nytimes.com/2012/07/09/world/asia/us-commander-apologizes-over-handcuffing-of-koreans.html?_r=0 |publisher=The New York Times|date=8 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Facilities===
All facilities accept [[United States dollar|US dollars]] and some accept [[South Korean won]]; AAFES BX/Shoppettes and the [[Defense Commissary Agency|DECA]] [[Commissary]] are the two notable exceptions that will only accept US dollars. With the exception of the [[US Post Office]], pennies (1 cent pieces) are not circulated. All transactions are rounded up or down to the nearest nickel when giving change.
{{Col-begin}}
{{Col-break}}
* [[Base Exchange]] (BX)
* Shopette
* Commissary
* Dining facilities
:Ginko Tree
:Pacific House (Pac House)
* Restaurants and other establishments
:[[Chili's]]
:Checkertails/Bada Bing Pizza (Formerly called OHOP)
:[[Burger King]] (Relocated to behind BX)
:Oriental House
:[[Popeye's Chicken &amp; Biscuits|Popeye's Chicken]] (Located in the same building as Burger King)

In the BX Mall
:[[Taco Bell]]
:[[Subway (restaurant)|Subway]]
:[[Baskin-Robbins]]
:[[Pizza Hut]]
:[[Charley's]]
:[[Arby's]]
:[[Starbucks]]
:[[Manchu Wok]]

{{Col-break}}
At the Clubs (There are two enlisted clubs:&lt;br /&gt;The [[Enlisted]] Club and the [[Mustang (military officer)|Mustang]] Club; there is one Officers Club)
:The End Zone
:Flying M Steak House
:Bella Panini's
:Challenger Club
:Black Cat Lounge
* Recreation Facilities
:Gym (open 24 hours)
:Mustang Pool (indoor)
:Defender Pool (outdoor – seasonal)
:[[Paintball]] Court (small)
:Golf Course
:MiG Alley Bowling Alley (also has a restaurant)
:Movie Theater
* [[Skatepark]] (now a roller hockey rink)
* Other facilities
:Library
:McPherson Community Center
{{Col-end}}

==In fiction and literature==
Osan Air Base is also prominently featured in the 2011 military thriller ''[[Thunder in the Morning Calm (novel)|Thunder in the Morning Calm]]'' by [[Don Brown (author)|Don Brown]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=PoU7atsxneYC&amp;pg=PT43&amp;lpg=PT43&amp;dq=%22osan+air+base%22 Reference to Osan Air Base] in the novel ''[[Thunder in the Morning Calm (novel)|Thunder in the Morning Calm]]''.&lt;/ref&gt; The Osan AB is also mentioned in [[The Interview (2014 film)]].

==See also==
{{portal | Military of the United States | United States Air Force}}
* [[Kunsan Air Base]]
* [[Camp Carroll]]
* [[Camp Humphreys]]
* [[Camp Red Cloud]]
* [[USAG Yongsan]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}
{{Refbegin}}
* {{Air Force Historical Research Agency}}
* Some of the text in this article was taken from pages on the [http://www.osan.af.mil Osan Air Base website], which as a work of the U.S. Government is presumed to be a [[public domain resource]].  That information was supplemented by:
* Endicott, Judy G. (1999) Active Air Force wings as of 1 October 1995; USAF active flying, space, and missile squadrons as of 1 October 1995. Maxwell AFB, Alabama: Office of Air Force History. CD-ROM.
* Fletcher, Harry R. (1989) Air Force Bases Volume II, Active Air Force Bases outside the United States of America on 17 September 1982. Maxwell AFB, Alabama: Office of Air Force History. ISBN 0-912799-53-6
* Milne, Duncan (1968) First hand account of conditions at Osan AFB during Pueblo incident, January 1968. Official Military Records.
* Maurer, Maurer (1983). Air Force Combat Units Of World War II. Maxwell AFB, Alabama: Office of Air Force History. ISBN 0-89201-092-4.
* Ravenstein, Charles A. (1984). Air Force Combat Wings Lineage and Honors Histories 1947–1977. Maxwell AFB, Alabama: Office of Air Force History. ISBN 0-912799-12-9.
* Rogers, Brian (2005). United States Air Force Unit Designations Since 1978. Hinkley, England: Midland Publications. ISBN 1-85780-197-0.
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20090130025918/http://home.att.net/~jbaugher/usafserials.html USAAS-USAAC-USAAF-USAF Aircraft Serial Numbers – 1908 to Present]
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Osan Air Base}}
* [http://www.osan.af.mil/ Osan Air Base], official website
* [http://www.usfk.mil/ US Forces Korea], official website
* [http://www.gisearch.com/search/i:osan-ab-80/ Osan AB Vets], searchable database of Osan Air Base vets at GI Search
* {{NWS-current|RKSO}}
* {{ASN|OSN}}

{{USAF Pacific Air Forces}}
{{USAF Korea}}
{{Airports in South Korea}}

[[Category:Airports in South Korea]]
[[Category:Airports established in 1952]]
[[Category:Bases of the United States Air Force in South Korea]]
[[Category:Buildings and structures in Gyeonggi Province]]
[[Category:Korean War air bases]]
[[Category:Pyeongtaek]]</text>
      <sha1>266hs93cek52h4yi61x03qc8mmpxyc7</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
