<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Pilatus PC-21</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>921260</id>
    <revision>
      <id>744131607</id>
      <parentid>738322453</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-13T09:12:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Marigold100</username>
        <id>18920676</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Para1, &quot;low-wing&quot; Development para 2, &quot;only much&quot; &quot;50%&quot; para 3, &quot;lifespan&quot; &quot;frontline&quot; deleted &quot;a&quot; para 4, &quot;rollout&quot; Design para 1, &quot;by&quot; para 2, &quot;allround&quot; para 3, &quot;only by&quot; SUI, &quot;eight&quot;</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="28102">&lt;!-- This article is a part of [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft]]. Please see [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft/page content]] for recommended layout. --&gt;
{|{{Infobox Aircraft Begin
|name= PC-21
|image= pilatus pc-21 hb-hzc lands arp.jpg
|caption= The PC-21 demonstrator lands at [[RIAT]] 2008, [[England]].
}}{{Infobox Aircraft Type
|type= Advanced [[Trainer aircraft]]
|manufacturer= [[Pilatus Aircraft]]
|designer= Pilatus Aircraft
|first flight= 1 July 2002
|introduced= April 2008
|retired=
|status=Active service
|primary user= [[Swiss Air Force]]
|more users= [[Republic of Singapore Air Force]] &lt;br/&gt; [[United Arab Emirates Air Force]] &lt;br/&gt; [[Royal Saudi Air Force]] &lt;!-- Only THREE &quot;more users&quot; here. Separate users with &lt;br&gt;. --&gt;
|produced= 2002–present
|number built= 131+
|unit cost=
|variants with their own articles= 
}}
|}

The '''Pilatus PC-21''' is a single-[[turboprop]], low-wing swept monoplane advanced [[Trainer (aircraft)|trainer]] with a stepped tandem cockpit manufactured by [[Pilatus Aircraft]] of [[Switzerland]].

==Development==
In November 1997, Pilatus flew a modified [[Pilatus PC-7|PC-7 Mk.II]] in order to test improvements for a prospective next generation turboprop trainer. As a result of these tests, Pilatus elected to fund the development of a new training system in November 1998; development of the new trainer, designated as the ''PC-21'', formally started in January 1999.&lt;ref name = &quot;hist 2006&quot;/&gt; The PC-21 would be developed and certified as a completely new training system, aimed at meeting future military customers' specifications in terms of capability and life-cycle costs for the next three decades.&lt;ref name=spec/&gt;

A key aim for the PC-21 was to allow jet aircraft pilots to perform the majority of the training using the type, converting  to jet-powered types only much later than typical contemporary practice, allowing operators to make substantial savings; in order to achieve this aim, the new trainer was required to have an expanded performance envelope in terms of [[aerodynamic]]s, cockpit equipment, flexibility, and ease of maintenance.&lt;ref name = &quot;hist 2006&quot;&gt;Hoyle, Craig. [https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/switzerland-special-pilatus-the-success-story-222274/ &quot;Switzerland special: Pilatus the success story.&quot;] ''Flight International'', 17 March 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;next gen trainer&quot;&gt;[http://www.pilatus-aircraft.com/#39 &quot;The NextGen Trainer.&quot;] ''Pilatus Aircraft'', Retrieved: 22 March 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/pc-21-set-to-revolutionise-training-for-air-forces-151905/ &quot;PC-21 set to revolutionise training for air forces.&quot;] ''Flight International'', 22 July 2002.&lt;/ref&gt; In May 2002, Pilatus announced that it aimed for the PC-21 to capture 50 % of the global trainer aircraft market between 2005 and 2030.&lt;ref name = &quot;pre-pro&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;50 market&quot;&gt;Wastnage, Justin. [https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/pilatus-aims-for-half-of-trainer-sales-with-pc-21-147384/ &quot;Pilatus aims for half of trainer sales with PC-21.&quot;] ''Flight International'', 7 May 2002.&lt;/ref&gt;

From the start of the aircraft's development, Pilatus aimed for the type to have a predictable cost profile over its full lifespan. To meet this goal, the firm chose to incorporate modern materials, an innovative design concept, and full-scale [[fatigue (material)|fatigue]] analysis.&lt;ref name = &quot;pil brouch&quot;/&gt; Additionally, accompanying the aircraft itself are integrated training systems to meet the pilot's needs; the full package offered by Pilatus includes synthetic training devices, computer-based training, and classroom instruction.&lt;ref name = &quot;next gen trainer&quot;/&gt; As a result of greater training effectiveness, pilots can graduate with fewer total training hours, reaching the frontline faster and at lower cost.&lt;ref name = &quot;pil brouch&quot;/&gt; In addition to pilots, various prospective aircrew, such as navigators, weapons officers, and electronic warfare operators, can be trained using the type's embedded simulation/emulation system.&lt;ref name = &quot;pil brouch&quot;/&gt;

On 30 April 2002, the rollout of the first PC-21 prototype was performed at Pilatus' factory in Stans, [[Switzerland]]; this aircraft conducted its first flight on 1 July of the same year.&lt;ref name = &quot;first proto fly&quot;&gt;[https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/pilatus-flies-pc-21-and-aims-for-certification-in-20-150856/ &quot;Pilatus flies PC-21 and aims for certification in 2004.&quot;] ''Flight International'', 9 July 2002.&lt;/ref&gt; In May 2003, Pilatus management formally green-lit the program to proceed to full development.&lt;ref name = &quot;pen simul&quot;/&gt; On 7 June 2004, a second PC-21 prototype, the construction of which having been delayed to incorporate improvements learnt from assembling the first, made its maiden flight.&lt;ref name = &quot;first proto fly&quot;/&gt; In December 2004, Switzerland's [[Federal Office for Civil Aviation of Switzerland|Federal Office for Civil Aviation]] granted [[type certificate|type certification]] for the PC-21; civil certification was attained despite it being a military aircraft as this permitted civil maintenance procedures to be used as well as allowing the aircraft to be supplied under private finance arrangements.&lt;ref name = &quot;pil brouch&quot;/&gt; Individual Swiss military certification for equipment such as ejection seats has been applied as necessary.&lt;ref name = &quot;flight test int&quot;&gt;Collins, Peter. [https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/flight-test-pilatus-pc-21-fast-learner-319516/ &quot;FLIGHT TEST: Pilatus PC-21 – Fast learner.&quot;] ''Flight International'', 2 December 2008.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 13 January 2005, the second of the two development aircraft crashed in [[Buochs]], Switzerland while conducting an aerobatic training flight; the accident resulted in the death of the pilot as well as injuring another person on the ground.&lt;ref&gt;Wastnage, Justin. [https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/test-pilot-killed-in-pc-21-accident-192584/ &quot;Test pilot killed in PC-21 accident.&quot;] ''Flight International'', 18 January 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; In response to the incident, all PC-21 prototypes were grounded until 1 February 2005, by which point Swiss authorities had established that there was no sign of technical malfunction.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/pc-21-grounding-lifted-after-crash-193289/ &quot;PC-21 grounding lifted after crash.&quot;] ''Flight International'', 1 February 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; In August 2006, it was announced that crash investigators had concluded that pilot error had been to blame for the accident in January 2005.&lt;ref&gt;Wastnage, Justin. [https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/january-2005-crash-of-prototype-pilatus-pc-21-attrib-208678/ &quot;January 2005 crash of prototype Pilatus PC-21 attributed to pilot error in official crash report.&quot;] ''Flight International'', 25 August 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; In late August 2005, the first pre-series production PC-21 performed its maiden flight.&lt;ref name = &quot;pre-pro&quot;&gt;[https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/swiss-air-force-poised-to-acquire-six-pc-21s-201506/ &quot;Swiss air force poised to acquire six PC-21s.&quot;] ''Flight International'', 13 September 2005.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Design==
[[File:Frola ? 16983 1243165361 (5719962279).jpg|thumb|A PC-21 on static display, 2009]]
The Pilatus PC-21 is an advanced single-engine trainer aircraft; it is often referred to by Pilatus as being the &quot;Twenty-first Century Trainer&quot;.&lt;ref name=spec/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;next gen trainer&quot;/&gt; The type can be applied for various training capacities, including basic flying training, advanced flight training, full mission management training, and embedded simulation/emulation. In order to perform these functions, the aircraft possesses a powerful, flexible, and cost-effective integrated training system; providing sufficient ease of use for inexperienced pilots while posing greater challenge to advanced pilots.&lt;ref name = &quot;pil brouch&quot;/&gt; According to Pilatus, upon product launch, the PC-21 possessed &quot;superior aerodynamic performance when compared with any other turboprop trainer on the market&quot;.&lt;ref name=spec/&gt;

The aircraft features a [[tandem]]-seating arrangement (student in-front/instructor behind) in a [[bird strike]]-resistant glass [[Aircraft canopy|canopy]] with allround vision. The cabin, which is pressurized, is equipped with an [[Oxygen concentrator#Military uses|On-Board Oxygen Generation System]] (OBOGS), [[air conditioning]], and [[Martin-Baker]] CH16C [[Ejection seat#Zero-zero ejection seat|Zero-Zero ejector seats]].&lt;ref name=spec/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;pil brouch&quot;&gt;[http://www.pilatus-aircraft.com/00-def/main/scripts/ckfinder/userfiles/files/Downloads/Brochures/Pilatus%20Aircraft%20Ltd%20-%20PC-21%20Brochure.pdf &quot;PC-21: 21st Century Training for 21st Century Air Forces.&quot;] ''Pilatus Aircraft'', Retrieved: 23 March 2016.&lt;/ref&gt; The flight controls, which are fully balanced and harmonized, are optimized for easy of operation and overall effectiveness.&lt;ref name = &quot;pil brouch&quot;/&gt; An anti-[[g-force|g]] system is also present in order to minimize the effects of high g-forces experienced during tactical training and aerobatic maneuvers. Pilots are able to spend a greater amount of time concentrating on the aircraft's external situation and upon mission data inputs due to an ergonomic design approach, ease-of-use controls, and clear visual/system data displays.&lt;ref name = &quot;pil brouch&quot;/&gt; In addition, a full [[autopilot]] and civil flight management system are also present.&lt;ref name = &quot;flight test int&quot;/&gt;

The PC-21 is powered by a single 1,600 [[Horsepower#Shaft horsepower .28shp.29|shaft horse power]] [[Pratt &amp; Whitney Canada PT6|Pratt &amp; Whitney Canada PT6A-68B]] [[turboprop]] engine, which drives a five-bladed [[graphite]] [[Hartzell]] [[scimitar propeller]] on the aircraft's nose;&lt;ref name=spec/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;pil brouch&quot;/&gt; it has been claimed by Pilatus that the PC-21 possesses speed and climb rates previously normally performed only by jet-powered aircraft.&lt;ref name = &quot;pil data&quot;/&gt; It is also fitted with a high-speed profile wing, rated for maneuvers up to 8 [[g-force|g]], complete with [[hydraulic|hyraulically]]-assisted [[aileron]]s and [[Spoiler (aeronautics)|spoilers]] which enable the execution of fighter-like rates of roll and other maneuvers.&lt;ref name=spec/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;pil data&quot;/&gt; In order to make the aircraft easy to fly at low speeds, crucial to the advanced trainer role, the PC-21 is furnished with a digital power management system and the [[tailplane|horizontal stabilizer]] is equipped with an automatic [[Aircraft principal axes#Vertical axis .28yaw.29|yaw]] compensator/suppression system to compensate for engine power and speed changes.&lt;ref name=spec/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;pil brouch&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;pil data&quot;&gt;[http://www.pilatus-aircraft.com/#40 &quot;Aircraft Data.&quot;] ''Pilatus Aircraft'', Retrieved: 22 March 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:PC-21 (5089438327).jpg|thumb|left|Underside of a PC-21 in-flight]]

A key feature of the PC-21 is the embedded simulation and training suite, which provides cross-platform cockpit emulation, weapons simulation, stores management system, simulated radar and [[electronic warfare]], a tactical situation display, and [[data link]] functionality.&lt;ref name = &quot;pil brouch&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;pen simul&quot;&gt;Penny, Stewart. [https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/pilatus-unveils-simulation-system-for-pc-21-trainer-166282/ &quot;Pilatus unveils simulation system for PC-21 trainer.&quot;] ''Flight International'', 3 June 2003.&lt;/ref&gt; Key to this is the Mission Support System (MSS), which comprises the Mission Planning System (MPS) and Mission Debriefing System (MBS); data can be loaded and unloaded from these, which is compatible with ground-based stations for pre-flight configuration or post-mission analysis.&lt;ref name = &quot;pil brouch&quot;/&gt; The integrated mission computer is of an [[open architecture]], allowing for third-party modifications and upgrades to take place; software can also be customized to conform to customer preferences.&lt;ref name = &quot;pil brouch&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hoyle, Craig. [https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/pilatus-to-adapt-pc-21-210564/ &quot;Pilatus to adapt PC-21.&quot;] ''Flight International'', 14 November 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Critical and non-critical software are also deliberately separated.&lt;ref name=spec/&gt;

The cockpit of the PC-21 features a high level of systems integration and conforms to modern avionics standards. The systems of the forward and rear cockpits can be 'de-coupled' between the student and instructor; the instructor may exercise real-time manipulation of the student's displays, sensor performance, and system modes such as to create synthetic air-to-air radar targets, artificial non-safety critical system failures, and controlled data degradation.&lt;ref name = &quot;pil brouch&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;pil cockpit&quot;/&gt; The aircraft's fully digital [[glass cockpit]] features three large colour [[liquid crystal display]]s (LCD), one performing as the primary flight display (PFD) and two multi-function displays (MFDs) for system/mission management, in addition to CMC Electronics-provided [[head-up display]]s (HUD) for both the pilot and instructor.&lt;ref name = &quot;pil brouch&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/integrated-cockpit-is-pillar-of-new-product-strategy-199539/ &quot;Integrated cockpit is pillar of new product strategy.&quot;] ''Flight International'', 15 June 2005.&lt;/ref&gt; The trim gauge is the only analogue dial in the cockpit.&lt;ref name = &quot;50 market&quot;/&gt; For control simplicity, a [[Hands on Throttle and Stick]] (HOTAS) control philosophy has been followed. Both the display and control systems present also resemble their counterparts used upon modern front-line combat aircraft for greater realism during training; and can be further customized in order to be more representative of specific combat aircraft.&lt;ref name = &quot;flight test int&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;pil cockpit&quot;&gt;[http://www.pilatus-aircraft.com/#41 &quot;A Cockpit for Maximum Training Value.&quot;] ''Pilatus Aircraft'', Retrieved: 22 March 2016.&lt;/ref&gt; The multi-sensor navigation system is capable of operating under a military tactical mode as well as a civil navigation mode.&lt;ref name = &quot;pil brouch&quot;/&gt;

==Operational history==
[[File:Pilatus PC-21, Pilatus AN1852215.jpg|thumb|A PC-21 landing at [[RAF Fairford]], [[Gloucestershire]], [[England]], 2010]]
In the Armament Program 2006, the [[Federal Assembly (Switzerland)|Swiss Parliament]] approved an initial purchase of the PC-21 for the [[Swiss Air Force]]. By April 2008, four PC-21 have been taken over by the Swiss Air Force following the passing of acceptance trials, and flight operations were set to start in July that year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite press release| url=http://www.news.admin.ch/message/index.html?lang=en&amp;msg-id=18550 |title= Acceptance of the first four Pilatus PC-21 by armasuisse |publisher=Swiss Federation |accessdate=29 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt; In December 2010, the Swiss Air Force placed an order for another two aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.defpro.com/news/details/20711/|title=Pilatus Wins PC-21 Follow-up Order From the Swiss Air Force|last=Stans|date=17 December 2010|publisher=Pilatus Aircraft|accessdate=22 June 2013|archiveurl=http://archive.is/viMH|archivedate=29 July 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Trimble, Stephen. [https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/pilatus-receives-follow-on-pc-21-trainer-order-from-351075/ &quot;Pilatus receives follow-on PC-21 trainer order from Swiss air force.&quot;] ''Flight International'', 17 December 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 2006, the [[Republic of Singapore Air Force]] (RSAF) awarded a service contract to Lockheed Martin Simulation, Training and Support (LMSTS) to deliver 19 PC-21 aircraft, to support the RSAF's Basic Wings training course in [[RAAF Base Pearce|Pearce]], [[Australia]] under a [[public–private partnership]] (PPP) arrangement, replacing the [[SIAI-Marchetti S.211]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.defense-aerospace.com/articles-view/release/3/75231/singapore-order-to-launch-pilatus-pc_21-production.html &quot;PC-21s to Replace S211s for RSAF's Basic Wings Training.&quot;] ''defense-aerospace'', 3 November 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wastnage, Justin. [https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/lockheed-martin-pilatus-team-win-singapore-trainer-deal-launch-of-pc-21-production-now-210372/ &quot;Lockheed Martin Pilatus team win Singapore trainer deal, launch of PC-21 production now possible.&quot;] ''Flight International'', 3 November 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; Singapore was the first export customer for the PC-21.&lt;ref&gt;David, Donald. [https://www.ainonline.com/aviation-news/defense/2016-02-14/australia-joins-singapore-pc-21-club &quot;Australia Joins Singapore in the PC-21 Club.&quot;] ''AIN Online'', 14 February 2016.&lt;/ref&gt; On 21 January 2008, the first RSAF PC-21 completed its flight test prior to being accepted into service.&lt;ref name= RSAF&gt;{{cite press release |url=http://www.mindef.gov.sg/imindef/news_and_events/nr/2008/feb/15feb08_nr2.html |title= RSAF Pilatus PC-21 Makes its Maiden Flight |publisher=[[Ministry of Defence (Singapore)|Ministry of Defence]] (MINDEF) |date=15 February 2008 |accessdate=29 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Warwick, Graham.[https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/picture-pilatus-flies-first-pc-21-for-singapore-221670/ &quot;PICTURE: Pilatus flies first PC-21 for Singapore.&quot;] ''Flight International'', 19 February 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; On 13 July 2008, the type began to provide the RSAF with basic flying training, by which point a further six aircraft had been delivered.&lt;ref name= fact&gt;{{cite press release |url=http://www.mindef.gov.sg/imindef/news_and_events/nr/2008/jul/13jul08_nr.html |title= Basic Flying Training on the Pilatus PC-21 Aircraft Trainer Commences |publisher=''MINDEF'' |date=13 July 2008 |accessdate=29 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the 2009 [[Dubai Airshow]], the [[United Arab Emirates]] announced an order of 25 PC-21 trainers for the [[United Arab Emirates Air Force]] (UAEAF) to replace their aging fleet of [[Pilatus PC-7]]s.&lt;ref name=UAE&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flightglobal.com/articles/2009/11/17/335112/dubai-09-uae-signs-deal-for-25-pc-21-trainers.html|title=Dubai 09: UAE signs deal for 25 PC-21 trainers|last=Craig|first=Hoyle|date=17 November 2009|publisher=[[Flightglobal.com|Flight Global]]|accessdate=30 September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 22 November 2010, the UAEAF's first PC-21 performed its maiden flight.&lt;ref name=&quot;AFM274-1&quot;&gt;{{cite magazine|date=February 2011|title=UAE's first PC-21 flown|magazine=[[Air Forces Monthly]]|publisher=[[Key Publishing|Key Publishing Ltd]]|issue= 274|page=26|issn=0955-7091}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hoyle, Craig. [https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/pictures-uaes-first-pc-21-makes-flight-debut-350071/ &quot;PICTURES: UAE's first PC-21 makes flight debut.&quot;] ''Flight International'', 23 November 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; In July 2012, it was announced that the [[Qatar Air Force]] had placed an order for a complete pilot training system from Pilatus centering upon the PC-21. The package included ground-based training devices, logistical support and maintenance in addition to 24 PC-21 aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;Pocock, Chris. [http://www.ainonline.com/aviation-news/defense/2012-07-27/pilatus-pc-21-scores-another-pilot-training-win-qatar &quot;Pilatus PC-21 Scores Another Pilot Training Win in Qatar.&quot;] ''AIN Online'', 27 July 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hoyle, Craig. [https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/first-qatari-pc-21-enters-ground-test-396170/ &quot;First Qatari PC-21 enters ground test.&quot;] ''Flight International'', 20 February 2014.&lt;/ref&gt; On 1 October 2014, the Qatar Air Force formally received its first batch of PC-21 trainers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.gulf-times.com/story/410667/Emiri-Air-Force-receives-first-batch-of-PC-21-airc &quot;Emiri Air Force receives first batch of PC-21 aircraft.&quot;] ''Gulf Times'', 1 October 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hoyle, Craig. [https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/first-pc-21s-head-for-qatar-404299/ &quot;First PC-21s head for Qatar.&quot;] ''Flight International'', 30 September 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 23 May 2012, [[Saudi Arabia]] signed a £1.6 billion ($2.5 billion) for a comprehensive next-generation military pilot training system, comprising 22 [[BAE Systems Hawk]] advanced jet trainers in addition to 55 PC-21 trainers.&lt;ref name = &quot;Saudi deal&quot;&gt;Hoyle, Craig. [https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/saudi-arabia-signs-102-aircraft-military-training-de-372229/ &quot;Saudi Arabia signs 102-aircraft military training deal.&quot;] ''Flight International'', 23 May 2012.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Trimble, Stephen, [https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/pilatus-pc-21s-in-package-deal-with-hawks-for-saudi-372004/ &quot;Pilatus PC-21s in package deal with Hawks for Saudi air force.&quot;] ''Flight International'', 17 May 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; In early June 2014, Pilatus commenced delivery of the first six PC-21s to Saudi Arabia;&lt;ref&gt;Hoyle, Craig. [https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/saudi-arabia-gets-first-six-pc-21-trainers-400296/ &quot;Saudi Arabia gets first six PC-21 trainers.&quot;] ''Flight International'', 11 June 2014.&lt;/ref&gt; by the end of 2015, this had risen to 46 PC-21s delivered.&lt;ref&gt;Hoyle, Craig. [https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/follow-on-purchase-to-boost-saudi-hawk-renewal-422194/ &quot;Follow-on purchase to boost Saudi Hawk renewal.&quot;] ''Flight International'', 19 February 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;

The PC-21 was one of the submissions for the [[Royal Australian Air Force]]'s project AIR 5428, which sought a replacement of its Pilatus PC-9s;&lt;ref&gt;Pittaway 2010, p. 20.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Waldron, Greg. [https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/lockheed-pilatus-hawker-pacific-bid-for-raaf-basic-391266/ &quot;Lockheed, Pilatus, Hawker Pacific bid for RAAF basic trainer deal.&quot;] ''Flight International'', 3 October 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; in September 2015, it was announced that the consortium comprising Lockheed Martin, Pilatus and Hawker Pacific (&quot;Team 21&quot;), had won the bid to provide 49 PC-21s to the Australian Defence Force.&lt;ref&gt;&quot;Lockheed Martin Wins Air 5428.&quot; ''Australian Defence Magazine'',  13 May 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Pittaway, Nigel. [http://www.defensenews.com/story/defense/training-simulation/2015/09/10/australia-buy-pc-21-trainers-relocate-basic-training/72031512/ &quot;Australia To Buy PC-21 Trainers, Relocate Basic Training.&quot;] ''Defense News'', 11 September 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, the PC-21 has been evaluated by the [[Spanish Air Force]], along the [[Beechcraft T-6 Texan II|T-6 Texan II]] and the [[PZL-130 Orlik|PZL-130 Orlik III]], as a possible substitute for its [[ENAER T-35 Pillan]] and [[CASA C-101 Aviojet]] trainer aircraft.&lt;ref name=&quot;Revista&quot;&gt;{{citation|date=November 2008|title=Evaluación del PC-21 Pilatus como entrenador Elemental/Básico/Avanzado|publisher=[[Revista de Aeronáutica y Astronáutica]]|journal=[[Ejército del Aire de España]]|number= 778|accessdate=19 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In August 2015, Pilatus received a contract to deliver nine PC-9Ms to the Royal Jordanian Air Force, but in April 2016 changed the order to eight PC-21s. Deliveries were due to start in January 2017 under the original deal.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/jordan-amends-pilatus-order-to-take-pc-21-trainers-424048/ |title=Jordan amends Pilatus order to take PC-21 trainers |date=11 April 2016 |publisher=FlightGlobal}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Operators==
[[File:Pilatus pc-21 1.jpg|thumb|upright|Pair of PC-21s, 2004]]
;{{AUS}}
*[[Royal Australian Air Force]]: 49 PC-21 on order, ordered September 2015.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Lockheed’s &quot;Team 21&quot; finally confirmed as AIR 5428 winning bidder|url=http://australianaviation.com.au/2015/09/lockheeds-team-21-finally-confirmed-as-air-5428-winning-bidder/|website=Australian Aviation|publisher=australianaviation.com.au|accessdate=27 October 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;
;{{QAT}}
*[[Qatar Emiri Air Force]]: 24 PC-21 on order, ordered July 2012, first delivery scheduled for 2014.&lt;ref name=&quot;QAT&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/qatar-signs-deal-for-24-pilatus-pc-21s-374615/|title=Qatar signs deal for 24 Pilatus PC-21s|last=Craig|first=Hoyle|date=23 July 2012|publisher=Flight Global|accessdate=29 September 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;

;{{SAU}}
*[[Royal Saudi Air Force]]: 55 PC-21 on order, ordered May 2012, first delivery scheduled for 2014.&lt;ref name = &quot;Saudi deal&quot;/&gt;
;{{SIN}}
*[[Republic of Singapore Air Force]]: launch customer; operates 19 PC-21 on Basic Wings Course (BWC) as part of a contact for availability, together with Lockheed Martin and Hawker Pacific.

;{{SUI}}
*[[Swiss Air Force]] operates eight PC-21s for advanced training, replacing the [[BAE Systems Hawk|BAe Hawk]] which had been retired since 2003.

;{{UAE}}
*[[United Arab Emirates Air Force]]: operates 25 PC-21s for advanced training, first flight made on 22 November 2010.

==Specifications (PC-21)==
[[File:pilatus.pc-21.fairford2006.arp.jpg|thumb|The Pilatus PC-21; note the stepped tandem cockpit]]
{{External media|topic= |width=20% |align=right |video1=[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dUyZJV7zpIU Swiss Air Force PC-12 flight demonstration at the Breitling Sion Airshow 2011] |video2=[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PaErmMEMC9Y In-cockpit video of PC-12 takeoff] |video3=[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BExHVHAL1gc PC-21s at Koor Airport, Qatar]}}
{{Aircraft specifications
|plane or copter?=plane
|jet or prop?=prop
|ref= [[Pilatus Aircraft]]&lt;ref name=spec&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pilatus-aircraft.com/00-def/main/scripts/ckfinder/userfiles/files/Downloads/Brochures/Pilatus%20Aircraft%20Ltd%20-%20PC-21%20Fact%20Sheet.pdf |title=Pilatus: PC-21 fact sheet |format=PDF |publisher=Pilatus Aircraft Ltd |accessdate=29 April 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;pil brouch&quot;/&gt;
|crew=two (student &amp; instructor)
|capacity=
|length main=11.233 m
|length alt=36 ft 11 in
|span main=9.108 m
|span alt=29 ft 11 in
|height main=3.749 m
|height alt=12 ft 4 in
|area main=15.221 m²
|area alt=163.848 ft²
|airfoil=
|empty weight main=2,270 kg
|empty weight alt=5,005 lb
|loaded weight main=&lt;!--kg--&gt;
|loaded weight alt=&lt;!--lb--&gt;
|useful load main=&lt;!--kg--&gt;
|useful load alt=&lt;!--lb--&gt;
|max takeoff weight main=3,100 kg (aerobatic) / 4,250 kg (utility)
|max takeoff weight alt=6,834 lb (aerobatic) / 9,370 lb (utility)
|more general=
|engine (prop)= [[Pratt &amp; Whitney Canada PT6#PT6A|Pratt &amp; Whitney Canada PT6A-68B]]
|type of prop= [[Turboprop]] engine
|number of props= 1
|power main= 1,200 kW
|power alt= 1,600 shp
|power original=
|max speed main=685 km/h
|max speed alt=370 knots, 428 mph
|cruise speed main=&lt;!--km/h--&gt;
|cruise speed alt=&lt;!--knots,mph--&gt;
|never exceed speed main=&lt;!--km/h--&gt;
|never exceed speed alt=&lt;!--knots,mph--&gt;
|stall speed main=170 km/h 
|stall speed alt=92 knots, 106.25 mph
|stall speed more=gear and flaps up (20 km/h less with flaps and gear down)
|range main=1,333 km
|range alt=720 nm, 828 miles
|ceiling main=11,580 m
|ceiling alt=38,000 ft
|climb rate main=1,219 m/min
|climb rate alt=4,000 ft/min
|loading main=208 kg/m²
|loading alt=42.7 lb/ft²
|thrust/weight=&lt;!--a unitless ratio--&gt;
|power/mass main=0.39 kW/kg
|power/mass alt=0.23 hp/lb
|more performance=
&lt;!-- data also from ref 1--&gt;
* '''g limits:''' + 8.0 g to – 4.0 (aerobatic) / + 5.0 g to – 2.5 g (utility)
|armament=

*'''[[Hardpoint]]s:''' Provisions provided for 4× under-wing and 1× centerline external store stations, capable of mounting up to {{convert|1150|kg|lb|abbr=on}} of payload of air-to-ground weapons to operate in the [[Counter-insurgency]] role.{{Citation needed|date=January 2015}}
|avionics=
}}

==See also==
{{Aircontent|
|related=
*[[Pilatus PC-7]]
*[[Pilatus PC-9]]
|similar aircraft=
*[[Beechcraft T-6 Texan II]]
*[[Embraer EMB 314 Super Tucano]]
*[[KAI KT-1]]
*[[TAI Hürkuş]]
|sequence=
|lists=
|see also=
}}

==References==
;Notes
{{Reflist|2}}

;Bibliography
{{refbegin}}
*{{Cite journal |last=Pittaway |first=Nigel |title=ADF pilot training under contract |journal=Defence Today |volume=8 |issue=2 |pages=20–21 |publisher=Strike Publications |location=Amberley |date=March 2010 |issn=1447-0446 }}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Pilatus PC-21}}
*[http://www.pilatus-aircraft.com/#39 Pilatus PC-21 Official Site]

{{Pilatus aircraft}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Pilatus Pc-21}}
[[Category:Pilatus aircraft|PC-21]]
[[Category:Swiss military trainer aircraft 2000–2009]]
[[Category:Single-engined tractor aircraft]]
[[Category:Low-wing aircraft]]
[[Category:Turboprop aircraft]]</text>
      <sha1>8eou9khf8ng6sl0xs07r74mvgn4hxjq</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
