<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Pilatus PC-6 Porter</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>915646</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745707251</id>
      <parentid>744119342</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-22T20:29:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Dawnseeker2000</username>
        <id>1544984</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>[[MOS:DASH]], [[Short Takeoff and Landing]] (STOL) → [[STOL|Short Takeoff and Landing]] (STOL) using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="32215">&lt;!-- This article is a part of [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft]]. Please see [[Wikipedia:WikiProject Aircraft/page content]] for recommended layout. --&gt;
{{Expand French|Pilatus PC-6|date=March 2016}}
{|{{Infobox Aircraft Begin
  |name = PC-6 Porter/Turbo-Porter
  |image = File:Pilatus PC-6 SkydiveLillo JD18032008.jpg
  |caption = A PC-6 Turbo-Porter, B2-H4 PT6A-34 variant, used for skydiving in Spain
}}{{Infobox Aircraft Type
  |type = STOL Passenger and utility aircraft
  |manufacturer = [[Pilatus Aircraft]]
  |builder = [[Fairchild Aircraft]]
  |first flight = Porter - 4 May 1959 &lt;br/&gt; Turbo-Porter - 2 May 1961. 
  |introduced = 
  |retired =
  |status = Active service, in production
  |primary user = Civil aviation
  |more users = [[Austrian Air Force]], [[Myanmar Air Force]], [[Swiss Air Force]]
  |produced = 1959–present
  |number built = 581 (As of August 2014)&lt;ref&gt;Paper Printout &quot;Rollout PC-24&quot; from Pilatus Flugzeugwerke AG Page 5, handed out on 01.08.2014 do the Rollout celebration of the PC-24 at Stans / Buochs Airport.&lt;/ref&gt;
  |unit cost = $55,000 (1962)&lt;ref name = &quot;fricker 103&quot;&gt;Fricker 1962, p. 103.&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;br /&gt; $1,900,000 (2010)&lt;ref name = &quot;flight test&quot;/&gt;
  |variants with their own articles = [[Fairchild AU-23 Peacemaker]]
}}
|}

The '''Pilatus PC-6 Porter''' is a single-engined [[STOL|Short Takeoff and Landing]] (STOL) [[utility aircraft]] designed by [[Pilatus Aircraft]] of Switzerland. First flown in 1959, the PC-6 continues in production at Pilatus Flugzeugwerke in Stans, Switzerland. It has been built in both [[piston engine]]- and [[turboprop]]-powered versions and was produced for a time by [[Fairchild Aircraft|Fairchild Hiller]] in the United States.

==Development==
On 4 May 1959, the first prototype, powered by a 254&amp;nbsp;kW (340 shp) [[piston engine]], made its maiden flight.&lt;ref name=&quot;JAWA65 p126-7&quot;/&gt; In early May 1961, the first ''Turbo Porter'', powered by a [[Turbomeca Astazou|Turbomeca Astazou II]] turboprop engine, performed its initial flight.&lt;ref name = &quot;fricker 38&quot;&gt;Fricker 1962, p. 38.&lt;/ref&gt; In comparison to its earlier piston engine-powered incarnation, the Astazou II-equipped ''Turbo Porter'' had an increased gross capacity and top speed, as well as benefitting from the engine's automatic handling functions. These benefits came at the expense of a greater initial purchase cost and higher fuel consumption.&lt;ref name = &quot;fricker 38&quot;/&gt; Both the piston and turbine-engine versions of the PC-6 became quickly known for their Short Takeoff and Landing (STOL) capabilities, requiring only a very short takeoff run before being ready for [[rotation (aeronautics)|rotation]] prior to taking off.&lt;ref name = &quot;fricker 102&quot;&gt;Fricker 1962, p. 102.&lt;/ref&gt;

The initial turbine-powered models of the PC-6 were equipped with the Astazou II powerplant, however complaints of the reliability of this engine were made. Another early turboprop powerplant that became available for the PC-6 was the [[Garrett TPE331|Garrett Air Research TPE 331]]. Some operators such as [[Air America (airline)|Air America]] chose to retrofit their Astazou II-powered PC-6s with the TPE 331 engine in its place.&lt;ref name = &quot;air america&quot;&gt;Leeker, Joe F. [http://www.utdallas.edu/library/specialcollections/hac/cataam/Leeker/aircraft/pc6.pdf &quot;Air America: Pilatus / Fairchild PC-6 Turbo Porters.&quot;] ''University of Texas at Dallas'', 24 August 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; In May 1996, the first PC-6 to be equipped with the [[Pratt &amp; Whitney Canada PT6|Pratt &amp; Whitney Canada PT6A]] engine performed its maiden flight.&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot;&gt;Moll 1993, p. 65.&lt;/ref&gt;

To offset rising labour and manufacturing costs in Switzerland, Pilatus distributed manufacturing work on the PC-6 to other countries; in 1993, [[Czech Republic]]-based [[Letov Kbely]] began manufacturing activity upon the type.&lt;ref name = &quot;small beaut&quot;/&gt; In 2013, Pilatus formed a [[joint venture]] with Beijing Tian Xing Jian Yu Science Co., Ltd. to locally manufacture the PC-6 and the newer [[Pilatus PC-12]] in [[Chongqing]], China; initially this facility performed subassembly work on the fuselage, and later other elements such as the wings and moving surfaces, which were conveyed to Pilatus' final assembly facility in [[Stans]], Switzerland.&lt;ref&gt;Spruce, Terry. [http://corporatejetinvestor.com/articles/pilatus-opens-jv-china-451/ &quot;Pilatus forms joint venture and opens new facility in China.&quot;] ''Corporate Jet Investor'', 7 August 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://aviationweek.com/zhuhai-2014/pilatus-bets-pc-6-porter-china &quot;Pilatus Bets On PC-6 Porter for China.&quot;] ''Aviation Week'', 11 November 2014.&lt;/ref&gt; Global production of the PC-6 shall be eventually transferred to the Chongqing facility. On 11 December 2014, the first Chinese-assembled PC-6 fuselage was completed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chinadaily.com.cn/regional/chongqing/liangjiang/2014-12/18/content_19123307.htm &quot;Swiss PC-6 aircraft fuselage tapes out.&quot;] ''China Daily'', 18 December 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.chinadaily.com.cn/regional/chongqing/liangjiang/2014-01/07/content_17205233.htm &quot;Pilatus PC-6 Airplanes.&quot;] ''China Daily'', 7 January 2014.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2014, the majority of PC-6s delivered that year were to Chinese customers.&lt;ref&gt;Trautvetter, Chad. [http://www.ainonline.com/aviation-news/business-aviation/2015-04-09/pilatus-tops-1b-revenues-second-year-row &quot;Pilatus Tops $1B in Revenues for Second Year in a Row.&quot;] ''AIN Online'', 9 April 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; By April 2016, around 20 PC-6s were in operation in the Chinese market; the type has often been used to replace the [[Antonov An-2]], being reportedly cheaper to operate.&lt;ref&gt;Thurber, Matt. [http://www.ainonline.com/aviation-news/business-aviation/2016-04-13/pilatus-pc-6-proves-popular-china &quot;Pilatus PC-6 Proves Popular in China.&quot;] ''AIN Online'', 13 April 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Porter was also manufactured under license by [[Fairchild Aircraft|Fairchild Hiller]] in the United States. Roughly 100 of these licence-produced aircraft would be completed, being mainly purchased by civil operators within the US.&lt;ref name = &quot;air america&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;moll 64&quot;/&gt; A number of Fairchild Hiller-built PC-6s were also procured for military operations during the [[Vietnam War]]. It received the designation [[Fairchild AU-23 Peacemaker|''AU-23A Peacemaker'']] for service with the U.S. Air Force and ''UV-20 Chiricahua'' for service with the U.S. Army. The Peacemaker was fitted with a side-firing 20mm XM-197 Gatling cannon, four wing pylons and a centre fuselage station for external ordnance. However, the AU-23A proved to be troublesome in service. All of them were returned to the continental U.S. and placed into storage after only a single year of operation. In 1979, a pair of UV-20s were assigned to the aviation detachment of the [[Berlin Brigade#United States|Berlin Brigade]] in Germany due to their suitability for operating within the heavily restricted airspace; they were fitted for carrying either cargo, up to eleven passengers, or three [[litter]]s with four medical attendants.&lt;ref&gt;Johnson and Jones 2013, pp. 433.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Design==
[[File:Pilatus PC-6A Turbo-Porter cabin.jpg|thumb|PC-6 cabin interior, circa 1960s]]
The Pilatus PC-6 Porter is a [[STOL|Short Takeoff and Landing]] (STOL) [[utility aircraft]]. The majority of aircraft are powered by a single [[Pratt &amp; Whitney Canada PT6|Pratt &amp; Whitney Canada PT6A]] turboprop engine, which drives a fully reversible, constant-speed, three-bladed HC-B3TN-3D (or an alternative four-bladed HC-D4N-3P unit) [[Hartzell]] aluminium propeller via a reduction [[gearbox]].&lt;ref name = &quot;pc6 factsheet&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;pc6 broch&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=R5uhU9wKe7wC&amp;pg=PA50 &quot;Datalink.&quot;] ''Flying Magazine'', November 2002. p. 50. Vol. 129, No. 11. ISSN 0015-4806.&lt;/ref&gt; Pilatus claims that it possesses unique STOL capabilities, capable of landing in places only otherwise accessible by [[rotorcraft]].&lt;ref name = &quot;pc6 broch&quot;/&gt; It is fully capable of being operated from unprepared rough airstrips, in remote areas, hot climates and at high altitudes in all-weather conditions. In particular, the undercarriage employed provides for high wing and propeller clearances, making the PC-6 less susceptible to damage than conventional nosewheel-type undercarriages.&lt;ref name = &quot;pc6 broch&quot;/&gt; For further landing versatility, various types of [[landing gear]] may be optionally installed allowing it to operate from different types of terrain; options include floats for water landings and skis for landing on snow.&lt;ref name = &quot;pc6 factsheet&quot;&gt;[http://www.pilatus-aircraft.com/00-def/main/scripts/ckfinder/userfiles/files/Downloads/Brochures/Pilatus%20Aircraft%20Ltd%20-%20Factsheet%20PC-6.pdf &quot;PC-6: The World's Leading STOL.&quot;] ''Pilatus Aircraft'', Retrieved: 17 March 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;

Early models of the PC-6 were equipped with a full instrument panel as standard, and were reportedly easy for unfamiliar pilots to intuit.&lt;ref name = &quot;fricker 101&quot;/&gt; Later-manufactured PC-6s are equipped with a [[Garmin]] G950 [[glass cockpit]] in place of analogue instrumentation; the majority of earlier-produced PC-6s can also be retrofitted with a glass cockpit as well.&lt;ref name = &quot;flight test&quot;&gt;Collins, Peter. [https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/flight-test-pilatus-pc-6-347732/ &quot;FLIGHT TEST: Pilatus PC-6.&quot;] ''Flight International'', 28 September 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pilatus-aircraft.com/#18 &quot;Cockpit.&quot;] ''Pilatus Aircraft'', Retrieved: 20 March 2016.&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to its flight functionality, the G950 system acts as a remote maintenance unit and [[electronic flight bag]] all in one. Two large 10.4-inch [[liquid-crystal display]]s (LCDs) are present, functioning as the Primary Flight Display for all key flight information and the Multi-function Display for system/mission management respectively; fully independent secondary flight instrumentation is also provided to provide backup altitude, attitude, and airspeed information in the event of complete electrical failure.&lt;ref name = &quot;flight test&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;pc6 broch&quot;/&gt; The cockpit has been designed for single pilot operations; additional [[aircraft flight control system|flight controls]] for a co-pilot can be optionally fitted.&lt;ref name = &quot;pc6 factsheet&quot;/&gt; Other optional features include an [[autopilot]] (capable of operating within all phases of flight), [[traffic collision avoidance system]] (TCAS), [[terrain awareness and warning system]] (TAWS), [[weather radar]], [[satellite phone]], [[Lidar|LIDAR]], [[forward-looking infrared]] (FLIR) and [[Lightning detection#Aviation use|lightning detector]]; in addition, onboard electrical and avionics equipment are readily modifiable to conform with customer requirements.&lt;ref name = &quot;flight test&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;pc6 broch&quot;/&gt;

[[File:PC-6 Turbo-Porter cockpit.jpg|thumb|left|Analogue cockpit instrumentation of a PC-6, 2007]]
The airframe is of a rugged and low-maintenance construction; featuring high levels of accessibility, interchangeability, and favourable manning levels.&lt;ref name = &quot;pc6 broch&quot;&gt;[http://www.pilatus-aircraft.com/00-def/main/scripts/ckfinder/userfiles/files/Downloads/Brochures/Pilatus%20Aircraft%20Ltd%20-%20PC-6.pdf &quot;PV-6 Turbo Porter: Anywhere, Anytime, in any Environment.&quot;] ''Pilatus Aircraft'', Retrieved: 19 March 2016.&lt;/ref&gt; The wings, fuselage, and empennage are manufactured using conventional semi-monocoque construction techniques, the primary structure being composed of aluminium;&lt;ref name = &quot;pc6 broch&quot;/&gt; the central structure retains critical strength despite the cutout areas for the sliding doors of the main cabin.&lt;ref name = &quot;fricker 101&quot;&gt;Fricker 1962, p. 101.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Corrosion]] resistance is achieved via a combination of [[plating]] and a [[polyurethane]]-based [[enamel paint]].&lt;ref name = &quot;pc6 broch&quot;/&gt; The simple nature of the structure allows for ease of repair in the field.&lt;ref name = &quot;moll 64&quot;/&gt; Features such as low-pressure tyres, twin-clipper [[disc brake]]s, and a highly energy-absorbent undercarriage enable the aircraft to be capable of operating from rough or otherwise challenging terrain.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pilatus-aircraft.com/#17 &quot;Operational Area.&quot;] ''Pilatus Aircraft'', Retrieved: 20 March 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;

For role flexibility, individual aircraft can be easily converted between various mission types, such as transport, [[paratrooper|paradrop]], [[aerial photography]], [[surveillance]], [[air medical services]] and [[search and rescue]] duties.&lt;ref name = &quot;pc6 factsheet&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;pc6 broch&quot;/&gt; A maximum of ten passengers, or a 2,200 lb payload, may be carried within the aircraft's main cabin area within the rear section of the fuselage; the standard passenger seats are designed to allow for rapid removal and may be stowed within an optional separate externally-accessed seat stowage compartment behind the main cabin.&lt;ref name = &quot;pc6 broch&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pilatus-aircraft.com/#19 &quot;Cabin.&quot;] ''Pilatus Aircraft'', Retrieved: 20 March 2016.&lt;/ref&gt; The main cabin area is furnished with [[soundproofing]] measures, ventilation, and heating as standard.&lt;ref name = &quot;fricker 101&quot;/&gt; A maximum of three fuel tanks can also be carried in the main cabin, accordingly reducing payload capacity, to increase the aircraft's flight endurance.&lt;ref name = &quot;pc6 broch&quot;/&gt; In addition to the large sliding doors at either side of the main cabin, separate hinged doors are present on either side of the cockpit; an optional pilot-controlled [[trapdoor]], to accommodate supply drops or surveillance payloads, may also be installed in the center of the cabin floor without any design changes required.&lt;ref name = &quot;air america&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;pc6 factsheet&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1960/1960%20-%200013.html &quot;Porter in England.&quot;] ''Flight International'', 1 January 1960. p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt; Additional equipment include a [[firefighting]] system, [[aerial application]] system, underwing tanks, [[sand filter]]s, propeller [[de-ice|de-icing]] system, [[mudguard]], tailwheel debris guard, oxygen system, and additional power distribution system.&lt;ref name = &quot;moll 64&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name = &quot;pc6 broch&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pilatus-aircraft.com/#149 &quot;Special Missions.&quot;] ''Pilatus Aircraft'', Retrieved: 20 March 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Operational history==
{{expand section|date=March 2016}}
The PC-6 is noted for its ''Short Takeoff and Landing'' ([[STOL]]) performance on almost any type of terrain - it can take off within a distance of {{convert|640|ft|m|0}} and land within a distance of {{convert|427|ft|m|0}} while carrying a payload of 2,646&amp;nbsp;lbs (1,200&amp;nbsp;kg). Thanks to its STOL performance, the PC-6 holds the world record for highest landing by a [[fixed-wing aircraft]], at {{convert|18,865|ft|m|0}}, on the [[Dhaulagiri]] glacier in [[Nepal]].&lt;ref&gt;Isserman, Weaver and Molenaar 2008, p. 358.&lt;/ref&gt;

Due to the type's favourable STOL characteristics, described by [[Flying Magazine]] as being &quot;one of the most helicopter-like airplanes in terms of takeoff performance&quot;, Pilatus has deliberately marketed the PC-6 towards helicopter operators at times, feeling the type to be complimentary to their typical mode of operation.&lt;ref name = &quot;moll 64&quot;/&gt; According to Pilatus, the PC-6 can provide very similar surveillance capabilities to a rotorcraft at a significantly lower cost to operate and procure.&lt;ref name = &quot;small beaut&quot;&gt;Moxon, Julian. [https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/small-is-beautiful-6801/ &quot;Small is beautiful.&quot;] ''Flight International'', 12 June 1996.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Peruvian Air Force Pilatus PC-6 Turbo Porter.jpg|thumb|left|Peruvian Air Force PC-6, 2014]]
During its early service, the PC-6 Porter was noted for its high level of comfort and usability against competing aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;Fricker 1962, pp. 100–101.&lt;/ref&gt; The type has also proven to have a long service life; by 1993, roughly 440 of the 500 PC-6 Turbo Porters completed by that point were still in service.&lt;ref name = &quot;moll 64&quot;&gt;Moll 1993, p. 64.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the 1960s and 1970s, the [[Central Intelligence Agency]] (CIA)-controlled airline [[Air America (airline)|Air America]] operated up to 23 PC-6s at a time. Many of these were operated in the South-East Asia region, including [[South Vietnam]] during the Vietnam War. The type was used for various missions including paradropping supplies to troops, passenger transport, [[psy ops]], reconnaissance, prisoner conveyance, [[airborne radio relay]], and other intelligence operations.&lt;ref name = &quot;air america&quot;/&gt;

Since 1976, the [[Austrian Air Force]] has operated a fleet of 12 PC-6 Porters as the mainstay of their fixed-wing transport fleet; the type has been used in various support roles, including transport, Search and Rescue, firefighting, observation, target-towing and paradropping.&lt;ref&gt;Moxon, Julian. [https://www.flightglobal.com/news/articles/austria-ready-to-modernise-57509/ &quot;Austria ready to modernise.&quot;] ''Flight International'', 27 October 1999.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.bundesheer.at/english/forces/airforce.shtml &quot;The Austrian Air Force - In the Past and Today.&quot;] ''Austrian Armed Forces'', Retrieved: 20 March 2016.&lt;/ref&gt;
 
According to ''Flying Magazine'', around 40 per cent of all PC-6s in use in Europe during the early 1990s were being used by [[parachuting|skydivers]].&lt;ref name=&quot;auto&quot;/&gt;

==Variants==
[[File:Pilatus PC-6-350 Porter HB-FAM.jpg|thumb|right|A PC-6/350 Porter]]
[[File:Metrum Pilatus PC-6 B2-H4 Turbo Porter YL-CCQ.jpg|thumb|PC-6/B2-H4 Turbo-Porter. YL-CCQ is currently (2016) used by Skydive Estonia as a jump plane.]]
[[File:Au23-1.jpg|thumb|A Fairchild Porter]]
[[File:Pilatus PC-6 B2H4.jpg|thumb|Pilatus PC-6/ B2-H4 in flight]]
[[File:Pilatus UV-20A.jpg|UV-20|thumb|right]]
;PC-6/340 Porter
:Initial production version, powered by a 254-kW (340-hp) [[Lycoming O-480|Lycoming GSO-480-B1A6]] flat-six piston engine. Max takeoff weight 1,960 kg (4,320 lb).&lt;ref name=&quot;JAWA65 p126-7&quot;&gt;Taylor 1965, pp. 126–127.&lt;/ref&gt;
;;PC-6/340-H1 Porter
::As PC-6/340, but with modified landing gear and increased weight (2,016 kg (4,444 lb)).&lt;ref name=&quot;JAWA65 p126-7&quot;/&gt;
;;PC-6/340-H2 Porter
::As for H-2, but with maximum takeoff weight increased to 2,200 kg (4,850 lb).&lt;ref name=&quot;JAWA65 p126-7&quot;/&gt;
;PC-6/350 Porter
:As PC-6/340, but powered by a 261&amp;nbsp;kW (350&amp;nbsp;hp) [[Lycoming O-540|Lycoming IGO-540-A1A]] piston engine.&lt;ref name=&quot;JAWA65 p126-7&quot;/&gt;
;;PC-6/350-H1 Porter
::As for /340 H1 but with O-540 engine.&lt;ref name=&quot;JAWA65 p126-7&quot;/&gt;
;;PC-6/350-H2 Porter
::As for 340 H2 with O-540 engine.&lt;ref name=&quot;JAWA65 p126-7&quot;/&gt;
;PC-6/A Turbo-Porter
:Initial turboprop powered version, fitted with a 390&amp;nbsp;kW (523&amp;nbsp;shp) [[Turbomeca Astazou]] IIE or IIG turboprop engine.&lt;ref name=&quot;JAWA65 p126-7&quot;/&gt;
;PC-6/A1 Turbo-Porter
:This 1968 version was powered by a 427-kW (573-shp) Turbomeca Astazou XII turboprop engine.
;PC-6/A2 Turbo-Porter
:This 1971 version was powered by a 427-kW (573-shp) Turbomeca Astazou XIVE turboprop engine.
;PC-6/B Turbo-Porter
:This version was powered by a 410-kW (550-shp) Pratt &amp; Whitney Canada PT6A-6A turboprop engine.
;PC-6/B1 Turbo-Porter
:Similar to the PC-6/B, but fitted with a 410-kW (550-shp) Pratt &amp; Whitney Canada PT6A-20 turboprop engine.
;PC-6/B2-H2 Turbo-Porter
:Fitted with a 507-kW (680-shp) Pratt &amp; Whitney Canada PT6A-27 turboprop engine.
;PC-6/B2-H4 Turbo-Porter
:The B2-H4 has improved airframe structuring and extended, upturned wingtips.
;PC-6/C Turbo-Porter
:One prototype built by [[Fairchild Industries]] in the United States, powered by a 429-kW (575-shp) [[Garrett TPE331]]-25D turboprop engine.
;PC-6/C1 Turbo-Porter
:Similar to the PC-6/C, but fitted with a 429-kW (575-shp) Garrett TPE 331-1-100 turboprop engine.
;PC-6/C2-H2 Porter
:Developed by Fairchild Industries in the USA. It was powered by a 485-ekW (650-ehp) Garrett TPE 331-101F turboprop engine.
;PC-6/D-H3 Porter
:One prototype, fitted with a 373-kW (500-hp) avco Lycoming turbocharged piston engine.
;[[Fairchild AU-23A Peacemaker|AU-23A Peacemaker]]
:Armed gunship, counter-insurgency, utility transport version for the [[U.S. Air Force]]. It was used during the Vietnam War in the early 1970s. 35 were built under licence in the USA by Fairchild Industries. All aircraft were sold to [[Royal Thai Air Force]].
;OV-12
:Designation for U.S. version, cancelled 1979.
;UV-20A Chiricahua
:STOL utility transport version for the [[U.S. Army]]. Two UV-20As were based in [[West Berlin]] during the 1970s and 1980s.
;[[Pilatus PC-8D Twin Porter|PC-8D Twin Porter]]
:Twin-engined version flown in 1967, but not subsequently developed.

==Operators==
[[File:Österreich, Zeltweg (Flughafen Hinterstoisser), Pilatus PC-6, 0086.JPG|thumb|[[Austrian Air Force]] PC-6, 2013]]
[[File:Au23-2.jpg|thumb|A Fairchild AU-23 in a steep climb]]
[[File:Pilatus PC-6-B2-H2 Turbo Porter EPS de la Moselle, LFGR Doncourt-les-Conflans, France PP1248766174.jpg|thumb|PC-6 prior to landing, 2009]]
[[File:Pilatus_PC-6_F-GLEU_(10654203326).jpg|thumb|A low-passing PC-6, 2009]]
[[File:Pilatus PC-6-B2-H2 Turbo Porter, Private JP6822824.jpg|thumb|Pilatus PC-6/B2-H2, 2010]]
[[File:Continental Air Service's Pilatus Turbo Porter Landing Up Country in Laos, 1969 - Flickr - The Central Intelligence Agency.jpg|thumb|Continental Air Service's PC-6, 2010]]

===Current military operators===
;{{ANG}}
*[[National Air Force of Angola]] {{citation needed|date=June 2012}}
;{{ARG}}
* [[Argentine Navy]]&lt;ref name=&quot;fiwaf15 p32&quot;&gt;Hoyle ''Flight International'' 8–14 December 2015, p. 32.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Gendarmeria Nacional Argentina]]
;{{AUT}}
* [[Austrian Air Force]]&lt;ref name=&quot;fiwaf15 p33&quot;&gt;Hoyle ''Flight International'' 8–14 December 2015, p. 33.&lt;/ref&gt;
;{{BIR}} ([[Myanmar]])
* [[Myanmar Air Force]]&lt;ref name=&quot;fiwaf15 p43&quot;&gt;Hoyle ''Flight International'' 8–14 December 2015, p. 43.&lt;/ref&gt;
;{{CHA}}
* [[Chad Air Force]]&lt;ref name=&quot;fiwaf11 p36&quot;&gt;Hoyle ''Flight International'' 13–19 December 2011, p. 36.&lt;/ref&gt;
;{{ECU}}
* [[Ecuadorian Army]]&lt;ref name=&quot;fiwaf11 p37&quot;&gt;Hoyle ''Flight International'' 13–19 December 2011, p. 37.&lt;/ref&gt;
;{{IRN}}
*[[Islamic Republic of Iran Air Force]]&lt;ref name=&quot;fiwaf15 p40&quot;&gt;Hoyle ''Flight International'' 8–14 December 2015, p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt;
;{{MEX}}
* [[Mexican Air Force]]&lt;ref name=&quot;fiwaf15 p43&quot;/&gt;
;{{PER}}
* [[Peruvian Air Force]]&lt;ref name=&quot;fiwaf15 p45&quot;&gt;Hoyle ''Flight International'' 8–14 December 2015, p. 45.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Slovenian Air Force - Pilatus PC-6 L6-03 - Short Field Landing at Murska Sobota Airport (LJMS).ogv|thumbnail|Slovenian Air Force Pilatus PC-6 L6-03 landing at the Murska Sobota Airport]]
;{{SLO}}
* [[Slovenian Air Force and Air Defence]]&lt;ref name=&quot;fiwaf15 p47&quot;&gt;Hoyle ''Flight International'' 8–14 December 2015, p. 47.&lt;/ref&gt;
;{{SUI}}
* [[Swiss Air Force]]&lt;ref name=&quot;fiwaf15 p49&quot;&gt;Hoyle ''Flight International'' 8–14 December 2015, p. 49.&lt;/ref&gt;
;{{THA}}
* [[Royal Thai Air Force]]&lt;ref name=&quot;fiwaf11 p49&quot;&gt;Hoyle ''Flight International'' 13–19 December 2011, p. 49.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Bureau of Royal Rainmaking and Agricultural Aviation]]
;{{USA}}
* [[United States Army]]&lt;ref name=&quot;fiwaf15 p52&quot;&gt;Hoyle ''Flight International'' 8–14 December 2015, p. 52.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Former military operators===
;{{DZA}}
;{{AUS}}
* [[Australian Army Aviation]] - 19 Turbo-Porters were in service with Australian Army from 1968 to 1992.
** [[6th Aviation Regiment (Australia)]]
*** [[173rd Surveillance Squadron (Australia)]]
** No. 161 Independent Reconnaissance Flight
** No. 163 Independent Reconnaissance Flight
** No. 171 Air Cavalry Flight
** School Army Aviation
; [[File:FlagofBophuthatswana.png|22px]] [[Bophuthatswana]]
* [[Bophuthatswana Air Force]] - Later transferred to [[South African Air Force]]
;{{BOL}}
;{{COL}}
* [[Colombian Air Force]]
** [[SATENA]]
;{{FRA}}
* [[French Army]]
;{{ISR}}
* [[Israeli Air Force]]
** [[100 Squadron (Israel)|100 Squadron]]
;{{NEP}}
;{{OMN}}
* [[Royal Air Force of Oman]]
;{{RSA}}
* [[South African Air Force]]
;{{THA}}
* [[Royal Thai Army]]
;{{SUD}}
* [[Sudanese Air Force]]
;{{UAE}}
* [[United Arab Emirates Air Force]]
;{{USA}}
* [[United States Army]]
* [[United States Air Force]]

===Law Enforcement operators===
;{{MYS}}
*[[Royal Malaysian Police]]
;{{OMN}}
*[[Royal Oman Police]]
;{{RSA}}
*[[South African Police Service]]
;{{THA}}
*[[Royal Thai Police]]

===Civil operators===
[[File:Air America Porter 01.jpg|thumb|[[Continental Air Services, Inc|Continental Air Services]] PC-6 Porter in [[Laos]], ca. 1970]]
[[File:Pilatus PC-6-B2-H4 Turbo Porter, Swissboogie AN0805653.jpg|thumb|Swissboogie PC-6/B2-H4 Turbo Porter, 2005]]
[[File:Airborne magnetometer.jpg|thumb|[[United States Geological Survey]] PC-6 Porter, 2007]]
[[File:ZK-MCN 2 Pilatus Turbo Porter Mt Cook Ski Planes Franz Joseph Glacier 09JAN99 (6934547689).jpg|thumb|PC-6 upon [[Franz Josef Glacier]], 1999]]
;{{AUS}}
* [[Mission Aviation Fellowship]]
;{{IDN}}
* [[JAARS|Yajasi Aviation]]
* [[Susi Air]]
;{{flagcountry|Mongolia}}
*[[Thomas Air]]
;{{NEP}}
* [[Yeti Airlines]]
;{{NZL}}
* [[Mount Cook Airlines]]
;{{PNG}}
* [[Mission Aviation Fellowship]]
;{{THA}}
*Thai Ministry of Agriculture
;{{USA}}
* [[Air America (airline)|Air America]]
* [[Continental Air Services, Inc|CASI]]

===Former civil operators===
;{{HUN}}
*National Hydrological Service
*National Ambulance Service
;{{NEP}}
*[[Tara Air]]

==Accidents and incidents==
* 26 December 1999 A Pilatus PC-6/B2-H4 Turbo porter registration HB-FKJ&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aviation-safety.net/wikibase/wiki.php?id=30298|title=ASN Aircraft accident 26-DEC-1999 Pilatus PC-6/B2-H4 Turbo Porter HB-FKJ|first=Harro|last=Ranter|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; crashed near [[Turin]]. Because of heavy turbulence a wing broke causing the plane to  crash, the two people aboard died.
* 30 May 2008 A Pilatus PC-6/B2-H4 Turbo porter registration EC-JXH&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aviation-safety.net/wikibase/wiki.php?id=20232|title=ASN Aircraft accident 30-MAY-2008 Pilatus PC-6/B2-H4 Turbo Porter EC-JXH|first=Harro|last=Ranter|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; crashed near [[Lillo, Spain]]. After going into a stall, the plane's left wing broke causing the door to open, allowing nine skydivers to jump out and survive. One skydiver and the pilot died in the crash.
* 19 October 2013: A Pilatus PC-6/B2-H4 Turbo Porter registration OO-NAC&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pc-6.com/history/710.htm|title=PC-6 History s/n 710|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; carrying ten skydivers (instructors and students) and a pilot, lost height and impacted terrain at [[Fernelmont]] some ten minutes after takeoff from nearby [[Namur-Suarlee Airport|Namur-Suarlée Airport (EBNM)]], Belgium. All aboard died. The aircraft (S/N 710) was built in 1969 and had been rebuilt in 2002 by Pilatus Flugzeugwerke following a takeoff accident at [[Moorsele Airfield|Moorsele (EBMO)]] on 12 March 2000.&lt;ref name=&quot;ASN#161542&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://aviation-safety.net/wikibase/wiki.php?id=161542|title=ASN Aircraft accident 19-OCT-2013 Pilatus PC-6/B2-H4 Turbo Porter OO-NAC|first=Harro|last=Ranter|publisher=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The crash has been caused by the loss of a wing because of a wrong manoeuvre made by the pilot.
* 19 June 2016 - Pilatus PC-6 disintegrated in midair while carrying seven skydivers for practice in Beja, Portugal. All skydivers survived, although two were severely wounded. The pilot was the single fatality.

==Specifications (PC-6 B2 Turbo-Porter)==
[[File:Pilatus Turbo-Porter.svg|right|300px]]
[[File:Fairchild_AU-23A_Peacemaker_with_XM197_20mm_cannon.jpg|thumb|Fairchild AU-23A Peacemaker with XM197 20mm cannon]]
{{aircraft specifications
|plane or copter?=plane
|jet or prop?=prop
|ref=Jane's All The World's Aircraft 1993–1994,&lt;ref name=&quot;JAWA93 p358-9&quot;&gt;Lambert 1993, pp. 358–359.&lt;/ref&gt; Pilatus Aircraft,&lt;ref name = &quot;pc6 factsheet&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.pilatus-aircraft.com/#20 &quot;Performance &amp; Specs.&quot;] ''Pilatus Aircraft'', Retrieved: 20 March 2016.&lt;/ref&gt; Flying Magazine.&lt;ref name = &quot;moll 68&quot;&gt;Moll 1993, p. 68.&lt;/ref&gt;
|crew=one, pilot
|capacity= up to ten passengers
|payload main=1,130 kg
|payload alt=2,491 lb
|length main= 11.00 m
|length alt=  36 ft 1 in
|span main= 15.87 m
|span alt=  52 ft 0¾ in
|height main= 3.20 m 
|height alt= 10 ft 6 in
|aspect ratio=8.4:1
|area main= 30.15 m²
|area alt= 324.5 sq ft
|airfoil=NACA 64-514
|empty weight main= 1,270 kg 
|empty weight alt= 2,800 lb
|loaded weight main= 
|loaded weight alt= 
|useful load main= 
|useful load alt= 
|max takeoff weight main= 2,800 kg
|max takeoff weight alt= 6,173 lb
|more general=
|engine (prop)= [[Pratt &amp; Whitney Canada PT6A]]-27
|type of prop= [[turboprop]]
|number of props=1
|power main= 410 kW
|power alt= 550 shp
|power original= (downrated from 507 kW (680 shp))
|max speed main= 232 km/h&lt;ref name=&quot;Brasseys 99 p489&quot;&gt;Taylor 1999, p. 489.&lt;/ref&gt;
|max speed alt= 125 knots, 144 mph
|cruise speed main= 213 km/h
|cruise speed alt= 115 knots, 132 mph
|cruise speed more=at 3,050 m (10,000 ft)
|stall speed main=96 km/h 
|stall speed alt= 52 knots, 60 mph
|stall speed more=(flaps down, power off)
|never exceed speed main= 280 km/h
|never exceed speed alt= 151 knots, 174 mph
|range main=  730 km 
|range alt=394 nmi, 453 mi
|range more=with maximum payload
|ferry range main=1,612 km
|ferry range alt=870 nmi, 1,002 mi
|ferry range more= with maximum internal and underwing fuel
|ceiling main= 8,197 m 
|ceiling alt= 25,000 ft
|climb rate main= 4.8 m/s
|climb rate alt= 941 ft/min
|loading main=
|loading alt=
|thrust/weight=
|power/mass main=
|power/mass alt=
|more performance=
|armament=
|avionics=
}}

==See also==
{{External media|topic= |width=20% |align=right |video1=[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=92ErTsiMwLw Documentary featuring the PC-6] |video2=[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BMzN_Gb8AXk STOL takeoff performed by a PC-6] |video3=[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=f3hyfkcZ59w PC-6 display at the 2009 Durban Virginia airshow]}}
{{aircontent|
|related=
* [[Fairchild AU-23 Peacemaker]]
* [[Pilatus PC-8D Twin Porter]]
|similar aircraft=
* [[de Havilland Canada DHC-6 Twin Otter]]
* [[Antonov An-2]]/[[Antonov An-3|An-3]]
* [[de Havilland Canada DHC-3 Otter]]
* [[Dornier Do 27]]
* [[GippsAero GA10]]
* [[PAC P-750 XSTOL]]
|lists=
|see also=
}}

==References==

===Citations===
{{reflist}}

===Bibliography===
{{refbegin}}
* Fricker, John. [https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=W9hDaNOiAXEC&amp;pg=PA38 &quot;Pilot Report: Pilatus&quot;.] ''Flying Magazine'', Vol. 70, No. 4. April 1962. ISSN 0015-4806. pp.&amp;nbsp;38, 100–103.
* Hoyle, Craig. &quot;World Air Forces Directory&quot;. ''[[Flight International]]'', Vol. 180, No. 5321, 13–19 December 2011. pp.&amp;nbsp;26–52. {{ISSN|0015-3710}}.
* Hoyle, Craig. &quot;World Air Forces Directory&quot;. ''Flight International'', Vol. 180, No. 5517, 8–14 December 2015. pp.&amp;nbsp;26–53. ISSN 0015-3710.
* Isserman, Maurice., Stewart Angas Weaver and Dee Molenaar. ''Fallen Giants: A History of Himalayan Mountaineering from the Age of Empire to the Age of Extremes.'' Yale University Press, 2008. ISBN 0-3001-4266-8.
* Johnson, E.R. and Lloyd S. Jones. ''American Military Transport Aircraft Since 1925.'' McFarland, 2013. ISBN 1-4766-0155-0.
* Lambert, Mark. ''Jane's All The World's Aircraft 1993–1994''. Coulsdon, UK: Jane's Data Division, 1993. ISBN 0-7106-1066-1.
* Moll, Nigel. [https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=XPB1MpYNfPUC&amp;pg=PA62 &quot;Ugly is Only Skin-Deep.&quot;] ''Flying Magazine'', Vol. 120, No. 2. February 1993. ISSN 0015-4806. pp.&amp;nbsp;62–68.
* [[John W. R. Taylor|Taylor, John W. R.]] ''Janes's All The World's Aircraft 1965–66''. London: Sampson Low, Marston &amp; Company, 1965.
* Taylor, Michael J. H. ''Brassey's World Aircraft &amp; Systems Directory 1999/2000 Edition''. London: Brassey's, 1999. ISBN 1-85753-245-7.
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons|Pilatus PC-6}}
* [http://www.pilatus-aircraft.com/#2 Pilatus PC-6 Porter webpage]
* [http://www.pc-6.com The PILATUS PORTER World by Markus Herzig]
* [http://aviation-safety.net/wikibase/wiki.php?id=27006 ASN Wikibase Occurrence # 27006]
* [http://aviation-safety.net/wikibase/wiki.php?id=161542 ASN Wikibase Occurrence # 161542]
 
{{Pilatus aircraft}}
{{Fairchild aircraft}}
{{US STOL and VTOL aircraft}}

[[Category:Pilatus aircraft|PC-06]]
[[Category:Swiss civil utility aircraft 1950–1959]]
[[Category:Single-engined tractor aircraft]]
[[Category:High-wing aircraft]]
[[Category:Turboprop aircraft]]
[[Category:Articles containing video clips]]</text>
      <sha1>gk53y9q8koimsy21y48s6o73gftj84g</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
