<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Royal Air Force Ensign</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3741568</id>
    <revision>
      <id>746816118</id>
      <parentid>746813064</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-29T19:03:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Dating maintenance tags: {{Fact}}</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10263">{{EngvarB|date=July 2016}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2016}}
[[File:Ensign of the Royal Air Force.svg|thumb|300px|right|Royal Air Force [[Ensign]]]]
The '''Royal Air Force Ensign''' is the official [[flag]] which is used to represent the British [[Royal Air Force]]. The ensign has a field of [[air force blue]] with the United Kingdom's [[Flag of the United Kingdom|flag]] in the canton and the Royal Air Force's [[Royal Air Force roundels|roundel]] in the middle of the fly.

The RAF Ensign was introduced in 1921 after some opposition from senior members of the Royal Navy. Various countries' air force ensigns have been based upon the RAF's ensign. Currently it is flown from the flagstaff of every [[Royal Air Force station]] during daylight hours and has been permanently displayed on the [[Cenotaph]] in London since 1943.

==Early history and authorisation==
Ever since the formation of the RAF in 1918, the [[Air Council]] had wanted to introduce a flag which would be flown at RAF stations. However, the [[Admiralty]] had the right to veto the introduction of any new flag that was to be flown within the [[British Empire]] or on a British vessel.  Although the Admiralty were initially opposed to granting the RAF its own flag, after considerable pressure from the Air Council, they reluctantly agreed to the introduction of such a flag, stating that the Air Force should adopt the Union Flag defaced with a suitable device. The Air Council did not welcome the Admiralty's condition, as they wished to use the [[White Ensign]] with the St George's Cross removed.  Whilst the [[War Office]] had no objections to this proposed design, the Admiralty certainly did, and they rejected the Air Council's suggestion on the basis that the White Ensign was exclusively reserved for [[Royal Navy]] use.

The Air Council then submitted a design featuring a jack with a white border, but the Admiralty rejected this submission, as it was the already in use as the signal to summon a ship's pilot. The Air Council then re-submitted the original design which, unsurprisingly, was rejected once again.

When the situation came to the attention of [[George V of the United Kingdom|King George V]], he suggested that the matter be referred to the Cabinet. Although papers were drafted, the question was never debated in Cabinet.

The dispute soon became more widely known and various designs were suggested by members of the public. Although none of these suggestions were accepted, the idea that the [[Roundel]] (which had been used by both the [[Royal Flying Corps]] and the [[Royal Naval Air Service]]) might be adopted was viewed favourably by senior RAF commanders.
[[Air Vice Marshal]] Sir [[John Salmond]] suggested that the [[Union Flag]] be placed in the canton in order that the design carry the mark of British authority.  The Air Council subsequently agreed upon the design in use today as their preferred option.

The [[Chief of the Air Staff (United Kingdom)|Chief of the Air Staff]], [[Air Marshal]] Sir [[Hugh Trenchard, 1st Viscount Trenchard|Hugh Trenchard]], then brought the design before King George V who approved the design. The design was then sent to the Admiralty and it was accepted as an Ensign in December 1920. On 24 March 1921, the King signed an [[Order in Council]] ratifying its use.

The official design code for the RAF Ensign is &quot;UNKG0018&quot; and the azure blue used is &quot;NATO stock no.8305-99-130-4578, Polyester Bunting in Pantone 549C&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;FOTW&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://flagspot.net/flags/gb-raf.html |title=United Kingdom: Royal Air Force |website=[[Flags of the World]] |accessdate=5 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Use on the Cenotaph==
[[File:The Cenotaph, Whitehall, London (14 July 2011) 2.jpg|thumb|left|The Cenotaph, London.]]
Following the institution of the RAF Ensign in 1921, there were occasional suggestions that it should be flown on the [[The Cenotaph, Whitehall|Cenotaph]]. These suggestions were rejected, as the RAF Ensign had not been created until after the [[World War I|Great War]], and the RAF itself had only been established for the last seven months of the War. At this time a Union Flag, a White Ensign and a [[Red Ensign]] were flown on one side of the Cenotaph and a Union Flag, a White Ensign and a [[Blue Ensign]] were flown on the other side.

During February 1943, the [[Chief of the Air Staff (United Kingdom)|Chief of the Air Staff]], [[Air Chief Marshal]] [[Charles Portal, 1st Viscount Portal of Hungerford|Sir Charles Portal]], succeeded in getting the informal agreement of [[Buckingham Palace]] that the RAF should be represented on the Cenotaph by the flying of RAF ensigns on either side of the monument. However, when this request was passed to the Prime Minister, [[Winston Churchill]], he rejected the proposal, stating his opposition to any change.  To make a second attempt at gaining the approval of the Prime Minister, the agreement of the [[First Lord of the Admiralty]] and the [[Secretary of State for War]] to the substitution of only one flag was secured.  The [[Cabinet of the United Kingdom|Cabinet]] also favoured the new proposal, and although the Prime Minister remained opposed to any change, he acceded to the will of the Cabinet.

The Admiralty requested that the substitution be done with no ceremony and only involve the minimum number of people necessary for the task. On 1 April 1943, exactly a quarter of a century after the foundation of the RAF, an RAF Ensign was substituted for the White Ensign on the west side of the Cenotaph, with the change being effected just after dawn.  Later the same day at 1130 am, an [[RAF Regiment]] guard paraded at the Cenotaph and a wreath was placed underneath the RAF Ensign.&lt;ref name=&quot;FOTW&quot;/&gt;

==Use on sea-going craft==
The RAF Ensign was flown by vessels belonging to the [[RAF Marine Branch]] including those sea-going craft assigned to the [[RAF Search and Rescue Force|Air Sea Rescue Service]].

Although the 1921 Order in Council gave the RAF the authority to display the Ensign as they saw fit, the Admiralty maintained that the Order did not supersede the regulations of the Merchant Shipping Act. In 1947 [[Her Majesty's Customs and Excise|His Majesty's Customs and Excise]] took control of an RAF vessel on the basis that the RAF Ensign it displayed was illegal.  After the incident, air force vessels continued to display the RAF Ensign.

==Modern usage==
[[File:No1 Squadron RAF Regiment on Parade MOD 45155860.jpg|thumbnail|upright|The ensign at RAF Honington]]
The RAF Ensign is flown from the flagstaff of every [[Royal Air Force station]] during daylight hours. Ordinarily, it is hoisted and hauled down by the station's duty [[Non-commissioned officer|NCO]] and saluted by the station's orderly officer. The Ensign may also be hoisted or hauled down during a parade.

As the professional head of the RAF, the Chief of the Air Staff may fly the RAF Ensign.  [[Air Attaché]]s and the Heads of RAF Missions may also fly the RAF Ensign.  It is also flown daily from the [[Ministry of Defence (United Kingdom)|Ministry of Defence]] building in [[Whitehall]], London.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.britishflags.net/RAF%20Ensign.html |title=Royal Air Force Ensign |work=britishflags.net |accessdate=5 June 2016}} {{dead link|date=June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the general British flag precedence, the Royal Air Force Ensign is just below the Royal Navy's White Ensign and just above the Blue and Red Ensigns.  The only exception to this rule is when the RAF Ensign is being flown in place of the Union Flag when it takes that flag's precedence.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.flaginstitute.org/wp/british-flags/flying-flags-in-the-united-kingdom/british-flag-protocol/#index24 |title=British Flag Protocol |work=The Flag Institute |accessdate=5 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Restrictions on use===
The RAF Ensign may not be used as bunting or decoration, or draped over a coffin, except at civilian funerals.  In the latter case, only the Union Flag may be used at a British military funeral.

==Other Air Force ensigns==
The ensigns of the following air forces have been derived from or influenced by the RAF Ensign:{{fact|date=October 2016}}

&lt;gallery&gt;
File:Ensign of the Royal Australian Air Force.svg|[[Royal Australian Air Force Ensign|Royal Australian Air Force]]
File:Bangladeshi Air Force Ensign.svg|[[Bangladesh Air Force]]
File:Ensign of Belgian Air Force.svg|[[Belgian Air Component]]
File:Royal Canadian Air Force ensign.svg|[[Royal Canadian Air Force Ensign|Royal Canadian Air Force]]
File:Ensign of the Colombian Air Force.svg|[[Colombian Air Force]]
File:Eafflag.svg|[[Egyptian Air Force]]
File:Ensign of the Ghana Air Force.svg|[[Ghana Air Force]]
File:Ensign of the Indian Air Force.svg|[[Indian Air Force]] 
File:Ensign of the Royal Jordanian Air Force.svg|[[Royal Jordanian Air Force]]
File:Flag of the Kenyan Air Force.svg|[[Kenya Air Force]]
File:Flag of the Lithuanian Air Force.png|[[Lithuanian Air Force]]
File:Ensign of the Royal Malaysian Air Force.svg|[[Royal Malaysian Air Force]]
File:Flag of the Myanmar Air Force.svg|[[Myanmar Air Force]]
File:Ensign of the Royal New Zealand Air Force.svg|[[Royal New Zealand Air Force]]
File:Air Force Ensign of Nigeria.svg|[[Nigerian Air Force]]
File:Ensign of the Sultan of Oman's Air Force.svg|[[Royal Air Force of Oman|Royal Omani Air Force]]
File:Pakistani Air Force Ensign.svg|[[Pakistan Air Force]]
File:Flag of the Qatar Air Force.svg|[[Qatar Air Force|Qatar Emiri Air Force]]
File:Ensign of the South African Air Force.svg|[[South African Air Force]]
File:Ensign of the Sri Lanka Air Force.svg|[[Sri Lanka Air Force]]
File:Sudanese Air Force Ensign.svg|[[Sudanese Air Force]]
File:Ensign of the Syrian Arab Air Force.svg|[[Syrian Air Force]]
File:Zambian Air Force ensign.svg|[[Zambian Air Force]]
File:Flag of the Air Force of Zimbabwe.svg|[[Air Force of Zimbabwe|Zimbabwean Air Force]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==See also==
*[[British ensigns]]

==References==
;Notes
{{reflist}}
;Bibliography
* {{cite web |url=http://www.raf.mod.uk/history/theroyalairforceensign.cfm |title=The Royal Air Force Ensign |work=Royal Air Force |year=2016}}

{{UKFlags}}
{{Royal Air Force}}

[[Category:Royal Air Force]]
[[Category:Flags of the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Air Force ensigns]]</text>
      <sha1>mhmmx48riam69si0kaq2ei20cqjf95p</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
