<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Ruhr uprising</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>25750099</id>
    <revision>
      <id>738770292</id>
      <parentid>737878638</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-10T23:47:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mangokeylime</username>
        <id>20770885</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>edited the sidebar</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12972">{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Ruhr uprising
| width       = 
| partof      = the [[Revolutions of 1917–23]]
| image       = [[Image:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1978-029-31, Bürgerkrieg, Möllen.jpg|200px]]
| caption     = Members of the Reichswehr and shot members of the Red Ruhr Army, 2 April 1920, Möllen near Duisburg
| date        = March 1920
| place       = [[Ruhr]], [[Germany]]
| coordinates = 
| map_type    = 
| map_relief  = 
| latitude    = 
| longitude   = 
| map_size    = 
| map_marksize = 
| map_caption = 
| map_label   = 
| territory   = 
| result      = Uprising crushed
| status      = 
| combatants_header = 
| combatant1  = {{flagicon image|Socialist red flag.svg}} [[Red Ruhr Army]]
* [[Communist Party of Germany]]
* [[Communist Workers' Party of Germany]]
* [[Independent Social Democratic Party of Germany]]
* [[Social Democratic Party of Germany]]
* [[Free Workers' Union of Germany]]
| combatant2  = {{flagicon image|Flag_of_Germany_(3-2_aspect_ratio).svg}}[[Weimar Republic]]
*[[Freikorps]]
*[[Reichswehr]]
| combatant3  = 
| commander1  = 
| commander2  = 
| commander3  = 
| units1      = 
| units2      = 
| units3      = 
| strength1   = 50,000
| strength2   = 
| strength3   = 
| casualties1 = 
| casualties2 = 
| casualties3 = 
| notes       = 
| campaignbox = 
}}
[[Image:Hagen Rembergfriedhof Märzgefallene.JPG|right|thumb|250px|Memorial to the Ruhr Uprising, [[Hagen]]]]
[[Image:Ruhraufstand 1920 002.jpg|right|thumb|250px|Map showing the path taken by the &quot;Red Ruhr Army&quot;, 17-23 March 1920.]]
The '''Ruhr uprising''' ({{lang-de|Ruhraufstand}}) or '''March uprising''' (''Märzaufstand'') was a left-wing workers' revolt in the [[Ruhr]] region of [[Weimar Republic|Germany]] in March 1920. The uprising took place initially in support of the call for a [[general strike]] issued by the [[Social Democrat]] members of the [[Weimar_Republic#Years_of_crisis_.281919.E2.80.931923.29|German government]], the unions and other parties in response to the right-wing [[Kapp Putsch]] of 13 March 1920.

However, the communists and socialists in the Ruhr had previously laid plans for &quot;winning political power by the [[dictatorship of the proletariat]]&quot; in the event of a general strike. After the collapse of the Kapp Putsch, the German government sent in the [[Reichswehr]] (the German army) and rightwing [[Freikorps]], to crush the ongoing insurgency of the around 50,000 members of the &quot;Red Ruhr Army&quot;. This was done with considerable brutality and involved numerous summary executions. 

==Origins==
As the [[Treaty of Versailles]] came into force on 20 January 1920, the German government had to drastically reduce the headcount of its regular armed forces, and dissolve paramilitary units like the right-wing ''[[Freikorps]]''. Consequently, the German ''Reichswehrminister'' (defence minister) [[Gustav Noske]] ordered the dissolution of the Freikorps ''Marinebrigaden'' &quot;[[Marinebrigade Ehrhardt|Ehrhardt]]&quot; and &quot;Loewenfeld&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Noske&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dhm.de/lemo/html/biografien/NoskeGustav/index.html|title=Biografie Gustav Noske (German)|publisher=Deutsches Historisches Museum|accessdate=12 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The highest ranking general of the Reichswehr, [[Walther von Lüttwitz]] refused to comply, which resulted in what became known as ''[[Kapp Putsch]]'' or ''Lüttwitz-Kapp-Putsch''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Noske&quot;/&gt; On 13 March 1920, the right-wing ''Marinebrigade Ehrhardt'' led by von Lüttwitz marched into Berlin, occupied the government buildings and installed [[Wolfgang Kapp]] as new chancellor, calling for a return of the monarchy. To restore order, Noske then asked [[Hans von Seeckt]], who at the time was the head of the ''[[Truppenamt|Truppenamt im Reichswehrministerium]]'', to order the regular army, the &quot;Transitional [[Reichswehr]]&quot;, to put down the putsch. Von Seeckt and the other senior commanders with the exception of General [[Walther Reinhardt]] refused and the government was forced to flee from Berlin. Since the ministerial bureaucracy did not cooperate with the Kapp government, however, it could not govern effectively. On the very day of the putsch, the Social Democratic members of the government and [[Otto Wels]], head of the SPD, signed a call for a [[general strike]] to topple the putschists. It was supported by the ''[[Allgemeiner Deutscher Gewerkschaftsbund]]'' (ADGB) led by [[Carl Legien]], the ''Arbeitsgemeinschaft für Angestellte'' (ADA) and the ''Deutsche Beamtenbund''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Strike&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dhm.de/lemo/html/weimar/innenpolitik/generalstreik/index.html|title=Der Generalstreik 1920 (German)|publisher=Deutsches Historisches Museum|accessdate=12 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Separately, the KPD, USPD and the [[German Democratic Party|DDP]] also called for a strike. Although protests by conservative groups including the Reichswehr soon caused the ''Reichsregierung'' to distance itself from this call to strike, the general strike of around 12 million workers helped bring about the putsch's collapse on 17 March 1920.&lt;ref name=&quot;Putsch&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dhm.de/lemo/html/weimar/gewalt/kapp/index.html|title=Der Militärputsch 1920 (Lüttwitz-Kapp-Putsch)(German)|publisher=Deutsches Historisches Museum|accessdate=12 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

==Strike and uprising in the Ruhr region==
{{more refs|section|date=June 2013}}
The first demonstrations against the putsch were in the Ruhr region on 13 March 1920. For example, in [[Bochum]], 20,000 people turned out. Whilst the [[Kapp Putsch]] was in progress in Berlin, on 14 March 1920, in [[Elberfeld]] a meeting of representatives of the [[Communist Party of Germany]] (KPD), the [[Independent Social Democratic Party of Germany]] (USPD) and the [[Social Democratic Party of Germany]] (SPD) was held. The left-wing workers' parties decided on a spontaneous alliance against the putschists. The SPD, USPD and KPD drafted a joint appeal to &quot;winning political power by the [[dictatorship of the proletariat]]&quot;. 

As a consequence of this appeal and in the context of the general strike, some workers' organisations attempted to seize state power on a regional scale. Across the Ruhr area, spontaneously formed local &quot;Executive Councils&quot; took over political power. These were mostly dominated by the USPD, with the KPD also participating. The anarcho-syndicalist [[Free Workers' Union of Germany]] (FAUD) was also represented. Worker-soldiers were deployed, who controlled the cities.

The [[Red Ruhr Army]], whose strength was estimated at approximately 50,000 members judging by the number of rifles that were later confiscated, managed to prevail over the government forces in the area in a very short time.

On 17 March 1920, units of the Red Ruhr Army near [[Wetter (Ruhr)|Wetter]] attacked an advance party of the ''[[Freikorps Lichtschlag]]'' under Hauptmann Hasenclever, who upon being asked had identified himself as a supporter of the new Kapp government. They took the enemy force's weapons, captured 600 Freikorps members and occupied [[Dortmund]].&lt;ref name=&quot;C1920&quot;/&gt; On 20 March 1920 in Essen, a Central Committee (''Zentralrat'') of the [[Workers' council|Workers' Councils]] was formed, the latter being in the process of taking power in parts of the Ruhr.&lt;ref name=&quot;C1920&quot;/&gt; Another central organ was in Hagen. The uprising possessed no common leadership nor a common political program, although turning ownership of important industries over to the workers was an important issue.&lt;ref name=&quot;March&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dhm.de/lemo/html/weimar/innenpolitik/maerzaufstand/index.html|title=Der Märzaufstand 1920(German)|publisher=Deutsches Historisches Museum|accessdate=12 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==After the defeat of the Kapp Putsch==
{{more refs|section|date=June 2013}}
The general strike was officially declared as having ended on 22 March by the unions, the USPD and the KDP after additional concessions by the government of chancellor [[Gustav Bauer]]. These included the dismissal of ''Reichswehrminister'' Noske as well as changes to social and economic policies. General Reinhardt also resigned. [[Otto Gessler]] succeeded Noske, von Seeckt became ''Chef der Heeresleitung''. The demands by the USPD that a socialist workers' government be installed to prevent a move of the Reich to the right were rejected.&lt;ref name=&quot;Strike&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;C1920&quot;/&gt;

The legitimate government, newly returned to Berlin, issued an ultimatum on 24 March, demanding that the workers' councils put an end to the strike and the uprising by 30 March (later extended to 2 April); the councils did not comply with this. On 25 March, the government of Gustav Bauer resigned and on 26 March ''Reichspräsident'' [[Friedrich Ebert]] appointed [[Hermann Müller (politician)|Hermann Müller]] as the new chancellor.&lt;ref name=&quot;C1920&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dhm.de/lemo/html/1920/index.html|title=Chronologie 1920(German)|publisher=Deutsches Historisches Museum|accessdate=12 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
 
The attempt to settle the conflict at the negotiating table in the [[Bielefeld Agreement]] failed ultimately due to the unauthorized actions of the regional military commander, [[Oskar von Watter]].

The consequence was the renewed proclamation of a general strike. More than 300,000 miners (about 75% of the work force in mining) joined this. The communist uprising brought [[Düsseldorf]] and Elberfeld into the hands of the communists. Until the end of March the whole Ruhr area was taken.

Those involved in the uprising, who were often world war veterans, even received wages from the workers' councils. They often operated in small groups, transporting themselves by bicycle. The ''[[Wesel citadel|Zitadelle Wesel]]'' was attacked on 24 March, but here the Ruhr Army experienced its first defeat. 

The structure of the Ruhr Army was, like the political demands and positions of the different workers' councils, very heterogeneous and subject to frequent changes. In general, one can make out a strong difference between East and West. The USPD-dominated eastern Ruhr area organised and armed itself earlier, but did not support a continuation of armed action against the newly restored Reich government. On the other hand, the mobilization was slower in the trade union-dominated western Ruhr area, but later the continuation of the uprising found greater support here.

On 2 April 1920, Reichswehr units marched into the Ruhr area to suppress the uprising.&lt;ref name=&quot;C1920&quot;/&gt; This force also contained units that had supported the putsch only days previously, such as the ''Marinebrigade von Loewenfeld'' and even the ''Marinebrigade Ehrhardt''.&lt;ref name=&quot;Putsch&quot;/&gt;

==Bloody suppression==
With the support of the Reich government, the uprising was suppressed by General Watter, approaching from the north. Based in [[Münster]], his staff led the civil war in the Ruhr area. Units of the Reichswehr and ''Freikorps'' successfully suppressed the Red Ruhr Army. The fighting was followed by death sentences and mass executions. Those who were found carrying weapons at the time of their arrest were shot—including the wounded. On 3 April 1920, Reichspräsident Ebert forbade these summary executions. On 12 April 1920, General von Watter forbade his soldiers from engaging in &quot;unlawful behaviour&quot;. The actions of both sides in the fighting have been described as showing &quot;a maximum of cruelty&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;March&quot;/&gt;

On 5 April, a large part of the Ruhr Army fled before the Reichswehr to the region [[Occupation of the Rhineland|occupied]] by the [[French Army]]. In response to the Reichswehr presence in the Ruhr, which contravened the Treaty of Versailles, the French occupied towns like [[Frankfurt]], [[Hanau]] and [[Darmstadt]] on 6 April.&lt;ref name=&quot;C1920&quot;/&gt;

The Reichswehr stopped itself only at the river Ruhr, as the British occupation forces were threatening to occupy the [[Bergisches Land]] due to the breach of the Versailles Treaty. By 8 April, the Reichswehr controlled all of the northern Ruhr area.&lt;ref name=&quot;C1920&quot;/&gt;

By the end of the fighting, the participants in the uprising had lost in excess of 1,000 lives, the Reichswehr 208 dead and 123 missing,&lt;ref&gt;Winkler, HA (2006) Germany: The Long Road West Vol 2 OUP, Oxford 371&lt;/ref&gt; and ''Freikorps'' about 273 lives.

==See also==
* [[History of the Ruhr District]]
* [[Hans Marchwitza]]
* [[Wilhelm Zaisser]]
* [[Cuno strikes]]

{{Commons category|Ruhr Uprising}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Bibliography==
* Waite, Robert G L. ''Vanguard of Nazism'', 1969, W W Norton &amp; Co

{{Anarchy!}}
[[Category:Politics of the Weimar Republic]]
[[Category:Labor history]]
[[Category:Labor in Germany]]
[[Category:20th-century revolutions]]
[[Category:Aftermath of World War I in Germany]]
[[Category:1920 in Germany]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1920]]
[[Category:20th century in North Rhine-Westphalia]]
[[Category:Ruhr]]
[[Category:Military operations involving Germany]]
[[Category:Rhine Province]]
[[Category:Province of Westphalia]]</text>
      <sha1>228vil0ljcpyvsjau9sbgwzslchqqol</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
