<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Side cap</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1778218</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750678964</id>
      <parentid>750678897</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-21T06:06:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>110.148.121.61</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Australia */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="27224">[[File:Lt Gen William Fraser greets Air Chf Mshl Sir Jock Stirrup.jpeg|thumb|Senior British and American Air Force officers wearing flight caps]][[File:Luftwaffen Schiffchen.jpg|thumb|upright|German Air Force Garrison cap (German word &quot;Schiffchen&quot;, &quot;small ship&quot;) from 1962]]

A '''side cap''' is a foldable military cap with straight sides and a creased or hollow crown sloping to the back where it is parted. It is known as a '''garrison cap''' or '''flight cap''' (in the [[United States]]), a '''wedge cap''' (in [[Canada]]), or officially '''field service cap'''&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Dress Regulations for the Officers of the Army 1900|publisher=The War Office|year=1900|location= |pages= |url= |doi= |id= |isbn=0-85368-044-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; (in the [[United Kingdom]] and [[Commonwealth of Nations|Commonwealth]] countries). It follows the style which originated with the so-called [[Austrian Cap|Austrian cap]] in the 1890s. There was also a previous version known as the '[[Torin (cap)|torin]]', which had a much more curved top line when viewed from the side. Both Austrian and torin types were distinguished by the inclusion of a fold-down section for warming the ears and back of the head in inclement weather. These two styles are still used by officers of some British units and continue to include this feature. In appearance the cap is similar to the [[glengarry]], but differs by a lack of the tartan, or check trim, toorie, and ribbons typical of the Scottish cap. It has been associated with various military forces from the time of [[World War I]] to the present day, and various youth organizations. A convenient feature of this cap is that when the owner is indoors and no coat-hook is available, it can be easily stored by folding it over the belt or, unofficially, by tucking it under a [[shoulder strap]].

==Synonyms and slang terms==
Other terms for this cap in semi-official and or slang usage include ''garrison cover'' (USMC and USN), '''''flight cap''''' (USAF), ''side cap'', ''overseas cap'', ''envelope hat'', ''piss-cutter'' (USMC and USN), ''chip hat'', ''bider'', ''cunt cap''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=The New Partridge Dictionary of Slang and Unconventional English|author1=Partridge, Eric |author2=Dalzell, Tom |author3=Victor, Terry |year=2005|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|isbn=0-415-25938-X|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=4YfsEgHLjboC&amp;lpg=PA529&amp;dq=cuntcap&amp;pg=PA529| accessdate=2009-06-29|page=529}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Australia==
All ranks of the [[Royal Australian Air Force]] (RAAF) are entitled to wear the blue '''garrison cap''' with appropriate cap badge in service dress and flying dress uniforms.&lt;ref name=&quot;RAAF Manual of Dress - chap 2&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=DI(AF) AAP 5135.003 (AM1) – Manual of Dress|chapter=Chapter 2|url=https://archive.org/stream/RoyalAustralianAirForceInsigniaAndUniforms/c2_djvu.txt|date=15 September 2008|publisher=Royal Australian Air Force}}&lt;/ref&gt; The piping of the garrison cap for [[air officer]]s is light blue, the piping for all other ranks is solid blue.&lt;ref name=&quot;RAAF Manual of Dress - chap 5&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=DI(AF) AAP 5135.003 (AM1) – Manual of Dress|chapter=Chapter 5|url=https://archive.org/stream/RoyalAustralianAirForceInsigniaAndUniforms/c5_djvu.txt|date=15 September 2008|publisher=Royal Australian Air Force}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The RAAF is the only branch of the [[Australian Defence Force]] entitled to wear the garrison cap.

==Canada==
{{Main|Uniforms of the Canadian Forces}}

===Army===
In the Canadian Forces, the '''field service cap''' ({{lang-fr|calot de campagne}}) is defined by the Canadian Forces Dress Instructions as a &quot;cloth folding or 'wedge cap'...Originally designed for wear during field operations and training, it may now also be worn as an undress cap with full and undress uniforms.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Canadian Forces Dress Instructions'', Chap 1, para 22&lt;/ref&gt; The cap is worn as part of the undress uniform by students of [[Royal Military College of Canada]],&lt;ref&gt;''Canadian Forces Dress Instructions'', Chap 5, Annex B, para 2&lt;/ref&gt; and as an optional  item by all ranks of rifle regiments with ceremonial dress, mess dress, and service dress uniforms.&lt;ref&gt;''Canadian Forces Dress Instructions'', Chap 6, Sect 1, para 4c&lt;/ref&gt;

The field service cap was originally adopted army-wide in 1939, and replaced in 1943 by a khaki beret. The coloured field service cap was a variant permitted for private purchase and worn only when off duty. These were in the colours of the regiment or corps of the wearer.

===Air Force===
For Canadian Forces members who wear air force uniform, the blue '''wedge cap''' (French: ''calot'') is authorized for wear with all orders of dress, save for the combat uniform.&lt;ref&gt;''Canadian Forces Dress Instructions'', Chap 6, Sect 1, para 5&lt;/ref&gt; It is properly worn &quot;on the right side of the head, centred front and back, with the front edge of the cap {{convert|2.5|cm|in|frac=8}} above the right eyebrow.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;''Canadian Forces Dress Instructions'', Chap 2, Sect 2, para 15d&lt;/ref&gt; Cap badges are worn on the left side, with the centre of the badge {{convert|6.5|cm|in|frac=8}} from the front of the cap centred between the flap and the top seam.&lt;ref&gt;''Canadian Forces Dress Instructions'', Annex D, Appendix 1&lt;/ref&gt; The cap worn by [[general officer]]s is embellished with silver [[piping (sewing)|piping]].&lt;ref&gt;''Canadian Forces Dress Instructions'', Chap 3, Sect 2, para 9&lt;/ref&gt; Air force military police in dress uniform wear a scarlet flash in the front of their wedge caps showing {{convert|1|cm|in|frac=8}}. Air force members of [[Canadian Special Operations Forces Command]] wear a tan flash in the front of their wedge caps.&lt;ref&gt;''Canadian Forces Dress Instructions'', Chap 6, Sect 1, para 5c&lt;/ref&gt;

Prior to Unification in 1968, the Royal Canadian Air Force wore uniforms similar to those worn by the [[Royal Air Force]], including a blue wedge cap. After 1968, the uniforms of the three services were replaced by a universal rifle-green uniform; the air force, however, was permitted to retain the wedge cap, although in rifle green instead of blue. With the advent of the [[Uniforms of the Canadian Forces#Distinctive Environmental Uniform|Distinct Environmental Uniform]], the blue wedge cap returned.

The wedge cap is also the official headdress of the [[Air Force Association of Canada]] and the [[Royal Canadian Air Cadets]].

==Italy==

In [[Italy]], the side cap was called ''bustina''. It was adopted by the ''[[Regio Esercito]]'' in the 1920s, and by the 1930s it was the main cap used by personnel belonging to the Royal Italian Army, the [[Regia Aeronautica]] and the [[MVSN]]. It remained in use until well after [[World War II]].

==France==
[[File:CRS officer DSC00783.jpg|thumb|upright|right|150px|A [[Compagnies Républicaines de Sécurité|CRS]] in normal gear, standing by a [[Bastille Day]] parade]]

In [[France]], the '''''bonnet de police''''' (or &quot;'''''calot'''''&quot;) replaced the [[kepi]] because of its greater convenience, when the &quot;Adrian&quot; steel helmet was issued in 1915. The French ''bonnet de police'' had a different origin than that of the glengarry. The French headdress originated as a long, pointed bonnet worn by [[grenadier]]s and [[dragoon]]s, having a [[pompon]] at the end of the [[Liripipe]] trailing crown (resembling the English [[nightcap (garment)|nightcap]]). The rim of the cap was folded upward when in garrison, and the tall mitre insignia of their regiment removed, while the falling top looped sideways or backwards sometimes fixed within the rim or knotted by the tassel to the shoulder epaulets to prevent its swinging. Originally the pompon or tassel hung down at the back between the soldier's shoulder blades; subsequently the cap became shorter and the tail hung near the soldier's ear.

By the mid-nineteenth century the ''bonnet de police'' had become a true flat cap with no trailing crown. Instead the pompon dangled from a short cord sewn onto the rim in front of the ''bonnet de police'', hanging above the soldier's right eye. This style of headdress with a trailing tassel was widely worn by both the [[Belgian Army]] and the [[Spanish Army]] during the first half of the 20th Century. It is still used by the [[Spanish Foreign Legion]].

When reintroduced for undress or fatigue wear in the 1890s, the French army's ''bonnet de police'' had become a plain item of dress without decoration. The colour of this working cap matched that of the tunic with which it was worn (either dark blue, light blue or black prior to World War I; horizon blue from 1915 to 1930; and thereafter khaki). Between 1944 and 1962 however this headdress was worn by most branches of the [[French Army]] in a wide variety of colours, which normally matched those of the [[kepi]]s historically worn by the particular branch or regiment. Line infantry caps for example had a dark blue base with a red top. At the end of the [[Algerian War]] in 1962 the ''bonnet de police'', was replaced by the [[beret]] for most units.

In the modern French Army the ''bonnet de police'' is still worn by the 1st Regiment of [[Spahi]]s in the historic bright red of this branch. The ''bonnet de police'' is also worn by anti-riot law enforcement units, such as the [[Mobile Gendarmerie|Gendarmerie Mobile]] of the [[French Gendarmerie]] (at least when in riot control gear) and the [[Compagnies Républicaines de Sécurité|CRS]] of the [[French National Police]]. Members of these units may have to change quickly from an ordinary headdress to a helmet, and an easily foldable cap is therefore practical.

==Norway==
In Norway, this is known as ''båtlue'', literally boat cap and is used by the [[Royal Norwegian Air Force]]. [[Hans Majestet Kongens Garde|The Royal Guards]] use a distinct variety commonly known as ''[http://www.webstaff.no/180000%20Army%20Part%208%20Kings%20Guard%20Dress%20regulations/080531.htm gardelue]'' which is worn in garrison and while on leave.

==Portugal==
[[File:Lusitano horses, GNR cavalry (Portugal).jpg|250px|thumb|right|Members of GNR wearing typical pointed ''bivaques'', while patrolling a Portuguese beach on horse.]]
In [[Portugal|Portuguese]] service, the side cap is known as ''barrete de bivaque'' (bivouac cap) and often referred simply as ''bivaque''.

Two basic models are in use by the [[Portuguese Armed Forces|armed forces]], the security forces and the fire services of Portugal.

The first model has a curved top line and is used by the [[Portuguese Air Force]] (all personnel, except members of [[Polícia Aérea|Air Police]]), the [[Portuguese Navy]] (officers and sergeants), the [[Public Security Police]] (all personnel, except members of special units) and the fire services.

The second model is a pointed cap and is used by the [[Portuguese Army]] (only personnel in training) and by the [[Portuguese National Republican Guard|National Republican Guard (GNR)]].

==Russia/Soviet Union==
[[File:Bustinaurss.jpg|thumb|right|Pilotka of the [[Red Army]]]]
[[File:Dashing_war_veteran_and_cadets_in_SPb.jpg|thumb|left|[[Great Patriotic War]] veteran wearing both a [[gymnastyorka]] and a [[pilotka]].]]

In the Soviet Union, the garrison cap was known as ''pilotka'' (пилотка, from &quot;pilot&quot; — the original cap was a part of the air force pilots' uniform in [[World War I]]). It was the most common type of cap used by the [[Red Army]] during WWII and after until the 1980s. The pilotka was worn during the summer season instead of the winter [[ushanka]]s. It continues to be worn in modern Russia, although more in the Air Force and the Navy, especially among submarine personnel, where its compactness is inherently practical. In the Ground Forces the pilotka has been more or less displaced by the [[kepi]] and the [[beret]] as an undress headgear, although it remains in the regulations. Navy tropical uniform also features the peculiar ''vizored'' pilotka, to protect its wearers from the sun. The garrison cap is also the standard [[Dress uniform|dress]] headgear for women in all of the Russian armed services (except for those units authorised to wear berets, such as airborne troops and marines).

[[Aeroflot]] flight attendants wear a scarlet-colored garrison cap with a gold Aeroflot winged sickle-and-hammer stitched in the center.

==Spain==
The ''gorro de cuartel'' – referred to variously as ''gorrillo'', ''gorra'', ''chapiri'' or ''platano'' – was modelled on the later versions of the French ''bonnet de police'' and has the same vestigial tassel hanging from the front of the crown. The ''gorro de cuartel'' was originally known as the ''Isabellina; ''a large beret-like headdress which also included a tassel and was worn by the supporters of Queen Isabella II during the Carlist Wars of the mid-19th century.

It was in common use by both sides during the [[Spanish Civil War]] and continued in use by the Francoist forces after the war ended. It is now the distinguishing headgear of the [[Spanish Legion]] who wear it in barracks and on parade.

==Sweden==
In [[Sweden]] this style of headdress is known as a &quot;båtmössa&quot; (lit. &quot;boat cap&quot;). It is mainly used by the [[Swedish police]], and also by navy and air force personnel.

==United Kingdom==
[[File:Sir Hugh Dowding with George VI and Queen Elizabeth.jpg|thumb|right|[[King George VI of the United Kingdom|King George VI]] and Air Chief Marshal [[Hugh Dowding]] wearing the RAF Field Service Cap in 1940]]

In the [[British Army]], the first cap to be adopted of this style was the &quot;[[Glengarry]]&quot;, which was authorised for all British infantry regiments in 1868 (although Scottish regiments had been wearing it since 1848). The Glengarry was replaced for officers of most non-Scottish units by a cap called the &quot;Torin&quot; (similar in shape to the USSR's pilotka), which was worn from circa 1884 until 1896, when it too was replaced by a style for all ranks known as the &quot;Austrian Cap&quot;, which had a fold down arrangement, giving the appearance when unfolded of a balaclava, thus warming the ears and back of the neck. The Austrian Cap (officially known as the field cap) was then replaced by [[forage cap#British Army|an entirely different style of head dress]] in 1902 and so went into abeyance from general usage, although officers continued to wear them as a private purchase item of undress uniform. An all-khaki version was also selected in 1912 as a practical head dress by the fledgling Royal Flying Corps that went on to become the Royal Air Force (who continue to use the same type of cap to this day). Additionally, in 1937, a khaki field service cap, described in an amendment to the Dress Regulations for the Army that year as &quot;similar in shape to the [[Glengarry]]&quot; was introduced as the ''Universal Pattern Field Service Cap'', and saw extensive service during [[World War II]] as a head dress to be worn with Battle Dress when steel helmets were not required. At around the same time coloured versions were introduced for officers of both regular and territorial regiments, although these were an optional item and in the midst of war not every officer chose to purchase one. Nevertheless, some did and they were produced in a wide range of colours for the different infantry, cavalry and yeomanry regiments.

Since the universal introduction of the beret in 1947, the field service cap continued as an optional officer's accessory to be worn in barrack dress (as an alternative to the peaked, khaki Service Dress cap). They are still tailored in regimental colours and have become less common with the introduction of Combat Soldier '95 camouflaged uniform (which for the first time serves as both barrack and combat dress), although they are still worn by the Rifles, Royal Artillery and some cavalry and other infantry regiments. A more obscure type known as the &quot;Tent Cap&quot; is worn by officers of the Queen's Royal Hussars only and is unique in that it is not fitted with a badge, but identified instead by its regimental colouring. Its origins lie with one of their forebears, the 8th Kings Royal Irish Hussars, who adopted the cap in WW2 to reflect their long association with the Danish Royal family, whose Life Guards wear a similar design of cap with their undress uniform. This cap is in turn based on the French, 'bonnet-de-police', that was worn by Hussars in the Napoleonic wars and after. The Torin style of cap is still worn by the Duke of Lancaster's Regiment and the Royal Dragoon Guards.

In the [[Royal Air Force]], a blue-grey field forage cap&lt;ref&gt;http://www.raf.mod.uk/rafcms/mediafiles/0F179C00_5056_A318_A8D8F975CD47447B.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; (sometimes called the 'chip bag hat') of an identical style remains widely worn with both working dress and flying suits.

==United States==
[[File:Lloyd_McCarter.jpg|thumb|upright|Medal of Honor recipient Private [[Lloyd McCarter]] of the [[United States Army]] wearing a garrison cap]]
[[File:Omar Bradley, official military photo, 1949.JPEG|thumb|right|General [[Omar Bradley]] of the [[United States Army]] wearing a garrison cap, 1949]]

In the [[U.S. armed forces]] it is known as a garrison cap, ''campaign cap'' (not to be confused with ''[[campaign hat]]'', a distinct form of headgear), ''flight cap'', ''garrison hat'', ''fore-and-aft cap'', ''envelope cap'', ''overseas cap'', or more profanely ''piss-cutter'' or ''cunt cap''.

===U.S. Army===
When first issued to U.S. &quot;[[doughboy]]s&quot; in World War I, the hat was called the '''''overseas cap''''' as it was only worn by troops in France who were given the French type forage cap, as they did not have their wide-brimmed campaign hats with them. The overseas cap could be stored easily when the helmet was being worn. A blue overseas cap was adopted post-war by the [[American Legion]], but the hat largely disappeared from the Army between the wars, with the exception of the [[United States Army Air Forces|Army Air Corps]] (who called it the &quot;flight cap&quot;) where it was authorized in August 1933&lt;ref&gt;Rottman, Gordon ''US Army Air Force (2)''  Osprey Publishing, 18 Sep 2012&lt;/ref&gt; and armored units. However it returned in 1939 with a finalized specification as of February 1941. The hat was widely issued from then on as &quot;the garrison cap.&quot; With the replacement of the service cap and campaign hat, the garrison cap was given branch of service color piping, as had earlier been the case with the cord of the campaign hat (light blue for infantry, red for artillery, yellow for cavalry, etc.). This practice was discontinued when individuals had to purchase a new hat if they were transferred to a different branch of the service (i.e., infantry, armor, quartermaster, ''et al.'') Officers' piping was similarly carried over from campaign hat cords and continues: warrant officers' caps are piped in silver and black, commissioned officers' caps are piped in gold and black, and general officers' caps are piped in gold.

Recently, it has been replaced in the U.S. Army by the [[Military beret|beret]]. Until May 2004, it was also part of the initial uniform issue for soldiers who received their [[Army Service Uniform#Green Service Uniform|Army Green Service Uniform]] before becoming [[United States military occupation code|MOS]]-qualified, and thus being allowed to wear the standard black Army beret. The green service uniform is scheduled to become obsolete in 2015.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=ALARACT 099/2011:  UPDATE ALARACT MESSAGE 202/2008 ARMY SERVICE UNIFORM (ASU)|url=http://www.jber.af.mil/shared/media/document/AFD-120501-101.pdf|website=Joint Base Elmendorf-Richardson Website|publisher=U.S. ARMY|accessdate=11 February 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; The garrison cap remains the default headgear for U.S. Army [[ROTC]] cadets while wearing the Army Green Service Uniform.

===U.S. Marine Corps===
The overseas cap (&quot;cover&quot;) was first issued to Marines in France in early 1918.  Originally Marine officers wore red piping and Marine generals wore gold piping with all ranks wearing the Eagle, Globe and Anchor on the left hand side.&lt;ref&gt;p.13 Henry, Mark ''US Marine Corps in World War I 1917-18'' Osprey Publishing, 23/10/2012&lt;/ref&gt; The cover was made in both forest green wool and khaki cotton.

Usage is common in the U.S. Marine Corps as the headgear when wearing service uniforms (the other option being the bulkier frame-type &quot;[[Peaked cap|barracks cover]]&quot;). In addition, it is the standard headgear for Marine [[Naval Aviator]]s, [[Naval Flight Officer]]s and enlisted Aircrewmen wearing flight suits. The Marine officer's garrison cap, unlike those of the Army or Air Force, does not have metallic piping; the only marking that distinguishes it from the enlisted cap is the placement of small officer's rank insignia on the right side of the cap. Enlisted garrison caps carry no rank insignia, however all Marine garrison caps carry the [[Eagle, Globe, and Anchor]] insignia on the left side.

===U.S. Air Force===
A blue flight cap is the most common headgear worn with the U.S. Air Force's [[Uniforms of the United States Air Force#Service dress|service dress]] or &quot;blues&quot; uniform. The color of the piping varies: solid blue for enlisted, blue and silver metallic braid for [[company-grade officer]]s and [[field officer|field grade officers]], and solid silver metallic for [[general officer]]s. Officers wear large metal rank insignia affixed to the left front of the cap in a manner similar to that historically used by the Army with their garrison caps. No other accoutrements are worn.&lt;ref name=&quot;AFI36-2903&quot;&gt;[http://www.e-publishing.af.mil/shared/media/epubs/afi36-2903.pdf], Air Force Instruction 36-2903.&lt;/ref&gt;  The flight cap is also worn by senior members of the [[Civil Air Patrol]] in a manner appropriate to their rank.  The company grade officer version is also worn by [[USAFA]] and [[Air Force ROTC]] cadets as well as officer trainees at [[Air Force Officer Training School|OTS]].  Cadets in the [[AFJROTC]] and [[Civil Air Patrol]] cadet programs wear the enlisted version of the flight cap, albeit with metal pin-on insignia.

===U.S. Navy===
In the [[U.S. Navy]] the garrison cap (&quot;cover&quot;) was first authorized during [[World War II]], originally for [[naval aviator|aviators]] and later for all officers and [[Chief Petty Officer (United States)|CPO]]s. Blue and white versions, as well as a forest green version for aviation officers and CPOs were later developed, although the blue and whit versions were discontinued after the war.  Today, garrison caps in khaki are almost always worn with service khakis and flight suits. Officers wear a miniature version of the officer crest on the left and small rank insignia on the right side of the cap, while CPOs will wear a CPO, SCPO or MCPO fouled anchor/USN insignia on the left as appropriate. Like the Marine Corps, and in contrast to their Army and Air Force counterparts, the Navy caps for officers also avoid the use of metallic piping. The blue version garrison cap, essentially black, was resurrected in the mid-1990s for wear with flight suits and blue working uniforms.  Enlisted personnel since 2008 have been issued a black garrison cap for wear with the new [[Uniforms of the United States Navy#Junior Enlisted|Navy Service Uniform]]. It has since been authorized for the officer and CPO [[Uniforms of the United States Navy#Officers and Chief Petty Officers|Service Dress Blue]] uniforms. The garrison cap is also worn by midshipmen and officer candidates.

===U.S. Coast Guard===
The U.S. Coast Guard issues the garrison cap (&quot;cover&quot;) to all service members. The cap is serge and is authorized with [[United States Coast Guard#Uniforms|Tropical Blue]], the Winter Dress Blue, and [[Uniforms of the United States Coast Guard#Uniforms|Service Dress Blue]] uniform. Regulations for the placement of insignia are similar those of the U.S. Navy and Marine Corps.   Like the Navy and Marine Corps, and in contrast to their Army and Air Force counterparts, the Coast Guard garrison caps for officers also avoid the use of metallic piping.

==Yugoslavia==
[[File:Titovka.jpg|thumb|A Titovka]]
In Yugoslavia, the garrison cap was known as a &quot;[[Titovka (cap)|Titovka]]&quot; and was first used by the [[Yugoslav Partisans]] during WWII and later by the [[Yugoslav People's Army]]. The Titovka earned its name after [[Josip Broz Tito]], leader of the partisans, who popularized its use during the war.

==Civil use==
[[File:Mange Ram2.jpg|thumb|A constable of the [[Uttar Pradesh Police]] in [[India]] in forage cap]]

Officers and Instructors of the [[Australian Air Force Cadets]] are also entitled to wear a garrison cap with service dress uniform.&lt;ref name=&quot;AAFC Manual of Dress&quot;&gt;{{cite book|title=Australian Air Force Cadets Manual of Dress|date=13 December 2013|publisher=[[Australian Air Force Cadets]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Royal Canadian Air Cadets]] wear wedge caps in Air Force blue as part of their uniform.

United States [[Civil Air Patrol]] personnel wear the US Air Force Flight Cap with distinctive CAP hat insignia. Senior members (ages 18 and above) will wear the company grade/field grade officer or general officer style flight cap, dependent on CAP rank, but will wear a small version of the service hat device in lieu of rank insignia in order to distinguish themselves from actual Air Force officers (e.g., those in the active duty regular Air Force, the [[Air Force Reserve]] and the [[Air National Guard]]). CAP Cadet officers will wear the Air Force enlisted flight cap with cadet rank insignia instead of the CAP insignia, while cadets who are not cadet officers will wear a generic insignia. This hat is the standard cover with most of the Air Force style uniforms.&lt;ref&gt;CAPM 39-1, downloaded 10 Sept 2010 from http://www.capmembers.com/media/cms/u_082203102943.pdf&lt;/ref&gt;

Many uniformed civilian organizations such as the [[Boy Scouts of America]] (which no longer uses them) have used garrison caps.

Waiters at many old fashioned style diners also wear garrison caps.

The [[American Legion]] and many other veterans service organizations wear distinctive garrison caps.

Some commercial air-line employees, particularly flight attendants, wear garrison caps.

Participants of U.S. military [[ROTC]] and [[JROTC]] programs are issued garrison caps for the duration of their studies.

The [[Massachusetts Maritime Academy]] and [[State University of New York Maritime College]]&lt;ref&gt;Maritime College, State University of New York, Uniform Regulations For the Regiment of Cadets, downloaded 5 Sept 2015 from http://www.sunymaritime.edu/sites/default/files/media/Documents/SUNY%20MARITIME%20UNIFORM%20REGULATIONS%20%28final%20%2009FEB15%29.docx&lt;/ref&gt; also require their cadets to wear garrison covers.

[[New York City Police Department]] trainees in the Corps of Cadets and the Police Academy also wear garrison covers.

==See also==
*[[Boonie hat]]
*[[Patrol cap]]
*[[Utility cover]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Side caps}}
* [http://www.army.forces.gc.ca/lf/Downloads/cfp265.pdf Canadian Forces Dress Instructions]
* [http://histclo.com/style/head/cap/style/camp/cap-camp.html The campaign cap]
* [http://www.oryansroughnecks.org/uniforms.html O'Ryan's Roughnecks – Uniforms]

{{US Army uniforms}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Side Cap}}
[[Category:Caps]]
[[Category:Military uniforms]]</text>
      <sha1>fkulw5mtg6uibqzckk3fcg553mvt6ed</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
