<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Siege of Cattaro</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>39025198</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748261002</id>
      <parentid>725915476</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-07T07:54:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Aftermath */clean up; http&amp;rarr;https for [[Google Books]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15233">{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2013}}
{{infobox military conflict
|conflict    =Siege of Cattaro
|partof      =the [[Napoleonic Wars]]
|image       =[[File:IMG 5438Montenegro Kotor (7586309972).jpg|300px]]
|caption     =View of Cattaro (present day Kotor) from the castle of St. John
|date        =14 October 1813 – 3 January 1814
|place       =[[Kotor|Cattaro]], [[Illyrian Provinces]], [[Adriatic Sea]],&lt;br&gt;(present-day [[Kotor]], [[Montenegro]])
|coordinates =
|map_type    =
|map_relief  =
|latitude    =
|longitude   =
|map_size    =
|map_marksize =
|map_caption =
|map_label   =
|territory   =
|result      =Anglo-Montenegrin victory&lt;ref name=autogenerated&gt;Jacques p. 213&lt;/ref&gt;
|status      =
|combatants_header =
|combatant1  ={{flagicon|UK}} [[United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland|United Kingdom]]&lt;br&gt;[[File:Flag of the Prince-Bishopric of Montenegro2.svg|25px]] [[Prince-Bishopric of Montenegro|Montenegro]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Two Sicilies}} [[Kingdom of Sicily]]
|combatant2  ={{flagicon|France}} [[First French Empire|French Empire]]
|commander1  ={{flagicon|UK}} [[William Hoste]]&lt;br&gt;[[File:Flag of the Prince-Bishopric of Montenegro2.svg|25px]] [[Petar I Petrović-Njegoš|Petar I]]
|commander2  ={{flagicon|France}} [[Jean-Joseph Gauthier]]
|units1      =
|units2      =
|strength1   =800 Marines, soldiers &amp; sailors&lt;br&gt;One 38 gun [[fifth rate]]&lt;br&gt;One 18 gun [[Brig]]&lt;br&gt;3 gunboats
|strength2   =600 men&lt;ref name=autogenerated1&gt;&quot;Marshall&quot; pg. 478-79&lt;/ref&gt;
|casualties1 =20 casualties
|casualties2 =All captured
|notes       =
|campaignbox ={{Campaignbox Adriatic campaign of the Napoleonic Wars}}
}}
The '''Siege of Cattaro''' was fought between a British [[Royal Navy|Royal Naval]] detachment and Montenegrin forces under Captain William Hoste, John Harper and [[Petar I Petrović-Njegoš]] respectively and the French garrison under command of Jean-Joseph Gauthier of the mountain fortress of Cattaro (now [[Kotor]], Montenegro). The siege lasted from 14 October 1813 to 3 January 1814 during the [[Adriatic campaign of 1807–1814|Adriatic campaign]] of the [[Napoleonic Wars]] when the French surrendered.&lt;ref name=autogenerated /&gt; The engagement was fought in the [[Adriatic Sea]] for possession of the important fortress of Cattaro.

==Background==
{{details|Adriatic campaign of 1807–1814}}
As part of [[Venetian Albania]], Cattaro had belonged to the [[Republic of Venice]] from 1420 to 1797, when it passed to the [[Habsburg Monarchy]] with the [[Treaty of Campo Formio]]. In 1805, it was assigned to the [[First French Empire|French Empire]]'s client state, the [[Kingdom of Italy (Napoleonic)|Napoleonic Kingdom of Italy]] by the [[Treaty of Pressburg (1805)|Treaty of Pressburg]], but occupied by Russian troops under [[Dmitry Senyavin]] until they left after the [[Treaty of Tilsit]] in 1807. Three years later it was incorporated into the French Empire's [[Illyrian Provinces]]. Austria declared war on France in August 1813 and by the Autumn the [[Royal Navy]] enjoyed unopposed domination over the Adriatic sea. Working in conjunction with the Austrian armies now invading the Illyrian Provinces and Northern Italy, Rear Admiral [[Thomas Fremantle (Royal Navy officer)|Thomas Fremantle's]] ships were able to rapidly transport British and Austrian troops from one point to another, forcing the surrender of the strategic ports, [[Zadar|Zara]] for example [[Siege of Zara (1813)|had been liberated]] in December.&lt;ref name=&quot;WJ6:257&quot;&gt;James, Vol. 6, p. 257&lt;/ref&gt;

Meanwhile Royal Naval Captain [[William Hoste]] with his ship [[HMS Bacchante (1811)|HMS ''Bacchante'']] (38 guns) and a brig-sloop HMS ''Saracen'' (18-guns), under Captain [[John Harper(Royal Navy)|John Harper]] had been given orders for the swift expulsion of the French in the region.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bjelovucic2&quot;&gt;Bjelovucic pg 143-44&lt;/ref&gt; They took part in an attack that seized the islands of [[Hvar]] and [[Brač]] and moved along the coast. Cattaro was next on the target for the British; a body of Montenegrin troops under [[Petar I Petrović-Njegoš]] a popular spiritual and military leader of the [[Serbian Orthodox Church]] from the [[Petrović dynasty]] had surrounded the place. ''Saracen'' arrived first just outside [[Bay of Kotor|Cattaro Bay]] but it was impossible to sail direct to the main fortress so Harper called on the local inhabitants to tow her along the rocky shore for 3 miles. Hoste in ''Bacchante'' arrived soon after with three Sicilian gunboats carrying fifty soldiers and assumed command. The British and Sicilians forced the passage between [[Herceg Novi]] and Fort Rosa and secured an anchorage some three miles inside the outer bay.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cosic2000&quot;&gt;{{cite journal | title=Dubrovnik Under French Rule (1810–1814)|first=Stjepan|last=Ćosić|url=http://hrcak.srce.hr/file/12648|format=PDF|journal=[[Dubrovnik Annals]]|year=2000| issue=4|pages=136–137|accessdate=11 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|141}}

==Blockade and Siege==
On the evening of the 14th Harper left with two gunboats, the launch and barge of ''Bacchante'' and the boats of ''Saracen'' entered the inner bay where he was fired on from the [[Sveti Đorđe|Island of St George]]. Afterwards heading four miles towards Cattaro he found four gunboats in a state of revolt and took possession of them. He then landed at various places where the local inhabitants were arming themselves against the French and collected volunteer crews for his new captures.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;
[[File:Montenegro, Kotor 01.jpg|thumb|left|The Northern walls of the Cattaro fortress]]

At [[Perast]] Hoste found that the locals had taken possession of a French fort with 3 guns which they placed at his disposal, hoisting the English and Austrian colours. At 6am he used these guns, those of his gunboats and the newly acquired gunboats to bombard the island of St. George. Then within fifteen minutes the [[Royal marines]] and the Sicilians under Captain Harper in several smaller craft attacked a French gunboat force off the island seizing all four. The following day the boats of the squadron attacked the island itself and captured it, stationing a garrison to blockade Cattaro.&lt;ref name=&quot;WJ6:181&quot;&gt;James, Vol 6, p. 181&lt;/ref&gt; The prize gunboats each had a long 24-pounder in the bow and two of them each carried a 12-pounder carronade.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Cosic2000&quot; /&gt;{{rp|137}}
[[File:William-hoste-1-sized.jpg|thumb|180px|right|Captain William Hoste who famously ordered guns to be hauled up the mountain to besiege Cattaro]]

By now only the main fortress of Cattaro was left and Hoste, Harper and his assortment of allies - British, Croats, Montenegrins and Sicilians - surrounded the area. With the help of Montenegrins and the pro-Austrian natives of the liberated shores of the Bay of Kotor, Hoste found himself in an unpleasant position between the Montenegrins and their support on the one hand, and on the other the pro-Austrian population who were unwilling to submit themselves to Montenegrin domination. Hoste made sure to remain neutral as his main objective was the defeat of the French in the region. However, he knew that politics would eventually play a role if and when the area was under allied control and therefore also had to try to satisfy the British commissioner in the region [[George Hamilton-Gordon, 4th Earl of Aberdeen|Lord Aberdeen]] by ensuring that the Austrians were the ones to end up with the spoils.&lt;ref name=&quot;Bjelovucic2&quot;/&gt; Hoste meanwhile had been ordered to attack elsewhere leaving Harper with the ''Saracen'' in charge. Hoste in the next month helped to take [[Split, Croatia|Split]] with troops of the [[35th (Royal Sussex) Regiment of Foot|35th Foot]] and for the next month a close blockade was made on Cattaro with the hope of the arrival of Austrian troops. Bad weather had not helped the situation and after capturing [[Cavtat]] further north Hoste soon returned to the bay but found no Austrian troops.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cosic2000&quot; /&gt;{{rp|137}}

By early December the local French commander, General Gauthier, had retired to Fort St. John with 600 men.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt; This fort lay on the side of the hill protecting the Western side of the fortified town of Cattaro. Hoste and Harper both agreed that use would be made of the local armed populace for the final stages of the siege. Preparations were made to place batteries all around Cattaro including the use of the top of the hill of St John as a primary position, right above the fortress itself. Hoste and Harper led their men in the difficult task of scattering batteries down the forbidding slopes of the Cattaro hills using [[block and tackle]]. In an &quot;unmilitary manner&quot; after 3 weeks of great exertion by ''Bacchante'' and ''Saracen''s seamen in continuous rain an 18-pounder was hoisted to the summit on 23 December, a height of nearly 3,000 feet.&lt;ref&gt;{{DNB Cite|wstitle=Hoste, William}}: &quot;in what was denounced as a 'very unmilitary manner,' established a battery of heavy guns and mortars on the top of a rugged hill which dominated the enemy's position.&quot;&lt;/ref&gt;  Meanwhile ''Bacchante'' and the rest of her crew mounted further pieces of ordnance; two batteries of 18 and 32-pounders were added. Hoste, despite being ill, personally helped the men get the equipment up the slopes of the mountain but further North and South respectively of the fort and the main battery on the slope.&lt;ref name=autogenerated1 /&gt;

On Christmas Day, with all guns in position and with the return of good weather, Hoste ordered the commencement of the bombardment. Fire was opened up from four different points, with the 18 pounder above the St John fortress being particularly effective. ''Saracen'' and ''Bacchante'' stayed out of range of the fort's guns until the bombardment started but then opened up with all they had. Hoste on the 2nd ordered Harper to lead a surprise night time assault. This was not necessary, however, as on 3 January 1814, when Harper was about to lead an assault, Gauthier offered to surrender. After ten days of shelling and no hope of relief the French surrendered to Hoste under honourable conditions and the British and Montenegrins took control of the fort and the town.&lt;ref name=phillips/&gt; After a ten-day siege, the French garrison had no alternative and surrendered on 5 January 1814.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nafziger&quot;&gt;&quot;Nafziger, Gioannini&quot; pg. 148-9&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=phillips&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ageofnelson.org/MichaelPhillips/info.php?ref=0265|author=Michael Phillips' Ships of the Old Navy |title=Bacchante (38)|accessdate=2008-11-16|quote=)n 1 January 1814 two additional batteries of 18 and 32-pounders began to play on the castle.}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:CattaroMedal.jpg|thumb|right|155px|Medal commemorating HMS ''Bacchante's'' bombardment of Cattaro 1814]]

==Aftermath==
The loss on the British, amounting to only one seaman killed, and Lieutenant of marines slightly wounded. In the course of the twenty-day siege, Hoste had counted on the support of Austrian infantry which failed to show up. Hoste signed the articles of capitulation and the remaining French and Italian troops marched out in surrender, after which British troops marched in along with the Montenegrins. Hoste gave the town to the Montenegrin commission under Peter which aggravated Lord Aberdeen but Hoste argued that he had no choice in the matter.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Stevenson|first=Francis Seymour|title=A History of Montenegro|date=1 May 1971|publisher=Arno Press|isbn=9780405027758|page=176|url=https://books.google.com/books?ei=jGuKUcqiF6mW0QW20ICACw&amp;id=XQQ_AQAAIAAJ&amp;dq=hoste+lord+aberdeen+cattaro&amp;q=lord+aberdeen+#search_anchor}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{citation needed|date=April 2013}}

Hoste with ''Bacchante'' and ''Saracen'' after a short rest and recuperation left Cattaro to sail to the fortress of [[Dubrovnik|Ragusa]] where they [[Siege of Ragusa|laid siege]] to the place in a very similar manner to Cattaro and on the 28th it surrendered.&lt;ref name=&quot;Cosic2000&quot; /&gt;{{rp|141}} By the end of March all towns and cities had surrendered to the British or the allied rebels that had risen in revolt, leaving the Adriatic in complete allied control with the exception of Corfu. Cattaro was restored to the [[Habsburg Monarchy]] of the [[Austrian Empire]] by the [[Congress of Vienna]].&lt;ref&gt;Die postalischen Abstempelungen auf den österreichischen Postwertzeichen-Ausgaben 1867, 1883 und 1890, Wilhelm KLEIN, 1967&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Fortifications of Kotor]]
* [[Siege of Ragusa]]
{{Wikipedia books|Adriatic campaign of 1807–1814}}

==References==
;Citations
{{reflist|2}}
;Bibliography
* {{cite book| last1 =  Nafziger| first1 = George F.| last2 = Gioannini| first2 = Marco | year = 2011| title = The Defense of the Napoleonic Kingdom of Northern Italy, 1813-1814| publisher = Greenwood Press | isbn = 0275967972 }}
* {{cite book | last = Bentley | first = R.| year = 1833| title = Memoirs and Letters of Capt. Sir William Hoste, Bart, Volume 2| id = }}
* {{cite book| last = Bjelovucic | first = Harriet| year = 1970| title = The Ragusan Republic: Victim of Napoleon and its own conservatism| publisher = Brill | ASIN=B0006D1YHY}}
* {{cite book | last = Chandler | first = David| authorlink = David G. Chandler | year = 1999 |origyear=1993| title = Dictionary of the Napoleonic Wars | publisher = Wordsworth Military Library| isbn = 1-84022-203-4}}
* {{cite book | last = Clowes | first = William Laird| authorlink = William Laird Clowes| year = 1997| title = The Royal Navy, A History from the Earliest Times to 1900, Volume V.| publisher = Chatham Publishing| isbn = 1-86176-014-0}}
* {{cite book| last= Jaques| first= Tony| year= 2006| title= Dictionary of Battles and Sieges: A Guide to 8500 Battles from Antiquity Through the Twenty-first Century| publisher= Greenwood Pres| isbn= 978-0313335365}}
* {{cite book| last = James| first = William| authorlink = William James (naval historian) | year = 2002 |origyear=1827 | chapter =| title = The Naval History of Great Britain, Volume 5, 1808–1811| publisher = Conway Maritime Press | isbn = 0-85177-909-3}}
* {{cite book | last =  Marshall | first = John | year = 2010| title = Royal Naval Biography 12 Volume Set: Royal Naval Biography| publisher = Cambridge University Press| isbn = 978-1108022668}}
* {{cite book | last = Smith | first = Digby| year = 1998 | title = The Napoleonic Wars Data Book| publisher = Greenhill Books| isbn = 1-85367-276-9}}
* {{cite book| last= White| first= Colin| year= 2005| title= Nelson the Admiral| publisher=Sutton Publishing Limited| location= Phoenix Mill, Stroud, Glos| isbn= 0-7509-3713-0}}
;External links
* [http://www.pbenyon.plus.com/Naval_History/Vol_VI/P_257.html James, William. ''Naval history of Great Britain'' - Vol. VI]
* [http://www.ageofnelson.org/MichaelPhillips/info.php?ref=1974 Phillips, Michael. ''HMS Saracan - Age of Nelson - Ships of the Old Navy'']

{{coord missing}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Cattaro, Siege of (1814)}}
[[Category:1814 in Europe]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1814]]
[[Category:History of the Adriatic Sea]]
[[Category:Sieges involving France]]
[[Category:Sieges involving Montenegro]]
[[Category:Sieges involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Sieges of the Napoleonic Wars]]
[[Category:19th century in Montenegro]]</text>
      <sha1>c8h2gyl1t42081tstk8ibjpzsb6o9sz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
