<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Singeing the King of Spain's Beard</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>22303374</id>
    <revision>
      <id>737456847</id>
      <parentid>735710816</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-02T22:26:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lord Eastfarthing</username>
        <id>11187569</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16123">
{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2015}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Singeing the King of Spain's Beard
| partof      = the [[Anglo–Spanish War (1585)|Anglo–Spanish War]]
| image       = [[File:AtaqueDrakes.jpg|300px]]
| caption     = Drake's map of his attack on Cádiz.
| date        = 12 April – 6 July 1587&lt;ref name=&quot;fecha&quot;&gt;[[New Style]], Gregorian Calendar. English sources often give dates from Julian cal. (old style)&lt;/ref&gt;
| place       = [[Bay of Cádiz]], [[Algarve]], [[Lisbon]] and the [[Azores]]
| result      = English victory
| combatant1  = {{flagdeco|Spain|1506}} [[Habsburg Spain]]
* {{flagicon|Portugal|1578}} [[Iberian Union|Portugal under Philip of Spain]]
| combatant2  = {{flagdeco|Kingdom of England}} [[Kingdom of England|Elizabethan England]]
| commander1  = [[Alonso Pérez de Guzmán, 7th Duke of Medina Sidonia|Duke of Medina Sidonia]] (Cádiz)&lt;br /&gt;[[Álvaro de Bazán]] (Lisbon)
| commander2  = [[Francis Drake]]
| strength1   =
| strength2   =
| strength3   =
| casualties1 = 100 ships destroyed, captured or sunk&lt;ref name=&quot;Hakluyt&quot; /&gt;
| casualties2 = Unknown but many to disease
| casualties3 =
| campaignbox ={{Campaignbox Anglo-Spanish War}}
}}

'''Singeing the King of Spain's Beard''' is the name derisively given&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;&gt;''[https://books.google.com/books?id=nqYNAAAAQAAJ&amp;pg=PA113 The Life, Voyages, and Exploits of Sir Francis Drake: With Numerous Original Letters From Him And The Lord High Admiral To The Queen And Great Officers Of State]'' John Barrow, Esq, F.S.A, 1844&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[https://books.google.com/books?id=1KndC335GBAC&amp;pg=PA43 Elizabethan Sea Dogs 1560-1605]'' Angus Konstam, 2000&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[https://books.google.com/books?id=jXLqAgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA212 Elizabethan Sea-Dogs: Sir Francis Drake and his Companions]'' William Wood, 2014&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[https://books.google.com/books?id=0c9FAQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT67 The Spanish Armadas]'' Winston Graham, 2013&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[https://books.google.com/books?id=sl4aAQAAIAAJ&amp;q=%22Singeing+the+King+of+Spain%27s+Beard%22++drake+-wikipedia+-%22Books,+LLC%22&amp;dq=%22Singeing+the+King+of+Spain%27s+Beard%22++drake+-wikipedia+-%22Books,+LLC%22&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=RUxiU4zGGsT9ygPItoKYCQ&amp;ved=0CP8BEOgBMCY Sir Francis Drake]'' Peter Whitfield, 2004&lt;/ref&gt; to the attack in April and May 1587 in the [[Bay of Cádiz]], by the English [[privateer]] [[Francis Drake]] against the Spanish naval forces assembling at [[Cádiz]]. Much of the Spanish fleet was destroyed, and substantial supplies were destroyed or captured. There followed a series of raiding parties against several [[Fort#Early modern|forts]] along the Portuguese coast. A [[Spanish treasure ship]], returning from the Indies, was also captured. The damage caused by the English delayed Spanish [[Spanish Armada|plans to invade England]] by more than a year, yet did not dispel them.

==Background==
In the second half of the 16th century a series of economic, political and religious circumstances created tensions in the relations between [[England]] and [[Spain]]. [[Protestant Reformation|Protestant]] England came into direct confrontation with [[Counter-Reformation|Catholic]] Spain; [[Elizabeth I of England]] had been [[excommunicate]]d by 
[[Pope Pius V]] in 1570 whilst in 1584 [[Philip II of Spain]] had signed the Treaty of Joinville with the [[Catholic League (French)|French Catholic League]] with the aim of eradicating [[Protestantism]].

The constant raids by English [[privateer]]s against [[Spanish Main|Spanish territories in the West Indies]] and against the [[Spanish treasure fleet]], which carried the wealth that supported [[Madrid|Madrid's]] finances, were considered by the Spanish as a threat to their economic interests. The support of the English for the [[Dutch Republic|United Provinces]], who were at this time engaged in the [[Eighty Years' War]] against Spain with the intention of gaining their independence, was sealed by the [[Treaty of Nonsuch]] in 1585, whereby it was agreed to form an Anglo-Dutch military alliance against Spain. The English support for the pretender to the Portuguese throne, [[António, Prior of Crato|Dom António]], was another source of contention.

The increasing power of the [[Spanish Empire]], which in 1580 had entered a [[dynastic union]] with the [[Iberian Union|kingdom of Portugal]] and [[Portuguese Empire|its empire]] under Philip of Spain, was [[Spanish colonization of the Americas|expanding in the Americas]] and had the support of the [[House of Habsburg|German Habsburgs]] as well as the Italian princes, was regarded by the English as a major threat to their security.

In 1585 the tension between the two countries erupted into the [[Anglo-Spanish War (1585–1604)|Anglo-Spanish War of 1585–1604]]. Philip II ordered the arming of a great military fleet, which was to become known as the [[Spanish Armada|Invincible Armada]], and it was hastily assembled in the Spanish port of [[Cádiz]] and in the Portuguese port of [[Lisbon]] with the objective of invading England.

==Drake's expedition==
===Preparations===
[[File:Francis Drake and Queen Elizabeth.gif|thumb|left|175px|Francis Drake in an audience with Queen Elizabeth]]
Queen Elizabeth gave the English privateer, Sir [[Francis Drake]], an outstanding leader of [[Francis Drake#Great Expedition|previous naval expeditions]], the command of a fleet whose mission was to inspect the Spanish military preparations, intercept their supplies, attack the fleet and if possible the Spanish ports.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barrow&quot;&gt;John Barrow: [https://books.google.com/books?id=nqYNAAAAQAAJ&amp;oe=UTF-8 ''The life, voyages, and exploits of Admiral Sir Francis Drake''.]&lt;/ref&gt; To that end, the Queen put at Drake's disposal four Royal Naval [[galleon]]s: the [[English ship Bonaventure (1567)|''Elizabeth Bonaventure'']], which was under Drake's own command; [[English ship Lion (1557)|''Golden Lion'']], captained by William Burroughs; [[English ship Rainbow (1586)|''Rainbow'']], under Captain Bellingham; and [[English ship Dreadnought (1573)|''Dreadnought'']] under Captain Thomas Fenner. A further twenty [[cargo ship|merchantmen]] and armed [[Full-rigged pinnace|pinnaces]] joined forces with the expedition.&lt;ref name=&quot;Barrow&quot; /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[John Lothrop Motley]]: [http://www.gutenberg.org/dirs/etext04/jm53v10.txt ''History of the Netherlands''] reference to 24 ships and 4 Royal Naval ships.&lt;/ref&gt; The cost of these boats was met by a group of London merchants, whose profits were to be calculated in the same proportions as their investment in the fleet; the Queen, as owner of the four Royal Naval vessels, was to receive 50% of the profits.&lt;ref&gt;[https://archive.org/details/sirfrancisdrakes00lengrich Drake's agreement and relations with the London merchants], pag. 26-27.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 12 April 1587&lt;ref name=&quot;fecha&quot;/&gt; the English fleet set sail from [[Plymouth]]. Seven days after their departure, the Queen sent a counter-command to Drake with instructions not to commence hostilities against the Spanish Fleet or ports.&lt;ref&gt;Instructions to Drake 19 April; ibid, pag. 28.&lt;/ref&gt; Drake never received this order as the boat carrying it was forced back into port by [[headwind]]s before it was able to reach him. Queen Elizabeth had in fact never intended for this note to reach Drake in time and was part of the usual process in which Elizabeth could have plausible deniability over Drake's actions should they not go exactly to plan.&lt;ref&gt;English government's explanation for Drake's conduct; ibid, pag. 43.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Raid on Cadiz===
[[File:1590 or later Marcus Gheeraerts, Sir Francis Drake Buckland Abbey, Devon.jpg|thumb|200px|left|upright|alt=Portrait of Sir Francis Drake by Marcus Gheeraerts.|Sir Francis Drake]]
Off the coast of [[Galicia (Spain)|Galicia]] the fleet was dispersed by a storm that lasted several days, during which one of the pinnaces foundered.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leng&quot;&gt;Robert Leng, On board the English Fleet: [https://archive.org/details/sirfrancisdrakes00lengrich ''Sir Francis Drake's memorable service done against the Spaniards in 1587''].&lt;/ref&gt; After the fleet regrouped, they met two Dutch ships from [[Middelburg]], [[Zeeland]], who informed them that plans were in readiness to sail a huge Spanish war fleet from Cádiz to Lisbon.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hakluyt&quot;&gt;[[Richard Hakluyt]]: [https://books.google.com/books?id=3A5xEsyJzVkC&amp;printsec=toc&amp;source=gbs_summary_r&amp;cad=0#PPA360,M1 ''A brief relation of the notable service performed by Sir Francis Drake''], p.362 1587.&lt;/ref&gt;

At dusk on 29 April the English fleet entered the [[Bay of Cádiz]]. There were at that precise moment sixty [[carrack]]s (naus) and various smaller boats in the port. Further sightings revealed twenty French ships present in the bay, and other smaller vessels were seeking refuge in [[Puerto Real|Port Royal]] and [[El Puerto de Santa María|Port Saint Mary]], which were protected by sand banks that the larger carracks could not cross. Juan de Vega, Mayor of Cádiz, sent word to [[Alonso Pérez de Guzmán, 7th Duke of Medina Sidonia|Alonso Pérez de Guzmán]], who arrived from [[Sanlúcar de Barrameda|Sanlúcar]] that night to take over the defence of the main square. The Spanish galleons, who in the absence of the Governor of [[Castile (historical region)|Castile]] were under the command of [[Pedro Bravo de Acuña|Pedro de Acuña]], sailed out to meet the English fleet but were forced to retire back to Cádiz before the superiority of the English. Gun positions on the shore opened fire, shelling the English fleet from the coast with little effect, but they managed to repulse an attempted landing by launches at El Puntal.&lt;ref&gt;Spanish reference given but inaccessible. To be researched further.&lt;/ref&gt; During the night of the 29th and all the following day and night the battle raged in the bay. At dawn on 1 May, the English withdrew having destroyed two&lt;ref&gt;Despatch of the Duke de Medina-Sidonia to Philip II about the attack on Cádiz: [http://memory.loc.gov/cgi-bin/ampage?collId=rbdk&amp;fileName=d005/rbdkd005.db&amp;recNum=0 Facsimil] y [http://www.loc.gov/rr/rarebook/catalog/drake/drake-7-cadizraid.html transcripción].&lt;/ref&gt; or three&lt;ref&gt;Letter of [[Francis Drake]] to [[Francis Walsingham]], secretary to Elizabeth I, [https://archive.org/details/lifevoyagesexplo00barrrich (Barrow, p.102)].&lt;/ref&gt; Spanish ships, with a combined [[tonnage]] of 100.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hakluyt&quot; /&gt; Furthermore, they had captured four other ships, laden with provisions.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.hillsdalesites.org/personal/hstewart/war/Navy2/1587-DrakeCadiz.htm Letter]{{dead link|date=April 2011}} of Francis Drake to [[John Foxe]] British Library MS. Harley 167f. 104.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Portugal===
[[File:ÁlvaroDeBazánRafaelTegeo1828.jpg|thumb|right|200px|upright|alt=Portrait of Alvaro de Bazán.|Don Álvaro de Bazán]]
After leaving Cadiz, Drake's fleet set course along the south-west coast of Spain and Portugal, destroying all the shipping they encountered, including fishing vessels. On 14 May, 1,000 men disembarked at [[Lagos, Portugal|Lagos]] in the [[Algarve]] and stormed the fortresses of [[Sagres (Vila do Bispo)|Sagres]], Baleeira, Beliche and [[Cape St. Vincent]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://amerilis.iespana.es/alonsoperez/6parte/1suenoingles.htm Amerilis.]&lt;/ref&gt; From there the fleet sailed towards Lisbon where [[Álvaro de Bazán, 1st Marquis of Santa Cruz]] was supervising the preparations of the fleet that was to join the Cádiz fleet for the invasion of England. The English fleet stopped in [[Cascais]], from where they proposed to Alvaro de Bazán an exchange of prisoners. Bazán responded that he was neither holding any English subject nor was he preparing for any action against England. There was an exchange of artillery fire between the English fleet and the Spanish-Portuguese shore batteries, producing minor damage and no casualties.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leng&quot; /&gt; Drake gave the order to weigh anchor and return to Sagres, where the English troops were supplied with water, whilst confronting the Spanish [[caravel]]s that had pursued them from Cádiz. On June 2nd the English sick and wounded were evacuated back to England. That same night a storm broke which prevented further sailing for three days.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leng&quot; /&gt;

Second in command Captain [[William Burroughs (disambiguation)|William Burroughs]] considered the decision to land in the Algarve as dangerous and unnecessary. Drake's plans to sail to the [[Terceira Island|Isle of Terceira]] drove Burroughs to contradict Drake's orders, prompting Drake to relieve him of his command and place him under arrest.&lt;ref&gt;Barrow, p.108&lt;/ref&gt; Burroughs would be sent back to England, leaving Drake with only nine ships.&lt;ref name=&quot;Leng&quot; /&gt;

===Capture of ''São Filipe'' off the Azores===
[[File:Theodore de Bry - Harbour scene (colorized).jpg|thumb|right|175px|Portuguese [[carrack]]s unload cargo in Lissabon. Original engraving by [[Theodor de Bry]], 1593, coloured at a later date.]]
On June 8th, Drake's fleet sighted  a Portuguese carrack, the ''São Filipe'', twenty [[League (unit)|leagues]] from the Island of [[São Miguel Island|São Miguel]], returning from the Indies laden with treasure. After a brief exchange of fire it was [[prize ship|captured]], the first ship to be so on the return run from the Indies. Its enormous fortune of [[gold]], [[spices]] and [[silk]] was valued at £108,000&lt;ref&gt;[https://archive.org/details/sirfrancisdrakes00lengrich Inventory of the cargo of the ''San Felipe''], p.50&lt;/ref&gt; (of which 10% was to go to Drake&lt;ref&gt;Hans P. Kraus: [http://www.loc.gov/rr/rarebook/catalog/drake/drake-7-cadizraid.html ''Sir Francis Drake: A pictorial biography''].&lt;/ref&gt;); the fleet returned to England, arriving on July 6th.

==Conclusion==
The expedition led by Francis Drake was a resounding military success: over one hundred Spanish vessels of different tonnages were destroyed or [[prize ship|captured]] during the expedition.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hakluyt&quot; /&gt; Economic and material losses caused to the Spanish fleet by the English attack ensured that Spanish plans for the invasion of England had to be postponed for over a year. It was not until August 1588 that the Armada was ready to leave for the British Isles.

Documents seized by the English with the ''São Filipe'', which had details of the [[East Indies]] maritime traffic and the [[spice trade|lucrative trade in the area]], would years later be used as the basis for the founding of the [[East India Company]].&lt;ref&gt;Christian Isobel Johnstone: [https://books.google.com/books?id=s5kNAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA110&amp;dq=drake+1587&amp;lr=&amp;num=100&amp;as_brr=1#PPA111,M1 ''Live and voyages of Drake''], 1837.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Explanation of Drake's phrase===

The phrase was facetiously used by Francis Drake to indicate he had inflicted delay, though not crippling damage, upon the Spanish.&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;/&gt; At the time, the best-known use of the phrase was by the [[Vizier]] of the [[Ottoman Empire]]. In 1571, an [[Holy League (1571)|alliance of Christian nations led by Spain]] had destroyed the Ottoman fleet at the [[Battle of Lepanto]]. The Ottomans had rebuilt their fleet, and later [[Ottoman–Venetian War (1570–73)|captured the island of Cyprus]] from the [[Venetian Republic#League of Cambrai, the loss of Cyprus and Battle of Lepanto|Venetians]], forcing them to sue for peace. The Vizier remarked to the Venetian envoys, &quot;You come to see how we bear our misfortune. But I would have you know the difference between your loss and ours. In wresting Cyprus from you, we deprived you of an arm; in defeating our fleet, you have only [[shaving|shaved]] our [[beard]]. An arm when cut off cannot grow again; but a shorn beard will grow all the better for the razor.&quot;

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

[[Category:Anglo-Spanish War (1585–1604)]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1587]]
[[Category:Naval battles of the Anglo-Spanish War (1585–1604)]]
[[Category:Privateering]]
[[Category:Royal Navy]]
[[Category:Francis Drake]]
[[Category:Military expeditions]]
[[Category:1587 in England]]
[[Category:1587 in Spain]]
[[Category:History of Cádiz]]
[[Category:Expeditions from the Kingdom of England]]
[[Category:1587 in the British Empire]]</text>
      <sha1>sepyxf0z5np0qrtu257b8wzpokrjt6a</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
