<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Soldier settlement (Australia)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9701860</id>
    <revision>
      <id>751071767</id>
      <parentid>751071711</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-23T05:53:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Kerry Raymond</username>
        <id>300735</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>fixing wikilink</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="19091">{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2011}}
{{Use Australian English|date=July 2011}}
[[Image:KentuckySoldiersSettlementEstateSettlerscottage.jpg|thumb|right|Settler's Cottage - Kentucky, New South Wales Soldier Settlement Estate]]

'''Soldier settlement''' refers to the settlement of land throughout parts of [[Australia]] by returning discharged soldiers under schemes administered by the state governments after World Wars I and II.

== World War I ==
[[Image:StateLibQld 1 204240 Christmas greetings from the Minister and Officers of the Department of Public Lands, Brisbane, 1920.jpg|thumb|250px|right|Map of Queensland Soldiers' Settlements October 1920]]
Such settlement plans initially began during [[World War I]], with [[South Australia]] first enacting legislation in 1915. Similar schemes gained impetus across Australia in February 1916 when a conference of representatives from the Commonwealth and all States was held in [[Melbourne]] to consider a report prepared by the Federal Parliamentary War Committee regarding the settlement of returned soldiers on the land.  The report focused specifically on a Commonwealth-State cooperative process of selling or leasing Crown land to soldiers who had been [[demobilization|demobilised]] following the end of their service in this first global conflict.&lt;ref&gt;[http://investigator.records.nsw.gov.au/Details/Agency_Detail.asp?Id=3836 State Records NSW]&lt;/ref&gt;  The meeting agreed that it was the Commonwealth Government's role to select and acquire land whilst the State government authorities would process applications and grant land allotments.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web  | year = 2005 | url =  http://www.naa.gov.au/The_collection/family_history/armed_services.html | title = Defence service records| work =  | publisher = [[National Archives of Australia]] | accessdate =2007-02-26 |archiveurl = http://web.archive.org/web/20070126081221/http://www.naa.gov.au/The_collection/family_history/armed_services.html &lt;!-- Bot retrieved archive --&gt; |archivedate = 2007-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Crown land]] was used where possible, but much land was acquired.  By 1924, just over 24 million acres (97,000&amp;nbsp;km²) had been acquired or allocated.  Of this nearly 6.3 million acres (25,000&amp;nbsp;km²) was purchased and 18 million acres (73,000&amp;nbsp;km²) was crown land set aside.  23.2 million acres (93,900&amp;nbsp;km²) had been allotted 23,367 farms across Australia.&lt;ref name=&quot;ABS_YB_1925&quot;&gt;{{cite web   | year = 1925 | url = http://www.abs.gov.au/AUSSTATS/abs@.nsf/featurearticlesbyCatalogue/72BB159FA215052FCA2569DE0020331D?OpenDocument | title = Special Article - Settlement of returned soldiers 1914-18  | work = 1301.0 - Year Book Australia, 1925 | publisher = Australian Bureau of Statistics  | accessdate = 2007-03-02 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other  than supporting soldiers and sailors that were returning from those wars the various governments also saw the opportunity of attracting both Australians and specific groups of allied 
service personnel to some of the otherwise little inhabited, remote areas of Australia. Although the Commonwealth held responsibility for defence, and thus might have taken responsibility for demobilised soldiers, it was the States which took responsibility for land settlement and thus enacted separate soldier settlement schemes.  The States also wished to take an active role in recognising the contribution of soldiers.&lt;ref name = &quot;Keneley&quot;&gt;{{cite web | last = Keneley | first =  Monica | authorlink =  | coauthors =  | year = 2000 | url =  http://www.jcu.edu.au/aff/history/articles/keneley2.htm   | title = Land of Hope: Soldier Settlement in the Western District of Victoria 1918-1930| publisher = The Electronic Journal of Australian and New Zealand  History | accessdate = 2007-02-28}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Areas that gained such settlement included places such as:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.australiandiggers.com/users/anzacs/settlement.htm australiandiggers.com Soldier Settlement]&lt;/ref&gt;
; New South Wales
* [[Dorrigo, New South Wales|Dorrigo]]
* [[Griffith, New South Wales|Griffith]]
; Queensland
* [[Amiens, Queensland|Amiens]]
* [[Atherton Tableland]]
* [[Beerburrum Soldier Settlement]]
* [[Cecil Plains, Queensland|Cecil Plains]]
* [[Coominya Soldier Settlement]]
* [[El Arish, Queensland|El Arish]]
* [[Ubobo, Queensland|Ubobo]] Soldier Settlement Scheme, where one of the [[Soldier Settler House, Ubobo|soldier settler's houses]] is now heritage-listed&lt;ref name=&quot;qhr&quot;&gt;{{cite QHR|17042|Soldier Settler House|602229|accessdate=1 August 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
; South Australia
* [[Kangaroo Island]]
* [[Murray Bridge, South Australia|Murray Bridge]]
; Victoria
* [[Merbein, Victoria|Merbein]]
* [[Mortlake, Victoria|Mortlake]]
* [[Red Cliffs, Victoria|Red Cliffs]]

By 30 June 1924 a total of 23,367 returned soldiers and sailors had taken up settlement farms on 23,275,380 acres (94,192&amp;nbsp;km²) across Australia as per the following breakdown:&lt;ref name=&quot;ABS_YB_1925&quot;/&gt;

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;
|-
!State !!Scheme commenced !! Area allotted !! Number of farms
|-
|South Australia ||1915||2,779,078 acres (11,247&amp;nbsp;km²) ||3,240 settlement farms
|-
|New South Wales||1916||8,134,009 acres (32,917&amp;nbsp;km²)||6,448 settlement farms
|-
|Queensland|| 1916 ||705,565 acres (2,855&amp;nbsp;km²)||2000 settlement farms
|-
|Victoria||1917||2,290,489 acres (9,269&amp;nbsp;km²)||8,640 settlement farms
|-
|Western Australia|| ||9,094,711 acres (36,804&amp;nbsp;km²) ||1,095 settlement farms
|-
|Tasmania|| ||271,537 acres (1,098&amp;nbsp;km²)||1,935 settlement farms
|}

==World War II==
The procedure of supporting such soldiers was repeated after [[World War II]] with all Australian state governments using the previous and amended forms of such acts of parliament to reinvigorate the programme for this new generation of returned soldiers.

==Rules of holding soldier settlement land==
[[Image:TullakoolMemorial.JPG|thumb|Memorial marking the site of the first commercial rice crop in the Murray Valley at [[Tullakool, New South Wales]] ]]
In most cases Crown land was set apart for returning soldiers who in order to buy or lease such a block were required to be certified as qualified and to remain in residence on that land for 5 years.  In this way remote rural areas set aside for such settlement were guaranteed a population expansion which remained to increase infrastructure in the area.

Soldiers who were successful in gaining such a block of land had the opportunity to start a farming life in a number of rural activities including as [[wool]], [[dairy]], [[cattle]], pigs, fruit, fodder and [[grain]].  These initial land allotments resulted in triumph for some and despair for others.  Indeed, specifically following World War I, in some cases these new farmers, unable to cope with the climatic variances of Australia and devoid of the capital to increase stock or quality of life, simply walked off the land back to the large towns and cities from whence they had come.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.abc.net.au/rural/nsw/stories/s1018098.htm Soldier settlers Pt 1 ABC Rural Radio]&lt;/ref&gt;

The success of the program increased after World War II when the infrastructure required for these new farmers was improved as a direct result of learning from the mistakes that came during and after the first attempts at such settlement.

== Settlement by state ==

=== South Australia===
Following World War I, soldiers who had previously worked on irrigation activities along the [[Murray River]] during the years leading up to the war returned to find that their previous jobs were no longer available.

The South Australian government responded as early as 1915 with the first of the acts of parliament designed to both repatriate and compensate returning servicemen, and to meet the political and economic need to 'sponsor' the development of intensively productive agriculture pursuits. Soldiers were informed of the availability of the scheme via the media and in the material provided in both recruitment packages and general information forwarded to men serving overseas.

Settlement schemes during and after the conclusion of World War I saw properties specialising in dairy, grapes, vegetables, grains, and grazing develop along the River in [[Cobdogla, South Australia|Cobdogla]], [[Waikerie, South Australia|Waikerie]], [[Berri, South Australia|Berri]], [[Cadell, South Australia|Cadell]], [[Chaffey, South Australia|Chaffey]] and near [[Renmark, South Australia|Renmark]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.slsa.sa.gov.au/murray/content/europeanSettlement/soldierIntro.htm State Library of South Australia]&lt;/ref&gt;

Following a number of acts that dealt with Soldier Settlement the South Australian government introduced the ''Discharged Soldier Settlement Act 1934'' which consolidated acts such as the ''Crown Lands Act 1929'' and the ''Irrigation Act 1930'' for the benefit of any discharged soldier who had served in connection with the [[World War I|Great War]] and had been a member of the British Army or Navy or of the Australian Imperial Force or of any other naval or military force raised in any part of the British Empire for service in that War, or to the widow (who had children) of any such who had died or dies from wounds inflicted, accident occurring, or disease contracted whilst on service.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.legislation.sa.gov.au/LZ/C/A/DISCHARGED%20SOLDIERS%20SETTLEMENT%20ACT%201934/CURRENT/1934.2152.UN.PDF  Discharged Soldiers Settlement Act 1934]&lt;/ref&gt;

Settlement schemes after World War II expanded to include the [[Loxton, South Australia|Loxton]] Irrigation Area, which became the largest such scheme in South Australia, and to another part of the previously developed area of Chaffey. The [[Returned Services League]] (RSL) lobbied the state government to open up more land for returned soldiers at Loxton, and returning soldiers were informed of the scheme at the RSL through handout material.  Settlement schemes after World War II also led to the establishment of the new towns of [[Parndana]] on [[Kangaroo Island]] and [[Padthaway]] in the south east of the state.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite paper|url=http://environment.sa.gov.au/heritage/pdfs/surveys/20_century/stage_1.pdf|title=Twentieth Century Heritage Survey - Stage 1:Post Second World War (1946 -1959)|author=Susan Marsden|publisher=Department for Environment and Heritage, South Australia|year=2004|accessdate=2007-07-12}}&lt;/ref&gt;

However whilst the first world war settlers had achieved only a modicum of success the benefit of that previous experience helped the second world war veterans, particularly in Loxton, to avoid some past mistakes and with the assistance of the Department of Lands, the community worked together in order to survive and prosper.  Irrigation schemes that eventually arrived saw the advent of the productive orchard and vineyard concerns that became so important to the overall region as it exists today.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.slsa.sa.gov.au/murray/content/europeanSettlement/soldierIntro.htm State Library of South Australia - op cit]&lt;/ref&gt;

=== New South Wales ===
[[Image:ObanSoldiersSettlementEstateCartingPosts.jpg|thumb|Carting posts at Oban, New South Wales Soldiers Settlement]]
[[Image:BatlowSoldiersSettlementEstateSettlersAndFamilies.jpg|thumb|[[Batlow, New South Wales|Batlow]] Soldier's Settlement Estate - settlers and their families]]
The State Government of New South introduced the Returned Soldiers Settlement Act, 1916 shortly after the combined Commonwealth and State meeting held in Melbourne earlier that year (see above).  Soldiers who had served outside of Australia either as a part of the Australian Imperial Forces or as a part of the British Defence Service and who had been honourably discharged were eligible to apply for Crown Lands.  This was land that the Commonwealth Government had acquired under either the Closer Settlement Acts, [[Murrumbidgee Irrigation Area|Murrumbidgee Irrigation]] Act, or was available as a part of general disposal under the Crown Lands Consolidation Act.&lt;ref&gt;[http://investigator.records.nsw.gov.au/Details/Agency_Detail.asp?Id=3836 State Records NSW op cit]&lt;/ref&gt;

Ex-servicemen were required to apply for such land via completion of appropriate paperwork and if successful a soldier could gain additional financial assistance for the purpose of clearing, fencing, drainage, water supply and other improvement of the land as well as for the erection of buildings and the purchase of stock, seeds, implements, plants and similar material necessary for the occupation and development of the land.

By 1917 the state government saw fit to enact the Returned Soldiers Settlement (Amendment) Act, which broadened the definition of returned soldiers to include those who had not enlisted in Australia and those who had not served overseas, as well as providing for potential further categories of soldiers.

In the period October 1917 – June 1917, twelve soldier settlement projects were commenced.  Projects areas included [[Bankstown, New South Wales|Bankstown]] and [[Seven Hills, New South Wales|Seven Hills]] in the outer metropolitan area&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | last = Olling | first = Wayne | authorlink = | coauthors = | title = Grantham Heritage Park Memorial | work = War Memorials in Australia | publisher = | year = 2005 | url = http://www.skp.com.au/memorials2/pages/20776.htm | doi = | accessdate = 26 January 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; and rural [[Glen Innes, New South Wales|Glen Innes]], [[Hillston, New South Wales|Hillston]], and [[Batlow, New South Wales|Batlow]].  Industries commenced included [[poultry]], [[horticulture]], [[pig]], [[fruit]], and [[market gardening]].

New South Wales also repeated the process following World War II with settlements commencing in areas including [[Dareton, New South Wales|Dareton]].

=== Victoria ===
The ''Discharged Soldiers' Settlement Act'' of 1917 established the scheme.  Between 1918 and 1934, 11,639 returned servicemen were allocated blocks under the soldier settlement scheme.&lt;ref name = &quot;Keneley&quot;/&gt; Most settled in the Mallee, South Gippsland, the Western District and the irrigation areas of the North West, Central Gippsland near Maffra and Sale and in the Goulburn Valley.&lt;ref name=&quot;DPI_VE_S&quot;&gt;{{cite web  | year = 2006 | url =  http://www.nre.vic.gov.au/virtualexhibition/settle/index.htm| title = Settlement: Introduction| work = The Virtual Exhibition  | publisher = Victorian Department of Primary Industries | accessdate = 2007-03-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;

During the 1920s soldier settlers struggled and of those allocated blocks under the scheme, only sixty-one per cent were on blocks in 1934.&lt;ref name = &quot;Keneley&quot;/&gt; By 1939 60% had left their blocks.&lt;ref name = &quot;DPI_VE_S&quot;/&gt; The scheme was criticised by a Victorian Royal Commission in 1925 and a later Commonwealth inquiry.  The Royal Commission identified four main reasons for the failure of soldier settlers:
*The selection of inexperienced settlers
*Lack of capital
*The size of blocks allocated
*Prices received for agricultural products.&lt;ref name = &quot;Keneley&quot;/&gt;

It was also claimed that returned soldiers were allocated blocks of land without having established their ability to manage a farm.&lt;ref name = &quot;Keneley&quot;/&gt;

The soldier settler scheme in Red Cliffs, Victoria was very successful.&lt;ref&gt;http://redcliffshistory.wordpress.com/history/town-settlement/&lt;/ref&gt;

After World War II, the Soldier Settlement Scheme was refined in the light of past failures.  Blocks were bigger, were more carefully selected and roads, housing and fences were supplied to prospective settlers.&lt;ref name=&quot;DPI_VE_S&quot;/&gt;

The [[Heytesbury Settlement Scheme]] was one of the last large scale soldier settlement schemes in Victoria.

=== Western Australia ===
In Western Australia, the War Service Settlement program settled hundreds of soldiers, mostly in the [[Wheatbelt (Western Australia)|Wheatbelt]]. Initially, fully and partially developed farms were bought, improved and subdivided by the government, then sold to returned soldiers. In 1949, the price of land rose sharply, so the government began to develop virgin Crown land in the south of the state. By 1958, demand for land by ex-servicemen had declined, but the scheme had been so successful that the government was reluctant to end it, so it instead opened it up to all civilians. This continued until 1969, when a wheat glut forced the government to impose quotas on wheat planting.&lt;ref name=&quot;WA&quot;&gt;{{cite book | author = Jarvis, N. T. (ed.) | title = Western Australia:An Atlas of Human Endeavour: 1829–1979 | year = 1979 | publisher = Western Australian Government}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Homestead Act]], [[United States]] legislation with many of the same effects after the end of the [[American Civil War]]
* [[G.I. Bill]], United States legislation with the same aim of assisting World War II veterans
* [[Roman legion#Pay]]

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
*Australia. Rural Reconstruction Commission.(1944) ''Settlement and employment of returned men on the land : the Commission's second report to the Honorable J.B. Chifley, M.P., Minister for Post-war Reconstruction, dated 18th day of January 1944''. Canberra : L.F. Johnston, Commonwealth Govt. Printer.
*Hawkins, H.S. and A.S. Watson, A.S.(1972) ''Shelford : a preliminary report of a social and economic study of a Victorian soldier settlement area'' Melbourne : University of Melbourne, School of Agriculture. ISBN 0-85873-003-0
*Lake, Marilyn.(1987) ''The limits of hope : soldier settlement in Victoria, 1915-38'' Melbourne: Oxford University Press. ISBN 0-19-554666-0
*Lloyd, Clem and Rees, Jacqui (1994) ''The last shilling : a history of repatriation in Australia'' Carlton, Melbourne University Press. ISBN 0-522-84508-8
*Western Australia (1923). Royal Commission on Repatriated Soldiers of the A.I.F. under the Discharged Soldiers' Settlement Act, 1918. ''Report of the Royal Commission on Repatriated Soldiers of the A.I.F., under &quot;The Discharged Soldiers' Settlement Act, 1918&quot;.''Perth, W.A.: Govt. Printer.

==External links==
{{Commons category|Soldier settlement (Australia)}}
*[http://www.australiandiggers.com/users/anzacs/settlement.htm Australiandiggers.com]
*[http://investigator.records.nsw.gov.au/asp/photosearch/search.asp?series=8095&amp;B1=Search NSW Images related to Soldier Settlers]
*[http://www.archives.qld.gov.au/downloads/BriefGuides/BG35SoldierSettlement.pdf QLD Archives Soldier Settlement]
*[http://www.cv.vic.gov.au/stories/memories-of-a-soldier-settlement/ Video accounts from the Red Cliffs soldier settlement area in Victoria.]
*[http://wiki.prov.vic.gov.au/index.php/Trawalla_Estate_Soldier_Settlers Case Study of Trawalla Estate Soldier Settlers]
* {{cite web | url = http://dictionaryofsydney.org/entry/bankstown_soldier_settlement_milperra | title = Bankstown Soldier Settlement Milperra | accessdate = 24 September 2015 | author = Glenys Allison | date = 2010 | work=[[Dictionary of Sydney]]}} [CC-By-SA]

[[Category:Military history of Australia]]
[[Category:History of agriculture in Australia]]
[[Category:Settlement schemes]]
[[Category:Australian soldier settlements|*]]
[[Category:Military veterans' affairs in Australia]]</text>
      <sha1>1vdp27pmzopaw0dv8j9bpy5xpeafd6y</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
