<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Uniforms of the Canadian Armed Forces</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>3793441</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749887208</id>
      <parentid>749007947</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-16T18:03:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Indefatigable</username>
        <id>20612</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Colour */ Copyedit (minor)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="53219">{{More footnotes|date=November 2008}}
[[File:PPCLI CADPAT.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Infantry from the 3rd Battalion, Princess Patricia's Canadian Light Infantry in [[CADPAT]] combat clothing]]
[[File:CAFUniforms.jpg|thumbnail|300px|The Royal Canadian Navy (pictured here), Canadian Army and Royal Canadian Air Force use distinctive uniforms for ceremonial and daily wear. When deployed, all Canadian Armed Forces personnel wear the operational uniform that is most appropriate for the working environment, regardless of whether they are in the Navy, Army or Air Force.]]

The '''Uniforms of the Canadian Armed Forces''' are the official dress worn by members of Canada's military while on duty.

[[Image:Memorial Stained Glass window, Class of 1933, Royal Military College of Canada.jpg|right|thumb|Memorial Stained Glass window, Class of 1933, [[Royal Military College of Canada]]]]

Prior to [[Unification of the Canadian Forces|unification in 1968]], the uniforms of the [[Canadian Army]], [[Royal Canadian Navy]] (RCN) and [[Royal Canadian Air Force]] (RCAF) were similar to their counterparts in the forces of the [[United Kingdom]] and other [[Commonwealth of Nations|Commonwealth]] countries, save for national identifiers and some regimental accoutrements. With unification in 1968 all branches started wearing the new Canadian Forces CF rifle green uniform. The present ''distinctive environmental uniforms'' in different colours for the army, navy and air force were introduced in the late 1980s and are generally similar to their pre-1968 counterparts.

==History==
[[Image:Ben Weider, Canadian Military, 1942.jpg|thumb|right|Canadian Military 1942]]
Shortly following unification, the service-specific uniforms (navy blue, khaki, and light blue) were abandoned in favour of the [[Canadian Forces]] [[rifle green]], [[single-breasted]], four-button [[tunic]] and pants, with [[beret]] or [[combination cap|service cap]] uniform, commonly referred to as &quot;CFs&quot; or &quot;CF greens&quot;. Though accommodation was made for army regiments' ceremonial uniforms ([[kilt]]s for Highland and Irish Regiments, for example), no allowance was made for the Navy or Air Force, with the exception of a rifle-green [[garrison cap|wedge cap]] for optional wear by the latter. The traditional Navy and Air Force rank names were replaced by the army equivalents, with naval-style rank badges for officers and army-style for non-commissioned members. Navy rank names were restored a few years later.  However, the Air Force retains what had formerly been considered &quot;army&quot; rank (but which is similar to that used by the air forces of many other nations).

For everyday work wear, in environments or occasions where the CF greens would not be appropriate, personnel were issued the Work Dress uniform. This consisted of rifle-green work trousers; a zippered rifle-green work jacket; a &quot;lagoon green&quot; work shirt; and beret. The jacket collar was worn open; the shirt was either worn with a tie, or with the collar open and over the jacket collar. For a brief period in the 1980s, [[ascot tie|ascots]] or &quot;dickies&quot; in regimental or branch colours were worn inside the open shirt collar. Army field units normally wore combat boots with work dress, &quot;blousing&quot; the trousers with elastic boot bands. Many Army regiments wore regimental shoulder flashes on the work dress jacket.

A notable exception was the Special Service Force (SSF), who wore a [[camouflage]] [[Canadian Para Smock|jump smock]], regimental T-shirt, beret, and high-top paratrooper boots, with work dress or combat trousers as applicable.

===Distinctive Environmental Uniform===&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Canadian Forces]] and [[History of the Royal Canadian Air Force]]--&gt;
[[File:Canadian Armed Forces service uniforms.jpg|thumbnail|The Canadian Army, Royal Canadian Navy and Royal Canadian Air Force each have a distinctive service dress uniform differentiated by colour, cut and headdress.]]

Distinctive Environmental Uniforms (DEU) were issued to the CF beginning in 1986. Members of the sea, land and air forces were issued uniforms distinctive to their service or &quot;environment&quot;.  While the term &quot;DEU&quot; refers to ''all'' the different environmental uniforms, in practical usage it refers to what is more properly known as &quot;No 3 (Service) Dress&quot;.

====Royal Canadian Navy====
[[File:Royal Canadian Navy service uniform.jpg|thumbnail|The Royal Canadian Navy service uniform features a peaked cap and double-breasted tunic. The rank pattern and ribbon placement shown on this Canadian War Museum display have since been changed: rank now incorporates an executive curl on the upper bar, and ribbons are worn at chest level.]]
{{main|Uniforms of the Royal Canadian Navy}}
*Ceremonial Dress
*Mess Dress
*Service Dress
*Naval Combat Dress

====Canadian Army====
[[File:Canadian Army summer service uniform.jpg|thumbnail|The Canadian Army service uniform features a beret and single-breasted tunic. This tan uniform for summer use on display at the Canadian War Museum has been replaced with a dark-green version for year-round wear. The rank insignia has also been discontinued, replaced by ''pips and crowns'' insignia.]]
=====Service dress=====
Land personnel were issued new tunics and trousers similar in style to the old CF greens, but with the addition of shoulder straps. They were issued in heavy-weight rifle green (worn with the old CF green dress shirt) for winter wear, and lighter weight tan for summer; in the latter case, headgear, neckties, belts and badges were still rifle-green or on rifle-green backing. Only the Army retained the branch or regimental collar badges on the dress jacket, such non-traditional devices having been abandoned on Navy and Air Force jackets. Army personnel were also issued epaulets that could be sewn to the old CF green service dress tunic to convert it to a &quot;new&quot; DEU tunic.

Recently, the peaked service cap was retired for Land personnel (with the exception of regimental forage caps in the [[Governor General's Foot Guards]] and the [[Canadian Grenadier Guards]]), and the beret (except in Scottish and Highland regiments) is the universal Army headdress. Most recently, the heavy combat sweater was retired, replaced with a lighter-weight [[V-neck sweater]] for Service Dress wear, and with a fleece sweatshirt for Operational wear.

=====Garrison dress=====
The unpopular work dress was replaced with &quot;No. 4 (Garrison) Dress&quot;, which consisted of the old-style work dress pants, a disruptive-pattern jacket, a black web belt, a short-sleeve summer Service Dress shirt with the collar open and over the jacket collar, and high paratrooper-style garrison boots. The rifle-green crew-neck combat sweater doubled as a sweater for wear with Service Dress and Garrison Dress. Due to concerns over the number of uniforms Army personnel had to carry with them on postings and taskings, the tan summer DEU was eventually retired, and the winter uniform mandated for year-round wear. The garrison dress uniform was never popular with the combat arms, as the boots were easily scuffed, especially when doing manual labour; the jacket was hot (being heavily lined) and restrictive; the belt was designed to ride very high on the body and served no practical purpose. Army troops generally eschewed garrison dress for the combat uniform when possible, even in garrison.  [[Land Force Western Area]] actually instructed its units to wear the combat uniform instead, and Land Force Command later adopted the practice across the rest of the country, authorizing combat uniform for all occasions where garrison dress was deemed appropriate.  This authorization is often extended to Land environment personnel in other commands.

=====Operational Dress=====
[[File:Canadian Armed Forces operational uniforms.jpg|thumbnail|right|Different uniforms are provided for naval, field and air operations. Whereas the field uniform places rank insignia on the chest, naval and air uniforms display rank on the shoulders.]]

Until the early 1960s, the Army [[Battle Dress]] uniform was worn both on parades and in combat. It was common to maintain traditional regimental  distinctions, even in the thick of battle. A notable exception to this was the Highland regiments, who were ordered to cease wearing their kilts in 1939 in favour of more generic service dress, the kilt being deemed &quot;unsuitable for modern war&quot;.

By the time of the Korean War, more comfortable combat clothing was being designed, notably &quot;Bush Dress&quot;, in dark green cotton and bearing a resemblance to the Khaki Drill uniform of the Second World War.  Lightweight Service Dress known as &quot;T-Dubs&quot; were issued for parades in the summer months.

In the early 1960s, Battle Dress was replaced for field wear by the '''combat uniform''', often referred to merely as &quot;combats&quot;. It was issued as a standard order of dress for the pre-Unification Army, and later Regular Force &quot;army&quot; personnel in field units of Force Mobile Command and for personnel in field units or detachments in Canadian Forces Communication Command, as well as for personnel in other organizations as required for employment in a land combat environment. Combat uniforms were not issued to Reservists until 1972, although they were permitted to wear it if they purchased it themselves (usually at war surplus stores).

&lt;!-- Deleted image removed: [[Image:Combatshirta.png|right|thumb|300px|Mark I Combat Shirt circa 1970, courtesy of [http://www.canadiansoldiers.com Canadian soldiers.com]. The uniform depicts a [[Private (rank)|private]] of [[The Royal Canadian Regiment]].]] --&gt;The combat uniform consisted of a long-sleeve olive-drab (OD) shirt, with two voluminous cargo pockets at the hip and two slanted pockets (designed for the 20-round [[FN FAL|FNC1 rifle]] magazine) at the breast, and drawstrings at the waist and hem; OD trousers, with regular pockets at the front and back and a large cargo patch pocket on each thigh, drawstrings at the cuff, and buttons on the belt loops for the attachment of optional suspenders; an OD V-neck undershirt; and black combat boots, with trouser cuffs bloused over. The beret was often worn, but could be replaced by a soft OD field hat or the American M1 steel helmet as the tactical situation dictated (while the Canadian combat uniform was universally olive green, American style cloth helmet covers with two types of camouflage pattern were issued; the woodland pattern worn in Vietnam and an autumn pattern).  At the time of adoption, the OD colour was a standard among NATO forces; however, as other NATO forces adopted camouflage uniforms (for example, the British DPM (Disruptive Pattern Material) uniforms, or the Americans their woodland camouflage BDUs (Battle Dress Uniforms)), the Canadian Forces quickly became one of the only first world militaries not to adopt camouflage garments.

Officers displayed their rank on slip-ons on the epaulets of the shirt or jacket; NCMs wore small OD versions of their rank insignia stitched in the centre of the upper sleeve, although for a period in the 1980s these were stitched onto slip-ons, ostensibly to save wear-and-tear on the uniforms, but also providing the ability to remove rank for security purposes. The national identifier consisted of a &quot;CANADA&quot; flash stitched on the upper shoulder just below the sleeve seam, and unit or trade identifiers were worn on slip-ons on the shirt's epaulets; however, personnel belonging to Canadian Forces Europe and other overseas missions wore full-colour Canadian flag patches on the upper sleeve. In the 1990s, the &quot;CANADA&quot; flash was replaced with a subdued olive-drab Canadian flag, worn on the upper left sleeve below the epaulet. Interestingly, these flag badges showed up in full-colour red-and-white when illuminated by a blue light.

Lightweight coats, rain suits, parkas, and other tactical clothing (in OD) were issued to deal with different weather conditions. For winter conditions, personnel were issued white mukluks, mitts, and balaclavas, as well as white camouflage covers for their parkas, trousers, helmets, and rucksacks.

In the late 1980s, the CF experimented with an alternative combat shirt designed by an Air Command officer.  The Mark III Combat Shirt had flat breast pockets and lacked the hip cargo pockets and drawstrings. It was designed to be tucked into the trousers like a regular shirt if desired, or worn untucked like the older style shirt. It proved rather unpopular from an operational standpoint due to its lack of storage capacity, and was considered to look sloppier than the older style; few were issued after initial stocks were depleted but the Mark III was worn alongside the earlier marks by some individuals until the adoption of CADPAT throughout the Army. Today they remain in small numbers in the Cadet program and are issued at summer training facilities to junior cadets for survival exercises.

====Royal Canadian Air Force====
[[File:Royal Canadian Air Force service uniform.jpg|thumbnail|The Royal Canadian Air Force service uniform, displayed here at the Canadian War Museum, features a wedge cap and a single-breasted tunic. The uniform has somewhat changed appearance with the gold having been replaced with pearl-grey on the ranks and elsewhere on the uniform, as well as the gold buttons on the wedge and the tunic have been replaced by silver buttons.]]
Personnel in the Air element were issued a uniform of similar cut to the old CF greens, but in blue, with a light-blue shirt, black necktie, and air force blue wedge cap, forage cap and beret. No 4 (Base) Dress consists of blue work pants, light blue dress shirt (open-necked or with necktie), and optional V-neck sweater. Air personnel were eventually authorized to wear the Navy's work shirt, which was similar in dark blue, though this was recently replaced by a camouflage uniform similar to the Land combat uniform.  Air personnel were issued a blue beret for wear when appropriate; it was soon authorized as was the blue flyer's jacket and [[Gore-Tex]] &quot;line&quot; jackets for use with work dress, then with service dress; the wedge cap is still popular. Forage caps are still authorized for wear by officers as an optional item. Non-aircrew personnel wear a &quot;half-wing&quot; trade badge on the right side of the service dress tunic above the right breast pocket.

====The &quot;purple&quot; trades====
For military occupations that are not specifically designated to a particular element (e.g. clerks, military police, medical personnel, etc.), an element is usually assigned or may be requested on enrolment. Due to the way that members of these &quot;[[purple trades]]&quot; frequently have environments different from their current assignments, many units of the Canadian Forces, when on parade in dress uniform, will display a mix of navy, army, and air force uniforms. As various specialty courses become more widely available, no longer restricted only to &quot;soldiers&quot; or &quot;sailors&quot;, for example, it is not unheard-of to see a Navy clerk in a tactical air squadron with parachutist's wings, or an Air Force medic in a tank regiment with a submariner's &quot;dolphins&quot; badge.

==Current Uniforms==

===No. 1 (Ceremonial) Dress===
Full formal dress uniforms for ceremonial parades and other special occasions. 

* '''No.1 (Accoutrements)''': Service Dress (see below) uniform with medals and ceremonial accoutrements (swords, white web belts, gloves, etc.).

* '''No.1A (Medals Only)''': Service Dress uniform with medals, but no ceremonial accoutrements.

* '''No.1B (Full Dress)''': Regimental full dress (such as scarlet tunics and bearskin hats of Guards regiments). Regimental uniforms are normally not provided at public expense; purchase of these uniforms is done either by individuals or by various regiments out of non-public funds.

* '''No.1C (Semi-Ceremonial)''': Patrol dress (a slightly less elaborate regimental uniform).

* '''No.1D (Undress Ribbons)''': Patrol dress worn with ribbons instead of medals.

===No. 2 (Mess) Dress===
[[Image:Messkit1.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Three Canadian officers in [[shawl collar]]ed [[mess jacket]] and waistcoated mess dress. Miniature medals and other accoutrements are also worn.]]Formal evening attire for mess dinners. Mess Dress is not provided at public expense; however, all commissioned officers of the Regular Force are required to own Mess Dress within six months of being commissioned.

* '''No.2 (Mess Standard)''': Full [[Mess dress|mess kit]] with dinner jackets, [[cummerbund]]s or [[waistcoat]]s, etc.

* '''No.2A (Mess White)''': No.2 with summer white jacket.

* '''No.2B (Mess Service)''': No.3 with white dress shirt and [[bow tie]]; worn by CF members who do not own mess kit.

* '''No.2C (Mess Shipboard)''': No.3B with a cummerbund and without ribbons or name tag; worn as evening wear on board ship. Sometimes called [[Red Sea rig]].

===No. 3 (Service) Dress===
Also called a &quot;walking-out&quot; or &quot;duty uniform&quot;, it is the military equivalent of the business suit; it is the standard uniform for appearing in public (hence the moniker &quot;walking-out dress&quot;).The Navy also has an optional white summer uniform with white high-collared tunic. With the exception of the high collar white option, &quot;Service Dress&quot; becomes No 2 (Mess) Dress by replacing the shirt and tie with a white shirt and bow tie, or to No 1 (Ceremonial) Dress by the addition of ceremonial web or sword belts, gloves, and other accoutrements.

* '''No.3 (Duty Service)''': Tunic and necktie, with medal ribbons.

* '''No.3A (Long-Sleeved Shirt)''': No.3 with jacket removed; worn only indoors, within DND buildings.

* '''No.3B (Short-Sleeved Shirt)''': Short-sleeved shirt, without tunic or tie; worn during the summer on less formal occasions.

* '''No.3C (Sweater)''': Shirt and sweater, with or without tie; worn in place of No.3C in cooler weather.

* '''No.3D (Tropical)''': Alternative tan uniform with optional shorts; worn in tropical climates.

===No. 4 (Base) Dress===
Known as &quot;Garrison Dress&quot; in the Army. It was a more informal uniform, originally for day-to-day wear in garrison or on base, out of the public eye. It usually consisted of work trousers and either a dress shirt or work shirt, with an optional sweater; Army personnel wore a disruptive-pattern jacket. It has been phased out; No. 5 dress (for the army) and No. 3 (for the air force and navy, became No. 3E) has been adapted to replace it.

===No. 5 (Operational) Dress===
Originally specialized uniforms for wear in an operational (i.e. combat) theatre, they have now superseded No 4 uniform for everyday wear in garrison. It consists of [[Naval Combat Dress]] (NCD) for the Navy, [[CADPAT]] &quot;field combat clothing&quot; for the Army and Air Force, and olive green &quot;flying clothing&quot; for [[aircrew]].&lt;ref name=&quot;CFDI-5D-1&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Canadian Forces Dress Instructions|year=2011 |publisher=Department of National Defence |page=5D-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Certain trades such as firefighters and military police wear working dress similar to their civilian counterparts.

[[File:Canadian infantry in Ancon 2010-07-19 1.JPG|left|250px|thumb|Soldier wearing CADPAT TW]]
====CADPAT and the &quot;Clothe the Soldier&quot; program====
{{main|CADPAT}}
Canadian Disruptive Pattern (CADPAT) camouflage replaced olive green as the colour of the CF combat uniform between 1997 and the mid-2000s.&lt;ref name=&quot;CADPAT&quot;&gt;[http://www.forces.gc.ca/en/news/article.page?doc=canadian-disruptive-pattern-cadpat-tm-uniform/hnmx1bjg] Canadian Forces article on the introduction of CADPAT&lt;/ref&gt; CADPAT camouflaged clothing items include shirts, pants, raingear, parkas, and fleece sweaters. CADPAT uniforms are worn by army and air force personnel (as well as navy personnel attached to army or airforce units) as working and operational dress.

CADPAT Temperate Woodland (TW) is a primarily green pattern worn in Canada and in similar environments overseas, while CADPAT Arid Regions (AR) is worn only on deployments to desert regions (such as [[War_in_Afghanistan_(2001–2014)|Afghanistan]]).&lt;ref name=&quot;CADPAT&quot;&gt;&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Web 060714-N-8629M-163 Training.jpg|thumb|250px|Sailors on board [[HMCS Algonquin (DDG 283)|HMCS ''Algonquin'']] wearing NCDs]]
====Naval Combat Dress====
{{main|Uniforms of the Royal Canadian Navy#No. 5 (Naval Combat) Dress}}
RCN personnel wear naval combat dress (NCD) as operational dress. NCD consists of a blue shirt, black pants, and black jacket or parka for colder weather. Originally designed for wear on board ship, naval combat dress is made of [[nomex]].

[[File:Royal_Canadian_Air_Force,_RIMPAC_2014_140721-N-FC670-045.jpg|thumb|left|250px|[[CC-130 Hercules]] crew from [[435 Transport and Rescue Squadron]] wearing flying suits]]
====Flying Suit====
Canadian Forces aircrew wear green [[flight suit|flying suits]] as operational dress. The two-piece flying suit (originally worn only by tactical helicopter crews) and the one-piece coverall flying suit are worn interchangeably by most CF aircrew. Prior to the mid-2000s, the one-piece flying suit was blue and worn by all [[fixed-wing]] aircrew.

==Royal Military College of Canada uniforms and proficiency badges==
[[File:Royal Military College of Canada uniforms.jpg|thumb|right|480px|Royal Military College of Canada uniforms]] 
[[File:Royal Military College of Canada badges 2011.jpg|thumb|right|480px|Royal Military College of Canada badges 2011]]
[[File:Royal Military College of Canada badges (band) 2011.jpg|thumb|right|480px|Royal Military College of Canada bands badges]]
At the [[Royal Military College of Canada]], cadets wear a variety of uniforms depending on the occasion and their environment: ceremonial dress (semi ceremonial); full dress (formal occasions); ceremonial dress (semi ceremonial); outside sports dress; service dress Air Force; service dress Navy; service dress Navy without jacket; Service dress Air Force without jacket; service dress Army without jacket; and combat dress.

Cadets wear a variety of badges, depending on their proficiency and rank. The gold thread crossed pistols are awarded as a military badge for marksmanship when marksman levels are achieved for the pistol; a crown is awarded in May to the top score in the college. The gold thread crossed rifles are awarded as a military badge for marksmanship when marksman levels are achieved for the rifle; a crown is awarded in May to the top score in the college. The gold thread cross swords in a [[laurel wreath]] military proficiency badge is awarded if the following conditions have been met by the student: a mark of at least B in military assessment; positive leadership qualities in the summer training report; an academic average of at least 70%; a mark of at least B in physical training; a satisfactory mark in the bilingualism profile; A crown is awarded to the top cadet having received this award, by year. Students are awarded a blue maple leaf for the minimum bilingual profile standard of BBB. If they achieve higher bilingual proficiency, they receive a silver or gold maple leaf. An academic distinction badge is awarded to a student with an academic average of at least 80% at the end of the year. Physical fitness badges are awarded upon reaching a certain number of points. As cadets learn and demonstrate leadership skills, they are appointed to different positions. The number of bars increases from zero to five as students are promoted. There are 5 no-bar positions and 15 two-bar positions. The brass or gold thread [[lyre]] is awarded as a proficiency badge for brass and reed by the band officer when a student is considered capable of participating in parades.  A brass or gold [[treble clef]] is awarded by the band officer as a proficiency badge for choir when a student is considered to be ready for concerts. A brass or gold thread pipe is awarded by the band officer as a proficiency badge for pipes when a student is considered capable of participating in parades. A brass or gold thread drum is awarded as a proficiency badge for drums by the band officer when a student is considered capable of participating in parades. The brass or gold thread [[thistle]] is awarded by the band officer as a proficiency badge for [[Scottish highland dance]] when a student is considered capable of participating in parades.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.forces.ca/interactive/rmc/kingston/index.html Royal Military College of Canada uniforms &amp; badges]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Maternity dress==
When conventional pattern uniforms are no longer comfortable or aesthetically appropriate, a pregnant woman can wear maternity dress. The non-operational maternity dress is a common-pattern ensemble in light-weight, washable material in three environmental colours. There is also
a white occupational variant for medical, dental, and food services personnel, worn as well by navy personnel during the summer dress period. The ensemble consists of general-purpose items suitable for wear as alternatives to those of service dress and its ceremonial and mess derivatives. Medals and accoutrements may be worn on ceremonial dress occasions. The ensemble includes a long tunic, a short tunic, slacks, maternity shirts in both long and short sleeve, a light jacket and a maternity top-coat with a removable liner.&lt;ref&gt;A-AD-265-000/AG-001 - Canadian Forces Dress Instructions&lt;/ref&gt;

==Uniform of the Commander-in-Chief==
{{Main|Commander-in-Chief of the Canadian Forces}}

The [[Governor General of Canada]], who is the [[Commander-in-Chief of the Canadian Forces#Rank insignia|Commander-in-Chief of the Canadian Forces]], may choose to wear the uniform of an officer of the Royal Canadian Navy, the Canadian Army, or the Royal Canadian Air Force.  The uniform worn by the Governor General includes the following:
* A flag or general officer's cap badge
* A flag or general officer's sleeve braid embellished with the crest of the [[Arms of Canada|Royal Arms of Canada]]
* The crest of the Royal Arms of Canada embroidered on the shoulder straps or shoulder boards
* Various orders and decorations as applicable

==Military police==
{{Unreferenced section|date=November 2011}}
[[File:Canadian Military Police Photo 2.png|thumb|left|Canadian Forces Military Police Reserve Uniform]]
[[File:MP OPD.jpg|thumb|right|Canadian Forces Military Police Domestic Operational Uniform]]
After unification, [[Canadian Forces Military Police|military police]] (MPs) wore the same uniforms as other personnel, distinguished only by a few unique accoutrements: a white vinyl cover over the service cap, a gold-coloured police-style badge on the breast pocket, and/or a [[brassard]] or armlet bearing the title &quot;MP&quot; or &quot;MILITARY POLICE MILITAIRE&quot;.

With the introduction of DEU, these accoutrements (except the brassards) were replaced.  Now the main identifying feature of the military police was the addition of the colour red: a red service cap band for Naval and Air Force personnel, a red beret for army MPs and red backing for the cap badges of air force and navy MPs.  In 2005, the dress regulations were amended to permit all MPs to wear the red beret regardless of their element, with any order of dress that may include a beret, except the number three order of dress for the Navy, in which the peaked cap is still worn, and the Air Force, in which case the Wedge is worn - both of which have a red identifier around the Military Police cap badge.

In 2001, the CF formally introduced the '''Military Police Operational Patrol Dress''' (MP OPD), a marked departure from standard military uniforms: it is immediately recognisable as a police uniform as opposed to a military one.  It consists of black trousers, short-sleeved shirts for summer wear, long-sleeved collared shirts for winter, the naval pattern sweater, patrol jacket, body armour, police equipment belt and MP [[Gore-Tex]] boots, with a red beret for all MPs.  It is normally authorised for wear on patrol duties only, by members up to and including the rank of Warrant Officer / Petty Officer 1st Class. Some units, however, have begun to dress all uniformed and badged MPs of all ranks (including those above Warrant Officer / Petty Officer 1st Class) and those outside of patrol duties, in MP OPD and accoutrements. This is to ensure that all MP are available at any time in the case of an Immediate Rapid Deployment (similar to the US SWAT) scenario.

==Berets==
The [[beret]] is still the most widely worn headgear, and is worn with almost all orders of dress with the exception of the more formal orders of Naval and Air Force dress (i.e. Ceremonial, Mess, and Service Dress). A regimental or branch badge is worn centred over the wearer's left eye, and excess material pulled to the wearer's right.

===Colour===

The colour of the beret is determined by the wearer's environment, branch, or mission. The beret colours listed below are the current standard:

{| class=&quot;wikitable&quot; border=&quot;0&quot;
|-
! colspan=&quot;2&quot; | Colour || Wearer
|-
| style=&quot;background:#4A84A5;&quot; | &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;|| [[Air force blue]] || [[Canadian Forces Air Command|Air force]] 
|-
| style=&quot;background:black;&quot; | || [[black beret|Black]] || [[Royal Canadian Armoured Corps|Armoured]], [[Canadian Forces Maritime Command|navy]]
|-
| style=&quot;background:#414833;&quot; | || [[Variations of green#Rifle green|CF green]] || [[Army]]
|-
| style=&quot;background:#5B92E5;&quot; | || [[Blue beret|UN blue]] || Personnel serving with the [[United Nations]] on [[peacekeeping]] missions
|-
| style=&quot;background:red&quot; | || [[Scarlet (color)|Scarlet]] || [[Canadian Forces Military Police|Military police]]
|-
| style=&quot;background:#800000&quot; | || [[maroon beret|Maroon]] || [[Paratrooper]]s serving in active jump companies 
|-
| style=&quot;background:#FF6600&quot; | || [[Blaze orange]] || [[Canadian Armed Forces Search and Rescue|Search-and-rescue technicians]]
|-
| style=&quot;background:#b21c0d&quot; | || [[Terracotta]] || Personnel serving with the [[Multinational Force and Observers]]
|-
| style=&quot;background:tan&quot; | || [[tan beret|Tan]]|| [[Canadian Special Operations Force Command|Special operations forces]]
|}

===History===

Berets were first worn in the [[Canadian Army]] in 1937 when tank regiments (at that time part of the infantry) adopted the black beret of the [[Royal Armoured Corps]]. The black beret, which is now the headdress of the [[Royal Canadian Armoured Corps]] (RCAC), was first worn by the Essex Regiment (Tank), now renamed The Windsor Regiment (RCAC). This was because the other new tank units were ordered to wear the headdress that they had while serving as infantry. The Essex Regiment (Tank) was a new unit, formed as a tank regiment, with no connection to the Infantry. As such, it picked the headdress that was worn by the Royal Tank Corps of the [[British Army]].&lt;ref&gt;''Dressed to Kill'' ([[Service Publications]], Ottawa, ON, 2001) ISBN 1-894581-07-5&lt;/ref&gt;

During the Second World War, a khaki beret was adopted throughout the [[Canadian Army]], with the Canadian Armoured Corps (later Royal Canadian Armoured Corps) wearing the black beret and parachute troops wearing the [[maroon beret]] adopted by British airborne forces.  The 2nd Canadian Parachute Battalion (the Canadian component of the [[First Special Service Force]]) wore a red beret with the dress uniform. Wartime berets were much fuller in cut than postwar berets.

[[Image:Berets541.jpg|thumb|right|Midnight Blue Beret with coloured flash, worn by a soldier of the Royal Canadian Ordnance Corps in 1954.]]
After the Second World War, a series of coloured berets were adopted, with infantry regiments wearing scarlet, rifle regiments wearing dark (rifle) green, the armoured corps wearing black, and other arms and services wearing midnight blue berets, with a large coloured &quot;flash&quot; in corps colours - dull cherry for the [[Royal Canadian Army Medical Corps]], Emerald Green for the [[Royal Canadian Dental Corps]], etc.  The coloured flashes were not popular and replaced in 1956 with forage caps bearing coloured bands in corps colours.  The midnight blue beret itself was retained, however.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.canadiansoldiers.com/mediawiki-1.5.5/index.php?title=Beret canadiansoldiers.com]&lt;/ref&gt;

When the Canadian Forces unified on 1 February 1968, the rifle green beret was adopted as the CF standard.  The [[Royal Canadian Armoured Corps|RCAC]] successfully fought to retain its distinctive black beret, and the [[Canadian Airborne Regiment]] wore the [[maroon beret]] until the unit was disbanded.  Scottish and Irish infantry regiments wear [[Tam o' Shanter (cap)|Tam o' Shanters]], [[glengarry|glengarries]], [[Balmoral bonnet|balmorals]] or [[caubeen]]s instead of berets.

The beret is used with service dress as formal headdress (especially after the move away from the [[combination cap|forage cap]] in the 1990s) as well as with [[CADPAT]] clothing as garrison dress and as a form of combat dress. In certain cases the beret is even used as Ceremonial Dress, most commonly in units of the Royal Canadian Armoured Corps.

==Full dress and patrol dress==
The armoured, artillery, and infantry regiments are authorized ceremonial uniforms, but they are rarely seen because they are not provided at public expense (with a few exceptions).

===Regular force===
These regular force regiments have authorized full dress.
{| class=wikitable
! Regiment
! Headgear
! Jacket
! Trousers or kilt
|-
| [[Royal Canadian Horse Artillery]]
| [[Busby]], scarlet bag, white over scarlet plume
| Blue light-cavalry jacket, scarlet facings, yellow frogging, blue cuffs, yellow [[Austrian knot]]
| Blue trousers, scarlet stripe
|-
| [[The Royal Canadian Dragoons]]
| Brass helmet, black plume
| Scarlet tunic, blue facings, yellow heavy-cavalry knot
| Blue trousers, yellow stripe
|-
| [[Lord Strathcona's Horse (Royal Canadians)]]
| Brass helmet, red and white plume
| Scarlet tunic, myrtle green facings, yellow heavy-cavalry knot
| Blue trousers, yellow stripe
|-
| [[12e Régiment blindé du Canada|12&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; Régiment blindé du Canada]]
| Black [[beret]]
| Scarlet tunic, yellow facings, yellow heavy-cavalry knot
| Blue trousers, yellow stripe
|-
| [[The Royal Regiment of Canadian Artillery]]
| Busby, scarlet bag, white plume
| Blue tunic, scarlet facings, blue cuffs, yellow Austrian knot
| Blue trousers, scarlet stripe
|-
| [[The Royal Canadian Regiment]]
| White [[Wolseley helmet]], scarlet [[puggaree]]
| Scarlet tunic, blue facings, white piping
| Blue trousers, scarlet stripe
|-
| [[Princess Patricia's Canadian Light Infantry]]
| White Wolseley helmet, French grey puggaree
| Scarlet tunic, French grey facings, white piping
| Blue trousers, scarlet stripe
|-
| [[Royal 22e Régiment|Royal 22&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; Régiment]]
| [[Bearskin cap]], scarlet plume
| Scarlet tunic, blue facings, white piping
| Blue trousers, scarlet stripe
|}

===Reserve force===
These reserve force regiments have authorized full dress and  undress uniforms.
{| class=wikitable
! Regiment
! Full dress headgear&lt;br&gt;Undress headgear
! Full dress jacket&lt;br&gt;Undress jacket
! Trousers or kilt
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Governor General's Horse Guards]]
| White metal helmet, scarlet plume
| Blue tunic, scarlet facings, white heavy-cavalry knot
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, scarlet stripe
|-
| [[Forage cap]] with scarlet band{{Citation needed|date=April 2013}}
| Blue jacket, shoulder [[chain mail]]
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[8th Canadian Hussars (Princess Louise's)]]
| Blue busby, white bag and plume
| Blue [[hussar]] tunic, white facings, yellow light-cavalry knot
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, two yellow stripes
|-
| Black beret
| Blue jacket, shoulder chain mail
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Ontario Regiment (RCAC)]]
| rowspan = 2 | Black beret
| Scarlet tunic, blue facings, yellow heavy-cavalry knot
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers (NCM/NCO) Black trousers (Officer), yellow stripe
|-
| Blue jacket (NCM/NCO) Black jacket (Officer), shoulder chain mail
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Queen's York Rangers (1st American Regiment) (RCAC)]]
| rowspan = 2 | Black beret
| Green tunic, blue amethyst facings, white heavy-cavalry knot
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, yellow stripe
|-
| Blue jacket, shoulder chain mail
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[Sherbrooke Hussars]]
| Wolseley helmet, blue pugaree
| Blue hussar tunic, blue facings, yellow light-cavalry knot
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, two yellow stripes
|-
| Black beret
| Blue jacket, shoulder chain mail
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[12e Régiment blindé du Canada|12&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; Régiment blindé du Canada]]
| rowspan = 2 | Black beret
| Scarlet tunic, yellow facings, heavy-cavalry knot
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, yellow stripe
|-
| Blue jacket, shoulder chain mail
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[1st Hussars]]
| Busby, buff bag, white plume
| Blue hussar tunic, buff facings, yellow light-cavalry knot
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, two white stripes
|-
| Black beret
| Blue jacket, shoulder chain mail
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Prince Edward Island Regiment (RCAC)]]
| Wolseley helmet, yellow over red plume
| Scarlet tunic, yellow facings
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, yellow stripe
|-
| Black beret
| Blue jacket, shoulder chain mail
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Royal Canadian Hussars (Montreal)]]
| Busby, white bag and plume
| Blue hussar tunic, white facings, yellow light-cavalry knot
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, two white stripes
|-
| Scarlet forage cap
| Blue jacket, shoulder chain mail
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The British Columbia Regiment (Duke of Connaught's Own)]]
| rowspan = 2 | Black beret
| Green tunic, black facings, yellow heavy-cavalry knot
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, yellow stripe
|-
| Blue jacket, shoulder chain mail
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The South Alberta Light Horse]]
| Wolseley helmet
| Scarlet tunic, yellow facings, light-cavalry knot
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, two yellow stripes
|-
| Brown [[Stetson]] or black beret
| Blue jacket, shoulder chain mail
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Saskatchewan Dragoons]]
| Wolseley helmet
| Scarlet tunic, blue facings, yellow heavy-cavalry knot
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, yellow stripe
|-
| Black beret
| Blue jacket, shoulder chain mail
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The King's Own Calgary Regiment (RCAC)]]
| Black beret
| Scarlet tunic, Oxford blue facings, yellow heavy-cavalry knot
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, yellow stripe
|-
| Black beret
| Blue jacket, shoulder chain mail
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The British Columbia Dragoons]]
| Wolseley helmet
| Scarlet tunic, blue facings, yellow heavy-cavalry knot
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, yellow stripe
|-
| Black beret
| Blue jacket, shoulder chain mail
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Fort Garry Horse]]
| Wolseley helmet
| Scarlet tunic, yellow facings, yellow heavy-cavalry knot
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, yellow stripe
|-
| Black beret
| Blue jacket, shoulder chain mail
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[Le Régiment de Hull (RCAC)]]
| rowspan = 2 | Black beret
| Scarlet tunic, blue facings, yellow heavy-cavalry knot
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, yellow stripe
|-
| Blue jacket, shoulder chain mail
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Windsor Regiment (RCAC)]]
| rowspan = 2 | Black beret
| Scarlet tunic, black facings, yellow heavy-cavalry knot
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, two white stripes
|-
| Blue jacket, shoulder chain mail
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Royal Regiment of Canadian Artillery]]
| Busby, scarlet bag, white plume
| Blue tunic, scarlet facings, blue cuffs
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, scarlet stripe
|-
| [[Pillbox cap]]
| Blue jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[Governor General's Foot Guards]]
| Bearskin cap, scarlet plume
| Scarlet guardsman tunic, blue facings, buttons in twos. Pipers: blue [[doublet (clothing)|doublet]].
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, scarlet stripe. Pipers: Black Watch [[tartan]].
|-
| Forage cap with white band&lt;ref name=&quot;CFDI-6B-2&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Canadian Forces Dress Instructions|year=2011 |publisher=Department of National Defence |page=6B-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| Blue jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Canadian Grenadier Guards]]
| Bearskin cap, white horsehair plume
| Scarlet guardsman tunic, blue facings, buttons worn singly. Pipers: blue doublet
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, scarlet stripe. Pipers: Black Watch tartan
|-
| Forage cap with scarlet band&lt;ref name=&quot;CFDI-6B-3&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Canadian Forces Dress Instructions|year=2011 |publisher=Department of National Defence |page=6B-3}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| Blue jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Queen's Own Rifles of Canada]]
| Busby, black over scarlet plume
| Green rifleman tunic, scarlet facings
| rowspan = 2 | Green trousers, scarlet stripe
|-
| Field service cap&lt;ref name=&quot;CFDI-5-1-2&quot;&gt;{{cite book |title=Canadian Forces Dress Instructions |year=2011 |publisher=Department of National Defence |page=5-1-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| Green jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Black Watch (Royal Highland Regiment) of Canada]]
| [[Feather bonnet]], red plume
| Scarlet doublet, blue facings. Pipers: Green doublet
| rowspan = 2 | Black Watch tartan kilt. Pipers: Royal Stewart tartan kilt
|-
| [[Balmoral bonnet]], [[Tam o' Shanter (cap)|Tam o' Shanter]], or battle bonnet depending rank and title, red hackle, or [[glengarry]], plain border
| Green [[coatee]]
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[Les Voltigeurs de Québec]]
| Green [[shako]], falling green cock's feather plume
| Green rifleman tunic, scarlet facings
| rowspan = 2 | Green trousers, scarlet stripe
|-
| Field service cap&lt;ref name=&quot;CFDI-5-1-2&quot; /&gt;
| Green jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Royal Regiment of Canada]]
| Bearskin cap, scarlet over white plume
| Scarlet guardsman tunic, buttons worn singly
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, scarlet stripe
|-
| 
| Blue jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Royal Hamilton Light Infantry (Wentworth Regiment)]]
| Wolseley helmet, scarlet puggaree
| Scarlet tunic, blue facings
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, scarlet stripe (thick stripe in patrol dress)
|-
| Forest green forage cap, scarlet band
| Forest green jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Princess of Wales' Own Regiment]]
| Wolseley helmet, blue puggaree
| Scarlet tunic, blue facings
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, scarlet stripe
|-
| 
| Blue jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Hastings and Prince Edward Regiment]]
| Wolseley helmet, blue puggaree
| Scarlet tunic, blue facings
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, scarlet stripe
|-
| 
| Blue jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Lincoln and Welland Regiment]]
| Wolseley helmet, white puggaree
| Scarlet tunic, blue facings
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, scarlet stripe
|-
| 
| Blue jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Royal Canadian Regiment]]
| Wolseley helmet, scarlet puggaree
| Scarlet tunic, blue facings
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, scarlet stripe
|-
| 
| Blue jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Royal Highland Fusiliers of Canada]]
| Balmoral, red, white, and green diced border, white fusilier hackle. Drum major: bearskin cap, white hackle.
| Scarlet doublet, blue facings. Pipers: blue doublet
| rowspan = 2 | Mackenzie tartan kilt. Pipe band: Erskine tartan kilt and hose
|-
| Balmoral, red, white, and green diced border, white fusilier hackle
| Blue cut-away jacket with [[Inverness flap]]s
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Grey and Simcoe Foresters]]
| Wolseley helmet, blue puggaree
| Lincoln green facings
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, scarlet stripe
|-
| 
| Blue jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Lorne Scots (Peel, Dufferin and Halton Regiment)]]
| Feather bonnet, primrose plume
| Scarlet doublet, white facings
| rowspan = 2 | Campbell Ancient kilt
|-
| Balmoral, red, white, and green diced border, green toorie. Drummers: Glengarry, red, white and green diced border, scarlet toorie.
| Green coatee
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Brockville Rifles]]
| Busby, black over scarlet plume
| Green tunic, scarlet facings
| rowspan = 2 | Green trousers, scarlet stripe
|-
| Field service cap&lt;ref name=&quot;CFDI-5-1-2&quot; /&gt;
| Green jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[Stormont, Dundas and Glengarry Highlanders]]
| Feather bonnet, white plume
| Scarlet doublet, blue facings. Pipers: green doublet
| rowspan = 2 | MacDonnell of Glengarry tartan kilt
|-
| Glengarry, red and white diced border
| Green coatee
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[Les Fusiliers du St-Laurent|Les Fusiliers du S&lt;sup&gt;t&lt;/sup&gt;-Laurent]]
| Bearskin cap, white plume
| Scarlet tunic, blue facings
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, scarlet stripe
|-
| 
| Blue jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[Le Régiment de la Chaudière]]
| Wolseley helmet, blue puggaree
| Scarlet tunic, blue facings
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, scarlet stripe
|-
| 
| Blue jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[Royal 22e Régiment|Royal 22&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; Régiment]]
| Bearskin cap, scarlet plume
| Scarlet tunic, blue facings
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, scarlet stripe
|-
| 
| Blue jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[Les Fusiliers Mont-Royal]]
| Bearskin cap, white plume
| Scarlet tunic, white facings
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, scarlet stripe
|-
| 
| Blue jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Princess Louise Fusiliers]]
| Bearskin cap, grey plume or Wolseley helmet, blue puggaree
| Scarlet tunic, blue facings
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, scarlet stripe
|-
| Forage cap, grey plume
| Blue jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Royal New Brunswick Regiment]]
| Wolseley helmet, blue puggaree
| Scarlet tunic, blue facings
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, scarlet stripe
|-
| 
| Blue jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The West Nova Scotia Regiment]]
| Wolseley helmet, blue puggaree
| Scarlet tunic, blue facings
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, scarlet stripe
|-
| 
| Blue jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Nova Scotia Highlanders]]
| Feather bonnet, white plume
| Scarlet doublet, blue facings. Pipers: green doublet
| rowspan = 2 | MacDonald tartan kilt
|-
| Green balmoral, red toorie.
| Green coatee
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[Le Régiment de Maisonneuve]]
| Wolseley helmet, blue puggaree
| Scarlet tunic, blue facings
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, scarlet stripe
|-
| 
| Blue jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Cameron Highlanders of Ottawa (Duke of Edinburgh's Own)]]
| Feather bonnet, white plume
| Scarlet doublet, blue facings. Pipers: green doublet
| rowspan = 2 | Cameron of Erracht tartan kilt
|-
| Glengarry, plain border (pipers add eagle feather), or Balmoral, blue hackle
| Green coatee
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Royal Winnipeg Rifles]]
| Busby, black plume
| Green tunic, black facings
| rowspan = 2 | Green trousers, black stripe
|-
| Field service cap&lt;ref name=&quot;CFDI-5-1-2&quot; /&gt;
| Green jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Essex and Kent Scottish]]
| Feather bonnet, white plume
| Scarlet doublet, blue facings. Pipers: green doublet
| rowspan = 2 | MacGregor tartan kilt
|-
| Glengarry, red, white, and blue diced border
| Blue cut-away jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[48th Highlanders of Canada]]
| Feather bonnet, white plume
| Scarlet doublet, blue facings. Pipers: green doublet
| rowspan = 2 | Davidson tartan kilt. Pipers: Stewart of Fingask tartan
|-
| Glengarry, red, white, and blue diced border
| Green coatee
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[Le Régiment du Saguenay]]
| Wolseley helmet, blue puggaree
| Scarlet tunic, blue facings
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, scarlet stripe
|-
| 
| Blue jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Algonquin Regiment]]
| Wolseley helmet, blue puggaree
| Scarlet tunic, blue facings
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, scarlet stripe
|-
| 
| Blue jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | The [[Argyll and Sutherland Highlanders of Canada]] (Princess Louise's)
| Feather bonnet, white plume
| Scarlet doublet, yellow facings
| rowspan = 2 | Argyll and Sutherland tartan kilt
|-
| Glengarry, red and white diced border
| Green coatee
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Lake Superior Scottish Regiment]]
| Feather bonnet, white plume
| Scarlet doublet, blue facings. Pipers: green doublet
| rowspan = 2 | MacGillivray tartan kilt
|-
| Glengarry, red, white, and blue diced border, light blue toorie
| Green coatee
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The North Saskatchewan Regiment]]
| Wolseley helmet, blue puggaree
| Scarlet tunic, blue facings. Pipers: blue doublet
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, scarlet stripe. Pipers: Mackenzie tartan kilt
|-
| 
| Blue jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Royal Regina Rifles]]
| Busby, black over scarlet plume
| Green tunic, scarlet facings
| rowspan = 2 | Green trousers, scarlet stripe
|-
| Field service cap&lt;ref name=&quot;CFDI-5-1-2&quot; /&gt;
| Green jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Rocky Mountain Rangers]]
| Wolseley helmet, blue puggaree
| Scarlet tunic, rifle green facings
| rowspan = 2 | Rifle green trousers, scarlet stripe
|-
| 
| Green jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Loyal Edmonton Regiment (4th Battalion, Princess Patricia's Canadian Light Infantry)]]
| Wolseley helmet, black puggaree
| French grey facings
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, scarlet stripe
|-
| 
| Blue jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Queen's Own Cameron Highlanders of Canada]]
| Feather bonnet, white plume. Pipers: Glengarry, eagle feather
| Scarlet doublet, midnight blue facings. Pipers: green doublet
| rowspan = 2 | Cameron of Erracht tartan kilt
|-
| Glengarry, blue hackle
| Green coatee
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Royal Westminster Regiment]]
| Wolseley helmet, scarlet puggaree
| Scarlet tunic, blue facings
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, scarlet stripe
|-
| 
| Blue jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Calgary Highlanders]]
| Glengarry, red and white diced border
| Scarlet doublet, yellow facings. Pipers: green doublet
| rowspan = 2 | Argyll and Sutherland tartan kilt
|-
| [[Tam o' Shanter (cap)|Tam o' Shanter]] or balmoral (no plume)
| Green coatee
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[Les Fusiliers de Sherbrooke]]
| Bearskin cap, white plume
| Scarlet tunic, blue facings
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, scarlet stripe
|-
| 
| Blue jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Seaforth Highlanders of Canada]]
| Feather bonnet, white plume. Pipers: glengarry, cockfeathers.
| Scarlet doublet, buff facings. Pipers: green doublet.
| rowspan = 2 | Mackenzie tartan kilt
|-
| Glengarry or balmoral, red, white, and blue diced border.
| Green coatee, buff turn-back tails
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Canadian Scottish Regiment (Princess Mary's)]]
| Feather bonnet, white plume. Pipers add eagle feather.
| Scarlet doublet, blue facings. Pipers: green doublet
| rowspan = 2 | Hunting Stewart tartan kilt
|-
| Glengarry, red, white, and blue diced border
| Blue cut-away jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Royal Montreal Regiment]]
| Wolseley helmet, blue puggaree
| Scarlet tunic, blue facings
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, scarlet stripe
|-
| 
| Blue jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Irish Regiment of Canada]]
| Feather bonnet, white plume
| Scarlet cut-away tunic, dark green facings
| rowspan = 2 | O'Saffron tartan
|-
| [[Caubeen]], green hackle
| Green cut-away jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[The Toronto Scottish Regiment (Queen Elizabeth the Queen Mother's Own)]]
| Feather bonnet, blue hackle
| Hodden grey doublet, blue facings
| rowspan = 2 | [[Hodden grey]] kilt
|-
| Glengarry, white, Skye blue, and Hodden grey diced border, Skye blue toorie
| Hodden grey cut-away jacket
|-
| rowspan = 2 | [[Royal Newfoundland Regiment]]
| Wolseley helmet, blue puggaree
| Scarlet tunic, blue facings
| rowspan = 2 | Blue trousers, scarlet stripe
|-
| 
| Blue jacket
|}

===Air Force===
Air Force pipe bands also have an authorized full-dress uniform. There is a ceremonial Air Force full-dress uniform authorized.
{| class=wikitable
! Type of unit
! Headgear
! Jacket
! Trousers or kilt
|-
| rowspan = 2 | Pipe bands
| Feather bonnet, blue plume
| rowspan = 2 | Air force blue doublet, air force blue facings
| rowspan = 2 | RCAF tartan
|-
| Glengarry, light blue toorie
|}

==Regulations==
Regulations for the wear of uniforms are contained in the CF publication ''Canadian Forces Dress Instructions''. Amendments to dress regulations are issued through the office of the [[Vice Chief of the Defence Staff (Canada)|Vice Chief of the Defence Staff]] (VCDS), initially in the form of a CANFORGEN (Canadian Forces General) message, which is placed in the dress manual until an official publication amendment can be promulgated.

Dress regulations may also be amplified, interpreted, or amended by the commanders of formations and units (depending on the commander's authority) through the issuing of Standing Orders (SOs), Ship's Standing Orders (SSO), Routine Orders (ROs), and Standard Operating Procedures (SOPs). This may include amplification where the regulations are unclear or are not mandatory; amendments or reversal of some existing regulations for special occasions or events; or the promulgation of regulations regarding the wear of traditional regimental articles (such as kilts).

==See also==
{{Portal|Canadian Armed Forces}}
* [[Military uniform]]
*[[Canadian military fur wedge cap]]
*[[Canadian Armed Forces ranks and insignia]]

==References==
{{reflist}}
* A-AD-265-000/AG-001, Canadian Forces Dress Instructions.
* Dorosh, Michael A. ''Dressed to Kill'' ([[Service Publications]], 2001).

==External links==
* [http://www.canadiansoldiers.com/uniforms/uniform.htm Canadian Militia/Canadian Army/Canadian Armed Forces Uniforms]
* [http://epe.lac-bac.gc.ca/100/205/301/ic/cdc/analogue/uniforms/default.htm The Whole Kit and Kaboodle Canadian Military Uniforms]
{{Canadian Armed Forces}}
{{Canadian Forces Maritime Command}}
{{Canadian Forces Land Force Command}}
{{Canadian Forces Air Command}}

[[Category:Canadian Armed Forces|uniforms]]
[[Category:Canadian military uniforms]]
[[Category:Military equipment of Canada]]</text>
      <sha1>2bsihxs3cjl6cozggkwmhqteufas6y6</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
