<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>United States Army's Family and MWR Programs</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>28308266</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750355811</id>
      <parentid>740405853</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-19T05:36:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GreenC bot</username>
        <id>27823944</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>8 archive templates merged to {{[[template:webarchive|webarchive]]}} ([[User:Green_Cardamom/Webarchive_template_merge|WAM]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="51656">{{Use American English|date=May 2015}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2011}}
{{Infobox military unit
|unit_name= Family and MWR Programs
|image= [[File:FMWRCLogo.jpg|center|250px]]
|caption='''Soldiers, Families, Retirees, Civilians'''
|dates=June 2011&amp;nbsp;– Present
|country= {{flag|United States of America}}
|allegiance=United States
|branch=[[United States Army]]
|type=
|size=
|command_structure= [[United States Department of Defense|Department of Defense]]&lt;br&gt;
[[United States Department of the Army|Department of the Army]]&lt;br&gt;
[[United States Army Installation Management Command|Installation Management Command]]
|garrison=
|garrison_label=
|nickname=MWR
| website        = [https://www.army.mil/familymwr/?from=wiki Official MWR News]
|motto= 
|colors=
|colors_label=
|march=
|mascot=
|equipment=
|equipment_label=
|battles=
|anniversaries=
|decorations= 
|battle_honours=
&lt;!-- Commanders --&gt;
|commander1= 
|commander1_label= 
|commander2= 
|commander2_label= 
|commander3= 
|commander3_label= 
|commander4= 
|commander4_label= 
|notable_commanders=
&lt;!-- Insignia --&gt;
|identification_symbol= 
|identification_symbol_label= 
|identification_symbol_2=
|identification_symbol_2_label=
|identification_symbol_3=
|identification_symbol_3_label=
|identification_symbol_4=
|identification_symbol_4_label=
&lt;!-- Aircraft --&gt;
|aircraft_attack=
|aircraft_bomber=
|aircraft_electronic=
|aircraft_fighter=
|aircraft_helicopter=
|aircraft_interceptor=
|aircraft_patrol=
|aircraft_recon=
|aircraft_trainer=
|aircraft_transport=
}}
The United States Army's '''Family and Morale, Welfare and Recreation (MWR) Programs''' are executed within the [[Installation Management Command]] G9, Family and MWR Directorate,&lt;ref name=&quot;armymwr.org&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.armymwr.com/commander/history.aspx|title = webpage|format = |date = |accessdate = 2012-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; following the deactivation of the Family and Morale, Welfare and Recreation Command on 3 June 2011 in a ceremony at Fort Sam Houston.&lt;ref name=&quot;about MWR&quot;&gt;[http://www.armymwr.com/commander/aboutfmwrc.aspx ] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110508024916/http://www.armymwr.com/commander/aboutfmwrc.aspx |date=8 May 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt; According to the organization's official mission statement, IMCOM G9 delivers &quot;quality Family and Morale, Welfare, and Recreation programs and services supporting the readiness and resilience of the All-Volunteer Army.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.armymwr.com/commander/mission.aspx|title = Family and MWR Mission and Vision|publisher = |date = |accessdate = 2012-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to U.S. Army Regulation 215-1, Army MWR is a quality-of-life program that directly supports readiness by providing a variety of community, soldier, and family support programs, activities and services. Included in MWR are social, fitness, recreational, educational, and other programs and activities that enhance community life, foster soldier and unit readiness, promote mental and physical fitness, and generally provide a working and living environment that attracts and retains quality for [[U.S. Army]] soldiers, family members, retirees and its civilian workforce.&lt;ref name=&quot;Army Regulation 215-1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.army.mil/usapa/epubs/pdf/r215_1.pdf |title=Army Regulation 215-1 |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2012-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The range of MWR programs offered at Army garrisons is based on the needs of authorized patrons who work and reside there. Programs are managed by garrison commanders within the framework of authorized and available appropriated and non-appropriated funds. Non-appropriated funds are those funds that are locally generated by MWR programs or provided by [[Installation Management Command]] (IMCOM) region directors and/or the Family and MWR Programs. AAFES dividends are also a source of non-appropriated funding.&lt;ref name=&quot;Army Regulation 215-1&quot;/&gt;

Each MWR program is classified by category. Categories are determined by their effect on the military mission and their ability to generate revenue.&lt;ref name=&quot;Army Regulation 215-1&quot;/&gt;

==Objectives==
Family and MWR supports combat readiness and effectiveness; supports recruitment and retention of quality personnel; provides leisure time activities, which support a quality of life commensurate with generally accepted American values; promotes and maintains the mental and physical wellbeing of authorized personnel; fosters community pride, soldier morale, and family wellness and promotes unit esprit de corps, eases the impact of unique aspects of military life, such as frequent relocations and deployment.&lt;ref name=&quot;Army Regulation 215-1&quot;/&gt;

==History&lt;ref name=&quot;MWR History and Philosophy&quot;&gt;[http://www.armymwr.org/commander/aboutfmwrc.aspx MWR History and Philosophy] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110725013847/http://www.armymwr.org/commander/aboutfmwrc.aspx |date=25 July 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;==

[[File:MWR GWOT.JPEG|thumb|left|U.S. Army Specialist (SPC) Brian Buss, 3rd Battalion, 187th Infantry, performs incline bench presses, with a spotter, at the gym tent provided by the Morale Welfare Recreation (MWR) staff on Kandahar Air Base, Afghanistan, during Operation Enduring Freedom.]]

Although the United States Army was founded in 1775,&lt;ref&gt;[[United States Army Center of Military History]], The Birthday of the U.S. Army [http://www.history.army.mil/html/faq/birth.html]&lt;/ref&gt; Morale, welfare, and recreation programs did not exist for the Army until the start of the twentieth century.&lt;ref name=&quot;MWR History and Philosophy&quot;/&gt;

Before that time, troop support came informally in the form of tradesmen and trading posts. The goods they were able to provide included meals, clothing, and laundering.&lt;ref name=&quot;MWR History and Philosophy&quot;/&gt;

The formalization of MWR services began with limited Congressional oversight established in 1876 over &quot;Post Traders&quot; and then the establishment of Army &quot;PX&quot; or The Post Exchange, by Headquarters, [[Department of the Army]] (HQDA) in 1895, with [[United States Department of War|War Department]] General Order No. 46, 1895.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aafes.ws/pa/history/docs/BriefHistory.pdf Army and Air Force Exchange Service Official Website]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Military Homefront, History of MWR&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.militaryhomefront.dod.mil/portal/page/mhf/MHF/MHF_DETAIL_1?section_id=20.80.500.387.0.0.0.0.0&amp;current_id=20.80.500.387.500.60.30.0.0 |title=Military Homefront, History of MWR |publisher=Militaryhomefront.dod.mil |date= |accessdate=2012-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Profits from the Post Exchange were used to support recreational activities for the troops.&lt;ref name=&quot;MWR History and Philosophy&quot;/&gt;

In 1903, the [[United States Congress]] passed the 1903 Army Appropriations Act, which provided funds to build, operate and maintain PXs, libraries, schools, recreation centers, and gyms for the troops.&lt;ref name=&quot;MWR History and Philosophy&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Military Homefront, History of MWR&quot;/&gt;

[[File:27 Jun 51 Hospital Library Ward Service.jpg|thumb|A 1951 image from Hospital Library Ward Service. U.S. Army Photo.]]

The Army Morale Division was established in 1918, followed by the Army Motion Picture Service in 1920 and the Library Service in 1923. In 1941, the Army Morale Division and these other organizations collectively became &quot;Special Services.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;MWR History and Philosophy&quot;/&gt;

By 1943, Special Services had grown to include all of Army Recreation Services, the Army Exchange (the precursor to the Army and Air Force Exchange [AAFES]), and the Army Soldier Show. Special Services soon established the first [[Armed Forces Recreation Center]] (AFRC) in Bavaria (FMWR currently manages five AFRCs) and, by 1950, Special Services was placed under the Army Adjutant General’s Office during an Army reorganization.&lt;ref name=&quot;MWR History and Philosophy&quot;/&gt;

Services for families, rather than just troops, began to emerge in the mid to late 1960s. In 1965, Army Community Services was created, followed in 1968 by a Youth Activities Program and, in 1971, an Outdoor Recreation Program.&lt;ref name=&quot;MWR History and Philosophy&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Jessica Simpson at the PGA.jpg|thumb|left|[[Jessica Simpson]] sings &quot;The Star-Spangled Banner&quot; during the opening ceremony of the AT&amp;T National PGA Tour event July 1 at Congressional Country Club in Bethesda]]
Emphasis on the family continued in 1981 with the first Family Advocacy Program and the first Army Family Symposium.&lt;ref name=&quot;MWR History and Philosophy&quot;/&gt;

With the publication in 1983 of [[Chief of Staff of the United States Army|Army Chief of Staff]] General John A. Wickham Jr’s White Paper, the Army Family, the integral support role of Soldiers’ families was acknowledged. The development of Gen. Wickham's White Paper led to initiatives such as the Army Family Action Plan (AFAP), Family Readiness Groups and Army Family Team Building.&lt;ref&gt;The Army Family by General [[Eric K. Shinseki]] – Foreword (June 2003)[http://www.whs.mil/library/dig/ar-m620u_20080912.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt;

On 23 November 1984, the U.S. Army Community and Family Support Center (CFSC) was formed under General Order Number 40, as a Field Operating Agency.&lt;ref name=&quot;MWR History and Philosophy&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.penfed.org/usawoa/downloads/CFSC_Fact_Sheet.pdf |title=Pentagon Federal Credit Union, CFSC Fact Sheet |publisher=Penfed.org |date= |accessdate=2012-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1993, oversight of CSFC changed from the [[Office of the Deputy Chief of Staff for Personnel]] (DCSPER), to the Office of the Assistant Chief of Staff for Installation Management (ACSIM) and the organization itself changed from a Field Operating Agency to a Direct Reporting Unit on 24 October 2006 when [[Installation Management Command]] (IMCOM) was activated and the Installation Management Agency (IMA) was deactivated.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.imcom.army.mil/hq/about/history/ Installation Management Command History] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100911030122/http://www.imcom.army.mil/hq/about/history/ |date=11 September 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; With the activation of IMCOM, CFSC became the Family and Morale, Welfare and Recreation Command (FMWRC) on 24 October 2006.&lt;ref name=&quot;MWR History and Philosophy&quot;/&gt;  Since 1996, ArmyMWR.com has been the website serving Soldiers and their Families at Garrisons and Installations in the United States and throughout the world.

The Family and MWR Command revised and published a new brand logo in 2010.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://mwrbrandcentral.com/HOMEPAGE/ourbrand.html |title=new brand logo in 2010 |publisher=Mwrbrandcentral.com |date=2012-10-11 |accessdate=2012-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 26 May 2011, the command retired its flag in Alexandria, Va., to prepare for a move to San Antonio, Texas, in accordance with Base-Realignment and Closure law.&lt;ref&gt;United States Army, Evan Dyson [http://www.army.mil/article/58740/ &quot;Flag casing ceremony marks new era for Army MWR&quot;] 1 June 2011. Retrieved 8 September 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Family and Morale, Welfare and Recreation Command was deactivated on 3 June 2011 in a ceremony at Fort Sam Houston. The deactivation ceremony formally changed FMWRC into the [[Installation Management Command]] G9 Division, commonly known as Family and MWR Programs.&lt;ref&gt;United States Army, Tim Hipps [http://www.army.mil/article/59047/ &quot;Army MWR integrated into Installation Management Command&quot;] 6 June 2011. Retrieved 13 September 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

The first Director, G9 for MWR Programs was James C. Abney, SES.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.armymwr.com/commander/director.aspx |title=Director, G9 |publisher=Armymwr.com |date= |accessdate=2012-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; The SES (Senior Executive Service)&lt;ref&gt;[[Senior Executive Service (United States)]]&lt;/ref&gt; is a pay grade for civilians in the Federal Government, somewhat equivalent to the rank of General.  Prior to this appointment,&lt;ref&gt;Deputy to the Commanding General of the Family and Morale, Welfare and Recreation Command (FMWRC)&lt;/ref&gt; Mr. Abney was Deputy to the Commanding General of the Family and Morale, Welfare and Recreation Command (FMWRC) (now deactivated), and a Highly Qualified Expert (HQE)&lt;ref&gt;http://cpol.army.mil/library/nonarmy/dod_062706.html&lt;/ref&gt; with duties as the Special Assistant to the FMWRC Commanding General.

A new campus for the [[Installation Management Command]] was dedicated at [[Fort Sam Houston]] on 19 Aug. 2011.&lt;ref&gt;United States Army, Tim Hipps [http://www.army.mil/article/63962/ &quot;Ribbon cutting opens Installation Management Command on Fort Sam&quot;] 25 August 2011. Retrieved 13 September 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; Besides adding additional office space for MWR employees, the campus also features a new building for the Maj. Gen. Robert M. Joyce Family and MWR School of the Installation Management Academy, formerly the Maj. Gen. Robert M. Joyce Family and MWR Academy.&lt;ref name=&quot;army.mil&quot;&gt;United States Army, Tim Hipps [http://www.army.mil/article/64535/ &quot;Installation Management Academy welcomes students to Fort Sam Houston&quot;] 30 August 2011. Retrieved 13 September 2011.&lt;/ref&gt; The historic Fort Sam Houston Theatre is also being adapted for use by the organization. When complete, interior modifications will include a modified stage, additional storage space and more room for lighting and recording equipment.&lt;ref name=&quot;United States Army 2011&quot;&gt;United States Army, Evan Dyson [http://www.army.mil/article/64964/ &quot;Army Entertainment Detachment holds change of command ceremony&quot;] 6 September 2011. Retrieved 13 September 2011.&lt;/ref&gt;

The current director of Family and MWR Programs is Ms. Stephanie L. Hoehne.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|title = Command|url = http://www.armymwr.com/commander/command.aspx|website = www.armymwr.com|accessdate = 2016-01-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Executive summary==

The Non-Appropriated Fund Instrumentality Program (NAFI),&lt;ref name=&quot;Army Regulation 215-1&quot;/&gt;  is operated by the Army for Department of Defense agencies and MWR programs are established, maintained, and disestablished under sole authority of Army Regulation AR215-1.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.scribd.com/doc/35622762/Army-Regulation-215-1-Military-Morale-Welfare-and-Recreation-Programs-and-Nonappropriated-Fund-Instrumentalities |title=Army Regulation 215_1 Military Morale, Welfare and Recreation Programs and Nonappropriated Fund Instrumentalities |publisher=Scribd.com |date= |accessdate=2012-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

FMWR’s major business partner, the [[Army and Air Force Exchange Service]], provides a dividend to Army FMWR based on two distinct agreements. In the first, the Army shares 50 percent of AAFES net income after depreciation with the Air Force based on the number of active duty Soldiers and Airmen in each service—currently the Army receives 30 percent and the Air Force 20 percent of AAFES generated dividend revenue. Through the Army Simplified Dividend, garrisons receive 100 percent of profits from &quot;Class VI&quot; or personal demand supply items (such as health and hygiene products, soaps and toothpaste, writing material, snack food, beverages, cigarettes, batteries, and alcohol), 80 percent of pay telephone revenue, and 0.4 percent of all local AAFES sales. The latter component is deducted from the Army share of total AAFES profits with the remainder going to the Army Morale, Welfare, and Recreation Fund.&lt;ref name=&quot;armymwr.org&quot;/&gt;

Revenues received from Army Lodging room charges are used solely to sustain and recapitalize the Lodging program and its facilities.&lt;ref name=&quot;armymwr.org&quot;/&gt;

Monies derived from user fees and sales, AAFES, and recreation and amusement machine operations are invested and earn interest to benefit Army FMWR operations. When combined, NAF represents 42 percent of all funding, allowing Army FMWR programs to continue to serve more than 3.9&amp;nbsp;million patrons.&lt;ref name=&quot;armymwr.org&quot;/&gt;

Most of this money goes to Army installations and is used to run FMWR operations, programs, and services. What is left is focused on Army-wide capital improvements and minor construction and capital purchases.&lt;ref name=&quot;armymwr.org&quot;/&gt;

==Army Family Covenant==
[[File:Army Family Covenant1.jpg|thumb|Chief of Staff of the Army Gen. George W. Casey, Jr. and Secretary of the Army Pete Geren pose with Army family members after signing the Army Family Covenant at Fort Knox, Ky, 18 Oct. 2007. U.S. Army photo.]]

Unveiled on 8 October 2007, the Army Family Covenant institutionalized the U.S. Army’s publicly announced pledge to support its soldiers and their families—Active, Guard and Reserve—with resourced programs to deliver a quality of life &quot;commensurate with their service and sacrifice to the nation&quot;.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.myarmyonesource.com/CommunitiesandMarketplace/ArmyFamilyCovenant/default.aspx |title=Army Family Covenant Official Website |publisher=Myarmyonesource.com |date= |accessdate=2012-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to U.S. Army officials, the Army Family Covenant commits the U.S. Army to enhance soldier and family readiness by:

*Standardizing family programs and services
*Increasing accessibility to health care
*Improving Soldier and family housing
*Ensuring excellence in Child, Youth &amp; School Services
*Expanding education and employment opportunities for family members.&lt;ref name=&quot;armymwr.org&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Army News Service [http://www.military.com/features/0,15240,153120,00.html &quot;Army Leaders Sign Covenant with Families&quot;] 18 Oct 2007. Retrieved 11 Aug 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

Since implementing the Army Family Covenant, U.S. Army senior leaders say they’ve made significant progress in fulfilling its promises.&lt;ref&gt;Stars and Stripes, Matt Millham – [http://www.stripes.com/news/covenant-benefits-kick-in-for-army-programs-1.75748 &quot;Covenant benefits kick in for Army programs&quot;] 1 March 2008. Retrieved 11 Aug 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; But, they also acknowledge more work is needed to build an environment where Army families can prosper and realize their full potential within the constraints of persistent conflict.&lt;ref name=&quot;armymwr.org&quot;/&gt; In 2015, the Army renamed the covenant program to &quot;Total Army Strong.&quot;

==Family and Morale, Welfare and Recreation programs==

===Armed Forces Recreation Centers===

Armed Forces Recreation Centers (AFRC) full-service resort hotels are Joint Service Facilities developed to provide vacation recreation opportunities to service members, their families, and other authorized patrons (including official travelers) of the Total Defense Force.&lt;ref&gt;Army Times [http://www.armytimes.com/legacy/rar/1-213095-901876.php &quot;Armed Forces Recreation Centers&quot;]&lt;/ref&gt; The AFRCs are centrally-managed, U.S. Army FMWR-operated facilities.&lt;ref name=&quot;myarmyonesource.com&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.myarmyonesource.com/RecreationTravelandBOSS/ArmedForcesRecreationCenters/default.aspx |title=Armed Forces Recreation Centers, Army OneSource |publisher=Myarmyonesource.com |date= |accessdate=2012-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:DHL construction AFRC.JPEG|In 1998, the U.S. Army added 99 rooms to The Dragon Hill Lodge on Yongsan Garrison, Seoul, South Korea.
Image:DisneyShadesOfGreen.jpg|Shades of Green on Walt Disney World Resort in Florida.
Image:HaleKoaHotel.jpg|Entrance to Hale Koa Hotel in May, 2006.
&lt;/gallery&gt;

Four&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Dozier|first1=Robert|title=Supervisor Public Affairs Specialist|url=http://www.armytimes.com/benefits/mwr/online_hbm08_leisure_facilities/|website=Army MWR|publisher=U.S. Installation Management Command|accessdate=5 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; AFRCs operate worldwide, overseen by the Army's Family and Morale, Welfare and Recreation Programs in San Antonio, Texas.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.armytimes.com/benefits/mwr/online_hbm08_leisure_facilities/ |title=Army Times Leisure: Facilities |publisher=Armytimes.com |date=2010-07-04 |accessdate=2012-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; The four resorts include Dragon Hill Lodge in Seoul, Korea; Edelweiss Lodge and Resort in Garmisch-Partenkirchen, Germany; the Hale Koa Hotel in Hawaii; and Shades of Green&lt;ref name=&quot;shadesofgreen1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.shadesofgreen.org/ |title=shadesofgreen.org |publisher=shadesofgreen.org |date= |accessdate=2012-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; located in Walt Disney World in Orlando, Florida.&lt;ref name=&quot;myarmyonesource.com&quot;/&gt;

====Dragon Hill Lodge====
Resting in the heart of Seoul, Korea, the Dragon Hill Lodge&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dragonhilllodge.com/ |title=dragonhilllodge.com |publisher=dragonhilllodge.com |date= |accessdate=2012-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; offers 394 spacious guest rooms, health club with indoor pool, and four restaurants to serve military personnel, Department of Defense Civilian employees, and their family members.&lt;ref name=&quot;armymwr.org&quot;/&gt;

====Edelweiss Lodge and Resort====
Long revered as one of the most desirable vacation destinations in the Bavarian Alps and Germany's premiere sports center, the Garmisch-Partenkirchen area is an idyllic location nestled at the foot of sweeping Alpine vistas and home to the Edelweiss Lodge and Resort.[[File:EdelweissLodge.jpg|thumb|The view of mountains from the main entrance of Edelweiss Lodge and Resort.
More than 350 employees at the Edelweiss Lodge and Resort&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.edelweisslodgeandresort.com |title=edelweisslodgeandresort.com |publisher=edelweisslodgeandresort.com |date= |accessdate=2012-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; provide support and care for service members and their families at this location in Germany.&lt;ref name=&quot;armymwr.org&quot;/&gt;]]

====Hale Koa Hotel====
On 25 October 1975 a traditional Hawaiian blessing complete with royal procession opened the Hale Koa Hotel.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|author=Hale Koa Hotel and Resort |url=http://www.halekoa.com/ |title=halekoa.com |publisher=halekoa.com |date= |accessdate=2012-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Hale Koa History&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.halekoa.com/about_us/history.cfm |title=Hale Koa History |publisher=Halekoa.com |date=1975-10-25 |accessdate=2012-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;http://www.militaryspot.com/travel/item/hale_koa_hotel/&lt;/ref&gt;

Today, Fort DeRussy Armed Forces Recreation Center is the home of the Hale Koa Hotel,&lt;ref name=&quot;halekoa1&quot;/&gt; or House of the Warrior, an 817 room resort hotel.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hale Koa History&quot;/&gt;

In 1991, a major expansion project began at the Hale Koa,&lt;ref name=&quot;halekoa1&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.halekoa.com/splash.cfm |title=Welcome to the Hale Koa Hotel Online :: Honolulu, Hawaii Waikiki :: A Resort for the Military |publisher=Halekoa.com |date= |accessdate=2012-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; including the development of {{convert|66|acre|m2}} of Fort DeRussy, a new swimming pool complex, two snack bars, a beverage bar and luau garden. In addition, Kalia Road, fronting the Hale Koa Hotel,&lt;ref name=&quot;halekoa1&quot;/&gt; was also realigned and improved. By 1995, the new Maile Tower took its place beside the existing Ilima Tower increasing the number of guestrooms from 419 to 817. Also, debuting was a 1,287 stall parking garage, fitness center, adults only pool, and a new restaurant, Bibas.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hale Koa History&quot;/&gt;

The Hale Koa&lt;ref name=&quot;halekoa1&quot;/&gt; operates without taxpayer dollars supporting upkeep or operation. It’s estimated that over one million military personnel and dependents visit Hale Koa’s&lt;ref name=&quot;halekoa1&quot;/&gt; facilities each year.&lt;ref name=&quot;Hale Koa History&quot;/&gt;

====Shades of Green====
Shades of Green&lt;ref name=&quot;shadesofgreen1&quot;/&gt; opened 1 February 1994.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.shadesofgreen.org/about.htm |title=Shades of Green, About |publisher=Shadesofgreen.org |date=1994-02-01 |accessdate=2012-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The facility describes its amenities as &quot;...a peaceful wooded setting surrounding 586 oversized guest rooms, cascading waterfalls, lush tropical gardens, spectacular views from private patios and balconies amid stunning sunrises.&quot; Shades of Green&lt;ref name=&quot;shadesofgreen1&quot;/&gt; is located on [[Walt Disney World Resort]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.shadesofgreen.org/ |title=Shades of Green, Website |publisher=Shadesofgreen.org |date= |accessdate=2012-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Arts and crafts===
The arts and crafts program offers educational, self-development activities that advance technical knowledge and
skills and offer opportunities for creative growth. This is accomplished through individual participation in arts and crafts processes, to include fine arts, crafts, and industrial/vocational arts. Participants will develop manual dexterity, self-confidence, visual acuity, safety awareness, and knowledge/skills directly transferable to military occupational specialties (MOS).

FMWR hosts an annual U.S. Army Arts and Crafts and All-Army Photography Contests.&lt;ref name=&quot;Army Regulation 215-1&quot;/&gt;

===Automotive skills===
The FMWR automotive skills program offers facilities, equipment, technical instruction, skilled assistance,
and problem-solving services. Industrial/vocational experiences offer a self-help alternative to commercially available repair garages. Patrons can reduce their automobile repair costs through hands-on participation in mechanical processes and develop skills, which sustain morale, enhance self-development, and expand recreational opportunities. Performing incidental repairs and maintenance for a fee may be done as a resale operation of the automotive skills program. Such incidental repair services may be established on a space available basis and when it does not interfere with use of the skills program.&lt;ref name=&quot;Army Regulation 215-1&quot;/&gt;

===Better Opportunities for Single Soldiers===
The BOSS program addresses single Soldier quality of life (QOL) issues and initiatives. BOSS provides a vehicle through which single soldier QOL concerns are identified and recommendations for improvement are made. This vehicle is a means to assess the interests and needs of the single Soldier. The BOSS program provides an
opportunity for single Soldiers to participate in, and contribute to, their respective communities. It is an avenue for military and civilian leaders to gauge and enhance the morale of single Soldiers, which reportedly leads to retention and combat readiness.&lt;ref name=&quot;Army Regulation 215-1&quot;/&gt;

===Bowling===
FMWR Bowling center activities include bowling leagues, open bowling, tournaments, instructional
programs, exhibitions, youth services-sponsored events, locker rentals, and child care services for bowling center
patrons.&lt;ref name=&quot;Army Regulation 215-1&quot;/&gt;

===Child, Youth, and School Services (CYSS)===
CYSS consists of four services: Child Development Services (CDS); School Age Services (SAS), Youth Services (YS), and School Liaison Officers (SLOs). Each service has associated programs. For CDS, these programs are CDCs and FCC homes. For SAS, these programs are School-Age Centers and Camps. For YS, these programs are: Youth Centers/Teen Centers and CYSS Sports and Fitness (S&amp;F). For SLOs, these programs are Youth Education Support and Outreach.&lt;ref name=&quot;Army Regulation 215-1&quot;/&gt;

===Community Recreation Centers===
Community Recreation Center (CRC) programs and services support the overall FMWR mission and according to the U.S. Army are directly related to unit readiness by delivering individual and group activities during peacetime, mobilization, contingency, and wartime operations. CRC programs provide individual physical, mental, and social benefits.&lt;ref name=&quot;Army Regulation 215-1&quot;/&gt;

===Entertainment (performing arts)===
[[File:ArmySoldierShowRehearsal.jpg|thumb|Soldiers perform &quot;Jai Ho&quot; from the soundtrack of multiple Oscar Award-winning ''[[Slumdog Millionaire]]'' during rehearsals for the 2009 U.S. Army Soldier Show at Wallace Theater on Fort Belvoir, Va.]]

The FMWR entertainment program provides diverse musical, unit entertainment activities, special events, and theater entertainment. The U.S. Army's entertainment program also includes local performing arts centers and the U.S. Army Soldier Show.&lt;ref name=&quot;Army Regulation 215-1&quot;/&gt;

===Golf===
The Army golf program offers recreational golf, open play, tournaments, and services such as golf
instruction, golf resale, food and beverage services, catering, and other golf-related activities for eligible patrons.&lt;ref name=&quot;Army Regulation 215-1&quot;/&gt;

===Gyms &amp; physical fitness centers===
According to the U.S. Army, physical fitness programs develop the cardiovascular fitness, strength conditioning, flexibility, and recreation of Army personnel. For most U.S. Army garrisons, physical fitness facilities are the hub of the installation-level sports and fitness programs. Authorized patrons are generally afforded access to Army gyms and physical fitness centers at no cost to the patron.&lt;ref name=&quot;Army Regulation 215-1&quot;/&gt;

===Leisure Travel Services===
FMWR Leisure Travel Services (LTS) provide information and access for personal travel and travel related services at representative industry or discount prices. LTS often provide Army personnel access to commercial travel and tourism discounts.&lt;ref name=&quot;Army Regulation 215-1&quot;/&gt;

===Library &amp; information services===
According to the U.S. Army, on-post libraries are a central information resource for the military community providing the tools and services to impact mission readiness, support lifelong learning, enable literacy, and enhance the military community’s well being. Services found at garrison libraries include borrower services, inter-library loan access, reference/research support, educational support, and technical services. Army libraries also offer information technology resources, and internet access. Army libraries are subject to standards of regional educational accrediting associations, the American Council on Education, and the Military Installation Voluntary Educational Review, which review and accredit colleges and universities offering classes on Army installations.&lt;ref name=&quot;Army Regulation 215-1&quot;/&gt;

[[File:Yongsan Army Library.jpg|thumb|Joanne Sharp, wife of Gen. Walter Sharp, United States Forces Korea commanding general, visits the U.S. Army's Yongsan Garrison Library on 21 Nov. 2009 to read to military family members as part of a Thanksgiving Story Hour. U.S. Army photo]]

A listing for all the Army MWR libraries can be found at the FMWR website.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://mylibraryus.fmwr.net/ |title=mylibraryus.fmwr.net |publisher=mylibraryus.fmwr.net |date= |accessdate=2012-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Movies===
The FMWR movie program provides free-admission motion picture entertainment to isolated or deployed military personnel and civilians.&lt;ref name=&quot;Army Regulation 215-1&quot;/&gt;

===Food, beverage, and entertainment on military installations===
By U.S. Army regulation, MWR food, beverage, and entertainment (FB&amp;E) programs encompass all MWR food operations such as military clubs (membership and nonmembership), FB&amp;E operations, and snack bar operations in MWR facilities such as bowling, golf, and recreation centers. MWR FB&amp;E programs are a part of a commander's overall food service programs and assist the commander, along with AAFES and subsistence/troop feeding, in meeting the food service needs an Army installation’s assigned or visiting personnel.&lt;ref name=&quot;Army Regulation 215-1&quot;/&gt;

===Outdoor recreation===
The FMWR outdoor recreation program provides structured and recreation activities and instruction. By regulation, it offers diverse, healthful, vigorous, and comprehensive outdoor recreation programs, while conserving and protecting wildlife, forests, wetlands, and other natural resources.&lt;ref name=&quot;Army Regulation 215-1&quot;/&gt;

===Sports and fitness===
U.S. Army installation and unit-level intramural programs are designed for broad-based participation in a full range of individual and team intramural programs consistent with patron interest, availability of suitable facilities, unit missions, and climate. The U.S. Army encourages commanders to use these programs provide opportunities to enhance individual morale and unit esprit de corps, promote teamwork and cooperation, engage in competitive recreation, and to encourage individuals to attain and sustain high levels of physical fitness and physical readiness. FMWR emphasizes group participation in unit and intramural sports with wide appeal, such as softball, volleyball, flag football, basketball, running, skeet, and soccer. Sports and fitness programming also includes instruction, practice, and competition at all skill levels. Generally, playing rules published by U.S. national sports governing bodies are used for all competitions conducted within the Army.&lt;ref name=&quot;Army Regulation 215-1&quot;/&gt;

===Swimming===
U.S. Army swimming programs a designed promote fitness and recreation and include instruction, lifeguard training, fitness programs, comptetive swimming, water safety, military survival training and recreation.

==Special programs and services==

===Survivor Outreach Services===

Survivor Outreach Services (SOS) provides specialized resources to assist families of deceased soldiers.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.military.com/military-report/army-survivor-outreach-services Army Survivor Outreach Services 27 Oct 2008. Retrieved 11 Aug 201].&lt;/ref&gt; The program aims to provide access to support, information and services at a location near the survivor, for as long as needed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.myarmyonesource.com/FamilyProgramsandServices/SurvivingFamilies/SurvivorOutreachServices.aspx |title=Survivor Outreach Services |publisher=Myarmyonesource.com |date= |accessdate=2012-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The program exists as a joint effort between FMWR, the [[Installation Management Command]] (IMCOM), the Casualty and Mortuary Affairs Operation Center (CMAOC), the Army National Guard and Army Reserve.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.army.mil/standto/archive/2009/03/06/ |title=Stand-to: Survivor Outreach Services 6 March 2009. Retrieved 11 August 2010 |publisher=Army.mil |date= |accessdate=2012-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Exceptional Family Member Program===

The [[Exceptional Family Member Program]] (EFMP) works with other military and civilian agencies to provide comprehensive and coordinated community support, housing, educational, medical, and personnel services worldwide to military families with special needs. As a specific example, EFMP provides temporary rest periods for family members who serve as caregivers to persons with disabilities. Depending on unique circumstances, the care can be provided at either the home of the care user or the home of care provider. It can also be provided in other settings such as camps and enrichment programs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.army.mil/aps/08/information_papers/sustain/Exceptional_Family_Member_Respite_Care.html |title=2008 Army Posture Statement, Exceptional Family Member Program Respite Care |publisher=Army.mil |date=2008-02-04 |accessdate=2012-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Within the Army, EFMP is governed by Army Regulation 608-75.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.army.mil/usapa/epubs/pdf/r608_75.pdf |title=Army Regulation 608-75 |format=PDF |date= |accessdate=2012-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Army Entertainment Detachment===

====Soldier Show====

The U.S. Army Soldier Show is a musical ensemble of soldiers which tours military installations annually.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.armymwr.com/recleisure/entertainment/soldiershow/default.aspx |title=U.S. Army Soldier Show |publisher=Armymwr.com |date= |accessdate=2012-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its current form originated in 1983 from several existing shows, but Sgt. Israel Beilin directed the first version of the Army Soldier Show, &quot;Yip Yip Yaphank&quot; in 1918. Beilin is better known as [[Irving Berlin]]. He also coined the ensemble's motto: &quot;Entertainment for the Soldier, by the Soldier.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;About the 2010 Soldier Show&quot;&gt;[http://www.armymwr.com/recleisure/entertainment/soldiershow/2010_soldiershow_mediakit.aspx About the 2010 Soldier Show] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101204033534/http://www.armymwr.com/recleisure/entertainment/soldiershow/2010_soldiershow_mediakit.aspx |date=4 December 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the selection of the cast and crew, soldiers work with the Army Entertainment Detachment of FMWR as a deployable military unit. Training at [[Fort Belvoir]] lasts six weeks, after which time, the group tours for up to seven months. Performances can include up to 40 songs in a variety of genres during each 90 minute performance.&lt;ref name=&quot;About the 2010 Soldier Show&quot;/&gt;

The Soldier Show is not funded with any taxpayer funds, but with non-appropriated funds generated by business programs of FMWR.&lt;ref name=&quot;About the 2010 Soldier Show&quot;/&gt;

The theme for the 2011 season is &quot;Carnival&amp;nbsp;– A Traveling Thank You.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.army.mil/-news/2011/05/03/55898-fort-belvoir-gets-a-taste-of-the-carnival-at-soldier-show-kickoff// |title=Fort Belvoir gets a taste of the carnival at Soldier Show kickoff&quot; 3 May 2011. Retrieved 5 May 2011 |publisher=Army.mil |date= |accessdate=2012-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:RaiseTheRoof_-_Spc._Corrin_Zielger_on_front_right_-_Flickr_-_familymwr.jpg|U.S. Army Soldier Show at Fort Belvoir, Va.
Image:Sgt_Quashika_Taylor_-_US_Army_-_FMWRC_PAO_-_Flickr_-_familymwr.jpg|Staff Sgt. Talitha Nettles of Walter Reed Army Medical Center in Washington sings Mariah Carey's &quot;Hero&quot; during live auditions for the 2011 U.S. Army Soldier Show at Wallace Theater on Fort Belvoir.
&lt;/gallery&gt;

====Operation Rising Star====

Operation Rising Star is an annual singing competition for military service members and their spouses in the style of ''[[American Idol]]''. Auditions are conducted annually at military garrisons around the world and the semifinalists travel to Fort Belvoir in Virginia to compete in the final phases of the competition.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.myfoxwfld.com/myvoicedc/2008/11/14/operation-rising-star-looking-for-a-military-idol/ &quot;Operation Rising Star Looking for a ‘Military’ Idol&quot; 14 Nov. 2008. Retrieved 11 Aug. 2010]&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the competition, winners record a three-song demo CD at DMI Music's Firehouse Recording Studios in Pasadena, California.&lt;ref&gt;United States Army, Tim Hipps. [http://www.army.mil/-news/2010/02/02/33887-operation-rising-star-winner-cuts-cd-praises-army-family-covenant/ &quot;Operation Rising Star winner cuts CD, praises Army Family Covenant&quot;] 2 Feb 2010. Retrieved 11 Aug 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:LisaPrattWins2009ORS.jpg|thumb|Army Family and Morale, Welfare and Recreation Commander then [[Reuben D. Jones|Brig. Gen. Reuben D. Jones]] (right) presents a boarding pass to Operation Rising Star winner Lisa Pratt as co-host GeNienne Samuels (left) applauds on 20 Nov. 2009 at Fort Belvoir, Va.'s Wallace Theater.]]

&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:2008 Operation Rising Star (Reveal) - U.S. Army - FMWRC - Flickr - familymwr (32).jpg|Army Family member and veteran Joyce Dodson won the 2008 Operation Rising Star military singing contest Nov. 14 at Wallace Theater.
Image:2008 Operation Rising Star (Finals) - U.S. Army - FMWRC - Flickr - familymwr (12).jpg|Operation Rising Star (Finals), 2008  
&lt;/gallery&gt;

====Army Concert Tour====

The Army Concert Tour is a summer concert series that brings popular music acts to Army installations.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.armymwr.org/news/news.aspx?nid=26 |title=Toby Keith headlines first three shows of Army Concert Tour IMCOM Public Affairs, 2 June 2010. Retrieved 11 Aug 2010 |publisher=Armymwr.org |date=2012-12-03 |accessdate=2012-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; Performers for the 2010 season include [[Toby Keith]], [[Ludacris]], [[Sammy Hagar]], [[Creed (band)|Creed]] and [[Miranda Lambert]], in addition to others.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.armymwr.com/recleisure/entertainment/2010_act_schedule.aspx 2010 Army Concert Tour schedule Retrieved 11 Aug 2010] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20101204055547/http://www.armymwr.com/recleisure/entertainment/2010_act_schedule.aspx |date=4 December 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:CrowdAtFortKnoxConcert.jpg|Audience members rush toward the stage after the gates open at an Army Concert Tour stop at Fort Knox.
Image:TobyKeithPerformsAtFortKnox.jpg|[[Toby Keith]] is a headliner at several Army Concert Tour stops during the 2010 season. 
Image:CartersChordAtFortKnox.jpg|[[Carter's Chord]] performs at Fort Knox as part of the Army Concert Tour.
Image:KatharineMcPheeAtFort.jpg|As part of the Army Concert Tour, [[Katharine McPhee]] sings for the crowd at Fort Knox.
&lt;/gallery&gt;

===Warrior Adventure Quest===

Warrior Adventure Quest provides recreational opportunities for soldiers during the transition period immediately following deployment. Past activities have included white-water rafting, paintball and mountain biking. Army officials hope that by utilizing the program, there will be a reduction in high-risk off-duty activities.

WAQ is managed by the Outdoor Recreation Program of Family and MWR. According to Army officials, the average cost per person to participate in WAQ is $86.&lt;ref&gt;Department of Defense [http://www.defense.gov/news/newsarticle.aspx?id=51348 &quot;Warrior Adventure Quest Helps Soldiers Return to Normalcy&quot; 1 Oct. 2008. Retrieved 11 Aug 2010]&lt;/ref&gt;

===World Class Athlete Program===

The [[US Army World Class Athlete Program|U.S. Army World Class Athlete Program (WCAP)]] provides soldier-athletes the opportunity to compete toward qualifying for the United States Olympic team. Qualified soldiers must be nationally ranked in their chosen sport and be certified by the [[United States Olympic Committee]] at a world class level. Athletes join the program at least three years before the Olympic Trials.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.goarmy.com/events/army_athletes/army_sports_programs.jsp U.S. Army Recruiting, &quot;Army Sports Programs&quot;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100514163219/http://www.goarmy.com/events/army_athletes/army_sports_programs.jsp |date=14 May 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;armymwr.com&quot;&gt;[http://www.armymwr.com/sports/entry_standards.aspx World Class Athlete Program Entry Standards] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100727165404/http://www.armymwr.com/sports/entry_standards.aspx |date=27 July 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; To be eligible for the U.S. Army World Class Athlete Program, soldiers must currently be a member of the Active Army, Army Reserve, or Army National Guard. Soldiers must also be eligible to represent the USA in international competitions and demonstrate the potential to qualify for the U.S. Olympic Team or U.S. Paralympic Team.&lt;ref name=&quot;armymwr.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.armymwr.com/sports/how_to_apply.aspx U.S. Army Recruiting, &quot;Army Sports Programs&quot;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100727165414/http://www.armymwr.com/sports/how_to_apply.aspx |date=27 July 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;gallery&gt;
Image:wcap6.jpg|Army National Guard Outstanding Athlete Program, 2010 Winter Olympics.
Image:DF-SD-08-05994.JPEG|U.S. Army's World Class Athlete Program, 2004 Summer Olympics.
Image:Wcap3.JPEG|U.S. Army's World Class Athlete Program, 2004 Summer Olympics.
Image:Wcap2.jpg|2009 U.S. National Boxing Championships.
Image:WCAPWrestlerUSArmy.jpg|Army World Class Athlete Program, 2010 World Team Trials for USA Wrestling.
Image:WCAPTeelaShooting.jpg|Army World Class Athlete Program Olympic biathlete Jeremy Teela practicing.
Image:Flickr_-_The_U.S._Army_-_Skiing_to_victory.jpg|U.S. Biathlon World Team Trials in Coleraine, Minn..
Image:WCAPAthletesSignAutographs.jpg|WCAP athletes sign autographs for fans, 2009 AUSA Conference.
Image:U.S. Army World Class Athlete Program wrestler Sgt. Iris Smith (right) defeats Chinas Lijun Yang.jpg|U.S. Army World Class Athlete Program wrestler Sgt. Iris Smith (right) defeats China's Lijun Yang 1-1, 0-1, 3-0 en route to winning the gold medal in the women's 72-kilogram/158.5-pound freestyle division Aug. 14 at the 27th World Military Wrestling Championships in Lahti, Finland.
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==MG Robert M. Joyce FMWR School==

The Installation Management Academy is a full-fledged brick and mortar institution of professional learning and career development, featuring the Maj. Gen. Robert M. Joyce Family and MWR School. The school includes numerous subject matter experts in various areas of U.S. Army Family and Morale, Welfare and Recreation Activities. Nearly 100 courses are offered through online or classroom formats. Recently, 39 courses have received college credit recommendations from the [[American Council on Education]] (ACE) and graduates are increasingly transferring them to colleges and universities to receive college credits. Since its inception, employees have completed over 28,400 courses in various Family and MWR program areas.&lt;ref name=&quot;Family and MWR Academy Website&quot;&gt;[https://www.mwraonline.com/index.asp Family and MWR Academy Website]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:MWRAcademyDedicationCeremony.jpg|thumb|right|Maj. Gen. Reuben Jones and Virginia &quot;Ginny&quot; Joyce unveil the plaque commemorating the newly named Maj. Gen. Robert M. Joyce Family and MWR Academy at a ceremony 27 May 2010.]]In May 2010 the Family and MWR Academy was renamed the MG Robert M. Joyce Family and MWR Academy in honor of the first Commander of the Community and Family Support Center. MG Joyce was instrumental in the founding of the Academy and the inspired vision of a professional and developed workforce.&lt;ref name=&quot;Family and MWR Academy Website&quot;/&gt; Following the transition from a headquarters in Alexandria, Va., to San Antonio, Texas, The Academy became the Maj. Gen. Robert M. Joyce Family and MWR School within the Installation Management Academy.&lt;ref name=&quot;army.mil&quot;/&gt;

On 7 April 1986 the Commanding General of Community and Family Support Center (CFSC) tasked Colonel Perkins, as Chief of Field Operations, to review training within MWR and its programs throughout the Army. The focus of the review was to identify the system's currently available training, specify its shortfalls, determine the optimum training program, and project the estimated resources necessary to fund an improved program. The ultimate qualifier to apply to the review was &quot;What is best for the Army.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Family and MWR Academy – About Us&quot;&gt;[https://www.mwraonline.com/aboutus.asp Family and MWR Academy – About Us]&lt;/ref&gt;

Upon completion of Colonel Perkins' task, a Master Training Concept was developed and approved, and the MWR Academy was launched. A graphical representation of the Master Training Concept was defined in terms of a pyramid. The Master Training Concept was designed to integrate all levels of training and all programs for training, and ensure availability of training to the workforce.&lt;ref name=&quot;Family and MWR Academy – About Us&quot;/&gt;

The Master Training Concept is still applicable today. This plan, in conjunction with the Army Civilian Training, Education and Development System (ACTEDS) Plan for Career Field 51 (MWR) forms the basis of the Family and MWR Academy's curriculum. Together, these guidelines provide a structured, progressive, and sequential approach to Family and MWR employee development and training for entry-level through executive-management positions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Family and MWR Academy – About Us&quot;/&gt;

The Family and MWR School is also an Authorized Provider (AP) of [[Continuing Education Unit]]s (CEUs) from the [[American National Standards Institute]] (ANSI)/ International Association for Continuing Education and Training (IACET). All Family and MWR-sponsored courses are reviewed for their compliance with ANSI/IACET standards and receive CEUs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Family and MWR Academy – About Us&quot;/&gt;

Since the Academy's inception, over 28,400 family and MWR employees have been trained in various Family and MWR program areas and at various levels.&lt;ref name=&quot;Family and MWR Academy – About Us&quot;/&gt;

==Funding categories==

===Category A: Mission-sustaining programs===
Considered essential to sustaining readiness, these programs generally enhance and promote the physical and mental
well being of Soldiers. Programs in this category have little or no capacity for generating Non-appropriated Fund (NAF) income and are supported almost entirely with funds appropriated by the U.S. Congress (APF).&lt;ref name=&quot;Army Regulation 215-1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://appropriations.senate.gov/ht-defense.cfm?method=hearings.download&amp;id=a2613a06-d133-4e73-9a5a-3ece411fcac9 |title=Senate Committee on Appropriates, Subcommittee on Defense, Second Session, 111th Congress, on the Posture of the United States Army |date= |accessdate=2012-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Category B: Community support programs===
These programs are closely related, in terms of supporting the military mission, to those grouped in category A. They satisfy the basic physiological and psychological needs of Soldiers and their Families and provide, to the extent possible, the community support systems that make military garrisons temporary hometowns for a mobile military population. These support programs will receive substantial amounts of APF support, but differ from those programs in category A, in part because of their ability to generate NAF revenues. That ability to generate revenues is limited, however, and in no case may they be sustained without substantial APF support.&lt;ref name=&quot;Army Regulation 215-1&quot;/&gt;

===Category C: Revenue-generating programs===
These programs have less impact on readiness. They offer desirable social and recreational opportunities. Programs in this category have the capability of generating enough income to cover most of their operating expenses, but they lack the ability to sustain themselves based purely on their business activity; consequently, they receive limited APF support. Chapter 5 addresses funding for category C MWR programs located at remote and isolated sites, funding for base closures, and funding as a result of special security conditions.&lt;ref name=&quot;Army Regulation 215-1&quot;/&gt;

==Nonappropriated Fund Instrumentalities (NAFI)==

Every NAFI is legally constituted as an &quot;instrumentality of the United States.&quot; The term &quot;NAFI&quot; includes entities at the garrison level, also referred to as garrison MWR operating entities or simply entities (previously the installation MWR fund). Funds in NAFI/entity accounts are Government funds, and NAF property, including buildings, is Government property. However, NAFs are separate from APFs of the U.S. Treasury. They are not commingled with APFs and are managed separately, even when supporting a common program.&lt;ref name=&quot;Army Regulation 215-1&quot;/&gt;

Each NAFI/entity operates under the authority of the U.S. Government in accordance with applicable Federal laws and departmental regulations. Because NAFIs/entities operate under the authority of the Federal Government, they are entitled to the same sovereign privileges and immunities as the Federal Government accorded by Federal law.&lt;ref name=&quot;Army Regulation 215-1&quot;/&gt;

Applicable DOD directives and implementing Army regulations are binding on NAFIs. NAFI/entity programs and facilities are operated, maintained, and funded as part of the U.S. Army's personnel and readiness program.&lt;ref name=&quot;Army Regulation 215-1&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://appropriations.senate.gov/ht-defense.cfm?method=hearings.download&amp;id=1eebbcfa-f06a-4c10-bedd-d11132ea1136 |title=2009 Army Posture Statement |date= |accessdate=2012-12-13}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==External links==
*{{Official website|http://www.armymwr.com/ }}
*[https://www.army.mil/familymwr/?from=wiki Family and MWR News]
*[http://www.armymwr.com/recleisure/entertainment/soldiershow/default.aspx The U.S. Army Soldier Show]
*[http://www.armymwr.org/ Family and MWR Employee Portal]
*[http://www.flickr.com/photos/FamilyMWR Family and MWR Command Official Image Archive]
*[http://www.youtube.com/FamilyMWR Family and MWR Command Official Video Archive]
*[http://www.armymwr.com/news/social_media.aspx Family and MWR Command Social Media Presences]
*[http://www.AFRCResorts.com/ AFRC Resorts Official Website]

{{US Army navbox}}
{{United States armed forces}}
{{United States topics}}

[[Category:United States Army|Army]]</text>
      <sha1>pwiuhaqh0pzzoesm76lclup840iuqc8</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
