<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>USS Wedderburn</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1427441</id>
    <revision>
      <id>743718903</id>
      <parentid>743664676</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-10T21:26:18Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cydebot</username>
        <id>1215485</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Robot - Moving category Ships built in San Francisco, California‎ to [[:Category:Ships built in San Francisco]] per [[WP:CFD|CFD]] at [[Wikipedia:Categories for discussion/Log/2016 September 6]].</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="27097">{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2012}}

{|{{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
|Ship image=[[Image:USS Wedderburn;0568406.jpg|300px|USS Wedderburn (DD-684)]]
|Ship caption=
}}
{{Infobox ship career
|Hide header=
|Ship country=United States
|Ship flag={{USN flag|1969}}
|Ship name=
|Ship namesake=[[Charles F. Wedderburn]]
|Ship ordered=
|Ship builder=[[Bethlehem Shipbuilding Corporation]], [[San Francisco, California]]
|Ship laid down=10 January 1943
|Ship launched=1 August 1943
|Ship acquired=
|Ship commissioned=9 March 1944
|Ship decommissioned=1 October 1969
|Ship in service=
|Ship out of service=
|Ship struck=1 October 1969
|Ship reinstated=
|Ship honours=
|Ship fate=Sold 25 January 1972 for scrapping
|Ship status=
|Ship notes=
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
|Hide header=
|Header caption=
|Ship class=[[Fletcher class destroyer]]
|Ship displacement=2,050&amp;nbsp;tons
|Ship length=376.4&amp;nbsp;ft (114.7&amp;nbsp;m) 
|Ship beam=39.6&amp;nbsp;ft (12.1&amp;nbsp;m)
|Ship draught=
|Ship draft=13.8&amp;nbsp;ft (4.2&amp;nbsp;m)
|Ship propulsion=*60,000&amp;nbsp;shp (45&amp;nbsp;MW);
*2 propellers
|Ship speed=38&amp;nbsp;[[knot (unit)|kt]] (70&amp;nbsp;km/h)
|Ship range=6500&amp;nbsp;[[nautical mile|nmi]] (12,000&amp;nbsp;km)  @ 15&amp;nbsp;kt
|Ship complement=329
|Ship sensors=
|Ship EW=
|Ship armament=*5 × 5&amp;nbsp;in/38 guns,
*10 × 40&amp;nbsp;mm AA guns,
*7 × 20&amp;nbsp;mm AA guns,
*10 × 21&amp;nbsp;in torpedo tubes
|Ship armour=
|Ship armor=
|Ship aircraft=
|Ship aircraft facilities=
|Ship notes=
}}
|}
'''USS ''Wedderburn'' (DD-684)''', a [[Fletcher class destroyer|''Fletcher''-class]] [[destroyer]], was a ship of the [[United States Navy]] named for lieutenant (j.g.) [[Charles F. Wedderburn]], a destroyerman who was killed during [[World War I]].

''Wedderburn'' (DD-684) was laid down on 10 January 1943 at [[San Francisco]] by the [[Bethlehem Steel]] Co.; [[Ship naming and launching|launched]] on 1 August 1943; sponsored by Mrs. Gertrude F. Wedderburn; and [[ship commissioning|commissioned]] on 9 March 1944, Commander John L. Wilfong in command.

== 1944 ==
Following shakedown training along the west coast and post-shakedown availability back at the Bethlehem Steel Co., ''Wedderburn'' departed San Francisco on 21 June in company with [[USS Fieberling (DE-640)|''Fieberling'' (DE-640)]]. The two warships arrived in [[Pearl Harbor]] six days later, and ''Wedderburn'' joined Task Unit (TU) 19.3.2 with which she served briefly on plane guard and anti-submarine duty. On 1 July, the destroyer continued her voyage west to [[Eniwetok]] in the [[Marshall Islands]] where she joined Task Force (TF) 53 for the second assault of the Marianas operation, the [[Battle of Guam (1944)|battle of Guam]].

She stood out of Eniwetok on 17 July in company with Task Group (TG) 53.4, the Southern Transport Group. She arrived off [[Guam]] on 22 July, the day after the initial assault on that island and, for the next three weeks, performed yeoman service protecting the invasion fleet&amp;mdash;upon which the battle ashore depended&amp;mdash;from the threat of Japanese [[submarine]] attack. Her service in the [[Mariana Islands|Marianas]] ended on 10 August when she shaped a course back to Eniwetok.

''Wedderburn'' reentered the [[lagoon]] at Eniwetok on 14 August. There, she was reassigned to the antisubmarine screen of a fast carrier task group, TG&amp;nbsp;38.2, built around [[USS Intrepid (CV-11)|''Intrepid'']] (CV-11), [[USS Hancock (CV-19)|''Hancock'']] (CV-19), [[USS Bunker Hill (CV-17)|''Bunker Hill'']] (CV-17), [[USS Cabot (CVL-28)|''Cabot'']] (CVL-28), and [[USS Independence (CVL-22)|''Independence'']] (CVL-22). She sailed from Eniwetok on 29 August in company with the entire [[fast carrier task force]] (TF&amp;nbsp;38) to conduct a major sweep of Japanese-held islands including the [[Philippines]], the [[Palau Islands|Palaus]], and [[Yap]] Island. ''Wedderburn'' screened the carrier from enemy submarine attacks while they sent their planes against targets on [[Mindanao]] and [[Leyte (island)|Leyte]] and, later, the [[Visaya Islands|Visayas]] sub-group. They also provided initial aerial bombardment for the [[Battle of Palau|Palau invasion]] and for the [[Battle of Morotai|Morotai operation]]. Those missions took up almost the entire month of September, and the destroyer did not enter a &quot;port&quot; until the 28th when TG&amp;nbsp;38.2 arrived at Saipan. On 1 October, she and TG&amp;nbsp;38.2 moved on to recently captured [[Ulithi]] where the ships arrived the next day. ''Wedderburn'', however, soon returned to sea. Task Force 38 rendezvoused about 375&amp;nbsp;miles west of the Marianas on 7 October to open the preliminaries to the [[Battle of Leyte|invasion of Leyte]]. ''Wedderburn'' continued her antisubmarine vigil while the [[Aircraft carrier|carriers]] she protected launched their aircraft first against [[Okinawa]], then [[Taiwan|Formosa]], and finally Philippine targets, striking enemy air bases on [[Luzon]] and the Visayas to give the United States dominance in the air over Leyte when the invasion began on 20 October.

''Wedderburn'' continued to guard the fast carriers while they operated off the northeastern shore of Luzon providing distant air support for the Leyte invasion. By the 24th, it had become apparent that the Japanese planned to dispute the landing with some variety of naval force. The result was the four-phase [[Battle for Leyte Gulf]]. That same day, planes from ''Wedderburn''-protected carriers opened the battle striking at the enemy's Center Force, commanded by [[Vice Admiral]] [[Takeo Kurita]]&amp;mdash;while it traversed the [[Sibuyan Sea]] toward the [[San Bernardino Strait]]. Late that evening, after having sunk [[battleship]] [[Japanese battleship Musashi|''Musashi'']] and damaged other Japanese ships, the fast carriers raced northward to take the bait offered by a force of almost plane-less aircraft carriers which Vice Admiral [[Jisaburo Ozawa]] was using as a decoy force. Thus, ''Wedderburn'' was far north when the [[Battle of Surigao Strait|Surigao Strait]] and [[Battle off Samar|Samar]] phases were fought on the night of 24&amp;ndash;25 October and the morning of the 25th, respectively. Instead, she participated in the final phase of the battle, against Ozawa's force, though her role remained one of support for the carriers which she screened against submarine attack while she rescued their downed aviators.

After the Battle for Leyte Gulf, the destroyer continued to operate off Luzon with TG&amp;nbsp;38.2 while the carriers' planes provided additional air cover for the troops fighting to capture Leyte. That duty lasted until 5 November when engine trouble forced her to set a course for Ulithi. The warship arrived at that advanced base on 10 November, quickly completed repairs, and rejoined TG&amp;nbsp;38.2 off Luzon just after mid-month. Her return, however, proved brief; for, on 23 November, she received orders to return to Ulithi to join TG&amp;nbsp;38.1. At Ulithi, she conducted exercises until 10 December when she departed the atoll with TG&amp;nbsp;38.1 to support the [[Battle of Mindoro|landings on Mindoro]]. During that operation, TF&amp;nbsp;38 passed through the infamous [[Typhoon Cobra (1944)|typhoon of December 1944]] which damaged many ships in the force and sank three. ''Wedderburn'', however, suffered only minor damage and participated in the search for survivors of [[USS Hull (DD-350)|''Hull'']] (DD-350), [[USS Monaghan (DD-354)|''Monaghan'']] (DD-354), and [[USS Spence (DD-512)|''Spence'']] (DD-512) though she did not engage in any actual rescue operations. The damage caused by the typhoon necessitated a return to Ulithi for repairs. The destroyer and the other ships of TF&amp;nbsp;38 entered the lagoon on Christmas Eve and remained there six days, resuming operations on 30 December 1944.

== 1945 ==
The return to sea brought TF&amp;nbsp;38 into active participation in support of the [[Battle of Luzon|Luzon invasion]] at [[Lingayen, Pangasinan|Lingayen]]. The fast carriers sought to keep Japanese reinforcements&amp;mdash;airborne, naval, and land&amp;mdash;from entering the fray against the invading forces by keeping enemy air-power grounded and by sinking as much of his shipping as possible. Thus, ''Wedderburn'' resumed her role as guardian of the carriers while their planes made up the offensive arm of the [[United States Third Fleet|Third Fleet]]. On 3 and 4 January 1945, fast carrier aircraft hit air installations and shipping at Formosa and Okinawa. They went after targets on Luzon itself on the 6th and 7th and, on the 9th, the day of the initial landings, returned to Formosa for air suppression duty while troops were going ashore. Following that assignment, she moved through [[Bashi Channel]] with TF&amp;nbsp;38 for two weeks of air raids on Japanese-held [[Northern and southern China|southern China]] and [[French Indochina]] which included an anti-shipping sweep of the [[South China Sea]]. On the return voyage, TF&amp;nbsp;38 planes struck at the [[Nansei Shoto]], a group of islands near Okinawa, on the 21st and 22d before reentering Ulithi Lagoon on the 25th.

Soon thereafter, the Third Fleet became the [[United States Fifth Fleet|Fifth Fleet]] when [[Admiral (United States)|Admiral]] [[Raymond A. Spruance]] relieved Admiral [[William F. Halsey]]. The change in designation reflected the change of command only, and all else remained substantially as it was. ''Wedderburn'' continued to provide antisubmarine protection for her task group, redesignated TG&amp;nbsp;58.2. Early on 10 February, the fast carriers again stood out of Ulithi to provide air support for the assault on [[Iwo Jima]] in the [[Volcano Islands]]. On 16 February, they launched planes for a strike against air installations around [[Tokyo]], the first air raid on the Japanese capital since 1942 when the Fast Carrier Task Force commander, Vice Admiral [[Marc A. Mitscher]]&amp;mdash;then captain of [[USS Hornet (CV-8)|''Hornet'' (CV-8)]]&amp;mdash;launched [[Lieutenant colonel (United States)|Lieutenant Colonel]] [[Jimmy Doolittle|James Doolittle's]] [[B-25 Mitchell|B-25]] bombers on [[Doolittle Raid|their famous raid]]. During the current two-day attack, the American planes made 138 sorties in which their pilots claimed to have sunk three picket boats and an [[escort carrier]] as well as to have destroyed over 700 enemy aircraft. Following the raid, ''Wedderburn'' escorted the carriers south to Iwo Jima where she participated in shore bombardments and patrolled against submarines in TF&amp;nbsp;51's transport area. On 23 February, she departed Iwo Jima and rejoined TG&amp;nbsp;58.2 as it headed off north with the rest of TF&amp;nbsp;58 for another round of strikes on the Japanese home islands. Foul weather, however, forced the cancellation of those strikes; and, after a refueling rendezvous, the carriers and their escorts reentered the lagoon at Ulithi on 4 March.

After 10 days of refueling, rearming, and repairing, TF&amp;nbsp;58 left Ulithi and shaped a course for Japan. Their first targets were the airfields on [[Kyūshū]], located within striking range of Okinawa, the 5th Fleet's next objective. The carriers launched planes on 18 March, but the enemy struck back with fighters, bombers, and [[kamikaze]]s. In the ensuing battle, near misses damaged [[USS Enterprise (CV-6)|''Enterprise'']] (CV-6), [[USS Yorktown (CV-10)|''Yorktown'']] (CV-10), and [[USS Intrepid (CV-11)|''Intrepid'']] (CV-11). The next day, [[USS Franklin (CV-13)|''Franklin'']] (CV-13) received a direct bomb hit; and the enemy scored one on [[USS Wasp (CV-18)|''Wasp'']] (CV-18) as well. However, on a more positive side, ''Wedderburn'' gunners claimed two of the attacking enemy planes. After TF&amp;nbsp;58 sustained the damage of 18 and 19 March, it was reorganized somewhat. Wedderburn's TG&amp;nbsp;58.2 became a [[task force|task group]] made up of damaged carriers ''Enterprise'', ''Franklin'', and ''Wasp'', and gave up a number of its screening units to the similarly reformed TG&amp;nbsp;58.1.

''Wedderburn'' was one of those escorts so reassigned and consequently remained with TF&amp;nbsp;58 while the task group of cripples retired to base. She continued to screen the carriers as they launched air strikes on Okinawa during the last week in March and the week following the 1 April [[Battle of Okinawa|landings]]. Throughout the entire period, the Japanese launched air attacks at them incessantly.

It was not until the 6th, however, that sighting reports made it apparent that the enemy planned a suicidal surface attack with the remnants of their fleet. Superbattleship [[Japanese battleship Yamato|''Yamato'']], screened by a cruiser and eight destroyers, started south to contest the landings. The fast carriers continued to steam on station off Okinawa protected by ''Wedderburn'' and her colleagues but, on 7 April, launched a series of search and attack sorties which ultimately sent the mighty Japanese battleship to the bottom along with [[light cruiser]] [[Japanese cruiser Yahagi (1942)|''Yahagi'']] and four of the escorting destroyers.

After that scrape, TF&amp;nbsp;58 concentrated its efforts on supporting the troops ashore and defending itself and the invasion force from the final onslaught of Japanese air power. ''Wedderburn'' remained in the vicinity of the [[Ryukyu Islands]] for another 20 days until TG&amp;nbsp;58.1 headed for Ulithi on 27 April. On 18 May, the destroyer departed Ulithi to escort [[USS Missouri (BB-63)|''Missouri'']] (BB-63) to Guam to pick up Admiral William F. Halsey who was scheduled to take command of the naval forces off Okinawa later that month. She then escorted ''Missouri'' back to the Ryukyus and reentered the fray at Okinawa at the beginning of the final week of May.

Halsey took over from Admiral [[Raymond Spruance]] on 27 May; and&amp;mdash;now that Admiral Halsey was back in overall command&amp;mdash;''Wedderburn'' and her associates became units of the [[US 3rd Fleet|3d Fleet]] rather than of the 5th Fleet. For the remainder of World War II, she screened various task groups of TF&amp;nbsp;38 first while they continued support for the Okinawa operation and, later that summer, when they went on their final rampage in the Japanese home islands. The Japanese capitulation on 15 August found her in the screen of TG&amp;nbsp;38.4 while the carriers were preparing for yet another air strike&amp;mdash;one which they did not launch.

Immediately following the war, the destroyer served with the occupation forces around [[Tokyo Bay]], escorting Japanese merchant ships, supervising [[Naval mine|mine]]-clearing operations, and making hydrographic surveys. On 31 October, she shaped a course back to the United States. After a stop at Pearl Harbor from 9 to 13 November, she resumed her voyage and arrived at the [[Puget Sound Naval Shipyard]] on 19 November. Following repairs at Puget Sound, she was placed out of commission in March 1946 and was berthed at [[San Diego]].

== 1950 &amp;ndash; 1953 ==

In August 1946, she returned to semi-activity when she began training naval reservists, until 21 November 1950 when she was recommissioned, Comdr. Richard B. Franklin in command.

The newly recommissioned destroyer joined the Pacific Fleet Destroyer Force in January 1951; completed her reactivation work at [[Hunters Point Naval Shipyard]]; and, in May, finished underway training. On 18 June, she departed the west coast for her first tour of duty in the [[Korean War]]. Though assigned operationally to the Blockading and Escort Force ([[Task Force 95|TF&amp;nbsp;95]]), she also served periodically as a plane guard for the fast carriers of [[Task Force 77 (U.S. Navy)|TF&amp;nbsp;77]] as well as on the [[Taiwan Strait]] patrol ([[Task Force 72|TF&amp;nbsp;72]]). For the most part, though, her duties consisted of blockading the coastline of [[Korea]] and providing gunfire support for the [[United Nations]] troops operating ashore. She concluded her first tour of duty in the Far East with the Taiwan Strait patrol and returned to the United States in February 1952.

After an overhaul at the [[San Francisco Naval Shipyard]] and several weeks of training, the warship headed back to Korea in August 1952. Once again, she divided her time between blockading and gunfire support missions along the Korean coast and escort duty with the fast carriers as well as short periods with the Taiwan Strait patrol. ''Wedderburn'' concluded her second Korean War deployment and returned to San Diego in March 1953.

During the next seven months, the destroyer conducted normal west coast operations out of San Diego. The Korean War ended with the armistice of 27 July 1953 right near the midpoint of ''Wedderburn'''s seven months of [[US 1st Fleet|1st Fleet]] operations. When she returned to the Far East in October, she began the first essentially peacetime deployment of her career.

== 1954 &amp;ndash; 1964 ==
[[Image:USS Wedderburn 1964.jpg|thumb|250px|right|USS Wedderburn (DD-684) firing her 5&quot;/38 guns at a target drone aircraft, during exercises, 21 August 1964.]]
In the decade between 1954 and 1964, the warship continued to alternate deployments to the western Pacific with tours of duty along the coast of southern California. For the most part, the seven tours she made to the Far East consisted of port visits and training exercises. During the 1958 deployment, she visited [[Sydney]], Australia, in addition to her usual ports of call farther north and participated in the multinational [[SEATO]] exercise, [[Operation Ocean Link]]. That deployment also saw her on patrol in the Taiwan Strait during the American show of force over the [[Quemoy]] and [[Matsu Islands|Matsu]] bombardment by the Chinese communists. The remainder of her deployments were more routine in nature consisting of plane guard duty with TF&amp;nbsp;77, port visits, training exercises, and periods of time with the Taiwan Strait patrol. When not in the Orient, she conducted type training, upkeep, and periodic overhauls on the west coast.

The warship departed San Diego on 5 August 1964 to begin her 11th deployment to the Far East. Four days before, the [[Gulf of Tonkin incident]] occurred, signaling a stepped-up American involvement in the strife in [[South Vietnam]]. That involvement dictated the nature of ''Wedderburn'''s 7th Fleet assignments for the remainder of her active career. During the fall of 1964, she operated off the Vietnamese coast as plane guard and escort for TF&amp;nbsp;77, duplicating her service during World War II and the Korean War. She also provided sporadic gunfire support for units ashore in the [[Mekong Delta]] area. She departed the newly established combat zone in November for a SEATO weapons demonstration and then put into [[Subic Bay]] in the Philippines for upkeep.

== 1965 &amp;ndash; 1969 ==

After Christmas liberty at [[United States Fleet Activities Yokosuka|Yokosuka]], Japan, she returned to active operations in the South China Sea in January 1965. At the conclusion of that duty, late in the month, she set course for home, arriving in San Diego on 6 February. She spent the remainder of 1965 in the eastern Pacific. After a month of post-deployment stand-down followed by four weeks of local operations out of San Diego, she entered the [[Long Beach Naval Shipyard]] for a month-long availability. In June and July, she embarked [[NROTC]] [[midshipman|midshipmen]] for their summer cruise, during which she visited [[San Francisco, California|San Francisco]] and the islands of [[Kauai]] and [[Oahu]] in [[Hawaii]]. Returning to San Diego on 4 August, the warship conducted three weeks of repairs and then resumed training operations which continued until she began preparations for another Far Eastern cruise in November.

On 7 January 1966, ''Wedderburn'' departed San Diego in company with [[USS Worden (DLG-18)|''Worden'']] (DLG-18), [[USS Richard B. Anderson (DD-786)|''Richard B. Anderson'']] (DD-786), and [[USS Bausell (DD-845)|''Bausell'']] (DD-845). After stops at Oahu, [[Midway Atoll|Midway]], and Guam, she arrived in Subic Bay on 28 January. On 1 February, she headed for the South China Sea where she became a unit of TG&amp;nbsp;77.5 and served as escort and plane guard for the carriers until 28 February. Following a brief return to Subic Bay, she visited [[U.S. Fleet Activities Sasebo|Sasebo]], Japan, and Okinawa early in March. She returned to the Vietnam combat zone on 12 March as a unit of TG&amp;nbsp;77.7 and again served as escort and plane guard for carriers conducting air strikes in North Vietnam. She continued in that role until 2 April when she was detached and reassigned to Task Unit (TU) 70.8.9 to conduct gunfire support missions near [[Danang]] and [[Quang Tri]]. On the 6th, the warship resumed her former assignment with TG&amp;nbsp;77.7. On 24 April, she joined a different unit, TU 77.0.3, to conduct trawler surveillance in the [[Gulf of Tonkin]]. On 2 May, she returned to gunfire support duty, this time near [[Chu Lai]], until 8 May. On that day, the destroyer resumed duty with TF&amp;nbsp;77 as a [[search and rescue]] (SAR) vessel on the southern SAR station. On 15 May, she concluded her last combat assignment of the 1966 deployment. After a week's liberty call at Hong Kong and repairs at Yokosuka, ''Wedderburn'' headed home on 3 June and arrived in San Diego 10 days later. Following local operations, the destroyer entered the Long Beach Naval Shipyard on 11 August for a three-month overhaul. She completed sea trials on 20 November and resumed normal operations on the 21st.

During the first two months of 1967, ''Wedderburn'' conducted extensive refresher training exercises and, during March and early April, made preparations for overseas movement. On 8 April, she stood out of San Diego once more in company with ''Worden'', [[USS Brush (DD-745)|''Brush'']] (DD-745), and [[USS Lyman K. Swenson (DD-729)|''Lyman K. Swenson'']] (DD-729). She stopped at Pearl Harbor from 14 to 17 April and arrived in Yokosuka on the 27th. Three days later, she got underway for Okinawa whence she continued on to [[Yankee Station]] in the Gulf of Tonkin where she conducted plane guard duty with TG&amp;nbsp;77.6. Five days later, she shifted to shore bombardment duty near the [[Vietnamese Demilitarized Zone|demilitarized zone]] (DMZ). That assignment lasted until 27 May when she returned to the carriers on Yankee Station. She left the combat zone on 5 June and arrived in Subic Bay two days later.

She made repairs and embarked two NROTC midshipmen and then departed the Philippines on 10 June to return to the Gulf of Tonkin. There, she divided her time between plane guard duty for [[USS Hancock (CVA-19)|''Hancock'']] (CVA-19) and [[Antisubmarine warfare|ASW]] exercises with [[USS Bronstein (DE-1037)|''Bronstein'']] (DE-1037) and [[USS Catfish (SS-339)|''Catfish'']] (SS-339). She visited [[Kaohsiung]], Taiwan, from 25 June to 10 July and underwent repairs alongside [[USS Delta (AR-9)|''Delta'']] (AR-9). On her return to the coast of Vietnam, she rejoined TU 70.8.9 for a series of gunfire support missions in the [[US I Corps|I Corps]] zone of operations. Her guns helped the [[United States Marine Corps|marines]] ashore complete [[Operation Bear Chain]], an [[amphibious assault]] by Special Landing Force &quot;Bravo&quot; near [[Quang Tri City]]. On 21 July, she headed back to Subic Bay for a week of repairs and upkeep.

She did not return to the Vietnamese coast for a month due to repairs to her evaporator system. However, on 20 August, she headed back to the combat zone where, on the 22d, she resumed gunfire support duty for troops in the [[U.S. II Corps|II Corps]] zone. Relieved by [[USS Eaton (DD-510)|''Eaton'']] (DD-510) on 26 August, she rejoined TF&amp;nbsp;77 in the Gulf of Tonkin and served as escort for the carriers until 3 September. She departed the Gulf of Tonkin late on the 3d and shaped a course for Okinawa, arriving there on the 7th. From there, she moved on to Yokosuka for a 10-day layover before getting underway for home on the 21st. ''Wedderburn'' reached San Diego on 6 October and began the normal post-deployment stand-down. It was then that Dan Waddell Jr. was conceived.  In mid-November, she resumed normal operations in the southern California operating area. That routine continued until she began repairs at Long Beach on 19 April 1968. She returned to San Diego on 24 May and resumed normal operations out of her home port.

''Wedderburn'' embarked upon the final western Pacific deployment of her career on 30 September. Steaming in company with [[USS Hornet (CVS-12)|''Hornet'']] (CVS-12), she stopped at Oahu for nine days in mid-October and then continued her voyage to Yokosuka, where she arrived on the 27th. On the 30th, she accompanied ''Hornet'' out of Yokosuka, and together, they laid course for the Tonkin Gulf. They arrived in the gulf on 3 November; but, two days later, ''Wedderburn'' became an escort for [[USS Constellation (CVA-64)|''Constellation'']] (CVA-64) for two days. After that, she rejoined her old colleague, ''Hancock''. On 17 November, a recurring [[sonar]] problem forced the destroyer to head for Subic Bay, where she remained until 9 December. She returned to duty in the Tonkin Gulf on 11 December but remained on station only until the 31st when steam leaks forced her back to Subic Bay.

She completed repairs late in January 1969 and returned to the combat zone soon thereafter. The warship remained on station, dividing her time between gunfire support, carrier escort, and [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] trawler surveillance, until mid-March. After a brief return to Subic Bay, she began her final tour of duty on the gunline on 22 March. ''Wedderburn'' served as a gunfire support ship for about a month before beginning her homeward voyage on 20 April. En route, she made stops at Yokosuka, Japan, and [[Buckner Bay]], Okinawa; and arrived back in San Diego on 12 May. She remained in port throughout the summer of 1969 due to a casualty to her propulsion plant and, in September, received word that she was going to be decommissioned.

On 1 October 1969, ''Wedderburn'' was placed out of commission at San Diego, and her name was struck from the [[Navy list]]. On 25 January 1972, she was sold to Dhon's Iron &amp; Steel Co., Ltd., for scrapping.

''Wedderburn'' earned seven [[battle star]]s for [[World War II]] service, four battle stars for [[Korean War]] service, and six battle stars for service in the [[Vietnam War]].

{{Clear}}

== References ==
*{{DANFS|http://www.history.navy.mil/research/histories/ship-histories/danfs/w/wedderburn.html}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|USS Wedderburn (DD-684)}}
*[http://www.navsource.org/archives/05/684.htm   navsource.org: USS ''Wedderburn'']
*[http://www.hazegray.org/danfs/destroy/dd684txt.htm  hazegray.org: USS ''Wedderburn'']

{{Fletcher class destroyer}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Wedderburn (DD-684)}}
[[Category:World War II destroyers of the United States]]
[[Category:Cold War destroyers of the United States]]
[[Category:Korean War destroyers of the United States]]
[[Category:Vietnam War destroyers of the United States]]
[[Category:Ships built in San Francisco]]
[[Category:1943 ships]]
[[Category:Fletcher-class destroyers of the United States Navy]]</text>
      <sha1>s5kywyz8av7wpb1n5e9rysxdxhmejke</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
