<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>USS Agerholm</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1558846</id>
    <revision>
      <id>745737313</id>
      <parentid>745730404</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-23T00:41:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Izno</username>
        <id>2927383</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Izno moved page [[USS Agerholm (DD-826)]] to [[USS Agerholm]] over redirect: [[WP:CONCISE]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20847">{|{{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
|Ship image=[[File:Ussagerholm-dd.jpg|300px]]
|Ship caption=USS ''Agerholm'' (DD-826)
}}
{{Infobox ship career
|Hide header=
|Ship country=United States
|Ship flag={{USN flag|1946}}
|Ship name=USS ''Agerholm''
|Ship namesake= [[Harold C. Agerholm]]
|Ship ordered=
|Ship awarded=
|Ship builder=
|Ship original cost=
|Ship yard number=
|Ship way number=
|Ship laid down=10 September 1945
|Ship launched=30 March 1946
|Ship sponsor=
|Ship christened=
|Ship completed=
|Ship acquired=
|Ship commissioned=20 June 1946
|Ship recommissioned=
|Ship decommissioned=1 December 1978
|Ship maiden voyage= 
|Ship in service=
|Ship out of service=
|Ship renamed=
|Ship reclassified=
|Ship refit=
|Ship struck=1 December 1978
|Ship reinstated=
|Ship homeport=
|Ship identification=DD-826
|Ship motto=
|Ship nickname=
|Ship honors=
|Ship captured=
|Ship fate=Sunk as a target on 18 July 1982
|Ship status=
|Ship notes=
|Ship badge=
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
|Hide header=
|Header caption=
|Ship class={{sclass-|Gearing|destroyer}}
|Ship displacement=2,425 tons full load
|Ship length={{convert|390.5|ft|abbr=on}}
|Ship beam={{convert|41.1|ft|abbr=on}}
|Ship height=
|Ship draft={{convert|18.5|ft|abbr=on}}
|Ship power=
|Ship propulsion=
|Ship speed={{convert|35|kn|abbr=on}}
|Ship range=
|Ship endurance=
|Ship complement=367
|Ship sensors=
|Ship EW=
|Ship armament=*6 x 5 in (127&amp;nbsp;mm) guns
*4 x 40&amp;nbsp;mm guns
*5 x 21 in (533&amp;nbsp;mm) [[torpedo tube]]s
*6 depth charge projectors
*2 depth charge racks
|Ship armor=
|Ship aircraft=
|Ship aircraft facilities=
|Ship notes=
}}
|}

'''USS ''Agerholm'' (DD-826)''' was a {{sclass-|Gearing|destroyer}} of the [[United States Navy]]. She was the only ship named for [[Harold C. Agerholm|Harold Crist Agerholm]] (29 January 1925 – 7 July 1944), a Private First Class (Pfc.) in the [[2nd Marine Division (United States)|2nd Marine Division]] of the [[United States Marine Corps]]. He was killed during the [[Battle of Saipan|assault on Saipan]], and posthumously awarded the [[Medal of Honor]].

== Construction and career ==
''Agerholm'' was [[Keel laying|laid down]] on 10 September 1945 at [[Bath, Maine]], by the [[Bath Iron Works]], [[Ceremonial ship launching|launched]] on 30 March 1946, sponsored by Mrs. Rose Agerholm, mother of Pfc. Agerholm; [[Ship commissioning|commissioned]] on 20 June 1946, Commander Frank D. Schwartz in command.&lt;ref name=DANFS&gt;{{cite DANFS|url= https://www.history.navy.mil/research/histories/ship-histories/danfs/a/agerholm.html |title= Agerholm (DD-826)}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After commissioning and fitting out, the destroyer conducted shakedown training at [[Guantanamo Bay Naval Base]], Cuba, and underwent post- shakedown repairs at the [[Boston Naval Shipyard]] before receiving orders to duty with the Pacific Fleet. Proceeding to the Pacific by way of the [[Panama Canal]], she reached her new home port of [[San Diego]] on 21 January 1947.&lt;ref name=DANFS /&gt;

===First operations===
''Agerholm'' was assigned to Destroyer Division (DesDiv) 12 and settled into a routine of local training operations in the waters off southern California. On 10 March, the warship sailed from San Diego on her first extended cruise to the western Pacific. While operating with the [[United States Seventh Fleet|7th Fleet]], ''Agerholm'' visited the Chinese ports of [[Qingdao|Tsingtao]], [[Shanghai]], and [[Amoy]], before they were closed to American traffic. She also visited [[Kwajalein]], [[Okinawa]], [[Hong Kong]], and several ports in Japan. The destroyer returned to San Diego on 26 November and remained there for the holiday season.&lt;ref name=DANFS /&gt;

Between January 1948 and June 1950, ''Agerholm'' alternated two WestPac deployments with operations out of San Diego. Upon her return to San Diego in June 1950, she commenced overhaul at [[Mare Island, California]], while other ships steamed to Korea as part of the United Nations task force defending [[South Korea]] from the aggression of her northern counterpart. Completing her overhaul in late 1950, ''Agerholm'' trained for war and set a course for the Far East. She entered the combat zone on 19 February 1951 and was assigned to [[Task Force 77 (U.S. Navy)|Task Force 77]] as screening ship and plane guard. The destroyer also aided in shore bombardment, training her guns on [[Wonsan]] on 28 April and 1 May to 4 May, and on [[Kojo, North Korea|Kojo]] on 29 April. ''Agerholm'' returned to San Diego on 20 September for upkeep and local operations.&lt;ref name=DANFS /&gt;

In May 1952, the warship left San Diego for her second tour with TF&amp;nbsp;77 in Korea. In addition to screening and planeguard duties, ''Agerholm'' conducted naval gunfire support as required. During one exchange of gunfire with a communist shore battery a single enemy shell struck the destroyer in the after part of the ship, starting a small fire in the crew's after berthing compartment but causing only minor damage to the weatherdeck. ''Agerholm'' continued on assigned duties until December, when she set a course for San Diego, arriving there on 21 December.&lt;ref name=DANFS /&gt;

On 2 February 1953, the destroyer commenced another overhaul at Mare Island, followed by refresher training in May. After several months of preparation and fulfilling local training commitments, ''Agerholm'' got underway on 8 September for her sixth WestPac cruise. Although the [[Korean War]] had ended the 7th Fleet conducted various operations to ensure the continuation of peace in the Far East. ''Agerholm'' steamed many miles in support of the [[Taiwan|Formosa]] patrol, designed to deter both the [[Kuomintang|Chinese Nationalists]] and the [[Chinese communists]] from invading each other, before she returned to her home port on 16 April.&lt;ref name=DANFS /&gt;

===Further operations===
The destroyer made her seventh WestPac cruise from November 1954 to April 1955. While operating with TF&amp;nbsp;77, she again found herself involved in peacekeeping operations. Task Force 77 covered the evacuation of the Chinese Nationalist forces from the [[Tachen Islands]] in [[Operation Pullback]]. Following this mission the destroyer returned to the United States and commenced an overhaul at Mare Island on 29 April.&lt;ref name=DANFS /&gt;

During the next five years, ''Agerholm'' deployed to the western Pacific four more times, and briefly stopped in Australia during the summer of 1958 to participate in ceremonies commemorating the [[Battle of the Coral Sea]]. In May 1960, the destroyer reported to Mare Island for extensive modification and changes under the [[Fleet Rehabilitation and Modernization]] (FRAM) program. ''Agerholm'' left the shipyard in March 1961 equipped with the latest antisubmarine rockets ([[ASROC]]), [[torpedo]]es, helicopter facilities, radar and sonar. During 1961, the destroyer devised and tested new techniques and tactics for use of her new capabilities.&lt;ref name=DANFS /&gt;

[[File:Asrocnuke1962.jpg|thumb|left|''Agerholm'' tests an [[ASROC]] anti-submarine rocket armed with a nuclear depth bomb in 1962]]
On 11 May 1962, ''Agerholm'' participated in [[nuclear weapons test|nuclear weapon testing]] in the Pacific in the &quot;Swordfish&quot; test, part of [[Operation Dominic I and II|Operation Dominic]]. During this exercise the destroyer became the first surface ship to fire an antisubmarine nuclear weapon;&lt;ref name=DANFS /&gt; the nuclear explosion occurring only about 4,000 yards from the ship.{{cn|date=October 2016|reason= not in citation given}}

The [[submarine]] {{USS|Razorback|SS-394|2}} participated in the test, at the same distance as ''Agerholm''.  A video of this test is available from the [[United States Department of Energy|Department of Energy]].{{cn|date=October 2016|reason= not in citation given}}

In November, following continued training in the San Diego area, ''Agerholm'' sailed to the western Pacific on her 12th deployment. She returned to her home port in June 1963 and commenced overhaul at the [[NASNI|Naval Repair Facility, San Diego]], to update and improve the electronic and weapons systems on board. Following completion of the overhaul in January 1964, ''Agerholm'' continued her routine of local operations and preparations for deployment.&lt;ref name=DANFS /&gt;

===Vietnam===
In August, the destroyer got underway for the western Pacific where she spent six months patrolling off the coast of [[Vietnam]] and in the [[Taiwan Strait]]. Upon her return to her home port early in 1965, ''Agerholm'' underwent a brief overhaul and in August embarked [[midshipman|midshipmen]] for a cruise to Hawaii. With the escalation of American involvement in Vietnam, the destroyer prepared for another cruise to that area.&lt;ref name=DANFS /&gt;

''Agerholm'' began her next deployment in January 1966 when she departed San Diego for Vietnam. There, her assigned duties included [[Naval Gunfire Support]] (NGFS), [[anti-submarine warfare]] (ASW), carrier escort, and [[search and rescue]] (SAR). In May during NGFS off the [[South Vietnam]]ese coast, ''Agerholm'' provided call fire for a [[United States Marine Corps|Marine Corps]] air spotter who was drawing heavy gunfire. The destroyer silenced the [[Viet Cong]] machine gun nest with just four rounds from her 5-inch (127&amp;nbsp;mm) guns. On 17 June ''Agerholm'' aided a South Vietnamese patrol boat and took off 12 badly wounded men while on a SAR mission in the [[Gulf of Tonkin]]. The ship visited [[Subic Bay]], [[United States Fleet Activities Yokosuka|Yokosuka]], [[Kaohsiung]], Hong Kong and [[Pearl Harbor]] before returning to San Diego in July.&lt;ref name=DANFS /&gt;

''Agerholm'' began another modernization overhaul at the [[Long Beach Naval Shipyard]] in August. She received new 5-inch gun mounts, and advanced [[radar]] and [[sonar]] gear, as well as communications systems and engineering plant alterations. The destroyer left the shipyard in December to spend the holiday season in her home port.&lt;ref name=DANFS /&gt;

With the advent of 1967, ''Agerholm'' once again prepared for deployment to the Far East. On 15 May, she departed for the Gulf of Tonkin, joining the [[aircraft carrier]] {{USS|Intrepid|CV-11|6}} at [[U.S. Naval Base Subic Bay|Subic Bay]]. The ships sailed to &quot;[[Yankee Station]]&quot; where they arrived on 20 June. For the next four months, ''Agerholm'' provided plane guard assistance for the carriers ''Intrepid'', {{USS|Constellation|CVA-64|2}}, and {{USS|Coral Sea|CVA-43|2}}.&lt;ref name=DANFS /&gt;

When a major fire broke out on the aircraft carrier {{USS|Forrestal|CVA-59|2}} on 29 July all ships in the area, including ''Agerholm'', aided in the rescue operations and stood by until the damaged carrier was able to steam under her own power for Subic Bay. The destroyer departed &quot;Yankee Station&quot; on 1 October and arrived in San Diego on 25 October.&lt;ref name=DANFS /&gt;

''Agerholm'' spent most of 1968 on training cruises for [[United States Naval Academy]] and [[Reserve Officers' Training Corps|ROTC]] midshipmen. In May, she participated in tests conducted off [[San Clemente Island]] by the [[China Lake Naval Weapons Testing Center]], and fired the new rocket-assisted projectile (RAP). Two days before the year was out, ''Agerholm'' sailed from San Diego on her 16th WestPac cruise. During the transit to the Gulf of Tonkin via Pearl Harbor and Subic Bay, the destroyer escorted the aircraft carrier {{USS|Kitty Hawk|CVA-63|2}}, and subsequently served as plane guard for that carrier's first combat launch from &quot;Yankee Station&quot; during the new year 1969.&lt;ref name=DANFS /&gt;

From 28 January to 10 February, ''Agerholm'' served as escort for the [[destroyer leader]] {{USS|William H. Standley|DLG-32|2}} in the positive identification radar advisory zone ([[PIRAZ]]). She then proceeded to the Southern SAR station to ride shotgun for the destroyer leader {{USS|Fox|DLG-33|2}}. The destroyer shifted to the gunline on 23 March, and provided naval gunfire support to troops in the Viet Cong-dominated Rung Sat Special Zone (RSSZ). Anchored in the shallow restricted water with the Viet Cong less than {{convert|6000|yd|km}} away, ''Agerholm'' was vulnerable to enemy fire, underwater swimmers, and mines. On 25 March, the destroyer first fired both RAP and conventional ammunition into the RSSZ with great accuracy. On 13 April, she retired from NGFS to visit [[Singapore]], Hong Kong, and [[Kaohsiung|Kaohsiang]].&lt;ref name=DANFS /&gt; ''Agerholm'' returned to the gunline on 15 May, conducting shore bombardments off [[Phan Thiet]] until 23 May. She then reported to the [[cruiser]] {{USS|Chicago|CG-11|2}} on PIRAZ station in the Gulf of Tonkin for her last assignment. On 10 June, the warship was relieved and ordered to Subic Bay to prepare for her return voyage. After port visits to [[Brisbane]], Australia, and [[Auckland]], New Zealand ''Agerholm'' set a course for San Diego, where she arrived on 24 July.&lt;ref name=DANFS /&gt;

===Further cruises===
The destroyer entered [[Hunters Point Naval Shipyard]] on 11 September for overhaul, which was completed on 19 December. ''Agerholm'' returned to San Diego the next day for the Christmas holidays. ''Agerholm'' got underway on 26 January 1970 for type training, followed by eight weeks of refresher training. On 15 April, the destroyer completed the exhausting round of drills and commenced preparations for overseas deployment.&lt;ref name=DANFS /&gt;

''Agerholm'' departed San Diego on 6 July and steamed via Pearl Harbor, [[Midway Atoll|Midway]], and [[Guam]], to Subic Bay, arriving on 28 July. From there, the destroyer served on the gunline, on the northern SAR station, as PIRAZ escort, and as plane guard.&lt;ref name=DANFS /&gt; On 14 October, ''Agerholm'' was detached for independent transit to Hong Kong. En route, the destroyer passed within {{convert|60|mi|km}} of the center of [[Typhoon Joan (1970)|Super Typhoon Joan]] in the [[South China Sea]]. For two tense days, the crew was uncertain of surviving the {{convert|60|kn}} winds and {{convert|40|ft|m|adj=on}} seas, but the destroyer began to open the typhoon center late on 16 October. The remainder of her deployment was spent at PIRAZ station until 4 December when ''Agerholm'' cleared the area for Guam, Midway, and Pearl Harbor. The ship arrived back in San Diego on 20 December and spent the remainder of the year in her home port.&lt;ref name=DANFS /&gt;

''Agerholm'' spent the first six months of 1971 in port at San Diego or operating off the California coast. On 29 June, the destroyer began another WestPac cruise, taking up gunline duties near [[Binh Thuy, South Vietnam]], on 6 August. In addition to NGFS, ''Agerholm'' served as planeguard and SAR ship before departing the area on 4 December. She returned to San Diego for the holidays, and closed out the year with post-deployment standdown.&lt;ref name=DANFS /&gt;

Local exercises and inspections occupied ''Agerholm'' until 24 July 1972 when she entered the Long Beach Naval Shipyard for a five-month overhaul. The destroyer departed the shipyard on 21 December and steamed to San Diego, where she began preparations, both at sea and in port, for refresher training on 7 February 1973. After seven weeks of continuous drills, ''Agerholm'' successfully completed refresher training and qualified in NGFS at San Clemente Island.&lt;ref name=DANFS /&gt;

On 7 February 1973, three sailors were injured in an engine room fire aboard ''Agerholm'' while off San Diego.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= https://www.history.navy.mil/research/library/online-reading-room/title-list-alphabetically/c/casualties-usnavy-marinecorps-personnel-killed-injured-selected-accidents-other-incidents-notdirectly-result-enemy-action.html |title= Casualties: US Navy and Marine Corps Personnel Killed and Injured in Selected Accidents and Other Incidents Not Directly the Result of Enemy Action |publisher= Naval History and Heritage Command |accessdate= 22 October 2016 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 26 April, ''Agerholm'' set sail in company with the [[destroyer escort]] {{USS|Stein|DE-1065|2}} for the western Pacific. She arrived off the coast of Vietnam at &quot;Yankee Station&quot; on 28 May to serve as plane guard for Constellation. The destroyer then underwent a two-week availability alongside the auxiliary veseel {{USS|Ajax|AR-6|2}} in [[Sasebo, Japan]] commencing 8 June. Upon completion of those repairs, she put to sea for radar picket duty in the Gulf of Tonkin. Another two weeks at &quot;Yankee Station&quot; followed by two weeks on PIRAZ station brought her Vietnam service to an end. On 30 August, ''Agerholm'' departed the Gulf of Tonkin en route to [[Mackay, Queensland|MacKay, Australia]], for liberty.&lt;ref name=DANFS /&gt;

After that port visit, the destroyer sailed to Auckland, New Zealand to join the other ships participating in [[Operation Longex 73]], a joint surface, air, and submarine warfare exercise. From 25 September to 3 October ''Agerholm'' drilled in ASW and [[anti-aircraft warfare]] (AAW) exercises — including night surface attacks on the task groups. Upon completion of the drill, she steamed to Sydney, Australia; [[Suva]], [[Fiji]]; and Pearl Harbor, before arriving back in San Diego on 1 November.&lt;ref name=DANFS /&gt;

Upon arrival, ''Agerholm'' commenced a post-deployment readiness improvement program of schools, on board training, and a repair availability. On 25 February 1974, the warship got underway for readiness exercises in the southern California area until 17 September, when she departed San Diego on her 20th WestPac cruise. Remaining primarily in the Subic Bay operating area, ''Agerholm'' participated in gunnery, ASW, AAW, and ship handling drills until 13 December, when she shaped a course for [[Apra Harbor]], Guam. She ended the year at the ship repair facility there. The destroyer visited Hong Kong and Singapore for liberty, but received orders on 8 February 1975 to join [[Operation Eagle Pull]],&lt;ref name=DANFS /&gt; the evacuation of the American embassy in [[Phnom Penh]], Cambodia. ''Agerhoim'' completed her role in the evacuation on 26 February, and she began the long voyage home.&lt;ref name=DANFS /&gt;

''Agerholm'' arrived in San Diego on 8 April and spent the rest of 1975 and 1976 on the west coast participating in local operations and midshipman training cruises, and eventually landing a role in the movie ''[[Airport '77]]''. The year 1977 began the same way with only a drydock period at [[Todd Pacific Shipyards, Los Angeles Division|Todd Pacific Shipyards]] in [[San Pedro, California|San Pedro]] from May to July to interrupt the routine. On 6 September, the destroyer made her 21st and last WestPac cruise. ''Agerholm'' conducted NGFS training, ASROC test firings, and participated in [[Exercise Fortress Lightning]], a full-scale amphibious landing on [[Mindoro Island]] in the [[Philippines]]. She stopped for liberty calls at Suva, Auckland, [[Whangarei]], and [[Nelson, New Zealand]], [[Newcastle, New South Wales|Newcastle]] and [[Devonport, Australia]], before returning: to San Diego early in 1978 to resume a local operation schedule.&lt;ref name=DANFS /&gt;
[[File:Tomahawk missile sinking USS Agerholm (DD-826) 1982.JPEG|thumb|''Agerholm'' being sunk by an [[Tomahawk cruise missile|UGM-109]] launched from {{USS|Guitarro|SSN-665|6}}, 1982.]]

===Disposal===
From 10 to 13 October 1978, the [[Board of Inspection and Survey]] conducted a survey of ''Agerholm'' to determine her material condition and the feasibility of keeping her in active service. The board found that her age and lack of modern capabilities could not be corrected economically. ''Agerholm'' was [[Ship decommissioning|decommissioned]] on 1 December 1978, and her name was struck from the Navy List on the same day. She was sunk as a target on 18 July 1982.&lt;ref name=DANFS /&gt; The wreck lies in 400&amp;nbsp;[[fathom]]s (730&amp;nbsp;m) of water, at approximately {{coord|32|45|N|119|32|W|display=inline, title}}.{{cn|date=October 2016}}

''Agerholm'' earned four battle stars for Korean War service and eight for tours off Vietnam.&lt;ref name=DANFS /&gt;

== References ==
*{{DANFS|https://www.history.navy.mil/research/histories/ship-histories/danfs/a/agerholm.html}}
{{reflist|30em}}

== External links ==
{{Commons category|USS Agerholm (DD-826)}}
*[http://www.navsource.org/archives/05/826.htm    navsource.org: USS ''Agerholm'']
*[http://www.hazegray.org/danfs/destroy/dd826txt.htm         hazegray.org: USS ''Agerholm'']

{{Gearing class destroyer}}
{{1982 shipwrecks}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2012}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Agerholm (DD-826)}}
[[Category:Cold War destroyers of the United States]]
[[Category:Korean War destroyers of the United States]]
[[Category:Vietnam War destroyers of the United States]]
[[Category:Ships built in Bath, Maine]]
[[Category:1946 ships]]
[[Category:Ships sunk as targets]]
[[Category:Maritime incidents in 1982]]
[[Category:Shipwrecks of the California coast]]
[[Category:Gearing-class destroyers of the United States Navy]]</text>
      <sha1>j3th52pyyp559woo8kifrhbu4bdoq7m</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
