<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>USS Aucilla (AO-56)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>12719824</id>
    <revision>
      <id>737775597</id>
      <parentid>688149017</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-05T00:11:58Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>BD2412</username>
        <id>196446</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Convoyed to the United Kingdom */Per consensus in discussion at [[Talk:New York#Proposed action to resolve incorrect incoming links]], replaced: [[New York]] → [[New York City|New York]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22498">{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2012}}

{|{{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
|Ship image=[[File:Aucilla (AO-56).JPG|300px]]
|Ship caption=
}}
{{Infobox Ship Career
|Hide header=
|Ship country=United States
|Ship flag={{USN flag|1945}}
|Ship name=USS ''Aucilla''
|Ship namesake=
|Ship owner=
|Ship operator=
|Ship registry=
|Ship route=
|Ship ordered=as T3-S2-A1 tanker hull, MC hull 722
|Ship awarded=
|Ship builder=
|Ship original cost=
|Ship yard number=
|Ship way number=
|Ship laid down=25 May 1943
|Ship launched=20 November 1943
|Ship sponsor=
|Ship christened=
|Ship completed=
|Ship acquired=
|Ship commissioned=  22 December 1943
|Ship recommissioned=
|Ship decommissioned=18 December 1970
|Ship maiden voyage= 
|Ship in service=
|Ship out of service=
|Ship renamed=
|Ship reclassified=
|Ship refit=
|Ship struck=1 December 1976
|Ship reinstated=
|Ship homeport=
|Ship identification=AO-56
|Ship motto=
|Ship nickname=
|Ship honours=
|Ship honors=
|Ship captured=
|Ship fate=scrapped 25 October 1992
|Ship status=
|Ship notes=
|Ship badge=
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
|Hide header=
|Header caption=
|Ship class={{sclass-|Cimarron|oiler (1939)|0}} [[fleet oiler]]
|Ship type=
|Ship tonnage=
|Ship displacement=7,236 t.(lt) 25,440 t.(fl)
|Ship tons burthen=
|Ship length={{convert|553|ft|m|abbr=on}} 
|Ship beam={{convert|75|ft|m|abbr=on}} 
|Ship height=
|Ship draught={{convert|32|ft|m|abbr=on}} 
|Ship draft=
|Ship depth=
|Ship hold depth=
|Ship decks=
|Ship deck clearance=
|Ship ramps=
|Ship ice class=
|Ship power={{convert|30,400|hp|lk=in|abbr=on}}
|Ship propulsion=geared [[turbines]], twin screws
|Ship sail plan=
|Ship speed={{convert|18|kn|lk=in}}
|Ship range=
|Ship endurance=
|Ship test depth=
|Ship boats=
|Ship capacity=146,000 barrels
|Ship troops=
|Ship complement=314
|Ship crew=
|Ship time to activate=
|Ship sensors=
|Ship EW=
|Ship armament=one single 5-inch/38 dual purpose [[gun mount]]; four single 3-inch/50 dual purpose gun mounts; four twin 40mm AA gun mounts; four twin 20mm AA gun mounts
|Ship armour=
|Ship armor=
|Ship aircraft=
|Ship aircraft facilities=
|Ship notes=
}}
|}

'''USS ''Aucilla'' (AO-56)''' was a {{sclass-|Cimarron|oiler (1939)|0}} [[fleet oiler]]. She was constructed for the [[United States Navy]] during World War II and her assignment was to provide liquids, such as fuel or water, to ships in the forward battle areas. She survived this dangerous task and returned home post-war with five [[battle star]]s to her credit.

{{TOClimit|2}}
''Aucilla''  was laid down on 25 May 1943 at [[Sparrows Point, Maryland]], by the [[Bethlehem Steel]] Co. under a [[Maritime Commission]] contract (MC hull 722); launched on 20 November 1943; sponsored by Mrs. Hope Ridings Miller; and commissioned on 22 December 1943, Comdr. Cornelius M. Sullivan in command.

==World War II==

===North Atlantic operations===
 
The oiler remained at Sparrows Point until 28 December at which time she got underway for [[Portsmouth, Virginia]]. She arrived at the [[Norfolk Navy Yard]] on the 29th and began training the crew at battle stations and loading ammunition. ''Aucilla'' continued her training both in port and underway in the lower [[Chesapeake Bay]]. On 2 February 1944, she departed Norfolk in company with the [[destroyer]] {{USS|Goldsborough|DD-188|2}} on her way to the [[British West Indies]]. The oiler arrived at the Naval Operating Base (NOB), [[Trinidad]], on 7 February and began dispensing fuel to [[warships]] operating in the vicinity. She remained there until 14 March at which time she put to sea, in [[convoy]], for [[Aruba]]. ''Aucilla'' arrived at her destination on 16 March, took on a cargo of [[aviation gasoline]], and departed Aruba on 17 March. After a stop at [[Guantanamo Bay, Cuba]], the oiler arrived in [[Norfolk, Virginia]], on 24 March.

===Convoyed to the United Kingdom===
 
For about a month, she operated out of Norfolk in the lower [[Chesapeake Bay]] testing fueling at sea gear and techniques. On 26 April, ''Aucilla'' departed Norfolk in company with the destroyer {{USS|Belknap|DD-251|2}} and, five days later, arrived in [[Baytown, Texas]]. After taking on a cargo of fuel, the ship stood out of Baytown on 4 May and arrived at [[Staten Island, New York]], on the 8th. On 14 May, she was underway, in convoy, for the [[British Isles]]. The oiler parted company with the convoy on 25 May and entered port at [[Liverpool, England]], that same day. She discharged her cargo on 27 May and got underway for Ireland the next day. She visited [[Belfast Lough]] from 29 May to 5 June and then headed back to the United States. ''Aucilla'' arrived at Norfolk on 16 June.
 
Six days after her arrival, the oiler sailed from Norfolk for [[New York City|New York]]. She arrived on 23 June and operated in that locale until the end of the month. On 2 July, ''Aucilla'' put to sea bound for Europe once again. She returned to [[Belfast]] on 12 July but stopped only briefly, returning to sea that same day. The oiler visited [[Swansea]], Wales, between 13-16 July before heading home via [[Belfast]]. She reentered [[Hampton Roads]] on 27 July. There, she stayed for almost a month. On 22 August, ''Aucilla'' put to sea in company with the destroyer {{USS|J. Fred Talbott|DD-156|2}} bound for [[Baytown, Texas]]. She took on a cargo of fuel oil at Baytown before returning to sea. The ship arrived at [[Bermuda]] on 3 September and unloaded her cargo. She then headed back to [[Hampton Roads, Virginia]], where she dropped anchor on 8 September. Operations in Chesapeake Bay followed.

===Transfer to the Pacific Fleet===
 
On 4 October, ''Aucilla'' put to sea bound for the Caribbean. She arrived at [[Aruba]] on 9 October and loaded fuel oil until 11 October when she set sail for [[Panama]]. The oiler transited the [[Panama Canal]] on 13 October and, the following day, departed [[Balboa, Panama]], for the [[Hawaiian Islands]]. She stopped over at [[Pearl Harbor]] from 26 to 29 October and then continued her voyage west. The ship anchored in [[Eniwetok]] [[lagoon]] on 5 November. She spent the next two days unloading her cargo of fuel before continuing on to [[Ulithi]] on 7 November. There, she reported for duty to the Commander, Service Squadron ([[ServRon]]) 10.

===Supporting Iwo Jima and Okinawa operations===
 
For the remainder of the war, ''Aucilla'' supported [[U.S. 3rd Fleet]]/[[U.S. 5th Fleet]] operations in the western Pacific Ocean by refueling its units at sea. She provided fuel to the 3rd Fleet during its air attacks on [[Luzon]] in mid-December 1944 and again at the end of the first week in January 1945. When the 3rd Fleet entered the [[South China Sea]] in mid-January, ''Aucilla'' continued her fueling rendezvous with its warships. Between 15 and 26 February, she steamed in an area off [[Iwo Jima]] providing logistics support for the 5th Fleet. She fueled that same fleet from 16 March to 4 May during the invasion of [[Okinawa]]. The oiler rounded out her wartime service supporting the 3rd Fleet on its final series of raids on the [[Empire of Japan|Japanese]] home islands between 11 July and 15 August.

===End-of-war activity===
 
Following the cessation of hostilities, ''Aucilla'' continued steaming with the 3rd Fleet off Japan. After a brief stop at [[Ulithi]], she set sail for Japan on 27 September. The oiler entered [[Tokyo Bay]] on 2 October—one month to the day after Japan formally surrendered. The oiler performed extensive occupation duty at various locations in the [[Far East]] between the end of the war and the summer of 1947.

===Supporting nuclear test ships at Bikini===
That service also included some logistics support work for the ships of Joint [[Task Force]] 1, the task organization engaged in the [[atomic bomb]] tests conducted at [[Bikini Atoll]] during the summer of 1946. The western Pacific cruise in the summer and fall of 1948 ended with ''Aucilla'' steaming through the [[Indian Ocean]], the [[Suez Canal]], and the Mediterranean before she crossed the Atlantic to join the fleet stationed on the eastern seaboard of the United States.

==East Coast operations==
For about four years, the oiler operated along the [[U.S. East Coast]], in the [[Gulf of Mexico]], and in the Caribbean taking on oil at various oil ports and carrying it to the fleet.  She also conducted independent ship's exercises and amphibious exercises both at [[Vieques]] Island near [[Puerto Rico]] and at [[Onslow Beach]] in [[North Carolina]]. At this time she was attached to MSTS.  In 1950 she was deployed to Sasebo Japan to support the Korean War operation. She left Norfolk,Va in October 1950, where she was in for repairs at the Portsmouth Navy yard. Her home port was Mare Island Ca.  She steamed through the Med. down through the Suez Canal,the Red Sea and up into the Persian Gulf to Ras Tanura where she loaded bunker oil. Leaving this port she headed through the Indian Ocean, the Straights of Molacca, around Singapore and headed North for Sasebo where she unloaded her cargo.  Headed south again to Bahrain for another load of oil. Again leaving, headed for Sasebo once again. Arriving Sasebo and unloading she headed for Pearl Harbor. leaving Pearl harbor and returning to Sasebo, Japan. She returned to San Francisco and was detached from MSTS and attached to the fleet as a fleet tanker. Returning to Norfolk via the Panama Canal, completing her round the world voyage and assumed her duties a fleet tanker.  
 
In June 1952, ''Aucilla'' embarked upon the first of a long series of deployments to the Mediterranean. Four months later, she resumed operations along the eastern seaboard and in the [[West Indies]]. The first part of 1953 saw the oiler engaged in another series of training evolutions in the [[Puerto Rico]]-Vieques Island area.

==Midshipman cruise to Rio==
June and July 1953 brought a [[midshipman]] cruise which took her to [[Rio de Janeiro]], Brazil, and [[Barbados]] in the [[British West Indies]]. In September, ''Aucilla'' deployed to the Mediterranean Sea once more. She completed that assignment late in January 1954 and returned to Norfolk on 3 February 1954. Following post-deployment standdown and participation in the annual fleet exercise, [[Operation Springboard]], the oiler resumed fuel services for the [[U.S. 2nd Fleet]] from her base at [[Norfolk, Virginia]]. May brought rough weather fueling tests in the North Atlantic followed by a two-month overhaul at a civilian shipyard in [[Baltimore, Maryland]].

==Caribbean operations==
 
In August, ''Aucilla'' departed Baltimore and steamed down Chesapeake Bay to rejoin the active units of the [[United States Fleet Forces Command|Atlantic Fleet]]. She performed normal logistics services and training operations out of Norfolk until November. Late that month, the oiler put to sea for [[Gonaïves]], Haiti, to provide support for some unspecified tests conducted by the Operational Development Force for the [[Bureau of Ordnance]]. In the course of those operations, the oiler visited [[Guantanamo Bay, Cuba]], and [[Port-au-Prince]], Haiti. When the ship returned to the United States early in December, she entered the [[Bethlehem Shipyard]] at [[Hoboken, New Jersey]], for a three-month modification and repair period. Between mid-April and early May 1955, ''Aucilla'' completed refresher training out of [[Newport, Rhode Island]]. She then returned to Norfolk where she began preparations for an extended tour of duty with the 6th Fleet.

==Service in the Mediterranean Sea==

===Homeported in Barcelona, Spain===
 
On 31 May 1955 the ship stood out of Norfolk en route to her new home port, [[Barcelona]], Spain. She reached her destination on 20 June. For the next 22 months, ''Aucilla'' served with [[Task Force]] (TF) 63 in a logistics support role. She participated in a number of exercises and visited ports all along the shores of the Mediterranean Sea. On 2 April 1957, the oiler headed back to the United States. She spent the entire summer of 1957 engaged in repairs, first a four-month regular overhaul at the [[New York Naval Shipyard]] and then [[boiler]] repairs at Key Highway Shipyard of the Bethlehem Steel Corporation, in [[Baltimore, Maryland]]. Between 16 September and 27 October, ''Aucilla'' completed refresher training—out of Guantanamo Bay—and post-refresher availability.

===Supporting landings in Lebanon===
 
On 28 October 1957, she set sail from Norfolk on her way back to the Mediterranean Sea. Once again, she spent her time ranging the length and breadth of the Mediterranean supporting the operations of TF 63. During the summer of 1958, ''Aucilla'' provided logistics support for the ships, sailors, and marines involved in the landings in [[Lebanon]] earned out in order to help restore order after severe factional fighting. Following that interlude, the oiler resumed normal [[U.S. 6th Fleet]] operations. On 30 May 1959, ''Aucilla'' headed back to the United States for a regular overhaul at the [[Boston Naval Shipyard]]. The overhaul lasted about six months. During that time, the oiler received a new home port assignment, Norfolk. The ship completed overhaul and set sail from Boston on 18 November, bound for refresher training in the Guantanamo Bay operating area. She shaped a course from the [[West Indies]] back to Norfolk on 16 December and arrived at her destination in time to spend the holidays there.

===Continued support of the 6th Fleet===
 
Underway again on 4 January 1960, ''Aucilla'' operated in the vicinity of Norfolk until late in the month. On the 28th, she put to sea bound for the Mediterranean Sea. That seven-month deployment followed the pattern of previous ones, mixing port visits with logistics missions in support of 6th Fleet combat units. The oiler returned to Norfolk on 31 August and, after the usual leave and upkeep period, resumed normal east coast-West Indies operations. That routine lasted into 1961. In February and March 1961, she participated in the annual fleet exercise [[Operation Springboard]]. She returned to Norfolk on 17 March and began preparations for another tour of duty with the 6th Fleet. On 15 May 1961, she stood out of Norfolk and shaped a course for the Mediterranean Sea. ''Aucilla'' served a 14-week deployment that followed patterns established earlier.

==Yard Overhaul at Norfolk==
 
The oiler reentered Norfolk on 11 September 1961 and began post-deployment standdown. Following the leave and upkeep period, she started preparations for overhaul. On 20 November, she entered the yard at the [[Norfolk Shipbuilding &amp; Drydock]] Co. ''Aucilla'' completed her overhaul on 20 February 1962 and then set sail on 1 March for five weeks of refresher training in the [[West Indies]]. Upon completion of refresher training, the oiler joined an underway replenishment group to support the amphibious Exercise &quot;Phiblex 1-62&quot;, also conducted in the West Indies. Later, she returned to United States' waters to participate in Fleet Exercise &quot;Quick Kick.&quot; That summer, she conducted a [[midshipman]] training cruise and took part in convoy exercises off the eastern seaboard.

==European tour of duty==
 
The oiler continued operations out of Norfolk through the end of 1962 and into 1963. On 7 March 1963, Aucilla left Chesapeake Bay on her way back to the Mediterranean. The deployment lasted just under four months. She was back in Norfolk by 1 July. Following post-deployment standdown, the oiler got underway on 6 August to participate in [[NATO]] Exercise &quot;Riptide IV&quot; conducted in the eastern Atlantic. As an adjunct to that mission, she visited [[Bremerhaven, Germany]], and [[Rota, Spain]], before returning to Norfolk on 11 September. For the remainder of 1963, ''Aucilla'' conducted local operations out of her home port.

==Visiting the 1964 New York World's Fair==
 
Similar duty occupied her time during the first two months of 1964. On 3 March 1964, however, the oiler entered the yard at the Norfolk Shipbuilding &amp; Drydock Co. for a regular overhaul. She completed repairs and modifications late in June and put to sea on 29 March for a month of refresher training in the Guantanamo Bay operating area. At the conclusion of refresher training, ''Aucilla'' voyaged north to New York where her crew members visited the [[1964 New York World's Fair|World's Fair]]. The ship returned to Norfolk on 8 August and resumed local operations. That resumption lasted just one month. On 8 September, ''Aucilla'' got underway from Norfolk once more to participate in a series of [[NATO]] exercises in the eastern Atlantic. She visited [[Bremerhaven, Germany]], again at the end of the exercises early in October. She returned to Norfolk on 23 October 1964.

==Reassigned to the 6th Fleet==
 
Upon her return to her home port, she began preparations for another assignment with the 6th Fleet. ''Aucilla'' left Norfolk on 27 November and arrived in [[Rota, Spain]], on 8 December. Another standard 6th Fleet tour of duty ensued with ''Aucilla'' fueling units of the fleet, participating in exercises, and visiting Mediterranean ports. She concluded the deployment with her arrival back in Norfolk on 11 May 1965. From late June to late July, ''Aucilla'' cruised the waters of the [[West Indies]] in support of [[U.S. 2nd Fleet]] units keeping an eye on the latest crisis to trouble the [[Dominican Republic]].

==Supporting Gemini space shots==
She returned to Norfolk on 23 July and resumed local operations out of her home port. Those operations included support roles in the [[Gemini 6]] and [[Gemini 7]] space shots during October, November, and December. ''Aucilla'' reentered Norfolk on 23 December to begin her holiday leave and upkeep period.
 
Further upkeep and a tender availability period occupied her time during January and February 1966. Early in March, the oiler put to sea for another cruise with the 6th Fleet in the Mediterranean. She arrived in [[Cartagena, Spain]], on 15 March and, for the next five months, provided logistics support for United States naval forces in the Mediterranean. ''Aucilla'' departed Rota, Spain, on 12 August and set a course for home. The oiler arrived in Norfolk on the 22d and remained there in a leave and upkeep status until the middle of October.

==Assigned recovery ship for Titan IIIC heat shield==
She put to sea again on 18 October to serve as a recovery ship for an [[U.S. Air Force]] [[Titan III-C]] [[heat shield]] qualification test. She returned to Norfolk from that mission on 21 November and remained in port for the rest of the year.

==Responding to the Six-Day Arab-Israeli War==
 
On 6 February 1967, ''Aucilla'' stood out of Norfolk once again on her way to the Mediterranean. She arrived in Rota, Spain, on the 17th and soon began making the rounds to ports in the &quot;middle sea.&quot; The most notable event of that deployment was the [[Six-Day Arab-Israeli War]] to which units of the 6th Fleet -- ''Aucilla'' included—responded with alacrity. She and her colleagues moved quickly to the eastern Mediterranean early in June, out the rapidity with which the [[Arab]] forces collapsed allowed them to return to a more normal routine at mid-month. Thus, the oiler resumed port visits, exercise, and fueling operations. She completed turnover proceedings at Rota on 19 and 20 August and headed back to the United States on the latter day. ''Aucilla'' arrived back in Norfolk on 30 August. After post-deployment standdown, the oiler entered the yard at the Norfolk Shipbuilding &amp; Drydock Co. for regular overhaul on 13 November.

==South Atlantic operations==
 
''Aucilla'' completed her overhaul by 5 April 1968. On that day, she stood out of Norfolk on her way to refresher training in the West Indies. The oiler completed that mission in May and returned to Norfolk on the 19th. Soon thereafter, she embarked upon a two-month voyage that took her to the [[Cape of Good Hope]] where she refueled the [[Vietnam]]-bound [[aircraft carrier]] {{USS|Intrepid|CVS-11|2}}. In addition, ''Aucilla'' made port calls at [[Rio de Janeiro]] in Brazil, [[Saint Thomas, U.S. Virgin Islands|St. Thomas]] in the [[Virgin Islands]], [[Nassau, Bahamas|Nassau]] in the [[Bahamas]], and at [[Philadelphia, Pennsylvania]], before returning to Norfolk on 10 August.

==Last voyage and disposal==
 
At that time, the oiler began a tender availability as well as a leave and upkeep period preparatory to overseas movement. ''Aucilla'' stood out of Norfolk on 23 September; and, on 3 October she relieved {{USS|Kaskaskia|AO-27|2}} at [[Rota, Spain|Rota]]. After almost five months fueling the ships of the 6th Fleet and making port visits throughout the Mediterranean, ''Aucilla'' departed Rota late in March 1969. She arrived back in Norfolk on 5 April. After the usual post-deployment standdown, the oiler began normal operations out of Norfolk. For the next 14 months, the ship cruised the waters along the eastern seaboard and the West Indies in support of the ships of the Atlantic Fleet. ''Aucilla'' returned to Norfolk from her last voyage early in July 1970.

In the middle of September 1970, she began preparations for inactivation. ''Aucilla'' was placed out of commission at Norfolk on 18 December 1970. On 7 October 1971, she was transferred to the [[Maritime Administration]] for berthing with its [[James River (Virginia)|James River, Virginia]], facility. Her name was struck from the [[Naval Vessel Register|Navy List]] on 1 December 1976. She was subsequently withdrawn from MARAD twice for further stripping, and last returned to MARAD on 21 August 1985. Sold on 27 April 1992, she was scrapped on 25 October 1992.&lt;ref&gt;[https://pmars.marad.dot.gov/detail.asp?Ship=363 PMARS Ship Record Detail - AUCILLA (AO-56)&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Military awards and honors==
 
''Aucilla'' earned five [[battle star]]s for her World War II service.

==References==
:{{DANFS}}
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
* [http://www.navsource.org/archives/09/19/19056.htm NavSource Online: Service Ship Photo Archive - AO-56 Aucilla]

 &lt;!-- non-breaking space to keep AWB drones from altering the space before the navbox--&gt;

{{Cimarron class oiler (1939)}}
{{Type T3-S2-A tankers}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Aucilla (AO-56)}}
[[Category:Cimarron-class oilers (1939)]]
[[Category:Ships built in Sparrows Point, Maryland]]
[[Category:1943 ships]]
[[Category:World War II auxiliary ships of the United States]]
[[Category:World War II tankers of the United States]]
[[Category:Cold War auxiliary ships of the United States]]</text>
      <sha1>bgqqg2tzzxa67c3hrag81dphcbwefqz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
