<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>USS William Ward Burrows (AP-6)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>16038670</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748177975</id>
      <parentid>747342131</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-06T20:31:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Manxruler</username>
        <id>299164</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>catfix</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="45094">{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2012}}

{|{{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
|Ship image=[[Image:USS William Ward Burrows (AP-6).jpg|300px|USS William Ward Burrows 6 July 1942]]
|Ship caption=USS ''William Ward Burrows'' (AP-6) on 6 July 1942. Her 3&quot;/23 guns have been replaced with 3&quot;/50 guns and the sponson in the forward well deck for the 50-foot motor launches has been removed. (''Navy photo collection Photo No. 19-N-32040'')
}}
{{Infobox ship career
|Hide header=
|Ship country=
|Ship flag={{USN flag|1945}}
|Ship name=*''Santa Rita'' (1929)
*''William Ward Burrows'' (1940)
|Ship namesake= [[William Ward Burrows I|William Burrows]]
|Ship owner=
|Ship operator=
|Ship registry=
|Ship route=
|Ship ordered=
|Ship awarded=
|Ship builder=[[Burmeister &amp; Wain]]
|Ship original cost=
|Ship yard number=
|Ship way number=
|Ship laid down= 
|Ship launched=1929
|Ship sponsor=
|Ship christened=
|Ship completed=
|Ship acquired=6 February 1940
|Ship commissioned=15 May 1940
|Ship recommissioned=
|Ship decommissioned=16 May 1946
|Ship maiden voyage= 
|Ship in service=
|Ship out of service=
|Ship renamed=
|Ship reclassified=
|Ship refit=
|Ship struck=15 August 1946
|Ship reinstated=
|Ship homeport=
|Ship identification=
|Ship motto=
|Ship nickname=
|Ship honours=
|Ship honors=Four [[battle stars]] for [[World War II]] service
|Ship captured=
|Ship fate=Sold for scrap, delivered National Metal &amp; Steel 18 May 1957{{sfn|MARAD Vessel Status Card: ''Santa Rita''}} 
|Ship status=
|Ship notes=U.S. O/N: 228577{{sfn|MARAD Vessel Status Card: ''Santa Rita''}}
|Ship badge=
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
|Hide header=
|Header caption=
|Ship class=
|Ship type=
|Ship tonnage={{GRT|4576}}{{sfn|MARAD Vessel Status Card: ''Santa Rita''}}
|Ship displacement={{convert|8450|LT|t}}
|Ship tons burthen=
|Ship length=386 ft 2 in
|Ship beam=53 ft
|Ship height=
|Ship draught=
|Ship draft=9 ft 6 in
|Ship depth=
|Ship hold depth=
|Ship decks=
|Ship deck clearance=
|Ship ramps=
|Ship ice class=
|Ship power=
|Ship propulsion=2 x Diesel, twin propellers{{sfn|MARAD Vessel Status Card: ''Santa Rita''}} 
|Ship sail plan=
|Ship speed=12.5 [[knot (unit)|knots]]
|Ship range=
|Ship endurance=
|Ship test depth=
|Ship boats=
|Ship capacity=
|Ship troops=
|Ship complement=178
|Ship crew=
|Ship time to activate=
|Ship sensors=
|Ship EW=
|Ship armament=*4 × 3&quot; guns
*5 × .50 cal
*4 × .30 cal machine guns
|Ship armour=
|Ship armor=
|Ship aircraft=
|Ship aircraft facilities=
|Ship notes=
}}
|}
'''USS ''William Ward Burrows''''', built as '''MV ''Santa Rita''''' for the [[W. R. Grace and Company|Grace Steamship Company]] launched in 1929 at [[Copenhagen]], Denmark, by [[Burmeister &amp; Wain]], was a transport ship that saw service with the [[United States Navy]] in [[World War II]]. As a Grace liner ''Santa Rita'' served the New York—South American West Coast trade from 1929 until 1939. As ''William Ward Burrows'' the ship served in the Pacific. From October 1940 she assisted in the buildup of Central Pacific bases, being caught in transit from Hawaii to [[Wake Island]] when news of the attack on Pearl Harbor came. She later saw service in the South Pacific and West Pacific. On 29 June 1946 the ship went into reserve at [[Olympia, Washington]] until removed for scrapping 18 May 1957.

==Construction==
''Santa Rita'' was a twin-screw, steel-hulled, passenger and cargo motorship launched in May 1929 at Copenhagen, Denmark, by Burmeister &amp; Wain built for the Grace Steamship Company, Inc., and operated between [[New York City|New York]] and ports in South America and on the [[west coast of the United States]], carrying passengers and freight.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}} The ship was the second Grace Line ship of the name and two more would follow.{{sfn|Swiggum &amp; Kohli, TheShipsList}}

The design was for four passenger decks with accommodations for 80 first and 48 intermediate class passengers in beds rather than berths in all outside rooms. The recreational facilities included a swimming tank, golf practice area along with social hall, smoking room, lounge and verandah cafe. Cargo capacity was 5,100 tons handled by four extra large hatches and nine electric winches. Insulated chambers were provided for carrying of fruit and other perishables.{{sfn|Pacific Marine Review, June 1929|p=27}}

The diesel engines driving the twin screws developed 4,500 horsepower for a service speed of {{convert|14|knots|mph km/h}}.{{sfn|Pacific Marine Review, June 1929|p=27}}

==Commercial service==
''Santa Rita'' followed [[USS Bowditch (AG-30)|''Santa Inez'']] in inaugurating Grace Line's service between New York through the [[Panama Canal]] to [[Buenaventura, Colombia]] and [[Guayaquil, Ecuador]], the first direct passenger service to those ports, with ''Santa Inez'' departing on 20 April and ''Santa Rita'' due to depart 8 June. The planned run between New York and Buenaventura was eight days and Guayaquil twelve days. After those initial ports the ships were to call at South American West Coast ports as far south as [[Valparaiso]].{{sfn|Pacific Marine Review, June 1929|p=27}}

By September, 1932, declining trading conditions along the run from New York to Peru led to the announcement that the ships operating on the run, ''Santa Inez'', ''Santa Olivia'' and ''Santa Rita'', were to be withdrawn and laid up; however, they were put back in service the next year.{{sfn|The Seamen's Journal, September 1932|p=11}}{{sfn|Swiggum &amp; Kohli, TheShipsList}} In 1935 the growth in the fruit trade to the West Coast of South America resulted in fitting five of the line's vessels, including {{convert|55000|cuft|m3|1}} in four compartments for ''Santa Rita'', with [[York International|York Ice Machinery Corporation]] refrigeration plants that included a patented system of air circulation developed by [[United Fruit Company]].{{sfn|Pacific Marine Review, August 1935|p=250A}}

In mid 1939 Grace Line announced it was trading in ''Santa Rita'' and ''Santa Inez'' as part payment to the Maritime Commission for two of its new [[Type C2 ship|C-2 type]] cargo ships.{{sfn|Pacific Marine Review, August 1939|p=46}} The ships were then to be bought by Navy for use as a tender for the Alaska air bases and the other as a survey ship.{{sfn|Pacific Marine Review, August 1939|p=46}}&lt;ref group=note&gt;''Santa Inez'' did become a [[USS Bowditch (AG-30)|survey ship]]. By the time of actual Navy acquisition of ''Santa Rita'' the threat of war in the Pacific had resulted in a major effort to develop bases on the mid-Pacific islands linking Hawaii and the Philippines and, as the threat in the [[Japanese Mandated Islands]] increased, developed into a [[South Pacific air ferry route in World War II|South Pacific air ferry route]]. ''Santa Rita'' became quickly involved in those efforts until war actually came, cutting off the central Pacific routes to the Philippines. The replacement {{SS|Santa Rita|1941|2}} was completed 17 September 1941 and delivered to WSA by Grace 23 March 1942 for operation by Grace under an Army Transportation Corps agreement according to the MARAD Vessel Status Card. The ship was torpedoed and sunk [[List of shipwrecks in July 1942|9 July 1942]] in the Caribbean.&lt;/ref&gt; The ship went into the yard for drydock and general repairs at [[General Engineering &amp; Drydock Company]], [[Oakland]], California for refit and was reported there in January and February, 1940 issues of a monthly trade journal.{{sfn|Pacific Marine Review, February 1940|p=60}}&lt;ref group=note&gt;The January issue of the same reference shows the ship in the yard on page 90. A check of the same journal's December, 1939 issue for the same yard does not show the ship. Considering publication dates the January data was probably ''effective'' in December. The Navy acquired the ship 9 February at Norfolk, Virginia. Thus the probable West Coast yard period was December, 1939—January, 1940.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Navy acquisition==
''Santa Rita'' was purchased by the [[War Shipping Administration]] from Grace Lines for $511,513.11 on 6 February 1940 and simultaneously transferred to the Navy.{{sfn|MARAD Vessel Status Card: ''Santa Rita''}} The ship was commissioned &quot;in ordinary&quot; as transport ''William Ward Burrows'' (AP-6) on 9 February at Pier 5 of the [[Norfolk Navy Yard]], [[Portsmouth, Virginia]]. Converted to a [[troop transport]] at the Norfolk Navy Yard, ''William Ward Burrows'' was placed in full commission on 15 May 1940, Comdr. Ross A. Dierdorff in command.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

==Operational service==

===Pre war===
After fitting-out, ''William Ward Burrows'' sailed from Norfolk on her maiden voyage on 6 July and proceeded to [[Weehawken, New Jersey]], to take on a cargo of structural steel. Departing that port on the 15th, the transport embarked a company of [[US Marines|marines]] as well as a group of women and children - naval dependents - for transportation to [[Guantanamo Bay, Cuba]]. After delivering her passengers, she touched at [[San Juan, Puerto Rico]]; [[Cristóbal, Colón|Cristóbal]], [[Panama Canal Zone|Canal Zone]]; transited the [[Panama Canal]]; visited [[Balboa, Panama|Balboa]], Canal Zone and the [[California]] ports of [[San Diego, California|San Diego]], [[San Pedro, California|San Pedro]], [[Vallejo, California|Vallejo]] (the [[Mare Island Navy Yard]]); and the Naval Air Station at [[Alameda, California|Alameda]], before she proceeded on to her ultimate destination of [[Midway Island]], where she dropped anchor on 2 October.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

''William Ward Burrows'' began, consequently, what would become a series of voyages that formed part of the belated American attempt to fortify her outposts in the [[Pacific]] - islands such as Wake, Midway, and [[Johnston Island|Johnston]]. ''William Ward Burrows'' carried the pioneer construction unit - 80 men and 2,000 tons of equipment - to Wake Island in January 1941, departing [[Honolulu]] the day before Christmas of 1940 and arriving at destination late in the afternoon of 9 January 1941.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

''William Ward Burrows'' would conduct eight more voyages prior to the outbreak of war in the Pacific, carrying construction employees, sailors, and marines, and the miscellaneous cargo necessary to sustain the outposts of the American defense system in the Pacific. On what proved to be her last pre-war voyage to Wake, the transport took westward a cargo of [[dynamite]], as well as employees of civilian contractors and a sprinkling of Navy and Marine Corps personnel. In addition she towed ''Pan American Airways Barge'' No. 4, laden with general cargo. She arrived at Wake on 11 November, disembarked her passengers, discharged her cargo, and delivered her tow before she headed back to [[Hawaii]] on the 13th.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

Soon after arriving, she shifted to Honolulu and embarked 33 marines, 60 sailors, and 55 civilian contractor's employees for transport to Wake on the 28th. She got underway at 0825 on 29 November, towing PAB-7. The ship, herself, carried 1,819 tons of cargo - general supplies, lumber, &quot;reefer boxes&quot; (refrigerators), a boat, 10 trailers, and 20 tons of gasoline in tins.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

Heavy seas and stormy winds prevailed for the entire passage. ''William Ward Burrows'', nevertheless, plowed along at five knots with PAB-7 in tow; she rendezvoused with {{USS|Sonoma|AT-12|3}} on 5 December and took on board an [[appendicitis]] patient from the Hawaii bound tug for medical attention. As the transport continued on toward Wake Island, the weather - as Commander Dierdorff observed - was &quot;uniformly abominable&quot;, but all hands took the rough weather well.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

The ship crossed the [[international date line]] on 6 December and accordingly set her calendars ahead to compensate. Unbeknownst to the solitary transport, a [[Imperial Japanese Navy|Japanese]] carrier task force was proceeding toward [[Pearl Harbor]]. On the morning of 7 December 1941 (8 December on the transport's side of the date line), that task force struck Pearl Harbor a devastating blow and plunged the [[United States]] into a war in both oceans.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

===War===
At 0705 on 8 December, ''William Ward Burrows'' received word of the attack. The crew was called to [[general quarters]], the captain set air and [[submarine]] watches; lookouts were alerted, as were the gun crews. Civilian workmen embarked on board immediately volunteered their services &quot;in any capacity.&quot;{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

The next day, 9 December, ''William Ward Burrows'' received orders to return to Honolulu with her loaded cargo and PAB-7. The war news she received was grim. Pearl Harbor had been attacked and Midway shelled (by the Japanese [[destroyer]]s [[Japanese destroyer Ushio|''Ushio'']] and [[Japanese destroyer Akebono (1930)|''Akebono'']]). False sightings of Japanese task forces here and there proliferated. Comdr. Dierdorff later recalled: &quot;As reports came in, the general impression we gained was that most of the [[Japan|Nippon]]ese fleet was between us and Hawaii.&quot; He was not far from the truth.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

On 13 December, the transport received word to take PAB-7 to [[Johnston Atoll|Johnston Island]]. Accordingly, the ship altered course and on 15 December delivered the [[barge]]—with her cargo load of &quot;general cargo&quot; and [[lumber]]—and embarked passengers for transportation to Hawaii. That day, at 1340, ''William Ward Burrows''' rudder touched a 3-[[fathom]] (5 m)  [[coral head]]—in an area believed to have been dredged to a safe depth of 30 feet (5 fm; 9 m). Fortunately, the transport cleared the navigational hazard with only minor damage to the tip of the [[rudder]].{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

That evening, ''William Ward Burrows'' remained at anchor to the south of Johnston Island in an anchorage deemed safe from submarine attack. Comdr. Dierdorff posted full submarine lookouts, fully manned the [[bridge (nautical)|bridge]], and put the engine room on five minutes' notice to get underway. [[Squall]]y weather prevented his using a 40-foot [[motor launch]] as picket.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

At 1810, Ens. J. A. Peterson, USNR - the officer of the deck - sounded the general alarm; when Comdr. Dierdorff reached the bridge, he saw that enemy ships were shelling Johnston Island from the northward, setting fire to oil storage tanks near the center of the island. One large shell struck 30 yards astern of ''William Ward Burrows'', and another passed over the forecastle. Other splashes erupted from the waters between the ship and the island.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

Fortunately for ''William Ward Burrows'' and her 227 passengers - 132 of them civilians - the enemy did not see her. Knowing that his 3-inch guns were inadequate for a surface gunfire duel with ships of unknown size, Comdr. Dierdorff wisely decided not to open fire. Favored by darkness and rain squalls, ''William Ward Burrows'' got underway at 1830 and escaped to the southward. By that time, the bombardment had ceased. At about 2330, Johnston Island reported no casualties and advised ''William Ward Burrows'' not to return; thus, early the next morning, the transport set course for Honolulu and home.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

''William Ward Burrows'' entered [[drydock]] on New Year's Day 1942 for repairs to her rudder and nine days later emerged and began loading cargo destined for Midway. After embarking a draft of marines for transportation to that key atoll, the transport got underway on 18 January. She arrived five days later and began working her cargo. Two days later, a Japanese submarine boldly surfaced a mere mile away and began shelling the island. However, about three minutes later, fire from Marine Corps guns ashore drove the submarine away.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

The ship soon headed back to Pearl Harbor and arrived there on 3 February. Between early February and mid-March, she made two more round-trip voyages to Midway before she conducted an inter-island trip among the islands of the Hawaiian group carrying general cargo and transporting Army troops to Hilo and Maui. She next voyaged to Midway, carrying general cargo, lumber, provisions, &quot;reefer boxes&quot;, cable reels, and a two-ton truck while transporting naval and Marine Corps personnel. In mid-May, she returned to the west coast of the United States.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

Following an overhaul at the Mare Island Navy Yard, Vallejo, California, ''William Ward Burrows'' loaded to within 90 percent of her capacity, taking on board 1,437 tons of cargo - which included [[ammunition]] and lumber - and departed [[San Francisco]] at 1053 on 23 July. The transport arrived at Pearl Harbor on the 31st and unloaded. After taking on a different cargo, the ship sailed for the New Hebrides at 1849 on 4 August.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

After picking up her escort, destroyer {{USS|Flusser|DD-368|3}}, later that day, ''William Ward Burrows'' made [[Fila Harbor]], [[Efate Island]], on 17 August. Underway again from Efate on 26 August, this time escorted by destroyer [[seaplane tender]] {{USS|McFarland|AVD-14|3}}, ''William Ward Burrows'' headed for the [[Solomon Islands|Solomons]]. Destroyer [[minelayer]]s {{USS|Tracy|DM-19|2}} and {{USS|Gamble|DM-15|2}}, and high speed transports {{USS|Colhoun|APD-2|3}}, {{USS|Gregory|APD-3|3}} and {{USS|Little|APD-4|3}}, as well as [[Kapara|SS ''Kapara'']] joined them the next day.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

While passing through [[Indispensable Strait]] on the 29th, the ships received word from &quot;Cactus&quot; - the codename for [[Honiara International Airport|Henderson Field]], [[Guadalcanal]] - at 1105 that an enemy air raid was imminent. While the APD's and DM's deployed to provide an [[antiaircraft]] screen around ''William Ward Burrows'' and ''Kapara'', the transport prepared for action. At 1205 - exactly an hour after the alert was broadcast from &quot;Cactus&quot; - a formation of Japanese planes droned overhead at 25,000 feet. Two minutes later, ''William Ward Burrows'' opened fire with her 3-inch battery and expended 50 rounds. Seven minutes later, lookouts observed two enemy [[bomber]]s falling in flames, due to the fire from the task group. The surviving enemy aircraft soon fled, having caused no damage.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

Shortly thereafter, ''William Ward Burrows'' proceeded to [[Lunga Roads]], off [[Kukum Point]], Guadalcanal, and dropped [[anchor]]. She got underway for [[Tulagi Harbor]] that afternoon but ran hard aground on the southeast end of [[Sylvia Reef]] at 1750, only five minutes after entering the harbor channel. In an effort to get out of the predicament, ''William Ward Burrows'' rang down full speed astern at 1752 and attempted to use her stern anchor as a [[kedge]]; but the ship refused to budge. ''Little'' passed a towline to the transport at 1904, but darkness intervened and kept ''William Ward Burrows'' aground for the night.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

The next day, the transport passed a line to ''Tracy''. The minecraft began pulling, backing with ''William Ward Burrows''' engines running full [[astern]], but the towline parted. Meanwhile, the transport's crew had begun unloading equipment into lighters, in an effort to lighten the ship. At 1458, lookouts spotted 18 Japanese bombers - [[Mitsubishi G4M]] &quot;Betties&quot; - at 22,000 feet. Helplessly aground, ''William Ward Burrows'' was in a bad situation; but, fortunately for her, the Japanese had business elsewhere. They attacked ''Colhoun'' at 1512 - after she had unloaded 17 tons of stores consigned to the Marine Corps garrison on Guadalcanal - and, in two minutes, succeeded in scoring four direct hits. The luckless fast transport sank by the stern at about 1515.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

At 2035, 20 wounded men from ''Colhoun'' were brought on board the transport for medical attention. Reflecting later upon the incident, ''William Ward Burrows''' commanding officer, Lt. Comdr. E. I. McQuiston, concluded that, had she not run aground, his ship, too, would have been at Kukum Point and probably would have been the object of the Japanese attack. In that light, perhaps the grounding had been a blessing for the transport.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

On the morning of the 31st, ''William Ward Burrows'' once more ran up her engines at full speed astern in another attempt to free the ship. At 1100, she went to general quarters when she received word of approaching Japanese planes - unable to maneuver and hard aground, the ship was still in a vulnerable position. Again, however, good fortune was with the ship, for the air raid never materialized.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

Finally, on 2 September, with the aid of patrol craft YP-346 (on the port quarter), YP-239 (on the starboard), and ''Gamble'', ''William Ward Burrows'' at last floated free. She remained anchored off Sylvia Reef to take stock of the damage and found it light. ''Gamble'', however, soon reported a submarine in the immediate vicinity, and the transport got underway to seek safety in the inner harbor at [[Tulagi]]. Unfortunately, the ship developed too much way to clear a patch of shoals, and she again grounded - this time on [[Southern Cross Reef]].{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

Again, ''William Ward Burrows'' backed engines, but to no avail. Higgins boats pulling on the port quarter and pushing on the starboard side failed to budge her. Fortunately, that time aground was shorter than the first. On the afternoon of 3 September, aided by the trusty ''Gamble'' and YP-239, ''William Ward Burrows'' pulled free.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

After being refloated from Southern Cross Reef, the transport again got underway for Kukum Point to discharge part of her cargo. She then proceeded back to Tulagi to unload the remainder. Upon completing that task, she again headed for Kukum Point at 0545 on the 5th; she hove to at 0756 finding all available boats engaged in picking up the survivors from ''Little'' and ''Gregory'', APD's that had tangled with a detachment of the &quot;[[Tokyo Express]]&quot; and been sunk by the gunfire of Japanese destroyers [[Japanese destroyer Yudachi|Yudachi]], [[Japanese destroyer Hatsuyuki|Hatsuyuki]], and [[Japanese destroyer Murakumo|Murakumo]] on the night of 4 and 5 September. As those boats passed his ship, Comdr. McQuiston invited them to come alongside and transfer the wounded to the transport. ''William Ward Burrows'' picked up 27 that morning and an additional 214 later, all for passage to [[Espiritu Santo]]. Her task completed at Guadalcanal, ''William Ward Burrows'', escorted by ''Gamble'', got underway at 1858.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

At 0715 on 8 September, the transport dropped anchor at [[Segond Channel]], Espiritu Santo, and later refueled from [[Oiler (ship)|oiler]] {{USS|Sabine|AO-25|3}}. After disembarking the APD survivors and discharging more of her cargo, ''William Ward Burrows'' took on passengers and light freight and pushed on independently for [[New Caledonia]] on the 12th. Reaching [[Noumea]] on the 14th, she continued her voyage through the Pacific war zone to [[Suva]], in the [[Fiji|Fiji Islands]], in company with US Army Transport ''Ernest R. Hinds'' and escorted by destroyer {{USS|Buchanan|DD-484|3}}. There, she brought on board more cargo and mail for delivery to Pearl Harbor.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

Again sailing in company with ''Ernest R. Hinds'' and escorted by [[light cruiser]] {{USS|Raleigh|CL-7|3}}, ''William Ward Burrows'' made port at Pearl Harbor on 28 September. She remained at that point until 4 October loading cargo at both the [[Hickam Field]] dock and at the Navy Yard. She sailed for the Fiji Islands at 1400 that day, in company with seaplane tender {{USS|Tangier|AV-8|3}} and escorted by destroyer {{USS|Woodworth|DD-460|3}}. Upon arrival at Suva on the 15th, the transport worked her cargo and, on the 18th, pushed on for Espiritu Santo where she arrived three days later.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

Underway for New Caledona on the 27th, ''William Ward Burrows'' arrived at Nouméa the following day and unloaded her passengers and mail. She tarried there until 14 November, when she pushed on for [[Samoa]]. Upon arrival, she discharged passengers and mail, picked up other passengers; and then proceeded back to the [[Hawaiian Islands]], arriving at Pearl Harbor on 27 November.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

The transport made one round-trip voyage to Midway and back before she shifted to the west coast of the United States for her second &quot;stateside&quot; visit since the war began. Arriving at San Francisco, California, on 2 February 1943, she spent the next few weeks exchanging cargoes and embarking passengers. She sailed for the Hawaiian Islands on 21 February, in company with transport {{USS|Henderson|AP-1|3}} and escorted by destroyers {{USS|Bulmer|DD-222|3}} and {{USS|Parrott|DD-218|3}}.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

The convoy, designated Task Group 15.6, ran into heavy weather on 25 February and for four days fought through mountainous seas. ''William Ward Burrows'' occasionally shipped water over both bow and stern and rolled very heavily in the rough seas and heavy swells, but arrived safely at Pearl Harbor on 2 March.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

The ship devoted most of 1943 to making inter-island transport runs, traveling among the islands of the [[Central Pacific Area|Central Pacific]], especially those of the Hawaiian chain. The most dramatic incident during this period of her service occurred on 6 November as she was approaching Midway toward the end of a run from Pearl Harbor. The ship's steering gear failed, and she was forced to lie to off the channel entrance until repairs could be made. Meanwhile, [[sub chaser]] [[USS PC-598|PC-598]] stood out of Midway to help protect the transport and joined PC-586 at 1418. At 2034, PC-598 reported picking up a submarine contact. A minute later, the transport went to general quarters. At 2040, PC-598 fired a floating flare to illuminate the area, and she commenced dropping depth charges a minute later. ''William Ward Burrows'' - underway off the coast, with PC-586 patrolling ahead - later lost contact with PC-598 as that vessel went off to the hunt.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

The next morning, with the danger passed and the steering casualty repaired, the transport entered the lagoon and began discharging her cargo. The ship remained at Midway from 8 to 10 November and soon set sail for Pearl Harbor, with PC-586 again as ocean escort. She made one more inter-island cargo-carrying voyage before she began her third run to the South Pacific.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

Three days before Christmas 1943, ''William Ward Burrows'', escorted by PC-549 and PC-596, departed Pearl Harbor with a cargo of ammunition. She traveled via [[Palmyra]] and [[American Samoa]] - transferring mail to PC-596 on 30 December to deliver it to the port of [[Tutuila]]. The transport ultimately arrived at [[Havannah Harbor]], Efate, at 0847 on 5 January 1944 and moored alongside the [[battleship]] {{USS|Alabama|BB-60}}. After working cargo on board the battleship between 6 and 11 January, she proceeded to Espiritu Santo, where she discharged cargo between the 13th and 15th.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

Proceeding thence to [[Funafuti]], in the [[Ellice Islands]], the ship remained at that port for two days before she set her course toward Pearl Harbor and arrived there on 28 January. After repairs, the transport made two more voyages to Midway Island - completing the second on 29 April - before she became the flagship of Service Squadron (ServRon) 12.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

ServRon 12 - dubbed &quot;the harbor stretchers&quot; - was a harbor development and salvage unit whose job was to clear harbors in the forward areas, making it possible to berth ships and bring supplies to the front-line areas at the earliest possible moment. Commanded by Capt. (later Commodore) [[Leon S. Fiske]], ServRon 12 would play a part in the stepping-stone advance that eventually carried American forces to the Japanese home islands themselves.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

Underway on 16 May - in company with store ship {{USS|Boreas|AF-8|3}}, unclassified vessel {{USS|Fortune|IX-146|3}}, and [[Minesweeper (ship)|minesweeper]]s {{USS|Triumph|AM-323|3}}, and {{USS|Vigilance|AM-324|3}} -  ''William Ward Burrows'' dropped anchor at [[Majuro]] lagoon in the [[Marshall Islands|Marshalls]], on the 25th. Two days later, she shifted to [[Kwajalein]], where she served into mid-July.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

The flagship of ServRon 12 departed Kwajalein on 15 July, bound for [[Eniwetok]] in company with the survey ship {{USS|Bowditch|AG-30|2}}, the former ''Santa Inez'' that had been her running-mate and sister ship, escorted by destroyer {{USS|Bancroft|DD-598|3}}, for the [[Mariana Islands|Marianas]].{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

On the 21st, lookouts in the ship sighted starshell and heard the sound of heavy gunfire from [[Saipan]] - probably the mopping-up operations by the American forces ashore, since organized Japanese resistance on Saipan had ceased on the 9th. ''William Ward Burrows'' passed near [[Tinian]] on the 22d, observing from close-hand the preparatory bombardments paving the way for the landing of Major General [[Harry Schmidt (USMC)|Harry Schmidt]]'s marines that would follow two days later. Late on the 23d, ''William Ward Burrows'' dropped anchor in [[Tanapag Harbor]], Saipan, where she became a base of operations for the harbor development unit and immediately began salvage and harbor development operations, providing water and stores to the various ships assigned to ServRon 12 as well as small craft from other units.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

Her stay at Saipan was not without incident. On 30 July, shortly after midnight, a tremendous explosion rocked the area; the concussion from the blast blew in the plywood light shields at the ''William Ward Burrows''' hatches facing the island. Japanese infiltrators had detonated a cache of 84 tons of dynamite. Boats from the ship put out to investigate, but could only ascertain that damage to the dump had been done and the guards had disappeared, probably killed in the blast.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

The following morning, ''William Ward Burrows'' disembarked a detachment of four officers and 180 enlisted men of [[Naval Construction Battalion]] (NCB) (&quot;Seabees&quot;) 301 to continue harbor development work at Saipan and stood out of Tanapag Harbor, bound for newly conquered [[Guam]] in company with cargo ship {{USS|Vega|AK-17|3}}, landing craft repair ship {{USS|Agenor|ARL-3|3}}, [[LST-431]], and escorted by the destroyer {{USS|Stockham|DD-683|3}} and [[destroyer escort]] {{USS|Tisdale|DE-33|3}}. After a one-day passage, ''William Ward Burrows'' dropped anchor at [[Apra Harbor]] and began unloading [[Marine salvage|salvage]] equipment. Soon, various barges and other salvage craft were operating from alongside the transport which supplied them with water and stores as they worked on local harbor development tasks.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

Commodore [[William M. Quigley]], the new Deputy Commander, Forward Area, and his staff reported aboard on 18 August. The ship's force immediately began constructing a wooden addition to the communication office on the [[promenade deck]], port side. In addition, a voice radio and operations office was built on the port side of the gun deck. These alterations were made to help the ship fill her new role as the ship in which the Senior Officer Present, Afloat, (SOPA) was embarked.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

''William Ward Burrows'' soon resumed her work as base ship for harbor operations at Apra Harbor. She again supplied various ships and small craft with stores and water, until she detected a leak in one of her fresh water tanks. After patient searching, the ship's force found the affected area and soon repaired it. Shortly thereafter, Commodore Quigley and his staff disembarked and set up shop in the internal combustion engine repair ship {{USS|Luzon|ARG-2}}.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

''William Ward Burrows'' next embarked [[seabees]] and their equipment and took on board a cargo of dynamite that partially filled one of her holds. She continued the loading evolution until 2 October when she got underway in company with her escort, minesweeper {{USS|Caravan|AM-157|3}}. Soon after they cleared the harbor, the barometer began dropping steadily - a sign of an impending [[typhoon]].{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

The storm developed throughout the night and struck with full force the next morning. ''William Ward Burrows'' plunged through the tempest, &quot;like a sailboat between two mountains of water&quot;, as the ships' historian later recounted. During the morning, hands in the transport estimated that the wind velocity was at least 85 knots. Fortunately, ''William Ward Burrows'' suffered little damage - one life raft lost over the side - and she and ''Caravan'' continued their voyage. On 4 October, they joined survey ship {{USS|Hydrographer|AGS-2}}, [[floating dry dock]] [[ARD-16]], and fleet ocean [[tug]] {{USS|Pakana|ATF-108|3}}.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

Altering course toward Ulithi Atoll, ''William Ward Burrows'' effected the necessary minor repairs to the storm damage suffered in the typhoon before she again got underway on 9 October, bound for her original destination, the [[Palau]]s. She hove to off [[Peleliu]] and unloaded her cargo into amphibious trucks ([[DUKW]]'s) and her dynamite cargo into an [[Landing Craft, Tank|LCT]].{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

Five days after her arrival, ''William Ward Burrows'' shifted to a position between the islands of [[Bairakaseru]] and [[Garakayo]], where she lay to, while a survey boat from [[NCB-301]] took soundings of a nearby inlet in preparation for anchoring [[ARD-16]]. The transport eventually moved to a spot between [[Angaur]] and Peleliu and hove to for the night. During her stay in the Palaus, several air alerts occurred, giving all hands some anxious hours; but the transport never sighted any enemy aircraft and continued her support duties, transferring navigational gear and [[buoy]]s to [[US Coast Guard|Coast Guard]] seagoing buoy tender {{USCGC|Papaw|WLB-308}}.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

Departing Peleliu on 23 October, ''William Ward Burrows'' headed back to the Marianas to resume her flagship duties for ServRon 12. En route, ''Caravan'' - again her ocean escort  - made a contact on what she believed was an enemy submarine and made one attack. However, she lost the contact and eventually rejoined her charge and shepherded the transport safely back to Guam.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

''William Ward Burrows'' operated at Guam into the spring of 1945. Getting underway for the Ryukyus on 30 May, in the wake of the [[invasion of Okinawa]], ''William Ward Burrows''  - escorted by minesweeper {{USS|Sustain|AM-119}} -  reached that island on 3 June and entered [[Buckner Bay]]. As she steamed to her assigned anchorage, the transport came under attack from a solitary &quot;Jill&quot; that roared down out of the clouds. Immediately, the ships in the anchorage blanketed the sky with antiaircraft fire and sent the &quot;Jill&quot; crashing about 1,000 yards from ''Burrows''' anchorage. This proved to be only the first of almost continuous air raid &quot;flash&quot; alerts that would characterize the ship's sojourn in Okinawan waters. Five days later, she observed a [[kamikaze]] crash the destroyer minelayer {{USS|J. William Ditter|DM-31|3}}, four miles away.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

At 1908 on 11 June, the transport - at general quarters and &quot;on the lookout for low-flying bogies&quot; - sighted a &quot;Jill&quot; or &quot;Sonia&quot; off her port side at 1,500 feet. The transport and all of the other ships in the area immediately opened fire, &quot;engulfing the plane and vicinity with [[Tracer ammunition|tracer]] fire and shell bursts.&quot; The plane roared past ''William Ward Burrows'', ''Bowditch'', an [[LSD]], and a [[Liberty ship]], making a banking turn over the nearby [[Katsuren Hanto]] peninsula, and crashed at 1911, about 700 yards astern of ''Burrows''.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

The following day, the transport moved to the [[Yonabaru]] anchorage and began unloading equipment for the Seabee unit that had begun to establish camps on the beach. Air alerts continued almost ceaselessly, day or night, but unloading operations proceeded regardless.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

After that period of work offshore, ''William Ward Burrows'' got underway and proceeded to [[Chimu Wan]], an anchorage on the northward side of Buckner Bay, and dropped anchor there on 2 July. However, twice after the ship reached that body of water, typhoons nearby forced her to get underway to seek maneuvering room in the open sea. On 19 July, for example, she sortied with LST group 35 - 16 [[Landing Ship, Tank|LST]]'s and two [[Landing Craft Mechanized|LCM]]'s - and remained at sea until the morning of the 21st. Air alerts, too, continued to make life hectic almost until the end, but Japan - worn down by ceaseless Allied pressure, particularly from American seapower  - indicated a willingness to surrender and accepted the terms of the [[Potsdam Declaration]] on 15 August.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

===War's end and deactivation===
But for ''William Ward Burrows'', however, the cessation of hostilities did not mean an end to the ship's work. The veteran transport participated in the occupation of the erstwhile enemy's homeland, continuing her vital support role between 2 September 1945 and 26 January 1946. During that time, she successfully weathered another major typhoon in September 1945 without suffering major damage.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

Her task completed in the [[Far East]], ''William Ward Burrows'' sailed for the United States in the spring of 1946. She reported to Commandant, 13th Naval District, for disposition on 17 March 1946 and was decommissioned on 16 May of the same year. Struck from the [[Naval Vessel Register|Navy list]] on 15 August 1946.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

''William Ward Burrows'' received four [[battle star]]s for her World War II service.{{sfn|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}

==Lay up and disposal==
On 29 June 1946 the ship, declared surplus, was delivered at Olympia, Washington to the War Shipping Administration and simultaneously delivered to the [[Maritime Commission]] reserve fleet for lay up.{{sfn|MARAD Vessel Status Card: ''Santa Rita''}} On 30 April 1957, after first bids were rejected as too low, the ship was sold to National Metal &amp; Steel Corporation for $111,887.87 and withdrawn from the reserve fleet by the purchaser 18 May 1957 for scrapping.{{sfn|MARAD Vessel Status Card: ''Santa Rita''}}

== Footnotes ==
{{reflist|group=note}}

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==Bibliography==
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite web |url=http://www.marad.dot.gov/sh/ShipHistory/Detail/12051 |title=''Santa Rita'' |author=Maritime Administration |date= |work=Ship History Database Vessel Status Card |publisher= U.S. Department of Transportation, Maritime Administration |accessdate=20 April 2015 |ref={{sfnref|MARAD Vessel Status Card: ''Santa Rita''}}}}
*{{cite web |url=http://www.history.navy.mil/research/histories/ship-histories/danfs/w/william-ward-burrows.html |title=''William Ward Burrows'' |author=Naval History And Heritage Command |date= |work=Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships |publisher=Naval History And Heritage Command |accessdate=20 April 2015 |ref={{sfnref|Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''William Ward Burrows''}}}}
*{{cite journal |last=Pacific American Steamship Association; Shipowners Association of the Pacific Coast |year=1929 |title=New Grace Liners for South American Service |journal=Pacific Marine Review |volume=26 |issue=June |page= |location=San Francisco |publisher=J.S. Hines |doi= |url=https://archive.org/stream/pacificmarinerev2629paci#page/n411/mode/1up |accessdate=20 April 2015 |ref={{sfnref|Pacific Marine Review, June 1929}}}}
*{{cite journal |last=Allen |first=William |year=1935 |title=Grace Installs Refrigeration for South American Fruits |journal=Pacific Marine Review |volume=32 |issue=August |page= |location=San Francisco |publisher=J.S. Hines |doi= |url=https://archive.org/stream/pacificmarinerev3235paci#page/n333/mode/1up |accessdate=21 April 2015 |ref={{sfnref|Pacific Marine Review, August 1935}}}}
*{{cite journal |last=Pacific American Steamship Association; Shipowners Association of the Pacific Coast |year=1939 |title=Trade-in Ships Bought by Navy |journal=Pacific Marine Review |volume=36 |issue=August |page= |location=San Francisco |publisher=J.S. Hines |doi= |url=https://archive.org/stream/pacificmarinerev3639paci#page/n421/mode/1up |accessdate=21 April 2015 |ref={{sfnref|Pacific Marine Review, August 1939}}}}
*{{cite journal |last=Pacific American Steamship Association; Shipowners Association of the Pacific Coast |year=1940 |title=Building in American Yards: General Engineering &amp; Drydock Company |journal=Pacific Marine Review |volume=37 |issue=February |page= |location=San Francisco |publisher=J.S. Hines |doi= |url=https://archive.org/stream/pacificmarinerev3740paci#page/n121/mode/1up |accessdate=21 April 2015 |ref={{sfnref|Pacific Marine Review, February 1940}}}}
*{{cite journal |year=1932 |title=Shipping News |journal=The Seamen's Journal |volume=46 |issue=September |page= |location=San Francisco |publisher=International Seamen's Union of America |doi= |url=https://archive.org/stream/seamensjour4446unse#page/n1160/mode/1up |accessdate=20 April 2015 |ref={{sfnref|The Seamen's Journal, September 1932}}}}
*{{cite web |url=http://www.theshipslist.com/ships/lines/grace.shtml |title=Grace Line (W. R. Grace &amp; Co.), New York 1882-1969 |last1=Swiggum |first1=S. |last2=Kohli |first2=M. |date=March 26, 2010  |work=TheShipsList |publisher= |accessdate=20 April 2015 |ref={{sfnref|Swiggum &amp; Kohli, TheShipsList}}}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
* [http://www.navsource.org/archives/09/22/22006.htm AP-6 ''William Ward Burrows], Navsource Online.

{{Unique United States Navy transports}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:William Ward Burrows AP-6}}
[[Category:1929 ships]]
[[Category:Ships built in Copenhagen]]
[[Category:Merchant ships of the United States]]
[[Category:World War II auxiliary ships of the United States]]</text>
      <sha1>6p41tae524pncnu8cocwwi87q7u36gg</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
