<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>USS Tills (DE-748)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>12124633</id>
    <revision>
      <id>743546690</id>
      <parentid>715535974</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-10T04:12:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cydebot</username>
        <id>1215485</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Robot - Moving category Ships built in Los Angeles, California‎ to [[:Category:Ships built in Los Angeles]] per [[WP:CFD|CFD]] at [[Wikipedia:Categories for discussion/Log/2016 September 6]].</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16752">{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2012}}
{|{{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
|Ship image=[[Image:USS Tills (DE-748).jpg|300px|Tills (DE-748) underway in the Pacific during World War II]]
|Ship caption=''Tills'' underway in the Pacific during World War II
}}
{{Infobox ship career
|Hide header=
|Ship country=United States
|Ship flag={{USN flag|1968}}
|Ship name=USS ''Tills''
|Ship namesake=Ensign [[Robert Tills]]
|Ship ordered=
|Ship awarded=
|Ship builder=[[Western Pipe and Steel Company]]
|Ship original cost=
|Ship yard number=
|Ship way number=
|Ship laid down=23 June 1943
|Ship launched=3 October 1943
|Ship sponsor=Helen Irene Tills, sister of Robert Tills
|Ship christened=
|Ship completed=
|Ship acquired=
|Ship commissioned=8 August 1944
|Ship decommissioned=June 1946
}}
{{Infobox ship career
|Hide header=yes
|Ship recommissioned=21 November 1950
|Ship decommissioned=18 October 1959
}}
{{Infobox ship career
|Hide header=yes
|Ship recommissioned=1 October 1961
|Ship decommissioned=23 September 1968
|Ship in service=
|Ship out of service=
|Ship renamed=
|Ship reclassified=
|Ship refit=
|Ship struck=23 September 1968
|Ship reinstated=
|Ship homeport=[[Portland, Maine|Portland]], [[Maine]]
|Ship identification=
|Ship motto=
|Ship nickname=
|Ship honors=
|Ship captured=
|Ship fate=Sunk as target off [[Virginia]], 3 April 1969
|Ship status=
|Ship notes=
|Ship badge=
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
|Hide header=
|Header caption=
|Ship class= {{sclass|Cannon|destroyer escort}}
|Ship displacement=*{{convert|1240|LT|t|0|abbr=on}} standard
*{{convert|1620|LT|t|0|abbr=on}} full
|Ship length=*{{convert|306|ft|m|abbr=on}} [[Length overall|o/a]]
*{{convert|300|ft|m|abbr=on}} [[Length at the waterline|w/l]]
|Ship beam= {{convert|36|ft|10|in|m|abbr=on}}
|Ship draft= {{convert|11|ft|8|in|m|abbr=on}}
|Ship depth=
|Ship hold depth=
|Ship propulsion=4 × GM Mod. 16-278A [[diesel engine]]s with electric drive, {{convert|6000|shp|0|abbr=on}}, 2 [[Propeller#Marine|screws]]
|Ship speed= {{convert|21|kn|lk=in}}
|Ship range= {{convert|10800|nmi|km|abbr=on}} at {{convert|12|kn|abbr=on}}
|Ship complement=15 officers and 201 enlisted
|Ship armament=*3 × single Mk.22 [[3&quot;/50 caliber gun]]s
*1 × twin [[Bofors 40 mm|40 mm Mk.1 AA gun]]
*8 × [[Oerlikon 20 mm cannon|20 mm Mk.4 AA guns]]
*3 × {{convert|21|in|mm|0|abbr=on}} [[torpedo tube]]s
*1 × [[Hedgehog (weapon)|Hedgehog]] Mk.10 [[anti-submarine mortar]] (144 rounds)
*8 × Mk.6 [[depth charge]] projectors
*2 × Mk.9 depth charge tracks
|Ship armor=
|Ship notes=
}}
|}
'''USS ''Tills'' (DE-748)''' was a {{sclass|Cannon|destroyer escort}} built for the [[United States Navy]] during [[World War II]].  She served in the [[Pacific Ocean]] and provided escort service against [[submarine]] and air attack for Navy vessels and [[convoy]]s.  After the war, she was converted into a training vessel.

She was named in honor of [[Robert George Tills]] who was the first American naval officer killed in the defense of the [[Philippines]]. The ship was laid down on 23 June 1943 at [[San Pedro, California]], by the [[Western Pipe and Steel Company]]; launched on 3 October 1943; sponsored by Miss Helen Irene Tills, the sister of the late Ensign Tills; and commissioned on 8 August 1944, Lt. Comdr. James L. Brooks, [[USNR]], in command.

== World War II Pacific Theatre operations==

''Tills'' was assigned to Escort Division ([[CortDiv]]) 53 and conducted trials and [[Shakedown (testing)|shakedown]] off [[San Diego, California]], before post-shakedown availability at [[Terminal Island]]. On 16 October, the ship departed the west coast in the screen for [[task force|Task Group]] (TG) 19.5, which included [[escort carriers]] {{USS|Makin Island|CVE-93|3}}, {{USS|Lunga Point|CVE-94|3}}, {{USS|Salamaua|CVE-96|3}}, and {{USS|Bismarck Sea|CVE-95|3}}. She reached [[Pearl Harbor]] on the 23rd and took part in [[anti-submarine]] operations in [[Hawaii]]an waters for the remainder of 1944.

On 2 January 1945, ''Tills'' departed Pearl Harbor for exercises with TG 12.3, before the [[Hunter-killer armored-vehicle team|hunter-killer]] group headed for the [[Marshall Islands|Marshalls]]. Arriving at [[Eniwetok]] on 15 January, the destroyer escort remained there a [[fortnight]] before beginning exercises on the 29th.

''Tills'' weighed anchor on 5 February for a hunter-killer mission. In this, like the other operations staged from the Marshalls, the ship sailed easterly by day and westerly by night to a distance some {{convert|400|mi|km}} east of Eniwetok. Her patrolling of this stretch of the Pacific between the [[Hawaiian Islands]] and the Marshalls continued for 10 days before ''Tills'' returned to Pearl Harbor for availability alongside tender {{USS|Alcor|AD-34|3}}.

The ship conducted post-availability exercises off [[Oahu]] before screening for {{USS|Sangamon|CVE-26|3}} in late February, while the escort carrier's planes carried out night flight training operations. Returning to Pearl Harbor on 2 March, the ship two days later joined TG 19.3, formed around {{USS|Kasaan Bay|CVE-69|3}}. Two five-day training cruises followed, before ''Tills'' was briefly reassigned to TG 19.2, whose nucleus was {{USS|Tripoli|CVE-64|3}}.

After routine training and availability at Pearl Harbor, the destroyer escort embarked 2 Navy officers and 23 Navy and Marine enlisted men for transportation to the Marshalls. On 29 March, she rendezvoused with destroyer escorts {{USS|Gilligan|DE-508|3}} and {{USS|Whitman|DE-24|3}} which helped her to screen a 17-ship convoy, PD-355T, to Eniwetok. After making port on 6 April, ''Tills'' rejoined TG 12.3, which conducted hunter-killer operations between the Hawaiian Islands and the Marshalls.

== Battered by a typhoon ==

Following her 14 April return to Eniwetok, the escort ship remained with TG 12.3, steaming on anti-submarine patrols east of the Marshalls. On 20 April, a [[typhoon]] upset the group's routine by grounding Corregidor's aircraft and pitching the small destroyer escorts in the heavy seas and {{convert|70|kn|km/h|sing=on}} winds. The storm finally abated three days later, and the battered task group returned to Eniwetok.

Designated Task Unit (TU) 96.6.7, ''Tills'' departed the Marshalls on 30 April and arrived at [[Ulithi]] on 3 May. Two days later, the destroyer escort rendezvoused with UOK-9 and screened that convoy to the [[Ryukyu Islands|Ryūkyūs]]. En route to [[Okinawa]], ''Tills'' sighted an abandoned Japanese patrol boat and sank the vessel with gunfire and [[depth charges]].

Dropping anchor off [[Hagushi]] Beach on 10 May, the destroyer escort got underway soon thereafter and relieved {{USS|Starling|AM-64|3}} on screening duty in the transport area. On the 12th, ''Tills'' went to [[general quarters]] upon learning that enemy aircraft had been sighted. Spotting two planes emerging from a smoke screen, her gunners opened fire with the 40-millimeter battery before a sharp-eyed lookout noted that the planes were &quot;friendly&quot;. The [[Bofors gun]]s ceased firing immediately, and the aircraft flew away undamaged.

== Escorting small carriers ==

Following her duties with the transport screen off Okinawa, ''Tills'' was assigned to the screen of Carrier Division 22 which contained escort carriers {{USS|Santee|CVE-29|3}}, {{USS|Chenango|CVE-28|3}}, and {{USS|Block Island|CVE-106|3}}. As these small carriers steamed toward [[Sakishima]], their planes loaded bombs and prepared to launch. Their target, Sakishima, had been serving as a refueling base for Japanese aircraft shuttling between [[Kyūshū]] and [[Taiwan|Formosa]] and was thus an important link in the chain of airbases which supplied Japan's dreaded [[kamikaze]] offensive with its deadly aircraft. ''Tills'' served as antisubmarine screen and plane guard for these strikes which commenced on 1 June. The group returned to [[Kerama Retto]] to rearm and refuel before proceeding northward on 20 June for further strikes.

Four days later, the destroyer escort returned to hunter-killer operations and maintained antisubmarine patrols on a continuous basis until making port at Ulithi for availability alongside repair ship {{USS|Oahu|ARG-5|3}}. For the remainder of July and into August, ''Tills'' continued antisubmarine operations on the sea lanes converging in the Western [[Caroline Islands|Caroline]] basin.

== End of war with Japan ==

As the war progressed to its conclusion in the Pacific, ''Tills'' commenced a needed availability at [[Guam]]. While in [[Apra Harbor]], the destroyer escort received word that an [[atomic bomb]] had been dropped on [[Hiroshima, Japan]], on 6 August. As ''Tills'' entered dry-dock ABSD-6 three days later for repairs to her [[sonar]] dome, a second atomic blast hit [[Nagasaki, Nagasaki|Nagasaki]]. While the destroyer escort was docked, in company with {{USS|Torrance|AKA-76|3}}, {{USS|Roberts|DE-749|3}}, and {{SS|A. McKensie}}, airwaves brought the welcome news that Japan had surrendered on 15 August. The long Pacific war was over.

After remaining at Apra Harbor until 29 August, the destroyer escort headed for [[Saipan]] which she reached later that day. She remained there for almost a month. On 24 September, she was assigned to duty with Transport Squadron 12 at [[Buckner Bay]], Okinawa.

Following her arrival at Nagasaki with transports bringing American occupation forces, ''Tills'' made two round trips between Nagasaki and [[Manila]] before making port at Saipan on 21 October, ending the initial leg of her homeward-bound voyage. Two days later, in company with three sister ships, the remainder of CortDiv 53. ''Tills'' weighed anchor, headed for Hawaii, and reached Pearl Harbor on 31 October.

== Return to Stateside ==

''Tills'' departed Hawaiian waters on 2 November, bound for the west coast. En route, the ship received word that a large transport plane had crashed into the sea off Oahu, and she was ordered to aid in the search for possible survivors. Of the eight people rescued, ''Tills'' picked up two and soon transferred them to {{USS|Casablanca|CVE-55|3}} where more complete medical treatment was available.

Arriving at San Diego, California, on 9 November, ''Tills'' underwent six days of availability before sailing for [[Panama]] on the 17th. Eight days later, on 25 November, she transited the [[Panama Canal]] for the first time.

Departing [[Coco Solo]] on 27 November, the destroyer escort proceeded to [[Hampton Roads]] for further availability in the [[Norfolk Navy Yard]] and initial preparations for decommissioning. On 16 January 1946, ''Tills'' reported to the [[St. Johns River]] berthing area to commence initial preservation work for her eventual decommissioning in June 1946.

== Reactivated as a training ship ==

Reactivated early in 1947 to an &quot;in-service status&quot;, the ship was towed to [[Miami, Florida]], where she was partially fitted out. In July, she made a two-week training cruise to [[San Juan, Puerto Rico]], with naval reservists on board. The following month, she entered the [[Charleston Naval Shipyard]] in [[South Carolina]] for overhaul. Refurbished by November, ''Tills'' was homeported at Miami and operated along the east coast from [[Boston, Massachusetts]], to Panama and in the [[Caribbean]], primarily training reservists.

Tills was placed back in full commission at [[Charleston, South Carolina]], on 21 November 1950, with Lt. Comdr. [[Elmo R. Zumwalt]] in command. The destroyer escort subsequently operated off the east coast as a [[School ship|training ship]], undertaking refresher and reserve training cruises. Homeported at Charleston, the ship took part in Exercise &quot;Convex III&quot; from 27 February to 20 March 1952 and in Operation &quot;Emigrant&quot; from 6 to 12 October 1952. In between these tasks, she made her first cruise to European waters in the summer of 1952, calling at [[Lisbon, Portugal]], and [[Arcachon]], [[France]], in June.

Continuing her reserve training cruises off the east coast through the summer of 1955, ''Tills'' cruised to Europe again and, after calling once more at Lisbon, added [[Cadiz, Spain]], to her itinerary. In 1956, the destroyer escort undertook a total of 13 naval reserve cruises.

On 1 May 1958, ''Tills''' home port was moved to Boston, Massachusetts, shifting the locus of her operations northward to the northeastern coast of the United States and to the Canadian provinces of [[Nova Scotia]] and [[Newfoundland and Labrador|Newfoundland]]. On 1 September 1959, after the ship had conducted reserve training and refresher training cruises for over a year, her home port was moved still farther north to [[Portland, Maine]]. On 18 October 1959, ''Tills'' was decommissioned and placed in service as a unit of the Selected Reserve Training Program. Administrative control was accordingly shifted from Commander, Destroyer Force, Atlantic Fleet, to Commandant, [[1st Naval District]].

== Recommissioned again as a training ship ==

After making weekend reserve cruises through the summer of 1961, ''Tills'' was recommissioned on 1 October 1961 in response to the Cuban missile crisis (blockade) with Lt. Comdr.W. L. Rich, USNR, in command. Following a six-week repair period at [[Newport, Rhode Island]], and refresher training in [[Guantanamo Bay, Cuba]], the ship operated out of her home port of [[Norfolk, Virginia]].

After the crisis situation eased, ''Tills'' returned to her erstwhile home port of Portland, Maine, on 12 July 1962, and was decommissioned there on 1 August 1962. Attached to Reserve Destroyer Squadron 30 and Reserve Destroyer Escort Squadron, 1st Naval District, ''Tills'' operated out of Portland, Maine, in an in-service basis and resumed making weekend reserve training cruises. On these brief voyages, she conducted antisubmarine exercises and steamed up and down the [[St. Lawrence Seaway]]. Moving to Newport, Rhode Island, on 20 October 1963, the ship underwent a one-month tender availability during which she received new [[torpedo]] tubes which replaced her old ones and her [[K-gun]]s. She returned to Portland on 17 November and remained there for the remainder of the year.

During 1964, ''Tills'' participated in a number of diverse and interesting events. After a tender availability alongside {{USS|Grand Canyon|AD-28|3}} from 22 March to 18 April, ''Tills'' returned to the Naval Reserve Training Center at South Portland, Maine, before getting underway for Boston on 13 June. A highlight of her reserve cruise was a four-day visit to the [[1964 New York World's Fair|New York World's Fair]].

After returning to her Maine base, the ship held an open house on 4 July and then visited [[Rockland, Maine]], for the annual Rockland Seafood Festival on 3 August. On 28 August, ''Tills'' served as patrol ship for the annual Starboat [[Yacht]] Races off [[Winthrop, Massachusetts]].

After subsequently participating in joint United States-Canadian antisubmarine exercises, the ship returned to the Naval Training Center at Portland for repairs before resuming her training cruises, a mission she faithfully carried out for the remainder of her career.

== Final disposition ==
Found unfit for further service, ''Tills'' was struck from the [[Naval Vessel Register|Navy List]] on 23 September 1968. On 3 April 1969, the ship was sunk as a target off [[Virginia]].

==Awards==
{|
|-
|[[Image:Combat Action Ribbon.svg|60px]]
|[[Combat Action Ribbon]] (retroactive)
|-
|[[Image:Navy Expeditionary ribbon.svg|60px]]
|[[Navy Expeditionary Medal]] ([[Cuba]])
|-
|[[Image:American Campaign Medal ribbon.svg|60px]]
|[[American Campaign Medal]]
|-
|{{ribbon devices|number=2|type=service-star|ribbon=Asiatic-Pacific Campaign ribbon.svg|width=60}}
|[[Asiatic-Pacific Campaign Medal]] (with two [[Service star|battle stars]])
|-
|[[Image:World War II Victory Medal ribbon.svg|60px]]
|[[World War II Victory Medal (United States)|World War II Victory Medal]]
|-
|{{ribbon devices|number=1|type=service-star|ribbon=National Defense Service Medal ribbon.svg|width=60}}
|[[National Defense Service Medal]] (with one [[service star]])
|}

== See also ==
* [[List of United States Navy ships]]

== References ==
* {{DANFS|http://www.history.navy.mil/research/histories/ship-histories/danfs/t/tills.html}}

== External links ==
* {{navsource|06/748|USS Tills (DE-748)}}

{{Cannon class destroyer escort}}
{{1969 shipwrecks}}

{{coord missing|Los Angeles County, California}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Tills (DE-748)}}
[[Category:Cannon-class destroyer escorts of the United States Navy]]
[[Category:Ships built in Los Angeles]]
[[Category:1943 ships]]
[[Category:World War II frigates and destroyer escorts of the United States]]
[[Category:Shipwrecks of the Virginia coast]]
[[Category:Ships sunk as targets]]
[[Category:Maritime incidents in 1969]]</text>
      <sha1>oighps0o8hi61cos6nfyiiox6qftn7v</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
