<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Vortex ring gun</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4979645</id>
    <revision>
      <id>674585192</id>
      <parentid>628660483</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-08-04T21:33:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JzG</username>
        <id>760284</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>rm. vanity press book</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="7573">[[Image:Vortex Ring Gun Test.jpg|thumb|250px|Knock-down test of a 109 mph (175 km/h) vortex ring gun.]] 
The '''vortex ring gun''' is an experimental [[non-lethal weapon]] for crowd control that uses high-energy [[vortex ring]]s of gas to knock down people or spray them with marking ink or other chemicals.

The concept was explored by the US Army starting in 1998, and by some commercial firms.  Knockdown of distant individuals currently seems unlikely even if the rings are launched at theoretical maximum speed, the [[speed of sound]].&lt;ref&gt;{{YouTube |id=QrgTtZXuj4w |title=Video of knock down tests}}&lt;/ref&gt; As for the delivery of chemicals, leakage during flight is still a problem.{{citation needed|date=June 2012}}

Weapons based on similar principles but different designs and purposes have been described before, typically using acetylene-air or hydrogen–oxygen explosions to create and propel the vortices.&lt;ref&gt;
[http://discaircraft.greyfalcon.us/FAULKER%20FEUERSTURM.htm &quot;Faulker Feuersturm&quot;]
by Rob Arndt: &quot;Dr. Zippermeyer ... designed and built a series of highly unorthodox anti-aircraft weapons ... Dr. Zippermeyer constructed both a huge Wirbelwind Kanone (Whirlwind Cannon) and Turbulenz Kanone (Vortex Cannon). ... used a detonation of hydrogen and oxygen ...&quot;
&lt;/ref&gt;

== Operation ==
[[Image:Vortex Ring Gun Schlierin.jpg|thumb|250px|Spark photography image of a vortex ring in flight.]]
[[Image:Optimum Vortex.jpg|thumb|250px|The vortex ring gun concept for maximum possible velocity and spin.]]
[[Image:Shock Bottle Vortex.jpg|thumb|250px|A degraded vortex ring fired without a nozzle.]]
In a typical concept, a [[blank (cartridge)|blank cartridge]] is fired into a gun barrel that has a diverging [[nozzle]] screwed onto the [[muzzle (firearm)|muzzle]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.defense-update.com/products/v/vortex-ring.htm &quot;Defense Update,&quot;] ''Qadima Israel internet magazine overview of the Vortex ring Gun.''&lt;/ref&gt; In the nozzle, the short pulse of high pressure gas briefly accelerates to a supersonic exit velocity, whereupon a portion of the exhaust transforms from axial flow into a subsonic, high spin [[vortex ring]] with the potential energy to fly hundreds of feet.&lt;ref&gt;George K. Lucey Jr., Vortex Ring Generator: Mechanical Engineering Design For 100Kpsi Operating Pressures, ARL-TR-2096, United States Army Research Laboratory, Adelphi, MD, January 2000 --- Includes equations and test results for a prototype vortex ring generator simulating a MK19 40mm grenade launcher.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GteGbZeKsOI|title=Vortex / Hail Cannon .  Welland Steam and Country Rally 2010|work=YouTube|accessdate=7 October 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The nozzle of a vortex ring gun is designed to both contain the short pulse of accelerating gas until the maximum pressure is lowered to atmospheric and to straighten the exhaust into an axial flow.&lt;ref&gt;Dr. John D. Anderson, Jr., &quot;Modern Compressible Flow With Historical Perspective,&quot; Second Edition, 1990 McGraw Hill Inc., NY, NY, pp 182-183, 327-329.&lt;/ref&gt; The objective is to form the vortex ring with the highest possible velocity and spin by colliding a short pulse of a supersonic jet stream against the relatively stagnant air behind the spherically expanding Blast Shock.  Without the nozzle, the high pressure jet stream is reduced to atmospheric by standing shock waves at the muzzle, and the resulting vortex ring is not only formed by a lower velocity jet stream but also degraded by turbulence.&lt;ref&gt;Daniel L. Clear, et al., &quot;Computational Fluid Dynamics Application To Gun Muzzle Blast - a Validation Case Study,&quot; Technical Report ARCCB-TR-03011, August 2003, US Army Armament Research Development And Engineering Center, Picatinny, NJ, Pages 6-7.&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==

===The 1998 US Army project===
The [[United States Army Research Laboratory]] was asked by the [[United States Marine Corps|Marine Corps]] Joint Non-Lethal Weapons Directorate to determine whether vortex rings could be used for non-lethal crowd control. Overall management authority for the study was assigned to the [[United States Army Materiel Command]], with support by [[ARDEC]]. Contributors to the study included individuals from the US Army's [[Aberdeen Proving Grounds]], [[Adaptive Research Incorporated]], [[Berkeley Research Associates]], [[EWS Limited]], [[Johns Hopkins University]], [[Pennsylvania State University]], [[Sara Corporation]], and  [[Sonic Development Laboratory]].&lt;ref&gt;Lucey, G &amp; Jasper, L., Vortex Ring Generator,  United States Army Research Laboratory, Adelphi, MD 1998. NLD III Conference, 25 February 1998, Johns Hopkins Applied Physics Lab., pp 1,41 -- Management description of the desired configuration, potential uses, performance requirements, technology gaps to overcome, and partners from academe, industry, and government.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Image:MK19-3 Machine Gun.jpg|thumb|250px|Figure 4. MK19-3 40mm grenade launch machine gun.]] The end product was to be a kit for quickly converting an existing lethal weapon to a non-lethal vortex ring generator that could knock-down an individual or spray him with a dye, malodorous chemical, or incapacitating chemical. The kit, consisting of a nozzle with chemical reservoirs and belts of blank 40mm cartridges modified to detonate at pressures up to 100,000 psi (690 KN/sqN), was being designed for the Navy [[Mk 19 grenade launcher|MK19-3]].&lt;ref&gt;George K. Lucey Jr., Vortex Ring Generator: Mechanical Engineering Design For 100Kpsi Operating Pressures, ARL-TR-2096, United States Army Research Laboratory, Adelphi, MD, January 2000.&lt;/ref&gt; The 40mm grenade machine gun was selected because firing at 4-10 shots per second resonates with many body parts and causes a stronger impact effect.&lt;ref&gt;Rasmussen, G., Human Body Vibrations Exposure And Its Measurement, Bruel and Kjer Technical Paper, 1982. Abstract 1983, Journal of Acoustical Society of America, 73(6) 2229.&lt;/ref&gt;

Single shot field tests performed without optimized nozzles led to the conclusion vortex rings were unsuitable for non-lethal crowd control.  This conclusion was reached partly because knock down did not appear to be feasible at the desired range of {{convert|100|ft}}, partly because of the excessive spillage onto bystanders under the flight path if used to transport chemicals or dyes, and partly because the flight noise and speed enabled it to be easily avoided at the downrange target.&lt;ref&gt;{{YouTube |id=7wGUYHcXnlc |title=Videos of prototype Vortex Ring Gun field tests.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{YouTube |id=NbAQcxmXeIk  |title=Sound track of a vortex ring approaching a target}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The foremost reliability issue with this project was turbulence caused by the high-energy propellant burning outside the barrel.

===The Hail cannon===
Later commercial designs overcame some problems of the US Army concept by using less energetic gas propellants. The [[Hail cannon]] reliably fires vortex rings at one third the speed of sound or better.&lt;ref&gt;{{YouTube |id=GteGbZeKsOI |title=Video of a very high speed Hail Gun vortex ring}}&lt;/ref&gt; (Note that Hail cannons have been in use for over a century and do not themselves qualify as &quot;later commercial designs&quot;.)

== References ==

{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
* [http://handle.dtic.mil/100.2/ADA351056 Overview of the vortex ring gun program]
* [http://handle.dtic.mil/100.2/ADA417311 Live rifle fire and computer modeling of the muzzle blast vortex ring]
* [http://handle.dtic.mil/100.2/ADA372518 Engineering design of the prototype vortex ring gun]

[[Category:Non-lethal firearms]]
[[Category:Vortices]]</text>
      <sha1>hsbszkiax6wscnrk9rpudcosi76wk2x</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
