<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Wilhelm Mohnke</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1712046</id>
    <revision>
      <id>748847887</id>
      <parentid>747614409</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-10T19:08:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Kierzek</username>
        <id>9088688</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>ce</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="28490">{{refimprove|date=December 2015}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2013}}
{{Infobox military person
|name=Wilhelm Mohnke
|birth_date=15 March 1911
|death_date= {{death date and age|df=yes|2001|8|6|1911|3|15}}
|image=SSWilhelmMohnke.jpg
|caption= Mohnke as a SS-Standartenführer in 1944
|birth_place=[[Lübeck]], [[Free City of Lübeck]], [[German Empire]]
|death_place=[[Damp, Germany|Damp]], [[Schleswig-Holstein]], [[Germany]]
|allegiance={{flag|Nazi Germany}}
|branch=[[File:Flag Schutzstaffel.svg|23px]] [[Waffen-SS]]
|serviceyears=1931–45
|rank=[[SS-Brigadeführer]] und [[Generalmajor]] der Waffen-SS
|servicenumber=[[NSDAP]] #649,684&lt;br/&gt;[[SS]] #15,541
|commands=[[File:12SSHJinsig.svg|21px]] [[12th SS Panzer Division Hitlerjugend|26th SS Panzergrenadier Regiment]]&lt;br/&gt;[[File:1. SS-Panzer-Division Leibstandarte-SS Adolf Hitler.svg|17px]] [[1st SS Division Leibstandarte SS Adolf Hitler]]&lt;br/&gt;Kampfgruppe Mohnke
|unit=
|battles=[[World War II]]
|awards=[[Iron Cross|Iron Cross 1st Class]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Iron Cross|Iron Cross 2nd Class]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Wound Badge]] (Black)&lt;br/&gt;[[Infantry Assault Badge]]&lt;br/&gt;[[War Merit Cross]] with Swords&lt;br/&gt;Wound Badge (Silver)&lt;br/&gt;[[German Cross]] (Gold)&lt;br/&gt;[[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross]]
|laterwork=}}

[[SS]]-''[[Brigadeführer]]'' '''Wilhelm Mohnke''' (15 March 1911 – 6 August 2001) was one of the original members of the [[SS]]-Staff Guard (''Stabswache'') &quot;Berlin&quot; formed in March 1933. From those ranks, Mohnke rose to become one of [[Adolf Hitler]]'s last remaining generals. He joined the [[Nazi Party]] in September 1931.

Mohnke saw action with the [[1st SS Division Leibstandarte SS Adolf Hitler|''Leibstandarte SS Adolf Hitler'']] in France, Poland and the Balkans. After several failed attempts to introduce a [[Panzer]] arm to the ''Leibstandarte'', he was transferred to the replacement battalion until he was given command of a regiment in the [[12th SS Panzer Division Hitlerjugend|12th SS Panzer Division ''Hitlerjugend'']]. It was with this regiment that he fought in the [[Battle for Caen]]. He received the [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross]] on 11 July 1944. After participating in most of the French campaign, he was given command of his original division, the ''Leibstandarte'', during the [[Battle of the Bulge]], which commenced on 16 December 1944.

He served until the very last day of the war in Europe; during the [[Battle of Berlin]], he commanded the ''Kampfgruppe Mohnke'' and was charged with defending the [[Berlin]] government district, including the [[Reich Chancellery]] and [[Reichstag (building)|''Reichstag'']] (nicknamed ''Die Zitadelle'' or &quot;The Citadel&quot;).{{sfn|Fischer|2008|pp=42–43}} He was investigated after the war for [[war crime]]s, including allegations that he was responsible for the murder of prisoners in France in 1940, Normandy in June 1944 and Belgium in December 1944. He was never charged and died in 2001, aged 90.

==Early life and SS service==
Mohnke was born in [[Lübeck]] on 15 March 1911. His father, who shared his name with his son, was a cabinetmaker. After his father's death, he went to work for a glass and porcelain manufacturer, eventually reaching a management position. Mohnke joined the [[Nazi Party]] with number 649,684 on 1 September 1931. Shortly thereafter, he joined the [[Schutzstaffel|SS]] with number 15,541. Mohnke began with the rank of SS-''Mann'' (private). After [[Adolf Hitler]] became Chancellor of Germany in January 1933, SS Headquarters in Berlin requested that all SS regiments submit three names of their best soldiers for transfer to a personal guard unit for Hitler. Mohnke was selected for the unit in March 1933. He was assigned to ''SS-Stabswache Berlin'', which established its first guard at the original [[Reich Chancellery]].{{sfn|Fischer|2008|p=1}} By August, Mohnke was one of two company commanders.{{sfn|Cook|Bender|1994|p=11}} In September, the unit became known as the ''SS-Sonderkommando Berlin'' after the training units ''SS-Sonderkommando Zossen'' and ''SS-Sonderkommando Jüterbog'' merged with it under Dietrich's command.{{sfn|Fischer|2008|p=1}}{{sfn|Cook|Bender|1994|pp=11, 13}} With the merger, Mohnke was transferred to the 2nd Battalion and given command of the 3rd Company.{{sfn|Cook|Bender|1994|p=14}}

==World War II service==
Mohnke took part in the Polish Campaign in September, 1939. He was wounded on 7 September 1939 and recovered in the hospital in Prague. For this, Mohnke received the Wound Badge in Black. He was awarded the Iron Cross, Second Class on 29 September 1939 and the Iron Cross, First Class on 8 November 1939.{{sfn|Fischer|2008|p=22}}

Mohnke led the 5th company of the 2nd Battalion of the ''Infanterie-Regiment Leibstandarte SS Adolf Hitler'' (mot.), at the outset of the [[Battle of France]] in 1940. He took command of the 2nd Battalion on 28 May after the battalion commander was wounded.{{sfn|Fischer|2008|pp=24–25}} It was around this time that Mohnke was allegedly involved in the murder of 80 British prisoners of war (POWs) of the 48th Division [[Wormhoudt massacre|near Wormhoudt]]. Mohnke was never brought to trial over these allegations, and when the case was reopened in 1988, a German prosecutor came to the conclusion there was insufficient evidence to bring charges.{{sfn|Weale|2012|p=253}} The case briefly resurfaced once again in late 1993 when it became evident that the British government had not revealed some pertinent files from its archives during the earlier investigation.{{sfn|The Independent|1993}} However, nothing substantial came from this either.

He commanded the 2nd Battalion during the Balkans campaign, where he suffered a severe leg wound in a Yugoslavian air attack on 6 April 1941, the first day of the campaign. It was the decision of the medics that his leg would need to be amputated, but Mohnke overrode them.{{sfn|Fischer|2008|p=32}} His wound was so grievous that they were still forced to remove part of his foot. On 26 December 1941, during the eight months he spent recuperating (due to the severity of his injury), Mohnke was awarded the [[German Cross]] in Gold.{{sfn|Fischer|2008|p=32–43}}

It was Mohnke who planted the seed for the formation of the ''Leibstandarte'' Panzer Battalion early in 1942, after returning to active service. He appointed Ralf Tiemann as his adjutant, whose first official task was finding recruits. Tiemann proceeded to compile a list, eventually with enough names to fill two companies. While the newly married [[Sepp Dietrich]] presented his new wife to his officers on 14 January, Mohnke presented the divisional commander (Dietrich) with his personnel list, which had in the meantime turned into transfer orders. Dietrich, who was caught unawares, finally gave in to Mohnke's pressure and signed the paper. So was born the ''Panzerwaffe der Leibstandarte Adolf Hitler''. It was not to be though, and Mohnke was relieved of his command and transferred to the replacement battalion on 16 March 1942.

==With the ''Hitlerjugend''==
On 1 September 1943, 16,000 new recruits of the ''Hitlerjugend'' (Hitler Youth) born in 1926 took part in the formation of the [[12th SS Panzer Division Hitlerjugend|12th SS Panzer Division ''Hitlerjugend'']], while the senior [[Non-commissioned officer|NCO]]s and officers were generally veterans of the Eastern Front.&lt;ref name=Latimer&gt;{{cite journal | last =Latimer | first = Jon | title = World War II: 12th SS Hitlerjugend Panzer Division Fought in Normandy | journal = World War II | issue = July | year = 2001 | url = http://www.historynet.com/world-war-ii-12th-ss-hitlerjugend-panzer-division-fought-in-normandy.htm/6 | accessdate =2009-02-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; SS-''[[Obersturmbannführer]]'' Mohnke was given command of the 26th SS ''Panzergrenadier'' Regiment, which was the second regiment formed in the 12th SS Panzer Division ''Hitlerjugend''.

Mohnke was implicated in the killing of 35 Canadian prisoners at [[Fontenay-le-Pesnel]], though he never faced a trial, owing to lack of conclusive proof of his involvement. Mohnke told historian Fischer that, at times, he had to take strong painkillers, such as morphine, due to the severe pain in his shortened right leg (from his combat injuries in April 1941) but whether these things affected his decision making process is not known.{{sfn|Fischer|2008|p=40}} What is known is that his physical health affected his deployment. Mohnke was commander of the ''Leibstandarte'''s replacement battalion from March 1942 till May 1943. Then being &quot;free enough from pain&quot;, SS-''Obersturmbannführer'' [[Kurt Meyer (soldier)|Kurt Meyer]] &quot;cajoled&quot; him into taking a command with the 12th SS Panzer Division. This led to commanding the 26th SS Pz-Gren Rgt on 15 September 1943.{{sfn|Fischer|2008|p=33}}

The structure of the 26th SS ''Panzergrenadier'' Regiment was somewhat unconventional. Although as a whole the regiment was labeled as ''Panzergrenadiers'', the III Battalion was the only battalion in the regiment that was actually armored. It did, however, have an additional company, designated the 15th Reconnaissance Company, which was outfitted with armored cars. This company helped make the 26th SS ''Panzergrenadier'' Regiment a unique fighting force.

While the 12th SS Panzer Division was fighting to keep the [[Falaise pocket]] open, in which the division suffered an estimated 40%-50% casualties, Mohnke withdrew his ''Kampfgruppe'' (Battle Group) east of the river Dives. As the situation in Normandy deteriorated for Germany and the front was pushed back to the [[Seine]], Mohnke was one of the few to lead organized resistance on the western bank in order to protect the river crossings there. After hard fighting, Mohnke was awarded the Knight's Cross on 11 July 1944. He led this ''Kampfgruppe'' until 31 August, when he replaced the badly wounded [[Theodor Wisch]] as commander of the ''Leibstandarte'' (LSSAH).{{sfn|Fischer|2008|pp=33, 38}} This promotion is the subject of speculation as to why Mohnke was given command of the LSSAH when then SS-''Obersturmbannführer'' [[Joachim Peiper]] had more combat experience. Peiper, the youngest regimental commander in the [[Waffen-SS]], was perhaps considered too junior to command a division.

==''Wacht am Rhein''==
[[Operation Wacht am Rhein|Operation ''Wacht am Rhein'']], followed by [[Operation Nordwind|Operation ''Nordwind'']] were the final major offensives and last gambles Hitler made on the [[Western Front (World War II)|Western Front]]. Mohnke, now in command of his home division, led his formation as the spearhead of the entire operation in the [[Ardennes]]. Attached to the [[I SS Panzer Corps]], the LSSAH was one of the most elite and highly trained units in the German military. The fuel crisis in Nazi Germany meant that the LSSAH had dangerously low amounts of fuel for the vehicles that they depended on to make the division a viable fighting force. On 16 December 1944 the operation began, with Mohnke designating, SS-''Obersturmbannführer'' Joachim Peiper, and his ''Kampfgruppe'' to lead the push to Antwerp.

By 0700 on 17 December 1944, Peiper's ''Kampfgruppe'' had seized the American fuel dump at [[Büllingen]]. At 1330 that same day, at a crossroads near [[Malmedy]], men from Peiper's combat formation shot and killed at least 68 [[United States]] POWs. The [[Malmedy massacre]], as it was to become known, is one of the most infamous killings of the war. Since ''[[Kampfgruppe Peiper]]'', the perpetrators of the massacre, were under Mohnke's overall command, there were several accusations that he should be held personally responsible, yet he was never found guilty of the crime. By the evening of 17 December, the leading element of the LSSAH was engaged with the 99th US Division at [[Stavelot]]. Mohnke's division was behind their deadline by at least 36 hours by the end of the second day. Progress was further delayed by the retreating troops blowing up important bridges and fuel dumps that Mohnke and Peiper had counted on taking intact.

With each passing day, enemy resistance stiffened and the advance was eventually halted on all fronts. Desperate to keep the assault going, the German High Command ordered that a renewed attack begin on 1 January 1945. Yet this time, the Allies had regrouped their forces and were ready to repulse any attacks launched by the Germans. The operation formally ended on 27 January 1945, and three days later Mohnke was promoted to SS-''[[Brigadeführer]]''. A short while later the LSSAH and 'I SS Panzer Korps' were transferred to Hungary to bolster the crumbling situation there. Mohnke was injured in an air raid where he suffered, among other things, ear damage. He was removed from front-line service and put on the Führer reserve.

==Berlin==
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1983-028-05, Helmuth Weidling.jpg|thumb|left|125px|[[Helmuth Weidling]] in 1943]]
After recovering from his wounds, Mohnke was personally appointed by Hitler as the ''Kommandant'' (Battle Commander) for the defense of the centre government district (''Zitadelle'' sector) which included the Reich Chancellery and ''[[Führerbunker]]''.{{sfn|Fischer|2008|pp=42–43}} Mohnke's command post was under the Reich Chancellery in the bunkers therein.{{sfn|Lehrer|2006|p=121}} He formed ''Kampfgruppe Mohnke'' (Battle Group Mohnke) and it was divided into two weak regiments. It was made up of the LSSAH Flak Company, replacements from LSSAH ''Ausbildungs-und Ersatz Battalion'' from Spreenhagen under SS-''Standartenführer'' Anhalt, 600 men from the ''[[Begleit-Bataillon Reichsführer-SS]]'', the ''Führer-Begleit-Kompanie'' and the core group being the 800 men of the ''Leibstandarte'' (LSSAH) SS Guard Battalion (that was assigned to guard the Führer).{{sfn|Fischer|2008|pp=42–43}}{{sfn|Stein|1984|p=162}}

Although Hitler had appointed General [[Helmuth Weidling]] as defense commandant of Berlin, Mohnke remained free of Weidling's command to maintain his defense objectives of the Reich Chancellery and the ''Führerbunker''. The combined total (for the city's defense) of Mohnke's SS ''Kampfgruppe'', General Weidling's [[LVI Panzer Corps]] (and the other few units) totaled roughly 45,000 soldiers and 40,000 ''[[Volkssturm]]''.{{sfn|Beevor|2002|p=287}} They faced a superior number of Soviet [[Red Army]] soldiers. There were approximately 1.5 million Soviet troops allocated for the [[investment (military)|investment]] and assault on the Berlin Defence Area.{{sfn|Beevor|2002|p=287}}

Since Mohnke's fighting force was located at the nerve center of the German [[Third Reich]], it fell under intense artillery bombardment, which began on Hitler's birthday of 20 April 1945 and lasted to the end of hostilities on 2 May 1945. Street fighting around the ''[[Reichstag building|Reichstag]]'' and Reich Chancellery was bitter and bloody. For the Soviets, the ''Reichstag'' was the symbol of Nazi Germany and therefore of significant military and political value to capture.{{sfn|Beevor|2002|pp=354–356}}

While the [[Battle in Berlin]] was raging around them, Hitler ordered Mohnke to set up a military tribunal for [[Hermann Fegelein]], adjutant to [[Heinrich Himmler]], in order to try the man for desertion. The tribunal consisted of Generals [[Hans Krebs (general)|Hans Krebs]], [[Wilhelm Burgdorf]], [[Johann Rattenhuber]], and Mohnke himself. Years later, Mohnke told author O'Donnell the following:&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;I was to preside over it myself...I decided the accused man [Fegelein] deserved trial by high-ranking officers...We set up the court-martial in a room next to my command post...We military judges took our seats at the table with the standard German Army Manual of Courts-Martial before us. No sooner were we seated than defendant Fegelein began acting up in such an outrageous manner that the trial could not even commence.

Roaring drunk..., Fegelein first brazenly challenged the competence of the court. He kept blubbering that he was responsible to...Himmler alone, not Hitler...He refused to defend himself. The man was in wretched shape - bawling, whining, vomiting, shaking like an aspen leaf...

I was now faced with an impossible situation. On the one hand, based on all available evidence, including his own earlier statements, this miserable excuse for an officer was guilty of flagrant desertion... Yet the German Army Manual states clearly that no German soldier can be tried unless he is clearly of sound mind and body, in a condition to hear the evidence against him. I looked up the passage again, to make sure, and consulted with my fellow judges...In my opinion and that of my fellow officers, Hermann Fegelein was in no condition to stand trial, or for that matter to even stand. I closed the proceedings...So I turned Fegelein over to [SS] General [[Johann Rattenhuber|Rattenhuber]] and his security squad. I never saw the man again.&quot;{{sfn|O'Donnell|2001|pp=182, 183}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-R77767, Berlin, Rotarmisten Unter den Linden.jpg|thumb|upright|After the battle, Soviet soldiers hoist the Soviet flag on the balcony of the [[Hotel Adlon]] in Berlin]]
On 30 April, after receiving news of Hitler's suicide, orders were issued that those who could do so were to break out. The plan was to escape from Berlin to the Allies on the western side of the [[Elbe]] or to the German Army to the North. Prior to the breakout, Mohnke briefed all commanders (who could be reached) within the ''Zitadelle'' sector about the events as to Hitler's death and the planned break out. They split up into ten main groups on 1 May 1945.{{sfn|Fischer|2008|p=49}} Mohnke's group included: secretary [[Traudl Junge]], secretary [[Gerda Christian]], secretary [[Else Krüger]], Hitler's dietician, [[Constanze Manziarly]], [[Ernst-Günther Schenck]], [[Walther Hewel]] and various others.{{sfn|O'Donnell|2001|pp=271–276}} Mohnke planned to break out towards the German Army which was positioned in Prinzenallee. The group headed along the subway but their route was blocked so they went aboveground and later joined hundreds of other Germans civilians and military personnel who had sought refuge at the Schultheiss-Patzenhofer Brewery on Prinzenallee. On 2 May 1945, General Weidling issued an order calling for the complete surrender of all German forces still in [[Berlin]]. Knowing they could not get through the Soviet rings, Mohnke decided to surrender to the Red Army. However, several of Mohnke's group (including some of the SS personnel) opted to commit suicide.{{sfn|Fischer|2008|pp=49–50}}

==Post-war life==
Following their surrender Mohnke and other senior German officers from ''Kampfgruppe Mohnke'' (including Dr. Schenck) were treated to a banquet by the Chief of Staff of the [[8th Guards Army (Soviet Union)|8th Guards Army]] with the permission of [[Lieutenant General]] [[Vasily Chuikov]].{{sfn|O'Donnell|2001|pp=325-330}} At 10:30 pm, the Germans were ushered out into another room where they were confined under guard. On the following night of 3 May, Mohnke and the rest of the Germans were handed over to the [[NKVD]].{{sfn|O'Donnell|2001|pp=331, 332}} On 9 May 1945, he was flown to [[Moscow]] for interrogation and kept in solitary confinement for six years, after being transferred to [[Lubyanka (KGB)|Lubjanka Prison]]. Thereafter, Mohnke was transferred again to the Generals' Prison in Woikowo. He remained in captivity until 10 October 1955.{{sfn|Fischer|2008|p=51}} Following his release, he worked as a dealer in small trucks and trailers, living in [[Barsbüttel]], [[West Germany]]. He died on 6 August 2001 in Barsbüttel-Hamburg, aged 90.{{sfn|Scherzer|2007|p=549}}&lt;ref group=&quot;Note&quot;&gt;Some other sources place his death in the coastal village of [[Damp, Germany|Damp]], near Eckernförde in [[Schleswig-Holstein]].&lt;/ref&gt;

==War crimes accusations==
Mohnke's regiment was involved in the murder of three Canadian prisoners of war in Normandy in 1944.{{sfn|The Independent|1993}} Mohnke himself was investigated by Canadian authorities, but was not charged.{{sfn|Margolian|1998|p=185}} There was also a campaign by British Member of Parliament [[Jeff Rooker, Baron Rooker|Jeff Rooker]] to prosecute him for his alleged involvement in war crimes during the early part of the war. Mohnke strongly denied the accusations, telling historian Thomas Fischer, &quot;I issued no orders not to take English prisoners or to execute prisoners.&quot;{{sfn|Fischer|2008|p=26}} After the case was reopened, a German prosecutor came to the conclusion there was insufficient evidence to bring charges.{{sfn|Weale|2012|p=253}}

==Promotions==
{| 
| 28 June 1933    || Commissioned
|-
| 1 October 1933  || SS-''[[Hauptsturmführer]]''
|-
|style=&quot;padding-right:1.5em;&quot;| 1 September 1940 || SS-''[[Sturmbannführer]]''
|-
| 21 June 1943    || SS-''[[Obersturmbannführer]]''
|-
| 21 June 1944    || SS-''[[Standartenführer]]''
|-
| 4 November 1944 || SS-''[[Oberführer]]''
|-
| 30 January 1945 || SS-''[[Brigadeführer]]''
|}

==Awards==
{|
|style=&quot;padding-right:1.5em;&quot;| 21 September 1939 || [[Iron Cross]] Second Class
|-
| 8 November 1939   || Iron Cross First Class
|-
| 10 February 1940  || [[Wound Badge]] (Black)
|- valign=&quot;top&quot;
|rowspan=&quot;2&quot;| 3 October 1940
                     | [[Infantry Assault Badge]] (General)
                     |-
                     | [[War Merit Cross]] with Swords
|-
| 15 September 1941 || Wound Badge (Silver)
|-
| 26 December 1941  || [[German Cross]] in Gold as SS-''[[Sturmbannführer]]'' in the II./&quot;Leibstandarte SS Adolf Hitler&quot;{{sfn|Patzwall|Scherzer|2001|p=313}}
|-
| 11 July 1944      || [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross]] as SS-''[[Obersturmbannführer]]'' and commander of SS-Panzergrenadier-Regiment 26 &quot;Hitlerjugend&quot;{{sfn|Fellgiebel|2000|p=314}}{{refn|1=According to Scherzer as commander of SS-Panzergrenadier-Regiment 26.{{sfn|Scherzer|2007|p=549}}|group=&quot;Note&quot;}}
|}

==Portrayal in the media==

Wilhelm Mohnke has been portrayed by the following actors in film and television productions:&lt;ref name=&quot;imdb&quot;&gt;{{cite web | url = http://www.imdb.com/character/ch0063971/ | title = Wilhelm Mohnke (Character) | accessdate = 8 May 2008 | author = | last = | first = | authorlink = | coauthors = | date = | year = | month = | format = | work = | publisher = [[IMDb.com]] | pages = | doi = | archiveurl = | archivedate = | quote = }}&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Michael Culver]] in the 1981 [[United States]] television production ''[[The Bunker (1981 film)|The Bunker]]''. Depicting Mohnke during the last days of Hitler in the [[Führerbunker]]; Berlin.
* [[Ralph Michael]] in the 1991 [[United Kingdom|British]] T.V. mini-series ''[[Hitler Diaries#Reception in popular culture|Selling Hitler]]''.
* [[André Hennicke]] in the 2004 German film [[Downfall (2004 film)|''Downfall'' (''Der Untergang'')]]. Depicting Mohnke during the [[Battle of Berlin]] and the last days of Hitler in the Führerbunker.

==See also==
* [[Battle of Berlin]]
* [[Glossary of German military terms|Glossary of German World War II military terms]]
* [[Glossary of Nazi Germany]]
* [[Wormhoudt massacre]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|group=&quot;Note&quot;}}

==References==

===Citations===
{{Reflist|30em}}

===Bibliography===
{{refbegin}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Beevor
  |first=Antony
  |year=2002
  |title=[[Berlin: The Downfall 1945]]
  |publisher=Viking-Penguin Books
  |isbn=978-0-670-03041-5
  |ref=harv
}}
* Botting, Douglas &amp; Sayer, Ian. ''Hitler's Last General: The Case Against Wilhelm Mohnke.'' [[Bantam Books]], 1989. ISBN 0-593-01709-9
* {{cite book
| last1 = Cook
| first1 = Stan
| last2 = Bender
| first2 = Roger James
| title = Leibstandarte SS Adolf Hitler: Uniforms, Organization, &amp; History
| year = 1994
| publisher = James Bender Publishing
| location = San Jose, CA
| isbn = 978-0-912138-55-8
| ref = harv
}}
* {{cite book
  |last=Fellgiebel
  |first=Walther-Peer
  |authorlink=Walther-Peer Fellgiebel
  |year=2000
  |origyear=1986
  |title=Die Träger des Ritterkreuzes des Eisernen Kreuzes 1939–1945 — Die Inhaber der höchsten Auszeichnung des Zweiten Weltkrieges aller Wehrmachtteile
  |trans_title=The Bearers of the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross 1939–1945 — The Owners of the Highest Award of the Second World War of all Wehrmacht Branches
  |language=German
  |location=Friedberg, Germany
  |publisher=Podzun-Pallas
  |isbn=978-3-7909-0284-6
  |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book
  |last=Fischer
  |first=Thomas
  |title=Soldiers of the Leibstandarte
  |year=2008
  |publisher=J.J. Fedorowicz Publishing, Inc
  |isbn=978-0-921991-91-5
  |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite web|website=The Independent |url=http://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/files-released-on-nazi-accused-over-massacre-ss-general-linked-to-pow-deaths-1466041.html |title=Files released on Nazi accused over massacre: SS general linked to POW deaths |author= |date=1993 |access-date=31 December 2015 |ref={{harvid|The Independent|1993}} |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20160104025520/http://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/files-released-on-nazi-accused-over-massacre-ss-general-linked-to-pow-deaths-1466041.html |archivedate=4 January 2016 }}
* {{cite book
  |last=Lehrer
  |first=Steven
  |year=2006
  |title=The Reich Chancellery and Führerbunker Complex: An Illustrated History of the Seat of the Nazi Regime
  |publisher=McFarland
  |location=Jefferson, NC
  |isbn=0-7864-2393-5
  |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book
  |last=Margolian
  |first=Howard
  |year=1998
  |title=Conduct Unbecoming: Conduct Unbecoming: The Story of the Murder of Canadian Prisoners of War in Normandy
  |location=Toronto
  |publisher=University of Toronto Press
  |isbn=978-0802083609
  |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book
  |last=O'Donnell
  |first=James P.
  |authorlink=James P. O'Donnell
  |title=[[The Bunker (book)|The Bunker]]
  |publisher=Da Capo Press
  |location=New York
  |year=2001
  |origyear=1978
  |isbn=978-0-306-80958-3
  |ref=harv
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last1=Patzwall
  |first1=Klaus D.
  |last2=Scherzer
  |first2=Veit
  |year=2001
  |title=Das Deutsche Kreuz 1941 – 1945 Geschichte und Inhaber Band II
  |trans_title=The German Cross 1941 – 1945 History and Recipients Volume 2
  |language=German
  |location=Norderstedt, Germany
  |publisher=Verlag Klaus D. Patzwall
  |isbn=978-3-931533-45-8
  |ref=harv
}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Scherzer
  |first=Veit
  |year=2007
  |title=Die Ritterkreuzträger 1939–1945 Die Inhaber des Ritterkreuzes des Eisernen Kreuzes 1939 von Heer, Luftwaffe, Kriegsmarine, Waffen-SS, Volkssturm sowie mit Deutschland verbündeter Streitkräfte nach den Unterlagen des Bundesarchives
  |trans_title=The Knight's Cross Bearers 1939–1945 The Holders of the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross 1939 by Army, Air Force, Navy, Waffen-SS, Volkssturm and Allied Forces with Germany According to the Documents of the Federal Archives
  |language=German
  |location=Jena, Germany
  |publisher=Scherzers Militaer-Verlag
  |isbn=978-3-938845-17-2
  |ref=harv
}}
* {{cite book | last = Stein | first = George H. | title = The Waffen SS: Hitler's Elite Guard at War, 1939–1945 | publisher = Cornell University Press | location = Ithaca, NY | year = 1984 | isbn = 0-8014-9275-0 | ref = harv }}
* {{Cite book
 |last = Weale
 |first = Adrian
 |authorlink = Adrian Weale
 |title = Army of Evil: A History of the SS
 |year = 2012
 |publisher = NAL Caliber (Penguin Group)
 |location = New York; Toronto
 |isbn = 978-0-451-23791-0
 |ref = harv
 }}
{{refend}}

==External links==
* {{DNB portal|119035340|TYP=}}

{{s-start}}
{{s-mil}}
{{succession box
| before = SS-Brigadeführer [[Theodor Wisch]]
| after  = SS-Brigadeführer [[Otto Kumm]]
| title  = Commander of [[1st SS Division Leibstandarte SS Adolf Hitler]]
| years  = 20 August 1944 – 6 February 1945
}}
{{s-end}}

{{Knight's Cross recipients of the 12th SS PD}}
{{Final occupants of the Führerbunker}}
{{Authority control}}
{{Subject bar
| portal1=Biography
| portal2=Military of Germany
| portal3=World War II
| q=y
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Mohnke, Wilhelm}}
[[Category:1911 births]]
[[Category:2001 deaths]]
[[Category:People from Lübeck]]
[[Category:SS-Brigadeführer]]
[[Category:Recipients of the War Merit Cross, 2nd class]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Gold German Cross]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross]]
[[Category:Battle of Berlin]]
[[Category:German prisoners of war in World War II held by the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:Waffen-SS personnel]]
[[Category:Recipients of the SS-Ehrenring]]
[[Category:Recipients of the Sword of Honour of the Reichsführer-SS]]</text>
      <sha1>5pxmoeo9ki2x8svq7kgb2sapij56ys2</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
