<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>William Mahone</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1175543</id>
    <revision>
      <id>726323034</id>
      <parentid>725308422</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-06-21T12:39:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cydebot</username>
        <id>1215485</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Robot - Speedily moving category Slave owners in the United States to [[:Category:American slave owners]] per [[WP:CFDS|CFDS]].</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="27112">{{for|his son|William T. Mahone Jr.}}
{{Infobox officeholder
|name                = William Mahone
|image = William Mahone.jpg
|jr/sr               = United States Senator
|state               = [[Virginia]]
|term_start          = March 4, 1881
|term_end            = March 4, 1887
|predecessor         = [[Robert E. Withers]]
|successor           = [[John W. Daniel]]
|birth_date          = {{birth date|1826|12|1}}
|birth_place         = [[Southampton County, Virginia|Southampton County]], [[Virginia]]
|death_date          = {{death date and age|1895|10|8|1826|12|1}}
|death_place         = [[Washington, D.C.]]
|resting_place       = [[Blandford Cemetery]], [[Petersburg, Virginia]]
|party               = [[Readjuster Party|Readjuster]]
|alma_mater          = [[Virginia Military Institute]]
|nickname=Little Billy
|allegiance    = {{flag|Confederate States}}
|branch        = {{army|CSA}}
|serviceyears  = 1861–1865
|rank          = [[File:Confederate States of America General-collar.svg|40px]] [[General officers in the Confederate States Army|Major General]]
|battles       = [[American Civil War]]
* [[Peninsula Campaign]]
* [[Second Manassas]]
* [[Battle of Fredericksburg]]
* [[Battle of Chancellorsville]]
* [[Battle of Gettysburg]]
* [[Overland Campaign]]
* [[Appomattox Campaign]]
}}

'''William Mahone''' (December 1, 1826{{spaced ndash}}October 8, 1895) was a [[civil engineer]], [[railroad]] executive, soldier and politician.

As a young man, Mahone was prominent in the building of Virginia’s roads and railroads. As chief engineer of the Norfolk and Petersburg Railroad, he built log-foundations under the [[Great Dismal Swamp]] that are still intact today. According to local tradition, several new railroad towns were named after the novels of Sir Walter Scott, a favourite author of Mahone’s wife Otelia.

In the American Civil War, Mahone was pro-secession and served as a Confederate general. He was best known for regaining the initiative at Petersburg, when the Southern troops were in shock after a huge mine was exploded beneath them ([[Battle of the Crater]], July 1864), and his counter-attack turned the engagement into a disastrous Union defeat.

After the war, he returned to railroad building, merging three lines to form the important [[Atlantic, Mississippi and Ohio Railroad]] (AM&amp;O), headquartered in Lynchburg. He also led the [[Readjuster Party]], a coalition of blacks, Republicans and conservative Democrats, and was elected to the [[United States Senate|U.S. Senate]] in 1881. His willingness to caucus with Republicans cost him some support from the white electorate, as did his relatively lenient treatment of [[African Americans]].

==Early life==
William Mahone was born at [[Brown's Ferry (Drakes Corner, Virginia)|Brown's Ferry]] near [[Courtland, Virginia|Courtland]] in [[Southampton County, Virginia]], to Fielding Jordan Mahone and Martha (née Drew) Mahone.&lt;ref name=VAnom&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dhr.virginia.gov/registers/Counties/Southampton/087-0120_Browns_Ferry_1979_Final_Nomination.pdf|title=National Register of Historic Places Inventory/Nomination: Brown's Ferry|author=Virginia Historic Landmarks Commission Staff|date=March 1979|publisher=Virginia Department of Historic Resources}}&lt;/ref&gt; Beginning with the immigration of his Mahone ancestors from [[Ireland]], he was the third individual to be called &quot;William Mahone.&quot; He did not have a middle name as shown by records including his two Bibles, [[Virginia Military Institute]] (VMI) Diploma, marriage license, and Confederate Army commissions. Likewise, the General and Otelia's first-born son was christened William Mahone. The suffix &quot;Jr.&quot; was added to his name later in his life, during a period of similar cultural naming transitions in Virginia.

The little town of [[Monroe, Virginia|Monroe]] was on the banks of the [[Nottoway River]] about eight miles south of the [[county seat]] at Jerusalem, a town which was renamed [[Courtland, Virginia|Courtland]] in 1888. The river was an important transportation artery in the years before railroads and later highways served the area. Fielding Mahone ran a store at Monroe and owned considerable farmland. The family narrowly escaped the massacre of local whites during [[Nat Turner's slave rebellion]] in 1831.

The local shift of transportation in the area was from the river to the new technology emerging with [[railroad]]s in the 1830s. In 1840, when William was 14 years old, the family moved to Jerusalem, where Fielding Mahone purchased and operated a tavern known as [[Mahone's Tavern]].&lt;ref name=VAnom1&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dhr.virginia.gov/registers/Counties/Southampton/201-0001_Mahones_Tavern_2008_NR_final.pdf|title=National Register of Historic Places Inventory/Nomination: Mahone's Tavern|author=Harwood Paige Watkinson Jr., Simone A. Kiere|date=July 2007|publisher=Virginia Department of Historic Resources}}&lt;/ref&gt; As recounted by his biographer, Nelson Blake, the freckled-faced youth of [[Irish-American]] heritage gained a reputation in the small town for both &quot;gambling and a prolific use of tobacco and profanity.&quot;

Young Billy Mahone gained his primary education from a country schoolmaster but with special instruction in mathematics from his father. As a teenager, for a short time, he transported the [[U. S. Mail]] by horseback from his hometown to Hicksford, a small town on the south bank of the [[Meherrin River]] in [[Greensville County, Virginia|Greensville County]] which later combined with the town of Belfield on the north bank to form the current [[independent city]] of [[Emporia, Virginia|Emporia]]. He was awarded a spot as a state cadet at the recently opened [[Virginia Military Institute]] (VMI) in [[Lexington, Virginia]].&lt;ref&gt;Blake, p. 13&lt;/ref&gt; Studying under VMI Commandant [[William Gilham]] and a professor named [[Stonewall Jackson|Thomas J. Jackson]], he graduated with a degree as a [[civil engineer]] in the Class of 1847.

==Early career==
Mahone worked as a teacher at Rappahannock Academy in [[Caroline County, Virginia]], beginning in 1848, but was actively seeking an entry into civil engineering. He did some work helping locate the [[Orange and Alexandria Railroad]], an 88-mile line between [[Gordonsville, Virginia]], and the [[Alexandria, Virginia|City of Alexandria]].&lt;ref&gt;Blake, p. 19&lt;/ref&gt; Having performed well with the new railroad, was hired to build a [[plank road]] between [[Fredericksburg, Virginia|Fredericksburg]] and Gordonsville.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mahone, William 1826–1895&quot;&gt;{{cite web|url=http://encyclopediavirginia.org/Mahone_William_1826-1895 |title=Mahone, William (1826–1895) |publisher=Encyclopedia Virginia |date= |accessdate=2010-11-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Blake, p. 22&lt;/ref&gt;

On April 12, 1853, he was hired by Dr. [[Francis Mallory]] of [[Norfolk, Virginia|Norfolk]], as chief engineer to build the new [[Norfolk and Petersburg Railroad]] (N&amp;P).&lt;ref&gt;Blake, p.26&lt;/ref&gt; Mahone's innovative 12 mile-long roadbed through the [[Great Dismal Swamp]] between [[South Norfolk, Virginia|South Norfolk]] and [[Suffolk, Virginia|Suffolk]] employed a log foundation laid at right angles beneath the surface of the swamp. Still in use 150 years later, Mahone's [[corduroy road|corduroy]] design withstands immense tonnages of modern [[coal]] traffic. He was also responsible for engineering and building the famous 52 mile-long [[tangent]] track between [[Suffolk, Virginia|Suffolk]] and [[Petersburg, Virginia|Petersburg]]. With no curves, it is a major artery of modern [[Norfolk Southern]] rail traffic.

In 1854, Mahone surveyed and laid out with streets and lots of [[Ocean View, Virginia|Ocean View City]], a new resort town fronting on the [[Chesapeake Bay]] in [[Norfolk County, Virginia|Norfolk County]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Blake, p. 33&quot;&gt;Blake, p. 33&lt;/ref&gt; With the advent of electric [[streetcar]]s in the late 19th century, an [[amusement park]] was developed there and a [[boardwalk]] was built along the adjacent [[beach]] area. Most of Mahone's street plan is still in use in the 21st century as Ocean View, now a section of the City of Norfolk, is redeveloped.

He was surveyor for the Norfolk and South Air Line Railroad, on the [[Eastern Shore of Virginia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Blake, p. 33&quot;/&gt;

On February 8, 1855, Mahone married [[Otelia Butler Mahone|Otelia Butler]] (1835 – 1911), the daughter the late Dr. [[Robert Butler (Virginia politician)|Robert Butler]] from [[Smithfield, Virginia|Smithfield]], who had been State Treasurer of the [[Commonwealth of Virginia]] from 1846 until his death in 1853.&lt;ref&gt;Blake, p. 35&lt;/ref&gt; Her mother was Butler's second wife, Otelia Voinard Butler (1803–1855), originally from [[Petersburg, Virginia|Petersburg]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Mahone, William 1826–1895&quot;/&gt;

Young Otelia Butler is said to have been a cultured lady. She and William settled in Norfolk, where they lived for most of the years before the Civil War. They had 13 children, but only 3 survived to adulthood, two sons, [[William T. Mahone Jr.|William Jr.]] and [[Robert Butler Mahone|Robert]], and a daughter, also named [[Otelia M. McGill|Otelia]].  From 1862 to 1868, the family resided at [[Clarksville, Virginia]] at the [[Judge Henry Wood, Jr. House]].&lt;ref name=&quot;vaNRHPnom&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.dhr.virginia.gov/registers/Counties/Mecklenburg/192-0060_Judge_Henry_Wood_House_1999_Final_Nomination.pdf|title=National Register of Historic Places Inventory/Nomination: Judge Henry Wood, Jr. House|author= John G. Zehmer and Donald S. B. Hall| date=April 1999 |publisher=Virginia Department of Historic Resources}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Mahone family escaped the [[yellow fever]] epidemic that broke out in the summer of 1855 and killed almost a third of the populations of Norfolk and [[Portsmouth, Virginia|Portsmouth]] by staying with his mother some distance away in Jerusalem. However, as a consequence of the epidemic, the decimated citizenry of the Norfolk area had difficulty in meeting financial obligations, and work on their new railroad to Petersburg almost came to a standstill. Ever frugal, Mahone and his [[mentor]], Dr. Mallory, nevertheless pushed the project to completion.

Popular legend has it that Otelia and William Mahone traveled along the newly completed railroad naming stations from ''Ivanhoe'' and other books she was reading written by Sir [[Walter Scott]]. From his historical Scottish novels, she chose the place names of [[Windsor, Virginia|Windsor]], [[Waverly, Virginia|Waverly]], and [[Wakefield, Virginia|Wakefield]]. She tapped the Scottish Clan &quot;McIvor&quot; for the name of [[Ivor, Virginia|Ivor]], a small [[Southampton County, Virginia|Southampton County]] town. When they reached a location where they could not agree, it is said that the name [[Disputanta, Virginia|Disputanta]] was created. The Norfolk and Petersburg Railroad was completed in 1858, and Mahone was named its president a short time later.

According to some records, in 1860, Mahone owned 7 [[slavery|slaves]], all [[Black people|black]]: 3 male (ages 13, 4, 2), 4 female (ages 45, 24, 11, 1). Nevertheless, during the Civil War and after, he showed an empathy for former slaves that was atypical for the times, and worked diligently for their fair treatment and education.

==American Civil War==
[[File:william mahone 2.jpg|thumb|left|William Mahone]]
As the political differences between [[Northern United States|Northern]] and [[Southern United States|Southern]] factions escalated in the second half of the 19th century, Mahone was in favor of [[secession]] of the Southern states. During the [[American Civil War]], he was active in the actual conflict even before he became an officer in the Confederate Army. Early in the War, in 1861, his [[Norfolk and Petersburg Railroad]] was especially valuable to the Confederacy and transported ordnance to the Norfolk area where it was used during the Confederate occupation. By the end of the war, most of what was left of the railroad was in Federal hands.

After Virginia seceded from the Union in April 1861, Mahone was still a civilian, and not yet in the Confederate Army, but working in coordination with [[Walter Gwynn]], he orchestrated the ruse and capture of the [[Norfolk Naval Shipyard|Gosport Shipyard]]. He bluffed the Federal troops into abandoning the shipyard in Portsmouth by running a single passenger train into Norfolk with great noise and whistle-blowing, then much more quietly, sending it back west, and then returning the same train again, creating the illusion of large numbers of arriving troops to the Federals listening in Portsmouth across the [[Elizabeth River (Virginia)|Elizabeth River]] (and just barely out of sight). The [[Deception|ruse]] worked, and not a single Confederate soldier was lost as the Union authorities abandoned the area, and retreated to [[Fort Monroe]] across [[Hampton Roads]]. After this, Mahone accepted a commission as [[Lieutenant colonel (United States)|lieutenant colonel]] and later [[colonel]] of the [[6th Virginia Infantry|6th Virginia Volunteer Infantry Regiment]] in the Confederate Army. He commanded the Confederate's Norfolk district until its evacuation. He was promoted to [[Brigadier General (CSA)|brigadier general]] in November 1861.

In May 1862, after the evacuation of Norfolk by Southern forces during the [[Peninsula Campaign]], he aided in the construction of the defenses of Richmond on the [[James River (Virginia)|James River]] around [[Battle of Drewry's Bluff|Drewry's Bluff]].&lt;ref&gt;Blake, p.43&lt;/ref&gt; A short time later, he led his brigade at the [[Battle of Seven Pines]],&lt;ref&gt;Blake, p. 43&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Battle of Malvern Hill]]. He also fought at [[Second Battle of Bull Run|Second Bull Run]], [[Battle of Fredericksburg|Fredericksburg]], [[Battle of Chancellorsville|Chancellorsville]],&lt;ref&gt;Blake,p. 47&lt;/ref&gt; [[Battle of Gettysburg|Gettysburg]], the [[Battle of the Wilderness|Wilderness]], and [[Battle of Spotsylvania Court House|Spotsylvania Court House]].

Small of stature, 5 foot 5 or 6&amp;nbsp;inches, and weighing only 100&amp;nbsp;lb (45&amp;nbsp;kg), he was nicknamed &quot;Little Billy&quot;. As one of his soldiers put it, &quot;He was every inch a soldier, though there were not many inches of him.&quot; Otelia Mahone was working in Richmond as a [[nurse]], when Virginia Governor [[John Letcher]] sent word that Mahone had been injured at Second Bull Run, but had only received a &quot;flesh wound.&quot; She is said to have replied &quot;Now I know it is serious for William has no flesh whatsoever.&quot;

Although his wound at [[Manassas, Virginia|Manassas]] had not been serious, Mahone did suffer from acute [[dyspepsia]] all of his life. During the War, a cow and chickens accompanied him in order to provide dairy products. Otelia and their children moved to Petersburg to be near him during the final campaign of the War in 1864-65 as Grant moved against Petersburg, seeking to sever the rail lines supplying the Confederate capital of Richmond.

It was during that final campaign that William Mahone became widely regarded as the hero of the [[Battle of the Crater]] on July 30, 1864. During the [[Siege of Petersburg]] of 1864–65, former [[Pennsylvania]] coal miners in the Union Army tunneled under the Confederate line and blew it up in a massive explosion, killing and wounding many Confederates and breaching a key point in the defense line around Petersburg. But Mahone rallied the remaining Confederate forces nearby, repelling the attack, and the Union lost their initial advantage. Having begun as an innovative tactic, the Battle of the Crater turned into a terrible loss for the Union leaders. The quick and effective action led by Mahone was a rare cause for celebration by the occupants of Petersburg, embattled citizens and weary troops alike. &quot;Little Billy&quot; Mahone was promoted to [[Major General (CSA)|major general]] as a result.&lt;ref&gt;Blake, p. 55&lt;/ref&gt;

However, Grant's strategy at Petersburg eventually succeeded as the last rail line from the south to supply the Cockcade City (and hence Richmond) was severed in early April 1865. At the [[Battle of Sailor's Creek]] on April 6, [[Robert E. Lee|Lee]] exclaimed in front of Mahone &quot;My God, has the army dissolved?&quot;, to which he replied &quot;No, General, here are troops ready to do their duty.&quot; Touched by the faithful duty of his men, Lee told Mahone, &quot;Yes, there are still some true men left ... Will you please keep those people back?&quot;&lt;ref&gt;Freeman, vol. 3., p. 711.&lt;/ref&gt; Mahone was also with Lee at the surrender at [[Appomattox Court House National Historical Park|Appomattox Court House]] three days later.

==Return to railroading==
After the war, Lee advised his generals to go back to work rebuilding the Southern economy. William Mahone did just that, and became the driving force in the linkage of N&amp;P, [[Southside Railroad (Virginia)|South Side Railroad]], and the [[Virginia and Tennessee Railroad]]. He was president of all three by the end of 1867.&lt;ref&gt;Blake, p. 85&lt;/ref&gt; During the post-war [[Reconstruction era of the United States|Reconstruction]] period, he worked diligently lobbying the [[Virginia General Assembly]] to gain the legislation necessary to form the [[Atlantic, Mississippi &amp; Ohio Railroad]] (AM&amp;O), a new line comprising the three railroads he headed, extending 408 miles from Norfolk to [[Bristol, Virginia]], in 1870.&lt;ref&gt;Blake, p. 111&lt;/ref&gt;
This conflicted with the expansion of the [[Baltimore and Ohio Railroad]] from Baltimore.
The Mahones were colorful characters: the letters A, M &amp; O were said to stand for &quot;All Mine and Otelia's&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Mahone, William 1826–1895&quot;/&gt;
They lived in [[Lynchburg, Virginia]], during this time, but moved back to [[Petersburg, Virginia|Petersburg]] in 1872.

The [[Panic of 1873|Financial Panic of 1873]] put the A,M &amp; O into conflict with its bondholders in England and Scotland. After several years of operating under receiverships, Mahone's relationship with the creditors soured, and an alternate receiver, Henry Fink, was appointed to oversee the A,M &amp; O's finances. Mahone still worked to regain control, but his role as a railroad builder ended, in 1881, when Philadelphia-based interests outbid him and purchased the A,M &amp; O at auction, renaming it [[Norfolk and Western]] (N&amp;W).

Before the Civil War, the [[Virginia Board of Public Works]] had invested state funds in a substantial portion of the stock of the A,M &amp; O's predecessor railroads. Although he lost control of the railroad, as a major political leader in Virginia, Mahone was able to arrange for a portion of the State's proceeds of the sale to be directed to help found a school to prepare teachers to help educate black children and former slaves near his home at Petersburg, where he had earlier been mayor. The Virginia Normal and Collegiate Institute eventually expanded to become [[Virginia State University]]. He also directed another portion of the funds to help found the predecessor of today's [[Central State Hospital (Virginia)|Central State Hospital]] in [[Dinwiddie County, Virginia|Dinwiddie County]], also located adjacent to Petersburg. Mahone personally retained his ownership of land investments which were linked to the N&amp;W's development of the rich [[coal]] fields of western Virginia and southern [[West Virginia]], contributing to his rank as one of Virginia's wealthiest men at his death, according to his biographer, author Nelson Blake.

==Virginia politics: Readjuster Party, U.S. Senate==
[[File:William Mahone - Brady-Handy.jpg|thumb|upright|Mahone, after the war]]

William Mahone was active in the economic and political life of Virginia for almost 30 years, beginning in the midst of the Civil War when he was elected to the [[Virginia General Assembly]] as a Delegate from Norfolk in 1863. He later served as mayor of [[Petersburg, Virginia|Petersburg]]. After his unsuccessful bid for governor in 1877, he became the leader of the [[Readjuster Party]], a coalition of [[United States Democratic Party|Democrats]], [[Republican Party (United States)|Republicans]], and [[African-American]]s seeking a reduction in Virginia's prewar debt, and an appropriate allocation made to the former portion of the state that constituted the new [[West Virginia|State of West Virginia]].&lt;ref&gt;Blake, p. 154&lt;/ref&gt; In 1881, Mahone led the successful effort to elect the Readjuster candidate [[William E. Cameron]] as the next governor, and he himself as a [[United States Senator]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lva.virginia.gov/exhibits/political/william_mahone.htm |title=William Mahone |publisher=Lva.virginia.gov |date= |accessdate=2010-11-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At the Congressional level, with a 37–37 split between Republicans and Democrats in the Senate and with a second third-party candidate willing to caucus with the latter, Mahone's affiliation would determine which party would control the Senate, since under Senate rules, [[Vice President of the United States]] [[Chester A. Arthur]], a Republican, would cast any tie-breaking votes. Mahone's eventual decision to caucus with the Republicans came at a high price to them. Despite being a freshman senator, he received chairmanship of the influential Agriculture Committee and gained control over Virginia's federal patronage, both from President [[James A. Garfield]], and by the right to select both the Senate's Secretary and Sergeant at Arms.&lt;ref&gt;[http://bioguide.congress.gov/scripts/biodisplay.pl?index=M000067 MAHONE, William - Biographical Information]&lt;/ref&gt;

Once affiliated with the Republican Party, Mahone led Virginia delegations to the Republican National Conventions of 1884 and 1888. However, he lost his Senate seat to Conservative Democrat [[John W. Daniel]] in 1886.&lt;ref&gt;Blake, p. 235&lt;/ref&gt; In [[Virginia gubernatorial election, 1889|1889]], he ran for governor on a Republican ticket, but lost to Democrat [[Philip W. McKinney]]. It was to be 80 more years before Virginia sent another non-Democrat to the Governor's Mansion (Republican [[A. Linwood Holton Jr.]] in 1969). Although out of office, the seemingly tireless Mahone continued to stay involved in Virginia-related politics until he suffered a catastrophic [[stroke]] in [[Washington, D.C.]], in the fall of 1895. He died a week later, aged 68. His widow, Otelia, lived on in Petersburg until her own death in 1911.

Although Mahone was not to live to see the outcome, for several decades, Virginia and West Virginia disputed the new state's share of the Virginia government's debt. The issue was finally settled in 1915, when the [[United States Supreme Court]] ruled that West Virginia owed Virginia $12,393,929.50. The final installment of this sum was paid off in 1939.

==Legacy==
[[File:Mahone Mausoleum.jpg|thumb|Mahone mausoleum at Blandford Cemetery, identified by its &quot;M&quot; insignia]]

William Mahone was interred in the family mausoleum in [[Blandford Cemetery]] in [[Petersburg, Virginia]]. His widow, Otelia, lived until 1911, and was interred alongside him. The mausoleum is identified by the General's well known monogram, the initial &quot;M&quot; centered on a star inside a shield.

Otelia and William Mahone's first home in Petersburg, originally occupied by John Dodson, Petersburg's mayor in 1851-2, was on South Sycamore St. That structure now serves as part of the Petersburg Public Library. In 1874, they acquired and greatly enlarged a home on South Market St. and it was their primary residence thereafter. [[Virginia State University]], which he helped found as a [[normal school]], is a major community presence nearby.

A large portion of [[U.S. Highway 460]] in eastern Virginia (between [[Petersburg, Virginia|Petersburg]] and [[Suffolk, Virginia|Suffolk]]) parallels the 52-mile tangent railroad tracks that Mahone had engineered, passing through some of the towns he and Otelia are believed to have named. Several sections of the road are labeled &quot;General Mahone Boulevard&quot; and &quot;General Mahone Highway&quot; in his honor. The [[Virginia State Route 35|Route 35]] overpass of [[U.S. Route 58|Route 58]] in his native [[Southampton County, Virginia]] is named &quot;The General William Mahone Memorial Bridge&quot;.

A monument to Mahone's Brigade is located on the [[Gettysburg Battlefield]].

The site of the [[Battle of the Crater]] is a major feature of the [[National Park Service]]'s [[Petersburg National Battlefield Park]]. In 1927, the [[United Daughters of the Confederacy]] erected an imposing monument to his memory. It stands on the preserved Crater Battlefield, a short distance from the Crater itself. The monument states:

&lt;blockquote&gt;To the memory of William Mahone, Major General, CSA, a distinguished Confederate Commander, whose valor and strategy at the Battle of the Crater, July 30, 1864, won for himself and his gallant brigade undying fame.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==See also==
*[[List of American Civil War generals (Confederate)]]
{{portal bar|American Civil War|Biography|Politics}}

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==References==
* Blake, Nelson, ''William Mahone of Virginia: Soldier and Political Insurgent'' Garrett and Maisie, 1935.
*[[Clement A. Evans|Evans, Clement A.]], ''Confederate Military History, Vol. III'' (biography of William Mahone)', 1899.
* Sifakis, Stewart. ''Who Was Who in the Civil War.'' New York: Facts On File, 1988. ISBN 978-0-8160-1055-4.
* Striplin, E. F. Pat., ''The Norfolk &amp; Western: a history'' Norfolk and Western Railway Co., 1981, ISBN 0-9633254-6-9.
* [[Ezra J. Warner (historian)|Warner, Ezra J.]] ''Generals in Gray: Lives of the Confederate Commanders.'' Baton Rouge: Louisiana State University Press, 1959. ISBN 978-0-8071-0823-9.

==External links==
* [http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.gmd/g3701p.rr004910 Map of Norfolk &amp; Petersburg Rail Road, issued by William Mahone]
* [http://memory.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/r?ammem/ncpsbib:@field(DOCID+@lit(ABQ7578-0149-92_bib)):: ''The New Method of Voting''] by William Mahone, ''The North American review.'' Volume 149, Issue 397, December 1889.
* {{Find a Grave|8339|accessdate=2009-05-06}}
* [http://www.senate.gov/artandhistory/history/minute/Presidents_Death_Eases_Senate_Deadlock.htm Conversion from Readjuster to Republican]

{{s-start}}
{{s-par|us-sen}}
{{U.S. Senator box
| state=Virginia
| class=1
| before=[[Robert E. Withers]]
| after=[[John W. Daniel]]
| alongside=[[John W. Johnston]], [[Harrison H. Riddleberger]]
| years=March 4, 1881 – March 4, 1887}}
{{s-end}}
{{Gettysburg figures|state=collapsed}}
{{USSenVA}}
{{SenPublic WorksCommitteeChairmen}}
{{Third Party US Senators}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Mahone, William}}
[[Category:1826 births]]
[[Category:1895 deaths]]
[[Category:19th-century American railroad executives]]
[[Category:Confederate States Army major generals]]
[[Category:Mayors of places in Virginia]]
[[Category:Members of the Virginia House of Delegates]]
[[Category:People from Southampton County, Virginia]]
[[Category:People of Virginia in the American Civil War]]
[[Category:Readjuster Party United States Senators]]
[[Category:Republican Party United States Senators]]
[[Category:American slave owners]]
[[Category:United States Senators from Virginia]]
[[Category:Virginia Military Institute alumni]]
[[Category:Virginia Republicans]]</text>
      <sha1>k3wm60ohwfpo0t1zj5zlb3h0la2jmof</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
