<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Yakima War</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2634723</id>
    <revision>
      <id>747779686</id>
      <parentid>745910317</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-04T09:47:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bender the Bot</username>
        <id>28903366</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* Literature */http&amp;rarr;https for [[Google Books]] and [[Google News]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="35326">{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Yakama War
| partof      = the [[American Indian Wars]]
| image       = [[File:1855 U.S. Army artillery uniform.jpg|300px]]
| caption     = In a generic scene depicting a U.S. Army battery of light artillery in 1855, a first sergeant of the light artillery is shown in the left foreground in the new jacket issued for American mounted troops in 1854.
| date        = 1855-1858
| place       = [[Washington Territory]]
| coordinates = 
| map_type    = 
| map_relief  = 
| latitude    = 
| longitude   = 
| map_size    = 
| map_marksize = 
| map_caption = 
| map_label   = 
| territory   = 
| result      = United States victory
| status      = 
| combatants_header =
| combatant1  ={{flag|United States|1851}}&lt;br&gt;[[Snoqualmie tribe]]
| combatant2  = [[Yakama Nation|Yakama tribe]]&lt;br&gt;[[Walla Walla tribe]]&lt;br&gt;[[Umatilla tribe]]&lt;br&gt;[[Nez Perce tribe]]&lt;br&gt;[[Cayuse people|Cayuse tribe]]
| combatant3  = 
| commander1  = {{Flagicon|USA|1851}} [[Isaac Stevens]]&lt;br&gt;{{Flagicon|USA|1851}} [[Joel Palmer]]&lt;br&gt;{{Flagicon|USA|1851}} [[George Wright (general)|Colonel George Wright]]&lt;br&gt; [[Patkanim|Chief Patkanim]]
| commander2  = [[Chief Kamiakin]]&lt;br&gt;[[Leschi (Native American leader)|Chief Leschi]]&lt;br&gt;[[Kanasket|Chief Kanaskat]]
| commander3  = 
| units1      = [[9th Infantry Regiment (United States)|9th US Infantry]]&lt;br&gt;[[3rd Air Defense Artillery Regiment (United States)|3rd US Artillery]]&lt;br&gt;[[6th Infantry Regiment (United States)|6th US Infantry]]&lt;br&gt;[[4th Infantry Regiment (United States)|4th US Infantry]]&lt;br&gt;{{USS|Decatur|1839|6}}&lt;br&gt;Snoqualmie warriors&lt;Br&gt;Washington militia&lt;br&gt;Oregon militia
| units2      = Yakama warriors&lt;br&gt;Walla Walla warriors&lt;br&gt;Umatilla warriors&lt;br&gt;Nisqually warriors&lt;br&gt;Cayuse warriors
| units3      = 
| strength1   = 
| strength2   = 
| strength3   = 
| casualties1 = 
| casualties2 = 
| casualties3 = 
| notes       = 
| campaignbox = 
}}
{{Campaignbox Yakima War}}
The '''Yakima War''' (1855-1858) was a conflict between the [[United States]] and the [[Yakama]], a [[Sahaptian]]-speaking people of the Northwest Plateau, then part of [[Washington Territory]], and the tribal allies of each. It primarily took place in the southern interior of present-day [[Washington (state)|Washington]], with isolated battles in [[western Washington]] and the northern [[Inland Northwest (United States)|Inland Empire]] sometimes separately referred to as the [[Puget Sound War]] and the [[Palouse War]], respectively. This conflict is also referred to as the ''Yakima Native American War of 1855.''

== Background ==
Treaties between the [[United States]] and several Indian tribes in the [[Washington Territory]] resulted in reluctant tribal recognition of U.S. sovereignty over a vast amount of land in the [[Washington Territory]]. The tribes, in return for this recognition, were to receive [[United States v. Washington|half of the fish in the territory in perpetuity]], awards of money and provisions, and [[Indian reservation|reserved lands]] where white settlement would be prohibited.

While governor [[Isaac Stevens]] had guaranteed the inviolability of Native American territory following tribal accession to the treaties, he lacked the legal authority to enforce it pending ratification of the agreements by the [[United States Senate]]. Meanwhile, the widely-publicized discovery of gold in Yakama territory prompted an influx of unruly [[prospectors]] who traveled, unchecked, across the newly defined tribal lands, to the growing consternation of Indian leaders. In 1855 two of these prospectors were killed by Qualchin, the nephew of [[Chief Kamiakin|Kamiakin]], after it was discovered they'd raped a Yakama woman.&lt;ref name=&quot;CHRON&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Sonneborn |first=Liz |date=2009 |title=Chronology of American Indian History |url= |location= |publisher=Infobase |page=159 |isbn=9781438109848 |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Outbreak of hostilities ==

===Death of Andrew Bolon===
[[File:BIA Agent Andrew Bolon.jpg|thumb|left|The murder of BIA agent Andrew Bolon is considered an immediate cause of the war.]]
On September 20, 1855, [[Bureau of Indian Affairs]] agent [[Andrew Bolon]], hearing of the death of the prospectors at the hands of Qualchin, departed for the scene on horseback to investigate but was intercepted by the Yakama chief Shumaway who warned him Qualchin was too dangerous to confront. Heeding Shumaway's warning, Bolon turned back and began the ride home. En route he came upon a group of Yakama traveling south and decided to ride along with them. One of the members of this group was Mosheel, Shumaway's son.&lt;ref name=&quot;HL&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://historylink.org/index.cfm?DisplayPage=output.cfm&amp;file_id=8118 |title=Yakama tribesmen slay Indian Subagent Andrew J. Bolon near Toppenish Creek on September 23, 1855 |last1=Wilma |first1=David |last2= |first2= |date=2007 |website=historylink.org |publisher=History Ink |accessdate=17 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; Mosheel decided to kill Bolon for reasons that are not entirely clear. Though a number of Yakama in the traveling party protested, their objections were overruled by Mosheel who invoked his regal status. Discussions about Bolon's fate took place over much of the day (Bolon, who did not speak Yakama, was unaware of the conspiracy unfolding among his traveling companions). During a rest stop, as Bolon and the Yakama were eating lunch, Mosheel and at least three other Yakama set upon him with knives. Bolon yelled out in a [[Chinookan languages|Chinook dialect]], &quot;I did not come to fight you!&quot; before being stabbed in the throat.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://washingtonhistoryonline.org/leschi/prelude/bolon-murder.htm |title= The Murder of A. J. Bolon |last1= |first1= |last2= |first2= |date= |website=washingtonhistoryonline.org |publisher=Washington State History Museum |accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; Bolon's horse was then shot, and his body and personal effects burned.&lt;ref name=&quot;OH&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last= |first= |date=1918 |title=Oregon Historical Quarterly, volume 19 |url= |location= |publisher=W.H. Leeds, State Printer |page=341 |isbn= |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Battle of Toppenish Creek===
When Shumaway heard of Bolon's death he immediately sent an ambassador to inform the U.S. Army garrison at Fort Dalles, before calling for the arrest of his son, Mosheel, who he said should be turned-over to the territorial government to forestall the American retaliation he felt would likely occur. A Yakama council overruled the chief, however, siding with Shumaway's older brother, Kamiakin, who called for war preparations. Meanwhile, district commander [[Gabriel Rains]] had received Shumaway's ambassador and, in response to the news of Bolon's death, ordered Major Granville O. Haller to move out with an expeditionary column from Fort Dalles. Haller's force, was met and turned-back at the edge of Yakama territory by a large group of Yakama warriors. As Haller withdrew, his company was engaged and routed by the Yakama at the [[Battle of Toppenish Creek]].&lt;ref name=&quot;becker&quot;/&gt;

==War spreads==

The death of Bolon, and the United States defeat at Toppenish Creek, caused panic across the territory with fears that an Indian uprising was in progress. 

The same news, however, emboldened the Yakama and uncommitted bands rallied to Kamiakin.

Rains, who had just 350 federal troops under his immediate command, urgently appealed to Acting Governor [[Charles Mason]] (Isaac Stevens was still returning from [[Washington, D.C.]] where he had traveled to present the treaties to the Senate for ratification) for military aid, writing that,&lt;Ref name=&quot;NGHISTORY&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last= |first= |date= |title=THE OFFICIAL HISTORY OF THE WASHINGTON NATIONAL GUARD VOLUME 2 WASHINGTON TERRITORIAL MILITIA IN THE INDIAN WARS OF 1855-56  |url=http://washingtonguard.org/museum/documents/FIELDS_VOL_II.pdf |location= |publisher=Washington Department of Military Affairs |page=2 |isbn= |accessdate=24 May 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt; 

{{cquote|&quot;...  all the disposable force in the district will at once take the field, and I have the honor to make a requisition upon you for two companies of volunteers to take the field the earliest possible moment. The composition of these companies to be as follows: One Captain, one First Lieutenant and one Second Lieutenant, two musicians, four Sergeants, four Corporals and seventy four privates. The greatest exertions should be made to raise and equip these companies at once.}}

Meanwhile, Oregon Governor [[George Law Curry]] mobilized a cavalry regiment of 800 men, a portion of which crossed into Washington territory in early November.&lt;ref name=Utley&gt;{{cite book |last=Utley |first=Robert |date=1991 |title=Frontiersmen in Blue: The United States Army and the Indian, 1848-1865 |url= |location= |publisher=University of Nebraska Press |pages=189–191 |isbn=0803295502 |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Now with more than 700 troops at his disposal, Rains prepared to march on Kamiakin who had encamped at [[Union Gap]] with 300 warriors.&lt;ref name=&quot;becker&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.historylink.org/index.cfm?DisplayPage=output.cfm&amp;file_id=5311 |title=Yakama Indian War begins on October 5, 1855 |last1=Becker |first1=Paula |last2= |first2= |date= |website=historylink.org |publisher=History Ink|accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Raid on the White River Settlements ===
[[File:Connell's Prairie Marker.jpg|thumb|right|Marker at the site of the ambush of McAllister and Connell, photographed in 2005.]]
As Rains was mustering his forces, in [[Pierce County, Washington|Pierce County]] [[Chief Leschi|Leschi]], a Nisqually chief who was half Yakama, had sought to forge an alliance among the Puget Sound tribes to bring war to the doorstep of the territorial government. Starting with just the 31 warriors in his own band, Leschi rallied more than 150 Muckleshoot, Puyallup and Klickitat, though other tribes rebuffed Leschi's overtures. In response to news of Leschi's growing army, a volunteer troop of 18 [[dragoon]]s, known as Eaton's Rangers, was dispatched to arrest the Nisqually chief.&lt;ref name=&quot;pioneer&quot;/&gt;

On October 27, while surveying an area of the [[White River (Washington)|White River]], ranger James McAllister and farmer Michael Connell, were ambushed and killed by Leschi's men. The rest of Eaton's Rangers were besieged inside an abandoned cabin, where they would remain for the next four days before escaping. The next morning, Muckleshoot, and Klickitat warriors raided three settler cabins along the White River, killing nine men and women. Many settlers had left the area in advance of the raid, having been warned of danger by [[Chief Kitsap]] of the neutral [[Suquamish]]. Details of the raid on the White River settlements were told by one of the four survivors, John King, who was seven years old at the time and was - along with two younger siblings - spared by the attackers and told to head west. The King children eventually came upon a local Native American known to them as Tom.&lt;ref name=&quot;pioneer&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Meeker |first=Ezra |date=1903 |title=Pioneer Reminisences of Puget Sound |url= |location= |publisher=Lowman and Hanford |pages=289–303 |isbn= |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

{{cquote|&quot;I told him of the massacre.  He said he suspected something of the kind, as he had heard firing in that direction.  He told me that I should get the children and take them to his wigwam, adding that 'when the moon was high' he would take us to Seattle in his canoe.  His squaw was as kind and amiable as could be, and did all in her power to make it pleasant for us, but the children were very shy.  She set out dried fish and whortleberries for our repast, but nothing she could do would induce them to go to her.  Our hunger was so great that the various and penetrating odors permeating the food she had brought us was no bar to our relish for it as I remember.&quot;}}

Leschi would later express regret for the raid on the White River settlements and post-war accounts given by Nisqually in his band affirmed that the chief had rebuked his commanders who had organized the attack.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.narhist.ewu.edu/pnf/articles/s1/i-1/leschi/leschi.html |title=Washington Biography: Leschi, Last Chief of the Nisquallies |last1=Carpenter |first1=Cecilia |last2= |first2= |date=1976 |website=narhist.ewu.edu |publisher=[[Eastern Washington University]] |accessdate=23 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Battle of White River ===

Army Captain Maurice Maloney, in command of a reinforced company of 243 men, had previously been sent east to cross the Naches Pass and enter the Yakama homeland from the rear. Finding the pass blocked with snow he began returning west in the days following the raid on the White River settlements. On November 2, 1855 Leschi's men were spotted by the vanguard of Maloney's returning column, and fell back to the right bank of the White River.&lt;ref name=&quot;pioneer&quot;/&gt;
[[File:Tyee Dick 1814-1904.jpg|thumb|left|Tyee Dick, pictured here later in life, was one of Leschi's soldiers at the Battle of White River. After the war he would rise to the chiefdom of the Puyallup.]]
On November 3 Maloney ordered a force of 100 men under Lt. William Slaughter to cross the White River and engage Leschi's forces. Attempts to ford the river, however, were stopped by the fire of Indian sharpshooters. One American soldier was killed in a back-and-forth exchange of gunfire. Accounts of Indian fatalities range from one (reported by a Puyallup Indian, Tyee Dick, after the end of the war) to 30 (claimed in Slaughter's official report), though the lower number may be more credible (one veteran of the battle, Daniel Mounts, would later be appointed Indian agent to the Nisqually and heard Tyee Dick's casualty numbers confirmed by Nisqually). At four o'clock, when it was becoming too dark for the Americans to cross the White River, Leschi's men fell back three miles to their camp on the banks of the [[Green River (Duwamish River)|Green River]], jubilant at having successfully prevented the American crossing (Tyee Dick would later describe the battle as ''hi-ue he-he, hi-ue he-he'' - &quot;lots and lots of fun&quot;).&lt;ref name=&quot;pioneer&quot;/&gt;

The next morning Maloney advanced with 150 men across the White River and attempted to engage Leschi at his camp at the Green River, but poor terrain made the advance untenable and he quickly called off the attack. Another skirmish on November 5 resulted in five American fatalities, but no Indian deaths. Unable to make any headway, Maloney began his withdrawal from the area on November 7, arriving at Fort Steilacoom two days later.&lt;ref name=&quot;pioneer&quot;/&gt;

=== Battle of Union Gap ===

One hundred fifty miles to the east, on November 9, Rains closed with Kamiakin near [[Battle of Union Gap|Union Gap]].&lt;ref name=Becker&gt;{{cite web | url=http://www.historylink.org/index.cfm?DisplayPage=output.cfm&amp;file_id=5285 | title=HistoryLink.org Essay 5285, St. Joseph's Mission on Ahtanum Creek | author=Becker, Paula | date=February 23, 2003 | accessdate=June 19, 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Yakama had erected a defensive barrier of stone breastwork which was quickly blown away by American artillery fire. Kamiakan had not expected a force of the size Rains had mustered and the Yakama, anticipating a quick victory of the kind they had recently scored at Toppenish Creek, had brought their families. Kamiakan now ordered the women and children to flee as he and the warriors fought a delaying action. While leading a reconnaissance of the American lines, Kamiakan and a group of fifty mounted warriors encountered an American patrol which gave chase. Kamiakan and his men escaped across the Yakima River; the Americans were unable to keep up and two soldiers drowned before the pursuit was called off. 
[[File:Cutmouth John.png|thumb|right|Cutmouth John, a U.S. Army Indian scout, is believed to have inflicted the only fatality on the Yakama at Union Gap.]]
That evening Kamiakan called a war council where it was decided the Yakama would make a stand in the hills of Union Gap. Rains began advancing on the hills the next morning, his progress slowed by small groups of Yakama employing [[hit and run tactics]] to delay the American advance against the main Yakama force. At four o'clock in the afternoon Maj. Haller, backed by a howitzer bombardment, led a charge against the Yakama position. Kamiakan's forces scattered into the brush at the mouth of Ahtanum Creek and the American offensive was called off.&lt;ref name=&quot;kamiakan&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Splawn |first=A.J. |date=1917 |title=Ka-mi-akin, the Last Hero of the Yakimas |url= |location= |publisher=Kilham Stationery &amp; Printing Company |pages=39–51 |isbn= |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

In Kamiakan's camp, plans for a night raid against the American force were drawn up but abandoned. Instead, early the next day, the Yakama continued their defensive retreat, tiring American forces who eventually broke off the engagement. In the last day of fighting the Yakama suffered their only fatality, a warrior killed by U.S. Army Indian Scout [[Cutmouth John]].&lt;ref name=&quot;kamiakan&quot;/&gt;

Rains continued to Saint Joseph's Mission which had been abandoned, the priests having joined the Yakama in flight. During a search of the grounds, Rains men discovered a barrel of gunpowder, leading them to erroneously believe the priests had been secretly arming the Yakama. A riot among the soldiers ensued and the mission was burned to the ground. With snow beginning to fall, Rains ordered a withdrawal, and the column returned to Fort Dalles.&lt;ref name=&quot;Utley&quot;/&gt;

===Skirmish at Brannan's Prairie===
By the end of November, federal troops had returned to the White River area. A detachment of the 4th Infantry Regiment, under Lt. Slaughter, accompanied by militia under Capt. Gilmore Hays, searched the area from which Maloney had previously withdrawn and engaged Nisqually and Klickitat warriors at Biting's Prairie on November 25, 1855, resulting in several casualties but no decisive outcome. The next day an Indian sharpshooter killed two of Slaughter's troops. Finally, on December 3, as Slaughter and his men were camped for the night on Brannan's Prairie, the force was fired upon and Slaughter killed. News of the death of Slaughter greatly demoralized settlers in the principal towns. Slaughter and his wife were a popular young couple among the settlers and the legislature adjourned for a day of mourning.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://washingtonhistoryonline.org/leschi/slaughter.htm |title=Lieutenant William Alloway Slaughter |last1= |first1= |last2= |first2= |date= |website=washingtonhistoryonline.org |publisher=Washington Historical Society |accessdate=23 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Governor.Gen.Stevens.jpg|thumb|left|Washington governor Isaac Stevens, pictured here in 1862, was joined by Oregon governor John Curry in calling for the dismissal of Gen. Wool.]]

===Conflict of command===

In late November 1855 Gen. [[John E. Wool]] arrived from [[California]] and assumed control of the [[United States]] side in the conflict, making his headquarters at [[Fort Vancouver]]. Wool was widely considered pompous and arrogant and had been criticized by some for blaming much of the western conflicts between Natives and whites on whites. After assessing the situation in Washington, he decided that Rains' approach of chasing bands of Yakama around the territory would lead to an inevitable defeat. Wool planned to wage a static war by using the territorial militia to fortify the major settlements while better trained and equipped U.S. Army regulars moved-in to occupy traditional Indian hunting and fishing grounds, starving the Yakama into surrender.&lt;ref name=&quot;wool&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://washingtonhistoryonline.org/leschi/wool.htm |title=General John Wool |last1= |first1= |last2= |first2= |date= |website=washingtonhistoryonline.org |publisher=Washington State Historical Society |accessdate=23 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

To Wool's chagrin, however, Oregon Governor Curry decided to launch a preemptive and largely unprovoked attack against the eastern tribes of the [[Walla Walla tribe|Walla Walla]], Palouse, [[Umatilla tribe|Umatilla]], and Cayuse who had, up to that point, remained cautiously neutral in the conflict (Curry believed it was only a matter of time before the eastern tribes entered the war and sought to gain a strategic advantage by attacking first). Oregon militia, under Lt. Col. James Kelley, crossed into the [[Walla Walla Valley]] in December, skirmishing with the tribes and, eventually, capturing Peomoxmox and several other chiefs. The eastern tribes were now firmly involved in the conflict, a state-of-affairs Wool blamed squarely on Curry. In a letter to a friend, Wool commented that,&lt;ref name=&quot;wool&quot;/&gt;

{{cquote|&quot;But for the ... barbarous determination of the Oregonians to extermin[ate] its Indians, I would soon put an end to the Indian War. It is these shocking barbarities that gives us more trouble than all else and is constantly increasing the ranks of the hostiles.&quot;}} 
Meanwhile, on December 20, Washington Governor Isaac Stevens had finally made it back to the territory after a perilous journey that involved a final, mad dash across the hostile Walla Walla Valley. Dissatisfied with Wool's plan to wait until spring before resuming military operations, and having learned of the raid on the White River settlement, Stevens convened the Washington Legislature where he declared &quot;the war shall be prosecuted until the last hostile Indian is exterminated.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Kluger |first=Richard |date= |title=The Bitter Waters of Medicine Creek: A Tragic Clash Between White and Native America  |url= |location= |publisher=Vintage |page=167 |isbn=0307388964 |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Stevens was further perturbed at the lack of a military escort afforded him during his dangerous passage through Walla Walla and went on to denounce Wool for &quot;the criminal neglect of my safety.&quot; Oregon Governor Curry joined his Washington counterpart in demanding Wool's dismissal. (The matter came to a head in the fall of 1856 and Wool was reassigned by the Army to command of the Eastern Department.)

== 1856 ==

=== Battle of Seattle ===
[[File:&quot;Battle of Seattle&quot; (painting).jpg|thumb|right|300px|Seattleites evacuate to the town blockhouse as {{USS|Decatur|1839|6}} opens fire on advancing tribal forces.]]
{{main article|Battle of Seattle (1856)}}
In late January 1856, Stevens arrived in Seattle aboard the ''[[USCS Active]]'' to reassure citizens of the town. Stevens confidently declared that, &quot;I believe that [[New York City|New York]] and [[San Francisco]] will as soon be attacked by the Indians as the town of Seattle.&quot; Even as Stevens' was speaking, however, a 6,000-man tribal army was moving on the unsuspecting settlement. As the governor's ship was sailing from the harbor - carrying Stevens back to Olympia - members of some of the Puget Sound's neutral tribes began streaming into Seattle requesting sanctuary from a large Yakama war party that had just crossed [[Lake Washington]]. The threat was confirmed with the arrival of [[Princess Angeline]] who brought news from her father, [[Chief Seattle]], that an attack was imminent. [[Doc Maynard]] began the evacuation of women and children from the neutral Duwamish, by boat, to the west side of Puget Sound while a group of citizen volunteers, led by the [[United States Marine Corps|marine detachment]] of the nearby-anchored {{USS|Decatur|1839|6}}, started construction on a [[blockhouse]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.history.navy.mil/library/online/decatur_sloop.htm |title=Reminiscences of Seattle Washington Territory and the U. S. Sloop-of-War Decatur During the Indian War of 1855-56 |last1= |first1= |last2= |first2= |date= |website=history.navy.mil |publisher=U.S. Navy |accessdate=23 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On the evening of January 24, 1856, two scouts from the massing tribal forces, dressed in disguise and talking their way past American sentries, covertly entered Seattle on a reconnaissance mission (some believe one of these scouts may have been Leschi himself).&lt;ref name=&quot;batsea&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Newell |first=Gordon |date=1956 |title=Totem Tales of Old Seattle. |url= |location= |publisher=Superior |pages=21–26 |isbn= |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Just after sunrise on January 25, 1856, American lookouts spotted a large group of Indians approaching the settlement under cover of trees. The {{USS|Decatur|1839|6}} began firing into the woods, prompting townspeople to evacuate to the blockhouse. Tribal forces - by some accounts composed of [[Yakama]], [[Walla Walla people|Walla Walla]], [[Klickitat (tribe)|Klickitat]] and [[Puyallup (tribe)|Puyallup]] - returned fire with small arms and began a fast advance on the settlement. Faced with unrelenting fire from ''Decatur'''s guns, however, the attackers were forced to withdraw and regroup, after which a decision was made to abandon the assault. Two Americans were killed in the fighting and 28 Natives lost their lives.&lt;ref name=&quot;batsea&quot;/&gt;

=== Snoqualmie operations ===

With a view to block the passes across the Cascade Mountains and prevent further Yakama movements against [[western Washington]], a small redoubt was established at [[Snoqualmie Pass]] in February 1856. Fort Tilton became operational in March 1856, consisting of a blockhouse and several storehouses. The fort was manned by a small contingent of Volunteers supported by a 100-man force of [[Snoqualmie tribe|Snoqualmie]] warriors, fulfillment of an agreement made by the powerful Snoqualmie chief Patkanim with the government the previous November.
[[File:Patkanim - Snoqualmie chief.jpg|thumb|Snoqualmie chief Patkanim led a raid on Leschi's camp in winter of 1856 but the elusive Nisqually chief avoided capture.]] 
Meanwhile, Leschi, having successfully repelled and evaded the previous American attempts to defeat his forces along the White River, now faced a third wave of attack. As construction on Fort Tilton got underway, Patkanim - brevetted to the rank of captain in the Volunteers - set out at the head of a force of 55 Snoqualmie and Snohomish warriors intent on capturing Leschi. Their mission was triumphantly announced by a headline in Olympia's ''Pioneer and Democrat''  &quot;Pat Kanim in the Field!&quot;

Patkanim tracked Leschi to his camp along the White River, but a planned night raid was aborted after a barking dog alerted sentries. Instead, Patkanim approached to within speaking distance of Leschi's camp, announcing to the Nisqually chief, &quot;I will have your head.&quot; Early the next morning Patkanim began his assault, the bloody fight reportedly lasting ten hours, ending only after the Snoqualmie ran out of ammunition. [[Edmond Meany]] would later write that Patkanim returned with &quot;gruesome evidences of his battles in the form of heads taken from the bodies of slain hostile Indians.&quot; Leschi's, however, was not among them.

=== Martial Law declared ===

By spring of 1856 Stevens began to suspect that some settlers in Pierce County, who had married into area tribes, were secretly conspiring with their Native American in-laws against the territorial government.&lt;ref name=&quot;bulwark&quot;&gt;{{cite book |last=Rowe |first=Mary Ellen |date=2003 |title=Bulwark of the Republic: The American Militia in Antebellum West |url= |location= |publisher=Greenwood |pages=177–178 |isbn=0313324107 |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt; Stevens' distrust of the Pierce County settlers may have been heightened by the strong [[Whig Party (United States)|Whig Party]] sentiment in the county and opposition to [[Democratic Party of the United States|Democratic]] policies. Stevens ordered the suspect farmers arrested and held at Camp Montgomery. When Judge Edward Lander ordered their release, Stevens declared [[martial law]] in Pierce and Thurston counties. On May 12 Lander ruled that Stevens was in [[contempt of court]]. Marshals sent to Olympia to detain the governor were ejected from the capitol and Stevens ordered Judge Lander's arrest by militia.&lt;ref name=&quot;martial&quot;&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.historylink.org/index.cfm?DisplayPage=output.cfm&amp;file_id=5130 |title=Governor Isaac Stevens ejects Judge Edward Lander from his court under martial law on May 12, 1856 |last1=Wilma |first1=David |last2= |first2= |date= |website=historylink.org |publisher=History Ink |accessdate=23 May 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Pierce County Martial Law decree.jpg|thumb|left]]
Learning of Lander's detention, [[Francis A. Chenoweth]], the chief justice of the territorial supreme court, left [[Whidbey Island]] - where he was recuperating from illness - and traveled by [[canoe]] to Pierce County. Arriving in Steilacoom, Chenoweth reconvened the court and prepared to again issue writs of [[habeas corpus]] ordering the release of the settlers. Learning of Chenoweth's arrival in Pierce County, Stevens sent a company of militia to stop the chief justice, but the troops were met by the [[Pierce County Sheriff's Office|Pierce County Sheriff]] whom Chenoweth had ordered to raise a [[Posse comitatus (common law)|posse]] to defend the court. The impasse was finally resolved after Stevens agreed to back down and release the farmers.&lt;ref name=&quot;martial&quot;/&gt;

Stevens subsequently pardoned himself of contempt, but the [[United States Senate]] called for his removal over the incident and he was censured by the [[Secretary of State of the United States]] who wrote to him that &quot;... your conduct, in that respect, does not therefore meet with the favorable regard of the President.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;martial&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Dennis |last=Clay |authorlink= |coauthors= |title= Concluding Soap Lake by Knapp; continuing Irrigation Project by Weber  |url=http://www.columbiabasinherald.com/community/bitsandpieces/article_c0fee42e-95cb-11e3-bc90-001a4bcf887a.html |work=Columbia Basin Herald |publisher= |date=15 February 2014 |accessdate=23 May 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== The Cascades Massacre ===

The Cascades Massacre on March 26, 1856 was an attack by a coalition of tribes against white immigrants in the [[Cascades Rapids]]. The native attackers included warriors from the Yakama, [[Klickitat tribe|Klickitat]], and so called ''Cascades tribes'' (today identified as belonging to [[Wasco-Wishram|Wasco tribes]]: ''Cascades Indians / Watlala'' or ''Hood River Wasco''). Fourteen settlers and three US soldiers died in the attack, the most losses for US citizens during the Yakima War. The United States sent reinforcements the following day to defend against further attackers and bring the murderers to justice. The Yakima people evaded prosecution, but nine Cascades Indians, including Chenoweth, Chief of the Hood River Band, were charged and executed for treason.&lt;ref name=historylink&gt;{{cite web|publisher=HistoryLink.org|title=Native Americans attack Americans at the Cascades of the Columbia on March 26, 1856|url=http://www.historylink.org/essays/output.cfm?file_id=5190}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Puget Sound War===
The U.S. Army arrived in the region in the summer of 1856. That August [[Robert S. Garnett]] supervised the construction of [[Fort Simcoe]] as a military post. Initially the conflict was limited to the Yakama, but eventually the Walla Walla and Cayuse were drawn into the war, and carried out a number of raids and battles against the American invaders.&lt;!--Bill Seidel says Yakamas attacked Seattle, but it seems a long way to go ... the Battle of Seattle doesn't seem well documented from the Indian side ... although from Stevens' POV it may all be one long campaign of suppressing various insurgents ... rewinn--&gt;Perhaps the best known of these raids culminated in the [[Battle of Seattle (1856)|Battle of Seattle]], in which an unknown number of raiders briefly crossed the Cascade Range to engage settlers, Marines and the U.S. Navy before retiring.

===Coeur d'Alene War===
The last phase of the conflict, sometimes referred to as the [[Coeur d'Alene War]], occurred in 1858.  General [[Newman S. Clarke]] commanded the [[Department of the Pacific]] and sent a force under Col. [[George Wright (general)|George Wright]] to deal with the recent fighting.  At the [[Battle of Four Lakes]] near [[Spokane, Washington]] in September 1858, Wright inflicted a decisive defeat on the Native Americans. He called a council of all the local Native Americans at Latah Creek (southwest of Spokane). On September 23 he imposed a peace treaty, under which most of the tribes were to go to reservations.

== Aftermath ==
As the war wound to a close, [[Chief Kamiakin|Kamiakin]] fled north to [[British Columbia]]. Leschi was twice tried for murder by the territorial government (his first trial resulted in a [[hung jury]]), convicted the second time, and then hanged outside Fort Steilacoom, the U.S. Army having refused to allow his execution to occur on Army property as military commanders considered him a [[lawful combatant]]. (In 2004 a Historical Court, convened by the State of Washington, conceded the Army's opinion and posthumously acquitted Leschi of murder.)

U.S. Army Indian Scouts tracked and captured Andrew Bolon's murderers who were subsequently hanged.

Snoqualmie warriors were sent to hunt-down remnant hostile forces, with the territorial government agreeing to pay a bounty on scalps, however, the practice was quickly terminated by orders of the territorial auditor after questions arose as to whether the Snoqualmie were actually engaging remnant hostiles, or executing their own slaves.

The Yakama people were forced onto a reservation south of the present city of [[Yakima, Washington|Yakima]].

== See also ==
*[[Bannock War]]
*[[Cayuse War]]
*[[Fort Dalles]]
*[[Fraser Canyon War]]
*[[Nez Perce War]]
*[[Okanagan Trail]]
*[[Rogue River War]]
*[[Spokane-Coeur d'Alene-Paloos War]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== Literature ==
* [https://books.google.com/books?id=sOkNAAAAIAAJ&amp;vq=Keyes&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s  Hubert H. Bancroft, ''History Of Washington, Idaho, and Montana, 1845-1889''] San Francisco: The History Company, 1890. Chapter VI: Indian Wars 1855-1856, and V :Indian Wars 1856-1858
* Ray Hoard Glassley: ''Indian Wars of the Pacific Northwest'', Binfords &amp; Mort, Portland, Oregon 1972 ISBN 0-8323-0014-4

== External links ==
* [http://www.historylink.org/essays/output.cfm?file_id=5311 &quot;Yakama (Yakima) Indian War begins on October 5, 1855&quot;], HistoryLink.org Essay 5311]
* [http://www.historylink.org/essays/output.cfm?file_id=8124 &quot;Major Gabriel Rains and 700 soldiers and volunteers skirmish with Yakama warriors under Kamiakin at Union Gap on November 9, 1855&quot;], HistoryLink.org Essay 8124]
* [http://www.historylink.org/essays/output.cfm?file_id=8118 &quot;Yakama tribesmen slay Indian Subagent Andrew J. Bolon near Toppenish Creek on September 23, 1855&quot;], HistoryLink.org Essay 8118]
* [http://nwda-db.wsulibs.wsu.edu/findaid/ark:/80444/xv85849 &quot;Guide to the Yakima War (1856-1858)&quot;], Washington State University Library

[[Category:Conflicts in 1855]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1856]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1857]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1858]]
[[Category:1855 in the United States]]
[[Category:Wars between the United States and Native Americans]]
[[Category:Native American history of Washington (state)]]
[[Category:History of Washington (state)]]
[[Category:Indian wars of the American Old West]]
[[Category:1856 in the United States]]
[[Category:1857 in the United States]]
[[Category:1858 in the United States]]</text>
      <sha1>lpaxv5mewts9b2xi0rv9znhb4k4ua07</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
