<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>HMS Arrow (1796)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>34767458</id>
    <revision>
      <id>730976138</id>
      <parentid>709116417</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-07-22T02:44:19Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Acad Ronin</username>
        <id>70274</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* French Revolutionary Wars */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="29533">{{other ships|HMS Arrow}}
{|{{Infobox ship begin}}
{{Infobox ship image
| Ship image=[[File:Arrow and Acheron against Hortense and Incorruptible.jpg|360px]]
| Ship caption=Action of HMS ''Arrow'' and ''Acheron'' against the French frigates ''Hortense'' and ''Incorruptible'': Beginning of the action, 4 February 1805, by Francis Sartorious Jr., [[National Maritime Museum]], Greenwich. Left to right: ''Acheron'', ''Hortense'', ''Arrow'', and ''Incorruptible'' 
}}
{{Infobox ship career
| Hide header=
| Ship country=[[United Kingdom]]
| Ship flag=[[File:Naval Ensign of the United Kingdom.svg|60px|Royal Navy Ensign]]
| Ship name=HMS ''Arrow''
| Ship owner=
| Ship ordered=
| Ship builder= Hobbs &amp; Hellyer at Redbridge
| Ship original cost=
| Ship laid down=
| Ship launched=
| Ship acquired=
| Ship commissioned=1796
| Ship decommissioned=1805
| Ship in service=
| Ship out of service=
| Ship renamed=
| Ship struck=
| Ship reinstated=
| Ship honours=
| Ship honors=*[[Naval General Service Medal (1847)|Naval General Service Medal]] with clasps
*&quot;Arrow 13 Sept 1799&quot;&lt;ref name=LG20939&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=20939|startpage=239|date=26 January 1849}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*&quot;Copenhagen&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=20939|startpage=240|date=26 January 1849}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*&quot;Arrow 3 Feby. 1805&quot;&lt;ref name=LG20939/&gt;
| Ship captured=4 Feb 1805
| Ship fate=Sank after capture
| Ship status=
| Ship notes=
}}
{{Infobox ship characteristics
| Hide header=
| Header caption=&lt;ref name=Winfield&gt;Winfield (2008), p. 384.&lt;/ref&gt;
| Ship class=
| Ship tons burthen=386 {{small|{{frac|16|94}}}} ([[Builder's Old Measurement|bm]])
| Ship length={{convert|128|ft|8|in|m|abbr=on}} (overall); {{convert|80|ft|8|in|m|abbr=on}} (keel)
| Ship beam={{convert|30|ft|m|abbr=on}}
| Ship draught=
| Ship draft=
| Ship hold depth= {{convert|7|ft|11|in|m|abbr=on}}
| Ship propulsion=
| Ship sail plan=Sloop
| Ship complement= 121 (later 140)
| Ship armament=*'''Initially''':
*Upper deck (UD): 24 x 32-pounder [[carronade]]s
*[[Quarterdeck|QD]]: 2 x 32-pounder carronades with two more being added later
*[[Forecastle|Fc]]: 2 x 32-pounder carronades
*'''Later''':
*UD: 18 x 32-pounder carronades
*QD: nil
*Fc: 2 x 6-pounder [[chase gun]]s
*Note: All the carronades were experimental 24cwt carronades
| Ship notes=
}}
|}

{{HMS|Arrow|1796|6}} was a sloop in the [[Royal Navy]] that the Admiralty purchased in 1796. during the [[French Revolutionary Wars]] she participated in many actions, including one that resulted in her crew qualifying for the Naval General Service Medal. On 3 February 1805 she and {{HMS|Acheron|1803|2}} were escorting a convoy from Malta to England when they encountered two [[French Navy|French]] frigates. ''Arrow'' and ''Acheron'' were able to save the majority of the vessels of the convoy by their resistance before they were compelled to [[striking the colours|strike]]. ''Arrow'' sank almost immediately after surrendering, and ''Acheron'' was so badly damaged that the French burnt her.

==Design==
''Arrow'' and her sister ship ''Dart'' were &quot;Two experimental vessels designed by [[Samuel Bentham]], Esq., at that time inspector-general of his majesty's naval works. They were in shape much sharper than vessels of war in general, and projected or raked forward, at each end like a wherry. Their breadth increased from the water-line upwards ; whereby it was considered that they would be stiffer, and less liable to overset than ordinary vessels. The decks were straight fore and aft, and the frames or ribs of less curvature than usual. They were constructed to carry twenty-four 32-pounder [[carronade]]s upon the main deck, and were afterwards fitted to receive two more carronades of the same nature on each of their two short decks, which we may call the quarterdeck and forecastle. All these carronades were fitted upon the non-recoil principle. It is believed that both the Arrow and Dart subsequently took on board, for their quarterdecks, two additional 32s. They proved to be stiff vessels and swift sailers, but it was found necessary to add some dead wood to their bottoms, in order to make them stay better. Not knowing exactly what characteristic designation to give the Arrow and Dart, we have merely named them: they must be considered, especially when their force is compared with that of the two or three classes next above them, as extraordinary vessels for sloops of war, but as such only they ranked.&quot;&lt;ref&gt;James (1837), Vol. 1, p. 403.&lt;/ref&gt;

==French Revolutionary Wars==
Commander [[Nathaniel Portlock]] commissioned ''Arrow'' in 1796.&lt;ref name=Winfield/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;NMM-WH-380211&quot;/&gt; On 1 June 1797 ''Arrow'' captured two French merchant vessels, the ''Jeune Albe'' and the ''Sept Freres''.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=14036|startpage=775|date=12 August 1797}}&lt;/ref&gt; Then on 25 April 1798 ''Arrow'' captured the ''Jonge Ferdinand''.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=15268|startpage=698|date=17 June 1800}}&lt;/ref&gt; Then on 1 September ''Arrow'' captured the ''Jong Jan Swart''.&lt;ref name=LG15714&gt;{{London Gazette|startpage=801|issue=15714|date=26 June 1804}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Between April and July 1799 ''Arrow'' sailed in company with {{HMS|Wolverine|1798|2}} and the [[hired armed vessels|hired armed]] [[cutter (ship)|cutter]] [[Hired armed cutter Kent|''Kent'']]. Together, these three vessels captured a number of prizes. On 23 April they captured ''Blenie Rosetta''.&lt;ref name=LG15547/&gt; On 21 May they captured ''Rosalia''.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=15520|startpage=1066|date=2 October 1802}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eight days later, on 29 May, they took ''Active'' and ''Providence''. One month after that, on 28 June, they captured five fishing boats. Then on 13 July they captured the ''Altona''.&lt;ref name=LG15547/&gt; Three days later they captured the ''Antony Wilhelm''.&lt;ref name=LG15547/&gt; Lastly, on 29 July, they captured the ''Nancy''.{{#tag:ref|On 20 January 1803 prize money resulting from the capture of the ''Blenie Rosetta'', ''Active'', ''Providence'', five fishing boats, ''Altona'', ''Antony Wilhelm'' and ''Nancy'' was due for payment.&lt;ref name=LG15547&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=15547|startpage=40|date=4 January 1803}}&lt;/ref&gt;|group=Note}} ''Arrow'' also captured the [[hoy (boat)|hoy]] Johanna on 1 May.&lt;ref name=LG15714/&gt;

Next, ''Arrow'' was among the many British vessels that shared in the capture, on 28 August, of the Dutch hulks ''Drotchterland'' and ''Brooderschap'', the ships ''Helder'', ''Venus'', ''Minerva'', and ''Hector'', in the New Diep.{{#tag:ref|The prize money for a seaman was 6[[shilling|s]] 8[[pence|d]].&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|startpage=158|issue=15453|date=13 February 1802}}&lt;/ref&gt;|group=Note}} She also shared in the surrender, on 30 August, in the surrender of the Dutch Fleet at the [[Vlieter Incident]].&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|startpage=1184|issue=15531|date=9 November 1802}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 9 September Vice-Admiral Mitchell detached ''Arrow'' and ''Wolverine'' to attack a ship and a brig belonging to the [[Batavian Republic]] and anchored under the [[Vlie]] at the entrance to the [[Texel]]. ''Arrow'' had to lighten ship and the following day they crossed over the Flack abreast of Wieringen and saw the enemy in the passage leading from Vlie Island towards [[Harlingen, Friesland|Harlingen]]. On 12 September ''Wolverine'' anchored within 60 yards of the brig and only had to fire one gun before the brig hauled down her colours. She proved to be the ''Gier'', armed with fourteen 12-pounders. Next, ''Arrow'' exchanged broadsides with the ship ''Draak'', of 24 guns (six 50-pound brass howitzers, two 32-pounder guns, and sixteen long 18-pounder guns), which surrendered when ''Wolverine'' came up. ''Draak'' turned out to be a sheer hulk so Captain Bolton burnt her. The British also captured two schooners, each of four 8-pounder guns, and four schuyts, each of two 8-pounder guns. The Dutch prisoners numbered 380 men.&lt;ref name=LG15187&gt;{{London Gazette|startpage=982|endpage=984|issue=15187|date=24 September 1799}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1847 the Admiralty awarded the Naval General Service Medal with clasps &quot;Arrow 13 Sept 1799&quot; and &quot;Wolverine 13 Sept. 1799&quot; to any survivors of the two crews that claimed them.

''Arrow'' and ''Wolverine'' weighed on 15 September and near Vlie ''Wolverine'' went to take possession of a Batavian ship, the 24-gun {{HMS|Dolphin|1799|2}} (''Dolfijn''), which hoisted Orange colours as soon as the English came up. Two hundred and thirty prisoners were put aboard her and the command given to Lieutenant M'Dougall of ''Wolverine''. Command of the ''Gier'', a brand new vessel, went to Lieutenant Gilmour, [[First lieutenant]] of ''Arrow''.&lt;ref name=LG15187/&gt; Gilmour would receive promotion to the rank of Commander for his part in the action.

''Arrow'' was also involved in the wreck and attempted salvage of [[French frigate Lutine (1779)|HMS ''Lutine'']], which sank on 9 October 1799 carrying a large cargo of gold.&lt;ref&gt;Van Der Molen, p.37.&lt;/ref&gt;

In November 1799 W. Bolton replaced Portlock in command of ''Arrow''.&lt;ref name=&quot;NMM-WH-380211&quot;&gt;
{{cite web|url=http://www.nmm.ac.uk/upload/pdf/Warship_Histories_Vessels_v.pdf|title=NMM, vessel ID 380211|work=Warship Histories, vol v|publisher=[[National Maritime Museum]]|accessdate=30 July 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 25 July 1800 {{HMS|Nemesis|1780|2}} was part of a squadron that also included {{HMS|Terpsichore|1785|2}}, {{HMS|Prévoyante|1793|2}}, ''Arrow'', and the [[hired armed vessels|hired armed]] [[lugger]] [[Hired armed lugger Nile|''Nile'']]. The squadron encountered the Danish frigate [[HDMS Freja (1793)|HDMS ''Freja'']], which was escorting a convoy of two ships, two brigs and two [[galliot]]s.&lt;ref name=NC4/&gt; Captain Baker of ''Nemesis'' hailed ''Freja'' and said that he would send a boat to board the convoy. The Danish captain refused, and said that if a boat approached he would fire on it. Baker sent a midshipman and four men in a boat, and the Danes fired several shots, which missed the boat, but one of which killed a man on ''Nemesis''. ''Nemesis'' then opened fire with her broadside. After an engagement of about 25 minutes, ''Freja'', much damaged, [[striking the colours|struck]]. She had suffered eight men killed and many wounded; both ''Nemesis'' and ''Arrow'' each suffered two men killed and several wounded.&lt;ref&gt;''London Chronicle'', 26–29 July 1800, p.104.&lt;/ref&gt; The British brought ''Freya'' and her convoy into the Downs on 6 March.&lt;ref name=NC4&gt;''Naval Chronicle'', Vol. 4, p.157.&lt;/ref&gt; They later released her, and presumably the rest of the convoy.&lt;ref group=Note&gt;In 1807, after the [[Battle of Copenhagen (1807)|second battle of Copenhagen]], the British again captured ''Freja''. This time they took her into the Royal Navy as HMS ''Freya''.&lt;/ref&gt; This incident led to strained relations with [[Denmark]], and, in order to anticipate any hostile move from [[Copenhagen]], the British government despatched [[Charles Whitworth, 1st Earl Whitworth|Earl Whitworth]] in August on a special mission to Copenhagen. The Danes not being ready for war, his mission staved off hostilities for about a year.

On 20 September ''Arrow'' captured the ''Oster Rifoer''.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=15557|startpage=167|date=8 February 1803}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1801 ''Arrow'' came under the command of Commander Thomas-Charles Brodie.&lt;ref name=&quot;NMM-WH-380211&quot;/&gt; In February ''Arrow'' recaptured the ''Betsey'', of Montrose, which had been sailing from Riga to Shoreham when a French privateer had captured her.&lt;ref&gt;''Lloyd's List'', no. 4127,[http://www.1812privateers.org/LLOYDS/1801/02-20-1801.jpg] - accessed 15 October 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

Brodie was ''Arrow{{'}}''s captain at the [[Battle of Copenhagen (1801)|Battle of Copenhagen]]. ''Arrow'' suffered no casualties, though her sister ship ''Dart'' had two men killed and one wounded.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=15354|startpage=402|endpage=404|date=15 April 1801}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;James (1837), Vol. 3, pp. 66-80.&lt;/ref&gt; After the battle ''Arrow'' took the dispatches back to England.&lt;ref&gt;''The Gentleman's Magazine'' (May 1811), Vol. 81, Part 1, p.492.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1802 Commander Richard Budd Vincent replace Brodie.&lt;ref name=&quot;NMM-WH-380211&quot;/&gt; He had received his promotion to Commander on 29 April and his appointment to command ''Arrow'' on 17 May. He proceeded to sail her off the Devonshire coast on anti-smuggler patrol.&lt;ref name=Obit&gt;'&quot;Annual Obituary'' (1832), p. 474; Longman.&lt;/ref&gt; On 7 September ''Arrow'' seized  174 kegs of spirits and wine.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=15565|startpage=256|date=8 March 1803}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Napoleonic Wars==
''Arrow{{'}}''s design made her too recognizable at a distance so in February 1803 Vincent paid her off.&lt;ref name=Obit/&gt; On 1 March he was reappointed to her. However, he faced great difficulty in assembling a crew. He had to resort to sending one of his officers in a Customs House cutter into the Channel to impress seamen from vessels sailing there. He had no sooner succeeded in assembling a crew than the Lords of the Admiralty drafted the majority of the men Vincent had gathered and put them into a troopship sailing for the West Indies.&lt;ref name=Marshall/&gt;

On 1 May Vincent recommissioned ''Arrow'' for the Mediterranean.&lt;ref name=Marshall&gt;Marshall (1825), Supplement2, Part 2, pp.912-929.&lt;/ref&gt; In mid-June, ''Arrow'' recaptured the lugger ''Louisa'', which had been carrying spirits when a French privateer had captured her. ''Arrow'' sent ''Louisa'' into Portsmouth.&lt;ref&gt;''Lloyd's List'', no.4359,[http://www.1812privateers.org/LLOYDS/1803/06-17-1803.jpg] - accessed 15 October 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

In July Vincent sailed ''Arrow'' for the Mediterranean. When he left she had only about two-thirds of her official complement. Once in the Mediterranean, ''Arrow'' performed convoy duty in the Adriatic and the [[Aegean Sea|Archipelago]].&lt;ref name=Marshall/&gt; ''Arrow'' called in at Gibraltar, Malta, Sicily, Naples, Sardinia, Turkey, Corfu, [[Zakynthos|Zante]] and the neighboring isles, Venice, Trieste, [[Rijeka|Fiume]], and [[Smyrna]], as well as many smaller places.&lt;ref name=Marshall/&gt;

In March 1804 ''Arrow'' was in the [[Dardanelles]], convoying some vessels to Constantinople, when a fort on the European side fired on her. The wind was blowing too hard for ''Arrow'' to be able to stop and remonstrate with the fort's commander, but when she reached Constantinople VIncent complained to the British Minister, Alexander Stratton.{{#tag:ref|Marshall names Alexander Stratton as the Minister Plenipotentiary to the Ottoman court.&lt;ref name=Marshall/&gt; However, Wikipedia's [[list of diplomats of the United Kingdom to the Ottoman Empire]] has Stratton serving only between January to May '''1803'''. The British ambassador in March 1804 would have been [[William Drummond of Logiealmond]].|group=Note}} He in turn complained to the [[Divan]], who then fined the governor of the fort.&lt;ref name=Marshall/&gt;

While ''Arrow'' was in Constantinople, Vincent visited the Capitan Pacha [sic], the commander of the Ottoman fleet, and toured the arsenal and Ottoman vessels. The Capitan Pacha presented Vincent with an elegant [[sabre]]. When the Capitan Pacha and some of his officers toured ''Arrow'' Vincent reciprocated by presenting the Capitan Pacha with a [[2 (number)#In other fields|brace]] of pistols whose workmanship the Capitan Pacha had admired.&lt;ref name=Marshall/&gt;

On 3 June, Vincent sent in his boats under the command of Lieutenant Cuthbert Featherstone Daly to cut out the French privateer ''Actif'' from under the cliffs at [[Othonoi|Fano]] island, at the entrance to the Adriatic and belonging to the then neutral self-governing federation of the [[Septinsular Republic|Heptanesos]] (&quot;Seven Islands&quot;). ''Actif'' was a [[tartane]] of four guns, rowing 24 oars, and having a crew of 74 men. She was new but had had some success. The British were unable to get her out and after she grounded they set her on fire, destroying her. In the action, ''Arrow'' had two men killed and a number wounded, one mortally.&lt;ref&gt;Marshall (1827), Supplement, Part 1, pp.383-4.&lt;/ref&gt; This action led [[Horatio Nelson, 1st Viscount Nelson|Lord Nelson]] to write a letter to Vincent, dated 28 July, on {{HMS|Victory}} at sea. Nelson informed Vincent that he supported Vincent's decision to attack ''Actif'', and that he, Nelson, would advise the British minister at Corfu to draw the attention of the authorities that if enemy vessels took advantage of Corfu's neutrality to fire on British warships from Corfiote ports, the British would be justified in destroying the French privateers. At the same time, Nelson wanted Vincent to understand clearly that British vessels were not to fire on enemy vessels in neutral ports unless the enemy vessels forfeited the protection of the port by firing first.&lt;ref&gt;Nicholas &amp; Nelson (1846), Vol. 6, pp.116-7.&lt;/ref&gt;

By late August it was clear that the Malta Yard could not repair the many defects in ''Arrow'' that had accumulated, particularly with respect to her water tanks, which were integral to her hull. Nelson, therefore, decided that she should sail back to Britain as escort to a convoy in autumn.&lt;ref&gt;Nicholas &amp; Nelson (1846), Vol. 6, pp.167-8.&lt;/ref&gt; By 10 October, ''Arrow'' was back in Malta undergoing some repairs.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nicholas 1846 pp.213&quot;&gt;Nicholas &amp; Nelson (1846), Vol. 6, pp.213.&lt;/ref&gt;

Still, on 18 October ''Arrow'' was off Cape Spartivento when a bolt of lightning hit her main mast. Although main top-mast went overboard, the sails, being furled and wet, did not catch fire. There were no casualties and no further damage.&lt;ref name=Marshall/&gt;{{#tag:ref|Cape Spartivento was the one in [[Calabria]],&lt;ref name=NC/&gt; not the one at the southern tip of Sardinia, near [[Cagliari]].|group=Note}} The next day ''Arrow'' returned to Malta where she replaced her mast.&lt;ref name=NC/&gt;

''Arrow'' proceeded to [[Palermo]] and [[Agrigento|Gergenti]], where she gathered a convoy that she escorted to Malta, arriving on 17 November. Next, ''Arrow'' was dispatched on a secret mission to [[Messina]], Palermo, and Naples. She left Naples on 12 December and arrived at Malta on 20 December.&lt;ref name=NC/&gt;

At Malta, Vincent received instructions to take the merchant vessels gathered there to England, once some merchantmen arrived from [[Izmir|Smyrna]] to join the convoy. The orders further specified that he was to take the 8-gun [[bomb vessel]] ''Acheron'', under the command of Commander [[Arthur Farquhar (1772–1843)|Arthur Farquhar]], with him to assist him in protecting the trade.&lt;ref name=NC&gt;''Naval Chronicle'', Vol. 17, pp.278-306.&lt;/ref&gt; The vessels from Smyrna arrived on 2 January 1805, and the convoy left for England on 4 January. The brig [[French brig-corvette Jalouse (1794)|''Jalouse'']] had escorted the convoy from Smyrna and she continued on as an escort as far as western Sicily.&lt;ref name=NC/&gt;

The convoy numbered some 25-30 vessels.&lt;ref&gt;''Lloyd's List'', no.4197,[http://www.1812privateers.org/LLOYDS/1805/03-08-1805.jpg] - accessed 16 October 2014.&lt;/ref&gt; A later account gives the vessels as the transport ''Dutchess of Rutland'' and 29 British merchant vessels.{{#tag:ref|''Dutchess of Rutland'', Pascal, master, was about 20 years old, of 440 tons (bm), and built in Sweden. She was armed with six 3-pounder guns.&lt;ref&gt;''Lloyd's Register'' (1805).&lt;/ref&gt;|group=Note}} 

Between 19 and 22 January, bad weather off the coast of Spain caused the convoy to separate into two parts, one with ''Arrow'' and the other with ''Acheron''. During the night of 29 January the brig ''Union'' apparently foundered with all hands during a squall.&lt;ref name=NC/&gt;

On 2 February, the convoy fell in with the Spanish ship ''Gravina'', which {{HMS|Amazon|1799|2}} had captured on 27 January.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=15854|startpage=1322|date=22 October 1805}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''Gravina'' was on her way to Malta but Captain [[Hyde Parker (admiral)|Hyde Parker]] of ''Amazon'' had instructed the commander of the prize crew to sail to England should he encounter a convoy sailing there. ''Gravina'' therefore joined the convoy.&lt;ref name=NC/&gt;

==Fate==
The French frigates [[French frigate Hortense (1803)|''Hortense'']] and [[French frigate Incorruptible (1795)|''Incorruptible'']] were cruising off the coast of Algeria when on 1 February, they engaged a convoy, destroying seven ships. Two days later, they encountered another convoy.

[[File:Arrow sinking.jpg|thumb|360px|End of the action between HMS ''Arrow'' and ''Acheron'' and the French frigates ''Hortense'' and ''Incorruptible'', Francis Sartorious, Jr., [[National Maritime Museum]], Greenwich]]

This second convoy was the convoy that ''Arrow'' and ''Acheron'' were escorting. Early on the morning of 3 February the British were off Cap Caxine when they sighted the two French vessels, which the British initially thought they might be members of the convoy rejoining. When it became clear that the strange vessels were French frigates, ''Arrow'' threw of the tow to the brig ''Adventure'', which had been leaking and which the British destroyed to prevent her falling into enemy hands). ''Arrow'' and ''Acheron'' then placed themselves between the convoy and the pursuing French. Vincent signaled the vessels of the convoy to make for a per-designated rendezvous point. The French frigates did not catch up to the Royal Navy vessels until the morning of 4 February. Initially, ''Hortense'' engaged ''Acheron'', and ''Arrow'' fired a broadside into ''Hortense'' as well. About two hours later, ''Incorruptible'' joined the action. Vincent signaled to ''Duchess of Rutland'', the most capable, though minimally so, of the merchant vessels, to join the action, a signal ''Duchess of Rutland'' ignored. Throughout the action the Royal Navy vessels were at a disadvantage. Not only did the French frigates have more cannons and men, but the French cannons were guns, whereas the British cannons were almost all carronades. The French could therefore stand off and fire their guns while out of the effective range of the carronades. Also, the French were carrying a large number of troops who harassed the British with small arms fire whenever the vessels closed.&lt;ref name=LC15790&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=15790|startpage=365|endpage=366|date=19 March 1805}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Marshall/&gt;

After about an hour Vincent had to [[striking the colours|strike]]. ''Arrow{{'}}''s hold was filling with water and four of her cannons were dismounted. She also had heavy casualties. All of ''Arrow{{'}}''s boats had been destroyed, but boats from ''Incorruptible'' took off the survivors, and rescue those men from ''Arrow'' that jumped into the water as ''Arrow'' turned on her beam ends and sank.&lt;ref name=LC15790/&gt;&lt;ref name=Marshall/&gt;

In the battle ''Arrow'' lost 13 men killed and 27 wounded, at least two of whom died later, of the 132 men on board. The number included passengers, some 17 of whom were being invalided home. A lady, her infant, and her ladies' maid were also taking passage on board.&lt;ref name=NC/&gt;

''Acheron'' fought on for another quarter of an hour before she too struck. She had lost three or four men killed and eight wounded. She had complement of 67 men, and at least two passengers, a lieutenant of marines and his servant, both of whom were killed. She was so damaged that the French burnt her.&lt;ref name=Marshall/&gt; ''Hortense'' had 10 men killed out of her crew of 300 men and the 350 artillerymen she was carrying.&lt;ref name=Abeille&gt;''L' Abeille du nord'', Vol. 10, p.22.&lt;/ref&gt;

The French frigates also captured three ships of the convoy; the rest of the convoy escaped.&lt;ref&gt;James (1837), Vol. 3, pp.391-397.&lt;/ref&gt; One of the vessels the French captured was ''Dutchess of Rutland'', whose master failed to destroy her convoy signals and instructions; fortunately the French had to return to port to effect repairs and did not take advantage of the opportunity this represented.&lt;ref name=Marshall/&gt; The French scuttled the three merchant vessels they captured.&lt;ref name=Abeille/&gt;

After the loss of their escorts, some of the surviving vessels of the convoy fell prey to privateers. The ''Fuerte'', of Cadiz, captured the ''Alert'', Langley, master, ''Castle'', Anderson, master, a ship, and a brig, and sent them into Malaga. Reportedly, ''Fuerte'' had captured a fifth vessel that she sent into Algeciras.&lt;ref&gt;''Lloyd's List'', no.4205,[http://www.1812privateers.org/LLOYDS/1805/04-05-1805.jpg] - accessed 16 October 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;

It later turned out that British frigate [[French frigate Résistance (1796)|''Fisgard'']] and the sloop {{HMS|Wasp|1800|2}} had been at [[Cape Palos|Cape Pallas]] ({{coord|37|35|N|0|43|W}}), a few [[league (unit)|leagues]] of the action.&lt;ref name=&quot;Nicholas 1846 pp.213&quot;/&gt; However, they were unaware of it and so did not come to the convoy's assistance.

''Hortense'' took Farquhar and his men into Malaga, from where they were exchanged relatively quickly. The court martial of Farquhar, his officers, and men, for the loss of their vessel took place on {{HMS|Royal Sovereign|1786|2}} in Palma Bay, Sardinia.&lt;ref group=Note&gt;This appears to be Porto Palma, [[Caprera]], in the [[Maddalena archipelago]]. Nelson and his fleet were anchored there. Some accounts mistake Palma Bay for Palma, Mallorca.&lt;/ref&gt; Farquhar, his officers, and men, were honourably acquitted. Farquahar then received a promotion to post captain for his bravery.&lt;ref&gt; Hepper (1994), pp. 109-10.&lt;/ref&gt;  

The French held Vincent and his crew as prisoners in [[Cartagena, Spain]], for almost three months from 8 February until early May. Vincent had managed to keep his Turkish sabre when he left ''Arrow'', but a French officer confiscated it and the French refused to return it. Eventually, Admiral Lord [[Admiral Nelson|Nelson]] was able to arrange a [[cartel (ship)|cartel]] brig to return the British prisoners to Gibraltar. From there they left for England on 28 May on the storeship [[HMS Mediator (1782)|''Camel'']],&lt;ref name=Marshall/&gt; arriving at Saint Helen's on 4 June.&lt;ref name=NC/&gt;

The court martial of Vincent and his crew for the loss of ''Arrow'' convened on 17 June aboard {{HMS|Gladiator|1783|2}} at Portsmouth. The court martial honourably acquitted all; Vincent received promotion to [[post captain]] immediately thereafter.&lt;ref&gt;Hepper (1994), p.110.&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[Lloyd's Patriotic Fund]] awarded both Vincent and Farquahar honour swords, each worth ₤100. In addition, the Fund awarded Vincent a piece of plate of the same value.&lt;ref&gt;Barton &amp; McGrath (2013), p. 121.&lt;/ref&gt; Furthermore, the Fund paid out £545 to the wounded and the families of those who had died. The request of Lloyd's, the Chairman of the association of Merchants Trading to South of Europe provided Vincent with the sum of £477 10s, and a proportionate amount to Farquhar, for them to procure clothing and necessities for their officers and crew, who had lost everything when they were captured and their vessels were destroyed. Vincent received £50, and each seaman received £2 10s.&lt;ref name=NC/&gt;

On 19 September 1808, the merchants of Malta awarded Farquhar with a piece of plate and a complementary letter.&lt;ref&gt;''Dictionary of National Biography'' (1889), Vol. 18, p.221.&lt;/ref&gt; The merchants also presented Vincent with a piece of plate.&lt;ref&gt;''Dictionary of National Biography'' (1909), Vol. 20, p. 362.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1847 the Admiralty awarded the Naval General Service Medal with clasp &quot;Arrow 3 Feby. 1805&quot; to the eight surviving claimants from ''Arrow'', and the clasp &quot;Acheron 3 Feby. 1805&quot; to the one surviving claimant from ''Acheron''.

==Notes, Citations, and References==

===Notes===
{{reflist|group=Note}}

===Citations===
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

===References===
*Barton, Mark, and John McGrath (213) ''British Naval Swords and Swordsmanship''. (Seaforth). ISBN 978-1848321359  
*{{colledge}}
*{{cite book|last=Hepper|first=David J.|authorlink=|year=1994|title=British Warship Losses in the Age of Sail, 1650–1859|publisher=Jean Boudriot|location=Rotherfield|isbn=0-948864-30-3}}
*{{Citation
 | last1=James | first1=William | authorlink1=William James (naval historian)
 | last2=Chamier | first2=Frederick | authorlink2=Frederick Chamier
 | title=The naval history of Great Britain from the declaration of war by France in 1793 to the accession of George IV  
 | publication-date=1837
 | publisher=Bentley
 | edition=New ed., with additions and notes, and An account of the Burmese war and the battle of Navarino / by Captain Chamier
 | oclc=1924562
 | url = http://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/008224490}}
*{{Cite DNB|wstitle=Portlock, Nathaniel|last=Laughton|first=John Knox|authorlink=John Knox Laughton|volume=46}}
*Marshall, John (1823–1835) ''Royal naval biography, or, Memoirs of the services of all the flag-officers, superannuated rear-admirals, retired-captains, post-captains, and commanders, whose names appeared on the Admiralty list of sea officers at the commencement of the present year 1823, or who have since been promoted ...'' (London: Longman, Hurst, Rees, Orme and Brown).
*Nelson, Horatio and Nicholas Harris Nicolas (1846) ''The Dispatches and Letters of Vice Admiral Lord Viscount Nelson''. (Colburn).
*Van Der Molen, S. J. (1970) ''The Lutine Treasure''. (ISBN 0-229-97482-1)
*{{cite book |first=Rif|last=Winfield|title=British Warships in the Age of Sail 1793&amp;ndash;1817: Design, Construction, Careers and Fates|publisher=Seaforth|year=2008|isbn=1-86176-246-1}}

{{WarshipHist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Arrow (1796)}}
[[Category:1796 ships]]
[[Category:Southampton-built ships]]
[[Category:Sloops of the Royal Navy]]
[[Category:Captured ships]]
[[Category:Maritime incidents in 1805]]</text>
      <sha1>goj4hw4tk81zv0zamd0frjen7rwjtc9</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
