<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Islamic Unification Movement</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>15462262</id>
    <revision>
      <id>742797217</id>
      <parentid>741661443</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-05T21:16:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jopsach</username>
        <id>5817190</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Political beliefs */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="15662">{{Infobox War Faction
|name= Islamic Unification Movement&lt;br&gt;حركة التوحيد الإسلامي
|war=[[Lebanese civil war]] (1975–1990)
|image=
|caption=
|active=Until 1990 and 1991 - present
|leaders=[[Said Shaaban]], [[Bilal Shaaban]], [[Hashem Minqara]]
|clans=[[Islamic Group (Lebanon)|Lebanese Islamic Group]], [[Islamic Labor Front]]
|headquarters=[[Bab al-Tabbaneh]] ([[Tripoli (Lebanon)|Tripoli]])
|areas=[[Tripoli]], [[Akkar]], [[West Beirut]], [[Sidon]], [[Jabal Amel]]
|strength=1,000 fighters
|previous=
|allies=[[Palestine Liberation Organization]] (PLO)&lt;br&gt;[[Hezbollah]]&lt;br&gt;[[Syrian Army]]
|opponents=[[Israel Defense Forces]] (IDF)&lt;br&gt;[[South Lebanon Army]] (SLA)&lt;br&gt;[[Arab Democratic Party, Lebanon|Arab Democratic Party]] (ADP)&lt;br&gt;[[Lebanese Communist Party]] (LCP)&lt;br&gt;[[Jammoul]]&lt;br&gt;[[Syrian Social Nationalist Party]] (SSNP)&lt;br&gt;[[Baath Party]]&lt;br&gt;[[Syrian Army]] (formerly)
}}
{{Politics of Lebanon}}
The '''Islamic Unification Movement – IUM''' ({{lang-ar|حركة التوحيد الإسلامي}} | ''Harakat al-Tawhid al-Islami''), also named '''Islamic Unity Movement''' or '''Mouvement de Unification Islamique (MUI)''' in [[French language|French]], but best known as '''Al-Tawhid''', '''At-Tawhid''', or '''Tawheed''', is a [[Lebanon|Lebanese]] [[Sunni Islam in Lebanon|Sunni Muslim]] political party.  It plays an active role in Lebanese internal politics since the [[Lebanese Civil War]] in the 1980s.

==Origins==
The IUM was founded in [[Tripoli, Lebanon|Tripoli]] in 1982 from a splinter faction of the [[Islamic Group (Lebanon)|Lebanese Islamic Group]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://meria.biu.ac.il/journal/1997/issue3/jv1n3a2.html Islamism In Lebanon&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;]&lt;/ref&gt; led by [[Sheikh]] [[Said Shaaban]], one of Lebanon’s Islamist movements’ few charismatic [[Sunni Islam in Lebanon|Sunni]] religious leaders.  A hardliner who believed that force was a good solution in politics, the radical Shaaban broke away from the Islamic Group soon after the June 1982 [[1982 Lebanon War|Israeli invasion of Lebanon]], in protest for that Party’s leadership decision of adopting a non-violent, moderate political line in the early 1980s.  Nevertheless, the two organizations have always maintained a good relationship, especially with [[Sheikh]] [[Fathi Yakan]], founder and Secretary-general of the Islamic Group.

At the height of its power in 1985, the IUM splintered, when dissident leaders [[Khalil Akkawi]] and [[Kanaan Naji]] left the Movement to set up their own groups,&lt;ref&gt;''Al-Harakat al-Islamiya fi Lubnan'' (no date), pp. 93–141.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Deeb, ''Militant Islamic Movements in Lebanon'' (1986), pp. 7–8.&lt;/ref&gt; the Mosques’ Committee and the Islamic Committee.  Involved in imposing an Islamic administration on Tripoli in the 1980s, these latter two groups formed together with the IUM an umbrella organization, ''Al-Liqa' al-Islami''.

==Political beliefs==
Known to be anti-Syrian in policy and [[Sunni Islam in Lebanon|Sunni Muslim]] in composition, the IUM’s ideological anti-western and anti-Communist views stemmed from the radical Sunni wing of the [[Muslim Brotherhood]]. Consistent with these principles, Shaaban and its Movement ostensibly rejected [[Nationalism]], sectarianism and democratic pluralism in favor of an Islamic rule that &quot;absorbs and dissolves all social differences and unites them in one crucible&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ad-Diyar 1989&quot;&gt;''Ad-Diyar'' (Beirut), August 31, 1989.&lt;/ref&gt; Shaaban sought ways to unite Sunnis and Shi'ites, for example by suggesting that the holy [[Qur'an]] and the Prophet's biography provide foundations on which all Muslim groups and sects can unite.  Instead of arguing about sectarian representation in the parliament, he suggests that Muslims call for Islamic rule based on the [[Sharia]], without which no government can be legitimate. As such, the IUM strongly opposed the Christian-dominated political order in Lebanon and deeply resented the [[Syrian intervention in Lebanon|Syrian military intervention of June 1976]] in support of the [[Maronites]] who, Shaaban himself asserted, would have otherwise fled to [[Cyprus]] or [[Latin America]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Ad-Diyar 1989&quot; /&gt;

The Movement allegedly enjoyed since the mid-1980s close political ties with [[Iran]] and [[Hizbollah]],&lt;ref&gt;http://www.brookings.edu/views/papers/saabriedel_20070223.pdf&lt;/ref&gt; forged by [[Sheikh]] Shaaban frequent visits to [[Tehran]] and contacts with that Party’s leaders in Lebanon, which considers the IUM leader doctrinally a follower of [[Ayatollah]] [[Khomeini]].&lt;ref&gt;''Al-Massira'' (Beirut), February 10, 1992.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''An-Nahar al-Arabi wad-Duwali'', September 18–24, 1989.&lt;/ref&gt; Some sources even state that Shaaban was born and raised in a Shiite family of [[Batroun]] in [[North Governorate|Northern Lebanon]] and only later became a Sunni.&lt;ref&gt;''Al-Massira'' (Beirut), February 10, 1992.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Deeb, ''Militant Islamic Movements'', pp. 8–9.&lt;/ref&gt; While accepting the validity of the [[Iranian Revolution]] and emphasizing that the path started by Khomeini should be followed by all Muslims, the IUM leadership does not call for the establishment of an Iranian-style order in Lebanon, knowing that this would alienate their own Sunni followers.  Indeed, [[Sheikh]] Shaaban's speech delivered during the 3rd anniversary of Khomeini's death failed to mention his own relation to the latter and its theories.&lt;ref&gt;''Al-Ahd'' (Beirut), June 5, 1992.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Military structure and organization==
Controlled by the IUM's Military Command Council ([[Arabic]]: ''Majliss al-Kiyadi al-Harb'') headed by [[Sheikh]] [[Hashem Minqara]], their 1,000-men strong militia, also designated 'Tawheed', was created in 1982 and trained by the [[Palestine Liberation Organization]] (PLO), being initially provided with light weapons drawn from [[Lebanese Armed Forces]] (LAF) and [[Internal Security Forces]] (ISF) stocks or purchased on the black market. Upon the withdrawal of the Palestinian factions loyal to [[Yasser Arafat]] from Tripoli in December 1983, the Tawheed seized the opportunity to replenish themselves with vehicles, additional weapons and ammunition from PLO arms caches left behind. This allowed the IUM militia to raise a mechanized force made of ex-PLO [[gun-truck]]s, comprising Spanish [[Santana 88 Ligero Militar jeep]]s, [[Land-Rover|Land-Rover series II-III]], [[Toyota Land Cruiser (J40)]] and [[Toyota Land Cruiser (J55)]] light pickups equipped with [[heavy machine guns]], [[recoilless rifles]] and [[anti-aircraft]] [[autocannons]], plus mortars and a few truck-mounted [[BM-11]] 130&amp;thinsp;mm [[MBRL]]s for its artillery branch.

Its fighters consolidated their control over Tripoli in 1983–1984 by temporarily defeating a number of their secular left-wing and [[Pan-Arab]] rivals, in particular the predominantely [[Alawite]] [[Arab Democratic Party (Lebanon)|Arab Democratic Party]] (ADP) and the multi-confessional [[Lebanese Communist Party]] (LCP). They also clashed with the pro-Syrian [[Syrian Social Nationalist Party]] (SSNP) and [[Baath Party]] factions, and with the [[Syrian Army]] units stationed in Lebanon.

The IUM/Tawheed operated mainly on northern Lebanon, at Tripoli and its environs, though its militants were also active at the Sunni quarters of [[West Beirut]] and [[Sidon]], and at the [[Jabal Amel]] region of southern Lebanon.

==Illegal activities and controversy==
The IUM had its main strongholds at the predominantly Sunni district of [[Bab al-Tabbaneh]] in the western part of Tripoli, where the group's headquarters was located, and the [[Dinniyah]] sub-urban area east of the city.  They also controlled the nearby clandestine port of al-Mahdi, set up at Tripoli's western outskirts at [[El Mina]] and run by the Sunni businessmen [[Tariq Fakhr al-Din]], which was employed mainly for arms-smuggling operations and to levy illegal taxes on the transit trade of agricultural products and other goods.

Fanatical and ruthless fighters, Tawheed militiamen were responsible for several acts of violence in Tripoli against the local cells of the [[Alawite]] [[Arab Democratic Party, Lebanon|ADP]] and [[Lebanese Communist Party|LCP]].  On October 1983, the IUM/Tawheed executed a series of terrorist attacks against the Tripoli offices of the Communist Party, targeting Party cadres and their families. In one occasion, Tawheed fighters rounded up some 52 top Communist members, forced them to renounce their [[atheism]] and then summarily shot them, dumping the victims’ bodies into the [[Mediterranean]].&lt;ref&gt;Ihsan A. Hijazi, &quot;Communist Party in Lebanon hurt&quot;, ''New York Times'', March 4, 1987&lt;/ref&gt; Other actions held later that year targeted [[Syrian Army]] units stationed in Lebanon – on 19 December, the Tawheed was involved in the massacre of 15 Syrian soldiers at a checkpoint in Tripoli, carried out in retaliation for the seizure by the Syrians of one of their commanders the previous day.&lt;ref&gt;O'Ballance, ''Civil War in Lebanon'' (1998), p.  171.&lt;/ref&gt;

The IUM also run its own radio and television stations – the '''&quot;Voice of Right&quot;''' ([[Arabic]]: ''Sawt al-Haq'') and the '''&quot;Crescent&quot;''' ([[Arabic]]: ''al-Hilal''), respectively – which continued to operate in the post-war period, until being forcibly closed down in September 1997 by the Lebanese [[Internal Security Forces]] (ISF) during a nation-wide crack-down on Sunni religious extremists.

A former member, [[Khalid El-Masri]], was illegally kidnapped by the CIA. German reports assert that El-Masri himself reported his being a member of &quot;El-Tawhid&quot; or &quot;Al-Tawhid&quot; when he applied to Germany for refugee status, in 1985. The reference to &quot;El-Tawhid&quot; may have been confused with the group [[Abu Mussab al-Zarqawi]] lead, [[Al Qaeda in Iraq]], used to be called &quot;[[Jama'at al-Tawhid wal-Jihad]]&quot;.&lt;ref name=&quot;drudgearchive&quot;&gt;[http://www.drudgereportarchives.com/data/2003/02/05/20030205_182022_flash1.htm Al-Qaeda-Iraq link being investigated in Germany, report says], ''[[Drudge Report]]'', February 5, 2003,&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;derspiegell381940&quot;&gt;[http://service.spiegel.de/cache/international/0,1518,381940,00.html Terrorists with German Passports], ''[[Der Spiegel]]'', October 27, 2005&lt;/ref&gt; &quot;Jama'at al-Tawhid wal-Jihad&quot;, the former name for Zarqawi's group, translates as the &quot;movement for monotheism and struggle&quot;.

==The Tawheed in the Lebanese Civil War==
===Tripoli 1982–86===
In August 1984, violent clashes erupted between the Tawheed and the ADP, with the former been supported by the Mosques Committee and the Islamic Committee. The Tawheed’s position was strengthened when they gained control of the port area on 22 August, after a fierce battle on the streets of Tripoli that left more than 400 dead. Street fighting dragged for some days until 18 September, when it was brought to an end by a Syrian-mediated peace agreement between the IUM and the ADP.&lt;ref&gt;O'Ballance, ''Civil War in Lebanon'' (1998), pp. 146–47.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the fall of 1985 the Syrian army entered Tripoli and crushed Islamic Unity's militia, though it permitted Sha'ban to maintain leadership of his now unarmed movement.&lt;ref&gt;''Al-Jumhuriya'' (Cairo), September 19, 1985.&lt;/ref&gt;

Intermittent clashes occurred in the Tripoli area during the Spring and Summer of 1986, this time between the Tawheed and the pro-Syrian SSNP faction, until Syrian troops finally moved in to enforce a truce at the request of local community leaders.&lt;ref&gt;O'Ballance, ''Civil War in Lebanon'' (1998), p. 168.&lt;/ref&gt;

In Tripoli on December 18, 1986 the Tawheed commander [[Samir al-Hassan]] was arrested by the Syrians. His men responded by killing 15 Syrian soldiers at a checkpoint, which brought the wrath of the Syrians on the Tawheed. Aided by ADP, LCP, SSNP and Baath Party militias, the Syrians managed to defeat decisively the Tawheed, killing many of its fighters, arresting others and scattered the remainder.&lt;ref&gt;O'Ballance, ''Civil War in Lebanon'' (1998), p. 171.&lt;/ref&gt;

===South Lebanon 1988–2000===
The defeat at the [[battle of Tripoli]] did not mean the end of IUM/Tawheed military activities at Beirut, Sidon, and southern Lebanon. Underground guerrilla cells continued to operate in these areas until the end of the civil war, and afterwards. From 1988 to 2000, the Movement's guerrillas at the [[Jabal Amel]] fought alongside the Shia [[Hezbollah]] against the [[Israel Defense Forces]] (IDF) and their [[South Lebanese Army]] (SLA) proxies in the Israeli-controlled &quot;security zone.&quot;

==The post-war years==
Aside from rare instances of mild criticism, [[Sheikh]] Shaaban and the IUM were careful not to antagonize the Syrian authorities, particularly after Syria defeated their militia in late 1986. He spoke favorably of the Syrian military presence in Lebanon as a framework for unified, armed action against [[Israel]],&lt;ref&gt;''An-Nahar'' (Beirut), May 12, 1992.&lt;/ref&gt; a policy which was continued by its successors in the 1990s.

The Movement remains politically active, led by the Secretary-General [[Sheikh]] Minqara, a member of the pro-Syrian [[March 8 alliance]].&lt;ref&gt;http://google.com/search?q=cache:u1dAVhkue4oJ:www.stratfor.com/analysis/lebanon_militia_buildup_tripoli+stratfor+tawhid+al+islami&amp;hl=en&amp;ct=clnk&amp;cd=1&lt;/ref&gt; In 2005, the IUM joined the [[Islamic Labor Front]], an alliance of several Islamic parties and figures in Lebanon. The movement's militia re-emerged, this time in support of the Syrian Government in Tripoli. However, after a couple of years, the Lebanese Army virtually crushed the militia in a major security crackdown in 2014. &lt;ref&gt; http://www.albawaba.com/news/lebanon-tripoli-565878 &lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Hezbollah]]
* [[Lebanese civil war]]
* [[Islamic Group (Lebanon)|Lebanese Islamic Group]]
* [[Islamic Labor Front]]
* [[Popular Guard]]

==Footnotes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
* A. Nizar Hamzeh, ''Islamism in Lebanon: A Guide to the Groups'', Middle East Quarterly, September 1997.
* ''Al-Harakat al-Islamiya fi Lubnan'', Beirut: Ash-Shira, no date. (in [[Arabic]])
* [[Edgar O'Ballance]], ''Civil War in Lebanon, 1975-92'', Palgrave Macmillan, 1998. ISBN 0-333-72975-7
* Fawwaz Traboulsi, ''Identités et solidarités croisées dans les conflits du Liban contemporain; Chapitre 12: L'économie politique des milices: le phénomène mafieux'', Thèse de Doctorat d'Histoire – 1993, Université de Paris VIII, 2007. (in [[French language|French]]) – [http://www.111101.net/Writings/Author/Fawwaz_Traboulsi/]
* Marius Deeb, ''Militant Islamic Movements in Lebanon: Origins, Social Basis and Ideologies'', Center for Contemporary Arab Studies, Washington, D.C., 1986.
* Moustafa El-Assad, ''Civil Wars Volume 1: The Gun Trucks'', Blue Steel books, Sidon 2008. {{Listed Invalid ISBN|9953-0-1256-8}}
* Rex Brynen, ''Sanctuary and Survival: the PLO in Lebanon'', Boulder: Westview Press, 1990.
* Samer Kassis, ''30 Years of Military Vehicles in Lebanon'', Beirut: Elite Group, 2003. ISBN 9953-0-0705-5

===Further reading===
* Denise Ammoun, ''Histoire du Liban contemporain: Tome 2 1943-1990'', Fayard, Paris 2005. ISBN 978-2-213-61521-9 (in [[French language|French]])
* [[Robert Fisk]], ''Pity the Nation: Lebanon at War'', London: Oxford University Press, (3rd ed. 2001). ISBN 0-19-280130-9

==External links==
* http://www.attawhed.org/ – Islamic Unification official site.
* http://www.daawa.net/ – Islamic Labor Front official site (in [[Arabic]]).
{{Lebanese political parties}}
[[Category:Arab militant groups]]
[[Category:Islamic political parties in Lebanon]]
[[Category:Factions in the Lebanese Civil War]]
[[Category:Israeli–Lebanese conflict]]
[[Category:Irregular military]]</text>
      <sha1>3wkspzhmii8uztbjvmg3ixf4ei69sy8</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
