<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Joseph George Rosengarten</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>32210710</id>
    <revision>
      <id>743607621</id>
      <parentid>742361824</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-10T11:04:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cydebot</username>
        <id>1215485</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Robot - Moving category People from Philadelphia, Pennsylvania to [[:Category:People from Philadelphia]] per [[WP:CFD|CFD]] at [[Wikipedia:Categories for discussion/Log/2016 September 6]].</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="16046">'''Joseph George Rosengarten''' (July 14, 1835 - January 14, 1921) was a Philadelphia [[lawyer]], [[historian]], and [[American Civil War|Civil War]] [[veteran]]. He served on the staff of General [[John F. Reynolds]].&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;&gt;Chamberlain, Joseph Lawrence. (1901). ''University of Pennsylvania: Its history, influence, equipment and characteristics; with biographical sketches and portraits of founders, benefactors, officers and alumni, Vol. 1,'' pp. 440-441. Boston: R. Herndon Company. [https://books.google.com/books?id=hohPAAAAYAAJ&amp;dq=]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Early life and education==
Joseph George Rosengarten was born in [[Philadelphia]], [[Pennsylvania]], the child of German immigrants, George D. and Elizabeth (Bennett) Rosengarten.&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ancestry 2009&quot;&gt;Ancestry.com. ''1850 United States Federal Census [database on-line].'' Provo, UT, USA: Ancestry.com Operations, Inc., 2009. Images reproduced by FamilySearch. ''Spring Garden Ward 1, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, Roll: M432_818; Page: 355B; Image: 151.''&lt;/ref&gt; His father, one of Philadelphia's wealthiest men by the 1890s,&lt;ref name=Baltzell&gt;{{cite web|last1=Baltzell|first1=Edward Digby|title=Philadelphia Gentlemen: The Making of a National Upper Class|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=B1QAMx2idG0C&amp;pg=PA98&amp;lpg=PA98&amp;dq=Rosengarten+family+Phila&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=jJCWgaF8yj&amp;sig=oLqVyCRCWnzF4wQQQTNdoIHomVI&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=m0WTVN-3PMG1sQT0q4CQCw&amp;ved=0CCkQ6AEwAw#v=onepage&amp;q=Rosengarten%20family%20Phila&amp;f=false|website=https://books.google.com/bkshp?hl=en&amp;tab=pp|publisher=Google Books|accessdate=18 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; was a chemist and manufacturer, who created a &quot;large chemical establishment&quot; and had an interest in numerous other profitable business ventures, including the [[Pennsylvania Railroad]].&lt;ref name=&quot;Ancestry 2009&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;&gt;Jastrow, Morris Jr. ''Joseph George Rosengarten'', Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society, Vol. 60, No. 4, 1921&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ancestry 2010&quot;&gt;Ancestry.com and The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints. ''1880 United States Federal Census [database on-line].'' Provo, UT, USA: Ancestry.com Operations Inc, 2010. 1880 U.S. Census Index provided by The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints © Copyright 1999 Intellectual Reserve, Inc. All rights reserved. ''Philadelphia, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania; Roll: 1171; Family History Film: 1255171; Page: 395C; Enumeration District: 143; Image: 0260.''&lt;/ref&gt;

Rosengarten received his early education in private schools in Philadelphia, and for a time &quot;came under the influence of a scholarly man in [[York, Pennsylvania]], the Rev. Charles West Thomson, who aroused in him a liking for literature that became an abiding habit.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; He completed his secondary education at an academy then affiliated with the [[University of Pennsylvania]], studying under Dr. Samuel Crawford.&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;/&gt;

In 1849, at just fourteen years of age, Rosengarten was admitted to the University of Pennsylvania, graduating three years later with the degree of [[Bachelor of Arts|A.B.]] in the Class of 1852.&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; In 1855, Rosengarten received the degree of [[Master of Arts|M.A.]] from the same university.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; After graduation he studied law in the offices of Henry M. Phillips, a prominent member of the [[Pennsylvania Bar Association|Philadelphia Bar]], and in 1856, Rosengarten was admitted to practice.&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

Rosengarten's father then arranged for him to travel abroad to further his studies:

::''The elder Rosengarten, realizing the extraordinary value of foreign study and travel, sent four of his sons abroad to prepare themselves for their future careers. In pursuance of this plan Joseph Rosengarten went...to study history and Roman Law at the [[University of Heidelberg]] and to engage in travel.''&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

While abroad he was &quot;thrown into contact with men of distinction,&quot; including [[Ludwig Häusser]] and [[:de:Adolph von Vangerow]], who served respectively, as professors of history and law at the University of Heidelberg. During this period, Rosengarten also met the eminent [[United Kingdom|British]] [[jurist]] [[James Fitzjames Stephen]], and his brother, author and critic [[Leslie Stephen]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

In 1857, Rosengarten returned to the [[United States]] and began practicing law in Philadelphia.&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; His law partners were [[Henry Schell Hagert]] and George Junkin.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

==Witnesses John Brown's raid on Harpers Ferry==
In 1859, Rosengarten witnessed [[Abolitionism in the United States|abolitionist]] [[John Brown (abolitionist)|John Brown's]] famous [[John Brown's raid on Harpers Ferry|raid]] on [[Harpers Ferry, Virginia]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; Brown was attempting to start an armed [[slave]] revolt by seizing a United States Arsenal at Harpers Ferry. Brown's raid was defeated by a detachment of [[United States Marines|marines]] led by then Colonel [[Robert E. Lee]]. Rosengarten had been traveling at the time as a guest with the Directors of the Pennsylvania Railroad, his father being one of the directors.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; His train stopped at Harper's Ferry and Rosengarten witnessed the attack made by Lee's men on the engine house where John Brown had sought refuge.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; He later saw John Brown lying wounded.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; Rosengarten wrote a vivid account of the raid, and what he had witnessed, that was published in the ''[[Atlantic Monthly]]'' in 1865.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

==Civil war service==
On September 2, 1862, a year after the outbreak of the Civil War, Rosengarten was commissioned a first lieutenant in Company D of the [[121st Pennsylvania Infantry]].&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Historical Data Systems 2009&quot;&gt;Historical Data Systems, comp. ''U.S. Civil War Soldier Records and Profiles, [database on-line].'' Provo, UT, USA: Ancestry.com Operations Inc, 2009. Original data: Data compiled by Historical Data Systems of Kingston, MA&lt;/ref&gt; The regiment was soon ordered to Washington, D.C., and upon its arrival, went into camp at Arlington Heights.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; Arms and equipments were not delivered until some weeks after its arrival, but drill and instruction were immediately commenced, and prosecuted with vigor, the regiment becoming noted for good discipline at the drills and reviews of General Casey's Provisional Brigade, to which it was then attached.

Rosengarten fought with distinction at the [[Battle of Fredericksburg]], &quot;distinguishing himself for bravery, picking up the colors after four sergeants had been disabled and carrying them successfully through the engagement.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; As a result, he gained the notice of Major General John F. Reynolds, and was offered the post of Ordnance Officer and a position on General Reynolds' staff.&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

Rosengarten remained on Reynolds' staff, fighting under him at [[Battle of Chancellorsville|Chancellorsville]] and [[Battle of Gettysburg|Gettysburg]], until Reynolds was killed in action during the latter battle.&lt;ref name=&quot;Historical Data Systems 2009&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Trudeau, Noah Andre. ''Gettysburg: A Testing of Courage.'' p. 271 New York: HarperCollins, 2002. ISBN 0-06-019363-8&lt;/ref&gt; (In one eyewitness's later account of Reynolds' death, Rosengarten is referred to as &quot;Major ''Adolph'' Rosengarten.&quot;) &lt;ref name=&quot;Veil Memoir&quot;&gt;{{cite web|last1=Wittenberg|first1=Eric|title=Charles H. Veil on John F. Reynolds at Gettysburg|url=http://civilwarcavalry.com/?p=624|website=Rantings of a Civil War Historian:|publisher=Eric Wittenberg|accessdate=18 December 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Rosengarten was assigned the honor of escorting Reynolds' body to his final resting place in [[Lancaster, Pennsylvania]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; Due to his intimate association with Reynolds, Rosengarten was also chosen to deliver the address at the dedication of Reynolds' monument at [[Gettysburg, Pennsylvania|Gettysburg]] in 1889.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

==Later life==
On September 6, 1863, Rosengarten received an honorable discharge from the military.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;&gt;Historical Data Systems, comp. ''U.S. Civil War Soldier Records and Profiles [database on-line].'' Provo, UT, USA: Ancestry.com Operations Inc, 2009. Original data: Data compiled by Historical Data Systems of Kingston, MA&lt;/ref&gt; In March 1865, he received the rank of Brevet Captain.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceB&quot;/&gt;

After receiving his discharge, Rosengarten returned to his law practice in Philadelphia. He was also employed as his father's business manager and legal representative, overseeing his father's numerous business ventures and investments.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

Rosengarten maintained a lifelong interest in his [[alma mater]] the University of Pennsylvania, serving as president of the alumni association, and as a member of the Board of Trustees.&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;/&gt; He supported several other public institutions, among them the German Hospital, now [[Lankenau Hospital]], and the House of Refuge, the first institution in Pennsylvania established to reform [[Minor (law)|juveniles]] charged with delinquency.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Glazier, Mary Hendricks. ''The Origins of Juvenile Justice in Police in Pennsylvania.'' (January 1, 1985). Dissertations available from ProQuest. Paper AAI8603642. [http://repository.upenn.edu/dissertations/AAI8603642]&lt;/ref&gt; Rosengarten served on the Board of Managers (1878), and later as vice president (1893-1910), and finally, as president (1911-1914) of the House of Refuge.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; At his urging, the institution was moved from Philadelphia to the outlying countryside, where, instead of being &quot;treated as prisoners the boys and girls were placed in homes organized on the cottage system,&quot; provided with educational opportunities, plenty of fresh air, outdoor work and exercise.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

Rosengarten served as a board member (1895-1911) and president (1899-1909) of the [[Free Library of Philadelphia]], and it was largely through his efforts that the library received a bequest of five hundred thousand dollars from [[Andrew Carnegie]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; Carnegie remembered the kindness once shown to him, years before, while he was employed as secretary to the president of the Pennsylvania Railroad, by Rosengarten's father.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

Rosengarten developed a close association with [[Anthony J. Drexel]] and, as a result, served from its founding in 1892 until 1909 as a member of the board of the [[Drexel Institute]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

Rosengarten contributed frequently to newspapers and periodicals, including the ''[[New York Tribune]]'', the Philadelphia ''Public Ledger'', the ''[[North American Review]]'', the ''Atlantic Monthly'', the ''[[Wharton Barker|Penn Monthly]],'' and ''[[The Nation]]''.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; He also delivered numerous addresses before various literary and charitable associations, including one before the [[Historical Society of Pennsylvania]] on the “''Life and Public Services of General John F. Reynolds''” (Philadelphia, 1880).&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;/&gt;

Rosengarten was an active member of the [[American Philosophical Society]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; He contributed translations of Hessian soldier Stephan Popp's [[American Revolution|Revolutionary War]] diary and Achenwall's Observations on North America to a paper, &quot;''American History from German Archives'',&quot; published in the Society's ''Proceedings'' for 1900.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

Through his association with [[Henry C. Carey]], Rosengarten became interested in [[social science]], and was active in the establishment of the [[American Social Science Association]], which later became the [[American Academy of Political and Social Science]].&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

An amateur historian, Rosengarten was particularly interested in the subject of French and German [[immigration]] to the United States, and the role played by French and German immigrants in the foundation of the country.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt; He authored numerous articles on the subject and two books: ''The German Soldier in the Wars of the United States'' (Philadelphia, 1886)[https://books.google.com/books?id=sngTAAAAYAAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=the+german+soldier+in+the+wars+of+the+united+states&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=Jhb2T9yvJsirrQH_9sSLCQ&amp;ved=0CDMQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=the%20german%20soldier%20in%20the%20wars%20of%20the%20united%20states&amp;f=false ] and ''French Colonists and Exiles in the United States'' (Philadelphia, 1907)[https://books.google.com/books/about/French_colonists_and_exiles_in_the_Unite.html?id=CdgBAAAAYAAJ ].&lt;ref name=&quot;books.google.com&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

Rosengarten was also remembered for his large circle of influential friends and acquaintances:

::''Few men had [such] a large circle of acquaintance; and having a rare gift for friendship, he continued to maintain association with many of those with whom he was thrown into contact either in [Philadelphia] or through his frequent trips abroad. He knew [[Charles Darwin|the Darwins]], father and [[George Darwin|son]]; he came into close touch with eminent writers and scholars like [[Max Müller|F. Max Müller]], [[Thomas Hughes]], [[Goldwin Smith]], [[Herbert Spencer]] and [[James Bryce, 1st Viscount Bryce|Lord Bryce]]; he formed a friendship extending over many years with the [[Jean-Baptiste Donatien de Vimeur, comte de Rochambeau|de Rochambeau family]] and secured the passage of an act of [[United States House of Representatives|Congress]] for the purchase of the letters of Washington to [the Comte de] Rochambeau. He knew the great trio of American literature, [[Henry Wadsworth Longfellow|Longfellow]], [[Ralph Waldo Emerson|Emerson]] and [[James Russell Lowell|Lowell]]; he had met all the Presidents from [[James Buchanan|Buchanan]] to [[Woodrow Wilson|Wilson]], and knew practically all the generals in the Civil War.''&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;

Rosengarten never married, living first with his parents and unmarried siblings, and later, after the death of his parents, with his sister, Fanny Rosengarten.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ancestry 2010&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ancestry.com. ''1920 United States Federal Census [database on-line].'' Provo, UT, USA: Ancestry.com Operations Inc, 2010. Images reproduced by FamilySearch. ''Philadelphia Ward 8, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania; Roll: T625_1619; Page: 9B; Enumeration District: 183; Image: 207.''&lt;/ref&gt; He died in Philadelphia on January 14, 1921.&lt;ref name=&quot;ReferenceA&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;findagrave.com&quot;&gt;Findagrave.com ''Memorial of Joseph G. Rosengarten: Find A Grave Memorial# 22739'' [http://www.findagrave.com/cgi-bin/fg.cgi?page=gr&amp;GRid=22739]&lt;/ref&gt; He is buried beside his sister Fanny at Laurel Hill Cemetery in Philadelphia.&lt;ref name=&quot;findagrave.com&quot;/&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist|33em}}

==References==
*{{Appletons'|wstitle=Rosengarten, Joseph George|year=1900}}
* {{Findagrave|22739}}

==External links==
* {{Gutenberg author | id=Rosengarten,+J.+G.+(Joseph+George) | name=Joseph George Rosengarten}}
* {{Internet Archive author |sname=Joseph George Rosengarten}}
* {{Cite book|title=A Defence of the Hessians|year=1899|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=88Pt2juMqvAC|accessdate=25 June 2011}} A pamphlet, at [[Google Books]].
* Finding aid to the [http://hdl.library.upenn.edu/1017/d/ead/upenn_rbml_PUSpMsColl959 Joseph George Rosengarten papers] at the [http://www.library.upenn.edu/ University of Pennsylvania Libraries]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Rosengarten, Joseph George}}
[[Category:1835 births]]
[[Category:1921 deaths]]
[[Category:Pennsylvania lawyers]]
[[Category:People from Philadelphia]]
[[Category:University of Pennsylvania alumni]]
[[Category:Union Army officers]]
[[Category:American male writers]]</text>
      <sha1>h564xl5g6yq1a88wl6oqou57ansrakh</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
