<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.29.0-wmf.3</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="446" case="first-letter">Education Program</namespace>
      <namespace key="447" case="first-letter">Education Program talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Puckle gun</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4932685</id>
    <revision>
      <id>749028845</id>
      <parentid>748438062</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-11T22:30:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>100.15.52.163</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>fix double quotation marks within double quotation marks</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9885">[[File:Puckle gun advertisement.jpg|thumb|right↓|Flier for James Puckle's 1718 patent revolving firearm, shows various cylinders for use with round and square bullets.]]
[[File:Puckle gun Photo.jpg|thumb|right↓|Replica Puckle gun from [[Buckler's Hard]] Maritime Museum]]
The '''Puckle gun''' (also known as the ''Defence gun'') was a primitive crew-served, manually-operated [[flintlock]]&lt;ref name=&quot;Willbanks 2&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=James H. Willbanks|title=Machine Guns: An Illustrated History of Their Impact|year=2004|publisher=ABC-CLIO|page=23}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[revolver]] patented in 1718 by [[James Puckle]] (1667–1724) a British inventor, lawyer and writer. It was one of the earliest weapons to be referred to as a &quot;machine gun&quot;, being called such in a 1722 shipping manifest,&lt;ref name=&quot;Paul Wilcock&quot; &gt;{{cite web|url=http://eprints.hud.ac.uk/17394/1/BUCCLEUCH_PROJECT_Royal_Armouries_version_2_5_FinalProofEDIT.pdf|title=The Armoury of His Grace the Duke of Buccleuch and Queensberry|publisher=University of Huddersfield}}&lt;/ref&gt; though its operation does not match the modern use of the term.

==Design and patent==
The Puckle gun is a tripod-mounted, single-barreled [[flintlock]] weapon fitted with a manually operated&lt;ref name=&quot;Chinn&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=George M. Chinn|title=The Machine Gun: Design Analysis of Automatic Firing Mechanisms and Related Components, Volume IV, parts X and XI|year=1955|publisher=Bureau of Ordnance, Department of the Navy, US Government Printing office|page=185}}&lt;/ref&gt; revolving cylinder; Puckle advertised its main application as an anti-boarding gun for use on ships. The barrel was {{convert|3|ft|m}} long with a bore of {{convert|1.25|in|mm}}. The cylinder held 6 to11 shots depending on configuration, and was hand-loaded with powder and shot while detached from the weapon.{{efn-lr|Willbanks states 9, Puckle's patent depicting 9, 7 and 6 round cylinders&lt;ref name=&quot;Willbanks&quot;/&gt;}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Willbanks&quot; &gt;{{cite book|last=Willbanks|first=James H|title=Machine Guns: An Illustrated History of Their Impact|publisher=ABC-CLIO|year=2004|page=154|isbn=1-85109-480-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the [[UK Intellectual Property Office|Patent Office of the United Kingdom]], &quot;In the reign of [[Anne, Queen of Great Britain|Queen Anne]], the law officers of the Crown established as a condition of grant that 'the patentee must by an instrument in writing describe and ascertain the nature of the invention and the manner in which it is to be performed.'&quot;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.ipo.gov.uk/types/patent/p-about/p-whatis/p-history/p-history-18century.htm |title=The 18th century |publisher=Intellectual Property Office |deadurl=unfit |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140422075818/http://www.ipo.gov.uk/types/patent/p-about/p-whatis/p-history/p-history-18century.htm |archivedate=April 22, 2014 }}&lt;/ref&gt; This gun's patent, number 418 of 1718, was one of the first to provide such a description. [[T.W. Lee]] remarked, however, that &quot;James Puckle's patent in 1718 contains more rhetorical fervor than technical rigor.&quot;&lt;ref name=&quot;Lee2008&quot; &gt;{{cite book|author=T.W. Lee|title=Military Technologies of the World|year=2008|publisher=ABC-CLIO|isbn=978-0-275-99536-2|pages=238–239}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Two versions===
Puckle demonstrated two configurations of the basic design: one, intended for use against Christian enemies, fired conventional round bullets, while the second, designed to be used against the Muslim Turks, fired square bullets. The square bullets were considered to be more damaging. They would, according to the patent, &quot;convince the Turks of the benefits of Christian civilization&quot;. The weapon was also reported as able to fire shot, with each discharge containing sixteen musket balls.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ffoulkes &amp; Cottesloe&quot;&gt;{{cite book|author=Charles Ffoulkes, Lord Cottesloe|title=The Gun-Founders of England: With a List of English and Continental Gun-Founders from the XIV to the XIX Centuries|year=1937|publisher=Cambridge University Press|page=34}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Operation==
The Puckle gun was fired in a similar fashion to a conventional flintlock musket; however, after each shot, a crank on the threaded shaft at the rear would be unscrewed to release the cylinder to turn freely. The cylinder would then be advanced by hand to the next chamber, and the crank turned back again to lock the cylinder into the breech of the fixed barrel. The flintlock mechanism could then be primed for another shot: it was triggered using a lever which was separate from the crank assembly.

To reload the weapon, the crank handle could be unscrewed completely to remove the cylinder, which could then be replaced with a fresh one. In this way it was similar to earlier [[breech-loading swivel guns]] with a detachable chamber which could be loaded prior to use. The cylinder appears to have been referred to as a &quot;charger&quot; in contemporary documentation.&lt;ref name=&quot; Paul Wilcock&quot;/&gt;

==Production and use==
A prototype was shown in 1717 to the [[Board of Ordnance|English Board of Ordnance]], who were not impressed. At a later public trial held in 1722, a Puckle gun was able to fire 63 shots in seven minutes (approx 9 rounds per minute) in the midst of a driving rain storm.&lt;ref name=&quot;Willbanks 2&quot;/&gt;&lt;ref name=&quot;Ffoulkes &amp; Cottesloe&quot;/&gt; A rate of 9 rounds per minute compared favourably to musketeers of the period, who could be expected to fire between 2 and 5 rounds per minute depending on the quality of the troops, with experienced troops expected to reliably manage 3 rounds a minute under fair conditions; it was however inferior in fire rate to earlier repeating weapons such as the [[Kalthoff repeater]] which fired up to six times faster.

The Puckle gun drew few investors and never achieved mass production or sales to the British armed forces. As with other designs of the time it was hampered by &quot;clumsy and undependable flintlock ignition&quot; and other mechanical problems.&lt;ref name=&quot;Willbanks 2&quot;/&gt; A leaflet of the period sarcastically observed of the venture that &quot;they're only wounded who hold shares therein&quot;. Production was highly limited and may have been as few as just two guns, one a crude prototype made of iron, the other a finished weapon made from brass.{{efn-lr|Wilcock states a third example exists at the Tøjhusmuseet (Royal Danish Arsenal) in Copenhagen.&lt;ref name=&quot;Paul Wilcock&quot; /&gt;}}&lt;ref name=&quot;Ffoulkes &amp; Cottesloe&quot;/&gt;

[[John Montagu, 2nd Duke of Montagu]], [[Master-General of the Ordnance]] (1740-1749), purchased two guns for an ill-fated expedition in 1722 to capture [[St Lucia]] and [[Saint Vincent (island)|St Vincent]]. While shipping manifests state &quot;2 Machine Guns of Puckles&quot; (sic) were among the cargo that departed from Portsmouth,&lt;ref name=&quot;Paul Wilcock&quot; /&gt; there is no evidence that the guns were ever used in battle.&lt;ref name=&quot;Willbanks&quot;/&gt;

==Surviving examples==

Two original examples are on display at former Montagu homes: one at [[Boughton House]] and another at [[Beaulieu Palace]].&lt;ref name=&quot; Paul Wilcock&quot;/&gt; There is a replica of a Puckle gun at [[Bucklers Hard]] Maritime Museum in [[Hampshire]]. Blackmore's ''British Military Firearms 1650–1850'' lists &quot;Puckle’s brass gun in the Tower of London&quot; as illustration 77, though this appears to have been a gun belonging to the former Montagu estate (at that point owned by the Buccleuch family) on loan to the Tower at the time.&lt;ref name=&quot;Ffoulkes &amp; Cottesloe&quot;/&gt;

== Similar guns ==

===Collier Revolver===
[[Elisha Collier]] invented a flintlock revolver in 1814, nearly a hundred years after the Puckle gun (though examples of flintlock and matchlock revolvers exist much earlier, with the earliest known dating back to the 15th century). Unlike the Puckle, the cylinder of the Collier was not interchangeable, slowing reloading, but would have had a faster rate of fire for its five chambers due to the integral cylinder advancing of its [[Trigger (firearms)#Double-action.2Fsingle-action|single-action]] revolver mechanism, self-priming mechanism, and the lack of a need to screw and unscrew the cylinder between shots.

===Remington-pattern Revolvers===
During the period between the widespread adoption of the revolver, but prior to widespread use of cartridges, it was common to use multiple replaceable cylinders functioning as speedloaders, similar to the Puckle gun.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Bequette|first=Roy Marcot ; edited by James W.|title=Remington : &quot;America's oldest gunmaker&quot;|year=1998|publisher=Primedia|location=Peoria, IL|isbn=1-881657-00-0|author2=Gangloff, Joel J. Hutchcroft  |author3=foreword by Arthur W. Wheaton  |author4=chapter introductions by Richard F. Dietz  |author5= book design by Robert L. }}&lt;/ref&gt; This practice was primarily done on [[Remington Model 1858|Remington revolver]]s, as their cylinders were easily removable and were held by a cylinder pin, unlike the early [[Colt 1851 Navy Revolver|Colt revolver]]s which were held together by a wedge that went through the cylinder pin.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.floridareenactorsonline.com/revolvers.htm |title=Civil War Revolvers of The North and South |author=Robert Niepert |publisher=Florida Reenactors Online}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Confederate revolving cannon===
{{Main article|Confederate Revolving Cannon}}
A single example of a 2-inch bore, five-shot revolver cannon was built and used by the [[Confederate States of America]] during the [[Siege of Petersburg]]. It was captured on 27 April 1865 by Union troops and sent for examination to the [[United States Military Academy]] at [[West Point, New York]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author=George M. Chinn|title=The Machine Gun, History, Evolution and Development of Manual, Automatic and Airborne Repeating Weapons, Vol. 1|year=1951|publisher=U.S. Government Printing Office|page=46}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{commons category|Puckle Gun}}
{{Notelist-lr}}

{{Reflist}}

[[Category:Revolvers]]
[[Category:Early revolvers]]</text>
      <sha1>t0ca8d4m2xqocazmf27ylzw40qegfqk</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
